<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93899</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body image, eating behaviours and exercise trainign among male gym users and male non- users at the university</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study is to analyse whether men who regularly work out in the gym (gym users) can be differentiated from non-user university males from the general population according to the following variables: body image, altered eating habits and altered exercise habits. Two samples took part in the study: one with 78 gym users randomly chosen from gyms in Guadalajara (Jalisco-Mexico) and 340 non-user students from the UNIVA University in Guadalajara. The results of an attitude questionnaire show that as far as body image measured, there was no difference between gym users and non-user men from the general population. It was also observed that gym users had worse eating and physical exercise habits than the men surveyed from the general population. The intensity of the alteration in eating attitudes and attitudes towards physical exercise seem to be linked to the desire to have larger muscles as measured by a figure scale. These data indicate that gym users have a greater pathological tendency in eating and physical exercise habits than the general population. This may be related to engaging in a sport for an aesthetic outcome rather than for health reasons (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baile Ayensa, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Ortiz, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Díaz, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Andujo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tiene por objeto analizar si los varones usuarios de gimnasio se diferencian de los no usuarios, estos últimos, universitarios procedentes de población general, en las siguientes variables: imagen corporal, hábitos de alimentación alterados y hábitos de ejercicio alterados. Participaron dos muestras: una de 78 hombres usuarios de gimnasios elegidos al azar entre gimnasios de Guadalajara (Jalisco-México), y 340 sujetos no usuarios de gimnasio, estudiantes de la universidad UNIVA en Guadalajara (Jalisco- México). Los resultados muestran que ambas submuestras, varones usuarios y no usuarios de gimnasio, no se diferencian en cuanto a imagen corporal medida con un cuestionario de actitudes. También se observó que los primeros tienen peores hábitos de alimentación y de ejercicio físico que los hombres de población general. La intensidad de la alteración de actitudes alimentarias y de actitudes hacia el ejercicio físico estaba en relación con el deseo de tener mayor tamaño y musculación, medido con una escala de figuras. estos datos apuntan a que los usuarios de gimnasio tienen mayores tendencias patológicas en hábitos de alimentación y ejercicio físico que la población general, lo que podría estar relacionado con una práctica del deporte con fines estéticos más que de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;20(2): 353-366, jul.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93899</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Imagen corporal, hábitos alimentarios y hábitos de ejercicio físico en hombres usuarios de gimnasio y hombres universitarios no usuarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
