<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141017</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute heart failure: acute cardiogenic pulmonary edema and cardiogenic shock</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute cardiogenic pulmonary edema and cardiogenic shock are two of the main forms of presentation of acute heart failure. Both entities are serious, with high mortality, and require early diagnosis and prompt and aggressive management. Acute pulmonary edema is due to the passage of fluid through the alveolarcapillary membrane and is usually the result of an acute cardiac episode. Correct evaluation and clinical identification of the process is essential in the management of acute pulmonary edema. The initial aim of treatment is to ensure hemodynamic stability and to correct hypoxemia. Other measures that can be used are vasodilators such as nitroglycerin, loop diuretics and, in specific instances, opioids. Cardiogenic shock is characterized by sustained hypoperfusion, pulmonary wedge pressure &gt; 18 mmHg and a cardiac index &lt; 2.2 l/min/m2. The process typically presents with hypotension (systolic blood pressure &lt; 90 mmHg or a decrease in mean arterial pressure &gt; 30 mmHg) and absent or reduced diuresis (&lt; 0.5 ml/kg/h). The most common cause is left ventricular failure due to acute myocardial infarction. Treatment consists of general measures to reverse acidosis and hypoxemia, as well as the use of vasopressors and inotropic drugs. Early coronary revascularization has been demonstrated to improve survival in shock associated with ischaemic heart disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urrutia, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Marteles, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El edema agudo de pulmón y el shock cardiogénico son 2 de las formas principales de presentación de la insuficiencia cardíaca aguda. Ambos cuadros son graves, con alta mortalidad, y requieren de un diagnóstico precoz y de un manejo urgente y agresivo. El edema agudo de pulmón es consecuencia del paso de líquido a través de la membrana alveolocapilar, suele ser consecuencia de un episodio cardíaco agudo. En el manejo del edema agudo de pulmón es fundamental una correcta evaluación e identificación clínica del cuadro. En el tratamiento, el objetivo inicial es asegurar la situación hemodinámica y la corrección de la hipoxemia. Vasodilatadores como nitroglicerina, diuréticos de asa y, de forma puntual, opiáceos son otras de las armas terapéuticas a utilizar. El shock cardiogénico se caracteriza por una hipoperfusión mantenida, presión pulmonar enclavada &gt; 18 mmHg y un índice cardíaco &lt; 2,2 l/min/m2. De forma típica se presenta con hipotensión (presión arterial sistólica &lt; 90 mmHg o un descenso de la presión arterial media &gt; 30 mmHg) y una diuresis ausente o disminuida (&lt; 0,5 ml/kg/h). La causa más frecuente es la insuficiencia ventricular izquierda secundaria a un infarto agudo de miocardio. El tratamiento consta de medidas generales para revertir la acidosis y la hipoxemia, así como el uso de fármacos vasopresores e inotrópicos. La revascularización coronaria precoz ha demostrado mejorar la supervivencia en el shock por cardiopatía isquémica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);142(supl.1): 14-19, mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formas de presentación de la insuficiencia cardíaca aguda: edema agudo de pulmón y shock cardiogénico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13148^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15068^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13148^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13148^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7202^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15065^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31982^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31982^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4293</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9489^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13148^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2358^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13147^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51201^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
