<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128213</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lipedematous Scalp</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lipedematous scalp is a rare condition first described by Cornbleet in 1935. An increased thickness of subcutaneous tissue in the scalp gives rise to a soft spongy appearance of the surface and occasionally causes pruritus and pain in the affected area. When hair loss is also associated with the condition, it is described as lipedematous alopecia. To date, 10 cases of lipedematous scalp and 13 of lipedematous alopecia have been reported. We present the case of a 77-year-old white women who developed dysesthesia on her scalp 5 months after the death of her husband. Biopsy revealed subcutaneous tissue thickening that even extended to the dermis. Computed tomography showed thickening of subcutaneous tissue at the vertex and in the occipital region. We diagnosed a new case of lipedematous scalp in a white women. This case highlights the importance of differential diagnosis in cases of dysesthetic syndrome of the scalp (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Muñoz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Morán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torné, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda-Romero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda-Sivelo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cuero cabelludo lipedematoso es una rara entidad que fue descrita por Cornbleet en 1935, en la que un aumento del tejido subcutáneo del cuero cabelludo produce un aspecto suave y esponjoso de la superficie del mismo y ocasionalmente prurito y dolor de la zona afectada. Cuando además esta condición produce alopecia se denomina alopecia lipedematosa. Hasta la fecha se han descrito 10 casos de cuero cabelludo lipedematoso y 13 de alopecia lipedematosa. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 77 años de raza caucásica con sensación disestésica en el cuero cabelludo 5 meses después de la muerte de su esposo. Realizamos una biopsia donde se observaba un engrosamiento del tejido graso subcutáneo que incluso se extendía a la dermis. Una tomografía computarizada mostraba este engrosamiento de los tejidos subcutáneos en el vértex y el área occipital. Diagnosticamos un nuevo caso de cuero cabelludo lipedematoso en una mujer caucásica, destacando la importancia del diagnóstico diferencial con el síndrome disestésico del cuero cabelludo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(1): 69-72, ene. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuero cabelludo lipedematoso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36513^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12918^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11976^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12918^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
