<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163823</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Principles of urinary tract reconstructive surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In the last 15 years, the role of laparoscopic surgery has progressively increased to include reconstructive procedures such as pyeloplasty and management of ureteral stricture, in addition to being a field in continuous development, this refers to the improvement of ergonomics, new instruments and new techniques. We present a review on basic features of laparoscopic reconstructive surgery in urology. Acquisition of Evidence: For this review, an exhaustive literature search was performed in PUBMED, MEDILNE, BioMed central and others, with the keywords: reconstructive surgery, urology, laparoscopy. Only articles including urologic procedures in the adult and published in the last 6 years, were selected for this review. Synthesis of evidence: One of the objectives of any urological reconstructive procedure is to treat any segment of the genitourinary tract that is obstructed due to scar tissue following trauma or iatrogenic causes. After the excision of such segment or scar, a mobilization of the 2 healthy extremities of the urinary tract must be performed in order to proceed with a tension-free anastomosis. Occasionally, if there is tension, a mobilization of the organs at each side of the lesion should be performed to reduce the tension of the anastomosis; also, it should be a water-tight anastomosis to ensure good functional results. Another type of procedure is to perform laparoscopic repair surgery of pelvic organ prolapse in which the vaginal anatomy should be adequately restored, with good function maintained (sexual, urinary, intestinal) and durability. Conclusions: With the worldwide expansion of minimally invasive surgery in the area of laparoscopy and robotics, it has been possible to reproduce many of the reconstructive techniques that have followed the evolutionary course of surgery from the open to the robot assisted technique, which has made clear that such therapeutic options exist and are reproducible with good results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Ledo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Rivas, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En los últimos 15 años, el papel de la laparoscopia ha aumentado progresivamente para incluir la realización de procedimientos reconstructivos como la pieloplastia y el manejo de estenosis ureteral, además de ser un campo que se encuentra en continuo desarrollo, esto se refiere a la mejora de la ergonomía, nuevos instrumentos y nuevas técnicas. Presentamos una revisión sobre aspectos básicos de la cirugía reconstructiva laparoscópica en urología. Adquisición de la evidencia: Para esta revisión se realizó una búsqueda exhaustiva de literatura en los buscadores PUBMED, MEDILNE, BioMed central entre otros con las palabras clave: cirugía reconstructiva, urología, laparoscopia. Se seleccionaron para esta revisión artículos que incluyeran procedimientos urológicos en el adulto y publicados en los últimos 6 años. Síntesis de la evidencia: Uno de los objetivos de cualquier procedimiento reconstructivo urológico es el de tratar algún segmento del aparato genitourinario que se encuentra obstruido debido a tejido cicatricial posterior a un traumatismo o por causa iatrogénica. Después de la escisión del segmento o cicatriz, se debe realizar una movilización de los 2 extremos sanos para proceder a la realización de una anastomosis libre de tensión.  Ocasionalmente, si hay tensión se debe realizar una movilización de los órganos que se encuentran en cada extremo de la lesión para reducir la tensión de la anastomosis; a su vez debe ser una anastomosis estanca para asegurar los buenos resultados funcionales de la misma. Otro tipo de procedimiento es el de realizar cirugía reparadora laparoscópica en el prolapso de órganos pélvicos en la cual se debe restaurar adecuadamente la anatomía vaginal, mantener la función (sexual, urinaria, intestinal) y durabilidad. Conclusiones: Con la expansión a nivel mundial de la cirugía mínimamente invasiva en el área de laparoscopia y robótica se ha logrado reproducir muchas de las técnicas reconstructivas que han seguido el curso evolutivo de la cirugía desde la técnica abierta hasta la asistida por robot, lo que ha dejado claro que dichas opciones terapéuticas existen y son reproducibles con buenos resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;70(4): 379-384, mayo 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Principios de la cirugía reconstructiva del tracto urinario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55679^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52133^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
