<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120366</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eating habits and attitudes towards change in Spanish university students and workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Universities and workplaces are important targets for the promotion of the nutritional interventions in adult population. OBJECTIVES: The aim of this study was to assess the dietary habits and attitudes towards change in workers and university students from different academic fields. METHODS: The study data came from a cross-sectional study of a Spanish University population of 1,429 participants. We analyzed the dietary habits and the attitudes toward dietary change. RESULTS: The mean age of workers and students was 37 and 23 years, respectively. Both groups reported eating four meals per day. Among students, the consumption of vegetables, wine, fish and nuts was less frequent whereas carbonated beverages, commercial bakery, fast food and red meat was higher. On the other hand, overall dietary pattern of science students was healthier than other students. Although no significant differences were found between students and workers in attitudes towards change, 32% of employees and 39% of students said they were seriously considering changing them. CONCLUSIONS: The dietary pattern was healthier among workers than among students, particularly those participants that studied social sciences degrees. They constituted the most vulnerable segment of the university population from a nutritional point of view. About a third of workers and students considered changing their habits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zazpe, Itziar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Montero, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beunza, Juan-José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Mourille, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Tainta, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El entorno educativo y laboral ha adquirido protagonismo como ámbito prometedor para llevar a cabo intervenciones nutricionales en población adulta. Objetivos: El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar los hábitos alimentarios y actitudes hacia el cambio en trabajadores y alumnos universitarios con distinto perfil académico. Métodos: Estudio epidemiológico descriptivo de tipo transversal en población universitaria española de 1.429 sujetos. Se analizaron los hábitos alimentarios y las actitudes hacia el cambio de hábitos. Resultados: La edad media de los trabajadores fue de 37 años y en los estudiantes de 23 años. En ambos grupos el fraccionamiento de la ingesta más frecuente fue de cuatro tomas al día. En los alumnos se observó menor frecuencia de consumo de verdura, vino, pescado y frutos secos y mayor de bebidas carbonatadas, repostería comercial, fast-food y carnes rojas. Por otro lado, en general los hábitos alimentarios de los estudiantes de ciencias fueron más saludables que los de letras. Aunque no se observaron diferencias significativas en las actitudes hacia el cambio entre estudiantes y trabajadores, el 32% de los empleados y el 39% de los estudiantes afirmaron estar planteándose seriamente cambiar sus costumbres. Conclusiones: El patrón alimentario fue más saludable entre los trabajadores que entre los alumnos, especialmente en aquellos que cursan grados de letras, que constituyen el grupo más vulnerable desde el punto de vista nutricional. Además, aproximadamente un tercio de los trabajadores y alumnos se planteaba modificar sus hábitos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(5): 1673-1680, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120366</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábitos alimentarios y actitudes hacia el cambio en alumnos y trabajadores universitarios españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23899</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
