<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108710</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autobiography of nursing: nursing professionalization during the war</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper proposes an historical analysis of a group of nurses whose autobiographies of dramatic experiences in the exercise of his profession during the American Civil War helped to shape the nursing profession. The autobiographies are an important component of self-perception that not only becomes a way of conveying a reality from the subjective point of view and personal, but also helps shape a collective identity. Thus, the historical analysis of the experiences of nurses can lead to understanding of the nature of a young profession that came in the nineteenth century and that has taken shape over the twentieth century, reaching a clearly defined status and self-discipline with its development and specific practice. We have chosen the context of the American Civil War because of its impact in the professional development of nursing. It is well known that the experience of the dramatic events excites reflection after a while, and often results in retrospective autobiographical accounts that reflect the referential aspect of events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Choperena Armendáriz, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo propone el análisis histórico de un grupo de autobiografías de enfermeras cuyas dramáticas experiencias en el ejercicio de su profesión durante la Guerra Civil Americana ayudaron a configurar la profesión de  enfermería. Las autobiografías tienen un importante componente de auto-percepción que no sólo les convierte en un modo de transmitir una realidad desde el punto de vista más subjetivo y personal, sino que también ayuda a configurar la identidad de un colectivo. De esta manera, el análisis histórico de las experiencias de enfermeras puede conducir al conocimiento de la naturaleza de una joven profesión que nació en el siglo XIX y que se ha ido configurando a lo largo del XX, alcanzando un estatus perfectamente definido y una disciplina propia, con su desarrollo y práctica específica. Se ha escogido el contexto de la Guerra Civil Americana por su repercusión en cuanto al desarrollo profesional de la enfermería. Es bien sabido que la experiencia de los acontecimientos dramáticos excita la reflexión personal al cabo de un tiempo, y en muchas ocasiones da lugar a relatos autobiográficos retrospectivos que reflejan el aspecto referencial de los acontecimientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;16(34): 51-55, sept.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108710</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autobiografías de enfermeras: la profesionalización de enfermería durante las guerras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6928^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38886</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
