<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038329</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Symbiotics: a new strategy in critically ill patients treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Maintenance of the gut environment is a key factor in determining outcome in the care of critically ill and postoperative patients. It is especially important to maintain both gastrointestinal secretions, full o anti-infectious and anti-inflammatory compounds, and the gut flora. Prebiotics, usually polysaccharides, exhibit strong bio-activity and the ingestion of prebiotics has been shown to reduce the rate of infection and restore health in sick and postoperative patients. Probiotics may have at least five functions, all of great importance to the sick patients: the reduction or elimination of potentially pathogenic micro-organism of various kinds; the reduction or elimination of various toxins, mutagens, carcinogens, etc.; modulation of the innate and adaptive immune defense mechanisms; the promotion of apoptosis; and the release of numerous nutrient, antioxidant, growth, coagulation and other factors necessary for recovery. A combination of pre and probiotics is referred to as "synbiotics". Our experience of synbiotic treatment in critically ill patients is limited, but cutting-edge results from studies of severe acute pancreatitis, chronic hepatitis and liver transplantation offer great hope for the future. This is especially importante as pharmaceutical treatment, including the use of antibiotics, has largely failed, and the medical world is in much need of new treatment paradigms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bengmark, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz de Urbina, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mantenimiento del entorno intestinal es un factor clave que determina el resultado en pacientes críticamente enfermos y post-operados. Es especialmente importante mantener tanto las secreciones gastrointestinales, llenas de compuestos anti-infecciosos y anti-inflamatorios, como la flora del intestino. Los prebióticos, normalmente polisacáridos, tienen una fuerte bio-actividad y su ingestión ha mostrado reducir la tasa de infección y mejorar el estado de salud en pacientes enfermos y post-operados. Los probióticos tienen, por lo menos, cinco funciones de gran importancia para los pacientes enfermos: la reducción o eliminacion de microorganismos potencialmente patógenos; la reducción o eliminación de varias toxinas, mutágenos, carcinógenos, etc.; la modulación de los mecanismos de la defensa inmune innatos y adaptativos; promoción de la apoptosis y la liberación de numerosos nutrientes, antioxidantes, factores de crecimiento y de coagulación necesarios para la recuperación. Una combinación de prey probióticos se denomina "simbióticos". La experiencia en el tratamiento de pacientes extremadamente enfermos con simbióticos es limitada, pero los resultados de los estudios realizados son prometedores. En pancreatitis aguda grave, hepatitis crónica y trasplante de hígado ofrecen una gran esperanza para el futuro. Esto es especialmente importante puesto que los tratamientos farmacéuticos, incluido el uso de antibióticos, han fallado en gran medida y la medicina está necesitada de nuevos modelos de tratamientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;20(2): 147-156, mar.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038329</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Simbióticos: una nueva estrategia en el tratamiento de pacientes críticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33510^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
