<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143791</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between waist circumference and sagittal abdominal diameter measured at different anatomical sites and inflammatory biomarkers in apparently health men</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Visceral fat accumulation is associated with several changes, such as, increased production of inflammatory biomarkers, especially, C-reactive protein (CRP) and fibrinogen. Anthropometric measurements for central adiposity evaluation, such as, waist circumference (WC) and sagittal abdominal diameter (SAD) have been highlighted. However, there is no consensus on the best anatomical site for measurement. Objective: To evaluate the reliability of different measurements of WC and SAD and verify their capacity to discriminate changes in inflammatory biomarkers. Method: 130 men (20-59 years) were assessed, having measurements of weight, height, WC and SAD.  It was considered as the cutoff point for high-sensitivity CRP (hs-CRP) values &amp;#8805; 0.12 mg/dL and for fibrinogen the 50th percentile of the evaluated sample. Results: All measurements presented an intraclass correlation coefficient between 0.998 and 0.999. WC measured at the umbilical level (AUC=0.693±0.049) and the smallest circumference between the thorax and the hips (AUC=0.607±0.050) had greater ability to discriminate changes in concentrations of hs-CRP and fibrinogen, respectively.  SAD (umbilical level) showed the better ability to detect changes in concentrations of hs-CRP (AUC=0.698± 0.049) and fibrinogen (AUC=0.625±0.049), according to the ROC analysis (p&lt;0.05). Conclusion: WC (smallest circumference between the thorax and the hips) and SAD (umbilical level) are the anatomic sites of measurement for use in predicting the inflammatory risk in apparently health men (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidigal, Fernanda de Carvalho</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosado, Gilberto Paixão</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franceschini, Sylvia do Carmo Castro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro, Rita de Cassia Lanes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosadom, Lina Enriqueta Frandsen Paez de Lima</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La acumulación de grasa visceral se asocia con varios cambios, tales como, aumento de la producción de los biomarcadores inflamatorios, en especial, la proteína C-reactiva (PCR) y fibrinógeno. Las medidas antropométricas para la evaluación de la adiposidad central, como la circunferencia de la cintura (CC) y el diámetro abdominal sagital (DAS) se han destacado. Sin embargo, no hay consenso sobre el mejor sitio anatómico para la medición. Objetivos: Evaluar la fiabilidad de diferentes mediciones de CC y DAS y verificar su capacidad para discriminar los cambios en biomarcadores inflamatorios. Métodos: Se evaluaron 130 hombres (20-59 años). Se midió peso, estatura, circunferencia de la cintura (CC) y diámetro abdominal sagital (DAS). Se consideró como punto de corte para los valores de PCR ultrasensible (PCR-us) &amp;#8805; 0,12 mg/dL y para el fibrinógeno se utilizó el percentil 50 de la muestra evaluada. Resultados: Todas las mediciones presentaron un coeficiente de correlación intraclase entre 0.998 y 0.999. CC medida a nivel umbilical (AUC=0,693±0,049) y la circunferencia más pequeña entre el tórax y las caderas (AUC=0,607±0,050) tuvieron una mayor capacidad para discriminar los cambios en las concentraciones de PCRus y fibrinógeno, respectivamente. DAS (nivel umbilical) mostró la mejor capacidad para detectar cambios en las concentraciones de PCR-us (AUC=0,698±0,049) y fibrinógeno (AUC=0,625±0,049), de acuerdo con el análisis ROC (p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones: CC (circunferencia más pequeña entre el tórax y las caderas) y DAS (nivel umbilical) son los sitios anatómicos de elección para su uso en la predicción del riesgo inflamatorio en hombres adultos sanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(3): 663-670, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143791</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre la circunferencia de la cintura y el diámetro abdominal sagital medido en diferentes sitios anatómicos y biomarcadores del estado inflamatorio en hombres adultos sanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22179^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
