<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98545</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to a Mediterranean diet in a college population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the adherence to the Mediterranean diet of a university population and to analyze several factors that may condition its nutritional quality. Material and methods: Distribution of the Kidmed test to a random sample of 570 university students. The Kidmed index (0-12) indicated whether the adherence to the Mediterranean diet was low (0-3), intermediate (4-7) or high (8-12). The gender, age, weight, height, and body mass index were gathered from each participant, as well as the type of residence and the province of origin. Results: The sample comprised 217 men and 353 women aged 18-25 years. 9.5% of the university students had a low Kidmed index, 62.1% intermediate, and 28.4%high. Those students living at their parental home had a high percentage of adherence (35.6%), significantly higher (p &lt; 0.05) to that of those living at a student&#146;s residence(11.1%) or at a student&#146;s apartment (11.2%). Overweighed students had a low percentage of adherence(15.5%), significantly higher (p &lt; 0.05) to those with a normal nutritional situation (8.5%).Conclusions: 71.6% of university students need to improve their dietary pattern (low to intermediate adherence to the Mediterranean diet), and we could observe a certain family factor of preservation of the traditional dietary habits. Those university students with low adherence had a higher risk for being overweighed. It would be convenient to develop nutritional education programs in the university curricula (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Durá Travé, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castroviejo Gandarias, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la adherencia a la dieta mediterránea de una población universitaria y analizar diversos factores que pudieran condicionar su calidad nutricional. Material y métodos: Distribución del test kidmed a una muestra aleatoria de 570 universitarios. El índice kidmed (de 0 a 12) indicaba si la adherencia a la dieta mediterránea era baja (de 0 a 3), media (de 4 a 7) o alta (de 8 a 12).De cada encuestado se registraba sexo, edad, peso, talla e índice de masa corporal, tipo de residencia y provincia de procedencia. Resultados: La muestra era de 217 varones y 353 mujeres con edades entre 18 y 25 años. El 9,5% de los universitarios tenían un índice kidmed bajo, el 62,1% intermedio y el 28,4% alto. Aquellos universitarios que vivían en residencia familiar tenían un porcentaje de alta adherencia(35,6%) significativamente superior (p &lt; 0,05) a los que vivían en colegio mayor (11,1%) o piso de estudiantes(11,2%). Los universitarios con sobrepeso tenían un porcentaje de baja adherencia (15,5%) significativamente superior (p &lt; 0,05) a los que tenían una situación nutricional normal (8,5%). Conclusiones: El 71,6% de los universitarios necesitaban mejorar su patrón alimentario (adherencia media baja a la dieta mediterránea), apreciándose un cierto factor familiar conservador de las costumbres dietéticas tradicionales. Los universitarios con baja adherencia tenían mayor riesgo de sobrepeso. Seria conveniente desarrollar programas de educación nutricional en los curriculum universitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(3): 602-608, mayo-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98545</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia a la dieta mediterránea en la población universitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14893</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
