<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94094</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Similarities, differences and agonisms of pleiotropic effects of statins and omega-3 fatty acids</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper compares the pleiotropic effects of statins and omega-3 fatty acids (n-3 PUFA) in treating and preventing cardiovascular disease (CVD) and deals with the possible interactions of those compounds. Statins represent one of the most important discoveries to have been made in the field of cardiovascular medicine in recent decades. Their beneficial cardiovascular effects, which have reduced the number of fatal events in patients with atherosclerosis, encompass more than their ability to lower cholesterol levels. The pleiotropic effects of statins involve their anti-inflammatory and antiplatelet properties and their ability to normalize endothelial function. In addition, these drugs may display antiarrhythmic activity, improve insulin sensitivity and counteract hypertension and obesity. The low rate of coronary disease documented in Eskimos corroborates the cardioprotective effects of the n-3 PUFA eicosapentaenoic (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acids beyond their hypolipemic effects. The reduction of CVD-related deaths attributable to the action of &amp;#945;-linolenic fatty acid appears to be related to its strong antiarrhythmic properties. In addition, as a precursor of EPA and this last fatty acid of thromboxane A3, prostacyclin I3, serie-3 prostaglandines and serie 5-leukotrines and inhibitor/modulator of thromboxane A2, prostacyclin I2, serie-2 prostaglandines and serie 4-leukotrienes formation, the &amp;#945;-linolenic acid may reduce inflammation and thrombogenesis. As results of some studies suggest that the combined use of statins and n-3 PUFA improves cardiovascular protection and reduces the CVD-related mortality rate; the paper also reviews the possible synergism between both groups of compounds on CVD treatment and concludes that clear benefits may be obtained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acin, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Higueras, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalobos, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bastida, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez-Muniz, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo compara los efectos pleiotrópicos de las estatinas y los ácidos grasos poliinsaturados omega-3 (AGP n-3) en el tratamiento y prevención de enfermedades cardiovasculares (ECV) y revisa las posibles interacciones de estos dos grupos de compuestos. Las estatinas son uno de los descubrimientos más importantes realizados en el campo de la medicina cardiovascular en las últimas décadas. Sus efectos beneficiosos cardiovasculares, reduciendo el número de eventos fatales en pacientes con aterosclerosis, se extienden más allá de su capacidad para reducir los niveles de colesterol. Los efectos pleiotrópicos de las estatinas involucran sus propiedades anti-inflamatorias y antiagregantes y su capacidad para normalizar la función endotelial. Además, estos fármacos pueden generar actividad antiarrítmica, mejorar la sensibilidad a la insulina y contrarrestar la hipertensión y la obesidad. La baja tasa de enfermedad coronaria documentada en los esquimales corrobora los efectos cardioprotectores de los AGP n-3 en particular de los AGP eicosapentaenoico (EPA) y docosahexaenoico más allá de sus efectos hipolipemiantes. La reducción de las muertes relacionadas con enfermedades cardiovasculares atribuibles a la acción del ácido graso &amp;#945;-linolénico parece estar relacionado a sus potentes propiedades antiarrítmicas. Además, como un precursor del EPA y este a su vez de la formación de tromboxano A3, prostaciclina I3, prostaglandinas de la serie-3 y leucotrienos de la serie 5 e inhibidor/modulador de la formación de tromboxano A2, prostaciclina I2, prostaglandinas de la serie 2 y leucotrienos de la serie 4, el ácido &amp;#945;-linolénico puede reducir la inflamación y la trombogénesis. Los resultados de algunos estudios sugieren que el uso combinado de estatinas y AGP n-3 mejora la protección cardiovascular y reduce la tasa de mortalidad relacionada con ECV, por lo que en este trabajo también se revisan las posibles sinergias entre ambos grupos de compuestos en el tratamiento de CVD y se concluye que pueden obtenerse claros beneficios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(6): 889-909, nov.-dic. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Similitudes, diferencias y agonismos en los efectos pleiotropicosde las estatinas y los acidos grasos omega-3</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24651^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d931^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
