<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94739</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Global adherence project to disease-modifying therapies in patients with relapsing multiple sclerosis: 2-year interim results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In this article we report adherence data from the first 2 years in a subset of patients from the Global Adherence Project (GAP; p=2,648) in Spain. Methods: A questionnaire assessing adherence to Disease-modifying therapies (DMTs), was distributed annually to patients and their treating neurologists. Non-adherence was defined as missing a DMT injection or changing a dose in the four weeks prior to completing the survey. Patients signed informed consent and Ethics Committees approved annual follow-ups, visit 1 (V1) and visit 2 (V2) in 15 out of 18 centres in Spain. Results: A total of 254 patients were enrolled in Spain. Patients had a mean age of 37.9 years and 70.4% were female, and had been on their treatment for a median time of 28 months, and the overall adherence rate was 85.4%. Patients taking intramuscular interferon beta (IFNB)-1a (Avonex®) were significantly more adherent (94.6%) compared with patients taking subcutaneous (s.c.) IFNB-1a 22&amp;#956;g (Rebif®22) (79.1%; p=0.0064), s.c. IFNB-1a 44&amp;#956;g (Rebif®44) (79.6%; p=0.0064) and glatiramer acetate (GA) (82.7%; p=0.0184). At V1 (n=142), the overall adherence rate was 86.6% and patients on Avonex® were significantly more adherent than patients on Rebif®22 (93.9% versus 66.7%; p=0.0251). At V2 (n=131), the overall adherence rate was 82.4% (Avonex®, 87.5%; Rebif®22, 80%; Rebif®44, 77.8%; Betaferon®, 85.2%, and Copaxone®, 80%) without significant differences.Conclusions: Adherence remained high over the first 2 years of the study. It was highest with Avonex®, being significant on first assessment, after 40.5 months of therapy, on average compared with other DMTs and at year 1 compared with Rebif®22 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Soliño, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En este artículo comunicamos resultados de adherencia a los 2 años en la subpoblación de pacientes del estudio Global de Adherencia GAP (n=2.648) en España. Métodos: Pacientes y neurólogos completaron cuestionarios anuales para evaluar la adherencia a los tratamientos inmunomoduladores (IMA). Se definió la falta de adherencia como la pérdida de una inyección o el cambio de dosis en las últimas 4 semanas previas a completar el cuestionario. Los pacientes firmaron el consentimiento informado. Estudio aprobado en 15 de 18 centros en los seguimientos anuales de la visita 1 (V1) y la visita 2 (V2) por los comités éticos. Resultados:Se incluyó a 254 pacientes en España; la media de edad fue 37,9 años y el 70,4% eran mujeres; la mediana de tiempo en tratamiento fue 28 meses y la tasa de adherencia conjunta, del 85,4%. Los pacientes en tratamiento con interferón beta (IFNB)-1a intramuscular (Avonex®) fueron significativamente más cumplidores (96,4%) que los pacientes tratados con IFNB-1a 22&amp;#956;g subcutáneo (s.c.) (Rebif®22) (79,1%; p=0,0064), IFNB-1a 44&amp;#956;g s.c. (Rebif®44) (79,6%; p=0,0064) y acetato de glatiramero (Copaxone®) (82,7%; p=0,0184). En V1 (n=142), la tasa de adherencia fue del 86,6%; los pacientes con Avonex® fueron significativamente más cumplidores que aquellos con Rebif®22 (el 93,9 frente al 66,7%; p=0,0251). En V2 (n=131), la tasa de adherencia fue del 82,4% (Avonex®, 87,5%; Rebif®22, 80%; Rebif®44, 77,8%; Betaferon®, 85,2%, y Copaxone®, 80%) sin diferencias significativas.Conclusiones: La adherencia permaneció alta los 2 años observados. Avonex® mostró mayor adherencia frente al resto; esta diferencia fue significativa en la visita basal, tras 40,5 meses de media en tratamiento y en V1 frente a Rebif®22 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;25(7): 435-42, sept. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94739</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio global de adherencia a los tratamientos inmunomoduladores en pacientes con esclerosis múltiple remitente recidivante: resultados a 2 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
