<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124452</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intraluminal/endoscopic procedures in the treatment of obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Few effective therapeutic tools are currently available to fight the increasing prevalence of obesity and its associated comorbidities. Bariatric surgery is the only treatment with proven long-term effectiveness, but is associated to a high surgical risk and significant economic costs because of its technical complexity and the characteristics of patients. This is leading to development of new endoscopic procedures with less clinical risks and economic costs, while maintaining the benefits in terms of morbidity and mortality, which could even serve as a bridging element before surgery in cases where this is unavoidable, allowing for preoperative weight loss and control of comorbidities in order to improve anesthetic risks and possible complications. The purpose of this review was to analyze the most relevant and promising endoscopic techniques currently available (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aliaga-Verdugo, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Varo, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobrino-Rodríguez, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Lluch, Ana R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belda-Laguna, Ovidio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira-Cunill , José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Luna, Pedro Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ortega, Antonio Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad contamos con escasas herramientas terapéuticas eficaces para combatir la creciente prevalencia de obesidad y comorbilidades asociadas. La cirugía bariátrica es el único tratamiento que ha demostrado su efectividad a largo plazo. Sin embargo, la alta complejidad técnica de la misma, junto a las características de los propios pacientes, implican un elevado riesgo quirúrgico e importante coste económico. Esto está llevando al desarrollo de nuevos procedimientos por vía endoscópica con un menor riesgo clínico y coste económico, manteniendo los beneficios en cuanto a morbimortalidad, incluso pudiendo servir de elemento «puente» previamente a la cirugía en los casos en que esta sea inevitable, pero permitiendo una pérdida de peso y control de comorbilidades que mejoren el riesgo prequirúrgico. El objeto de nuestra revisión es el análisis de las técnicas endoscópicas más relevantes en estos momentos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(5): 264-273, mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124452</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Procedimientos endoluminales/endoscópicos en el tratamiento de la obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23642^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
