<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136813</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alcohol and human metabolismo</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the objectives of this present work is to carry out an up-to-date and summarised review of the most relevant aspects of alcohol absorption, distribution, metabolism and excretion processes. Although there are significant individual variations, alcohol is, in the main, absorbed at an intestinal level distributed by the organism in an analogous way to that of body water and most of it is metabolised. Given that the basic biotransformation of ethanol is produced by means of an oxidative enzymatic metabolism, we have set aside a section to analyse - insofar as possible- the enzymatic systems responsible for such oxidisation. In addition, in this chapter, we would like to provide a summary of the data available on the involvement of acetaldehyde, primary metabolic oxidative, in the effects of alcohol. Said involvement is not limited, as was hitherto believed, to the toxic effects derived from alcohol consumption. On the contrary, there is an increasingly solid body of experimental knowledge that associates acetaldehyde with the euphoric effects of alcohol and, consequently, with the ability of this drug to establish a pattern of repeated consumption. Finally, there is a review of the interactions that can occur between the metabolism of alcohol and the biotransformation of other substances. These interactions may always lead to endogenous or exogenous substances sharing the same enzymatic systems with ethanol. In this sense, the induction of the P-450 2E1 and other P-450 cytochromes in hepatic cells, provoked by the chronic consumption of alcohol, merits particular attention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aragón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchis-Segura, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miquel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los propósitos del presente trabajo es llevar a cabo una revisión actualizada y resumida de los aspectos más relevantes de los procesos de absorción, distribución, biotransformación (metabolismo) y excreción del alcohol. Aunque con variaciones individuales importantes, el alcohol se absorbe mayoritariamente a nivel intestinal, se distribuye por el organismo de forma análoga a la del agua corporal, y se metaboliza en su mayor parte. Dado que la biotransformación fundamental del etanol se produce mediante un metabolismo enzimático oxidativo, hemos reservado un apartado para analizar, en la medida de lo posible, los sistemas enzimáticos responsables de dicha oxidación. Asimismo, con este capítulo hemos querido ofrecer un resumen de los datos disponibles sobre la implicación del acetaldehido, primer metabolito oxidativo del etanol, en los efectos del alcohol. Dicha implicación no se reduce, como tradicionalmente se ha creído, a los efectos tóxicos derivados del consumo de alcohol. Por el contrario, existe un corpus de conocimientos experimentales cada vez más sólido que relaciona al acetaldehido con los efectos euforizantes del alcohol y, en consecuencia, con la capacidad de esta droga de establecer un patrón de consumo repetido. Finalmente, se revisan las interacciones que pueden ocurrir entre el metabolismo del alcohol y la biotransformación de otras sustancias. Dichas interacciones pueden tener lugar siempre que sustancias endógenas o exógenas compartan con el etanol los mismos sistemas enzimáticos. En este sentido, merece especial atención la inducción del P-450 2E1 y otros citocromos P-450 en las células hepáticas provocada por el consumo crónico de alcohol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);14(supl.1): 23-42, 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136813</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alcohol y metabolismo humano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19061^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d83^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33012^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23169^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
