<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95945</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Thyroid and parathyroid surgery are associated with upper and recurrent laryngeal nerve injury. The ProSeal®Larynx mask (LM-PS) allows endoscopic visualisation of the vocal cords during the stimulation of these nerves. This facilitates the identification of these nerves, reducing complications. Furthermore, avoiding endo-tracheal intubation allows a faster recovery and a functional larynx evaluation at the end of surgery, facilitating ambulatory surgery. Objective: To clinically evaluate the LM-PS as a ventilation device in thyroid and parathyroid surgery. Material and methods: Thirty seven patients (ASA I or II),operated on electively because of thyroid or parathyroid diseases, were included in the study. We collected data on: facility of insertion, seal, leakage pressure, effectiveness of ventilation, hemodynamicstatus, correct exposition, laryngeal nerve function and associated complications. Results: LM-PS was inserted on the first attempt in 97.3% of the patients. Mean leak and peak pressures were 40 and 26 cmH2O respectively, maintaining adequate ventilation. No hemodynamicalterations were registered. Only one case needed neurostimulation. I n another case we diagnosed a postoperative recurrent laryngeal nerve injury. Conclusions: The main qualities of the LM-PS mask are its facility of use, its efficiency for ventilation and the absence of significant complications. All these allow quick post-anaesthetic recovery facilitating patient&#146;s discharge. The laryngeal nerve identification at surgery contributes to reducing surgical morbidity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Simó, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Payá, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moret García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Guijarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La cirugía de tiroides y paratiroides asocia frecuente morbilidad, destacando las lesiones de los nervios laríngeo superior y recurrente. La utilización de la mascarilla laríngea Pro-Seal® (ML-PS), permite la visualización endoscópica de las cuerdas vocales al estimular dichos nervios, facilitando su identificación y reduciendo las secuelas. Además, la ausencia de intubación permite una rápida recuperación, así como la valoración funcional laríngea al término de la cirugía, diagnosticando y resolviendo precozmente cualquier complicación, facilitando la CMA. Objetivo: Valorar clínicamente la ML-PS como dispositivo de ventilación en cirugía de tiroides y paratiroides y sus posibles aportaciones. Material y métodos: Se incluyeron 37 pacientes, ASA I-II, programados para cirugía de tiroides o paratiroides. Registramos la facilidad de inserción, sellado, presión de fuga, eficacia ventilatoria, estabilidad hemodinámica, exposición del campo, funcionalidad de los nervios recurrentes y complicaciones asociadas. Resultados: La ML-PS se colocó al primer intento en el97,3% de los casos, las presiones medias de fuga y pico fueron40 y 26 cm H2O respectivamente, manteniendo adecuada ventilación. No se registraron alteraciones hemodinámicas tras su colocación ni complicaciones significativas. Solamente en uno de los casos se precisó neuroestimulación, y en otro caso se pudo diagnosticar precozmente una afectación recurrencial postoperatoria. Conclusiones: La facilidad de colocación, buen sellado, eficacia ventilatoria y ausencia de complicaciones significativas hacen de la ML-PS un dispositivo seguro y eficaz, permitiendo la rápida recuperación del procedimiento anestésico, facilitando el alta del paciente. Además, la mejor exposición e identificación nerviosa yla posibilidad de revisión al concluir la cirugía configuran la ML-PS como un elemento útil que contribuye a reducir la morbilidad operatoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;15(2): 44-48, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95945</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la mascarilla laríngea Proseal® en cirugía de tiroides y paratiroides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29078^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10468^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
