<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94084</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">(No) possible pradigms of nursing. The necessity of an extraordinary rupture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A Foucaultian approximation of the discussion in terms of the nature of the normal science of nursing and the possible extraordinariness of the Transformation paradigm described by Kerouack et al. and assumed as a desire for development of nursing. A theoretical exercise where Thomas Kuhn offers his concepts which allow for the discussion in terms of the limits of the (No) Possible Paradigms, like space and instance from where tensions could emerge that give rise to extraordinary investigations and paradigms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Irigibel-Uriz, Xabier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aproximación foucaultiana a la discusión en torno a la naturaleza de la ciencia normal de enfermería y la posible extraordinariedad del paradigma de la transformación descrito por Kerouack y col. y asumido como anhelo del desarrollo de la enfermería. Ejercicio teórico donde los aportes conceptuales de Thomas Kuhn permiten ubicar la discusión en torno a los límites de los paradigmas (No) Posibles, como espacio e instante desde donde podrían emerger los enfrentamientos que dieran origen a investigaciones y paradigmas extraordinarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(4): 274-278, oct.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paradigmas de enfermería (no) posibles. La necesidad de una ruptura extraordinaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10881</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
