<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152480</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of interventions for the treatment of dyslexia: a review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this report the research that supports various interventions for the treatment of dyslexia is revised, specifically the works of synthesis, especially synthesis of best evidence, systematic reviews or meta-analyses published about each type of intervention. A review of primary research is made in cases in which no synthesis work has been published or where these works are old. Localised works indicate that the phonological methods of intervention in dyslexia, i.e. those in which training in phonological skills is combined with knowledge of letters and the practice of reading, are widely supported by research. However, research on other methods is either extremely scarce or it offers conflicting results or it leads to the conclusion that they are inefficient methods. Interventions in this situation are: the auditory integration, the auditory training with computer support, visual therapy, the tinted lenses, motor-perceptual training, chiropractic techniques, sensory integration, the Davis method, neurofeedback, music therapy and music education or diets and dietary supplements. Promotion of phonological interventions is recommended; it is necessary to avoid recommendations of intervention methods for dyslexia which are not supported by scientific research; methods of intervention that have not proven their effectiveness may not be presented as therapies or treatments; and the creation and distribution of a guide on intervention in dyslexia based on scientific evidence is recommended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ripoll Salceda, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado Alonso, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este informe se revisa la investigación que respalda distintas intervenciones para el tratamiento de la dislexia, concretamente los trabajos de síntesis, en especial síntesis de las mejores evidencias, revisiones sistemáticas o metaanálisis publicados sobre cada tipo de intervención. En los casos en que no se ha publicado ningún trabajo de síntesis o estos trabajos son antiguos, se hace una revisión de la investigación primaria. Los trabajos localizados indican que los métodos fonológicos de intervención en la dislexia, es decir, aquellos en los que se combina el entrenamiento en habilidades fonológicas con el conocimiento de las letras y la práctica de la lectura, están ampliamente respaldados por la investigación. En cambio, la investigación sobre otros sistemas es sumamente escasa, ofrece resultados contradictorios o indica que se trata de sistemas ineficaces. Las intervenciones que están en estas situaciones son: la integración auditiva, el entrenamiento auditivo con soporte informático, la terapia visual, las lentes tintadas, el entrenamiento perceptivo-motor, las técnicas quiroprácticas, la integración sensorial, el método Davis, el neurofeedback, la musicoterapia y la educación musical o las dietas y suplementos alimenticios. A partir de esta revisión se realizan las siguientes recomendaciones: promocionar las intervenciones de tipo fonológico para el tratamiento de la dislexia, no utilizar o recomendar intervenciones que no estén respaldadas por la investigación científica, que los métodos de intervención que no hayan probado su eficacia no reciban el nombre de «terapia» o «tratamiento», y la creación y difusión de una guía sobre intervención en dislexia basada en evidencias científicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);36(2): 84-100, abr.-jun. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de las intervenciones para el tratamiento de la dislexia: una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4041^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6462^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4473^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2730^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4041^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6460</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4473^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
