<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72250</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7961</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Head  trauma and nutritional management of the neurological patient in a critical status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Head trauma (HT) and critically ill neurological patients represent one of the paradigms in severe acute lesion since, although being acutely and severely ill, many of them may recover. The extremely severe aggression determining this type of pathology is the trigger of a thunderstorm of inflammatory mediators, metabolic response, and neuroendocrine impairment that condition a burst in the combustion process of the injured organism. This internal combustion is nurtured by the organic reserves leading to their consumption and, thus, the dysfunction of the different organ systems.In this chapter a review is performed with an update of the pathophysiologic mechanisms that occur in these situations,their metabolic impact, and the possibilities for a specific and targeted nutritional and metabolic support.Special attention is paid to hyperglycaemia in the setting of head trauma and the support with pharmaconutrients (glutamine) in these situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de Lorenzo y Mateos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Montes, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes con traumatismo craneoencefálico (TCE) y los neurocríticos constituyen uno de los paradigmas en la agresión aguda grave pues aunque son agudos y graves son, afortunadamente, recuperables en una gran proporción de las ocasiones. La muy importante agresión que determina este tipo de patología es el detonante de una tormenta de mediadores inflamatorios, respuesta metabólica y alteración neuro-endocrina que condicionan una aceleración en el proceso de combustión del organismo lesionado. Esta combustión interna se nutre delas reservas orgánicas, determinando su consumo y con ello, disfunción de los diferentes órganos. En este capítulo se efectúa una revisión y puesta al día de los mecanismos fisiopatológicos que se producen en estas situaciones, de su repercusión metabólica y de las posibilidades que un soporte nutrometabólico -específico y dirigido- ofrece. Se dedica una especial atención a lahiperglucemia en el seno del trauma craneoencefálico y al aporte de farmaconutrientes (glutamina) en estas situaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;2(supl.2): 106-113, mayo 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72250</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Traumatismo craneoencefálico y manejo nutricional del pacienteneurológico en estado crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
