<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163642</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Care of oncological patients: a review on the impact of the chronic stress situation and its relation to the caregiver personality and other modulator variables</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The prevalence of long-term diseases such as cancer has increased in recent years. In this context, our aim will be to analyze the main consequences resulting from exposure to a chronic stress situation, such as the care of an oncologic patient. The effects of this situation on the psychosocial health and cognitive function of informal caregivers and their relationship with possible modulating variables will be revised. Method: A bibliographic review was performed in PubMed and PsycINFO databases about the consequences related to the caregiving of patients with chronic diseases. Results: Several studies suggest that the condition of caregiver of cancer patients could be considered as an and stressful situation. It has consequences on caregiver&#146;s physical and psychosocial health, and can induce a decrease of cognitive functioning, although these changes may be modulated by different variables. Conclusion: These data suggest the need of implementing intervention programs in order to mitigate the deleterious consequences of the caregiving situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesa-Gresa, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Campos, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redolat, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La incidencia y prevalencia de enfermedades de larga duración como el cáncer se ha incrementado en los últimos años. En este contexto, nuestro principal objetivo será el análisis de las principales consecuencias que la exposición a una situación de estrés crónico, como es el cuidado de un paciente oncológico, tiene sobre la salud psicosocial y la función cognitiva del cuidador informal y su relación con variables moduladoras. Método: Se realizó una revisión bibliográfica en las bases de datos PubMed y PsychINFO sobre las consecuencias de la situación de cuidado en pacientes crónicos. Resultados: Diversos estudios sugieren que la condición de cuidador de un paciente oncológico puede considerarse una situación estresante que conlleva consecuencias tanto a nivel de salud física como psicosocial del cuidador además de un deterioro en su funcionamiento cognitivo que pueden estar modulados por diferentes variables. Conclusión: Estos datos sugieren la importancia de implementar programas de intervención que amortigüen las consecuencias deletéreas de la labor de cuidado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);14(1): 93-106, ene.-jun. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163642</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidado de pacientes oncológicos: una revisión sobre el impacto de la situación de estrés crónico y su relación con la personalidad del cuidador y otras variables moduladoras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32195^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
