<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161302</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Related factors with extravasation of non-cytostatic agents in peripheral vein catheters</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know the independent variables related to the occurrence of extravasation in patients with peripheral vein catheters (PVC). Material and method:  Retrospective study carried out in 6 longitudinal cuts between July 2013 an January 2014. A total of 1,442 PVC were reviewed, of which 730 met the inclusion criteria, and were divided into 2 groups: extravasation and not extravasation, with 365 cases each. The variables of age, gender, admission unit, catheter gauge, insertion site, previous insertion into the same limb, hospital unit where the insertion took place, communication difficulties, personal health history and analyzed parenterally drug administered were considered. Results: Risk factors to develop extravasation were: female gender, with previous insertion in the same limb, &lt;72h PVC of insertion, communication difficulties, personal health history of neoplasia and KCl, gentamicin or beta lactam treatment. Conclusions: Our study allows to know the variables that are related to the emergence of extravasations in patients with non-cancer treatments (gender, medical service of admission, catheter gauge, elapsed time since the insertion, patient communication difficulties, personal health history, and intravenous treatments), as well as the factors that may be considered protective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mata Peón, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández García, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avanzas Fernández, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las variables independientes que tienen relación con la aparición de extravasación en pacientes portadores de catéteres venosos periféricos (CVP). Material y método: Estudio retrospectivo desarrollado en 6 cortes quincenales entre julio de 2013 y enero de 2014. Se revisaron un total de 1.442 CVP, de los que 730 cumplían los criterios de inclusión y se dividieron en 2 grupos: extravasación y no extravasación, con 365 casos cada uno. Se analizaron las variables edad, sexo, servicio de ingreso, calibre del CVP, lugar de inserción, inserción previa en la misma extremidad, unidad donde se insertó el CVP, dificultad de comunicación, antecedentes personales de salud y fármacos parenterales administrados. Resultados: Los factores de riesgo asociados a tener extravasación fueron: ser mujer, con inserción previa en el mismo brazo, &lt;72h de la inserción, con dificultades en la comunicación, tener antecedentes de neoplasia y con tratamiento de ClK, gentamicina o betalactámicos. Conclusiones: Nuestro estudio permite conocer las variables que tienen relación con la aparición de extravasaciones en pacientes con tratamientos no oncológicos (sexo, servicio médico de ingreso, calibre del catéter, tiempo transcurrido desde la inserción, facilidad de comunicación del paciente, antecedentes y tratamientos intravenosos), así como los factores que pueden considerarse protectores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);27(2): 71-78, mar.-abr. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161302</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores relacionados con extravasaciones de agentes no citostáticos en catéteres venosos periféricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5219^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55027^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
