<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87613</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of the control of blood pressure in Spain in the period 2002&#150;2006. PRESCAP Studies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesDiscuss the evolution of blood pressure (BP) control grade in a large sample of Spanish hypertensive patients in the period of 2002&#150;2006.Material and methodsThe PRESCAP were cross-sectional and multicenter studies designed to calculate prevalences that were conducted in 2002 and 2006 using the same methodology in similar populations attending in primary care (PC). They included patients &amp;#8805;18 years diagnosed of high blood pressure (HBP) who received anti-hypertensive drug treatment. Good control of HBP was considered as BP&lt;140 and&lt;90mmHg in general (&lt;130 and&lt;80mmHg in patients with diabetes, nephropathy or cardiovascular disease). A descriptive statistical study and comparison of means and percentages with the SPSS version 15.0 were made.ResultsA total of 12,754 patients (57.2% women) with mean age of 63.3±10.8 years were included in PRESCAP 2002 and 10,520 (53.7% women) with a mean age of 64.6±11.3 years in PRESCAP 2006. In the year 2002, control of systolic BP (SBP) and diastolic BP (DB) of 36.1% (95% CI, 35.2&#150;36.9) was observed and, in 2006, of 41.4% (95% CI, 40.5&#150;42.4). The percentage of diabetic patients with controlled BP was 9.1% (95% CI, 8.0&#150;10.2) in 2002 and 15.1% (95% CI, 13.8&#150;16.5) in 2006.ResultsIn the PRESCAP 2002, 56.0% received antihypertensive monotherapy, 35.6% combinations of two drugs and 8.4% three or more drugs, and in the PRESCAP 2006 these percentages were 44.4%, 41.1% and 14.5%, respectively.ConclusionsThe control grade of HBP in Spain improved in the period of 2002&#150;2006. The factors that may have had an influence in these results are the extensive amount of bibliography generated during this period on the need to achieve adequate control of BP and the change in the prescription profile of the PC physician, which indicates a greater percentage of combinations of antihypertensive drugs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Roca, G. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lou Arnal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Banegas Banegas, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Díaz, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Segura Alsina, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Divisón Garrote, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durá Belinchón, R. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Rodríguez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios Alonso, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Ruiz, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Moreno, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosDiscutir la evolución del grado de control de la presión arterial (PA) en una amplia muestra de pacientes hipertensos españoles durante el período 2002&#150;2006.Material y métodosLos PRESCAP fueron estudios transversales y multicéntricos diseñados para la estimación de prevalencias, que se realizaron en los años 2002 y 2006 con la misma metodología en poblaciones similares asistidas en atención primaria (AP). Éstos incluyeron a pacientes &amp;#8805;18 años diagnosticados de hipertensión arterial (HTA) que recibían tratamiento farmacológico antihipertensivo. Se consideró buen control de la HTA cuando la PA fue &lt;140 y&lt;90mmHg en general (&lt;130 y&lt;80mmHg en pacientes con diabetes, nefropatía o enfermedad cardiovascular). Se realizó estadística descriptiva y comparación de medias y porcentajes con el paquete SPSS versión 15.0.ResultadosSe incluyó a 12.754 pacientes (el 57,2% eran mujeres) con una edad media de 63,3±10,8 años en PRESCAP 2002 y a 10.520 pacientes (el 53,7% eran mujeres) con una edad media de 64,6±11,3 años en el PRESCAP 2006. En el año 2002 se observó un control de la PA sistólica (PAS) y de la PA diastólica (PAD) del 36,1% (intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC 95%]: 35,2&#150;36,9) y en 2006 del 41,4% (IC 95%: 40,5&#150;42,4). El porcentaje de pacientes diabéticos con PA controlada resultó del 9,1% (IC 95%: 8,0&#150;10,2) en 2002 y del 15,1% (IC 95%: 13,8&#150;16,5) en 2006.ResultadosEn el PRESCAP 2002 el 56,0% recibía monoterapia antihipertensiva, el 35,6% recibía combinaciones de dos fármacos y el 8,4% recibía tres o más fármacos, y en el PRESCAP 2006 estos porcentajes fueron del 44,4; el 41,1 y el 14,5%, respectivamente.Conclusiones(..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;26(6): 257-265, nov. -dic. 2009. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87613</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del control de la presión arterial en España en el período 2002&#150;2006. Estudios PRESCAP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1822^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
