<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10924</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Syphilis epidemics: a descriptive study of patients diagnosed in a tertiary hospital between 2011 and 2015</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: In the last decade, the incidence of syphilis has increased in our health area. Our objective is to describe the epidemiological and clinical characteristics of patients diagnosed with syphilis at our centre and their relationship with HIV. Patients and methods: The clinical and epidemiological variables of patients diagnosed with syphilis in a third-level hospital over a period of 4.5 years, as well as their HIV status, were analysed through a descriptive study. Results: There was a significant increase in the incidence of syphilis in the period 2011-2015. We included 220 patients, 98% men (94% MSM). 62% were HIV+ and 89% came in early/infectious stages of the disease. 7% were concomitantly diagnosed with HIV. There was a high number of sexual partners and frequent use of drugs associated with sexual activity (46%). Conclusions: The incidence of syphilis has increased in our centre in the last 2 years. The most affected group is MSM, with high HIV prevalence and risk behaviours for STI acquisition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fustà, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuertes, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alsina-Gibert, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, José Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lugo-Colón, Rossie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baras, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: En la última década la incidencia de sífilis se ha incrementado en nuestra área sanitaria. Nuestro objetivo es describir las características epidemiológicas y clínicas de los pacientes diagnosticados de sífilis en nuestro centro y su relación con el VIH. Pacientes y métodos: Se analizaron, mediante estudio descriptivo, las variables clínicas y epidemiológicas de los pacientes diagnosticados de sífilis en un hospital de tercer nivel en un período de 4,5 años, así como su estatus respecto al VIH. Resultados: Se observó un importante aumento en la incidencia de sífilis en el período 2011-2015. Se incluyeron 220 pacientes, el 98% hombres (el 94% HSH). El 62% eran VIH+. El 89% acudieron en etapas tempranas/infecciosas de la enfermedad. El 7% fueron diagnosticados de VIH de forma concomitante. Se observó un elevado número de parejas sexuales y frecuente consumo de drogas asociadas al ámbito sexual (el 46%). Conclusiones: La incidencia de sífilis se ha incrementado en nuestro centro en los últimos 2 años. El colectivo más afectado es el de los HSH, con gran prevalencia de VIH y con conductas de riesgo para la adquisición de ITS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);149(12): 536-539, dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10924</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Emergencia de la sífilis: Estudio descriptivo de pacientes diagnosticados de sífilis en un hospital de tercer nivel entre 2011 y 2015</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
