<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132394</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medicinal plants used in the communities of Ita Azul and San Gervasio (Paraguay)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present work was developed within the framework of the project «Conservation, strengthening and sustainable use of the flora of Ita Azul and San Gervasio, Colonia In dependencia, Managed Resources Reserve Yvyturuzú. Paraguay», aimed to determine the medicinal plants used by the communities of Ita Azul and San Gervasio, Colonia Independencia, Guairá Department, Paraguay. Surveys were conducted in the aforementioned communities to 81 people, who reported the use of 68 species of medicinal plants belonging to 35 families, mainly to Asteraceae (19%), Rutaceae (9 %), as well as Fabaceae, Lamiaceae and Verbenaceae (6% each). 53% of the species reported were native. The use of fresh plants (36%) was preferred, being the leaf the part of the plant most frequently used (32%). The plants were mainly prepared as infusion, mixed with mate leaf, in a preparation which is known as «tereré» (43%). The conditions for which the medicinal plants were used were grouped in 11 categories, being digestive disorders followed by respiratory conditions the most reported. For 11 species, no use was reported. The ethnofarmacological and ethnobotanical knowledge is transmitted orally from one generation to another, mainly by women. Scientific research can contribute efficiently to preserve this cultural heritage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Degen de Arrúa, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Yenny</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo se desarrolló dentro del marco del Proyecto: «Conservación, fortalecimiento y uso sostenible de la flora de Itá Azul y San Gervasio, Colonia Independencia, Reserva de Recursos Manejados Yvyturuzú. Paraguay», tuvo por objetivo determinar las plantas medicinales empleadas por las comunidades de Itá Azul y San Gervasio, (Colonia Independencia, Departamento de Guairá), Paraguay. Para ello se realizaron encuestas en las mencionadas comunidades, siendo encuestadas en total 81 personas, quienes reportaron un total de 68 especies de uso medicinal distribuidas en 35 familias, siendo las familias con mayor número de especies las Asteráceas (19%), Rutáceas (9%) y Fabáceas, Lamiáceas y Verbenáceas (6% cada una). El 53 % de las especies reportadas son nativas. Se prefiere el uso de las plantas en estado fresco (36%), siendo la parte de la planta más empleada la hoja (32%) y la forma de uso mayormente mencionada el tereré (infusión de las plantas conjuntamente con hoja de mate, 43%). Las afecciones reportadas se agruparon en 11 categorías, de las cuales los trastornos digestivos seguidos por las afecciones respiratorias fueron las más reportadas en el uso de plantas medicinales. Para 11 especies no se ha reportado el uso. El conocimiento etnofarmacobotánico se transmite oralmente de una generación a otra, principalmente a través de las mujeres. La investigación científica puede contribuir eficazmente a preservar este patrimonio cultural (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;14(2): 153-166, dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132394</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plantas medicinales utilizadas en las comunidades de Itá Azul y San Gervasio (Paraguay)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33302^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33148^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19405^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33148^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33297^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33302^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33297^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35936^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35936^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
