<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040532</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preparation and handling of powdered infant formulae: comments on the recommendations of the European Society for Paediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition Committee on Nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Powdered infant formulas are not sterile and can contain small numbers of bacteria. Serious infections, especially in newborns and infants at risk, have been attributed to the contamination of these products. Of all the contaminating microorganisms, Enterobacter sakazakii, a gram-negative rod-shaped bacterium, appears to pose particularly serious risks. For this reason, in recent years, the World Health Organization, the Food and Agriculture Organization and the European Society for Pediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition (ESPGHAN) have become concerned with this problem and have drawn up a series of recommendations for the preparation and handling of powdered infant formulae, in the attempt to minimize the risk of infections. These recommendations are intended not only for the manufacturers of these products, but for the institutional and home settings, as well.    The purpose of this review is to discuss these recommendations and a number of considerations concerning the use of powdered infant formulas</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dalmau Serra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galiano Segovia, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Villares, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fórmulas infantiles en polvo no son productos estériles. Se han descrito infecciones graves en recién nacidos y lactantes vulnerables relacionadas con la contaminación de las fórmulas infantiles en polvo. De entre todos los gérmenes contaminantes, adquiere especial relevancia el Enterobacter sakazakii. Por este motivo, la OMS/FAO y la Sociedad Europea de Gastroenterología, Hepatología y Nutrición Pediátricas han elaborado una serie de recomendaciones sobre la preparación y la manipulación de estas fórmulas en polvo, dirigidas tanto a los fabricantes de fórmulas infantiles, como a las instituciones en las que se utilicen estos productos y a los padres que preparan los biberones en casa.    Estas recomendaciones y algunas consideraciones sobre el uso de las fórmulas infantiles en polvo constituyen el objetivo de este trabajo de revisión</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;63(7): 279-282, jul.-ago. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Preparación y manejo de las fórmulas infantiles en polvo. Reflexiones en torno a las recomendaciones del Comité de Nutrición de la ESPGHAN</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5650^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38404^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38404^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38403^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37926^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38403^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24447^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24447^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37926^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
