<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165182</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Complex regional pain syndrome (CRPS I and CRPS II), also known as reflex sympathetic dystrophy and causalgia, is a disease characterized by the presence of severe pain, swelling and other changes that occur after an adverse trigger event. Spinal cord stimulation (SCS) is applied by the percutaneous placement of electrodes in the epidural space under fluoroscopy to produce electrical stimulation directly on the posterior spinal cords in order to inhibit the conduction of nociceptive stimuli. Object: The aims of this study were focused on identifying the variables analysed in studies of patients with type I complex regional pain syndrome (CRPS I) treated with SCS and determining the effectiveness of the SCS in type I complex regional pain syndrome. Material and methods: To meet the objectives proposed in the present study, a literature review was conducted in the following databases: MEDLINE, PEDro, LILACS, IBECS, SPORTDiscus, Academic search complete and CINAHL. In addition, publishing platforms such as ScienceDirect, Springer- Link, OVID, ProQuest and Elsevier were consulted. The most recent search among all documentary resources was conducted in June 2016. The studies to be included were those analysing the effects of SCS on CRPS I. Results and conclusions: From 213 articles identified, 22 studies were selected to be part of this review (11 clinical trials and 11 case reports). The variables studied were pain, quality of life, functional status, trophic and vasomotor disturbances, temperature, patient satisfaction and treatment costs. The studies revealed a significant decrease in pain, which greatly enhanced the quality of life of patients with CRPS I in the short term. SCS also influenced the temperature and improved the trophic changes of the affected limb, although the effect on vasomotor disturbances and functional status is unclear (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-López, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Fuentes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El síndrome de dolor regional complejo (SDRC I y SDRC II), también conocido como distrofia simpático refleja y causalgia, es una enfermedad caracterizada por la presencia de dolor intenso, edema y otras alteraciones que aparecen tras un episodio nocivo desencadenante. La estimulación eléctrica medular (EEM) se aplica mediante la colocación percutánea de electrodos en el espacio epidural bajo control radioscópico, para producir la estimulación eléctrica directamente sobre los cordones medulares posteriores con el fin de inhibir la conducción de los estímulos nociceptivos. Objetivos: Los objetivos de este estudio se centraron en identificar las variables analizadas en los estudios de pacientes con síndrome de dolor regional complejo tipo I (SDRC I) tratados con EEM y conocer la eficacia de la EEM en el síndrome de dolor regional complejo tipo I. Material y métodos: Para cubrir los objetivos propuestos en el presente estudio, se realizó una revisión bibliográfica en las bases de datos MEDLINE, PEDro, LILACS, IBECS, SPORTDiscus, Academic search complete y CINAHL. Además, se consultaron plataformas editoriales como ScienceDirect, Springerlink, OVID, Proquest y ELSEVIER. La última búsqueda en todos los recursos documentales se realizó en junio de 2016. Los estudios incluidos debían analizar los efectos de la EEM sobre el SDRC I. Resultados y conclusiones: De los 213 artículos identificados, 22 estudios fueron seleccionados para formar parte de esta revisión (11 ensayos clínicos y 11 informes de casos). Las variables estudiadas fueron el dolor, la calidad de vida, el estado funcional, las alteraciones tróficas y vasomotoras, la temperatura, la satisfacción de los pacientes y los costes del tratamiento. Los estudios revelaron una disminución significativa del dolor, lo que permitió aumentar la calidad de vida de los pacientes con SDRC I a corto plazo. La EEM también influyó sobre la temperatura y mejoró las alteraciones tróficas del miembro afectado, aunque no queda claro el efecto sobre las alteraciones vasomotoras y el estado funcional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;24(4): 169-178, jul.-ago. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la estimulación eléctrica medular en el síndrome de dolor regional complejo tipo I: revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55029^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34216^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12448^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34216^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4904^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
