<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82538</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The performance of school integration according to the perception of specialist teachers in therapeutic pedagogy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main purpose of this article is to analyse the perception that specialist teachers in therapeutic pedagogy have of the integration of students with specific needs for educational support. Diverse groups of students are differentiated. More specifically, it aims to know how teachers perceive students&#146; performance and participation, and also certain attitudes towards the students (acceptance, involvement of fellow students&#133;). Teachers&#146; opinions of various measures to improve integration are also analysed as are the diverse preferred means of schooling and support. For this purpose, a 114-item Lickert-type questionnaire, with 8 additional personal identification items, was used. The sample comprised 106 specialist teachers who work in Asturias, out of an entire sample of 406. The results reveal that specialist teachers do not perceive the same attitudes in the different groups studied. Students with behaviour disorders are the most rejected and the ones from whom teachers can expect the least. The group of ethnic minorities needs to improve family involvement. The specialists demand more human and physical resources and most of them think that ordinary centres provide the most suitable form of schooling (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro-Pañeda, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Manzanera, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo-Mon, M. Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Hernández, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Martino, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo central de este estudio es analizar la percepción que tienen los maestros especialistas en Pedagogía Terapéutica acerca de la integración de los alumnos con necesidad de apoyo educativo. Se diferencian distintos colectivos de alumnos. Más específicamente, se trata de conocer cómo los especialistas perciben el rendimiento y la participación de estos estudiantes, así como determinadas actitudes hacia ellos (aceptación, implicación de los compañeros&#133;). También se analiza su opinión acerca de las diferentes medidas que se proponen para mejorar la integración y cuáles son las modalidades de escolarización y de apoyo preferidas. Para alcanzar estos objetivos se ha utilizado un cuestionario tipo Lickert de 114 ítems, más 8 ítems de identificación personal. La muestra está compuesta por 106 maestros que trabajan en Asturias, de un total de 406. Los resultados revelan que los maestros no perciben las mismas actitudes en todos los colectivos estudiados. Los alumnos con trastornos de comportamiento son los más rechazados y los que menos expectativas generan en los docentes. El grupo de minorías étnicas necesita mejorar la implicación familiar. Los especialistas demandan más recursos personales y materiales y la mayoría opina que la modalidad de escolarización más conveniente la constituyen los centros ordinarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(4): 797-805, 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82538</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Funcionamiento de la integración en la enseñanza según la percepción de los maestros especialistas en Pedagogía Terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4589^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
