<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120202</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-3703</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assisted reproduction in single women and lesbian women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Contemporary societies conceive family models in a different way, to which reproductive medicine has given an answer. It is estimated that in Spain, lesbian population is 0.2% of women between 18 and 49 years old (around 258,500). There were 1,384 lesbian marriages in 2006. Additionally there are 3,619 couples made up of women, and it is estimated that around 300.000 children live within gay or lesbian parents. In the last years we have assisted to an increase on the demand of assisted reproduction techniques by these social groups.  Data of different assisted reproduction techniques employed at IB from 2007 until 2013 is shown, and legal and medical situation reviewed </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baviera, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque, Lydia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berbabeu, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las sociedades contemporáneas conciben los modelos familiares de otra manera, a los que la Medicina Reproductiva ha tenido que dar respuesta. Se estima que en España, la población lesbiana es el 2,7% de las mujeres entre 18 y 49 años (unas 258.500). Hubo 1.384 matrimonios entre mujeres en el año 2006, además existen 3.619 parejas formadas por mujeres, y se estima que unos 300.000 niños viven en el seno de familias homoparentales.   En los últimos años hemos asistido a un incremento de demandas de Técnicas de Reproducción Asistida para estos colectivos. Se presentan datos del IB de las diferentes TRA empleadas desde el año 2007 hasta el año 2013 y se revisa la situación jurídica, legal y médica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fertil. reprod. hum;31(1): 18-22, ene.-mar. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reproducción asistida en mujeres solas y mujeres lesbianas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36295^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32190^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13228^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
