<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165284</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Student-athletes&#146; perceptions of four dual career competencies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to assess athletes&#146; competencies required for a successful combination of elite sport and education, the perceptions of 107 Flemish elite student-athletes of the importance, possession, and need to develop four dual career competencies (DC management, DCM; Career Planning, CPL; Mental Toughness, MTO; Social Intelligence and Adaptability, SIA) were investigated using the Dual Career Competency Questionnaire for Athletes (DCCQ-A; De Brandt et al., 2017). Participants perceived all four competencies as important for a successful DC, reported average to good possession of DC competencies, and perceived a general need to develop their DC competencies. Female student-athletes rated the importance of three of four DC competencies (DCM, CPL, SIA) as well as their perceived possession of the competency DCM higher than their male counterparts, and evaluated a stronger need to develop the competencies MTO and SIA. The study confirmed the relevance (high importance) of the four DC competencies in a sample of Flemish student-athletes, and recommends that gender differences be considered in the development of student-athletes&#146; DC competencies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Defruyt, Simon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wylleman, Paul</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torregrosa, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brandt, Koen De</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Van Rossem, Nicky</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el objetivo de evaluar las competencias necesarias para combinar con éxito el deporte de élite y la educación, se han investigado las percepciones de importancia, posesión y necesidad de desarrollo de competencias para la Carrera Dual (CD; Gestión de CD, DCM; Planificación de Carrera, CPL; Fortaleza Mental MTO; Inteligencia social y Adaptabilidad, SIA respectivamente por sus siglas en inglés) en 107 estudiantes-deportistas Flamencos mediante el Cuestionario de Competencias para la Carrera Dual de Deportistas (DCCQ-A, por sus siglas en inglés; De Brandt et al., 2017). Los participantes perciben las cuatro dimensiones de competencias como importantes para una CD exitosa, reportan una posesión entre media y buena de competencias y, aun así perciben una necesidad general de mejorar sus competencias para la CD. Las estudiantes-deportistas femeninas puntúan la importancia de tres de las cuatro competencias (DCM, CPL, SIA) así como la posesión percibida de DCM más alta que los deportistas masculinos, y evalúan una necesidad más fuerte de desarrollar las competencias MTO y SIA. El estudio ha confirmado la relevancia (alta importancia) de las cuatro competencias de CD en una muestra de estudiantes-deportistas Flamencos y sugiere que debe tenerse en cuenta las diferencias de género, en el desarrollo de las competencias para seguir una CD estudios-deporte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.4): 28-33, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165284</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de cuatro competencias para la Carrera dual en estudiantes-deportistas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53814^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
