<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167913</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effect of pulmonary rehabilitation associated with nutritional supplementation on physical activity in patients with bronchiectasis: randomized trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: physical activity is closely related to mortality and respiratory status for respiratory diseases such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and cystic fibrosis (CF).Pulmonary rehabilitation (PR) programs have been shown to improve the level of physical activity in COPD patients. There are no specific studies on patients with bronchiectasis. Objectives: study the effect of PR on physical activity over 12 weeks, in comparison with PR plus a hyperproteic supplement enriched in beta-hydroxy-beta-methylbutyrate (HMB) in patients with non CF bronchiectasis. Material and methods: prospective, randomized study in which a structured PR program is applied in bronchiectasis patients for three months. Additionally, one of the groups received a hyperproteic supplement with HMB. The degree of physical activity was evaluated at baseline and after three and six months using the wGT3X (ActiGraph) accelerometer and the IPAQ (International Physical Activity Questionnaire).Data was analyzed using a repeated measures ANOVA (intention to treat). Results: 30 patients with non-CF bronchiectasis (15 in each group)were included, without differences in clinical variables between groups. After intervention, a significant percentage of patients in the supplement group increased their average physical activity according to the IPAQ after 3 and 6 months. Significant differences depending on type of intervention were not observed. A slight increase in average moderate intensity physical activity measured by accelerometer was observed at 3 and 6 months, but it did not reach statistical significance. Conclusions: PR, along with nutritional supplements, in non-CF bronchiectasis patients increased the level of physical activity measured by the IPAQ (at 3 and 6 months).However, it did not reach statistical significance according to accelerometer measurements. Further studies are needed to evaluate the validity of the different measurement instruments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Doña, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palenque, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Valero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olveira, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olveira, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la actividad física está fuertemente relacionada con la mortalidad y la situación respiratoria en patologías respiratorias como la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) y la fibrosis quística (FQ). Los programas de rehabilitación respiratoria (RR) han demostrado mejorar el grado de actividad física en pacientes con EPOC. No existen trabajos específicos en pacientes con bronquiectasias (BQ). Objetivos: comparar el efecto sobre la actividad física de la RR durante 12 semanas, comparado con RR más un suplemento hiperproteico enriquecido en beta-hidroxi-beta-metilbutirato (HMB) en pacientes con BQ no debidas a FQ. Material y métodos: estudio prospectivo aleatorizado, en el que se aplica un programa de RR estructurado a pacientes con BQ durante tres meses. A uno de los grupos, además, se le asoció un suplemento hiperproteico con HMB. Se valoró el grado de actividad física en situación basal, a los tres y seis meses mediante acelerómetro wGT3X (ActiGraph) y cuestionario IPAQ. Se analizaron los datos mediante una Anova de medidas repetidas (intención de tratar). Resultados: se incluyeron 30 pacientes con BQ no debidas a FQ (15 en cada rama) sin diferencias en variables clínicas entre los grupos. Después de la intervención, un porcentaje significativo de pacientes incrementaron la actividad física medida mediante el cuestionario IPAQ en el grupo suplementado a los 3 y 6 meses. No se observaron diferencias significativas en función del tipo de intervención. En ambos grupos se observó un discreto aumento de la actividad física de intensidad moderada medida por acelerómetro, a los 3 y 6 meses, pero no alcanzó significación estadística. Conclusiones: la RR, unida a suplementación nutricional en pacientes con BQ no debidas a FQ, aumentó el nivel de actividad física medida mediante el cuestionario IPAQ (a los 3 y 6 meses). Sin embargo, no alcanzó la significación estadística mediante acelerómetro. Son necesarios más estudios que evalúen la validez de los diferentes instrumentos de medida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;29(3): 167-175, oct. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la rehabilitación respiratoria asociada a suplementación nutricional sobre la actividad física en pacientes con bronquiectasias: estudio aleatorizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16558</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
