<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144014</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8169</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of medicine in a lawsuit on the adulteration of tobacco under the old regime (Burgos 1667)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article studies a court case on the adulteration of tobacco in Burgos in 1667. The expert work done by physicians and apothecaries throughout this trial plays a central role. The evolution of this judicial process is described in detail, and additional information is provided on the organization of the tobacconist´s, the preparation of tobaccos, the spectres associated with the adulteration of tobacco and the administration of justice under the old regime. In a second phase, the 'experiences' performed by professionals and the methods of analysis on which their ideas are based are studied, relating the irregular scientific performance to the position occupied in the field of health professionals in Burgos at that time. Finally, based on what has been observed, speculations are made on the shift in control of the adulteration, from the municipal ambit in the early Middle Ages to its integration into the Crown institutions and its relationship with the promotion of physicians and pharmacists as experts in the subject (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Belvis Costes, Francesc Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo estudia un juicio por adulteración del tabaco ocurrido en Burgos en 1667. Los peritajes realizados por médicos y boticarios a lo largo del mismo juegan un papel central. La evolución del proceso judicial es descrita en detalle, proporcionando además información contextual sobre la organización del estanco, la preparación de tabacos, los fantasmas asociados a la adulteración y el funcionamiento de la justicia bajo el antiguo régimen. En una segunda fase se estudian las 'experiencias' llevadas a cabo por los profesionales y los métodos de análisis sobre los que sustentan sus pareceres, relacionando e desigual desempeño científico con el lugar ocupado en el campo de las profesiones sanitarias del Burgos de la época. Finalmente a base a lo observado se especula sobre el desplazamiento del control de la adulteración, desde el ámbito municipal en la Baja Edad Medica hacia su integración en las instituciones de la Corona, y su relación con el ascenso de médicos y farmacéuticos como expertos en el tema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. hist;35(2): 20-40, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la medicina en un proceso por adulteración del tabaco bajo el antiguo régimen (Burgos 1667)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3273</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3433</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37690</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33187^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55775</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11252</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
