<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161256</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-9476</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After years of experience with urostomized patients, we detected a lack of information regarding the sexual life, when it is resumed and the changes that occur after the intervention. Our objective is to know patients who have had a cystectomy and have given information about sexuality, when it was received, if it was useful and what information users need. To do this, he carried out a study with some patients with a cystectomy at the Hospital Son Llàtzer between January 2007 and January 2016. Evaluating the results, those who inform the patients prior to the intervention, the latter receive an increase in their quality of sexual life. That we observe the need for the creation of a multidisciplinary guide to be able to provide the correct and necessary education in each case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Bestard, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz De Urbina Estrade, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll Juan, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Aranda, N de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez Cruz, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terrasa Lozano, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras años de experiencia con pacientes urostomizados detectamos una falta de información en relación a la vida sexual, cuándo podrán retomarla y los cambios que sufrirá tras la intervención. Nuestro objetivo es conocer si a los pacientes a los que se les ha realizado una cistectomía se les ha dado información relativa a la sexualidad, cuándo la recibieron, si fue de utilidad y qué necesidad de información tenían los usuarios. Para ello realizamos un estudio con pacientes sometidos a una cistectomía en el Hospital Son Llàtzer entre enero de 2007 y enero de 2016. Evaluados los resultados constatamos que, informando a los pacientes previamente a la intervención, estos podrían obtener un aumento de su calidad de vida sexual, por lo que observamos la necesidad de la creación de una guía multidisciplinar para poder proporcionar la educación correcta y necesaria en cada caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>ENFURO: Rev. Asoc. Esp. A.T.S. Urol;(132): 44-46, mar. 2017. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La información sexual en pacientes urostomizados, ¿una asignatura pendiente?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14947^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
