<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148914</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of 18F-FDG PET/CT volumetric parameters in recurrent epithelial ovarian cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Metabolic tumour volume (MTV) and total lesion glycolysis (TLG) from 18F-FDG PET/CT are emerging prognostic biomarkers in various solid neoplasms. These volumetric parameters and the SUVmax have shown to be useful criteria for disease prognostication in preoperative and post-treatment epithelial ovarian cancer (EOC) patients. The purpose of this study was to evaluate the utility of 18F-FDG PET/CT measurements to predict survival in patients with recurrent EOC. Material and methods. Twenty-six patients with EOC who underwent a total of 31 18F-FDG PET/CT studies for suspected recurrence were retrospectively included. SUVmax and volumetric parameters whole-body MTV (wbMTV) and whole-body TLG (wbTLG) with a threshold of 40% and 50% of the SUVmax were obtained. Correlation between PET parameters and progression-free survival (PFS) and the survival analysis of prognostic factors were calculated. Results. Serous cancer was the most common histological subtype (76.9%). The median PFS was 12.5 months (range 10.7&#150;20.6 months). Volumetric parameters showed moderate inverse correlation with PFS but there was no significant correlation in the case of SUVmax. The correlation was stronger for first recurrences. By Kaplan&#150;Meier analysis and log-rank test, wbMTV 40%, wbMTV 50% and wbTLG 50% correlated with PFS. However, SUVmax and wbTLG 40% were not statistically significant predictors for PFS. Conclusion. Volumetric parameters wbMTV and wbTLG 50% measured by 18F-FDG PET/CT appear to be useful prognostic predictors of outcome and may provide valuable information to individualize treatment strategies in patients with recurrent EOC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernandez-Martinez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lomeña, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aya, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El metabolic tumour volume (MTV) y la total lesion glycolysis (TLG) obtenidos de la 18F-FDG PET/TC son biomarcadores pronósticos emergentes en varias neoplasias. Estos parámetros volumétricos junto con el SUVmax son útiles para determinar el pronóstico preoperatorio y post-tratamiento de las pacientes con cáncer epitelial de ovario (CEO). El objetivo fue determinar la utilidad de los parámetros de la 18F-FDG PET/TC para predecir la supervivenvia de las pacientes con CEO recurrente. Material y métodos. Se incluyeron retrospectivamente 26 pacientes con CEO a las que se les realizó 31 estudios 18F-FDG PET/TC por sospecha de recidiva. Se obtuvo el valor del SUVmax, whole-body MTV (wbMTV) y whole-body TLG (wbTLG) con un umbral del 40% y 50% del SUVmax. Se estimó la correlación entre los parámetros PET y el intervalo libre de progresión (ILP) y se realizó análisis de supervivencia segun factores pronósticos. Resultados. El subtipo histológico más frecuente fue cáncer seroso (76,9%). La mediana del ILP fue 12,5 meses (rango 10,7-20,6 meses). Se observó correlación inversa moderada entre los parámetros volumétricos e ILP, sin evidenciar correlación significativa con SUVmax. La correlación fue más fuerte para primeras recidivas. Las curvas de supervivencia mostraron correlación entre wbMTV 40%, wbMTV 50% y wbTLG 50% con ILP. SUVmax y wbTLG 40% no fueron predictores de ILP de forma estadísticamente significativa. Conclusión. Los parámetros wbMTV y wbTLG 50% de la 18F-FDG PET/TC podrían utilizarse como factores pronósticos ofreciendo una valiosa información para individualizar el tratamiento de las pacientes con CEO recurrente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);35(2): 88-95, mar.-abr. 2016. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148914</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de los parámetros volumétricos de la 18F-FDG PET/TC en el cáncer epitelial de ovario recurrente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4927^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4927^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31753^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
