<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053128</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adenosquamous and squamous carcinoma of the gallbladder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Squamous and adenosquamous carcinomas of the gallbladder have poor prognosis. Because these tumors are silent in the initial stage, they are generally diagnosed in advanced stages.   Material and method. We performed a retrospective observational study of five patients with squamous or adenosquamous carcinoma of the gallbladder. There were two women and three men with a mean age of 71 years (range, 68-75). All patients showed abdominal pain, nausea, vomiting, and weight lost (4-8 kg). One patient presented with acute cholecystitis. None of the patients had jaundice and all had gallstone disease. Results. Surgery was performed in all patients. Extended cholecystectomy was performed in three patients, cholecystectomy and bile drainage in one patient, and colonic bypass and cholecystectomy in the remaining patient. Pathologic analysis revealed epidermoid carcinoma in two patients and adenosquamous carcinoma in three patients. Two patients were treated with adjuvant chemotherapy. All died within 6 months of surgery. Conclusions. In both histological types of gallbladder carcinoma, treatment depends on the grade of local and regional invasion and tumor spread at diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Taborda, Bruno</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alecha Gil, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echenique Elizondo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tommasino, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eduardo Lada, Paul</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gramática, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Rosso, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El cáncer adenoescamoso y epidermoide o escamoso de vesícula biliar se considera una neoplasia de mal pronóstico, generalmente diagnosticado en etapas avanzadas, fundamentalmente por la escasa repercusión clínica en estadios iniciales.  Material y método. Diseño: retrospectivo observacional. Se presenta a 5 pacientes con cáncer escamoso o adenoescamoso de vesícula biliar (2 mujeres y 3 varones, con una edad promedio de 71 [intervalo, 68-75] años). Todos presentaron dolor abdominal, náuseas, vómitos y pérdida de peso variable entre 4 y 8 kg. Uno de ellos ingresó por un cuadro de colecistitis aguda. Ninguno presentó ictericia. Todos tenían litiasis vesicular.   Resultados. Los 5 pacientes fueron intervenidos. A 3 de ellos se les realizó una colecistectomía ampliada, a 1 paciente, una colecistectomía más drenaje biliar y a otro, bypass cólico más colecistostomía. La anatomía patológica puso en evidencia en 2 un carcinoma epidermoide y en 3, carcinoma adenoescamoso. Del total, a 2 se les realizó quimioterapia adyuvante. Todos los pacientes fallecieron dentro de los 6 meses siguientes a la intervención. Conclusiones. En estas dos variantes histológicas de neoplasias, el tratamiento quirúrgico depende del grado de afección local y regional y de la extensión del tumor en el momento del diagnóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);81(4): 202-206, abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053128</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma adenoescamoso y epidermoide de la vesícula biliar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5843^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1675^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31598^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1675^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31598^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5843^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5843^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2816^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
