<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114680</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Four years experience with the AEC residents E-Book</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Material and method A register of the activities of residents in the AEC-E-Book. The overall activity per year and per rotation has been measured. The relationships of assisted interventions performed and their level of complexity have been analysed. The mean scientific and health care activities and the mean on-call periods per month. Results A total of 8 residents have registered their activity in the AEC-E-Book since the year 2004. They assisted in a mean of 1514 operations, of which 922 were performed as surgeon (62%). They assisted in 185 laparoscopic interventions, of which they performed 72 (39%). As surgeon, 864 (94%) of the 922 procedures 64% were level 1, 75% level 2, and 53% were level 3. They were on-call a mean of 5.75 times per month. They attended a total of 21 courses and congresses during residency. They took part in 24 presentations and posters, as well as in 6 journal publications during residence. Conclusions The AEC-E-Book enables the activity of the resident to be continually assessed. We have been able to find out the mean activities carried out by each resident during a particular rotation and year, thus being able to know exactly if they have fulfilled the defined minimums (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montmany Vioque, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Diaz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corredera Cantarin, Constanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona Navarro, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermoso Bosch, Judit</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Aracil, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio Rodríguez, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Soto, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La introducción del libro informático del residente, de la Asociación Española de Cirujanos (LIR-AEC), nos ha permitido realizar evaluaciones particulares y generales de cada residente. El objetivo ha sido conocer la media de actividades asistenciales, científicas y quirúrgicas según el programa de la especialidad. Material y método Registro de la actividad de los residentes en el LIR-AEC. Se ha cuantificado la actividad general por año y por rotación. Se ha analizado la relación de intervenciones asistidas y realizadas y según grados de complejidad. La media de actividades científicas y asistenciales y la de guardias al mes. Resultados Desde 2004, 8 residentes han registrado su actividad en el LIR-AEC. Asisten a una media de 1.514 intervenciones, de las cuales realizan como cirujano 922 (62%). Asisten a 185 intervenciones laparoscópicas, de las que realizan 72 (39%). Como cirujanos, 864 (94%) de los 922 procedimientos son de los niveles 1, 2 y 3 (el 64, el 75 y el 53%, respectivamente). Realizan una media de 5,75 guardias por mes. Acuden de media durante la residencia a un total de 21 cursos y congresos. Participan en un total de 24 comunicaciones y pósters, así como en 6 publicaciones de media en la residencia. Conclusiones El LIR-AEC permite una evaluación continua de la actividad del residente. Hemos podido conocer la media de actividades que realiza cada residente durante una rotación y un año determinados, esto permite conocer con exactitud si se cumplen los mínimos definidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);86(3): 147-153, sept. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114680</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuatro años de experiencia con el libro informático del residente de la AEC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19133^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
