<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041269</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Heart Transplantation Registry. 16th Official Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Heart Failure, Heart Transplantation, and Associated Therapies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper describes the general situation regarding heart transplantation in Spain and the results obtained using the technique, incorporating data for the year 2004. In 2004, 294 heart transplants were carried out, which brings the total number of procedures performed since 1984 to 4680. Clinically, the typical heart transplant recipient in Spain is male, aged around 50 years, has blood group A, has non-revascularizable coronary artery disease, and is in NYHA functional class IV/IV. The percentage of emergency heart transplantations was 35%, which is higher than in the previous year (29%), and higher than the mean for the preceding 5 years (22%). The early mortality rate was 10%, which is lower that the mean for the preceding 5 years (13%). After combining the results for 2004 with those of previous years, the probability of survival at 1, 5 and 10 years was 80%, 70% and 60%, respectively. When the survival rates for different time periods were analyzed, a significant improvement could be seen in the last 5 years, with recent survival rates being 85% and 72% at 1 and 5 years, respectively. The most frequent cause of death in the first month was acute graft failure; in the first year, infection and rejection; and, over the long term, tumors and a combination of graft vasculopathy and sudden death. A comparative analysis of survival rates showed that long-term results in Spain are slightly better than those published in the world literature. Moreover, survival has tended to improve gradually in recent years</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almenar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se describen las características generales y los resultados obtenidos con el trasplante cardíaco en España tras incluir los datos del último año. En 2004 se efectuaron 294 trasplantes que, junto con los realizados desde 1984, hacen un total de 4.680. El perfil clínico medio del paciente que se trasplanta en España corresponde a un varón de aproximadamente 50 años, de grupo sanguíneo A, con una enfermedad coronaria no revascularizable y en situación funcional IV/IV (NYHA). El porcentaje de trasplantes cardíacos urgentes fue del 35%; esta cifra es muy superior a la del año previo (29%) y a la media de los últimos 5 años (22%). La mortalidad precoz fue del 10%, cifra inferior a la media de los últimos 5 años (13%). Tras incorporar los resultados del pasado año a los previos se obtiene una probabilidad de supervivencia al primer, quinto y décimo años del 80, el 70 y el 60%, respectivamente. Al separar las curvas de supervivencia por períodos se aprecia la importante mejoría en los últimos 5 años, con valores en el primer y quinto años del 85 y el 72%. La causa más frecuente de fallecimiento en el primer mes es el fallo agudo del injerto; en el primer año, la infección y el rechazo, y a largo plazo, los tumores y el combinado de enfermedad vascular del injerto con muerte súbita. El análisis comparativo de la supervivencia muestra que los resultados a largo plazo son ligeramente superiores a los publicados en la bibliografía mundial, con una progresiva tendencia a mejorar la supervivencia en los últimos años</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;58(11): 1310-1317, nov. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041269</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro Español de Trasplante Cardíaco. XVI Informe Oficial de la Sección de Insuficiencia Cardíaca, Trasplante Cardíaco y Otras Alternativas Terapéuticas de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología (1984-2004)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
