<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121430</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results of the cooperative study of Spanish peritoneal dialysis registries: analysis of 12 years of follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: There is currently no registry that gives a complete and overall view of the peritoneal dialysis (PD) situation in Spain. However, a report on PD in Spain was developed for various conferences and meetings over several years from data provided by each registry in the autonomous communities and regions. The main objective of this study is to analyse this data in aggregate and comparatively to obtain a representative sample of the Spanish population on PD in recent years, in order that analysis and results in terms of demographic data, penetration of the technique, geographical differences, incidence and prevalence, technical aspects, intermediate indicators, comorbidity, and outcomes such as patient and technique survival may be extrapolated to the whole country Design, material and method: Observational cohort study of autonomous PD registries, covering the largest possible percentage of the adult Spanish population (over 14 years of age) on PD, at least in the last decade (1999-2010), and in the largest possible geographical area in which we were able to recruit. A precise data collection strategy was followed for each regional registry. Once the information was received and clarified, they were added as aggregate data for statistical study Results: The regional registries that participated represent a total geographical area that encompasses 32,853,251 inhabitants over 14 years of age, 84% of the total Spanish population older than that age. The mean annual rate of incidents per million inhabitants (ppm) was variable (between 17.81ppm in Andalusia and 29.90ppm in the Basque Country), with a discrete and permanent increase in the overall PD incidence in Spain being observed in recent years. The mean annual prevalence per million population (ppm) was very (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo Cooperativo Registros Españoles de Diálisis Peritoneal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Actualmente no existe un registro que muestre en su conjunto y globalidad la realidad de la diálisis peritoneal (DP) en España. Sin embargo, para distintos congresos y reuniones se ha elaborado durante varios años un informe sobre la DP en España a partir de datos comunicados por cada uno de los registros de las comunidades autónomas y regiones. El objetivo fundamental del presente trabajo es analizar todos estos datos en forma agrupada y comparativa, con objeto de conseguir una muestra representativa de la población española en DP en los últimos años, para su análisis y resultados en cuanto a datos demográficos, penetración de la técnica, diferencias geográficas, incidencia y prevalencia, aspectos técnicos, indicadores intermedios, comorbilidad y resultados finales como supervivencia del paciente y de la técnica puedan ser extrapolables a todo el territorio nacional. Diseño, material y métodos: Estudio observacional de cohortes de registros autonómicos de DP, abarcando el mayor porcentaje posible de la población española adulta (mayores de 14 años) en DP, al menos en la última década (1999-2010), y en la mayor área geográfica que nos ha sido posible reclutar. Se ha seguido una estrategia precisa de recogida de información de cada registro autonómico. Una vez recibida la información y depurada, se integran como datos agregados, para su estudio estadístico. Resultados: Los registros autonómicos que han participado representan un área geográfica total que engloba a 32 853 251 habitantes mayores de 14 años, el 84 % de la población   (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;34(1): 18-33, ene.-feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del trabajo cooperativo de los registros españoles de diálisis peritoneal: análisis de 12 años de seguimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16689</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
