<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82687</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rotavirus and seizures. A well-defined uncommon association</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Rotavirus infection, besides gastrointestinal symptoms, may cause several neurological complications. Among these, are benign convulsions with mild gastroenteritis (CwG). Despite having well defined clinical features, its incidence is not well known. Methods: We selected discharge diagnoses of acute diarrhea in children aged 1 month to 5 years who were admitted to Donostia Hospital between July 1996 and June 2008. Among them, we selected those cases with concomitant diagnosis of seizure. Results: Rotavirus was detected in 419 of 1114 children hospitalized for gastroenteritis. (39.2%), Five (1.2%) had symptoms compatible with CwG. The episodes occurred between December and January in all cases. The mean age at diagnosis was 19.6 months. The number of seizures per patient was 2.6 (range 1&#150;4). All the crises were short, the longest being 15min. The total duration of the episode was 1.6 days on average, with up to 3 days. Additional tests performed in all cases, were normal. In subsequent follow-up, one child at 26 months had another episode compatible with this entity at 26 months. During the follow-up period, all patients displayed normal psychomotor development with noe recurrence of seizures. Conclusion: CwG is a rare entity within all acute gastroenteritis associated with rotavirus, but has very specific clinical features that enable it to be identified which could avoid excessive medical tests, and aggressive treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martí, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pardos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Yarza, E. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eizaguirre, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomáriz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cilla, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La infección por rotavirus, además de los síntomas digestivos, puede producir múltiples complicaciones neurológicas. Entre estas se encuentran las convulsiones afebriles asociadas a gastroenteritis leve (CBG). A pesar de tener unas características bien definidas, su incidencia es poco conocida. Métodos: Se seleccionaron los diagnósticos de diarrea aguda de los niños que fueron hospitalizados en el Hospital Donostia, entre julio-1996 y junio-2008 y con edades entre un mes y 5 años. Se seleccionaron aquellos casos con diagnóstico asociado de convulsión. Resultados: Se detectó rotavirus en 419 de los 1.114 niños hospitalizados por GEA (39,2%). Cinco (1,2%) presentaron un cuadro compatible con CBG. Los episodios sucedieron entre diciembre y enero en todos los casos. La edad media de presentación fue 19,6 meses. El número de crisis por paciente fue de 2,6 de media (rango 1&#150;4). Todas las crisis fueron cortas, siendo la de mayor duración de 15min. La duración total del cuadro fue de 1,6 días de media, con un máximo de 3 días. Las pruebas complementarias realizadas en todos los casos, fueron normales. En el seguimiento posterior, uno de los niños a los 26 meses presentó de nuevo un cuadro compatible con esta entidad. Ninguno ha vuelto a presentar crisis y todos tienen un desarrollo psicomotor normal. Conclusiones: La entidad CBG, es una entidad poco frecuente dentro de las gastroenteritis agudas asociadas a rotavirus, pero tiene unas características clínicas muy precisas que permiten su identificación, pudiendo evitar excesivas pruebas complementarias y tratamientos médicos agresivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);73(2): 70-73, ago. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82687</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rotavirus y crisis convulsivas. Una asociación poco frecuente aunque bien definida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13024^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12776^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
