<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046409</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fragile X syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and development. Fragile X syndrome is the main inheritable genetic cause of mental retardation. It isa dynamic mutation and is due to the increase in the number of CGG triplets in exon 1 of the FMR1 gene, located in Xq27.3,and to the hypermethylation of the corresponding genomic region, which impedes production of messenger RNA and, therefore,of FMRP protein. Three types of alleles can be established, according to the number of repetitions: normal, with premutationand with full mutation. Only individuals with full mutation have fragile X syndrome. Two sub-phenotypes of the syndrome,associated to premutation, have recently been reported and are seen to appear from the fourth decade of life onwards.Conclusions. The number of female carriers of a premutation with early ovarian failure has increased, while reports have alsoappeared describing a neurological picture of intentional trembling and ataxia among carriers of the premutation (FXTAS)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Glóver-López, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén-Navarro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y desarrollo. El síndrome X frágil constituyela mayor causa genética heredable de retraso mental. Se tratade una mutación dinámica y se debe al incremento del número detripletes CGG en el exón 1 del gen FMR1, localizado en Xq27.3, ya la hipermetilación de la región genómica correspondiente, queimposibilita la producción del ARN mensajero y, por tanto, de laproteína FMRP. Según el número de repeticiones se pueden establecertres tipos de alelos: normal, con premutación y con mutacióncompleta. Sólo los individuos con mutación completa presentan elsíndrome X frágil. Recientemente se han descrito dos subfenotiposen el síndrome, asociados a la premutación, que se presentan a partirde la cuarta década. Conclusión. Se ha producido un incrementode mujeres portadoras de premutación con fallo ovárico precoz,a la vez que se ha descrito un cuadro neurológico de temblores intencionalesy ataxia entre portadores de la premutación (FXTAS)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(supl.1): s51-s54, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046409</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome X frágil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37282^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6737</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
