<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115574</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of femoral head positioning upon acetabular development</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the alterations produced by the different proximal femoral osteotomies upon acetabular morphology. Material and methods: Thirty 3-month-old lambs were divided into 5 groups: group 1 (varus osteotomy of the femur without modifying femoral version), group 2 (valgus osteotomy of the femur without modifying femoral version), group 3 (derotation osteotomy of the femur, reducing femoral anteversion without modifying the neck-diaphyseal angle), group 4 (derotation osteotomy of the femur, increasing femoral anteversion without modifying the neck-diaphyseal angle), and group 5 (control). The animals were sacrificed three months after the operation and the acetabular and femoral morphology was measured. Results: Femoral version on the operated side was not correlated to the difference between the right and left anteroposterior acetabular diameter, the difference between the right and left inferosuperior acetabular diameter, or the difference between the right and left acetabular volume. The operated neck-diaphyseal angle was correlated to the difference between the right and left acetabular volume (p = 0.023) &#150; the difference in volume decreasing with increasing neck-diaphyseal angle. Conclusion: A diminished neck-diaphyseal angle results in an increased acetabular volume. Therefore, varus osteotomy of the femur could be used to improve the acetabular volume (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moraleda, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albiñana, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forriol, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar las alteraciones que las diferentes osteotomías femorales proximales provocan sobre la morfología acetabular. Material y método: Se intervinieron 30 corderos, de tres meses de edad, divididos en cinco grupos: grupo 1, se efectuó una osteotomía varizante de fémur sin modificar la versión femoral; grupo 2, una osteotomía valguizante de fémur sin modificar la versión femoral; grupo 3, una osteotomía derrotatoria de fémur, disminuyendo la anteversión femoral sin modificar el ángulo cérvico-diafisario; grupo 4, una osteotomía derrotatoria de fémur, aumentando la anteversión femoral sin modificar el ángulo cérvico-diafisario; y grupo 5 o control. El sacrificio se realizó a los tres meses de la intervención y se midió la morfología acetabulo-femoral. Resultados: La versión femoral del lado intervenido no se correlacionó ni con la diferencia entre el diámetro acetabular antero-posterior derecho e izquierdo, ni con la diferencia entre el diámetro acetabular infero-superior derecho e izquierdo, ni con la diferencia entre el volumen acetabular derecho e izquierdo. El ángulo cérvico-diafisario intervenido se correlacionó con la diferencia entre el volumen acetabular derecho e izquierdo (p=0,023), siendo menor la diferencia entre el volumen acetabular derecho e izquierdo cuanto mayor era el ángulo cérvico-diafisario. Conclusión: Un ángulo cérvico-diafisario disminuido provoca un aumento del volumen acetabular. Por lo tanto, la osteotomía varizante de fémur podría utilizarse para mejorar el volumen acetabular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);24(3): 149-155, jul.-sept. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115574</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la posición de la cabeza femoral en el desarrollo acetabular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d81^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13165^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10187^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6773^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6777^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5374^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d81^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5493^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6773^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5374^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6773^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13165^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5493^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5374^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13165^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10187^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36573^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d81^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
