<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037467</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The modulatory role of neurokinins in affective behaviors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurokinins (NK) are peptide molecules with modulatory actions on other neurotransmitter systems, notably the monoaminergic ones, within the central nervous system and peripheral tissues. A great deal of evidence supports a role for these substances, mainly for substance P and its main receptor NK1, in a number of physiologic and pathologic conditions, including affective and behavioral responses to stress. NK1 receptor antagonists have shown preclinical activity in several paradigms of anxiety and depression. Mutant mice lacking the NK1 receptor gene have an increased firing rate of dorsal raphe serotonergic neurons, an effect that can also be seen after the administration of substance P antagonists. When given chronically, NK1 antagonists promote an enhancement of serotonergic transmission in the hippocampus that seems to be mediated by interaction with other neurotransmission systems. Clinical efficacy of such drugs has also been demonstrated among patients with major depression, although the results have been inconclusive. More research is needed to elucidate the precise role these drugs could play in the treatment of affective disorders in the future</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arranz Estévez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las neuroquininas (NK) son moléculas peptídicas que tienen una acción moduladora de otros sistemas neurotransmisores, entre ellos los monoaminérgicos, en el sistema nervioso central, así como en tejidos periféricos. Existen numerosas evidencias de que estas sustancias, y en especial la sustancia P y su principal receptor NK1, intervienen en numerosos procesos fisiológicos y patológicos, entre ellos las respuestas conductuales y afectivas al estrés. Los antagonistas del receptor NK1 han mostrado actividad preclínica en diversos modelos de ansiedad y de depresión. Los ratones mutantes con ausencia del gen del receptor NK1 presentan un aumento de la frecuencia de descarga de las neuronas serotoninérgicas del rafe dorsal, un efecto que también se observa tras la administración de antagonistas de la sustancia P. La administración crónica de antagonistas NK1 produce un aumento de la transmisión serotoninérgica en el hipocampo, que está mediada por la interacción con otros sistemas de neurotransmisión. También se ha demostrado la eficacia clínica de estos fármacos en pacientes con depresión mayor, aunque los resultados no han sido concluyentes. Son precisos más estudios para aclarar el papel que pueden desempeñar este tipo de fármacos en el tratamiento de los trastornos afectivos en el futuro</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(1): 55-65, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel modulador de las neuroquininas en las conductas afectivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23846^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
