<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057069</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-4358</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of the "Inspection Visa" (ex-ante authorization for precribed drugs) and of a health care alert concerning the utilization of topical tacrolimus and pimecrolimus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Tacrolimus and pimecrolimus are two nonsteroidal immunosuppressive agents for topical use        that are indicated in the treatment of the symptoms of atopic dermatitis. Objectives. To analyze the impact        of the passage of these two medications from the condition of «hospital diagnosis» (i.e. prescribed by physicians        in specialized centers) to that of «prescription drug» on the prescription rate. To analyze the impact of        the safety information alert of April 2005 on the rate of prescription of these two treatments. Material and        methods. Design: A retrospective, descriptive study. Setting: Galicia, Spain. Study data source: All the prescriptions        issued by physicians to adults and children. Outcome variable: Number of tubes dispensed (drug        dispensation database of the Galician Health Service). Treatment data: Simple and multiple linear regression        were used to develop an explanatory model. Results. The transition from «hospital diagnosis» to normal        prescription caused an immediate increase in the sales of tacrolimus at higher concentrations and, to a        lesser extent, in 0.03% tacrolimus.        The health alert produced an immediate decrease in sales, although the impact on 0.03% tacrolimus was less        marked. The sales of pimecrolimus initially increased, but were also lowered after the health alert. The sales        began to decrease with the publication from the Food and Drug Administration, before the Spanish Drug        Agency issued its publication. Pimecrolimus appears to be taking over the market that once belonged to 0.03%        tacrolimus</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Silva, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Tacrolimus y pimecrolimus son dos agentes inmunosupresores no esteroideos de administración        tópica, indicados en el tratamiento de los síntomas de la dermatitis atópica. Objetivos. Analizar la        influencia en la prescripción del paso de la condición de fármaco de diagnóstico hospitalario a la de fármaco        con receta médica de estos dos medicamentos. Analizar la influencia de la Nota Informativa de seguridad        de abril de 2005 sobre la prescripción de ambos medicamentos. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo        retrospectivo. Emplazamiento: Galicia. Material de estudio: Todas las prescripciones de médicos a adultos y        niños. Período: desde la comercialización en 2002, hasta septiembre de 2005. Variable: número de envases        dispensados (base de datos de dispensación con cargo al Servicio Galego de Saúde). Tratamiento de datos:        Desarrollo de un modelo explicativo mediante regresión lineal simple o múltiple. Resultados. El paso de la        condición de fármaco de diagnóstico hospitalario a fármaco dispensado con receta normal supuso un incremento        inmediato en las ventas en las series de tacrolimus más concentrado, y en menor medida, en las de        tacrolimus al 0,03%. La alerta sanitaria supuso un descenso inmediato de las ventas, dejándose influir        menos las series de tacrolimus al 0,03%. Pimecrolimus aumentó sus ventas, pero también reaccionó a la baja        con la alerta sanitaria. Las ventas empezaron a disminuir con la publicación de la alerta por parte de la        Food and Drug Administration, antes de la publicación de la Agencia Española del Medicamento. Pimecrolimus        parece acaparar el mercado de tacrolimus al 0,03%</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. aten. prim;5(1): 16-24, 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057069</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del visado de inspección y de una alerta sanitaria sobre la utilización de tacrolimus y pimecrolimus tópicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11792^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31194^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30103^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
