<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27620</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebrospinal fluid shunting and pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. The aim of this study is to survey the literature and update the steps to be taken in managing a pregnant patient in whom cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) shunting has been performed. Development. The risk of valve malfunction (VMF) during pregnancy is approximately 27.5% and is mainly produced by a functional obstruction due to an increase in intraabdominal pressure during gestation. The risk of VMF and complications rises until 6 months after childbirth. The study of the functioning of the shunt and genetic counselling prior to conception are of vital importance. We discuss the steps to be taken during pregnancy, and during and after childbirth, as well as the implications of CSF shunting in a pregnant patient from a neurological, neurosurgical, obstetric and anaesthetic point of view. Although maternal progress is excellent (100% were asymptomatic 6 months after childbirth), there is also a very high percentage of miscarriages (24%) of unknown causation. Conclusions. Prospective studies are needed to explain different conflicting points in the series currently available (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Realizar una revisión bibliográfica y actualización de los pasos a seguir en el manejo de la paciente embarazada portadora de derivación de líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR).Desarrollo. El riesgo de disfunción valvular (DFV) durante el embarazo es de aproximadamente un 27,5 por ciento, debido, fundamentalmente, a una obstrucción funcional por el aumento de la presión intraabdominal durante la gestación. El riesgo de DFV y de complicaciones es alto hasta 6 meses después del parto. Son de vital importancia tanto el estudio del funcionamiento de la derivación como el consejo genético, previos a la concepción. Se discuten los pasos a s eguir durante el embarazo, durante el parto y después del mismo, así como las implicaciones que supone una derivación de LCR en una paciente embarazada desde un punto de vista neurológico, neuroquirúrgico, obstétrico y anestésico. Aunque la evolución materna es excelente (100 por ciento asintomáticas 6 meses después del parto), existe una proporción muy elevada de abortos (24 por ciento) de causa desconocida. Conclusiones. Se necesitan estudios prospectivos para dilucidar diferentes puntos en los que las series existentes están en desacuerdo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(9): 872-876, mayo 2003. graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Derivación de líquido cefalorraquídeo y embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Isla Guerrero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez López, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27620</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23185</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
