<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121483</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Journey to what is essentially invisible: pysochosocial aspects of disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Physicians may be well equipped for the biological aspects of disease, but not for its psychosocial dimensions, an issue that has been absent in family medicine. The psychosocial aspects of the disease are the factors involved in how patients react to the disease, play a role in the expression of symptoms and disease, and have implications on the lives of patients. Moreover, the biological effects (specific) and psychosocial effects (non-specific) are not simply additive but interactive. Physicians should be aware of this hidden, essentially invisible patient psychosocial morbidity, and must incorporate bio-psychosocial interventions into routine medical care to be more effective. In addition, to consider these aspects in the context of care contributes to the distinctive elements of family medicine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Turabián, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Franco, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los médicos pueden estar bien equipados para los aspectos biológicos de la enfermedad, pero no para sus dimensiones psicosociales, y este tema ha estado ausente en la medicina de familia. Los aspectos psicosociales de las enfermedades son los factores que intervienen en los modos de reaccionar del paciente frente a la enfermedad, y tienen un papel en la expresión de los síntomas y las enfermedades, y en las implicaciones que producen en la vida de las personas. Además, los efectos biológicos (específicos) y psicosociales (inespecíficos) no son simplemente aditivos, sino que interactúan. Los médicos deben ser conscientes de esta morbilidad psicosocial oculta de los pacientes &amp;#8722;lo esencial invisible&amp;#8722; y deben incorporar las intervenciones biopsicosociales a la atención médica de rutina para ser más eficaces. Además, el tener en cuenta estos aspectos dentro del marco asistencial aporta elementos propios de la medicina de familia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);40(2): 65-72, mar. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121483</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Viaje a lo esencial invisible: aspectos psicosociales de las enfermedades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33145^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
