<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117204</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-031X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alpha blockers: effects on improvement of erectile dysfunction and sexual desire in patients with benign prostatic hypertrophy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesTo assess the impact of benign prostatic hyperplasia on both quality of life and sexual function as well as the benefits of using alpha-blockers, especially silodosin.Material and methodEpidemiological observational, multicenter nationwide study in which the data collection was performed retrospectively. A total of 175 urologists, who recruited 900 patients, participated in the study. Descriptive statistics of all variables were carried out, including measures of central tendency, dispersion for quantitative variables, and absolute and relative frequencies for qualitative variables.ResultsAt the beginning of treatment, 31.6% of the patients reported a lack of desire. This proportion decreased to 26.6% at the end of the study (P &lt; .0001). When the treatment was initiated, 64.6% of patients had mild or absent erectile dysfunction. This has increased to 71% at the present time (P = .0002).ConclusionsAdequate selection of patients who may benefit from treatment with alpha-blocker, explanation of their benefits and side effects will not only improved lower urinary tract symptoms, but also erectile dysfunction scores. In this case, the most uroselective alpha-blocker silodosin has shown excellent results in both fields, both when administered as monotherapy or associated with PDE5 inhibitors. Furthermore, use of silodosin improved sexual desire parameter as opposed to use of 5 alpha reductase inhibitors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balmori, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Valorar el impacto de la HIperplasia benigna de próstata tanto en la CAlidad de vida como en la función Sexual (estudio HICAS), así como los beneficios del uso de alfabloqueantes, en especial la silodosina. Material y método. Estudio epidemiológico observacional, multicéntrico y de ámbito nacional. La recogida de datos se realizó de forma retrospectiva. En el estudio participaron un total de 175 urólogos, que incluyeron 900 pacientes. La estadística descriptiva, de todas las variables de análisis descritas, se ha realizado incluyendo medidas de tendencia central y dispersión para las variables cuantitativas, y frecuencias absolutas y relativas para las variables cualitativas. Resultados. Un 31,6% de los pacientes referían falta de deseo al inicio del tratamiento, porcentaje que disminuyó al 26,6% en el momento actual (p &lt; 0,0001). En el momento de inicio del tratamiento el 64,6% de los pacientes presentaban una disfunción eréctil leve o ausente, aumentando al 71% en el momento actual (p = 0,0002). Conclusiones. La adecuada selección de los pacientes que se pueden beneficiar del tratamiento con alfabloqueantes, y la explicación de los beneficios y efectos secundarios de los mismos redunda no solo en la mejoría de los síntomas del tracto urinario inferior, sino también en los índices de disfunción eréctil. En este caso, silodosina ha demostrado excelentes resultados en ambos campos, tanto administrado como monoterapia como asociado a IPDE5. Así mismo, el uso de silodosina ha mejorado el parámetro de deseo sexual, en contra de lo que ocurre con el uso de inhibidores de la 5-alfa-reductasa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. androl. (Ed. impr.);11(4): 123-127, oct.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117204</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alfabloqueantes: efectos en la mejora de la disfunción eréctil y el deseo sexual en pacientes con hipertrofia prostática benigna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d320^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d320^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d320^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d320^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
