<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048511</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-7973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical and serological study of Brucella in our means</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE.Knowing the seroprevalencia of brucellosis, the risk factorsand the pathologies associated to the presence of specificantibodies opposite Brucella sp in patients of the area contingenton the Consortium Hospital General from Valencia, highlightingthe proximate populations to this pathology&#146;s endemiczones.METHODS.In a year, we examined 580 patients&#146;s serum from differentservices of the Hospital General from Valencia and correspondentHealt&#146;s Area. They all presented feverish syndrome tostudy and or clinical compatible manifestations with brucellosis.The intervening spdetermined the reactivity in front of Brucellaitselftests; Bengali rose ( RB ), Seroaglutination ( SAT ) andCoombs Test. We obtained positive results in 163 sera sample(28.1 %) of 122 patients. Only we had access to clinical historyof 46, being the revised variables; Sex, age, procedence,clinical manifestations and diagnosis.RESULTS.The RB test was positive in 35 samples of 8 patients withclinic of brucellosis. Significant levels of agglutinins and blockingantibodies, met in 14 patients and to low titles, in 32. Theclinical and serological diagnosed themselves, 8 patients ofacute brucellosis, 3 of chronic brucellosis and 3 with complicationsof acute brucellosis without treatment. CONCLUSIONS.Our seroprevalence ( 28.1 % ), was higher to the describedfor another authors. We found discrepancy among tests RB,SAT and Coombs Test, the same as another authors and wethought than it will be necessary, in front of a clinical suspicionof brucellosis, accomplishing more determinations to see seroconvertionavoiding thus problems of diagnosis, treatment andcontrol of this pathology</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lamo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraile, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guaita, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Resta, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO.Conocer la seroprevalencia de brucelosis, los factores deriesgo y las patologías asociadas a la presencia de anticuerposespecíficos frente a Brucela sp en pacientes del área dependientedel Consorcio Hospital General de Valencia, destacandolos pertenecientes a poblaciones próximas a zonas endémicasde esta patología.MÉTODOS.En un año, se analizaron 580 muestras de suero de pacientesde los distintos servicios del Hospital General de Valencia yArea de Salud correspondiente. Todos presentaban síndromefebril a estudio y/o manifestaciones clínicas compatibles conbrucelosis. Se determinó la reactividad frente a Brucela spmediante las pruebas; Rosa de Bengala (RB), Seroaglutinación(SAT) y Test de Coombs. Obtuvimos resultados positivos en163 muestras (28,1 %) de 122 pacientes. Sólo tuvimos accesoa la historia clínica de 46, siendo las variables revisadas;sexo, edad, procedencia, manifestaciones clínicas y diagnóstico.RESULTADOS.La prueba Rosa de Bengala fue positiva en 35 muestras de8 pacientes con clínica de brucelosis. Títulos significativos deAglutininas y Ac bloqueantes se encontraron en 14 pacientes y a títulos bajos, en 32. Clinica y serológicamente se diagnosticaron,8 pacientes de brucelosis aguda, 3 de brucelosis crónicay 3 de complicaciones de brucelosis aguda no tratada.CONCLUSIONES.Nuestra seroprevalencia (28,1 %), fue superior a la descritapor otros autores. Encontramos discrepancia entre las pruebasRB, SAT y Test de Coombs, lo mismo que otros autores ypensamos que seria necesario, ante una sospecha clínica debrucelosis, realizar más determinaciones para ver seroconversiónevitando así problemas de diagnóstico, tratamiento y controlde esta patología</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. diagn. biol;55(1): 32-37, ene.-mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048511</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio clínico serológico de Brucelosis en nuestro medio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2034^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22402^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2034^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24874</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22321^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
