<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103153</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The pure-tone audiometry via air conduction testing in the occupational health nursing visit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Pure-Tone Audiometry via air conduction is a complementary examination which the Occupational Health Nursing carries out frequently in the visit of Occupational Health in order to watch the workers´ health. All that is according to professional risks to which the worker, object of study, is exposed. Such examination is done as often as that circumstance occurs and depending on the worker´s individual conditions. The results have as consequence the decision-making and therefore the specialist nurse must have the necessary knowledge in order to obtain valid and reproducible results. It is proposed in the present article to present the application criteria, the characteristics of the audiometry cabin and the audiometer and the minimum knowledge the health nurse must have. Furthermore, the requirements to visit the nurse, the pre-examination procedures, the test method and the description of the ascending and bracketing methods are described. Also, the audiometric record, the symbols universally used and the contents of the maintenance and calibration of the audiometric test equipment are detailed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Higueras, Juan Enciso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes González, Carlos M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Aguilera, Antonio Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Audiometría de tonos puros por conducción aérea es una exploración complementaria que la enfermería del trabajo ejecuta de manera habitual en la consulta de salud laboral para la vigilancia de la salud de los trabajadores. Todo ello, en función de los riesgos profesionales a los que esté expuesto el trabajador objeto de estudio y con una periodicidad relacionada con dicha circunstancia y las condiciones individuales del mismo. Sus resultados tienen como consecuencia la toma de decisiones y, por ello, el enfermero especialista debe manejar los conocimientos necesarios para que el resultado obtenido sea válido y reproducible. En el presente artículo se definen los criterios de aplicación, las características de la cabina y el audiómetro, los conocimientos mínimos que debe manejar el enfermero, los requisitos de la consulta y los previos a la exploración, la técnica de ensayo y la descripción de los métodos ascendente y por encuadre, el registro audiométrico y símbolos usados universalmente, y además se detallan los contenidos del mantenimiento y la calibración a los que se debe someter el equipo de exploración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;58(227): 136-147, abr.-jun. 2012. ilus, mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103153</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La audiometría de tonos puros por conducción aérea en la consulta de enfermería del trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1306^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51559</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9970^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
