<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132805</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Workshop for teaching paediatricians. Teaching to learn</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The approach of the tutoring as a mere transmission of knowledge is inadequate. The resident is an adult able to learn by him/herself and the most important work of the tutor will consist of stimulating him, guiding him and fomenting his capacity of self-learning, equipping him with tools to assess his learning needs and with resources that allow him to acquire the necessary competencies and knowledge to reach the established objectives. Actually, it consists of teaching him to learn the base of a continued formation that will have to maintain throughout all his professional activity. In addition, the tutor would have to be a professional model and a moral support for the resident. For all, it would be advisable a certain formation in educational methodology and techniques of &#147;feedback&#148;, as well as the knowledge of learning needs assessment tools, equally applicable to the daily practice of the tutor. The learning methods are diverse and include the self-learning, practice learning, problem based learning, lessons, seminaries, group works, etc. Important aspects at practical level are: to decide and to plan for the rotation contents that, respecting basic knowledge, adapt to the necessities of each resident; to maintain with him constructive and empathic communication and &#147;feedback&#148;; to drive him from the first moment in the basic aspects of the daily work; to provide him a progressive assumption of responsibilities and to look for time for teaching (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Sigler, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Cuesta Valcarce, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El enfoque de la tutorización como una mera transmisión de conocimientos resulta inadecuado. El residente es un adulto capaz de aprender por sí mismo y la labor más importante del tutor consistirá en estimularle, orientarle y fomentar su capacidad de autoaprendizaje, dotándole de herramientas para detectar sus necesidades formativas y de recursos que le permitan adquirir las competencias y los conocimientos necesarios para alcanzar los objetivos establecidos. En definitiva, se trata de enseñarle a aprender como base de una formación continuada que deberá mantener a lo largo de toda su carrera profesional. Además, el tutor debería erigirse en modelo profesional y apoyo moral para el residente. Para todo ello serían convenientes una cierta formación en metodología docente y en técnicas de feedback, así como el conocimiento de herramientas específicas de detección de necesidades formativas, por otro lado igualmente aplicables a la práctica diaria del tutor. Los métodos de enseñanza son diversos e incluyen el autoaprendizaje, el aprendizaje de campo, el aprendizaje basado en problemas, la lección magistral, los talleres, los trabajos de grupo, etc. Aspectos importantes a nivel práctico son: acordar y planificar para la rotación unos contenidos que, respetando unos conocimientos básicos, se adapten a las necesidades de cada residente; mantener con él una comunicación empática y feedback constructivo; orientarle desde el primer momento en los aspectos básicos de la consulta; proporcionarle una asunción progresiva de responsabilidades y buscar tiempo para la docencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;9(supl.10): s91-s100, abr. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Taller para pediatras docentes. Enseñando a aprender</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11666^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22941</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
