<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95088</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of laparoscopic surgery in colorectal cancer patients: quality of life, emotional state and satisfaction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to evaluate quality of life, emotional state and satisfaction perceived with the treatment and the medical team in a simple of colorrectal cancer patients in which has been carried laparoscopic surgery. The sample is constituted by 35 patients and the variables objects of study were a) sociodemographics: age and sex; b) quality of life EORTC QLQ C-30); c) anxiety and depression (HADS); d) satisfaction with the treatment and the medical team (categorical scale). The obtained results show that dimensions of global quality of life, physical function role, emotional, cognitive and social are highly satisfactory, despite many patients show fatigue, nauseous, and pain symptoms. In reference to the anxiety and depression scores in the HADS are low: mean: 4,57 and 3,38 respectively, 19% of the sample can be considered clinical case of depression and 29% of anxiety. The perceived satisfaction is elevated, more than 50% of the patients were considered very or totally satisfied. It is concluded that the colorectal cancer patients need and integral attention in order to improve the quality of life and the emotional state, because the mere step of time does not produce a recovery. A psychological intervention is necessary to optimize the welfare quality. This intervention should be applied since the start of the medical process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balibrea, José Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, Israel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balibrea, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, Mª Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruzado, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantero, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio es evaluar la calidad de vida, el estado emocional y la satisfacción percibida con el tratamiento y con el equipo médico en una muestra de pacientes con cáncer colorrectal intervenidos mediante cirugía laparoscópica. La muestra está constituida por 35 pacientes y las variables objeto de estudio fueron: a) sociodemográficas: edad y género; b) calidad de vida (EORTC QLQ C-30); c) ansiedad y depresión (HADS); d) satisfacción con el tratamiento y con el equipo médico (escala categórica). Los resultados obtenidos muestran que las dimensiones de calidad de vida global, función física, rol, emocional, cognitivas y social son altamente satisfactorias, no obstante muchos pacientes muestran síntomas de fatiga, nausea y dolor. En cuanto la ansiedad y depresión las puntuaciones en el HADS son bajas: media de 4,57 y 3,38 respectivamente. El 19% de la muestra se puede considerar caso clínico de depresión y el 29% de ansiedad. La satisfacción percibida es alta, más del 50% de los pacientes se considera muy o totalmente satisfechos. Se puede concluir que los pacientes de cáncer colorrectal necesitan una atención integral para mejorar la calidad de vida y el estado emocional, ya que el mero paso de tiempo no produce una recuperación, sino que se precisa de una intervención psicológica, que ha de aplicarse desde el inicio del tratamiento medico para optimizar la calidad asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);4(1): 121-132, jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la cirugía Laparoscópica en pacientes de Cancer colorrectal: Calidad de vida, estado emocional y satisfacción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
