<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99503</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Strategy for improving the use of antibiotics in paediatrics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Among the activities of Primary Care Pharmacist we have drug prescription profiles analysis. In October 2008, antibiotics prescription at Distrito Costa del Sol was characterized by a high variability in the selection of antibiotics by paediatricians, which resulted in an overall quality indicator worse than the regional mean value. All this together with the high frequency of paediatric emergency services and discrepancy in prescription criteria with Primary Care Services prompted the development of this work. We designed an improvement plan consisting on establishing a multidisciplinary group that generateda &#147;Guide on empirical antibiotic therapy&#148;. This guide was distributed to all paediatricians and Emergency Services along with training sessions. Quality indicators in paediatric prescription were measured from January to April 2009 and compared to same period 2008 along with a satisfaction survey. We observed an increased prescription of antibiotics of choice that may lead to an improved therapeutic efficiency and decreased bacterial resistances and adverse effects. Acceptance of the plan by professionals was high based on, among other reasons, their active participation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llamas del Castillo, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Aznar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llamas Company, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Páez, Valle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pintor Mármol, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baró Rodríguez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La selección de un antibiótico debe basarse en criterios de eficacia, seguridad, adecuación y coste. En este sentido, la intervención produjo una mejora en la selección de antibióticos en pediatría a nivel de Atención Primaria, disminuyendo la variabilidad de la prescripción. En concreto, se incrementó la descripción de antibióticos de primera elección, bajo criterios de práctica clínica (amoxicilina, ampicilina, penicilinas frente a Gram positivo y cloxacilina) frente a macrólidos y cefalosporinas de 2ª y 3ª generación. Este aumento debe traducirse en un aumento de la eficiencia terapéutica y disminución de la aparición de resistencias bacterianas y efectos adversos. La aceptación del plan de mejora entre los profesionales fue bueno debido, entre otras causas, a la participación activa de los mismos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 447-451, jul. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99503</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategia para la mejora del uso de antibióticos en pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
