<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145527</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The management of qualitative and quantitative dietary treatment for overweight and obesity: methodology and a new perspective on individualised assessment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">%WL: percentage of weight loss; % FL: percentage of fat loss. Objective: to describe the management methodology of a qualitative and quantitative dietary treatment for overweight and obesity. Method: 4,625 consultations were conducted with 616 overweight and obese patients over the age of 25 in the south-east of Spain between 2006-12. A balanced, low-calorie, qualitative and quantitative diet based on locally grown food was employed. The weight loss and maintenance dietary treatment methodology is described, as are the units of measurement considered suitable for the expression of successful weight loss; a new vision of individualised counselling and multidisciplinary treatment. Results: 80% of patients obtained a % FL &amp;#8805; 5% (22.6±11.8-11.2±7.4), and attended appointments for more than a month and a half. Conclusion: the dietary treatment methodology is described; units of measurement are recommended for use in consultations and in clinical trial publications, creating a precedent with a degree of evidence on how to determine successful weight loss; it is recommended to measure hip and waist perimeters and incorporate a study of body image; a new vision of individualised assessment and advanced multidisciplinary care is presented, independent of age, pregnancy and physical disabilities. The health care professional&#146;s position should be seen as that of the person responsible for determining which techniques might be most effective in such loss (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reig García-Galbis, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">%WL: porcentaje de pérdida de peso; %FL: porcentaje de pérdida de grasa. Objetivo: describir la metodología en la gestión del tratamiento dietético cuali-cuantitativo en el sobrepeso y la obesidad. Método: se llevaron a cabo 4.625 consultas con 616 pacientes mayores de 25 años con sobrepeso y obesidad, en el sur-este de España, durante los años 2006-12. Se utilizó una dieta equilibrada, hipocalórica, cuali-cuantitativa con alimentos de la zona. Se describió la metodología del tratamiento dietético en la pérdida y el mantenimiento. Se trató qué unidades de medida son adecuadas para la expresión del éxito en la pérdida; una nueva visión del asesoramiento individualizado y el tratamiento multidisciplinar. Resultados: el 80% de los pacientes obtienen un %FL &amp;#8805; 5% (22,6 ± 11,8 - 11,2 ± 7,4), y asistieron a la consulta más de mes y medio. Conclusión: se presenta un esquema de la metodología del tratamiento dietético; se han recomendado las unidades de medidas a utilizar en consulta y en la publicación de ensayos clínicos, creando un precedente con grado de evidencia de cómo determinar la pérdida exitosa; se recomienda medir los perímetros de cadera y cintura, e incorporar el estudio de la imagen corporal; se presenta una nueva visión del asesoramiento individualizado y una atención multidisciplinar avanzada, independiente de la edad, el estado de gestación y las minusvalías físicas. La postura del sanitario debe de ser considerada como el gestor encargado de determinar qué técnicas podrían ser más efectivas en dicha pérdida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(5): 2019-2029, nov. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145527</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión del tratamiento dietético cuali-cuantitativo en el sobrepeso y la obesidad: metodología y una nueva perspectiva de asesoramiento individualizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7381</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32818^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
