<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122195</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Highlights from the 36th annual San Antonio Breast Cancer Symposium</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Among the many papers were presented at the 36th San Antonio Breast Cancer Symposium in 2013; the most important &amp;#8722;mainly oral presentations&amp;#8722;are summarized below. Notable for their clinical applicability were two studies on the management of the primary tumor in metastatic breast cancer and the PRIME II trial evaluating the impact of omitting adjuvant radiotherapy in elderly patients. The expected data from the BETH trial, evaluating the benefit of adding bevacizumab in the adjuvant treatment of HER2-positive tumors, were also reported, and interesting information was presented on the efficacy of carboplatin in triple-negative breast cancer. From the point of view of tumor biology, the organizers wanted to provide a platform for the potential role of immunity in the prognosis of breast cancer, and mutations in the estrogen receptor gene, which are emerging as a new mechanism of acquisition of hormone resistance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavilá, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillem, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">De entre los muchos trabajos presentados en la edición del año 2013 del San Antonio Breast Cancer Symposium, se resumen a continuación los más relevantes, que principalmente son aquellos que fueron motivo de presentación oral. Este año destacan, por su aplicabilidad clínica, 2 estudios sobre el manejo del tumor primario en cáncer de mama metastásico, y el estudio PRIME II que evalúa el impacto de omitir la radioterapia adyuvante en pacientes ancianas. También se comunicaron los esperados datos del ensayo BETH, que estudia el beneficio de añadir bevacizumab en la adyuvancia de tumores HER2-positivo, y se presentaron interesantes datos de la eficacia de carboplatino en cáncer de mama triple negativo. Desde el punto de vista de la biología tumoral, los organizadores quisieron dar voz al papel que podría desempeñar la inmunidad en el pronóstico del cáncer de mama, y a las mutaciones en el gen del receptor estrogénico, que emergen como un nuevo mecanismo de adquisición de hormonorresistencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);27(2): 87-93, abr.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">36th annual San Antonio Breast Cancer Symposium. Resumen de lo más destacado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54678^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9572^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
