<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103434</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional assessment for cancer patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Weight loss and malnutrition is common in cancer patients, both origin of complications during the course of the disease. Although weight loss is predominantly due to loss of fat mass, the morbidity risk is given by the decrease in muscle mass. The causes of malnutrition are numerous, but the tumor cachexia and anorexia are the principals. The assessment of nutritional status is essential for a diagnosis of nutritional compromise and for the multidisciplinary management required. Subjective Global Assessment combines medical history, physical examination to classify patients as well nourished, moderately or severely malnourished. Subjective global assessment generated by the patient also includes nutritional symptoms and weight loss. Both instruments can serve as indicators of survival. The objective assessment, a significant weight loss (&gt; 10%) for 6 months is considered an indicator of nutritional deficiency. BMI on the other hand has not proven to be a good indicator of malnutrition. Albumin and prealbumin, although widely used, should be used with caution. These are acute phase proteins, a situation that would alter specificity for diagnosis of visceral protein malnutrition. The bioelectrical impedance, in addition to determine body composition, has been linked to survival time and mortality. Although there are various methods, there is no "Gold Standard". The nutritional assessment instruments should be chosen according to the patient´s condition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Basfi-fer, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela-Landaeta, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La pérdida de peso y la desnutrición es frecuente en pacientes oncológicos, siendo ambas origen de complicaciones durante el transcurso de la enfermedad. Aunque la reducción de peso se debe predominantemente a la pérdida de masa grasa, el riesgo morbimortalidad está dado por la disminución de masa muscular. Las causas de desnutrición son múltiples, sin embargo la caquexia tumoral y la anorexia son las principales. La evaluación del estado nutricional es fundamental para un diagnóstico del compromiso nutricional y para el manejo multidisciplinario que se requiere. La evaluación global subjetiva combina antecedentes clínicos con el examen físico para catalogar a los pacientes como bien nutridos, moderada o severamente desnutridos. La evaluación global subjetiva generada por el paciente incluye además síntomas nutricionales y pérdida de peso. Ambos instrumentos pueden servir como indicadores de sobrevida. En la evaluación objetiva, una baja de peso significativa (&gt; 10%) durante 6 meses se considera indicador de déficit nutricional. El IMC por su parte no ha demostrado ser buen indicador de desnutrición. La albúmina y la prealbúmina, aunque de uso corriente, deben ser empleadas con precaución. Éstas son proteínas de fase aguda, situación que alteraría especificidad para el diagnóstico de desnutrición proteica visceral. La bioimpedanciometria, además de determinar composición corporal, se ha relacionado con tiempo de supervivencia y mortalidad. Aunque hay diversos métodos, no existe un "Gold Estándar". Los instrumentos para la evaluación nutricional deben ser escogidos según la condición del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(2): 516-523, mar.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103434</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación nutricional del paciente con cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
