<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129018</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fungal bloodstream infections in tertiary care hospitals in Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Fungal infections have increased in critical care patients, causing high morbidity and mortality. Aims. Describe the frequency and responsible fungal species involved in bloodstream fungal infection from 2001 to 2007 in tertiary care level hospitals belonging to a surveillance network in Colombian cities. Methods. Data were collected from a microbiology surveillance network based on 27 hospital laboratories in five Colombian cities. Data were entered into a Whonet® version 5.4 database. Fungemia data were analyzed according to location (Intensive care unit -ICU- vs. non-ICU services). Frequency over time was also described. Results. Fungal infections corresponded to 4.1% of all bloodstream infections. Candidemia represented 3.7% and 5.2% of all isolates in non-ICU and ICU services, respectively. Over 99% of the isolates were yeasts, and Candida albicans was the most frequently isolated organism in and out of the ICU, showing a decreasing trend in the last few years. In the adult ICU and non-ICU services, the second organism most frequently isolated was C. tropicalis, while C. parapsilopsis was the most frequent in the pediatric and neonatal ICU, also showing an overall decreasing trend. Cryptococcus neoformans was the fourth mycotic organism most frequently identified. Conclusions. In Colombia, epidemiology of fungal infections seems to be changing. C. albicans is the principal agent causing bloodstream fungal infection, but an increase of non-albicans species has been observed as well as high frequency of C. neoformans(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reyes, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal, Aura Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, Jorge Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buitrago, Giancarlo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Las infecciones micóticas han aumentado en los pacientes críticos y son responsables de una alta morbilidad y mortalidad. Objetivos. Describir la frecuencia de presentación y las especies de hongos responsables de las infecciones del torrente sanguíneo en una red de vigilancia de hospitales de tercer nivel en varias ciudades de Colombia en el periodo entre 2001 y 2007. Métodos. Los datos fueron obtenidos a partir de los laboratorios de microbiología de 27 hospitales de 5 ciudades colombianas. Estos datos fueron incorporados a una base creada en Whonet® versión 5.4 de la OMS. Se analizaron los datos de fungemias de acuerdo a la localización (servicios de cuidado intensivo -UCI- y servicios no-UCI) y se describe la tendencia en el tiempo. Resultados. En 27 hospitales de la red las fungemias correspondieron al 4,1% de los hemocultivos positivos, y las candidemias representaron el 3,7 y el 5,2% de todos los aislamientos en los servicios no-UCI y UCI, respectivamente. Las levaduras fueron los agentes etiológicos responsables en más del 99% de los casos, y Candida albicans fue el microorganismo más identificado tanto en la UCI como fuera de ella, con una menor frecuencia en los últimos años del estudio. En UCI de adultos y en los servicios no-UCI el segundo microorganismo más frecuente fue Candida tropicalis, mientras que en la UCI pediátrica y la neonatal fue Candida parapsilopsis. Cryptococcus neoformans fue el cuarto hongo más frecuentemente identificado. Conclusiones. En Colombia la epidemiología de las infecciones micóticas parece estar cambiando. C. albicans es el principal agente causal de fungemias pero se observa un incremento en el resto de especies del género y una alta frecuencia de C. neoformans(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;28(2): 74-78, abr.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129018</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones micóticas del torrente sanguíneo en hospitales de tercer nivel en Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29181^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3472^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36631^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29181^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2208^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3472^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3472^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
