<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131828</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Live events quality of life and social support prior to acute cerebral vascular disease, as predictive factors of the quality of life and functional state following stroke</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The repercussion of stroke on quality of life has been evaluated but not the possible relation between the quality of life before and months after an acute stroke. Objective. To study the possible relation between quality of life, social support, stressful life events prior to the stroke and quality of life, social support and functional state months after. Patients and methods. A prospective study was made of 34 patients (71.7 ± 8 years; 19 (56%) men; 15 (44%) women with stroke, by means of two evaluations: personal interview within the first 36 hours (quality of life &#150;Nothingham health profile (NHP)&#150;, perception of social support and stressful life events &#150;Holmes and Rake inventory&#150;) and an interview over the phone 16.5 ± 5.3 months after the stroke (NHP, perception of social support and functional state &#150;Rankin scale&#150;). Results. Following the stroke there was deterioration in perception of social support (19.8 ± 3 vs 12.5 ± 8; p= 0.000) and in the degree of social isolation of the NHP (9.4 ± 20 vs 21.1 ± 30; p= 0.03). The only relation found was between the following variables: pain at the first evaluation and pain (r= 0.45; p= 0.007) at the second evaluation; mobility at the first evaluation and emotional state (r= 0.39; p= 0.029) and social support (r= 0.37; p= 0.027) at the second evaluation; sleepiness at the first evaluation and energy (r= 0.55; p= 0.0006), pain (r= 0.39; p= 0.022), emotional state (r= 0.35; p= 0.038), mobility (r= 0.34, p= 0.048) and sleepiness (r= 0.51; p= 0.001) at the second evaluation. Conclusion. Our results indicate that there is little relationship between the previous state and that following stroke, and that the deterioration in perception of support and social isolation is due to the stroke itself (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valiente ibiza, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz de Salazar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peris Martí, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala Corbí, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se ha valorado la repercusión del ictus en la calidad de vida pero no la posible relación entre la calidad de vida previa y la que tienen los pacientes meses después del episodio agudo. Objetivo. Estudiar la posible relación entre calidad de vida, apoyo social y acontecimientos vitales estresantes previos al ictus y calidad de vida, apoyo social y situación funcional meses después del mismo. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio prospectivo de 34 pacientes (71,7 ± 8 años; 19 (56%) varones; 15 (44%) mujeres) con ictus mediante dos valoraciones: entrevista personal en las primeras 36 horas (calidad de vida &#150;perfil de salud de Nottingham (PSN)&#150;, percepción de apoyo social y acontecimientos vitales estresantes &#150;inventario de Holmes y Rake&#150;) y entrevista telefónica 16,5 ± 5,3 meses después del ictus (PSN, percepción de apoyo social y situación funcional &#150;escala de Rankin&#150;). Resultados. Después del ictus se produce un deterioro en la percepción del apoyo social (19,8 ± 3 frente a 12,5 ± 8; p= 0,000) y en la dimensión de aislamiento social del PSN (9,4 ± 20 frente a 21,1 ± 30; p= 0,03). Sólo se encontró relación entre las siguientes variables: dolor en la primera evaluación y dolor (r= 0,45; p= 0,007) en la segunda evaluación; movilidad en la primera evaluación y estado emocional (r= 0,39; p= 0,029) y apoyo social (r= 0,37; p= 0,027) en la segunda evaluación; sueño en la primera evaluación y energía (r= 0,55; p= 0,0006), dolor (r= 0,39; p= 0,022), estado emocional (r= 0,35; p= 0,038), movilidad (r= 0,34; p= 0,048) y sueño (r= 0,51; p= 0,001) en la segunda evaluación. Conclusión. Nuestros resultados sugieren que la relación existente entre la situación previa y la posterior al ictus es escasa, y que el deterioro en la percepción del apoyo y el aislamiento social se deben al ictus en sí mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;30(8): 707-711, abr. 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131828</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acontecimientos vitales, calidad de vida y apoyo social previos a la enfermedad vascular cerebral aguda, como factores predictores de la calidad de vida y situación funcional posteriores al ictus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13316^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
