<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135809</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical training in Spain: Results of a national survey</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of the study is to try and find out the state of surgical training in Spain and to determine whether it meets the objectives of the Program. Material and methods: The results of two surveys carried out on Residents and General Surgery Tutors by the Spanish Surgeons Association, based on the conclusions of the XXVII Congreso Nacional de Cirugía. The questions formulated referred to general aspects of the Service and specific ones related to access, teaching activity, surgery, research and personal perspectives. The responses were defined, adjusted and categorised as quantitative and qualitative variables. The statistics program G Stat 2.0 was used for processing and the descriptive presentation of the results. Results: The surveys were sent to 626 Residents and 142 Tutors, with a response rate of 19% and 29%,  respectively. First year residents predominated (32%) compared to later years, with an R-5 response index of 7.2%. A total of 91% knew the speciality Program well, and 76% were satisfied with the training received. Conclusions: The results obtained as regards surgical activity agree with those established in the Program, both in the number of procedures and in their progression throughout the Residency, although it is not possible to ensure its uniformity. The functions and accreditation of the Tutors which are one of the main foundations of the training process are pending specific regulations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jover Navalón, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landa García, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguelena Bobadilla, José Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Cenarruzabeitia, Iñigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales García, Dieter</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Docobo Durantez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobo Martínez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Jacinto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Sánchez, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iturbe Belmonte, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo del estudio intenta realizar una aproximación al estado de la formación quirúrgica en España y analizar su adecuación a los objetivos del programa. Material y métodos: Se presentan y se analizan los resultados de dos encuestas realizadas por la Asociación Española de Cirujanos a los residentes y a los tutores de Cirugía General basadas en las conclusiones del XXVII Congreso Nacional de Cirugía. Las cuestiones formuladas hacían referencia a aspectos generales del servicio y particulares en relación con el acceso, la actividad docente, la actividad quirúrgica, la actividad investigadora y las perspectivas personales. Las respuestas fueron definidas, adaptadas y categorizadas como variables cuantitativas y cualitativas. Se utilizó un programa estadístico G Stat 2.0 para el procesamiento y la presentación descriptiva de los resultados. Resultados: El número de residentes y tutores a quienes se enviaron las encuestas fue de 626 y 142. Fueron respondidas el 19% de las encuestas de residentes y el 29% de las encuestas de tutores. Según el año de residencia, predominaron las de residentes de primer año (32%) frente a los de años ulteriores, siendo el índice de respuesta de los R5 del 7,2%. El 91% conocía bien el programa de la especialidad y el 76% estaba satisfecho con la formación recibida. Conclusiones: Los resultados obtenidos en cuanto a actividad quirúrgica concuerdan con los previstos en el programa tanto en el número de procedimientos como en su progresión a lo largo de la residencia, aunque no es posible asegurar su uniformidad. Las funciones y la acreditación de los tutores que constituyen uno de los pilares fundamentales del proceso formativo están pendientes de regulación específica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);88(2): 110-117, ago. 2010. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135809</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formación quirúrgica en España: resultados de una encuesta nacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
