<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038480</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of refractive prognosis factors in myopic Lasik</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: Our objective was to evaluate myopic Lasik refractive results according to preoperative refraction findings.Methods: In 200 eyes, classified into 4 groups according to preoperative sphere and cylinder findings, different postoperative refractive parameters were compared: predictability, visual acuity (VA), security index (SI) and efficacy index (EI).Results: Grouped by sphere: spherical correction was better than cylindrical correction. Highest negative spheres resulted in undercorrection (p1.0 was similar to EI (±0.9), for preoperative sphere and cylinder groups.Best corrected visual acuity (BCVA) of 20/25 by sphere was 100% vs. 60% and of 20/30 by cylinder was 100% vs. 83%, for lower and higher myopic groups respectively.Conclusions: Analysis by grouping preoperative refractive errors is helpful for establishing its influence and improving LASIK prognosis and treatment. This procedure is effective and safe for all groups, and its inaccuracy is due more to astigmatism than to spherical error. As astigmatism increases, less spherical and higher cylindrical ablation should be performed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mura, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Donoso, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Nuestro objetivo es evaluar los resultados refractivos de LASIK miópico, según refracción preoperatoria.Método: En 200 ojos, agrupados en 4 grupos por esfera y cilindro preoperatorio, se compraró distintos parámetros refractivos postoperatorios: predictibilidad, agudeza visual (AV) e índices de seguridad (IS) y eficacia (IE).Resultados: Ordenados por esfera: La esfera se corrige mejor que el cilindro, subcorrigiéndose las más miopes (p1,0 fue similar al IE (±0,9), por esfera y cilindro preoperatorio.La predictibilidad de AV con corrección 20/25 fue de 100% a 60% por esfera, y para 20/30 por cilindro de 100% a 83%, en los grupos menos y más miopes respectivamente.Conclusiones: El análisis por grupos de error refractivo preoperatorio permite determinar su influencia para mejorar el pronóstico y tratamiento Lasik. Es muy seguro y eficaz para todos los grupos, y su inexactitud depende fundamentalmente del astigmatismo y en menor grado de la esfera preoperatoria. A mayor astigmatismo se debe disminuir la ablación esférica y aumentar la cilíndrica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;80(3): 179-186, mar. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de factores pronósticos refractivos en Lasik miópico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9408^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12451^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9408^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
