<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056197</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper is part of a large study on occupational    hearing loss linked to multi-exposure environments,    that is to say, due to both physical and    chemical agents. The effect of cigarette consumption    and noise exposure is evaluated, although it is    quite clear that part of the study population is also    under the influence of metal smoke cutting fluids    and noise exposure out of their workplace too. The    study is based on this population under multiple    exposures conditions. It arises from a methodology    based on "statistical follow up techniques", in    our case follow-up-resistance techniques, based    on the obtaining and contrast of logistics distributions.    Smoking among workers exposed to industrial    noise, seems to encourage the probability of    acquisition of Acute Acoustic Trauma (AAT) and    Initial Acoustic Trauma (IAT). The worst results    are of those smoking over 20 cigarettes a day and    undergoing 20 years or more of occupational    exposure</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Terrer, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Gracia, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conte Solano, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Aranda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Calvo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo forma parte de un amplio    estudio sobre pérdida auditiva laboral en condiciones    de multiexposición, es decir, por influencia    conjunta de agentes físicos y químicos. Se analiza    la influencia del consumo de tabaco y exposición    a ruido, si bien es cierto que parte de la población    analizada también está sometida a la influencia de    otros humos y de otros ruidos extralaborales. Se    analiza esta población en exposición múltiple, partiendo    de una metodología basada en las "técnicas    de seguimiento estadístico", en nuestro caso de    seguimiento-resistencia, basadas en la obtención y    contraste de las distribuciones logísticas.    En trabajadores expuestos a ruido industrial, el    hábito de fumar parece potenciar la probabilidad    de adquisición de las afecciones TAI y TAA.    Teniendo los peores resultados los fumadores de    mas de 20 cigarrillos diarios y 20 años o mas de    exposición laboral</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;52(205): 33-40, dic. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056197</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adquisición de un trauma acústico por multiexposición a tabaco y ruido laboral en la industria del metal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1313^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9809^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
