<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80167</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Necrotizing periodontal disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Necrotizing periodontal disease is an infection characterized by gingival necrosis, pain and gingival bleeding. Spirochetes are pathogens usually involvedin acute necrotizing gingivitis. Predisposing factors are tobacco smoking, alcohol abuse, poor diet, inmunosupression, specially in HIV infectedpatients, emotional stress and preexisting gingivitis. We present a 38-year-old man with gingival and upper lip lesiones, successfully treated withmetronidazole and spiramycin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pitarch Archelós, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Motilla, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pitarch Bort, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad periodontal necrosante es una infección con necrosis de las papilas interdentarias, dolor y hemorragia gingival. Las espiroquetas sonlos patógenos implicados en la gingivitis necrosante aguda. Los factores predisponentes son el consumo de tabaco y alcohol, el déficit alimentario, lainmunosupresión, especialmente en pacientes infectados por VIH, el estrés emocional y la gingivitis preexistente. Presentamos el caso de un hombrede 38 años con lesiones en encías y labio superior, tratado con éxito con metronidazol y espiramicina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;37(2): 108-110, mar.-abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80167</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad periodontal necrosante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24883^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
