<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87984</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients&#146; perception on attention received from Health Centres non-sanitary staff</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. To know patients&#146; perceptions about relational aspects and technical procedures when they are attended by the administrative staff in Health Centres. To assess the utility of two ways for measuring satisfaction. Material and methods. Cross-sectional study carried out in people attending the administrative sections of Health Centres for diverse reasons. Just after the interaction with the administrative they were interviewed using two different questions for assessing their opinions and satisfaction with communicational and technical aspects related with their demands. Descriptive analysis. Significant differences among mean was explored by X2 test. Open-ended questions were grouped in categories in a process involving three researchers independently. Results. Over than 90% (360) of the attendees declared to be satisfied or very satisfied with the service received from the staff personal. Nevertheless, among 18-36% gave suggestions for improving the service after their consultation. Independently the domain explored, people suggested the communicational, personal capability, quality and quantity of explanations and waiting time as the main aspects to be improved. Conclusions. Surveys with open-ended questions are more useful to assess the quality of the attention the citizens receive from no-sanitary staff in Health Centres. These type of questions are also more useful for detecting problems and planning new interventions. Relational and informative issues seem to be the most prioritary areas to improve in this section of Health Centres(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Torres, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alba Dios, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios Blasco, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Neubauer, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Moral, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérula de Torres, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Conocer la percepción que tienen los usuarios sobre algunos aspectos interpersonales y técnicos relacionados con la atención que reciben del personal de atención al ciudadano cuando acuden a los centros de atención primaria. Valorar la posible utilidad de dos modos de medición de la satisfacción. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional descriptivo realizado con usuarios que utilizaron los servicios de atención al ciudadano de los centros de salud. Tras consultar con este personal, los usuarios fueron entrevistados personalmente utilizando dos tipos de preguntas que evaluaron sus opiniones y satisfacción con diferentes aspectos comunicacionales y de tipo técnico relacionados con la demanda realizada. Las preguntas abiertas fueron agrupadas en categorías en un proceso que involucró a tres investigadores de manera independiente. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo e inferencial (test de la X2, p&lt;0,05). Resultados. Más de un 90% (360) de los usuarios encuestados declararon estar satisfechos o muy satisfechos con la atención recibida en atención al ciudadano; sin embargo, entre el 18 y el 36% hicieron sugerencias para mejorar esta atención tras su consulta. Independientemente del dominio explorado, destacaron las sugerencias referidas a la relación/comunicación, capacitación del personal para resolver los problemas, calidad y cantidad de las explicaciones y tiempo de espera. Conclusiones. Las encuestas que incorporan preguntas abiertas parecen más útiles para valorar la calidad de la atención recibida de los administrativos de los centros de salud, detectar problemas en esta atención y planificar nuevas intervenciones de mejora. Los aspectos relacionales e informativos representan un área de mejora prioritaria en este ámbito(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;26(2): 97-103, mar.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87984</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de los pacientes sobre la atención recibida por el personal no sanitario en los centros de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
