<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146893</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">SEMERGEN positioning for the treatment of alcohol disorders in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present manuscript is based on the recommendations of a panel of health care professionals, including several experts in primary health care, psychiatry and addictions. The participants are recognized specialists in the treatment of alcohol use disorder. The panel met in Barcelona on 2015 April 22 with the aims of evaluating the current management of alcohol use disorder in primary health care and developing a strategy to address this problem, basing on the evidence and the recommendations of the scientific societies and national and international organizations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bobes, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gual, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casquero, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbesú, José Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo se basa en las recomendaciones de un grupo de profesionales sanitarios, incluidos expertos en la atención primaria, psiquiatría y adicciones. Los participantes son reconocidos especialistas en el tratamiento del trastorno por consumo de alcohol. El grupo se reunió en Barcelona el 22 de abril de 2015 para evaluar la situación actual en el manejo del trastorno por consumo de alcohol en atención primaria y desarrollar una estrategia para abordar este problema, basándose en la evidencia y las recomendaciones de sociedades científicas y organismos nacionales e internacionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);41(supl.2): 1-9, dic. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146893</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posicionamiento de SEMERGEN para el abordaje de los trastornos por consumo de alcohol en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34378^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33536^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
