<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-35792</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterisation of the influence exerted by the visual factor in patients with balance disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Visual information provides data about the position and movement of the head with respect to objects and serves as a source of reference for the proper perception of verticality. It also plays a specific role in postural control by modifying the efficiency of the vestibular and proprioceptive responses. Aims. Our aim was to determine how visual information interacts with the symptoms of patients with vertigo, dizziness or instability and to find out the degree of disability it produces. Patients and methods. A study was conducted in 200 patients who had visited because of dizziness, vertigo, instability or loss of balance. We analysed the aspects related to the clinical symptoms of the patients. First, we examined the influence visual stimuli have on the symptoms of vestibular disease itself and their repercussions on the situation between crises. Second, the degree of disability was evaluated on the specific DHI (Dizziness Handicap Inventory) questionnaire. Results. As regards the influence exerted by visual stimulation on the main symptoms, 77.5% reported that it had no effect and 21% said that it made them worse. With regard to the influence of visual stimulation during the intercritical period, it was of no relevance in 53.5% of patients, 26.5% were unaffected, it had an exacerbating effect in 4% and in 7.5% it induced it. Different disorders were observed depending on the type of disease suffered by the patient, and disability was greater according to the influence exerted by the visual factor. Conclusions. Postural adjustments induced by visual stimuli are capable of triggering instability with serious consequences</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La información visual aporta datos acerca de la posición y el movimiento de la cabeza con respecto a los objetos y es fuente de referencia para la adecuada percepción de la verticalidad. Además, desempeña un papel específico en el control postural modificando la eficiencia de las respuestas vestibulares y propioceptivas. Objetivo. Determinar en pacientes con vértigo, mareo o inestabilidad cómo interactúa la información visual sobre su sintomatología y conocer el grado de discapacidad que produce. Pacientes y métodos. Se realizó el estudio de 200 pacientes vistos por mareo, vértigo, inestabilidad o desequilibrio. Analizamos los aspectos relacionados con la clínica de los pacientes. En primer lugar, la influencia que el estímulo visual tiene en los síntomas propios de la enfermedad vestibular y su repercusión en la situación entre crisis. En segundo lugar, el grado de discapacidad valorado por el cuestionario específico DHI (del inglés dizziness handicap inventory). Resultados. Respecto a la influencia que la estimulación visual tiene sobre la sintomatología principal, el 77,5 por ciento refería que no le afectaba, y el 21 por ciento, que le agravaba; en cuanto a la influencia de la estimulación visual durante el período intercrítico, en el 53,5 por ciento de los pacientes no era relevante, en el 26,5 por ciento no la afectaba, en el 4 por ciento la agravaba y en el 7,5 por ciento la inducía. Se observó la existencia de una afectación diferente según el tipo de enfermedad que sufría el paciente, y una mayor discapacidad según la influencia del factor visual. Conclusiones. Los ajustes posturales inducidos por el estímulo visual son capaces de provocar una desestabilización con serias consecuencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(6): 513-516, sept. 2004. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de la influencia del factor visual en los pacientes con alteraciones del equilibrio</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rama López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-35792</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3482</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5235</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4307</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4936</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24913</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15128</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33671</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
