<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163065</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are unwanted mental intrusions a transdiagnostic variable?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Unwanted mental intrusions (UMI) constitute the normal variants of obsessions in Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (OCD), preoccupations about defects in Body Dysmorphic Disorder (BDD), images about illness in Hypochondriasis (HYP), and thoughts about eating in Eating Disorders (EDs). We sought to investigate the relationships between frequency and discomfort associated with the experience of the four UMI contents, adopting a within-subject perspective. Method: A group of 438 university students and community participants (Mage = 29.84, SD = 11.41; 70.54% women), completed the Questionnaire of Unpleasant Intrusive Thoughts to assess the frequency and discomfort of four UMI contents related to OCD, BDD, HYP and EDs. Results: Just over 76% of participants reported having experienced the four sets of intrusions. The ED-related were the most frequent but the least disturbing, whereas HYP intrusions were the least frequent but the most disturbing. The four UMI were significantly related to each other, both in frequency and discomfort. Women experienced OCD, BDD, and ED-related intrusions more frequently than men. Age was negatively associated with the frequency and distress of the four UMIs. Conclusions: UMIs might be a transdiagnostic variable across different disorders such as OCD, BDD, EDs, and Hypochondriasis, and they might contribute to explaining the phenomenological similarities among them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Belloch Fuster, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual-Vera, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roncero Sanchís, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: las intrusiones mentales (IM) constituyen la variante normativa de las obsesiones en el Trastorno Obsesivo-Compulsivo (TOC), las preocupaciones sobre defectos en el Trastorno Dismórfico Corporal (TDC), las imágenes sobre enfermedad en Hipocondría (TH), y pensamientos sobre alimentación en los Trastornos Alimentarios (TA). Nuestro objetivo es explorar, a nivel intra-sujeto, las relaciones entre la frecuencia y la molestia asociadas a las cuatro modalidades de IM. Método: 438 participantes (Medad = 29.84, DT = 11.41; 70,54% mujeres) completaron el Inventario de Pensamientos Intrusos Desagradables (INPIDES), que evalúa la presencia y molestia de IM con contenidos obsesivos, dismórficos, hipocondríacos y alimentarios. Resultados: más del 76% de los participantes experimentaron las cuatro modalidades de IM. Las alimentarias fueron las más frecuentes pero las menos molestas, mientras que las hipocondríacas fueron las menos frecuentes pero las más molestas. La frecuencia y malestar de las cuatro IM correlacionaron entre sí. Las mujeres experimentaron las IM obsesivas, dismórficas y alimentarias más que los hombres. La edad se asoció negativamente con la frecuencia y el malestar de las IM. Conclusión: las IM pueden ser una variable transdiagnóstica a trastornos como el TOC, el TDC, los TA y la Hipocondría, y ello puede contribuir a explicar las similitudes fenomenológicas entre estos trastornos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);29(2): 166-171, mayo 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163065</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Son las intrusiones mentales no deseadas una variable transdiagnóstica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53747^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7175^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14230</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
