<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128123</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the novelties presented at the 29th Congress of the European Committee for Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis (ECTRIMS) (III)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The most relevant data presented at the 29th Congress of the European Committee for Treatment and Research in Multiple Sclerosis (ECTRIMS), held in October 2013 in Denmark, were summarised at the sixth edition of the Post- ECTRIMS Expert Meeting held in Madrid in October 2013, resulting in this review, which is being published in three parts. This third part of the Post-ECTRIMS review discusses the effects of immunomodulatory therapy on the natural history of multiple sclerosis, with special attention to the assessment of long-term effects and the use of historical controls as an alternative to randomised trials compared with placebo. This article contains possible future therapeutic strategies to be tested in experimental models and discusses clinical trials that are underway and future treatments. It also summarises the results of recent studies of disease-modifying treatments and developments in symptom management. Briefly, on the horizon are many drugs with different mechanisms of action, although new strategies and treatment algorithms are needed, as are new biomarkers and assessment measures of secondary progression and long-term records to assess safety. As for the symptomatic treatment of the disease, the proposal is a personalised treatment plan and a multidisciplinary approach to improve the quality of life of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Cermeño, José C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meca Lallana, José E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García, Delicias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Antigüedad, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brieva, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Pinel, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comabella, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández,  Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova Estruch, Bonaventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Nacarino, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramió Torrentà, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olascoaga, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Merino, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendibe Bilbao, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calles Hernández, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo González, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnal García, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oreja Guevara, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los datos más relevantes presentados en la XXIX edición del Congreso del Comité Europeo para el Tratamiento e Investigación en Esclerosis Múltiple (ECTRIMS), celebrado en octubre de 2013 en Dinamarca, se han resumido en la sexta edición de la Reunión de Expertos Post-ECTRIMS celebrada en Madrid en octubre de 2013, fruto de la cual nace esta revisión, que se publica en tres partes. Esta tercera parte de la revisión Post-ECTRIMS aborda los efectos del tratamiento inmunomodulador en la historia natural de la esclerosis múltiple, con especial atención a la valoración del efecto a largo plazo y al uso de controles históricos como alternativa a los estudios aleatorizados comparados con placebo. Este artículo recoge posibles estrategias terapéuticas futuras que pasan por los modelos experimentales, y expone los ensayos clínicos en marcha y futuros tratamientos. Asimismo, resume los resultados de los últimos estudios de los tratamientos modificadores de la enfermedad y las novedades en el manejo sintomático. Brevemente, en el horizonte, hay muchos fármacos con diferentes mecanismos de acción, aunque son necesarias nuevas estrategias y algoritmos terapéuticos, biomarcadores y nuevas medidas de evaluación de la progresión secundaria, y registros a largo plazo para evaluar la seguridad. En cuanto al tratamiento sintomático de la enfermedad, se apuesta por un plan personalizado de tratamiento y una aproximación multidisciplinar, de cara a mejorar la calidad de vida de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;59(8): 371-379, oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128123</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de las novedades presentadas en el XXIX Congreso del Comité Europeo para el Tratamiento e Investigación en Esclerosis Múltiple (ECTRIMS) (III)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53686^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53692^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
