<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108183</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic bariatric surgery program in the University Clinic of Navarre &#150; Hospital Complex of Navarre: results after 1-year follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The prevalence of obesity in Spain in recent years has shown an alarming increase. The repeated failure of balanced food patterns, physical activity, nutritional education and pharmacotherapy have led to the need touse bariatric surgery both to maintain long-term weight loss, and for the resolution of associated comorbidities. This article analyzes the initial results of the implementation of the laparoscopic bariatric surgery program in Navarre, obtained in a group of obese patients with surgical indication and operated on by means of the laparoscopic gastric bypass. Methods. From January 2010 until December 2011, 47 gastric bypasses were performed laparoscopic ally in the University Clinic of Navarre, all of them from the autonomous community of Navarre and previously and subsequently evaluated in the Hospital Complex of Navarre. The first 19cases amongst them were selected for this work, as they presented at least one year of follow-up. Results. The percentage of excess weight lost was 65.47%, with a 31.68% reduction of total weight. The figures for glucose, uric acid, arterial tension and lipid metabolism one year after the intervention presented a very significant progressive fall. No significant medical or surgical complications were presented. Conclusions. The laparoscopic gastric bypass is an efficient technique for the long-term treatment of morbid obesity, with a scant number of complications, excellent weight loss and curing or improvement of the associated comorbidities in these patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valentí Azcárate, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zugasti Murillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La prevalencia de obesidad en España en los últimos años muestra un incremento alarmante. El fracaso repetido de las pautas de alimentación equilibrada, actividad física, educación nutricional y farmacoterapia han conducido a la necesidad de utilizar la cirugía bariátrica tanto para el mantenimiento de la pérdida ponderal a largo plazo, como para la resolución de las comorbilidades asociadas. En el presente trabajo se pretende analizar los resultados iniciales de la puesta en marcha del programa de cirugía bariátrica laparoscópica en Navarra obtenidos en un grupo de pacientes obesos con indicación quirúrgica e intervenidos mediante el bypass gástrico laparoscópico (BPGYR). Material y métodos. Desde enero de 2010 hasta diciembrede 2011 se realizaron 47 BPGYR por vía laparoscópica en la Clínica Universidad de Navarra procedentes todos ellos de la Comunidad Foral de Navarra y evaluados previa y posteriormente en el Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra. De ellos, se han seleccionado para este trabajo los primeros 19 casos por presentar al menos un año de seguimiento. Resultados. El porcentaje de exceso de IMC perdido (PEIMCP) fue del 65,47%, con una disminución del porcentaje de peso total de 31,68%. Las cifras de glucosa, ácido úrico, tensión arterial y metabolismo lipídico al año de la intervención presentaron un descenso progresivo muy significativo, No se presentaron complicaciones importantes médicas ni quirúrgicas. Conclusiones. El bypass gástrico por laparoscopia es una técnica eficaz para el tratamiento a largo plazo de la obesidad mórbida, con escaso número de complicaciones, excelente pérdida de peso y curación o mejora de las comorbilidades asociadas en estos pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;35(3): 433-444, sept.-dic. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108183</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa de cirugía bariátrica laparoscópica en la Clínica Universidad de Navarra-Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra: resultados a un año</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23640^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28585</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
