<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042699</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vestibular drop attacks or Tumarkin&#146;s otolithic crisis in patients with Meniere&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Drop attacks (DA) are a sudden fall that comes without warning and without loss of consciousness, with no associated neurological symptoms and normal neurological examination. A certain number of patients with Meniere´s disease, develop Tumarkin´s otolithic crisis or DA. The purpose of this study is to document the frequency and clinical features of DA in patients with Meniere ´s disease. Methods: A cohort of 40 patients with "definitive" Meniere´s Disease were followed up between six months and 12 years. The presence and characteristics of Tumarkin´s otolithic crisis were recorded. Results: Thirteen (32.5%) patients developed DA during the outcome of their Meniere´s disease. The interval between the onset of typical symptoms of Meniere´s disease and the DA ranged from less than one year to 18 years. The number of DA varied from 1 to 14. The attacks typically occurred in a flurry during a period of 1 year or less. Six patients had only one DA. No patient requiered treatment for the DA. Conclusions: Tumarkin´s otolithic crisis in Meniere´s disease are not uncommon. They can occur at any time during the course of the disease, generally in a flurry of less than one year. Most patients have a spontaneus remission of the DA</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales Angulo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallo-Terán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los pacientes con enfermedad deMeniere pueden presentar a lo largo de su evolución crisisotolíticas de Tumarkin o drop attacks (DA) que consisten encaídas bruscas al suelo sin pródromos previo ni pérdida deconciencia, de segundos de duración. El objetivo de nuestroestudio fue determinar la frecuencia y características delos DA en el contexto de la enfermedad de Meniere. Métodos:Se incluyó en nuestro estudio una cohorte de 40 pacientescon enfermedad de Meniere definitivo, seguidos entre6 meses y 12 años. Todos ellos fueron entrevistadospara valorar la aparición de crisis otolíticas de Tumarkin alo largo de la evolución de su enfermedad y recoger las característicasde las mismas. Resultados: 13 pacientes (32,5%),presentaron crisis otolíticas de Tumarkin. El número deepisodios osciló entre 1 (en 6 pacientes) y 14. En ningúnpaciente constituyeron el síntoma de inicio de la enfermedad,apareciendo entre 3 meses y 18 años después deldiagnóstico de la misma. Ningún paciente precisó tratamientopara los DA. Conclusiones: Las crisis otolíticas deTumarkin son frecuentes en pacientes con enfermedad deMeniere. Pueden aparecer en cualquier momento del desarrollode la misma. Normalmente se presentan en brotesde varios meses de duración y generalmente no precisantratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;56(10): 469-471, dic. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042699</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crisis otolíticas de Tumarkin o drop attacks en pacientes con enfermedad de Meniere</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27731^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28304^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8745^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
