<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058245</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors of developing asthma in children with recurrent wheezing in the first three years of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: recurrent wheezing is a common problem during the first years of life, but it is still difficult to identify which of these children may develop asthma in the future.                 Objectives: To study risk factors of developing asthma in a group of patients with frequent wheezing during the first three years of life.                 Material and methods: A prospective study was performed of a group of 60 patients, aged below three, referred to our Hospital for recurrent wheezing. Age, sex, parental and personal history of atopy, clinical features, laboratory tests, evolution and response to treatment were analyzed.                 Results: 60 patients were enrolled in study. Most of children were boys and have had the first episode of wheezing after the 6 months of life. 63 % had personal history of atopy and 55 % parental history of allergy. The group of atopic children had more wheezing exacerbations and worse evolution than the group of non atopic. They also had more treatment necessities.                 Conclusions: The identification of young children at high risk of developing asthma could permit an early intervention before irreversible changes in the airway appeared</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Mateos, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giner Muñoz, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piquer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Alvarez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaza Martín, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Martínez, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las sibilancias recurrentes son un problema frecuente en los primeros años de vida. Sin embargo, es aún dificultoso identificar cuáles de estos niños van a desarrollar asma en el futuro.                 Objetivos: estudiar cuáles son los factores de riesgo de desarrollar asma en un grupo de pacientes con broncoespasmo de repetición durante los primeros tres años de vida.                 Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo de 60 pacientes con edad igual o inferior a los 3 años, remitidos a nuestro centro por crisis de broncoespasmo repetidas. Se recoge información acerca de: edad, sexo, antecedentes familiares y personales de atopia, exploración física y pruebas alergológicas. Asimismo, evolución clínica y respuesta al tratamiento.                 Resultados: De los 60 pacientes implicados en el estudio, la mayor parte eran varones y presentaron el primer episodio de broncoespasmo antes de los 6 meses de vida. El 63% tenían antecedentes personales de atopia y el 55% antecedentes familiares de alergia. Los pacientes atópicos presentaron más crisis de sibilancias y peor evolución a corto plazo que los no atópicos. Asimismo, requirieron más tratamiento de mantenimiento.                 Conclusiones: La identificación precoz de los niños con elevado riesgo de desarrollar asma permitiría una intervención temprana antes de que se desarrollaran cambios irreversibles en la vía aérea</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);35(6): 228-231, nov. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058245</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo para el desarrollo de asma en niños con dificultad respiratoria recurrente en los tres primeros años de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d325^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27799^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27799^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27799^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14764^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27799^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27799^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
