<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59133</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urinary tract infections in a postoperative recovery unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJETIVE: To analyze the frequency, etiology, riskfactors, and mortality relating to urinary tract infection(UTI) in a postoperative recovery unit.MATERIALS AND METHODS: A prospective study wascarried out from 1998 through 2003 of all patients whostayed longer than 48 hours in a 12-bed critical care unitand who were followed to 48 hours following dischargefrom the unit. A descriptive statistics were compiled andunivariate and multiple variable Cox regression analyseswere performed for episodes of nosocomial UTI.RESULTS: The incidence density for UTI associated withbladder catheterization was 8.4 cases per 1000 patientdays.The pathogens most frequently isolated in patientswith bacteriuria were Candida albicans and Escherichiacoli. The pathogen most frequently isolated in UTI intrauma patients was E coli, whereas C albicans was mostoften found in the postoperative patients. Multivariableanalysis identified 3 risk factors: degree of severity onadmission, duration of catheterization, and presence ofdiabetes mellitus. The mortality risk in patients withbladder catheterization and UTI was 2.20.CONCLUSIONS: UTIs can have serious consequences andare responsible for excess mortality. The real importanceof UTI is unknown and is probably underestimateddespite the publication of many studies. We found that theUTI microbiology findings were markedly different for thetrauma and postoperative cohorts in our department (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Vizuete, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayelo Navarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Garrido, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortiñas Sáenz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peyro García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Conocer la frecuencia, etiología, factores deriesgo, y mortalidad relacionados con la infección del tractourinario (ITU) en una Unidad de Reanimación.MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Estudio prospectivo de los años1998-2003, ambos inclusive, de todos los pacientes coningreso superior a 48 horas y con seguimiento hasta las 48horas posteriores al alta de una unidad de cuidados críticospolivalentes de 12 camas. Análisis descriptivo, univariantey multivariable con regresión de Cox para los episodiosde ITU nosocomiales.RESULTADOS: La densidad de incidencia de ITU asociadaa sondaje vesical es de 8,4 por 1.000 pacientes-día. Lospatógenos aislados con más frecuencia en los pacientes conbacteriuria son Candida albicans y Escherichia coli. El germenaislado con más frecuencia en las ITU de los pacientestraumáticos es Escherichia coli, mientras que Candidaalbicans predomina en la cohorte de pacientes postquirúrgicos.Tras el análisis multivariable, tres son los factores deriesgo hallados: grado de severidad a la admisión, duraciónde la cateterización y la presencia de diabetes mellitas.El riesgo de mortalidad en pacientes con sondaje urinarioe ITU es de 2,20.CONCLUSIONES: Las ITU tienen consecuencias potencialmentegraves y son responsables de sobremortalidad. Sedesconoce su importancia real y probablemente se lasubestima pese a la publicación de múltiples estudios. Secomprueba que la microbiología de la ITU de las cohortestraumáticas y postquirúrgicas es marcadamente diferenteen nuestra unidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;55(5): 266-270, mayo 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59133</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones urinarias en una unidad de reanimación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1460^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
