<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039519</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-3465</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiologic imaging of Wilm&#146;s tumor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Wilms´tumor is the most common abdominal neoplasm        in children and represents more than 90% of        primary renal malignancies in childhood. The National        Wilms Tumor Study Group (NWTS) has defined        two major groups that are favorable and unfavorable        histology, the last one with poor prognosis.        The purpose of this article is to illustrate the spectrum        of imaging findings of Wilms´tumor in children        and to evaluate the efficacy of ultrasound, computed        tomography and magnetic resonance imaging in the        diagnosis, staging and management of this neoplasm.        The imaging key findings of each imaging        modality are shown and compared with the underlying        gross and microscopic pathologic features. Associations        with specific syndromes and diseases are        also discussed. Pitfalls and diagnostic difficulties are        emphasized</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berrocal Frutos, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Allona Krayel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Pereira, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra Gutiérrez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Vigil Junco, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Aguilera, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tumor de Wilms es la neoplasia abdominal más        frecuente en niños y constituye más del 90% de los        tumores renales primarios de la infancia. Los dos        grandes tipos de tumor definidos por la NWTS (National        Wilms Tumor Study) son el de histología &#147;favorable&#148;        y el &#147;desfavorable&#148; siendo éste último el de        peor pronóstico.        El objetivo de este artículo es mostrar los hallazgos        de imagen del tumor de Wilms en niños y evaluar        la eficacia de la ecografía, la tomografía computada        y la resonancia magnética en el diagnóstico,        estadiaje y manejo de este tumor. Se discuten los        hallazgos típicos de las distintas modalidades de        imagen comparándolos con los hallazgos de la anatomía        patológica. Se discute la asociación del tumor        de Wilms con distintos síndromes y enfermedades,        poniendo énfasis en los errores y las dificultades        para el diagnóstico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediátrika (Madr.);25(7): 296-308, jul.-ago. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039519</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Imagen radiológica del Tumor de Wilms</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31926^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31926^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
