<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89300</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">assessment of permanet disability in 17 patients in working age with osteosarcoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims and purpose: To assess how occupation-related working capacity is affected in patients with a diagnosis of osteosarcoma and how the progonsis of the disease affects such assessment.Patients and methods: Retrospective analysis of 17 patients with a diagnosis of osteosarcoma assessed by the Disability Assessment Team of the Madrid Provincial Directorate of the National Social Security Institute (INSS) between January 2004 ans February 2009 in order to determine and grant a possible permanent disability.Results: In the 17 cases analysed as having all pertinent and required data, the final decision of the INSS was: 4 cases of total permanent disability and 8 of absolute permanent disability; no disability was granted, in any of its degrees, in 5 cases. Thus, permanent disability in some of its degrees was granted in 12 cases (70.5%).Conclusions: The lesions and sequels of osteosarcoma and of its treatment cause a considerable labour impact, particularly in patients whose work involved medium-to-high intensity requirements of biomechanical load of the upper or lower limbs (in relation to the location of the tumour). Furthermore, absolute permanent disability was granted to patients with metastatic disease as this represents a poorer prognosis (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Pulido, José Laureano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Roldán, Piedad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Gómez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar cómo se afecta la capacidad laboral en los pacientes diagnosticados de osteosarcoma, en relación con su profesión, y ver cómo afecta el pronóstico de la enfermedad a dicha evaluación.Pacientes y método: Análisis retrospectivo de 22 pacientes valorados en el Equipo de Valoración de Incapacidades de la Dirección Provincial del INSS de Madrid entre enero de 2004 y febrero de 2009, con diagnostico de osteosarcoma, con el fin de determinar una posible incapacidad permanente.Resultado: De los 17 casos estudiados, por tener todos los datos necesarios para su análisis, la resolución del INSS ha sido: 4 casos de incapacidad permanente total, 8 casos de incapacidad permanente absoluta y 5 casos no causaron incapacidad en ninguno de sus grados. En 12 casos (70,5%) se ha concedido incapacidad permanente en alguno de sus grados.Conclusiones: Las lesiones y secuelas que se derivan del osteosarcoma y su tratamiento ocasionan una importante repercusión laboral, especialmente en pacientes cuyas profesiones incluían intensidad media-alta o exigencia en cuanto a carga biomecánica de miembros inferiores y superiores según la localización del tumor. Asimismo, a los pacientes con metástasis, en tanto supone peor pronóstico, se les ha concedido incapacidad permanente en grado de absoluta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;19(3): 9-14, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la incapacidad permanente en 17 pacientes con osteosarcoma en edad laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31274^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
