<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133786</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">X-linked agammaglobulinemia: Experience in a Portuguese hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: X-Linked agammaglobulinemia (XLA) is characterized by an arrest of B cell differentiation, leading to recurrent bacterial infections. Lifelong immunoglobulin replacement therapy (IRT) is indicated to prevent infections and their complications. Material and methods: A retrospective study of patients with XLA followed in a level three hospital was performed; data was collected retrospectively by review of clinical files. Results: XLA was diagnosed in 9 children. One (11%) had a positive family history with a prenatal diagnosis. Infection was the clinical presentation in all the others (89%), at an average age of 13 months; diagnosis was established at a mean age of 3.4 years. Acute otitis media (7/9) and pneumonia (5/9) were the most frequently observed. Seven (78%) presented serum immunoglobulin G (IgG) levels below 200 mg/dL and all of them had CD19+ B cells below 2%. Neutropenia was present at diagnosis in three patients (33%). Bruton tyrosine kinase (BTK) mutations were identified in all cases. Intravenous IRT was initiated, switched later to subcutaneous administration, in all. The mean time of follow-up was 10.7 years with cumulative time of 97 years. Eight children (89%) achieved IgG serum levels above 800 mg/dL. One presented lower values due to renal loss. No deaths occurred. After diagnosis the most frequent infections were acute otitis media (6/9). In spite of stable adequate IgG levels on IRT, two patients developed  bronchiectasis.Conclusions: XLA overall prognosis is good, as long as patients have an early and adequate  treatment. However, bronchiectasis can occur even on adequate immunoglobulin replacement therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernandes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guedesa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vasconcelosa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nevesa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandes, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marquesa, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La agammaglobulinemia ligada al cromosoma X (ALX) se caracteriza por la detención de la diferenciación celular de los linfocitos B, que da lugar a infecciones bacterianas recurrentes. La terapia de por vida de reemplazo de inmunoglobulina (TRI) está indicada para prevenir infecciones y sus complicaciones. Material y métodos: Se hizo un estudio retrospectivo de pacientes con ALX en un hospital terciario. Los datos se revisaron retrospectivamente revisando historias clínicas. Resultados: Se diagnosticó ALX en 9 niños. Uno de ellos (11%) tenía antecedentes familiares y había sido diagnosticado prenatalmente. El resto presentó signos de infección (89%) a una edad media de 13 meses, siendo su edad media al diagnóstico de 3,4 a&#152;nos de edad. Las infecciones más frecuentes fueron otitis media aguda (7/9) y neumonía (5/9). Siete niños (78%) presentaron niveles séricos de inmunoglobulina G (IgG) inferiores a 200 mg/dL y todos tenían niveles de células B CD19+ B por debajo del 2%. Tres pacientes tuvieron neutropenia al diagnóstico (33%). En todos los casos se detectaron mutaciones en la tirosincinasa de Bruton (BTK). También en todos se inició la TRI por la vía intravenosa, que luego continuó por la vía subcutánea. La  duración media del seguimiento fue de 10,7 años, con un número total acumulado de 97 a&#152;nos. Ocho niños (89%) alcanzaron niveles séricos de IgG superiores a los 800 mg/dL. En un caso se observaron niveles más bajos por pérdida renal. No hubo ninguna defunción. El tipo de infección más frecuente tras el diagnóstico fue la otitis media aguda (6/9). A pesar de haberse conseguido niveles estables adecuados de IgG mediante la TRI, 2 pacientes desarrollaron bronquiectasias. Conclusiones: En general, el pronóstico de la ALX es bueno siempre y cuando los pacientes reciban el tratamiento adecuado de manera precoz. Aun así, es posible que a pesar de ser tratados correctamente con TRI desarrollen bronquiectasias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(3): 166-171, mar. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133786</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Agammaglobulinemia ligada al cromosoma X: experiencia en un hospital portugués</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d366^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29428^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
