<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135083</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional status in university students: its relation to the number of daily intakes and macronutrients consumption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is increasing scientific evidence that nutrition influence positive and negative on health along life. Many studies have reported that the student population is a particularly vulnerable group from the nutritional point of view, due to it is characterized by meal skipping frequently and nibble between eating occasions. Objective: To establish the relationship between the number of daily dietary intakes and nutritional status in male students aged 23 to 33 years of the National Technological University, in the city of Córdoba, in 2013. Methods: In order to achieve this aim, a prospective, cross-sectional and descriptive correlational design was used. Descriptive and inferential analysis were applied by using multiple logistic regression models. Results: Almost 50% of the sample analyzed presented overweight (OW) and 40% high body fat (BF). In relation to the intakes numbers, the students that take less than 4 and more than 6 had 2 times more chance of presenting overweight and high body fat. It was found that as age increases it also does the Body Fat Storage, whereas diminished physical activity increases the chance of having high Body Mass Index and Body Fat. Moreover, high ingestion of carbohydrates increases the chance of high Body Fat and Overweight, and a high intake of protein and lipids increases the risk of high Body Fat. Conclusion: It is recognized that high or low number of daily intakes than recommended, low level of physical activity, high consumption of carbohydrates and having more than 29 years is related to high overweight and body fat (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antonella Pi, Romina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aballay, Laura Rosana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brassesco, Bárbara Romina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Paula Daniela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viola, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existe una creciente evidencia científica de que la nutrición ejerce una influencia tanto positiva como negativa en la salud a lo largo de la vida. Diversos autores han destacado que la población universitaria es un grupo especialmente vulnerable desde el punto de vista nutricional ya que se caracteriza por omitir comidas con frecuencia y realizar pequeñas ingestas repetidas veces entre las comidas principales. Objetivo General: Establecer la relación existente entre el número de ingestas alimentarias diarias (NIAD), el consumo de macronutrientes y el estado nutricional (EN) en estudiantes de 23-33 años de la Universidad Tecnológica Nacional (UTN), de la ciudad de Córdoba, en el año 2013. Métodos: Se utilizó un diseño prospectivo de tipo descriptivo simple correlacional de corte transversal. Se realizó análisis descriptivo e inferencial mediante modelos de regresión logística múltiple. Resultados: De la muestra analizada casi un 50% presentó sobrepeso (SP) y un 40% grasa corporal (GC) elevada. En relación al número de ingestas, los estudiantes que realizaron menos de 4 y más de 6 ingestas tuvieron 2 veces más chance de presentar exceso de peso y de GC. A medida que aumenta la edad también lo hacen los depó- sitos de GC, y cuando disminuyen los niveles de actividad física (AF) aumenta la chance de presentar un índice de masa corporal (IMC) y GC elevada. Por otro lado, el consumo excesivo de glúcidos aumenta la chance de presentar GC elevada y SP, y el de proteínas y lípidos, el riesgo de GC elevada. Conclusión: Se reconoce al NIAD inferior o superior al recomendado, el bajo nivel de AF, el elevado consumo de carbohidratos, y la edad superior a 29 años como variables relacionados con el SP y la GC elevada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(4): 1748-1756, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135083</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado nutricional en estudiantes universitarios: su relación con el número de ingestas alimentarias diarias y el consumo de macronutrientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50311</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
