<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134996</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of literary texts in the teaching of health sciences: examples in cardiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The importance of humanities in the medical training is commonly recognized and it has been suggested that its implementation in the medical curricula as literature and medicine courses. In spite of its viability, there is often difficult to include specific subjects in the already crowded medical curricula. Therefore, it has been suggested the use of literary texts as a teaching tool in traditional subjects. However, there are few publications that analyse the potential usefulness of them. In the present paper three literary works that might be used to illustrate the experience of disease in cardiology are discussed. Two autobiographical texts, Un infart de miocardi of Josep Pla and Monte Sinaí of José Luis Sampedro, and a fiction work, Mémoires d&#146;Hadrien of Marguerite Yourcenar, were chosen. They were reviewed to establish their usefulness to understand the patient&#146;s experience of disease and to reach educative objectives. The paper shows the chosen fragments to illustrate the disease consequences and its usefulness to understand emotional aspects of sickness and the patient-physician relationship is discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guardiola, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eladi Baños, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La importancia de las humanidades en la educación médica es un hecho generalmente aceptado y se ha sugerido su introducción en los planes de estudio de cursos como los basados en literatura y medicina. A pesar de su viabilidad, existen dificultades en incluir asignaturas específicas en currículos ya apretados. Se ha planteado la posibilidad de utilizar textos literarios como elementos docentes en las asignaturas tradicionales. Sin embargo, existen pocas publicaciones que analicen la utilidad potencial de algunos de ellos. En el presente artículo se presentan tres obras que podrían emplearse para ilustrar la experiencia de la enfermedad en el caso de las cardiopatías. Se escogieron dos textos autobiográficos, Un infart de miocardi, de Josep Pla, y Monte Sinaí, de José Luis Sampedro, y uno de ficción, Mémoires d&#146;Hadrien, de Marguerite Yourcenar. Se revisaron para constatar que podían contribuir a comprender la vivencia de la enfermedad por los pacientes y alcanzar los objetivos educativos establecidos. Se presentan los fragmentos escogidos para ilustrar las repercusiones de la enfermedad y se debate la utilidad para la comprensión de los aspectos emocionales de la enfermedad y de la relación médico-paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);18(1): 5-14, ene.-feb. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los textos literarios en la docencia de ciencias de la salud: ejemplos en cardiología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8684</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2353^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
