<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14851</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Computational study of the effect of forced exercise (swin stredd) on the NADPH- diaphorase activity in the supraoptic nucleus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nitric oxide synthesizing neurons of the hypothalamus show changes following a variety of experimental and pathological conditions, such as salt loading, hypotension, cholestasis, water deprivation, and several types of stress including immobilization, exposure to low temperature and changes of environment. Recently, our group has shown that forced exercise (swim stress) is an additional stressor for the nitrergic neurons located in the paraventricular nucleus of the hypothalamus. On the other hand it is currently well-known, by means of histochemical (NADPH-diaphorase), immunohistochemical and hybridization methods, that the supraoptic nucleus contains an important nitrergic population of neurons. In the present study, the effect of forced exercise on these neurons was investigated in a computational study of the NADPH-diaphorase positive population of the supraoptic nucleus. A significant increase in the number of positive neurons was observed following forced swimming, especially after 30 and 40 min. These data indicate: 1.- The influence of stress on the NADPH-diaphorase-activity in the supraoptic nucleus. 2.- The involvement of hypothalamic nitric oxide synthesizing-neurons in the response to different types of acute stressors. 3.- The excellence of a combination of morphological and computational tecniques for the detection of changes in plasticity of the hypothalamic neurons (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las neuronas hipotalámicas que sintetizan óxido nítrico muestran cambios después de una variedad de condiciones experimentales y patológicas, tales como sobrecarga salina, hipotensión, colestasis, deprivación de agua y diferentes tipos de estrés incluyendo inmovilización, exposición a bajas temperaturas y cambios del entorno. Recientemente, nuestro grupo ha demostrado que el ejercicio forzado (estrés acuático) es un estresante adicional para las neuronas nitrérgicas localizadas en el núcleo paraventricular del hipotálamo. Por otra parte, es actualmente bien conocido, por medio de métodos histoquímicos (NADPH-diaforasa), inmunohistoquímicos y de hibridación que el núcleo supraóptico contiene una importante población neuronal nitrérgica. En el presente trabajo, el efecto del ejercicio forzado sobre estas neuronas ha sido investigado mediante un estudio computacional de la población NADPH-diaforasa del núcleo supraóptico. Se observó un aumento significativo en el número de neuronas positivas después de la natación forzada, especialmente a los 30 y 40 minutos. Estos datos indican: 1.- La influencia del estrés sobre la actividad NADPH-diaforasa en el núcleo supraóptico. 2.- La participación de las neuronas que sintetizan óxido nítrico en respuesta a diferentes tipos de estresantes agudos. 3.- La excelencia de la combinación de técnicas morfológicas y computacionales para la detección de cambios en la plasticidad de las neuronas hipotalámicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;6(2): 65-69, sept. 2002. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio computacional del efecto del ejercicio forzado (estrés acuático) sobre la actividad NADPH-diaforasa en el núcleo supraóptico</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>López, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, MN</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Vallejo, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alburquerque, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14851</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9444^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13876^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6810</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13931</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19269</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
