<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055792</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Doubts and confusions in the diagnosis and treatment of positional plagiocephaly. Management protocol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction    Positional plagiocephaly is currently the most frequent    cause of consultation at pediatric neurosurgical departments    in Spain and other western countries. There is considerable    confusion in the literature on the terminology    and physiopathology of this deformity, as well as its differential    diagnosis with true synostosis and treatment recommendations.    Objectives    To clarify these concepts and present a protocol for the    management of positional plagiocephaly, which was recently    requested by the Health Administration of the Community    of Madrid.    Protocol    The protocol aims to achieve coordination among pediatricians    and neurosurgeons, as well as to provide precise    information on this deformity for parents, pediatricians    and neurosurgeons.    Material and methods    Previous consensus was reached on a series of data. Infants    were classified into three categories of deformity (mild, moderate, severe) according to measurements on    digital photographs.    Diagnosis and treatment follows two phases: a pediatric    phase (up to 5 months of age) and a neurosurgical phase    (from 5 months onwards). Infants are referred to neurosurgical    consultation only after being treated with postural    changes and physiotherapy and only after reaching the    age of 5 months. The reasons for this approach are explained    in the protocol, which also defines the functions    and responsibilities of each specialty.    Conclusion    The treatment proposed in the protocol is staged, starting    with postural changes and physiotherapy, followed by    orthotic cranial devices and finally surgical treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza Rodrígueza, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Casado, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hinojosa Mena-Bernal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romance-García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Recuero, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción    La plagiocefalia posicional es actualmente la causa más    frecuente de asistencia en una consulta de neurocirugía    pediátrica, tanto en España como en todos los países occidentales.    A ello se suma la considerable confusión existente    en la literatura especializada en relación a aspectos    como la terminología, conceptos fisiopatológicos, diagnóstico    diferencial con la craneosinostosis y por supuesto    en el tratamiento más adecuado que hay que seguir.    Objetivos    Intentar clarificar estos conceptos y además presentar    un protocolo de asistencia que nos ha solicitado recientemente    la Administración Sanitaria de la Comunidad de Madrid.    Protocolo    Pretende lograr la coordinación entre pediatras y neurocirujanos,    así como conseguir una información precisa    de los principales datos de esta patología para los familiares,    pediatras y neurocirujanos.    Material y métodos    Se establecen una serie de datos de consenso. Los niños    son clasificados en 3 grados de deformación (leve, moderada    y grave) según los índices medidos en fotografías digitales.    Además el proceso del diagnóstico y tratamiento tiene    dos fases: fase pediátrica (hasta los 5 meses de edad) y fase    neuroquirúrgica (desde los 5 meses de edad). Los niños serán    enviados a neurocirugía después de haber sido tratados    con tratamiento posicional y rehabilitación y solamente    a partir de los 5 meses de edad.    Las razones de todo ello son explicadas en el protocolo    que define también las funciones y responsabilidades de    cada especialista.    Conclusiones    El tratamiento que se propone es escalonado, comenzando    por las medidas posicionales y de rehabilitación, seguidas    de ortesis craneal y en último lugar del tratamiento    quirúrgico</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(3): 243-252, sept. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055792</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enigmas y confusiones en el diagnóstico y tratamiento de la plagiocefalia posicional. Protocolo asistencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26970</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
