<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153165</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Food habits in Mexican pregnant adolescents according to their civil status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify the feeding habits of pregnant adolescents in four different civil status: married, cohabiting with a partner, single with no partner and single with a partner. Methods: In a cross-sectional study, 321 pregnant adolescents aged 13 to 19 years old who attended the Hospital Civil de Guadalajara Dr. Juan I Menchaca, Guadalajara (Jalisco, Mexico) were included. They were healthy, in any trimester of pregnancy and had either a low or medium-low socioeconomic status. The civil status of adolescents was stratified into: a) married, b) cohabiting with a partner, c) single with a partner and d) single without a partner. Socio-demographic, economic and feeding habits data were included. ANOVA, post-hoc tests for Chi2 , odds ratio and logistic regression models were used. Results: The frequency of married adolescents was 9.3%; 59.8% of the adolescents were cohabiting, 15.3% of the adolescents were single without a partner and 15.6% of the adolescents were single with a partner. Low schooling (OR 2.6 [1.5-4.4]) and occupation in housework (OR 4.47 [1.99-10.0]) predominated among adolescents in cohabitating with a partner; an occupation at home (OR 0.28 [0.127 to 0.61]) and unaccompanied dining (OR 4.12 [1.62-10.8]) were the factors with the most epidemiological significance in single without a partner adolescents. The consumption of vegetables was significantly lower in married adolescents and cohabiting-with-partner adolescents; consumption of beans and sweet bread was significantly lower in pregnant married adolescents. Conclusion: Because some variables and eating habits depended on civil status, it is pertinent to analyze them in each group of pregnant teenagers separately (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Troyo-Sanroman, Rogelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Velarde, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez-Garibay, Edgar M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán-Mercado, Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: identificar los hábitos alimentarios de adolescentes embarazadas en cuatro estados civiles diferentes: casada, cohabita con una pareja, soltera sin pareja y soltera con una pareja. Métodos: en estudio transversal, se incluyeron 321 adolescentes embarazadas de 13-19 años que acudieron al Hospital Civil de Guadalajara Dr. Juan I Menchaca, Guadalajara (Jalisco, México). Se encontraban sanas, en cualquier trimestre del embarazo y pertenecían a un nivel socioeconómico bajo o medio-bajo. El estado civil se estratificó en: casadas; en unión libre; soltera con una pareja y soltera sin pareja. Se incluyeron datos socio-demográficos, económicos y de hábitos de alimentación. Se utilizaron pruebas de ANOVA, pruebas post-hoc para Chi2 , razón de momios y modelos de regresión logística. Resultados: la frecuencia de las adolescentes casadas fue de 9,3%, 59,8% en unión libre, 15,3% eran solteras sin pareja y 15,6% solteras con pareja. La baja escolaridad (RM 2,6 [1,5-4,4]) y la ocupación en el hogar (RM 4,47 [1,99-10,0]) predominaron entre las adolescentes en unión libre; la ocupación en el hogar (RM 0,28 [0,127-0,61]) y cenar sin compañía (RM 4,12 [1,62-10,8]) fueron significativamente más frecuentes en adolescentes sin pareja. El consumo de verduras fue menor en las adolescentes casadas y en quienes cohabitaban con pareja; el consumo de frijoles y pan dulce fue menor en adolescentes embarazadas casadas. Conclusión: debido a que ciertas variables y hábitos de alimentación mostraron diferencias entre los grupos es pertinente analizar las adolescentes embarazadas de acuerdo a su estado civil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(2): 226-231, mar.-abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153165</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábitos de alimentación en adolescentes embarazadas de acuerdo a su estado civil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30663^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11695</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
