<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142912</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of diagnostic criteria for cholestatic jaundice during the first year of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Jaundice is a common reason for consultation in infants. Early detection of cholestatic jaundice may result in improved prognosis. Objectives. To analyze the distinct clinical features of the different types of cholestatic jaundice that can assist in an early diagnosis. Material and methods. Retrospective study of infants with cholestatic jaundice admitted between January 1997 and December 2001. Results. Sixteen infants (11 males), aged 17 days to 11 months, were included. Distribution by diagnosis was as follows: Hepatitis, 6 cases; Biliary atresia, 5 cases, alpha 1&amp;#945;antitrypsine deficiency, 2 cases; ARC-1 syndrome (arthrogryposis, renal tubulopathy, cholestasis and ichthyosis), 1 case; Wolman disease, 1 case; extrahepatic cholestasis with micronodular chirrosis, 1 case. Nine patients had hypocholia, 7 patients had choluria, and 3 patients had failure to thrive. The 4 patients with low birth weight had hepatitis. Five patients had hepatomegaly, and splenomegaly was only present in the case with Wolman syndrome. Total and direct bilirubin and gamma-glutamyltranspeptidase (GGT) were higher in biliary atresia than in hepatitis. Abdominal ultrasound failed to identify the gallbladder in 4 cases of biliary atresia, in one case of hepatitis, and in the case of micronodular chirrosis. A scintigraphy was diagnostic in the cases of biliary atresia, was abnormal in the cases of alpha-1-antitrypsine deficiency and micronodular chirrosis, and was normal in one case of hepatitis. Comments. Idiopatic hepatitis is more commonly associated with low birth weight than biliary atresia. A cholestasis with a total bilirrubin of &gt; 7 mg/dl and GGT &gt; 300 IU/L suggests biliary atresia. Abdominal ultrasound is the first imaging study that should be performed; the scintigraphy should be performed in those cases highly suspicious of biliary atresia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Compañón, Zuriñe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trenchs, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mainou, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alsina, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caritg, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La ictericia es motivo habitual de consulta en los lactantes. Es importante detectar las colestásicas para establecer precozmente el diagnóstico y mejorar el pronóstico. Objetivos. Analizar las diferencias clínicas y de las exploraciones complementarias de los lactantes con colestasis según la etiología, para determinar cuales tendrían que guiar al especialista para un diagnóstico precoz. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de los lactantes ingresados por ictericia colestásica entre enero de 1997 y diciembre de 2001. Resultados. Se recogen 16 casos, 11 masculinos, de 17 días a 11 meses de edad. Se diagnostican: 6 hepatitis (H), 5 atresias de vías biliares (AVB), 2 déficits de alfa-1-antitripsina, (D&amp;#945;1AT), un ARC-I (síndrome caracterizado por artrogriposis, tubulopatía renal, colestasis e ictiosis), una enfermedad de Wolman (W) y una colestasis extrahepática con cirrosis micronodular (CM). Presentan hipocolia 9 pacientes, coluria 7 y estancamiento ponderal 3. Hay 4 niños con bajo peso al nacer tienen H. Se detecta hepatomegalia en 5 pacientes y esplenomegalia sólo en W. La bilirrubina (Br) total, directa y gamma-glutamiltranspeptidasa (GGT) en las AVB son más elevadas que en las H. La ecografía abdominal no objetiva vesícula biliar en 4 AVB, una H y en la CM. Se realiza gammagrafía y es diagnóstica en las AVB, está alterada en un D&amp;#945;1AT y en la CM y es normal en una H. Comentarios. La hepatitis idiopática se relaciona más frecuentemente con bajo peso al nacer que la AVB. Una colestasis con Br total &gt; 7 mg/dl y GGT &gt; 300 UI/L sugiere AVB. La ecografía abdominal es la primera prueba de imagen a realizar ante una colestasis; la gammagrafía se reserva para los casos con alta sospecha de AVB (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;64(2): 56-60, mar.-abr. 2004. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de los criterios diagnósticos de la ictericia colestásica durante el primer año de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38066^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19088^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33363^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1183^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23863^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6657^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
