<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91587</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reassessment of crystals in synovial fluid: is it helpful?</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Larramendi Martínez, Carmen Hernando de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mena Pérez, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Pérez, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Background. White blood cell counts, analysis of crystals in synovial fluid (SF) and microbiological studies are key measurements in the diagnosis and management of joint effusion. The results may lead to clinical and therapeutic decisions. The diagnosis of crystals in SF, usually performed by examination with compensated polarised light microscopy (PL), is not easy. It depends on the experience of the examiner and amount of crystals in the sample, which is sometimes very small. In order to increase the performance, analysis may be performed on the sediment after centrifugation. Some authors suggest that due to in vitro maturation of crystals, they can be more easily identified 24hours after extraction. Others suggest that the sample deteriorates. We question whether re-examination of SF can increase the diagnostic yield of this test. Methods. Over a 4 month period we analysed crystals in SF received in the laboratory using a PL and ordinary light microscopy. Where this was possible, the SF was examined again after 24hours. Results. We received 174 SF; 138 (79.3%) were negative for the first analysis. In 84 cases (60.8%) a re-evaluation could be made after 24hours by trained staff. In 10 cases (11.9%) crystals that had not been seen previously became apparent. In all cases they were calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate crystals. The number of positive fluids increased by 27.8% (95% CI: 13.1-42.4) after a second assay. Conclusions. The re-analysis of crystals in SF at 24hours should be considered in cases of high suspicion of microcrystalline arthropathy when the first test is negative (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;4(4): 173-176, oct.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91587</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es útil la reevaluación de cristales en el líquido sinovial?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13963^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13963^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2487^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2487^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13963^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13963^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
