<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156912</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The wheel of emotions: a game as a strategy for emotional education in the nursing degree</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To strengthen the transversal development of emotional skills, allowing to understand and adjust emotions adequately, represents a challenge in the training of Nursing students. In order to strengthen the reflection on the role of emotions in professional behaviour, a dynamic workshop has been designed through the «Wheel of Emotions» game. Two questionnaires were previously handed out in order to activate reflection. Sixteen (16) students in their fourth year participated in the game, working on 14 emotions. During the activity, students distinguished between emotions and analyzed different behaviours. They assessed the experience as rewarding.  Guided practices are a laboratory for testing emotional skills. Reflective methods represent powerful tools to become aware of our own emotions as well as the emotions of others. The Wheel of Emotions encourages to identify the emotions experienced, and to analyze the way to manage them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Blázquez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oter Quintana, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Hidalgo, Adrián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Gil, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río Aragón, Paloma del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüello López, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canalejas Pérez, Coro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morena Villoria, Tatiana de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un reto en la formación de estudiantes de Enfermería es potenciar el desarrollo transversal de competencias emocionales que les permitan comprender y regular adecuadamente las emociones.  Para potenciar la reflexión sobre el papel de las emociones en la conducta profesional, se diseñó un taller dinamizado mediante el juego «Ruleta de emociones». Previamente se entregaron dos cuestionarios para activar la reflexión. Participaron 16 estudiantes de cuarto curso trabajando 14 emociones. Durante la actividad los estudiantes discriminaron emociones y analizaron comportamientos. Evaluaron la experiencia como enriquecedora.  Las prácticas tuteladas son un laboratorio para testar competencias emocionales. Los métodos reflexivos constituyen herramientas potentes para tomar conciencia de las emociones propias y de otros. La ruleta de emociones estimula a identificar emociones experimentadas y a analizar la forma de gestionarlas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(8): 20-25, oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">«Ruleta de emociones»: el juego como estrategia para la educación emocional en el Grado de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56170^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12960^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
