<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126306</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is psychiatry scientific? A letter to a 21st century psychiatry resident</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During the development of the DSM-5, even the lay press questioned psychiatry&#146;s scientific validity. This review provides 21st century psychiatry residents with ways of answering these attacks by defining the concepts and history of psychiatry  (a branch of medicine), medicine and science. Psychiatric language has two levels: first, describing symptoms and signs (19th century descriptive psychopathology developed in France and Germany), and second, describing disorders (psychiatric nosology was developed in the early 20th century by Kraepelin and resuscitated by the US neo-Kraepelinian revolution leading to the DSM-III I ). Science is a complex trial-and-error historical process that can be threatened by those who believe too much in it and disregard its limitations. The most important Psychiatric advances, electroconvulsive therapy and major psychopharmacological agents, were discovered by « chance » , not by scientific planning. Jaspers&#146;s General Psychopathology is a complex 100-year-old book that describes: 1) psychiatric disorders as heterogeneous and 2) psychiatry as a hybrid scientific discipline requiring a combination of understanding (a social science method) and explanation (a natural science method). In the 21st century Berrios reminds us of psychiatry&#146;s unfortunate methodological issues due to hybrid symptoms and disorders, some of which are better understood as problems in communication between interacting human beings; in those situations neuroscience methods such as brain imaging make no sense. A new language is needed in psychiatry. East Asian psychiatry residents, who are not particularly attached to the antiquated language currently used, may be particularly equipped for the task of recreating psychiatric language using 21st century knowledge (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>León, José de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante el desarrollo del DSM-5 incluso la prensa ha cuestionado la validez científica de la psiquiatría. Esta revisión proporciona a los residentes de psiquiatría del s. XXI maneras de responder a estas críticas a través de la definición de los conceptos y la historia de la psiquiatría (una rama de la medicina), la medicina y la ciencia. El lenguaje psiquiátrico tiene 2 niveles: primero, describir los síntomas y signos (la psicopatología descriptiva del s. XIX , desarrollada en Francia y Alemania), y, segundo, describir los trastornos (la nosología psiquiátrica fue desarrollada a principios del s. XX por Kraepelin y resucitada por la revolución americana neo-kraepeliniana, llevando finalmente al DSM- III ). La ciencia es un proceso histórico complejo de ensayo y error que puede verse amenazada por aquellos que creen demasiado en ella e ignoran sus limitaciones. Los avances psiquiátricos más importantes (la terapia electroconvulsiva y los principales agentes psicofarmacológicos) fueron descubiertos por «casualidad», no gracias a la planificación científica. La Psicopatología general, escrita por Jaspers, es un complejo libro de 100 años de antigüedad que describe: 1) los trastornos psiquiátricos como heterogéneos y 2) la psiquiatría como una disciplina científica híbrida que requiere una combinación de comprensión (un método del campo de las ciencias sociales) y explicación (un método del campo de las ciencias naturales). En el s. XXI Berrios nos recuerda los aspectos relacionados con la poco afortunada metodología de la psiquiatría debido a la heterogeneidad de sus síntomas y trastornos, algunos de los cuales resultan más comprensibles si son considerados problemas de comunicación fruto de la interacción entre seres humanos; en estas situaciones, los métodos neurocientíficos como las pruebas de neuroimagen no tienen sentido. Se necesita un nuevo lenguaje en la psiquiatría. Los residentes de psiquiatría del este de Asia, que no están particularmente apegados al lenguaje anticuado utilizado actualmente, pueden resultar especialmente preparados para la tarea de recrear el lenguaje psiquiátrico utilizando el conocimiento del s. XXI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);21(1): 14-24, ene.-abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es científica la psiquiatría? Carta al residente de psiquiatría del siglo XXI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14880^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
