<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78292</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metabolic syndrome and nutritional habits in adult population: contribution of a rural pharmacy offi ce in communal health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypertension (HTA), diabetes (DM), dyslipidemia, sedentarismand inappropriate nutrition are health related problems to theMetabolic Syndrome frequently dealt in the pharmacy offi cesObjective: To describe the lifestyle and nutritional habits in adultpopulation, with characteristics of Metabolic Syndrome, and tocompare them with the recommendations. To provide, nutritionaleducation in the cases when it is considered necessary.Methods: Descriptive cross-sectional study. Inclusion criteria:adults with HTA treated pharmacologically and MetabolicSyndrome diagnostic criteria. Informed consent was obtained:nutritional habits and lifestyle survey, morbidity and medicinetaking. Intervention phase: nutritional education. Data analysis:proportions estimations, relation test: Chi-square, and averagecomparison.Results: n=237, 53.6% women (W) and 46.4% men (M).Mean age 67±12.7 years old. Average values of blood pressure:149.8±20.02/82±11.9 mmHg; BMI 31.96±11.9 Kg/m2; Waistperimeter 107.8±11.9 cm W, 112.5±10.9 cm M; waist-hip index0.92±0.1 W, 1.01±0.9 M. Diagnosis and drug treatment: averageof 3.7±2.1 and 4.5±2.7 respectively. 100% hypertensive patients,60% badly controlled (150/82±18/11 mmHg). 37% Hypercholesterolemia;7.1% DM and 12% hypercholesterolemiaand DM. 12.2% were smokers and 68.8% sedentary. &gt;50% didnot comply with recommended portions of water, milk and legumes;&gt;20% do not comply with vegetables, garden products,fruits, proteins, although patients had a perception of good feedingof (73.4%). Differences between gender and age were detected.Conclusion: After defi ciencies found in the present populationand the intervention carried out, we believe that the communitypharmacist is essential, due to his training and privilegedsituation with patients, to perform activities and to cooperate inhealth community projects(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puig Soler, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler Márquez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig Salomón, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La hipertensión arterial (HTA), la diabetes mellitus(DM), las dislipemias, el sedentarismo y una incorrecta alimentaciónson problemas de salud relacionados con el síndromemetabólico (SM), abordados frecuentemente en la ofi cina defarmacia.Objetivo: Describir el estilo de vida y los hábitos alimentarios enla población adulta, con características de SM, y compararloscon las recomendaciones. Realizar educación nutricional en loscasos necesarios.Método: Estudio descriptivo y transversal, realizado en adultoscon HTA en tratamiento farmacológico que cumplan criteriosdiagnósticos de SM; obtención del consentimiento informado;encuesta de hábitos alimentarios y estilos de vida, morbilidad ytoma de medicación; fase de intervención, educación nutricional;análisis de datos (estimación de proporciones), y pruebasde relación (chi-cuadrado y comparación de medias).Resultados: Se incluyeron en el estudio un total de 237 participantes,un 53,6% mujeres y un 46,4% varones, con unaedad media de 67 ± 12,7 años, unos valores medios de presiónarterial de 149,8 ± 20,02/82 ± 11,9 mmHg, un índicede masa corporal de 31,96 ± 11,9, un perímetro de cintura de107,8 ± 11,9 cm (mujeres) y 112,5 ± 10,9 cm (varones), y uníndice de cintura/cadera de 0,92 ± 0,1 (mujeres) y 1,01 ± 0,9(varones). Diagnósticos y medicamentos: media de 3,7 ± 2,1 y4,5 ± 2,7, respectivamente. Un 100% eran hipertensos, un 60% estaban mal controlados (150/82 ± 18/11 mmHg), un37% tenían hipercolesterolemia, un 7,1% DM, y un 12% hipercolesterolemiay DM. Un 12,2% eran fumadores y un68,8% presentaban sedentarismo. Más del 50% no tomabanlas raciones adecuadas de agua, leche y legumbres; más del20% no tomaban las raciones adecuadas de verduras, hortalizas,frutas y proteínas, pese a la percepción de que seguíanuna correcta alimentación (73,4%). Se apreciaron diferenciasrespecto al sexo y la edad...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;11(3): 133-143, sept. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome metabólico y hábitos alimentarios en la población adulta: contribución de una ofi cina de farmacia rural a la salud comunitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17561^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17561^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17561^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28457^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
