<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103143</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic of risk factor related to the accidentes of hand in workers of solf-drinks industry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the purpose of deepen on the recognize of risk factors from this kind of business and from this specific activities, to prevent and minimize the health effects integrally at the industries, the present work pretend to determine the risk factors potentially related with hand accidents. Objective: Determine the risk factors related to the accidents of hand to identify and establish the risks allowing decrease the possibility of accidents in hand through the modification, elimination and or control of present factors. Material and methods: Observational, descriptive and longitudinal study develop in worker population of sales area, composed by 206 helpers and 81 agents, cooperative producers of soft drinks and carbonated beverages in México City, in a period between 2007-2009. Was employed the Freeman Modified Method for the Situational Diagnostic. Results: The risk factor related to hand accidents determined by the application of Freeman Modified Method in sales area according to the organization: were first derived from the psychosocial labor organization (accelerated pace of activity) and the Insecure Condition (transfer of the personnel within the rear bumper of the truck); second were found ergonomics (repetitive movements and manual handling of loads), along with Insecure Act (omission of the use of personal protection equipment), and the Insecure Condition (kind of unity, door and material transported, and lack of training); finally, in third psychosocial of Labor Organization (indefinite at least 8 hours maximum of 14) and unsafe (sharp boxes). Conclusions: The risk factors presents in the generation of hand accidents in sales area of a soft drink industry are: primarily psychosocial factors due to the rhythm of the activity; unsafe condition due to lack of safety regulation. In second place ergonomic factors and unsafe acts by omission of use of personal protective equipment and unsafe condition, specifically lack of training and use of unsafe resources provided to the worker. Third place, psychosocial factors due to over 8 hours and under 14 hours working day. Mentioned risk factors should be diagnosed promptly and to evidence in companies engages in the production of fruit drinks and carbonated, which seek to reduce work accidents though preventive and corrective measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Díaz, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva López, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peón Escalante, Ignacio Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betzabé Pérez-Manriquez, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Aguilar, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el propósito de que se profundice en el reconocimiento de factores de riesgos derivados de este tipo de empresas y de estas actividades específicamente, para que se prevengan y minimicen los efectos a la salud de forma integral al interior de las empresas, el presente trabajo pretende determinar los factores de riesgo potencialmente relacionados con los accidentes de mano. Objetivos: Determinar los factores de riesgo relacionados con los accidentes en mano para identificar que permitan disminuir la posibilidad de accidentes de mano mediante la modificación, eliminación y/o control de los factores presentes. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional, descriptivo y longitudinal llevado a cabo en la población trabajadora del área de ventas, compuesta por 206 ayudantes y 81 agentes, de una Cooperativa productora Bebidas frutales de la Ciudad de México, en el periodo de 2007-2009. Se empleó el Método de Freeman Modificado para el Diagnóstico Situacional. Resultados: Los factores de riesgo relacionados con accidentes de mano identificados y jerarquizados son: en primer lugar los psicosociales derivados de Organización Laboral (ritmo acelerado de la actividad) y la Condición Insegura (traslado del personal en la defensa trasera del camión); en segundo lugar se encontraron los Ergonómicos (movimientos repetitivos, manejo manual de cargas), junto con el Acto Inseguro (omisión del uso del equipo de protección personal), y la Condición Insegura (tipo de unidad, puerta y material transportado; y falta de capacitación); finalmente en tercer lugar los psicosociales de Organización Laboral (jornada indefinida mínima de 8 horas máxima de 14) y Condición Insegura (objetos punzocortantes en cajas). Conclusiones: Los accidentes de mano constituyen un problema de salud pública importante a nivel nacional e internacional. Es de suma importancia identificar los factores de riesgo que se relacionan con su génesis como son: los factores psicosociales, condiciones inseguras, factores ergonómicos y actos inseguros. Por lo que se considera que estos, se deben buscar intencionadamente en las empresas dedicadas a este rubro de actividades, y evidenciarlos cuando se pretendan disminuir este tipo de accidentes y generar medidas preventivas y correctivas para mejorar la calidad de vida del trabajador y el rendimiento del mismo en sus labores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;58(226): 13-26, ene.-mar. 2012. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103143</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico de factores de riesgo relacionados con la accidentabilidad de mano en trabajadores de una empresa refresquera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51665^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d62</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
