<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154406</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Learning to communicate: family prevention in the local sphere</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The problem of addictions in teenagers today involves certain features that are worsening. The prevalence of intensive patterns of drinking and problematic cannabis use has increased. At the same time, the perceived risk of such drugs is low. Effective preventive measures to reduce risk factors of the consumption problem detected and enhance protective factors are thus required. In this regard, research shows the importance of the family, not only as a protective agent, but also as a modulator of risk behavior of children, so this should be the basis on which the design of programs for prevention of addictions rests. In this context, family prevention program Learn to Communicate, is being presented as a municipal level family prevention program that seeks to promote functional communication between parents and children as a vehicle to improve the emotional bond between them and the importance of evaluating the results of the intervention program presented and the implementation process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vallés, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrosa, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tàpia, Fortunato</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdú, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hoy día, el problema de las adicciones en los adolescentes presenta unas características que lo están agravando. La prevalencia de los patrones de consumo intensivo de alcohol y el consumo problemático de cannabis se ha incrementado. A la vez, la percepción de riesgo de tales drogas es baja. Por ello, se precisan actuaciones preventivas efectivas que reduzcan los factores de riesgo de la problemática de consumo y potencien los factores de protección. Al respecto, las investigaciones ponen de manifiesto la importancia de la familia no sólo como agente de protección, sino también como modulador de las conductas de riesgo de los hijos, por lo que ésta debería ser la base sobre la que descansara el diseño de los programas de prevención de las adicciones. Se presenta el programa Aprender a Comunicar: prevención familiar en el ámbito local que persigue, entre otros objetivos, fomentar la comunicación funcional entre padres e hijos como vehículo para mejorar el vínculo afectivo entre éstos así como la importancia de evaluar los resultados de la intervención y el proceso de implementación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;41(2): 90-105, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aprender a comunicar: prevención familiar en el ámbito local</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3175</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56159^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56098^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35249</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
