<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164748</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of comorbidities in the mortality of patients with stable COPD</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to assess the relationship between comorbidities and all-cause mortality in stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients, in our geographic area. Methods: Prospective, multicenter, longitudinal study of patients with stable COPD. We recorded demographic characteristics, respiratory functional tests, Charlson comorbidity index and hospital anxiety and depression scale. Patients were followed up for 3 years. In the case of death it was investigated to determine the real cause of death. Results: 138 patients were studied with a mean age of 66.3 ± 10.3 years and mean FEV1 of 51.3 ± 16.9%. The mean Charlson index was 4.66 ± 1.57. 17.2% had depression and 12.7% anxiety. Thirteen (9.5%) patients died, 5 of lung cancer, 5 COPD exacerbation, 1 colon cancer, another for acute myocardial infarction (AMI) and another one for congestive heart failure (CHF). In the multivariate analysis the number of comorbidities (HR 1.926; IC 95%: 1.384 - 2.680) and anxiolytic treatment (HR 4.072; IC 95%: 1.106 - 14.987) showed relationship with mortality. Kaplan-Meier suvival plots showed that patients with 2 o more comorbilities, in addition to COPD, have higher mortality than patients with 1 or no comorbidity (35.52 ± 0.2 vs 33 ± 1.3 months, p = 0,039). Conclusions: The prevalence of comorbidities in patients with stable COPD was high. Mortality in these patients is related to the number of comorbidities and anxiolytic treatment. Mortality was higher in patients with 2 o more comorbidilites (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfageme Michavila, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Maldonado, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Campos, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero Montero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnedillo Muñoz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la relación entre las comorbilidades y la mortalidad por cualquier causa en pacientes con EPOC en fase estable, en nuestro ámbito geográfico. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional prospectivo longitudinal multicéntrico de una cohorte de pacientes con EPOC en situación estable. Se recogieron datos demográficos, funcionales respiratorios, índice de comorbilidad de Charlson y escala hospitalaria de ansiedad y depresión. Los pacientes fueron seguidos durante 3 años. En el caso de fallecimiento se indagó para determinar la causa de la muerte. Resultados: Se estudiaron 138 pacientes con una edad media de 66,3 ± 10,3 años y FEV1 medio de 51,3 ± 16,9%. El índice de Charlson medio fue de 4,66 ± 1,57. Presentaban depresión el 17,2% y ansiedad el 12,7%. Fallecieron 13 (9,5%) pacientes, 5 de cáncer de pulmón, 5 por agudización de la EPOC, 1 por carcinoma de colon, otro por infarto agudo de miocardio (IAM) y otro por insuficiencia cardiaca congestiva (ICC). En el análisis multivariado el número de comorbilidades (HR 1,926; IC 95%: 1,384 - 2,680) y la existencia de tratamiento ansiolítico (HR 4,072; IC 95%: 1,106 - 14,987) se asociaron a mayor mortalidad. El análisis mediante curvas de supervivencia de KaplanMeier, mostró que los pacientes con 2 o más comorbilidades, además de la EPOC, presentaban mayor mortalidad que los que tenían una o ninguna (35,52 ± 0,2 vs 33 ± 1,3 meses, p = 0,039). Conclusiones: La prevalencia de comorbilidades en pacientes con EPOC estable fue elevada. La mortalidad de estos pacientes se relacionó con el número de comorbilidades y el tratamiento ansiolítico. La mortalidad fue superior en aquellos pacientes con 2 o más comorbilidades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;29(2): 109-116, jun. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164748</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de las comorbilidades en la mortalidad de pacientes con EPOC estables</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
