<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155116</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of high-sensitivity troponin T after percutaneous coronary intervention in patients with stable coronary artery disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The prognostic value of high-sensitivity troponin T after percutaneous coronary intervention in patients with stable coronary artery disease is unclear. We investigated this clinically relevant question in 3463 consecutive patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention. Methods: This study included patients with stable coronary artery disease and baseline high-sensitivity troponin T below the 99th percentile upper reference limit (0.014 &amp;#956;g/L). High-sensitivity troponin T was measured before and at 6, 12 and 24 hours after the procedure. The primary outcome was all-cause mortality. Results: Patients were divided into a group with peak postprocedural troponin T &amp;#8804; 99th percentile (n = 742), a group with peak postprocedural troponin T &gt; 99th to 5 × 99th percentile (n = 1928), and a group with peak postprocedural troponin T &gt; 5 × 99th percentile upper reference limit (n = 793). Advanced age, smaller body mass index, baseline troponin level, complex lesions, bifurcation lesions and stented length were independently associated with elevated troponin T levels after the procedure. The median follow-up was 15.5 months. There were 56 deaths: 5 deaths (1.7%) among patients with peak postprocedural troponin T &amp;#8804; 99th percentile, 35 deaths (4.5%) among patients with peak postprocedural troponin T &gt; 99th to 5 × 99th percentile and 16 deaths (4.3%) among patients with peak postprocedural troponin T &gt; 5 × 99th percentile upper reference limit (hazard ratio = 1.50; 95% confidence interval, 1.01-2.25; P = .047). After adjustment, peak postprocedural troponin T level was not independently associated with mortality after percutaneous coronary intervention (P = .094). Conclusions: In patients with stable coronary artery disease and without elevated baseline high-sensitivity troponin T, elevated high-sensitivity troponin T level after percutaneous coronary intervention was not associated with postprocedural mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Braun, Siegmund</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lohaus, Raphaela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fusaro, Massimiliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cassese, Salvatore</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lahmann, Anna L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laugwitz, Karl-Ludwig</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ndrepepa, Gjin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schunkert, Heribert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayer, Katharina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kastrati, Adnan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Está por clarificar el valor pronóstico de la troponina T de alta sensibilidad tras una intervención coronaria percutánea en pacientes con enfermedad coronaria estable. Esta cuestión clínicamente relevante se ha investigado en 3.463 pacientes consecutivos a los que se practicó una intervención coronaria percutánea. Métodos: En este estudio se incluyó a pacientes con enfermedad coronaria estable y un valor basal de troponina T de alta sensibilidad menor que el límite superior de referencia del percentil 99 (0,014 &amp;#956;g/l). Se determinó la troponina T de alta sensibilidad antes de la intervención y luego al cabo de 6, 12 y 24 h. El objetivo principal fue la mortalidad por cualquier causa. Resultados: Se clasificó a los pacientes en un grupo con un valor máximo de troponina T tras la intervención &amp;#8804; percentil 99 (n = 742), un grupo con un valor máximo de troponina T tras la intervención entre &gt; percentil 99 y 5 veces el percentil 99 (n = 1.928) y un grupo con un valor máximo de troponina T tras la intervención &gt; 5 veces el percentil 99 (n = 793). La edad avanzada, el índice de masa corporal más bajo, el valor de troponina basal, las lesiones complejas, las lesiones en bifurcación y la longitud del stent se asociaron de manera independiente a concentraciones de troponina T aumentadas después de la intervención. La mediana de seguimiento fue de 15,5 meses. Hubo 56 muertes: 5 pacientes (1,7%) con valor máximo de troponina T tras la intervención &amp;#8804; percentil 99, 35 (4,5%) con valor máximo de troponina T tras la intervención entre &gt; percentil 99 y 5 veces el percentil 99, y 16 (4,3%) del grupo con valor máximo de troponina T tras la intervención &gt; 5 veces el percentil 99 (hazard ratio = 1,50; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,01-2,25; p = 0,047). Tras el ajuste, el valor máximo de troponina T tras el procedimiento no mostró asociación independiente con la mortalidad tras la intervención coronaria percutánea (p = 0,094). Conclusiones: En los pacientes con enfermedad coronaria estable y sin elevación basal de la troponina T de alta sensibilidad, la elevación de esta después de una intervención coronaria percutánea no se asoció a mayor mortalidad tras el procedimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;69(8): 764-753, ago. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155116</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de la troponina T de alta sensibilidad tras intervención coronaria percutánea en pacientes con enfermedad coronaria estable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14739^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54536^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55037^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
