<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14650</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sociosemantic analiysis in social psicology: a conceptual proposal and a technique for its implementation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of &#145;Sociosemantic Analysis&#146; is to reveal, in an intrinsically interconnected way, the communication structure of a given social group and the semantic content of that structure. As its name suggests, &#145;Socio-semantics&#146; interweaves in a single conceptual frame the two fundamental dimensions of human communication: people (the who aspect of communication) and content (the what aspect of communication). From a socio-semantic point of view individuals communicate semantically through concepts, and concepts &#145;communicate&#146; socially through individuals. Individuals are (socio-) semantically connected (they are potentially interacting units) through the concepts that they possess in common; and concepts are socio (-semantically) connected through the individuals who share them. The connectivities between concepts or individuals can be processed through nonmetric multidimensional scaling which generates sociosemantic plots which reveal the social and semantic structure of the social group in question. The paper shows the application of sociosemantic analysis to the study of one hundred adolescents selfperception patterns (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Martínez, Capitolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos la técnica del "Análisis Sociosemántico" cuyo objetivo es revelar la estructura de comunicación de un grupo social dado y el contenido semántico de esa estructura de manera intrínsecamente interconectada. La "socio-semántica" entreteje en una marco conceptual unitario las dos dimensiones fundamentales de la comunicación humana: la gente que comunica (el aspecto quién de la comunicación) y el contenido comunicado (el aspecto qué de la comunicación). Los individuos se encuentran (socio-) semánticamente conectados (son unidades potencialmente interactuantes) a través de los conceptos que poseen en común; y los conceptos se hallan socio (-semánticamente) conectados a través de los individuos que los comparten. La proximidad entre individuos o entre conceptos (conectividad semántica o social) puede ser procesada mediante un escalamiento multidimensional no métrico cuyo resultado revelará las estructuras semánticas y sociales del grupo estudiado. Se ofrece, en este artículo, el resumen de una aplicación del análisis sociosemántico al estudio de los sistemas de autopercepción de cien adolescentes. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(3): 451-457, ago. 2000. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14650</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El análisis sociosemántico en la psicología social: una propuesta teórica y una técnica para su aplicación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15110</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
