<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73360</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perioperative mortality in diabetic patients after non traumatic lower extremity amputations in Madrid from 1997 to 2005</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Chronic diabetic complications greatly affect thecost in health, economic productivity, with an emphasis on diabeticfoot. Objectives: Analysis of mortality trends and related factorsassociated with LEA.                                Material and methods: A retrospective observational study of LEA in Madrid between 1997 and 2005. Documentarysource: MBDS (discharge minimum basic data set). We selected cases that included an 84.1X procedure and 250.XX diagnosis (ICD-9-CM). Minor amputation was defined as distal to theankle joint and a perioperative death that occurred during hospitalization.The trend of mortality was assessed using joinpoint regressionanaly sis and expressed as percentage of annual change (PAC). We studied the risk of death by multivariate logistic regression using the independent variables age, sex, type of amputationand diabetes.                                  Results: During the study period there were 278 deaths (7.3%) in diabetic patients. Mortality trends: PAC 1.99% (&#150;2.7 to 6.9) was not significant. Risk of death (OR; 95%CI), patients over 65 years old (3.16; 2.03-4.91; p= 0.0001) and major LEA (2.75; 2.08-3.64; p= 0.0001).                                                  Conclusions: The perioperativemortality of LEA remains high and showed no downward trend duringthe study period with an increased risk of death for adults over65 years and major LEA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albarracín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Patiño, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molino, Á. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel, P. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Cruz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las complicaciones crónicas de la diabetes condicionanlos costes relacionados con la salud, la productividad y la economía,entre las que destacan el pie diabético. Objetivos: Análisis de latendencia y los factores relacionados con la mortalidad por amputaciónno traumática de miembros inferiores (AMI).                                                        Material y método: Estudio observacional retrospectivo de las AMI ocurridas en Madridentre 1997 y 2005. Fuente documental: Conjunto Mínimo Básicode Datos. Se seleccionaron las altas con un procedimiento 84.1X y undiagnóstico 250.XX (CIE-9-MC). Se defi nió amputación menor comodistal a la articulación tarsometatarsiana. La tendencia de la mortalidadse evaluó mediante modelos segmentados de regresión de Poisson yse expresó como porcentaje anual de cambio (PAC). Se estudió elriesgo de muerte mediante regresión logística multivariante para lassiguientes variables independientes: edad, sexo, tipo de amputación ydiabetes.                                                  Resultados: Se produjeron 278 muertes en diabéticos (7,3%). En la evolución de la mortalidad se obtuvo un PAC del 1,99% (intervalo de confi anza del 95%: &#150;2,7 a 6,9), no signifi cativo. El riesgo de mortalidad (odds ratio; intervalo de confi anza del 95%) fue en mayores de 65 años de 3,16 (2,03-4,91; p= 0,0001) y en la AMI mayorde 2,75 (2,08-3,64; p= 0,0001). Conclusiones: La mortalidadperioperatoria de la AMI permanece elevada y no muestran tendenciadescendente en el periodo de estudio con un mayor riesgo para losmayores de 65 años y AMI mayor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;25(4): 315-319, jul.-ago. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad perioperatoria en pacientes diabéticos sometidos a amputación no traumática de miembros inferiores en la Comunidad de Madrid de 1997 a 2005</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3948^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
