<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157812</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health education for prevalent problems in prison, Ocaña-I proyect (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Pilot project focusing on the implementation and evaluation of a health education (HE) program for inmates of the prison of Ocaña I (Spain). The objective was to analyze the intentions for change in health habits and perceptions, and to assess whether the HE-program had differential effects depending on whether the participants belonged to the PAIEM or not and their socio-demographic characteristics. Methodology: The participants were 65 men, who answered an ad hoc questionnaire at the end of each session. Data analysis applied was univariate and bivariate (one-way ANOVA, t-test for Equality of Means and Chi-Square test). Results: The average rating of the sessions was 3.51 out of 4 (SD = 0.62). The percentage of positive answers about the intention to adopt healthy habits was higher among non-PAIEM subjects (84.8%) than among those who were part of this program (57.9%). All subjects having a couple indicated an intention to change negative habits, compared to 67.3% for those without a couple. The percentage of subjects who said that their perception on the issue had changed was highest among those without education (89.7%) than among those with education (61.5%). Conclusions: The evaluation of implanted HE-program implemented in the Ocaña I prison was very positive, there are differences between subjects belonging to the PAIEM and those who do not (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maestre-Miquel, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antolín, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabala-Baños, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Proyecto piloto centrado en la implantación y evaluación de un programa de Educación para la Salud (EpS) en internos del Centro Penitenciario Ocaña I (España). El objetivo fue analizar las intenciones de cambio en los hábitos de salud y en la percepción, así como evaluar si el programa de EpS tenía efectos diferenciales dependiendo de si los participantes pertenecían o no al Programa de Atención Integral al Enfermo Mental (PAIEM) y de sus características sociodemográficas. Metodología: Los participantes fueron 65 varones que respondieron a un cuestionario ad hoc al finalizar cada sesión. Los análisis fueron univariantes y bivariantes (ANOVA de un factor, prueba t y test de independencia Chi-Cuadrado). Resultados: La valoración media de las sesiones fue de 3,51 sobre 4 (DE = 0,62). Las respuestas afirmativas sobre la intención de adoptar hábitos saludables fueron mayores entre los sujetos no pertenecientes al PAIEM (84,8%) que entre los que sí formaban parte del mismo (57,9%). Todos los sujetos con pareja indicaron tener intención de cambiar los hábitos negativos, frente al 67,3% entre aquellos sin pareja. El cambio en la percepción sobre el tema fue más alto entre los que no tenían estudios (89,7%) que entre aquellos que sí los tenían (61,5%). Conclusiones: La evaluación del programa de EpS implantado en el Centro Penitenciario Ocaña I fue muy positiva, existiendo diferencias entre los sujetos pertenecientes al PAIEM y los que no (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;18(3): 86-94, nov.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157812</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Educacion para la salud en los problemas prevalentes del medio penitenciario, proyecto en Ocaña-I (España)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
