<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94064</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of the effectiveness of isokinetic vs isometric therapeutic exercise in patients with osteoarthritis of knee</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Osteoarthritis is a chronic joint disease; isometric exercise leads to the development of mechanical work and isokinetic exercise leads to better joint mobility. Objectives. To compare the effectiveness of isometric versus isokinetic therapeutic exercises in patients with knee osteoarthritis. Material and methods. Quasiexperimental study in a population of 45 to 75 year old patients with a diagnosis of knee osteoarthritis. Group 1 (experimental) was put under isokinetic exercises and group 2 (control) under isometric exercises. The sample size was of 33 patients per group; the allocation to the experimentation or control group was nonrandom, but stratified by degrees of knee osteoarthritis. The effectiveness of the exercise was measured in three dimensions: muscle strength, joint range and pain. The intervention lasted eight weeks and the physical activity was carried out every third day. The statistical analysis included averages, standard deviation, percentage, Chi square test, z test for two populations, t test for two independent populations and twin t test. Results. The analysis of muscle strength comparing the categories independently demonstrates differences at 8 weeks; 33.3% of the isokinetic exercise is in the normal category and 15.2% in the isometric exercise (p= 0.04). There was not difference of joint range between groups, despite finding a stage I range in 100.0% of the isokinetic group and 97.0% in the isometric (p&gt; 0.05) group. Pain was milder in the isokinetic exercise group at 8 weeks (p= 0.01). Conclusions. Isokinetic exercises have a greater effectiveness than isometric exercises for muscle strength and pain in patients with knee osteoarthritis. However, other studies with randomized designs are needed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galicia Rodríguez, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Daza, Emma Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarreal Ríos, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Maya, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Rosa, Uganet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velásquez Tlapanco, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En el tratamiento de la artrosis se emplea tanto el ejercicio isométrico como el ejercicio isocinético, sin embargo, no queda claro cuál de los tipos de ejercicio es más eficaz en el manejo terapéutico. Objetivos. Comparar la eficacia del ejercicio terapéutico isométrico vs ejercicio terapéutico isocinético en pacientes con artrosis de rodilla. Material y métodos. Estudio cuasiexperimental en población 45 a 75 años de edad con diagnóstico de artrosis de rodilla. El grupo 1 (experimental) sometido a ejercicios isocinético y el grupo 2 (control) sometido a ejercicios isométricos. El tamaño de la muestra fue de 33 por grupo, la asignación al grupo de experimentación o control fue no aleatoria, pero se estratificó por grados de artrosis de rodilla. La eficacia del ejercicio se midió en tres dimensiones: fuerza muscular, rango articular y dolor. La intervención tuvo una duración de ocho semanas y la actividad física se realizó cada tercer día. El análisis estadístico incluyó promedios, desviación estándar, porcentajes, prueba de chi cuadrada, prueba de z para dos poblaciones, prueba de t para dos poblaciones independientes y prueba de t pareada. Resultados. El análisis de la fuerza muscular comparando las categorías de forma independiente demuestra diferencia a las 8 semanas, en la categoría normal se encuentra el 33,3% del ejercicio isocinético y el 15,2% del ejercicio isométrico (p=0,04). No se encontró diferencia del rango articular entre los grupos, no obstante, el rango articular fue grado I en el 100,0% del grupo isocinético y 97,0% del isométrico (p&gt;0,05). El dolor fue menor en el grupo de ejercicio isocinético a las 8 semanas (p=0,01). Conclusiones. El estudio sugiere que los ejercicios isocinéticos tienen una mayor efectividad que los ejercicios isométricos para la fuerza y dolor en el paciente con artrosis de rodilla. Son necesarios más estudios que confirmen estos resultados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);8(1): 10-14, ene.-feb.2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94064</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la eficacia ejercicio terapéutico isocinético vs isométrico en pacientes con artrosis de rodilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
