<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115709</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social dependency in old age: poor training, pension and housing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study is conducted in a geriatric institution in the province of Alicante (Spain) from in-depth interviews with 24 elderly people to analyze, among others, the causes that led him there. The information is processed using qualitative techniques and obtained the following results: except for two of them, they all are healthy and may have an independent life. Pensions are below 600 Euros, they do not have an own house and they have a lack of family support. Therefore, they cannot live outside the institution. Most respondents have been poor and remain like that. Poor and homeless people, who have been socially excluded from the culture, work, housing and at the end of their lives, even family. Elderly can be considered fragile from the social point of view, for its poor condition. We conclude that in this population poverty is the cause of institutionalization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maciá Soler, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ors Montenegro, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio que presentamos está realizado en una institución geriátrica de la provincia de Alicante (España), a partir de entrevistas en profundidad realizadas a 24 personas mayores, con objeto de analizar, entre otras, las causas que les llevaron allí. La información se procesa mediante técnicas cualitativas y se obtienen los siguientes resultados: a excepción de dos de ellos, la totalidad gozan de salud y podrían tener una vida independiente. Perciben pensiones por debajo de 600 euros, carecen además de vivienda en propiedad y de apoyo familiar, por ello, no pueden vivir fuera de la institución. La mayoría de los entrevistados han sido pobres y siguen siendolo. Pobres e indigentes, socialmente excluidos de la cultura, del trabajo, de la vivienda y al final de sus vidas, hasta de la familia. Pueden considerarse ancianos frágiles desde el punto de vista social, por su condición de pobres. Se concluye que en esta población la pobreza es la causa de institucionalización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(32): 147-162, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115709</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dependencia social en la vejez: pobres en formación, en pensión y en vivienda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50334^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50334^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11641^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11641^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
