<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91708</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non invasive home control and follow &#150;up program in pediatric patients. A multidisciplinary Unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Non-invasive mechanical ventilation is a new respiratory support therapy modality in which it is not necessary to invade the airway with tracheostomy or endotracheal intubation. It is used in patients with acute or chronic respiratory failure as a less aggressive alternative to conventional mechanical ventilation, seeking to avoid the complications associated to endotracheal intubation and to improve the patient´s quality of life. During the last 5-10 years, its use has become generalized, largely due to the medical and technological advances that have contributed to the increased survival of the critical patients, to the better diagnosis and knowledge of diseases that occur with increased resistances of the upper airway or with central and/or peripheral hypoventilation and to the development of new easily used apparatus adapted to home treatment. The creation of a control and follow-up program of non-invasive home ventilation in pediatric patients will produce psychosocial and economic benefits for the health care system. In this review, we are going to mention the out-patient and home treatment of children with chronic respiratory failure and the need to create specialized multidisciplinary intervention units in this type of patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cimadevilla, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berroya, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustinza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ventilación mecánica no invasiva constituye una nueva modalidad de terapia de soporte respiratorio en la que no se precisa invadir, mediante traqueostomía o intubación endotraqueal, la vía aérea. Se utiliza en pacientes con fallo respiratorio agudo o crónico como alternativa menos agresiva a la ventilación mecánica convencional, buscando evitar las complicaciones asociadas a la intubación endotraqueal y mejorar la calidad de vida del enfermo. Durante los últimos 5-10 años se ha generalizado su uso, debido en gran parte a los avances médicos y tecnológicos que han contribuido al aumento de supervivencia del paciente crítico, al mejor diagnóstico y conocimiento de enfermedades que cursan con aumento de resistencias de la vía aérea superior o con hipoventilación central o periférica así como al desarrollo de nuevos aparatos de fácil manejo adaptados al tratamiento domiciliario. La creación de un programa de control y seguimiento de ventilación no invasiva domiciliaria en pacientes pediátricos va a producir mejoras psicosociales para el paciente y su familia y beneficios económicos para el sistema de salud. En esta revisión nos vamos a referir al tratamiento ambulatorio y domiciliario de niños con insuficiencia respiratoria crónica y a la necesidad de creación de unidades especializadas multidisciplinares de intervención en este tipo de enfermos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;66(2): 127-135, mar.-abr. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91708</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa de control y seguimiento de ventilación no invasiva domiciliaria en pacientes pediátricos. Unidad multidisciplinar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
