<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60079</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bibliographic references of the articles of the Boletín de Pediatría: why don't we cite our colleagues?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know the most important characteristics of the Boletín de Pediatría bibliographic references. Material and methods: Review of 2005 to 2008 Boletín de Pediatría bibliographic references, without supplements. We studied: total reference number by article, less than 5years references, Spanish author references, electronic references, &#147;no scientific journal&#148; references, and references of the different paediatric Spanish journals. Results: We analysed 171 articles with 3316 total bibliographic references. The reference number mean by article was 19. The 5 year previous reference percentage was52%, the Spanish reference was 29.7% , the electronic reference was 5% and the &#147;no scientific journal&#148; was 18,9%.From 3,316 total references, 9.2% was from paediatric Spanish journals: 2.3% from Boletin de Pediatría and 5% from Anales de Pediatría. Conclusions: The bibliographic references from Boletín de Pediatría manage less than 30% of Spanish references and only 9% from Spanish paediatric journals. The references from our own Boletin de Pediatría are less than 3% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morán Poladura, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Avello, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Arias, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, EM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Sánchez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las características más importantes de las citas bibliográficas de los artículos publicados en el Boletín de Pediatría. Material y Métodos: Revisión de las citas bibliográficas de los artículos publicados durante los años 2005 a 2008en el Boletín de Pediatría, excluyendo suplementos. Se estudiaron: número de citas por artículo, número de citas de los5 años previos a la publicación del artículo, número de citas de autores españoles, número de citas electrónicas, número de citas que no fueran de revista científica y número de citas de las distintas revistas pediátricas españolas. Resultados: Se analizaron 171 artículos con un total de3316 citas bibliográficas. La media fue de 19 citas por artículo. El 52% de las citas eran de los 5 años previos al artículo, el 29,7% eran citas de autores españoles, el 5% eran citas electrónicas y el 18,9% eran citas de fuente diferente a revistas científicas. De las 3.316 citas totales, el 9,2% eran citas de revistas españolas de pediatría: 2,3% del Boletín de Pediatría y 5% de Anales de Pediatría. Conclusiones: La bibliografía de los artículos publicados en el Boletín de Pediatría utiliza menos del 30% de citas españolas y sólo un 9% de citas de revistas pediátricas españolas. Las citas de nuestro propio Boletín no llegan al 3% del total (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;49(208): 105-109, abr.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Citas bibliográficas de los artículos del Boletín de Pediatría: ¿por qué no citamos a nuestros colegas?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50123</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
