<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122203</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic guide to critical burn patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Burn injuries are defined as the destruction of skin tissue under the effects of a thermal, electrical, chemical or radioactive agent. They can cause local injuries, with no systemic effect, but in certain cases, considered as «critical burn patients», they can produce severe and immediate systemic injuries, thus making it necessary to address care from a comprehensive perspective in order to achieve a satisfactory evolution. With this in mind, as nursing staff we must consider the need to review the treatments and nursing care we are applying to critical burn patients, in order to prevent the onset of complications that might lead to unwanted consequences or even the death of the patient, and eventually unifying criteria of nursing care. The main goal of this guide is to provide an efficient and easy to use working tool that is suitable for adult burn patients, thus making it easier for nurses to update knowledge and decision making (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Píriz-Campos, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Espinosa, Noelia M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Postigo Mota, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las quemaduras se definen como la destrucción de los tejidos bajo el efecto de un agente térmico, eléctrico, químico o radiactivo. Pueden causar lesiones locales, sin afectación sistémica, pero, en determinados pacientes, que consideramos «quemados críticos», pueden originar lesiones sistémicas graves e inmediatas para el afectado, lo que hace necesario abordar su atención desde una perspectiva integral para su buena evolución. Partiendo de esta idea, como personal de enfermería, debemos plantearnos la necesidad de revisar qué tratamientos y cuidados realizamos a los pacientes quemados críticos, para prevenir la aparición de complicaciones que pudieran ocasionarles secuelas o incluso la muerte, con el fin de unificar criterios de actuación enfermera. El objetivo principal de esta guía es realizar una herramienta de trabajo ágil, de fácil manejo y adecuada para pacientes quemados adultos, que facilite a los profesionales de enfermería la actualización de conocimientos y la toma de decisiones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(2): 111-114, feb. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122203</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía terapéutica en el paciente quemado crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
