<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056683</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To carry out a bibliometric analysis of the Farmacia        Hospitalaria journal from 2001 to 2006.        Method: A retrospective analysis of all of the articles published        in Farmacia Hospitalaria from 2001-2006 was performed        and the main bibliometric indicators for production, circulation,        distribution and sales were calculated.        Results: 416 articles by 1,515 authors were analysed. Original        articles were the most predominant with a growth of 30%.        There were 4.6 ± 2.3 authors per article. The Community of        Valencia, Catalonia, Madrid and Andalusia were the autonomous        communities with the highest levels of production. Four authors        had a productivity index of &gt; 1, with one group of 15 authors        having an index of &gt; 0.75. Only 14% of articles were included in        presentations to congresses and 17% had funding. The subject        matters of drug treatment and safety had the highest production        levels. The publication delay remained constant. There was a circulation        index of 0.74 in Medline.        Conclusions: Farmacia Hospitalaria maintained or        improved their bibliometric indicators between 2001 and 2006.        There has been an increase in the publication of original articles        and letters to the editor over recent years and this increase was        in line with the journal&#146;s strategies. There has also been a        decrease in literature reviews. There were some generational        changes among the authors although the main authors        remained the same. The subject matters and geographical origin        of the authors corresponded to areas with the largest development        of the specialty in Spain</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ordovás, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferriols, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artacho, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clopés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Análisis bibliométrico de la revista Farmacia Hospitalaria        en el periodo 2001-2006.        Método: Análisis retrospectivo de todos los artículos publicados        en Farmacia Hospitalaria durante el periodo 2001-2006 y        cálculo de los principales indicadores bibliométricos de producción,        circulación, dispersión y consumo.        Resultados: Se analizan 416 artículos firmados por 1.515        autores. Predominan los originales con un crecimiento del 30%.        El número de autores por artículo fue de 4,6 ± 2,3. Las comunidades        autónomas con mayor producción fueron la Comunidad        Valenciana, Cataluña, Madrid y Andalucía. Cuatro autores tienen        un índice de productividad &gt; 1, destacando un grupo de 15 autores        que lo tienen &gt; 0,75. Sólo el 14% de los artículos procedían        de presentaciones a congresos y el 17% tenía financiación. Las        áreas temáticas con mayor producción son farmacoterapia y seguridad.        La demora en la publicación se mantiene constante. El índice        de circulación en Medline fue de 0,74.        Conclusiones: Farmacia Hospitalaria ha mantenido o        mejorado sus indicadores bibliométricos entre los años 2001 y        2006. Se detecta un aumento en la publicación de originales y        cartas al director en los últimos años de acuerdo con las estrategias        de la revista, así como una disminución de las revisiones        literarias. Se detecta una cierta renovación generacional en los        autores aunque se mantienen los mismos grandes productores.        Las áreas temáticas y la procedencia geográfica de los autores        se corresponden con las de mayor desarrollo de la especialidad        en España</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;31(3): 141-149, may.-jun.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056683</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis bibliométrico de la revista Farmacia Hospitalaria (2001-2006)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
