<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81002</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to analyse the inluenceof dietary calcium during pregnancy on Zn levels in maternalwhole blood (ZnWB).Methods: A group of 85 healthy pregnant women (meanage: 22,0 ± 6,0 years) were evaluated at &#147;Diego Paroissien&#148;Hospital since gestational age of: 19,6 ± 6,6 weeks (To) to,34,7 ± 2,8 weeks (Tf). At To mean daily dietary intake ofcalcium (CaI) and zinc (ZnI) was calculated. Women weredivided into three groups consuming daily a supplementof 600 mg of calcium as dried whole milk (GM, n=20);calcium citrate (GCit, n=12) or calcium carbonate (GCar,n=27). A group didn&#146;t accepted any treatment (GNt n=26).At To, T1 (end of 2º trimester) and Tf, hemoglobin andZnWB was determined.Results: Mean ± SD (mg/d): To: CaI: 579 ± 382; ZnI:6,5 ± 2,8. At To and T1 there were no significant differencesin ZWB; however, at Tf, GM decreased significantlyregarding the GNt, GCit and GCar groups (4,06 ± 1,08 vs5,64 ± 0,63; 6,58 ± 0,98; 6,47 ± 0,60, respectively;p&lt; 0.0001).Conclusions: This study shows that milk calcium intake, butnot calcium citrate and calcium carbonate, decreased ZnWBduring pregnancy, suggesting Zn-Ca interaction(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Carlos R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portela, MAría L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Laura B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Weisstaub, Adriana R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: estudiar los niveles de Zn en sangre (ZnSE)durante la gestación y la influencia de la ingesta de calcio.Métodos: 85 gestantes, clínicamente sanas (22,0 ± 6,0años), atendidas en un Hospital del Gran Buenos Airesdesde la edad gestacional de 19,6 ± 6,6 semanas (To).Se calculó la ingesta de calcio (ICa) y de Zinc (IZn) y sedividieron en grupos que recibieron diariamente 600 mgde calcio de : leche en polvo (GL, n=20); citrato de calcio(GCit, n=12) ó carbonato de calcio (GCar, n=27). Ungrupo no aceptó tratamiento (GNs, n=26). A To, al finaldel segundo trimestre (T1) y a Tf (34,7 ± 2,8 semanas)se determinó en sangre entera: hemoglobina (Hb) y Zn.Resultados: promedio ± DE (mg/d): To: ICa: 579 ± 382;IZn: 6,5 ± 2,8.ZnSE (&amp;#956;g/mL), a To y T1, no presentó diferencias significativasentre los cuatro grupos. Sin embargo, a Tf, GL disminuyósignificativamente (4,06 ± 1,08) (p&lt;0,0001) en relación aGNs (5,64 ± 0,63), GCit (6,58 ± 0,98) y GCar (6,47 ± 0,60).Conclusiones: el calcio lácteo disminuyó los valores de ZnSEdurante la gestación, sugiriendo interacción Zn-Ca, mientrasque el del citrato y carbonato no presentaron ese efecto(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;13(2): 58-64, abr.-jun.2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81002</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Zinc en sangre durante la gestación y su relación con la ingesta de calcio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15427^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2293^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3504^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
