<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118095</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Population parameters for first-trimester combined screening in the Ibero-American Fetaltest Multicenter Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the theoretical distribution of Down syndrome (DS) markers in the combined test (nuchal translucency [NT], PAPP-A and free beta-HCG) in a population of pregnant Ibero-American women recruited by the Fetaltest multicenter study, and to evaluate the theoretical ef&amp;#64257;ciency of screening with the use of these population parameters. Materials and methods: We retrospectively analyzed the combined test markers in 19,995 single consecutive pregnancies with unaffected fetuses and 72 fetuses with DS. We obtained the population parameters that de&amp;#64257;ne the theoretical distributions of the markers (mean, standard deviation and correlations) in affected and unaffected fetuses. A standard modeling technique ewas employed to analyze the ef&amp;#64257;ciency of the combined screening test by using the estimated parameters in comparison with those currently used .Results: We observed a signi&amp;#64257;cant reduction in the standard deviation of Log MoM NT with respect to the parameters currently in use in unaffected fetuses, with a statistically signi&amp;#64257;cant reducing trend as pregnancy progressed. The ef&amp;#64257;ciency of combined screening evaluated by modeling techniques improved with the use of the estimated parameters, yielding a detection rate of 90.5% for a &amp;#64257;xed false-positive rate of 5% compared with 86.1%, obtained with the parameters currently in use. Conclusions: Updating the population parameters of the markers with those obtained from our own population could noticeably improve the ef&amp;#64257;ciency of screening for DS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santiago Blázquez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Corpas , D. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la distribución teórica de marcadores de síndrome de Down (SD) del test combinado (Nuchal Translucency [NT], PAPP-A y free-beta-HCG) en una población de gestantes iberoamericanas reclutadas mediante el estudio multicéntrico Fetaltest, y evaluar la eficiencia teórica del cribado con el uso de tales parámetros poblacionales. Material y métodos Se analizan retrospectivamente los marcadores del test combinado en 19.995 gestantes simples consecutivas con fetos no afectados y 72 con fetos afectados por SD. Se obtuvieron los parámetros poblacionales que definen las distribuciones teóricas de los marcadores (media, desviación estándar y correlaciones) en fetos afectados y no afectados. Se analizó, mediante técnica estándar de modelado, la eficiencia del cribado combinado usando los parámetros poblacionales estimados en comparación con los usados actualmente. Resultados Se observó una importante reducción de la SD de Log MoM NT en fetos no afectados respecto a los parámetros actualmente en uso, con una tendencia estadísticamente significativa a la reducción con el avance de la gestación. La eficiencia del cribado combinado evaluada mediante modelo mejoró con el uso de los parámetros estimados, obteniéndose una tasa de detección de un 90,5% para una tasa de falsos positiva fija del 5%, frente al 86,1% que se obtendría con los parámetros actualmente en uso. Conclusiones La actualización de los parámetros poblacionales de los marcadores con los obtenidos de nuestra propia población podría mejorar sensiblemente la eficiencia del cribado de SD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);41(1): 2-8, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118095</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parámetros poblacionales para el cribado combinado del primer trimestre en el estudio multicéntrico iberoamericano Fetaltest</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32806^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38800^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11707</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
