<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92323</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic use of monoclonal antibodies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The utilization of therapies based on monoclonal antibodies has supposed a great advance in the clinical practice. They have a diverse field of use, including diagnostic and therapeutic applications. As treatment, the most benefited has been the oncology and immune system diseases.This is an area in continuous growth, so much for the appearance of new medicaments, since for the extension of indications of the already existing ones. This review summarizes the most important pharmacological characteristics of the monoclonal antibodies commercialized in our country. It centres principally on the authorized indications, dosing, adverse events of great clinical relevancy and important considerations for his correct administration. Also there is realized a brief note of the indications of the monoclonal antibodies authorized by the European agency of the medicine (EMEA) and that are in different phases of the process of commercialization(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Ramos, S. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Poza, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Díaz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilización de terapias basadas en anticuerpos monoclonales ha supuesto un gran avance en la práctica clínica. Tienen un ámbito de utilización muy diverso, incluyendo aplicaciones diagnósticas y terapéuticas principalmente. En cuanto a su uso como tratamiento, las áreas más beneficiadas con su descubrimiento han sido la oncología y las enfermedades del sistema inmune.Se trata de un área en continuo crecimiento, tanto por la aparición de nuevos fármacos, como por la ampliación de indicaciones de los ya existentes. Esta revisión resume las características farmacológicas más importantes de los anticuerpos monoclonales comercializados en nuestro país. Se centra principalmente en la utilidad terapeútica, dosificación, eventos adversos de gran relevancia clínica y consideraciones importantes para su correcta administración. También se realiza un breve apunte de las indicaciones de los anticuerpos monoclonales autorizados por la agencia europea del medicamento (EMEA) y que se encuentran en distintas fases del proceso de comercialización(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;52(3): 46-57, jul.-sept. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92323</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización terapéutica de los anticuerpos monoclonales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7335^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
