<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146144</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vitamin D and its relation with the anatomical location of hip fracture in Chilean older adults hospitalized</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: in older adults, deficit of Vitamin D and hip fractures are common. There exists relationships between both conditions, and it have been shown that supplementation of Vitamin D improve prognosis of hip fractures. In the case of Chile, information about relationship between Vitamin D and hip fractures is scarce. Objective: quantify plasma levels of vitamin D and relate them to the anatomical location of hip fracture. Methods: cross-sectional study. 222 Chilean adults &gt;=60 years, hospitalized for hip fracture between June, 2014 and June, 2015. We use data of medical records about gender, age, seasonality and anatomical location of hip fracture (intra and extracapsular). We measure plasmatic levels of Vitamin D (PLVD) and glomerular filtration rate (GFR) (MDRD-6). Kolmogorov-Smirnov test and non-parametric test were used. For determine relations between PLVD and anatomical location we use linear regression. Results: there was a predominance of women (80.6%). The average age was 80.7 years (SD=7.8). Intracapsular hip fractures were 43.2%. 80% of the sample presents Vitamin D in deficitary levels (n = 180). PLVD average was 13.3 ng/cc (SD=6.7), in subjects with intracapsular fractures were significantly lower (p&lt;0.001). Conclusions: PLVD in subjects with hip fracture should be monitored, as there are differences according to anatomical location of the fracture. This precedent could favor the treatment and recovery of subjects presenting for the first time hip fracture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Herrera, Ramona</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez Leiva, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dinamarca Montecinos, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Agüero, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: en los adultos mayores son frecuentes el déficit de vitamina D y las fracturas de cadera (FC). Existe relación entre ambas condiciones, demostrándose que la suplementación de vitamina D mejora el pronóstico de las FC. En el caso de Chile, existe escasa información sobre la relación entre vitamina D y FC. Objetivo: cuantificar los niveles plasmáticos de vitamina D (NPVD) y relacionarlos con la ubicación anatómica de la FC. Métodos: estudio transversal. 222 adultos mayores chilenos &gt;=60 años hospitalizados por FC entre junio de 2014 y junio de 2015. Se utilizaron los datos de ficha clínica de género, edad, estacionalidad y ubicación anatómica (FIC = intra, FEC = extracapsular) de la FC. Se midió NPVD y velocidad de filtrado glomerular (VFG) (MDRD- 6). Se utilizaron la prueba de Kolmogorov-Smirnov y pruebas no paramétricas. Para determinar la relación entre NPVD y el tipo de fractura se usó regresión lineal. Resultados: hubo predominio de mujeres (80,6%), la edad promedio fue 80,7 años (DE=7,8) y se encontró 43,2% de FIC. Los NPVD promedio fueron 13,3 ng/cc (DE=6,7); los sujetos con FIC tienen 4,52 ng/cc menos de vitamina D que aquellos con FEC (p&lt;0,001). El 80% de la muestra tuvo déficit de vitamina D. Conclusiones: los NPVD son generalizadamente deficitarios en los sujetos con FC, y estos valores son menores en los portadores de FIC. Este antecedente podría favorecer el tratamiento y recuperación de los sujetos que presentan por primera vez una FC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2777-2782, dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vitamina D y su relación con la ubicación anatómica de la fractura de cadera en adultos mayores chilenos hospitalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51205^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
