<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111641</identifier>
<setSpec>0367-2743</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The quality and purity of DNA ensures the success of molecular studies, there are many scientifics jobs that are reported obtaining genetic material contained in paraffin-embedded tissue, this time we present our experience to obtain DNA from lymph and nasal mucus slides smears encodings from   1 to 5, from multibacillary leprosy patients, by using the chelating resin Chelex-100. The quality of the extracted DNA is observed in the amplification product of the polymerase chain reaction in wich we amplified segments of the genome of M. leprae in the position 14676 (with size of 180 bp). All amplified DNA and its quality is comparable with that obtained by other  authors in similar studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Entenza Pérez, Anayma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Fuentes, Jenny</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brum Fontes, Amanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Moreno, Odelaisy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armas, Yaxier de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lugo Suárez, Odisney</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noel Suffys, Philip</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La calidad y pureza del ADN garantiza el éxito de los estudios moleculares, muchos son los trabajos en los que se reporta la obtención del material genético contenido en el tejido embebido de parafina, en esta ocasión presentamos nuestra experiencia al obtener ADN de linfa y mucus  nasal de láminas de baciloscopías con codificaciones desde 1 hasta 5, provenientes de pacientes multibacilares de lepra, para nuestro objetivo se utilizó la resina quelante Chelex-100. La calidad del ADN extraído se observa, en la fotografía realizada a la amplificación por la reacción en cadena de la polimerasa de los segmentos de la posición 14.676 del genoma de M. leprae (con talla de 180 pb). Todos los ADN amplificaron y su calidad  es comparable con el obtenido por otros autores en estudios similares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fontilles, Rev. leprol;28(6): 455-458, sept.-dic. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111641</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Extracción de ADN de Mycobacterium Lepra de láminas positivas de pacientes multibacilares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22153^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53481</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9359^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
