<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114330</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In October 2011, the journal Nature* announced the cloning of triploid human embryos. Unlike conventional embryo cloning, where the nucleus of the ovule is replaced with the nucleus of a somatic cell, in this case the nucleus of the somatic cell is implanted without removing the one in the ovule. The resulting  embryos develop up to the blastocyst stage and were used to derive pluripotent cell lines, which have the capacity to generate all of the tissues of the human organism. The experiment was conducted by a team from the New York Stem Cell Foundation Laboratory, under the management of Doctors Scott Noggle and Dieter Egli. This work attempts to place the experiment within the scientific and social framework of pluripotent-stem-cell research and offer reflections of an ethical and (to a lesser extent) legal nature on the results obtained by this research group. To these ends, the work is divided into two parts. The first part describes the most important aspects of Noggle and Egli´s announcement and the biotechnological and media context in which it was made. The second part is concerned with the bioethical issues raised by the experiment. There are basically four issues, which relate to: (1) the nuclear transfer technique, (2) the use of human ovules to carry out the experiment, (3) the destruction of human blastocysts, and (4) the ethical requirements of scientific publications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bellver Capella, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En octubre de 20122 la revista Nature* anunció la clonación de embriones humanos triploides. A diferencia de la clonación convencional de embriones, en la que el núcleo del óvulo es reemplazado por el núcleo de una célula somática, en este caso el núcleo de la célula somática se implantó sin retirar el del óvulo. Los embriones resultantes se desarrollaron hasta la fase de blastocisto y fueron empleados para derivar las líneas celulares pluripotentes, aquellas con capacidad para generar todos los tejidos del organismo humano. El experimento fue llevado a cabo por un equipo del New York Stem Cell Foundation Laboratory, bajo la dirección de los Dres. Scott Noggle y Dieter Egli. El presente trabajo pretende situar el experimento en el marco científico y social de la investigación con células troncales pluripotenciales y ofrecer unas consideraciones de carácter ético y (en menor medida) jurídico sobre los resultados obtenidos por este grupo de investigación. Para ello se divide el trabajo en dos partes. En la primera se presentan los aspectos más destacados del anuncio de Noggle y Egli así como el contexto biotecnológico y mediático en el que se realizó. La segunda se ocupa de las cuestiones bioéticas que suscita el experimento. Básicamente son cuatro y tienen que ver con: (1) la técnica de la transferencia nuclear, (2) el empleo de óvulos humanos para llevar adelante el experimento, (3) la destrucción de blastocitos humanos, y (4) las exigencias éticas de las publicaciones científicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(36): 25-63, ene.-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Embriones humanos clónicos triploides: aspectos éticos, sociales y jurídicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37583^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33589^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6957^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37583^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
