<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154870</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perception of professional competences of graduates in science of physical activity and sport</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyzes the level of importance perceived by individuals who work in physical activity and sport occupations in Spain on specific professional competences, mainly Graduates in Science of Physical Activity and Sport. The methodology consisted in a sectional survey of 2500 individuals. The results were that these graduates consider it is very important have all the specific professional competences studied for a highly professional performance. This perception is higher than other people working in physical activity and sport and increases with more than ten years of professional experience. Furthermore, according to occupation, the same perception of the great majority of these competences is maintained. Therefore, these competences should be the core of the training program of these graduates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Acero, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos-Izquierdo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio analiza el nivel de importancia que perciben las personas que trabajan en funciones laborales de actividad física y deporte en España sobre las competencias profesionales específicas, incidiendo principalmente en los Graduados en Ciencias de la Actividad Física y del Deporte. La metodología ha consistido en una encuesta seccional aplicada a 2500 personas. Los resultados obtenidos muestran que estos titulados consideran que para el mejor desempeño profesional es muy importante poseer todas las competencias profesionales específicas analizadas. Esta percepción es superior al resto de personas que trabajan en actividad física y deporte y aumenta con los que tienen más de diez años de experiencia profesional. Asimismo, desagregando por función laboral se mantiene la misma percepción sobre la inmensa mayoría de estas competencias. Por ello, estas competencias deben ser el eje vertebrador del programa formativo de estos titulados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(2): 339-346, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de las competencias profesionales de los graduados en Ciencias de la Actividad Física y del Deporte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
