<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126897</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyzes the efficacy and safety of the different pharmacological combinations to help smokers to quit. Four types of combinations are analyzed: combination of different types of Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT), combination of varenicline and bupropion, combination of bupropion and TRNand combination of varenicline and TRN. The main conclusions are as follows: a) combination of different types of NRT (short acting with long acting treatments) are most recommended, b) combination of nicotine patches and bupropion can be effective in specific groups of smokers, c) combination of nicotine patches with varenicline does not increase the efficacy of varenicline and d) combination of bupropion and varenicline increases short term efficacy but not long term efficacy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perera López, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Lozano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayayo Ulibarri, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cristóbal Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Ruiz, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Reina, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granda Orive, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cicero Guerrero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A lo largo del artículo se abordan las diferentes combinaciones de fármacos que han mostrado ser eficaces y seguras para ayudar a dejar de fumar. Se analizan cuatro tipos de combinaciones: la combinación de diferentes formas de Terapia Sustitutiva con Nicotina (TSN), la combinación de TSN y bupropión, la combinación de vareniclina y bupropión y la combinación de vareniclina y TSN. Las principales conclusiones son: a) la combinación de diferentes formas de TSN que agrupen la administración rápida con la crónica es una forma de tratamiento del tabaquismo muy recomendada en el momento actual, b) la combinación de bupropión más parches de nicotina pudiera prescribirse en algún grupo de sujetos, c) vareniclina combinada con TSN en forma de parches no parece incrementar significativamente la eficacia de la misma, d) la combinación bupropión y vareniclina incrementa la eficacia a corto y medio plazo pero no a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;17(3): 87-89, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Combinación de fármacos para el tratamiento del tabaquismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
