<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102460</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sagittal craniosynostosis. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Craniosynostosis is the premature fusion of one or more of the cranial sutures. It includes a wide spectrum of cranial malformations, from closing of an isolated suture to the closing of several sutures, or associated to other malformations, constituting syndromic craniosynostosis. The pediatrician must distinguish the positional deformities or postural plagiocephaly, more frequent, from the craniosynostosis, that needs surgical treatment and whose early diagnosis improves the prognosis. We present the case of an infant with scafocephaly due to isolated craniosynostosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega Gutiérrez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alía Arroyo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La craneosinostosis es el cierre precoz de una o más suturas craneales. Comprende un amplio espectro de malformaciones craneales, desde el cierre aislado de una sola sutura, al cierre de varias suturas, o asociado a otras malformaciones, constituyendo las craneosinostosis sindrómicas. El pediatra debe distinguir las deformidades posicionales o plagiocefalias posturales, más frecuentes, de las craneosinostosis, que requieren tratamiento quirúrgico y cuyo diagnóstico precoz mejora el pronóstico. Se presenta el caso de un lactante con escafocefalia debida a craneosinostosis aislada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;14(54): 149-152, abr.-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102460</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Craneosinostosis sagital. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35390^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35390^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38614^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13900^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38614^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13267^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29193^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13900^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3414^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
