<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166006</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Systemic necrotizing vasculitis affects the lung, especially in the context of granulomatous vasculitis syndromes or pulmonary-renal syndromes. The most serious complication, resulting from damage to the microcirculation, is pulmonary hemorrhage. It is clinically defined as a syndrome characterized by hemoptysis, anemia, acute respiratory failure, and sudden onset pulmonary alveolar infiltrates, along with other nonspecific symptoms. It is potentially fatal and has an unpredictable clinical course. We present the case of a 42 years old patient with diffuse alveolar hemorrhage and severe respiratory insufficiency, bilateral alveolar infiltrates and high titers of anti-neutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies (c-ANCA), finally being diagnosed as having granulomatosis with polyangeitis or Wegener's (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernádez Olivo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erro Iribarren, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca Noval, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón Moreno, R MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Fresneda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta Gutiérrez, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La vasculitis necrosante sistémica afecta al pulmón, sobre todo en el contexto de los síndromes de vasculitis granulomatosa o los síndromes pulmonares-renales. La complicación más grave, consecuencia del daño en la microcirculación, es la hemorragia pulmonar. Clínicamente se define como un síndrome caracterizado por hemoptisis, anemia, insuficiencia respiratoria aguda e infiltrados alveolares pulmonares de aparición brusca, junto con otros síntomas inespecíficos. Es potencialmente mortal y con una evolución clínica impredecible. Presentamos un caso de un paciente de 42 años que debutó con hemorragia alveolar difusa e insuficiencia respiratoria grave, infiltrados alveolares bilaterales y títulos altos de anticuerpos anticitoplasma de neutrófilo (c-ANCA), siendo diagnosticado finalmente de granulomatosis con poliangeítis o enfermedad de Wegener (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;20(2): 66-69, abr.-jun. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166006</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paciente con fiebre y hemoptisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29510^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3540^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27929^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53544^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6621^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
