<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92270</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pilot study on the prevalence of dual pathology in community mental health and substance misuse services in Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate retrospectively the comorbidity of mental and addictive disorders in community mental health and substance misuse services in Madrid. Methods: The medical records of 400 patients from mental health and substance misuse services in Madrid were evaluated. Records were examined for the last 20 patients from each service unit. Results: Dual pathology was constituted when a current diagnosis of mental and addictive disorders, excluding nicotine addiction, appeared on the patient&#146;s records. Prevalence of dual pathology was 34%. There were differences in the prevalence figures for the two kinds of service: 36.78% in substance misuse services, and 28.78% in mental health services. There was an association of dual diagnosis with alcohol or cocaine dependence, but not with opioid dependence. The mental disorders more prevalent in dually diagnosed than in non-dually diagnosed patients were mood disorders, personality disorders, and schizophrenia. Conclusion: There is a high prevalence of dual pathology in those seeking treatment, being higher in substance misuse services than in mental health services, and higher in patients with alcohol or cocaine dependence. These findings could be of help in the planning of care resource policies for these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Basurte Villamor, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesías Perez, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Mangado, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Astudillo, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Babín Vich, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morant, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Szerman Bolotner, Néstor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francisco Arias Horcajadas, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poyo Calvo, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo ha sido valorar la presencia de diagnósticos comórbidos de trastornos mentales y adictivos de forma retrospectiva en la historia clínica de pacientes en tratamiento en las redes asistenciales de salud mental o de adicciones en la Comunidad de Madrid. Material y métodos: Se valoraron las historias clínicas de 400 pacientes en tratamiento en Centros de Atención al Drogodependiente (CAD), Centros de Atención Integral al Drogodependiente (CAID), Centros de Salud Mental (CSM) o servicios de psiquiatría de Hospitales de Madrid. Se recogieron de forma retrospectiva los datos de las últimas 20 historias clínicas de cada centro seleccionado. Resultados: La prevalencia de patología dual, considerando como tal la presencia de un diagnóstico actual de trastorno mental y de trastorno por uso de sustancias distinto al tabaco, fue del 34%. Había diferencias en la prevalencia entre las dos redes asistenciales, un 36.78% de los pacientes en tratamiento en la red de drogas fueron considerados duales frente a un 28.78% en la red de salud mental. Había una asociación entre el diagnóstico de patología dual y el consumo perjudicial o dependencia de alcohol o cocaína pero no con el de heroína. Los trastornos mentales más frecuentes en los pacientes duales que en los no duales fueron los trastornos del humor, los trastornos de personalidad y la esquizofrenia. Conclusión: Por lo tanto, existe una elevada prevalencia de pacientes con patología dual entre los sujetos que buscan tratamiento, siendo mayor en la red de atención al drogodependiente y mayor entre aquellos con dependencia de alcohol o cocaína. Estos datos pueden ayudar a la horade planificar los recursos asistenciales para este tipo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);23(3): 249-255, jul.-sept. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92270</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio piloto sobre la prevalencia de patología dual en pacientes en tratamiento en la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31825^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
