<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101621</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyperglycaemia as a prognostic indicator during acute macrovascular events</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: An analytical, longitudinal and prospective study was conducted during the period 2009-2010 on a cohort of 100 patients with acute vascular events who were admitted to the Stroke and Coronary Units of the &#147;Hermanos Ameijeiras&#148; Hospital in Havana, Cuba. The aim was to evaluate whether there was relationship between hyperglycaemia and any immediate complication. Material and methods: Blood analysis was performed on all cases, such as glucose on admission, fasting and post-prandial, as well as glycosylated haemoglobin and a lipid profile. Summary statistics were used in the data analysis, as well as means and standard deviations (SD). The Chi-squared independence and Student t tests were used, and a ROC curve was constructed. Results: There were complications in 16% of the sample. The patient group with complications showed an increased mean in fasting blood glucose (P=.001), was associated with a history of diabetes (P=.022) and &#147;de novo&#148; diabetes (P=.021), which was demonstrated with the admission glucose level. Postprandial hyperglycaemia was associated with the occurrence of immediate events (P=.039), which also agreed with an abnormal fasting glucose, with this latter parameter having a larger area under the curve (ROC) 0.75. This gave a value of 6.1 mmol/L  as a prognostic indicator of complications after an acute vascular accident. Conclusions: We conclude that fasting and postprandial glucose disorders, as well as the presence of diabetes, are associated with early medical complications after coronary or cerebrovascular accidents(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Buchaca Faxas, Emilio Fidel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez Rojas, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Valdés, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Carrillo, Fredy Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Amador, Lays</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Rojas, Ángela Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se realizó un estudio analítico, longitudinal y prospectivo de una cohorte de 100 pacientes con eventos vasculares agudos que fueron atendidos en las unidades de ictus y coronario del Hospital «Hermanos Ameijeiras», en el período comprendido entre 2009-2010, con el objetivo de evaluar si existía asociación entre la hiperglucemia y cualquier complicación inmediata. Material y métodos: A todos los casos se les realizaron estudios sanguíneos como glucemia al ingreso, en ayunas y potprandial, hemoglobina glucosilada y lipidograma. Para el análisis de los datos se utilizaron medidas de resumen, así como medias y desviación estándar (SD). Se empleó además la prueba de independencia de chi-cuadrado, el test de T de student y se construyó una curva ROC. Resultados: Las complicaciones se presentaron en el 16% de la muestra. El grupo de enfermos complicados mostró aumento promedio de la glucemia en ayunas (p=0,001), se asoció con el antecedente de diabetes (p=0,022) y «de novo» (p=0,021), lo que no se demostró con la glucemia al ingreso. La hiperglucemia posprandial se asoció con la presencia de eventos inmediatos (p=0,039), lo que también se comprobó con la disglucemia de ayuno (p=0,009), siendo este último parámetro el que mostró una mejor área bajo la curva 0,75 (ROC), con el valor de 6,1 mmol/L como indicador pronóstico de las complicaciones después de un accidente vascular agudo. Conclusiones: Concluimos que los trastornos de la glucemia de ayuno y posprandial, así como la presencia de diabetes, se asocian con las complicaciones médicas tempranas después de un accidente en los territorios coronario y cerebrovascular(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;28(2): 48-54, mar.-abr. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101621</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperglucemia como indicador pronóstico durante los eventos macrovasculares agudos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3948^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3948^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
