<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93748</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of the taking blood pressure in a clinical case. Secondary hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Blood pressure, as with other vital signs, is an expression of health status. Any change in those vital signs indicates an abnormality. The lack of identification of high blood pressure can lead to many systemic changes progressing to the so called &#147;end-organs&#148;, such as heart, brain, kidney and retina, and also increase morbidity and mortality in hypertensive patients. High blood pressure can be easily identified and treated at primary level although is very often silent in this phase. Due to this fact, medical staff (medical practitioners and nurses) are responsible for a rapid diagnosis in order to reduce the numerous secondary effects may take place without an early detection. There are also repercussions from a sociological, economical, medical and psychological point of view if this diagnosis is not seriously taken into account(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estrada Alonso, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Palencia Calvillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poyatos Chiclana, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cotán Barbadillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poyatos Poyatos, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Al igual que los demás signos vitales, la presión arterial es una manifestación del estado de salud. Cualquier alteración de los signos vitales indica anormalidad. La falta de identificación de la hipertensión arterial (HTA) puede permitir la evolución de múltiples alteraciones sistémicas en los denominados órganos diana, como corazón, cerebro, riñón y retina y aumentar la morbimortalidad de los pacientes hipertensos. La HTA es fácilmente identificable, y tratable en estadios iniciales, aunque a menudo es clínicamente silente en esta fase, de tal manera que es el personal sanitario (médico de familia, enfermera), el responsable de diagnosticarla a tiempo y reducir los numerosos efectos secundarios que implica la falta de detección temprana y la repercusión desde el punto de vista, médico, socioeconómico y psicológico que tiene subestimarla(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(10): 576-579, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93748</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de la toma de la presión arterial: a propósito de un caso clínico. Hipertensión arterial secundaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53683^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6065^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55111^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23324^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4072^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5801^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4072^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30857^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
