<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73264</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low mortality rate in an outbreak of Legionnaires&#146; disease: Correlation with the cytopathogenity study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In 2001 an outbreak of Legionnaires&#146; diseases occurred in Murcia, Spain, with one of the lowest known rates of associated mortality. We describe the clinical data of a subgroup of patients, and present the results from molecular and virulence studies to correlate the lower mortality of the overall series with the strain virulence. Patients and methods: A subgroup of 86 patients from the outbreak of Legionnaires&#146;disease was prospectively included. Demographic, risk factors and clinical evolution data were obtained. Moreover, we performed a pulsed field gel electrophoresis and cytopathogenicity assay of the Murcia outbreak that were compared with other unrelated Legionella isolates. Results: Sixty-nine (77.9%) patients were males. The mean age of the patients was 58.2 years (range: 32&#150;87). Smoking was the most frequent risk factor in 62 patients (71.7%) and 61 patients (70.2%) had underlying diseases. Clinical, laboratory and radiological manifestations were compatible with the atypical pneumonia syndrome. The mortality rate was 3.2%. All the clinical L. pneumophila isolates analyzed by PFGE showed the same subtype. When analyzing theses strains together with other Legionella strains, they were included in the group with lower virulence in the cytopathogenicity study. Conclusions: The most outstanding data in this subgroup of patients were: male-sex, smoking, atypical clinical manifestations and low mortality. The low virulence of this molecular genotype of L. pneumophila may be responsible, in part, for the low mortality observed in the outbreak in Murcia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Núñez, marian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Módol, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baños, Victor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedro Botet, Mª Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: En el año 2001 tuvo lugar en Murcia un brote de enfermedad del legionario (EL) con una de las tasas de mortalidad más bajas conocidas. Los objetivos de este estudio fueron describir la presentación clínica y los resultados de los estudios molecular y de virulencia de los aislamientos clínicos de Legionella para correlacionar la baja mortalidad de la serie con la virulencia de la cepa. Pacientes y método: Estudio prospectivo y descriptivo de un brote de EL en un subgrupo de 86 pacientes. Se analizan datos demográficos, factores de riesgo y evolución clínica. Se ha practicado subtipificación molecular mediante electroforesis en campo pulsátil y estudio de citopatogenicidad de los aislamientos clínicos y se han comparado con los de aislamientos procedentes de otros brotes. Resultados: La edad media fue de 58,2 años, con predominio del sexo masculino (77,9%). El tabaquismo fue el factor de riesgo más frecuente (71,7%). El 70,2% de los pacientes presentaba enfermedades de base. Las manifestaciones clínicas, los datos de laboratorio y la radiología fueron compatibles con un cuadro de neumonía atípica. La mortalidad fue del 3,2%. Todos los aislamientos clínicos de Legionella pneumophila mostraron el mismo subtipo molecular. En el estudio de citopatogenicidad, las cepas de Legionella procedentes del brote se incluyeron dentro del grupo de menor virulencia. Conclusiones: En este subgrupo de pacientes predominaron el sexo masculino, el tabaquismo, la presentación clínica compatible con neumonía atípica y la baja mortalidad. La baja virulencia de este genotipo molecular de L. pneumophila podría ser causante, en parte, de la baja mortalidad observada en el brote de Murcia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);133(9): 325-329, sept. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73264</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Baja mortalidad en un brote de enfermedad del legionario: correlación con el estudio de citopatogenicidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d26532</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30016^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30016^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22539^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
