<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82948</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pancreatic pseudocyst. A retrospective study of 12 cases from autopsy reports from the General Hospital of Mexico</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Pancreatic pseudocyst (PP) is a complication of both acute pancreatitis (AP) and chronic pancreatitis (CP) that is difficult to diagnose. Material and methods. Autopsy reports from the General Hospital of Mexico were reviewed over a ten year period in order to determine the clinical and morphological data from the cases diagnosed as PP. Results. 12 cases were found (0.164%) with a predominance in women (7 cases). The most common past clinical histories were of alcoholism (33%) and cancer (25%), the most frequent location was the tail of the pancreas and the most common complication was rupture (16.66%). Conclusions. The possibility of PP should be considered in cases of AP and CP, since it can cause serious complications which may result in death(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lazos-Ochoa, Minerva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murguía-Pérez, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Córdoba, Felipe de Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El pseudoquiste pancreático (SP) es una complicación de la pancreatitis aguda (PA) y crónica (PC) que es de difícil diagnóstico. Material y métodos. Se revisaron los archivos de autopsias del Hospital General de México en un periodo de 10 años, para determinar las características clínicas, epidemiológicas y macroscópicas de los casos con diagnóstico de SP. Resultados. Se recabaron 12 casos (0,164%), predominaron en mujeres (7 casos). Los antecedentes más comunes fueron alcoholismo (33%) y cáncer (25%). La localización más frecuente fue la cola del páncreas. La mayoría de los casos se asociaron a PC. La ruptura fue la complicación más común (16,66%). Conclusiones. Es importante tener en cuenta esta patología en el curso de PA y PC, ya que puede tener complicaciones graves, incluso mortales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;43(4): 201-206, oct.-dic.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82948</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pseudoquiste pancreático. Estudio retrospectivo de 12 casos de autopsia en el Hospital General de México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10380^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15272^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10367^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10370^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
