<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81496</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transformational and transactional leadership: an analysis of the factor structure of the Multifactor Leadership Questionnaire (MLQ) in a Spanish sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Multifactor Leadership Questionnaire (MLQ) has been one of the most commonly used instruments to assess leadership in organizational settings for the last two decades. However, the factor structure proposed by the MLQ authors has received some criticism. The aim of this work is to examine the fit indices of several alternative factor models suggested by the literature. In order to accomplish this objective, we conducted confirmatory factor analyses in a sample of 954 participants using a Spanish version of the MLQ. Results show that the model that produces the better fit with the data consists of four factors: transformational leadership, developmental/transactional leadership, corrective leadership and avoidant/passive leadership. This model is parsimonious and consistent with the MLQ literature(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molero Alonso, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado Guirado, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recio Saboya, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Multifactor Leadership Questionnaire (MLQ) es, desde hace dos décadas, uno de los instrumentos más utilizados para medir el liderazgo en el ámbito organizacional. Sin embargo, la estructura factorial propuesta por los autores del cuestionario ha recibido diversas críticas. El objetivo de este trabajo es comprobar el ajuste de dicha estructura factorial y de otros posibles modelos alternativos utilizando una versión española del MLQ. Para ello, se aplicó el análisis factorial confirmatorio a los resultados obtenidos en una muestra de 954 participantes. Los resultados revelan que el modelo que mejor ajuste presenta es el que está formado por cuatro factores: liderazgo transformacional, liderazgo facilitador del desarrollo/transaccional, liderazgo correctivo y liderazgo pasivo/evitador. Este modelo es parsimonioso y teóricamente coherente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(3): 495-501, 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Liderazgo transformacional y liderazgo trasaccional: un análisis de la estructura factorial del Multifactor Leadership Questionnaire (MLQ) en una muestra española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14544^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14544^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
