<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158657</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transnational entanglements in the history of psychiatry. South Tyrolian patients in German Asylums, C. 1940-1945</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Object of this article is the destiny of psychiatric inmates in Wuerttemberg asylums, 1940-1945. These patients from Italian regions of Vicenza, Udine, Trento, Alto Adige and various locations more were delegated and, to a substantial number, illegally deported to the German asylums Zwiefalten, Schussenried and Weissenau, all in South Wuerttemberg, in 1940 and 1943. Attention is focused on the pioneering state pre-negotiations, and the so-called option treaties between the German Reich and Fascist Italy as part of the general aspect of National Socialist bio-Politics. The treatment of these South Tyrol patients in the asylums themselves, as well as their fate will be put into the context of the resettlement actions at the margins of the Third Reich, which started in 1939 and widely affected the European continent. It is referred to other sub-groups of migrating population from Italy to the German Reich as well, as a contrasting aspect of this contribution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Müller, Thomas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kanis-Seyfried, Uta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objeto de este trabajo es investigar el destino de un grupo de pacientes psiquiátricos ingresados en asilos de Württemberg (Alemania) durante el periodo de 1940 a 1945. Dichos internos, procedentes principalmente de las regiones italianas de Vicenza, Udine, Trento y Alto Adigio, fueron enviados (y un número importante entre ellos ilegalmente deportados) a los psiquátricos alemanes de Zwiefalten, Schussenried y Weissenau, situados todos en el sur de la región alemana de Württemberg, entre 1940 y 1943. Especial atención se dedica a los llamados Acuerdos para la Opción entre el Reich alemán y la Italia fascista, como parte de la biopolítica nacionalsocialista. El tratamiento de estos pacientes surtiroleses en los asilos, así como su destino, se sitúa en el contexto de las acciones de reubicación de la población realizadas en las zonas limítrofes del Tercer Reich, que comenzaron en 1939 y afectaron a amplias zonas del continente europeo. Se estudian comparativamente también en esta contribución otros subgrupos poblacionales que emigraron por entonces de Italia al Reich alemán (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;68(2): 0-0, jul.-dic. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158657</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicaciones transnacionales en la historia de la psiquiatría: la reubicación de pacientes de Tirol del Sur (Italia) en Institutciones Psiquiátricas Alemanas, 1940-1945</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7727^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55787^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55787^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5998^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
