<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142938</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the Specific Language Impairment in a three-generation family</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. Three members of a family, one of each generation, are studied in order to obtain their SLI language profile, together with motor and cognitive data. Additional information on the absence of FOXP2 mutations is also provided. Method. The language profile is twofold: natural conversation and language tests, and an evaluation of their cognitive abilities, oral-motor praxis, and laterality. Results. Cognitive abilities (short term and procedural working memory, perception, conceptual and coherence strategies) are not at the average level. General oral fine mobility (not the speech apraxia), fluency and auditory phonetic discrimination are impaired at different degrees. The language phenotype exhibits lexical as well as syntactic processing difficulties as the main impairments. The language competence of the adult members is simple but sufficient for everyday communication. Conclusions. The long-standing language competence results of SLI show an adaptation in terms of simplicity, high frequency strategies, and pragmatic resources. Language profile, sensory-motor abilities and cognition favour a non-specific approach to the language acquisition impairment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serra, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lluent, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estudiar tres miembros de una familia con Trastorno Específico del Lenguaje (TEL), uno de cada generación, para obtener su perfil de lenguaje, junto a otros datos de tipo motriz y cognitivo. Se aporta información adicional sobre la ausencia de mutaciones en el gen FOXP2. Método. El perfil del lenguaje que se presenta es doble: Los datos provienen de conversaciones naturales y de tests de lenguaje. También son evaluadas sus habilidades cognitivas, sus praxias oro- motrices y su lateralidad. Resultados. Las habilidades cognitivas de las memorias a corto termino y procedimental de trabajo, la percepción, la conceptuación y las estrategias de construcción de coherencia (texto), no alcanzan un nivel de normalidad. La movilidad fina oral general (no la apraxia de habla), la fluidez, y la fonética auditiva son deficientes en grados diversos. El fenotipo del lenguaje manifiesta sus máximas dificultades de procesamiento en los niveles léxico y sintáctico. Los adultos tienen un lenguaje coloquial muy simple pero normal. Conclusiones. La competencia lingüística de los miembros mayores muestra una buena adaptación, resaltando sus estrategias de simplicidad, usos de alta frecuencia y buena pragmática comunicativa. El perfil del lenguaje, las habilidades sensorio &#150; motrices y las cognitivas favorecen una aproximación no especifica al TEL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);35(4): 159-170, oct.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142938</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio del trastorno específico del lenguaje en tres generaciones de una familia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7982</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1079^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8018^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8018^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1079^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1079^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13872^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
