<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134338</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of Magnetic Resonance Imaging for Evaluating Atherothrombosis, Ischemic, Hibernating or Scarred Myocardium, and the Microcirculation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The technique of nuclear magnetic resonance imaging(MRI) is entering a period of great expansion thanks, in part, to the development of new molecular markers that enable extremely sophisticated images to be obtained in real time. Applications range from studying the pathophysiological mechanisms underlying the development of disease to improving diagnosis and evaluating the effects of specific treatments. The technique has the advantage that it is highly sensitive and specific, as well as non-invasive, and can be performed in a relatively short time. The molecular characterization of arterial lesions and the biological processes actively involved in ischemic heart disease, and the identification of new risk factors for atherosclerotic disease progression are some of the new applications currently under development. Using the technique, it is possible to quantify coronary flow reserve at a very high spatial resolution. Additionally, the passage of contrast medium through the myocardium after vasodilator drug administration can be visualized and its transit time quantified, thereby enabling the level of perfusion to be determined in different myocardial segments. In addition to providing useful information on the state of the microvasculature, perfusion, and myocardial contractility, MRI can also be used to determine the amount of necrotic tissue, and to identify myocardium that is viable but clearly dysfunctional (e.g., hibernating or stunned). Moreover, there is a broad spectrum of other applications that is just beginning to be explored with this imaging technology and that has a promising future; one example is monitoring the biodistribution of autologous cells used in myocardial regeneration therapy. There is no doubt that MRI will soon become fundamental to the study of cardiovascular disease, to its diagnosis and prognosis, and to monitoring treatment responses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuster, Valentín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tecnología de imagen basada en la resonancia magnética nuclear se encuentra en una fase de gran expansión gracias, en parte, al desarrollo de nuevos marcadores moleculares que permiten la obtención de imágenes sumamente sofisticadas en tiempo real. Sus aplicaciones abarcan desde el estudio de los mecanismos fisiopatológicos subyacentes al desarrollo de una enfermedad hasta mejoras en el diagnóstico y la evaluación de los efectos de un determinado tratamiento. Entre sus ventajas se encuentran sus altas sensibilidad y especificidad, y también la de ser una técnica no invasiva que puede realizarse en un tiempo relativamente corto. La caracterización molecular de las lesiones arteriales y de los procesos biológicos que tienen lugar en la cardiopatía isquémica o la identificación de nuevos factores de riesgo en la progresión de la enfermedad aterosclerótica son algunas de las nuevas aplicaciones que se están desarrollando. Con esta tecnología es posible cuantificar la reserva de flujo con una gran resolución espacial y visualizar el paso de contraste a través del miocardio en respuesta a fármacos vasodilatadores y medir su tiempo de tránsito, lo que permite establecer el grado de perfusión en distintos segmentos miocárdicos. Además de proporcionar información relevante sobre el estado de la microvasculatura, la perfusión y la contractilidad miocárdicas, la resonancia magnética también es capaz de determinar la extensión del tejido necrótico y de identificar el miocardio que es viable, pero claramente disfuncionante (hibernación, aturdimiento). Además, hay un amplio espectro de aplicaciones que empiezan a explorarse con esta tecnología de imagen y que tienen un futuro prometedor, como es el seguimiento de la biodistribución de células autólogas en la terapia de regeneración miocárdica. No cabe duda de que la resonancia magnética nuclear va a convertirse pronto en una herramienta básica en el estudio de las enfermedades cardiovasculares, su diagnóstico y pronóstico, así como en el seguimiento de la respuesta al tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;58(supl.2): 14-21, 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134338</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La resonancia magnética en la evaluación de la aterotrombosis, del miocardio isquémico, hibernado o cicatrizado y de la microcirculación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31288^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31490^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
