<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81830</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Darier White disease (keratosis follicularis). A case report with a special consideration of diferential diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Darier´s disease is a genodermatosis with characteristic epidermal keratinization patterns which affects both sexes equally and is more frequent in the 2nd&#150;3rd decade of life. Clinically, there is a slowly progressive eruption of crusted papules persistent in the skin, nails and mucous membranes. The characteristic histopathological changes are acantolysis with suprabasal cleavage and dyskeratosis in the form of corps ronds and grains. We present a case of Darier´s disease in a young man, with a 3 year clinical history of skin lesions but no family history of this condition(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lacarrubba, Luz Flores de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Di Martino, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giardina, Romy</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Darier es una genodermatosis caracterizada por queratinización tegumentaria particular, más frecuente en la 2-3 décadas de la vida, equitativa en ambos sexos. Clínicamente se presenta con un brote papuloso persistente en piel, mucosas y uñas e histopatológicamente con acantolisis, clivaje suprabasal y disqueratosis particular en forma de cuerpos redondos y granos. Presentamos el caso de un varón joven, con lesiones de 3 años de evolución y sin antecedentes familiares de enfermedad de Darier(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;43(3): 176-179, jul.-sept.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81830</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Darier-White (queratosis folicular). Descripción de un caso y revisión de los diagnósticos diferenciales(AU)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7811^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29312^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7811^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33362^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7811^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
