<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158568</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implementing evidence and implementation research: two different and prime realities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Scientific research can contribute to more efficient health care, enhance care quality and safety of persons. In order for this to happen, the knowledge gained must be put into practice. Implementation is known as the introduction of a change or innovation to daily practice, which requires effective communication and the elimination of barriers that hinder this process. Best practice implementation experiences are being used increasingly in the field of nursing. The difficulty in identifying the factors that indicate the success or failure of implementation has led to increased studies to build a body of differentiated knowledge, recognized as implementation science or implementation research. Implementation research is the scientific study whose objective is the adoption and systematic incorporation of research findings into clinical practice to improve the quality and efficiency of health services. The purpose of implementation research is to improve the health of the population through equitable and effective implementation of rigorously evaluated scientific knowledge, which involves gathering the evidence that has a positive impact on the health of the community. In this text, we set out the characteristics of nursing implementation research, providing a synthesis of different methods, theories, key frameworks and implementation strategies, along with the terminology proposed for greater conceptual clarity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sobrido Prieto, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Braña Marcos, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ques, Ángel Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rumbo Prieto, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Campo, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raña Lama, Camilo Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación científica puede contribuir a hacer más eficientes los cuidados de salud, a mejorar la calidad asistencial y la seguridad de las personas. Para que así suceda, el conocimiento generado debe transferirse a la práctica. Se conoce como implementación la introducción de un cambio o innovación en la práctica diaria, lo que exige una comunicación efectiva y la eliminación de barreras que dificulten este proceso. En el ámbito de enfermería, cada vez es más frecuente la realización de experiencias de implementación de buenas prácticas. La dificultad para identificar los factores que permiten conocer el éxito o fracaso de la implementación ha dado lugar al incremento de estudios encaminados a construir un cuerpo de conocimientos diferenciados, conocido como ciencia de la implementación o investigación en implementación. La investigación en implementación es el estudio científico cuyo objetivo es la adopción e incorporación sistemática de los resultados de investigación en la práctica clínica para mejorar la calidad y eficacia de los servicios de salud. El fin que persigue la investigación en implementación es mejorar la salud de la población mediante la aplicación equitativa y eficaz del conocimiento científico rigurosamente evaluado, lo que implica la captación de aquellas evidencias que hayan producido un impacto positivo en la salud de la comunidad. En este texto se exponen las particularidades de la investigación enfermera en implementación, realizándose una síntesis de los diferentes métodos, teorías, marcos determinantes y estrategias de implementación, junto con la terminología propuesta para una mayor claridad conceptual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);26(6): 381-386, nov.-dic. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158568</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implementar evidencias e investigar en implementación: dos realidades diferentes y prioritarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53368</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
