<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87050</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Occupational stress, self-concept and health in a sample of Spanish service members</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study has been carried out with a wide sample of Spanish service members from different Army units all over the national territory. It has a double objective: on one hand to identify the main causes of occupational stress in this group and, on the other hand, to evaluate whether the personal self-concept can cushion the effects that these occupational stressors can exert on health, satisfaction and length of stay in the Armed Forces, as the direct action on the stressors in the military environment is sometimes difficult. We have utilized the occupational stress model by Robertson, Cooper and Williams (1990) in which the influence of the occupational stressors on health and job satisfaction is modulated by different individual variables. In general, the results confirm the influence of the occupational stressors on  health, job satisfaction and tendency to stay in the service. Moreover it has been found out that the self-concept modulates some of these relationships. So, for instance, the subjects with a higher self-concept (especially in its social dimension) always enjoy a better physical wellbeing and satisfaction. It has also been confirmed that the stressors, the physical well-being and satisfaction predict the subjects&#146; tendency to stay in the service. Finally, and as far as possible gender differences are concerned, the results show that men and women are similar enough as there are hardly any differences between them. Lastly the practical implications of the results are discussed and some action proposals  suggested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oscar Segovia, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bardera Moral, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos de este trabajo son identificar las principales fuentes de estrés laboral de un grupo de soldados profesionales del Ejército español (N= 779) y analizar el papel de estas fuentes de estrés y del autoconcepto personal sobre la salud, la satisfacción y la permanencia temporal en la Institución. Para ello se ha partido del modelo de estrés laboral de Roberston, Cooper y Williams (1990) en el que la influencia del estrés sobre la salud física y la satisfacción laboral, está modulada por diferentes variables individuales. Los resultados  confirman una relación negativa entre los estresores laborales el bienestar físico, la satisfacción laboral y la tendencia a permanecer en la organización. También, como se esperaba los sujetos con mayor autoconcepto informan de mayor bienestar físico. Pero, además de las relaciones directas se ha encontrado que el autoconcepto actúa como variable moduladora. Así, los sujetos con mejor autoconcepto, señalan un mayor bienestar físico y satisfacción, pero sobre todo, en situaciones de alto estrés laboral. Se ha confirmado también que todos los estresores considerados, el bienestar físico y la satisfacción, predicen la tendencia de los sujetos a permanecer en la Institución. Al final, se  discuten las implicaciones prácticas de los resultados y se sugieren algunas propuestas de actuación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;65(3): 152-163, jul.-sept. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87050</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés laboral, autoconcepto y salud en una muestra de militares españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
