<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83787</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comorbidity of post-traumatic stress disorder in patients with severe mental illness. Clinical implications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) appears by comorbid severe mental illness (SMI) in 16%&#150;48% of cases, higher than in the general population (7.8% to 9.2%). Although these patients with severe primary psychiatric diagnosis of PTSD is often missed. Several etiopathogenic hypotheses could explain the high prevalence of PTSD in patients with SMI: diathesis trauma itself, a high risk of exposure to trauma, genetic predisposition to psychosis in a group of patients with PTSD and antidopaminergic effect of treatment itself. The impact of PTSD in patients with SMI is well documented in the literature. PTSD patients with more severe psychiatric symptoms, more alcohol use disorders and other substances, have a greater number of visits and psychiatric hospitalizations, lower work integration, poorer adherence to drug treatment, more risk behaviours, suicide attempts and self-harm, and poorer cognitive function. Antidepressants especially selective serotonin reuptake of serotonin and cognitive behavioral therapy would be the treatments of choice in PTSD. Recent studies indicate that cognitive behavioral therapy may also be useful in post-traumatic symptoms of patients with SMI. In clinical practice it is advisable to systematically perform an assessment of the traumas and investigate the existence of PTSD symptoms in clinical interviews (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Foguet Boreu, Quintí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cecilia Costa, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrufat Nebot, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Alonso, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll Negre, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno por estrés postraumático (TEPT) aparece de forma comórbida con el trastorno mental grave (TMG) en el 16&#150;48% de los casos, una cifra mucho más alta que en la población general (7,8&#150;9,2%). Aunque en estos pacientes con enfermedad psiquiátrica primaria grave el diagnóstico del TEPT es muy frecuentemente obviado. Hay varias hipótesis etiopatogénicas que explicarían la alta prevalencia de TEPT en pacientes con TMG: diátesis del propio trauma; alto riesgo de exposición a situaciones traumáticas; predisposición genética para la psicosis en un grupo de pacientes con TEPT, y efecto del propio tratamiento antidopaminérgico. Las repercusiones del TEPT en pacientes con TMG están bien documentadas en la bibliografía. Los pacientes con TEPT presentan síntomas psiquiátricos más severos, más trastornos por abuso de alcohol y otras sustancias, tienen un mayor número de visitas y hospitalizaciones psiquiátricas, una menor integración laboral, una peor adherencia al tratamiento farmacológico, más conductas de riesgo, intentos de suicidio y autolesiones, y una función cognitiva más pobre. Los antidepresivos, en especial los inhibidores selectivos de la recaptación de serotonina, y la terapia cognitivo conductual serían los tratamientos de elección en el TEPT. Los últimos estudios indican que la terapia cognitivo conductual podría ser también útil en los síntomas postraumáticos de pacientes afectados de TMG. En la práctica clínica es recomendable realizar de forma sistemática una valoración de los traumas sufridos e indagar acerca de la existencia de síntomas postraumáticos en las entrevistas clínicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);17(4): 134-137, oct.-dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comorbilidad del trastorno por estrés postraumático en pacientes con trastorno mental grave. Implicaciones clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30515^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1714^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
