<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157660</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Addiction to near-life (On pathological daydreaming and the disturbing ambiguity of faking true love)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author, in contraposition to the almost homonymous classic paper by Betty Joseph, relates the case of a patient with an addictive tendency to live in the world of her daydreams. Thus she describes a transference-coun-tertransference situation in which the patient leaves her analyst outside of an idealized relationship in her daydreams, thus avoiding a more direct contact with the complexity of the relationship with her most significant objects. She examines the description of analogous cases in psychoanalytic literature and discusses their metapsychological status, reflecting upon dissociative states and their avoidant or schizoid nature, applying her view of Freudian splitting and disavowal in the approach to this type of functioning (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sodré, Ignes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La autora, en contraposición al casi homónimo clásico trabajo de Betty Joseph, describe el caso de una paciente con tendencia adictiva a habitar en el mundo de sus ensoñaciones. Así, relata una situación transfero-contratransferencial en que la paciente deja fuera a su analista de una relación idealizada en sus ensoñaciones, evitando así un contacto más directo con la complejidad de la relación con sus objetos más significativos. Recorre la descripción de casos análogos en la literatura psicoanalítica y diserta sobre su estatus metapsicológico, reflexionando sobre los estados disociativos, la naturaleza evitativa o esquizoide de los mismos, aplicando su visión de la escisión y desmentida freudianos para acercarse a este tipo de funcionamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(77): 207-228, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157660</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adicción a la cuasi-vida (sobre la ensoñación patológica y la perturbadora ambigüedad de simular el amor verdadero)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4274^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4274^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d282^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d282^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1374^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
