<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89286</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria therapy with eculizumab: Spanish experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH) is a rare acquired clonal disease characterized by complement-mediated hemolysis, bone marrow failure and thrombosis. Eculizumab is a humanized monoclonal antibody that blocks the cytolytic component of the complement system by binding to complement C5. Material and Methods: We report the results of eculizumab treatment in 25 PNH patients from different centers in Spain. Statistical analysis was perfomed with a SPSS v15.0 software.Results: Fifty-eight per cent of the patients achieved transfusional independence after a median of 14 months. Transfusion requirements were reduced in 60% of the remaining cases. Fatigue resolved in 96% of the patients and smooth muscle dystony-related symptoms in all cases. A single case of treatment-related infection was observed. Conclusions: Eculizumab controls effectively hemolysis and greatly improves clinical symptoms. The drug is safe and well tolerated, without significant adverse effects except meningococcal infection. Patients with suboptimal response to treatment must be assessed for bone marrow insufficiency and extravascular haemolysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Rosa, Dora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Mendiguren, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fisac, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Damián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteagudo, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morado, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Rubio, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villegas, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaya, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La hemoglobinuria paroxística nocturna es una enfermedad clonal adquirida caracterizada por hemólisis mediada por complemento, insuficiencia medular y enfermedad tromboembólica. El eculizumab es un anticuerpo monoclonal dirigido contra la fracción C5 del complemento, que bloquea la formación del componente citolítico de este.Pacientes y método: Se estudian 25 pacientes en tratamiento con eculizumab en España. El análisis estadístico se realiza con el software SPSS v15.0. Resultados:Con una mediana de seguimiento de 14 meses (extremos 3-46), el eculizumab ha conseguido independencia transfusional en 58% de los pacientes y disminución del 60% de los requerimientos transfusionales en el resto de los pacientes, desaparición de la astenia en 96% de los casos y de los síntomas de distonía de músculo liso en la totalidad. Sólo un paciente ha presentado infección grave relacionada con el tratamiento.Conclusiones: El tratamiento con eculizumab es eficaz en el control de la hemólisis, con gran mejoría clínica. El fármaco es seguro y bien tolerado, sin efectos secundarios significativos, salvo el riesgo de infección meningocócica. En pacientes con respuesta subóptima a eculizumab es preciso valorar el grado de insuficiencia medular y la posibilidad de hemólisis extravascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);137(1): 8-13, jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89286</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la hemoglobinuria paroxística nocturna con eculizumab: experiencia en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6607^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6613^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
