<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102135</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To review in databases the relevant literature of adherence to chemotherapy and radiotherapy for cancer; which bring high biological, psychological, social and cultural costs and have been related to lower adherence rates. Method: A search in different databases was performed to identify relevant articles related to the key words. Results: A significant percentage of patients do not adhere to cancer treatments and the consequences of not doing it can unleash in a major risk of death or disease progression, then it is essential to approach this topic and take into account different variables of biological, psychological and social impact on the behavior of adherence or not adherence to the treatments; including the side effects, motivation, decision-making ability, emotional condition, autonomy and life philosophy of each patient. This research contributes to the health staff have more elements to approach this problem and so his interventions are more effective being able to increase the patient´s adherence. Conclusions: Adherence is a multifactorial and multi-determined construct, which has been extensively studied in non cancer treatments (e.g. AIDS) and there is few investigation that supports the efficacy of the psychological interventions to approach not adherence and to promote the adherence to cancer treatments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios Espinosa, Ximena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Sterling, Laura P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar una revisión de la literatura sobre la adherencia a la quimioterapia y a la radioterapia para el cáncer, por los altos costos biopsicosociales y culturales que acarrean y que están relacionados con bajas tasas de adherencia. Método: se realizó una búsqueda de la literatura en bases de datos especializadas utilizando las palabras clave. Resultados: Debido a que existe un porcentaje significativo de pacientes que no se adhieren a los tratamientos oncológicos y a que las consecuencias de no hacerlo pueden desencadenar un mayor riesgo de muerte o progresión de la enfermedad, es fundamental abordar este tema y para esto tener en cuenta las diferentes variables de tipo biológico, psicológico y social que influyen en la conducta de adherencia o no adherencia a los tratamientos, entre ellas la experimentación de efectos secundarios, la motivación, la capacidad de toma de decisiones, el estado emocional, la autonomía y la filosofía de vida de cada paciente. Esta investigación contribuye a que el personal de salud tenga más elementos para abordar esta problemática y así sus intervenciones sean más efectivas pudiendo incrementar la adherencia en los pacientes. Conclusiones: La adherencia es un constructo multifactorial y multideterminado, ampliamente estudiado en tratamientos no oncológicos (p.e. SIDA) y hay poca investigación que avale la eficacia de las intervenciones psicológicas para abordar la no adherencia y promover la adherencia a tratamientos oncológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);8(2/3): 423-440, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102135</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia a la quimioterapia y radioterapia en pacientes oncológicos: una revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
