<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045947</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The culture of overprotection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the text we pretend to argue the existence of a culture of overprotection respect from the treatment with old peoplein our society, and especially when they suffer from some grade of dependence which links them to somebody. They are attitudes that take place as much in the field of family as in the field of institutions, that promote the passiveness and the lost of independence of old people and that sometimes, as well as being invalidating, these attitudes make an attempt against their freedom and dignity of people. It should be also pointed some of the social and cultural factors that promote and naturalise this overprotection in our environment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el texto pretendemos argumentar la existencia de una cultura de la sobreprotección respeto del trato con las personas mayores en nuestra sociedad, y muy especialmente cuando estas sufren algun grado de dependenciaque las vincula directamente a terceros. Se trata de actitudes que tienen lugar tanto en el ámbito familiar como en el institucional, que fomentan la pasividad y la pérdida de autonomía de la persona mayor y que en ocasiones además de ser invalidantes, atentan contra su libertad y dignidad como personas. Se van a apuntar también algunos de los factores socioculturales que pueden contribuir a fomentar y a naturalizar esta sobreprotección en nuestro entorno</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;15(3): 165-170, jul.-sept. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045947</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La cultura de la sobreprotección</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35153</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35155</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
