<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105412</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pseudoaneurysm of poplíteal artery post traumatic: A Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pseudoaneurysms are more frequently found in arterial traumatisms in inferior members. According to international literaturethere is a risen incidence in orthopedics due to the use of fixers or nails in the tibia and fibula fractures. A case is reportedthat suffered a settle wound in the external face of the leg. It went without any diagnosis for 18 months. During this periodof time the leg presented and increase of progressive volume and the patient did not experience any symptom until his treatment.He underwent the evacuation of great haematoma and the restoration of the of the popliteal artery previous bond of the pseudoaneurysm. The wound closed up on second intention with the use of granulated sugar cane. After 29 days the patient was completely recovered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acosta, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balbona, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berlán, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pancorbo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pseudoaneurismas son más frecuentes hallarlos en los traumatismos arteriales en miembros inferiores. Se describe por la literatura internacional que hay una incidencia elevada en ortopedia con el uso de los fijadores en las fracturas de tibia yperoné. Se reporta un caso que sufrió una herida por arma blanca en cara externa de la pierna que estuvo sin diagnósticopor espacio de 18 meses, en todo este tiempo presentó aumento de volumen progresivo de la pierna y no padeció ningún síntomahasta su tratamiento. Se realizó la evacuación del gran hematoma con restauración de la arteria poplítea previa ligadura del pseudoaneurismas. La herida se cerró por segunda intención con el uso de azúcar de caña granulado. A los 29 días del postoperatorio el paciente estaba recuperado por completo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;15(3): 152-155, jul.-sept. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105412</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pseudonaneurisma de arteria poplítea post-traumático. Presentación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11593^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51368</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30856^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8047^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
