<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101894</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mechanical ventilation weaning protocol and decannulation of the Intermediate Respiratory Care Unit of the Fundación Jiménez Díaz</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article presents a decanulation protocol procedure for difficult to wean patients from the intensive care units in whom mechanical ventilation weaning has not been possible, and left this units needing invasive mechanical ventilation and tracheotomy. The appearance of the socalled Intermediate Respiratory Units allow pulmonologists, specialized in critical care medicine to treat these patients as those units deal with upper airway management, artificial invasive and non invasive mechanical ventilation and respiratory endoscopy. Our Pulmonology service include an intermediate respiratory unit and have wide experience in weaning patients from mechanical ventilation and subsequent decanulation. At present, no article in the literature globally explains the management of these patients. We present the protocol we follow in our unit with which we have obtained very favorable results in this type of patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heili Frades, S. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Checa Venegas, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Fonseca, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelicano, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peces Barba Romero, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Villa, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se pretende presentar un protocolo de decanulación de pacientes procedentes de los Servicios de Cuidados Intensivos en los que el destete de ventilación mecánica ha sido imposible, saliendo de esta unidad con ventilación mecánica sobre traqueotomía. La aparición de unidades de cuidados intermedios respiratorios ha hecho posible ubicar en ellas a estos pacientes al ser unidades donde se maneja la vía aérea superior, la ventilación mecánica y la endoscopia respiratoria. Nuestro Servicio de Neumología dispone de una Unidad de Cuidados Intermedios y tiene amplia experiencia en el destete de ventilación mecánica y posterior decanulación de estos enfermos. No existe en la literatura ningún artículo que presente de manera global el manejo de estos enfermos, por ello presentamos el protocolo que seguimos en nuestra unidad y con el que obtenemos unos resultados muy favorables en este tipo de enfermos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;14(3): 83-91, jul.-sept. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ventilación mecánica y traqueotomía. Protocolo de destete de ventilación mecánica y decanulación de la Unidad de Cuidados Respiratorios Intermedios de la Fundación Jiménez Díaz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14530^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
