<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85757</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of an intensive occupational therapy programme for amputated children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse myoelectric prostheses in amputated children on fulfilling activities of daily life (ADL) independently. Material and method: A structured occupational therapy programme was performed, based on fine and gross motor coordination activities as well as constant reinforcement of ADL for 6 days in 10 amputated children (4 boys and 6 girls) using myoelectric prostheses, aged within 4-0 years. The Assessment of Process and Motor Skills (AMPS) was administered to evaluate motor skills at the start and at the end of stay in the camp. Results: The following results were obtained in the first and the second assessment, by skills, respectively: reaches (2.0-1.4), bends (1.8-1.2), manipulates (2.1-1.6), coordinates (2.3-2.0), moves (2.1-1.7), positions (2.0- 1.7), walks (1.2-1.1), carries (1.7-1.6). All participants improved their skills referring to body position, obtaining and holding objects and moving themselves and objects. Conclusion: Invasive occupational therapy programmes in children using myoelectric prostheses are effective, as they improve quality in fulfilling ADL, leading to an improved self-esteem and quality of life of children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Piédrola, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Herrera Baeza, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Heredia Torres, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matesanz García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Camarero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Incio González, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vialás González, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaza de Andrés, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Calero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegre Ayala, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brea Rivero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Archilla Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar si los niños con prótesis mioeléctricas pueden mejorar sus destrezas motoras necesarias para la realización de las actividades de la vida diaria (AVD) de manera independiente. Material y método: Se realizó un programa estructurado de terapia ocupacional, basado en actividades de coordinación motora fina y gruesa, así como un refuerzo constante de las AVD, durante 6 días en 10 niños amputados (4 chicos y 6 chicas) usuarios de prótesis mioeléctricas, con edades comprendidas entre 4-0 años. Se administró el Assessment of Process and Motor Skills (AMPS) para evaluar las destrezas motoras al inicio y al finalizar la estancia en el campamento. Resultados: En la primera valoración y en la segunda obtuvieron respectivamente los siguientes resultados por destrezas: alcanza (2,0-1,4), se inclina (1,8-1,2), manipula (2,1-1,6), coordina (2,3-2,0), mueve (2,1-1,7), posiciona (2,0-1,7), camina (1,2-1,1), transporta (1,7-1,6). Todos los participantes mejoraron en las habilidades referidas a la posición corporal, obtener y sujetar objetos, y movilización de si mismos y de los objetos. Conclusiones: Los programas intensivos de terapia ocupacional en los niños usuarios de prótesis mioeléctricas son eficaces, ya que mejoran la calidad en la realización de las AVD lo que redunda en la mejora de la autoestima y en la calidad de vida de los niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);21(4): 237-240, oct.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85757</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de un programa intensivo de terapia ocupacional para niños amputados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29494^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29494^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29494^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
