<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165300</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of good and poor sleepers: stress and life satisfaction of university athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to compare differences in level of perceived stress, type of stress appraisal and life satisfaction between university athletes who declare problems with sleep (Poor Sleepers, PS, n = 72) and those without problems (Good Sleepers, GS, n = 105). In preliminary analyses the PS and GS were compared for group homogeneity with (a) the Chi-Square test for gender and type of sport, and (b) the Mann-Whitney U test for practice time and weekly frequency of trainings. In both analyses no differences were present. In the main analysis, prepared with the Mann-Whitney U test, GS and PS were compared in terms of psychological variables. Athletes who reveal problems with sleep quality (in comparison to their counterparts with good sleep quality) most often appraise stressful situations as a threat, perceive more stress in everyday life and declare lower life satisfaction. The differences between GS and PS groups may result from the bi-directional relationship between sleep quality and stress and life satisfaction. High stress and low life satisfaction can result in poor sleep quality and, on the other hand, sleep problems can aggravate stress and reduce the life satisfaction. Further studies and the use of advanced analyzes are needed to indicate the relationship between the studied variables in university athletes (e.g., mediation analysis, SEM) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Koty&amp;#347;ko, Martyna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Litwic-Kaminska, Kamila</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio fue comparar las diferencias en el nivel de estrés percibido, el tipo de evaluación del estrés y la satisfacción con la vida entre los atletas universitarios quienes declaran tener problemas de sueño (durmientes malos, DM, n = 72) y aquellos sin tales problemas (durmientes buenos, DB, n = 105). En los análisis preliminares los DM y los DB se compararon por la homogeneidad del grupo sobre la base de (a) la prueba Chi-Square por el género y el tipo de deporte, y (b) la prueba U de Mann-Whitney por el tiempo de práctica y la frecuencia semanal de entrenamientos. En ambos análisis no se detectaron diferencias. En el análisis principal, preparado con la prueba U de Mann-Whitney, los DB y los DM se compararon en términos de variables psicológicas. Los atletas quienes revelan problemas con la calidad del sueño (en comparación con sus homólogos con buena calidad del sueño) suelen evaluar las situaciones estresantes como una amenaza, perciben más estrés en la vida cotidiana y declaran una menor satisfacción con la vida. Las diferencias entre los grupos de DB y DM pueden ser el resultado de la relación bidireccional entre la calidad del sueño y el estrés y la satisfacción con la vida. El alto estrés y la baja satisfacción con la vida pueden resultar en mala calidad del sueño y, por otro lado, los problemas del sueño pueden agravar el estrés y reducir la satisfacción con la vida. Se requieren los estudios posteriores y el uso de análisis avanzados para indicar la relación entre las variables estudiadas en los atletas universitarios (p.ej., análisis de mediación, SEM) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.4): 121-126, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de los durmientes Buenos y malos: Estrés y satisfacción de vida de atletas universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
