<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050153</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social vision of HIV/AIDS</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Even though aspects relating to the transmission of HIV infection are well known, HIV infectioncontinues to be on the rise in our country. The characteristics of the epidemic havechanged and there many more women become infected through heterosexual contact. Thisarticle looks at how society views HIV-AIDS and the evident difficulty it faces to avoid it.The methodology used consisted in the analysis of the written press, mainly during the weekof the World AIDS Day and a semi-structured group interview of young individuals.The biological dimension (disease) of the cocondition is approached in several papers. Thesubjective dimension (illness) appeared in some others, while the majority of these papersmade reference to the social dimension (sickness), being classified as &#147;moral immunodeficiency&#148;or &#147;social dimension&#148; depending on the group that spoke about such disease.Young individuals have important gaps of basic knowledge and are still looking at the samequestions about disease transmission and infection as in the past, with some myths still presentin their minds.Information on AIDS or HIV is not transmitted properly to the rest of the population. The correspondingauthorities and some groups with social power should question their share ofinvolvement and responsibility in this issue</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Lahuerta, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de que los aspectos relativos a la transmisión de la infección por el VIH son bien conocidos,ésta se sigue produciendo e, incluso, aumentando en nuestro país. Las característicasde la epidemia han cambiado y hay muchas más mujeres infectadas por contacto heterosexual.En este trabajo se plantea la cuestión de la visión social de la enfermedad VIH-SIDA y surelación con la evidente dificultad para prevenirla.La metodología utilizada consistió en un análisis de contenido de la prensa escrita, fundamentalmentedurante la semana de celebración del Día Mundial del SIDA, y una entrevistagrupal semiestructurada de nueve jóvenes.La dimensión biológica (disease) de la enfermedad se aborda en pocos artículos, la dimensiónsubjetiva (illness) aparece en algunos más y la mayoría hacen referencia a la dimensión social(sickness), siendo calificada de &#147;inmunodeficiencia moral&#148; o &#147;enfermedad social&#148; dependiendodel grupo que hable sobre la misma.Los jóvenes tienen importantes lagunas de conocimientos básicos y todavía se plantean lasmismas preguntas acerca del contagio de la enfermedad que hace años y persisten algunosmitos.Lo que se sabe acerca del VIH-SIDA no se transmite eficazmente al resto de la población. Losorganismos pertinentes en la materia y algunos grupos de poder social deberían cuestionarsesu parte de responsabilidad en esto</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(8): 10-16, oct. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050153</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Visión social del VIH/SIDA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
