<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-21172</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Value of the intraoperative determination of parathyroid hormone (PTH) in hyperparathyroidism surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: The success in the surgical management of hyperparathyroidism has conventionally required a bilateral neck exploration. The intraoperative monitoring of intact parathyroid hormone (PTHi), allows a less extensive procedure by confirming the complete removal of hypersecreting tissue. METHODS: Plasma samples were obtained from 32 consecutive patients before and 10 minutes after removal of abnormal parathyroid tissue. PTH was measured with a modifie immunochemiluminometric assay with a short incubation time and the results made available in 15 minutes. RESULTS: PTHi decreased by at least 60% in 30 of 32 cases. A single adenoma was removed in 26 cases, and multiple hyperplastic glands in 4 cases. The two cases in which PTHi fell &lt; 60% were diagnosed as hyperplasia. PTHi decreased &gt; 60% after the removal of the remnant hyperplastic glands. CONCLUSIONS: The rapid PTHi assay had excellent analytical performance and predicted the success of parathyroid surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El éxito de la cirugía del hiperparatiroidismo se ha basado tradicionalmente en la exploración bilateral del cuello. La monitorización intraoperatoria de hormona paratiroidea intacta (PTHi), permite la confirmación bioquímica de que todo el tejido paratiroideo hiperfuncionante ha sido resecado, consiguiéndose cirugías menos extensas. Material y métodos: Se obtuvieron muestras de sangre de 32 pacientes antes y 10 minutos después de la exéresis del tejido paratiroideo patológico. La monitorización de PTHi se llevó a cabo mediante inmunoquimioluminiscencia, con un tiempo de incubación corto y resultados disponibles en 15 minutos. Resultados: Los niveles de PTHi descendieron &gt; 60 por ciento en 30 de los 32 pacientes estudiados, 26 casos de adenoma y 4 casos de hiperplasia. Dos casos en los que la PTHi descendió  60 por ciento tras la exéresis de las glándulas hiperplásicas remanentes. Conclusión: El análisis rápido de PTHi es una técnica fácil de realizar y es capaz de predecir el éxito de la cirugía del hiperparatiroidismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;54(4): 273-276, mar. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor de la determinación intraoperatoria de hormona paratiroidea en la cirugía del hiperparatiroidismo</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>López Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Gutierrez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver Oliver, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canós Llacer, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Ramírez, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-21172</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d20180</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28998</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7140^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7140^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10470</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
