<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142782</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional intake of north african migrants in Almeria: comparative study in the native place and with the spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To compare calorie, macronutrient and micronutrient intake among Moroccan immigrants in Almeria, Spain to the intake in their country of origin (Morocco), international recommendations and intake among the host population. Methods: Cross-sectional study including 95 Moroccan in Almeria (MA) and 30 in Morocco (MM). Dietary intake was recorded by using a weekly food frequency questionnaire and a 24-recall questionnaire; intake of calories and nutrients was calculated using computer software. Results: Fat and calorie intake among immigrants residing in Almeria is significantly higher than that in Morocco (p &lt;0.01); protein intake was the same, whereas carbohydrate intake was less (p &lt;0.01). They present micronutrient and vitamin D deficiencies according to the RDI and to Spanish consumption patterns (p &lt;0.01). Conclusions: When Moroccan immigrants move to Almeria, they follow a &#147;transitional diet&#148; which is closer to the internationally recommended intake and to the patterns of the Mediterranean diet, which has increased carbohydrates consumption and less saturated fat and animal protein consumption than that found in the Western diet (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Rodríguez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Soto, Mª Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Izquierdo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Checa Olmos, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Jiménez, Amalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrón Carreño, Tesifón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la ingesta de energía y nutrientes de los inmigrantes marroquíes en Almería con respecto al país de origen, Marruecos, comparando su adecuación a las ingestas dietéticas recomendadas (IDRS) y al consumo nutricional de los españoles. Metodología: Estudio epidemiológico transversal en 95 marroquíes en Almería (MA) y 30 en Marruecos (MM). Para determinar la ingesta alimentaria se ha utilizado un cuestionario de frecuencia de consumo de alimentos semanal y un recuerdo de consumo de 24 horas, con valoración de la ingesta de calorías y nutrientes mediante programa informatizado. Resultados: Los inmigrantes residentes en Almería tienen una ingesta calórica y de grasas significativamente mayor que en Marruecos (p&lt;0.01). Presentan déficit de micronutrientes y vitamina D respecto a la IDR y al consumo de los españoles. Conclusiones: Los inmigrados marroquíes, cuando se trasladan a Almería, realizan una &#147;dieta de transición&#148; que se adapta mejor a las ingestas recomendadas internacionalmente y al patrón alimentario de la dieta mediterránea, con aumento del consumo de hidratos de carbono y menos grasas saturadas y proteínas de origen animal que la dieta occidental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;19(2): 120-127, abr.-jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142782</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta nutricional de migrados marroquíes en Almería: estudio comparativo en el lugar de origen y con la población española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
