<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89192</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thirty years of diabetes in spanish law (1979-2009 Review)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Medicine and Law are branches of the knowledge that far from walking of an independent way, at every time are more interconnected. This fact, that in Medicine affects to anyone of the medical disciplines, has great importance in chronic pathologies like diabetes with a progression that has the development of multiple complications of medical conflict and administrative procedures of them derived that are not correctly managed, end at legal channels. It would be better to become familiarize with legal and jurisprudential search in Medicine, and as it has become a common situation and systematized form with the bibliometrical and bibliographical search through the internet portal of prestige, that the Pub-Med is the reference one, without a doubt, for the sanitary profession. The jurisprudential revision of the diabetes and its complications  in the four jurisdictional orders: penal, social, Administrative contentious and civil, allows to approach all the shades derived from the confliction of the pathology and can act with a basic legal and preventive knowledge before consequences within the complex management of the diabetic patient, who has repercussions, for the own involved sanitary professional, like company and society which finally fall the economic costs of this type of procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Capdevila García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejedo Benedicto, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñaga Sole, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramirez Iñiguez de la Torre, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, A. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Herrero, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terridillos García, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Jiménez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Alberich, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La medicina y el derecho son ramas del conocimiento que, lejos de caminar de una forma independiente, están cada vez más interconectadas. Este hecho, que en medicina afecta a todas las especialidades médicas, es de especial trascendencia en patologías crónicas como la diabetes, con un curso evolutivo tendente  al desarrollo de múltiples complicaciones que generan conflictos médicos y derivan con frecuencia en procedimientos administrativos que, si no son correctamente gestionados, desembocan en la vía judicial. Conviene, pues, familiarizarse con la búsqueda jurídica y jurisprudencial en medicina, como ya se hace de forma habitual y sistematizada con la búsqueda bibliométrica y bibliográfica a través de los portales de prestigio al uso, entre los que sin duda PubMed es el referente para la profesión sanitaria. La revisión jurisprudencial de la diabetes y sus complicaciones en los cuatro órdenes jurisdiccionales: penal, social, contencioso-administrativo  y civil, permite valorar todos los matices derivados de la conflictividad de la patología y actuar con un conocimiento básico jurídico y preventivo ante posteriores consecuencias, tanto para el propio profesional sanitario implicado como para la empresa y la sociedad en la que finalmente recaen los costes económicos de este tipo de procedimientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;19(1): 25-33, feb. 2010. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89192</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Treinta años de diabetes en la jurisprudencia española (revisión 1979-2009)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8062^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52952^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
