<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138305</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anoxic encephalopathy after ultraviolet radiation session: follow-up and results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anoxic encephalopathy is the consequence of acute cerebral oxygen deprivation usually generated by cardiac arrest and/or respiratory failure. Recently an interesting case of one patient with cerebral anoxia after ultraviolet radiation session has been published. This paper shows the clinical evolution of this patient after inclusion in a multidisciplinary rehabilitation program, which included treatment of the psychopathological, neuropsychological and functional impairments that this pathology often generates. Over successive decades cerebral anoxia has come to be identified principally as one of the most significant causes of an isolated amnesia syndrome. Our patient presented at baseline intense difficulties in every verbal and visual memory processes associated with moderate impairments in sustained, selective and shifting attention as well as temporal disorientation. Compensation of memory deficit was the main rehabilitation strategy used in this case. This rehabilitation approach was possible thanks to the high degree of self-awareness of memory deficits shown by the patient and the selective impairment of memory with partial preservation of the rest of cognitive functions. This particular case gives us the opportunity to show the multidisciplinary approach of cognitive rehabilitation and the process of reintegration to social activities and to productive work even when deficits persist (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chirivella Garrido, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noé Sebastián, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri Campos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Coulón, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La encefalopatía anóxica se produce tras una deprivación cerebral aguda de oxígeno generada comúnmente por una insuficiencia cardiocirculatoria y/o respiratoria. Recientemente se ha publicado un interesante caso de una mujer que sufrió una posible encefalopatía anóxica tras una sesión de rayos ultravioleta. En este trabajo presentamos la evolución clínica de la paciente tras su inclusión en un programa de rehabilitación multidisciplinar abordando el tratamiento del amplio espectro de alteraciones cognitivas, psicopatológicas y funcionales que esta patología puede generar. Durante mucho tiempo el síndrome anoxoisquémico ha sido el paradigma clínico con el que muchos tratados de neurología han estudiado el síndrome amnésico hipocámpico. En nuestro caso la paciente presentaba al ingreso intensas dificultades en todos los procesos mnésicos tanto verbales como visuales asociados a una moderada desorientación temporal y a ligeras deficiencias en atención sostenida, selectiva y alternante. La estrategia de rehabilitación fundamental y decisiva en la evolución de la paciente fue la compensación del déficit facilitada por su adecuada conciencia de enfermedad y por la especificidad de la afectación cognitiva sobre tareas mnésicas con relativa preservación del resto de funciones. La presentación de este peculiar caso nos da la ocasión de mostrar el enfoque global de la rehabilitación y la recuperación de la normalidad de la vida diaria, aun cuando los déficit persistan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(6): 318-322, jul.-ago. 2006. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138305</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encefalopatía hipoxico-isquémica tras session de rayos ultraviolet: evolución y seguimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2571^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2571^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14865^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2571^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2571^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
