<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055454</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fournier's gangrene. Experience of the CMN SXXI Hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To evaluate and review the Fournier´s gangrene clinical presentation, initial APACHEII score and integral treatment of patients affected in HECMNSXXI.METHODS: Retrospective, descriptive and cross-sectionalstudy in 40 patients with Fournier´s gangrene diagnosis,accepted for treatment in HECMNSXXI who gatherinclusion criteria, from February 1996 to February 2006.RESULTS: Patients were between 21 and 93 yr old. In total 39 men and 1 woman were recruited. The most common etiologic factor was urethral stricture in 40% of patients. escherichia coli was detected in 42.5 % of the cultures, and represented the most common pathogen. Initial Apache II score was more commonly between 10 and 14 points (35%). 6 patients died (15%) all of them with and Apache II score above 25 points. 55% of patientswere affected by diabetes mellitus. All patients with Fournier´s Gangrene received a triple antibiotic schema from admittance day, associated with emergency surgicaldèbridement in the whole group.CONCLUSIONS: Aggressive and multidisciplinary treatment is mandatory in all the patients affected by Fournier´s gangrene. We recommend utilisation of the APACHE II score as very useful tool to determine the prognosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ixquiac-Pineda, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Brambila, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peralta-Alarcón, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya&#150;Martínez, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado-Alcaraz, Efraín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Sámano, Virgilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Evaluar la presentación clínica de la gangrena de Fournier, la escala de APACHE II al ingreso de los pacientes y el manejo integral en el HE CMN SXXI.MÉTODOS: Estudios retrospectivo, transversal, descriptivoen 40 pacientes con diagnóstico de gangrena de Fournier ingresados en el Hospital de Especialidades del CMN SXXI que reunieron los criterios de inclusión, entre febrero de 1996 a febrero del 2006.RESULTADOS: El rango de edad osciló entre 21 y 93 años, siendo 39 pacientes del sexo masculino y una del sexo femenino. La etiología mas común encontrada de los pacientes estudiados fue estenosis de uretra 40%. El germen patógeno que se desarrolló en los cultivos fue principalmente Escherichia coli (42.5%). La calificación de acuerdo a la escala de Apache II al ingreso fue predominantemente de 10-14 puntos (35%). La mortalidadfue de 15% que corresponde a 6 pacientes, todos con escala de Apache II mayor a 25 puntos. El factor más importante asociado a la morbilidad fue diabetes mellitus (55%). Todos los pacientes recibieron terapia con antibióticos triple esquema desde su ingreso al servicio,asociado al manejo quirúrgico de urgencia en el 100%.CONCLUSIONES: El tratamiento agresivo y multidisciplinarioes obligatorio en los pacientes con diagnóstico de gangrena de Fournier. Se recomienda la utilización de la clasificación de Apache II ya que es una herramientaútil para determinar el pronóstico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(5): 525-530, jun. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055454</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gangrena de Fournier: experiencia en el Hospital de Especialidades del CMN SXXI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3270^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32745^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21035^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7887^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
