<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91441</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive learning in nutrient-based flavor conditioning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents two experiments on nutrient-based flavor conditioning with rats as subjects and sucrose as the unconditioned stimulus (US). Experiment 1 was aimed at establishing an optimal control for conditioning, comparing simultaneous and serial presentations of a flavor and the US. The results showed that simultaneous, but not serial training, produced conditioning. Experiment 2 was designed to obtain evidence of summation as an index of both conditioned inhibition and predictive learning. Group Simultaneous received Pavlovian conditioned inhibition training during which flavor A was simultaneously paired with sucrose on excitatory trials (A+), and forming an unreinforced compound with flavor B on inhibitory trials (AB-). An independent excitor for the summation test was also trained by simultaneous pairings with sucrose (C+). In the control group (Blocked), the AB- trials were presented forming a block at the beginning of training to avoid a negative contingency-relationship with sucrose, and flavor A received serial rather than simultaneous pairing with sucrose (A --&gt; +). On the summation test, only in group Simultaneous was consumption of the CB compound lower than that of flavor C alone, suggesting that, during training, flavor A activated an expectancy of the US occurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Burgos, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Reyes, Felisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan dos experimentos de condicionamiento al sabor basado en nutrientes con ratas. El Experimento 1 estableció una condición de control óptima para el condicionamiento comparando presentaciones simultáneas y seriales de un sabor y sacarosa. El procedimiento de entrenamiento simultáneo, pero no el serial, produjo condicionamiento. El Experimento 2 se diseñó para obtener evidencias de sumación como índice tanto de inhibición condicionada como de aprendizaje predictivo. El grupo simultáneo recibió entrenamiento en inhibición condicionada Pavloviana: el sabor A se presentó simultáneamente con sacarosa en los ensayos excitatorios (A+), y formando un compuesto no reforzado con el sabor B en los ensayos inhibitorios (AB-). Se entrenó también un excitador independiente para la prueba de sumación mediante emparejamientos simultáneos con sacarosa (C+). En el grupo control los ensayos AB- fueron presentados formando un bloque al inicio del entrenamiento, y el sabor A recibió emparejamientos seriales con la sacarosa en lugar de simultáneos (A --&gt; +). En la prueba de sumación, el consumo del compuesto CB fue menor que el del sabor C en solitario solo en el grupo simultáneo, sugiriendo que durante el entrenamiento el sabor A activó una expectativa de la ocurrencia de la sacaros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(4): 759-764, oct.-dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aprendizaje predictivo en condicionamiento al sabor basado en nutrientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13780^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13930^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3240^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
