<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039825</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acneiform eruption from epidermal growth factor receptor inhibitors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the fundamental aims of oncological research is the search for molecules with greater efficacy against tumors and less toxicity than the usual chemotherapeutic agents. Epidermal growth factor receptor inhibitors are a new group of drugs which, because of their more specific effect against neoplastic cells, seem to meet these characteristics. Skin eruptions are one of the most frequent adverse effects associated with their use, secondary to the drug's direct inhibitory effect on homeostasis of the epidermis and of the pilosebaceous follicle.         Several cases of cutaneous toxicity in patients treated with epidermal growth factor receptor inhibitors have recently been published. We present three cases of acneiform eruptions attributable to different drugs in this family (cetuximab, gefitinib and erlotinib)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Lagrán, Zuriñe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lasa, Olatz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acebo, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Pérez, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ratón, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los objetivos fundamentales de la investigación oncológica es la búsqueda de moléculas con mayor eficacia antitumoral y menor toxicidad que los agentes quimioterápicos habituales. Los inhibidores del receptor de crecimiento epidérmico son un nuevo grupo de fármacos que, por su efecto más específico frente a las células neoplásicas, parecen cumplir estas características. Entre los efectos adversos asociados a su uso, destacan por su frecuencia las erupciones cutáneas, secundarias a un efecto inhibitorio directo del fármaco sobre la homeostasis de la epidermis y del folículo pilosebáceo 1,2.         Recientemente se han publicado varios casos de toxicidad cutánea en pacientes tratados con inhibidores del receptor de crecimiento epidérmico. Presentamos 3 casos de erupciones acneiformes atribuibles a diferentes fármacos de esta familia (cetuximab, gefitinib y erlotinib)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;96(7): 450-454, sept. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Erupción acneiforme por inhibidores del receptor de crecimiento epidérmico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24479^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28920^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30320^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6281^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30873^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
