<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64831</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infants and children with moderate pneumonia can be safely cared for at home and should be re-examined within 48 hours of the beginning of treatment. An SaO2 of 92% or less, cyanosis, respiratory rate greater than70 breaths per minute, difficulty in breathing, intermittent apnea, grunting, inability to eat, and a family incapable of providing appropriate observation or supervision are indicators for hospital admission among infants. In the case of older children, theses indicators are an SaO2 of 92% or less, cyanosis, respiratory rate greater than 50 breaths per minute, difficulty in the intake of fluids or solids, grunting, signs of dehydration, or a family incapable of providing either appropriate observation or supervision. Since viruses are the sole cause of many cases of pneumonia in childhood, it is not appropriate to treat every child with antibiotics. However, therapeutic decisions can be difficult, because most tests do not adequately differentiate viral from bacterial infection in a given child. The problem of bacterial resistance to antibiotics has increased steadily in recent years, and it is certainly related to their overuse in situations in which viral involvement is quite probable or the illness is trivial and self-limiting, such as an upper respiratory infection. Hence, it is preferable to restrict antibiotics as much as possible and to use narrow-spectrum agents whenever appropriate, because less antibiotic pressure limits the emergence of bacterial resistance. Finally, we comment on the general management of pneumonias depending on the age, the impact on the general condition of the patient and the radiological pattern, laboratory data and the epidemiology of these infections in our general population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rueda Esteban, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Chércoles, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel Lavisier, B de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balboa de Paz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los niños con neumonía y afectación media o moderada pueden ser cuidados en su domicilio con seguridad y reexaminados a las 48 horas del inicio del tratamiento. En los niños pequeños, una afectación más intensa &#150;como tener una SaO2 &lt;92%, cianosis, polipnea &gt;70 rpm, esfuerzo respiratorio, apneas intermitentes, quejido, incapacidad para ingerir alimentos y limitación para observación o supervisión familiar&#150; es indicación para su ingreso hospitalario. En los niños más mayores, estas indicaciones serían una SaO2 &lt;92%, cianosis, polipnea &gt;50 rpm, dificultad para ingerir líquidos o alimentos, quejido, signos de deshidratación o dificultad familiar para su observación o supervisión. Como los virus son la causa única de muchos casos de neumonía en la infancia no parece apropiado tratar a cada niño con antibióticos. Las decisiones terapéuticas en un niño concreto pueden ser difíciles, pues la mayoría de las pruebas no son útiles para diferenciar de modo adecuado las infecciones virales de las bacterianas. La resistencia antibacteriana se ha incrementado constantemente en los últimos años y está relacionada con su uso abusivo en situaciones en que la afectación viral es muy probable o la enfermedad es leve y limitada a vías superiores. Por esta razón, es preferible restringir los antibióticos tanto como sea posible y, si se usan, utilizar agentes de espectro estrecho siempre que sea posible, pues la menor presión antibiótica limita la emergencia de resistencia antibiótica. Finalmente, se comenta el enfoque terapéutico de las neumonías, de acuerdo con la edad, la repercusión sobre el estado general, el patrón radiológico, los datos de laboratorio y la epidemiología de estas infecciones en nuestro medio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;66(1): 4-12, ene. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64831</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3510^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1056^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13147^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36322^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
