<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040017</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is conventional hemodialysis an appropriate dialysis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Conventional hemodialysis, three sessions per week through a low-flux membrane,is the dialysis method most widely used. However, its efficacy is limited.The concept of dialysis adequacy exclusively based on the concept of Kt/V is toorestrictive. Other solutes such as middle molecules should also be considered. Parameterssuch as phosphate and hypertension are very difficult to control with theconventional schedules. Observational studies demonstrate both a high morbidityand mortality. It is necessary a qualitative leap forward from the current conceptof «adequate dialysis» to a more modern of «optimal dialysis». Different strategiesthan those shown in recent prospective studies are needed to achieve that goal</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrés, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemodiálisis convencional, tres sesiones de 4 horas por semana con membranade flujo bajo, es el régimen dialítico más utilizado. No obstante, su eficaciaes limitada. El concepto de adecuación basado exclusivamente en el KtV esexcesivamente restrigido. Debe prestarse atención a otros solutos como las moléculasmedianas. Parámetros como el fosfato o la hipertensión arterial son de difícilcontrol con el esquema convencional. Los estudios observacionales revelan unamorbilidad y mortalidad elevadas. Es necesario un salto cualitativo para evolucionardel concepto de diálisis adecuada al de diálisis óptima. Para conseguirlo seprecisan otras estrategias distintas de las ensayadas en estudios prospectivos recientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;25(supl.2): 10-14, jun. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿La hemodiálisis convencional es diálisis adecuada?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10905^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14910^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4072</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
