<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049616</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacogenomics in neuro-oncology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and development. Chemotherapy protocols for treatment of brain tumors use toxic molecules forkilling cancer cells in a similar way that protocols for treating other cancers. Therefore, secondary effects and poor responseare the major handicaps. Technological developments based on pharmacogenomics and pharmacoproteomics will predictresponse and toxicity giving rise to a personalized medicine. However, there are only few studies that correlate chemotherapeuticalmolecules for brain tumor treatment and prediction of response and toxicity. Conclusions. The development ofnew technologies based on high-density microarrays allows the progressive identification of genes whose presence will predictthe efficacy of therapeutic protocols. Once identified, specific equipments based on low-density arrays will detect exclusivelyin an easy and fast way the presence of genes in order to predict patient&#146;s response and avoid toxicity. Other moresophisticated techniques at present still at an experimental step based on proteomics as MALDI (Matrix-Assisted LaserDesorption Ionization) and SELDI (Surface-Enhanced Laser Desorption Ionization) will allow the identification of proteinsthat could predict response and toxicity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Báez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riese, H. H Báez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y desarrollo. Los protocolos de quimioterapiaen el tratamiento de los tumores cerebrales, como en los deotras localizaciones, emplean moléculas tóxicas para matar célulascancerosas. Pero, al igual que sucede con todos los tratamientoscontra el cáncer, la aparición de efectos secundarios y la ausenciade respuesta son los principales problemas para su eficacia.Su predicción va a ser posible gracias a los avances tecnológicosque se apoyan en la farmacogenómica y farmacoproteómica, dandolugar a la medicina personalizada. Sin embargo, todavía sonpocos los estudios que relacionan moléculas activas para el tratamientode tumores cerebrales y la posibilidad de predecir el porcentajede respuesta y de toxicidad. Conclusiones. El desarrollo denuevas tecnologías basadas en los microarrays de alta densidadestá logrando la identificación de genes cuya presencia permitirápredecir el efecto de determinado protocolo terapéutico. Una vezidentificados, equipos de arrays de baja densidad detectarán exclusivamentelos genes que pueden intervenir en la capacidad derespuesta del paciente y la posibilidad de presentar cuadros tóxicos.Otras técnicas sofisticadas en fase más experimental, que sebasan en el estudio de proteínas (proteómica), como las MALDI(Matrix-Assisted Laser Desorption Ionization) y las SELDI (Surface-Enhanced Laser Desorption Ionization), permitirán reconocerproteínas asociadas a la predicción de respuesta y de toxicidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(6): 353-356, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Farmacogenómica en neurooncología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10788</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
