<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058890</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability of post-transfusional hematocrit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the blood transfusion diseases, basically AIDS, have arisen in our society, the decision to administer a transfusion to a patient not only requires an informed consent but also must be fully justified and documented. This implies that, except for emergencies, the hematocrit value must be measured previously. However, if the patient has just received a transfusion and due to the phenomenon of hemoconcentration, the reliability of this analysis during the first hours following the transfusion period is questionable. In fact, and according to the health care site in question, this time varies from a half hour to up to six hours. Not in vain, up to now, we only have one study that approaches this subject applying the scientific method, although it is limited to pediatrics. Our research team has established the purposes of «knowing the variations of the post-transfusional hematocrit in relationship with time», beginning with the hypothesis «the post-transfusional hematocrit value does not undergo relevant modifications as a consequence of the passing of time.» Based on the quantitative approach, we designed an experimental study in which we considered the hematocrit value as the dependent variable and time as the independent variable. As a result, we obtain that the comparison between the immediate analysis and the subsequent ones does not offer statistically significant differences. We conclude that it is possible to make the analysis coinciding with the end of the transfusion, with total reliability</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torné Pérez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfonso Dalda, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo Macías, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alaminos Romero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde que las enfermedades hemotransmisibles, fundamentalmente el sida, han irrumpido en nuestra sociedad, la decisión de transfundir a un paciente, además de precisar el consentimiento informado, ha de estar plenamente justificada y documentada. Esto implica que, salvo emergencias, es preceptivo determinar el valor del hematocrito previamente, pero si al paciente acaba de recibir una transfusión, y debido al fenómeno de la hemoconcentración, es frecuente que se cuestione la fiabilidad de este análisis durante las primeras horas del período postransfusional. De hecho, y según el centro sanitario de que se trate, ese tiempo varía desde la media hora hasta las 6 horas. No en vano, hasta la fecha sólo disponemos de un estudio que aborda este tema aplicando el método científico, aunque lo limita a la Pediatría. Nuestro equipo investigador se trazó como objetivo «conocer las variaciones del hematocrito postransfusional en relación con el tiempo», partiendo de la hipótesis «el valor del hematocrito postransfusional no sufre modificaciones relevantes como consecuencia del transcurso del tiempo». Apoyándonos en el enfoque cuantitativo diseñamos un estudio experimental en el que consideramos como variable dependiente el valor del hematocrito, y como variable independiente el tiempo. Como resultado obtenemos que la comparación entre el análisis inmediato y los posteriores no ofrece diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Concluimos que es posible realizar el análisis en el mismo momento de finalizar la transfusión, con total fiabilidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;18(4): 182-186, oct.2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058890</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad del hematocrito postransfusional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6550^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30229^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6588^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
