<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055532</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adenomatoid tumor of the epididymis. Report of two cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Tumors of the epididymis are rare. They are ususally benign and adenomatoid tumors are the most frequent. Report of two cases of this kind of tumor of the epididymis. METHODS/RESULTS: We report two cases of adenomatoid tumor of the epididymis diagnosed at our hospital during last year. Two males, 35 and 54 years old respectively asked for urology consultation about a palpable scrotal mass. They didn´t have any other symptoms. Imaging techniques revealeda solid epididymal mass. Epidydimectomy was performed. Pathological diagnosis was adenomatoid tumor. CONCLUSIONS: The majority of epipidydimal tumors follow a benign course. In the finding of an epididymal mass, after palpation and imaging tests, organ sparing surgery (epididymectomy) is recommended. We will avoid unnecessary orchiectomies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arellano Gañán, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bocardo Fajardo, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Gálvez, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Sanz, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Fernández, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Abad, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Los tumores de epidídimo constituyenuna entidad de rara aparición. Son en su mayoría benignos y de entre estos los más frecuentes son los tumores adenomatoides. Presentamos dos casos de este tipo de tumor epididimario. MÉTODO/RESULTADOS: Presentamos dos casos de tumor adenomatoide de epidídimo diagnosticados en nuestro hospital en el último año. Se trata de dos varones de 35 y 54 años, que acudieron a la consulta de urología por autopalpaciónde masa intraescrotal, en los que se diagnostica este tipo de tumor tras la realización de epidimectomía, en el estudio histopatológico. CONCLUSIONES: La mayoría de los tumores de epidídimopresentan una evolución benigna. Ante el hallazgo de masa epididimaria tras exploración física y pruebas de imagen es recomendable la realización de cirugía conservadora testicular, mediante epididimectomía. Evitaremos de este modo orquiectomías innecesarias</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(6): 700-703, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor adenomatoide de epidídimo. Aportación de dos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31677^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4902^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4902^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31677^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13902^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
