<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126142</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of a child abuse prevention programme in an educational context</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyses the effectiveness of a child abuse prevention programme in an educational context. The proposal for action is based on the use of stories as an instrument of primary prevention. The programme aims to improve a child&#146;s capacity to face potentially threatening situations and was applied in 10 primary schools of Extremadura (Spain) to 317 pupils aged 9 and 10 years old. There were 12 sessions whose aim was for the children to gain an awareness of abuse, identify situations of abuse and learn strategies to face them. This was done through the use of tutorials and by linking the programme to the aims of the pupils&#146; educational stage. The evaluation of the programme shows that the pupils in the experimental group resolved the situations with increasing skill, confidence and determination; and that they could see more clearly where to look for help in terms of protection measures. The tutors evaluated the programme positively, considering the contents useful for prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Manso, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Baamonde, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozueco-Romero, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blázquez-Alonso, Macarena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio analiza la eficacia de un programa de prevención del maltrato infantil en el contexto educativo. La propuesta de actuación parte de la utilización del cuento como instrumento para la prevención primaria. El programa trata de mejorar las capacidades de los niños para enfrentarse a situaciones potencialmente amenazantes. El programa fue aplicado en 10 colegios de Educación Primaria de Extremadura (España), a un conjunto de 317 alumnos de 9 y 10 años. Se estructura en 12 sesiones en las que se trata de que los niños tomen conciencia del maltrato, identifiquen situaciones de abuso y aprendan estrategias de afrontamiento, utilizando para ello la acción tutorial y vinculando el programa a los objetivos de la etapa educativa de los alumnos. La evaluación del programa, demuestra cómo los alumnos del grupo experimental resuelven las situaciones con mayor habilidad, confianza y firmeza, y tienen más claro cuáles son las fuentes de ayuda a las que recurrir como medida de protección. Los tutores valoran positivamente el programa, considerando los contenidos útiles para la prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(3): 1014-1024, sept.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126142</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de un programa de prevención del maltrato infantil en el contexto educativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35416</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37622^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37586</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
