<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79220</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology and classification for diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetes is a chronic metabolic disorder cause by an absolute or relative insulin deficit. Diabetes is characterized by the presence of hyperglycemia and by metabolic alterations regarding all the immediate principle nutrients: carbohydrates, lipids and proteins. Diabetes causes high morbidity and mortality derived by chronic micro-vascular complications such as retinopathy, nephropathy, or neuropathy and macro-vascular complications such as ischemic cardiac problems, cerebral vascular accidents, peripheral vascular disorders. The layman&#146;s belief that diabetes occurred only due to hereditary factors has been changing as numerous studies have shown that diabetes deals with a group of heterogeneous disorders which develop as a combination of hereditary and environmental factors(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castell, Conxa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes es un trastorno crónico del metabolismo debido a un déficit absoluto o relativo de insulina. Se caracteriza por presentar hiperglucemia y alteración del metabolismo de todos los principios inmediatos: hidratos de carbono, lípidos y proteínas. Causa elevada morbilidad y mortalidad derivadas de las complicaciones crónicas microvasculares (retinopatía, nefropatía, neuropatía) y macrovasculares (cardiopatía isquémica, accidente vascular cerebral, vasculopatía periférica). La creencia secular de que la diabetes era debida sólo a factores hereditarios ha ido cambiando a medida que numerosos estudios han mostrado que se trata de un grupo heterogéneo de trastornos que resultan de la intercurrencia de factores genéticos y ambientales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(2): 89-95, feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79220</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología y clasificación de la diabetes mellitas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30157^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30157^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29491^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30157^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
