<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75010</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Micotoxins research in humans</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Micotoxins research in humansThis study investigates the occurrence of aflatoxines in Ecuador. Earlyinvestigators proved the presence of aflatoxins on human and animal food, butthe disturbing data lead to the formation of two research teams at GuayaquilUniversity and the Agrarian University of Ecuador to investigate aflaxotins andother mycotoxins on food and its relationship to human health. Because theconcept of mycotoxicosis as a result of the secondary metabolites producedby different species of moulds could cause different clinical patterns, theresearch team includes Aspergillus metabolites found in the urine for a patientwith pulmonary aspergilloma. We considered that the body itself could createsecondary metabolites. An ELISA method was used to detect mycotoxins withthe specific reactive compounds using a company base assay. This allows thedetection quantitative of such metabolites in 24 h collected urine. The patientwas treated with itraconazol for nine months, after clinical, radiological andaflatoxins testing. We also investigated three other cases in children with asecond level of malnutrition and only with vomitoxins results and on threeinvestigated cases of otomycosis caused by Aspergillus niger only in one casetraces of aflatoxins was found(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lazo, Ramón F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de esta investigación es estudiar la presencia de las aflatoxinasen Ecuador. El escaso conocimiento en nuestro país a este respecto,nos llevó a un equipo de investigadores de las universidades de Guayaquil yAgraria del Ecuador, a realizar un proyecto de investigación, titulado&#147;Las aflatoxinas y otras micotoxinas en los alimentos y su relación con lasalud humana en nuestro medio&#148;. Siendo la micotoxicosis aquella intoxicaciónresultante de la ingesta de los metabolitos secundarios producidos pordiferentes especies de mohos que generan diferentes cuadros clínicos,¿por qué no investigar metabolitos de Aspergillus en la orina de una pacientecon aspergiloma pulmonar? Consideramos que el propio organismo podríagenerar metabolitos secundarios, por lo que incluimos en este estudio nuestrocaso de aspergiloma pulmonar comprobado. La determinación de lasmicotoxinas se realizó por ELISA, utilizando reactivos específicos de NeogenCorporation, que permiten determinaciones cuantitativas en orina. Se instauróa la paciente tratamiento con itraconazol durante nueve meses, realizandocontroles clínicos, radiológicos y determinación de aflatoxinas. Se estudiaron,también, tres casos de niños con desnutrición en grado III, detectándoseúnicamente la presencia de vomitoxina. Además, se encontraron trazas deaflatoxinas en uno de tres casos de otomicosis por Aspergillus niger(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;25(1): 7-11, 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75010</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Investigación del efecto de las micotoxinas en el ser humano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9375^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1235^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d353^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24791^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31378^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
