<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044131</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient in maintenance programme with methadone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The case of a patient addicted to heroine, receiving maintenance treatment with methadone and diagnosed as HIV positive since 1991, is presented. Material and methods: The toxicological history of a 43 year old male is revised, as is his organic and psychiatric pathology and the social problem that his dependency has produced. Results: After describing the patient's toxicological history in detail, the principal diagnosis is carried out along with that of other concomitant psychiatric disorders following the DSM-IV criteria. The possibilities for treatment of the opiate dependency disorder are mentioned, and the substitution treatment with agonists (methadone) is analysed in detail. Conclusions: For the patient addicted to heroine, the priority is to maintain adherence to the treatment, as this will achieve a reduction or suppression of the consumption, health control of accompanying pathologies and an improvement in the social conflict situation, all of which will result in an improvement in the quality of life. The substitution treatment with agonists (methadone, buprenorphine, etc.) has shown itself to be useful in this sense since, on alleviating the symptoms of abstinence and blocking the desire to consume opiates, it has been well accepted among these patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arranz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Se presenta el caso clínico de un paciente varón de 43 años, heroinómano en tratamiento de mantenimiento con metadona, diagnosticado de infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) desde 1991. Material y métodos: Se revisa la historia toxicológica del paciente, así como su patología orgánica y psiquiátrica y la problemática social que su dependencia le ha producido. Resultados: Después de describir detalladamente la historia toxicológica del paciente, se realiza el diagnóstico principal y el de otros trastornos psiquiátricos concomitantes según criterios DSM-IV. Se mencionan las posibilidades de tratamiento para el trastorno por dependencia de opiáceos, y se analiza con detalle el tratamiento sustitutivo con agonistas (metadona). Conclusiones: En el paciente heroinómano, un objetivo prioritario es la adherencia al tratamiento ya que con ello se consigue una reducción o supresión del consumo, un control sanitario de sus patologías concomitantes y una mejora de la conflictiva social, lo que redundará en una mejora en su calidad de vida. Los tratamientos sustitutivos con agonistas (metadona, buprenorfina, etc.) han demostrado ser muy útiles en este sentido ya que al aliviar los síntomas de abstinencia y bloquear el deseo de consumir opiáceos tienen muy buena aceptación en estos pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;7(4): 211-218, oct. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044131</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paciente en programa de mantenimiento con metadona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6715^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
