<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048316</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prospects of adjusted clinical groups (ACG´s) in capitated payment risk adjustment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Most patient classification systems have beendesigned in the United States for the purpose of availing of a toolproviding a means of gauging the use of resources. This study wasaimed at calculating the mean relative weights (MRW´s) for thecost of care at several primary care health facilities as compared tothose in the U.S. by using the Adjusted Clinical Groups (ACG´s) asa possible capitated payment risk adjustment.Methods: Descriptive study. All of the clinical records generatedby four primary care facilities throughout 2003 were included.The main measurements were: age and gender, resources (visits andcosts) and casuistics. The cost model was determined for each individualpatient by differentiating the fixed and variable costs. Aregression analysis was made for model adjustment purposes. Therelative cost of each ACG was calculated by dividing the mean costof each category by the mean cost of the population as a whole.Results: A total of 62,311 records were studied, revealing anaverage of 4.8±3.2 diagnoses and 7.8±7.5 visits/patient/year. Thetotal expense was 24.1 million euros, the fixed and semi-fixed coststotaling 28.9% and the variable costs 71.1%. The mean totalcost/patient/year was 387.34±145.87? (reference). The adjustedexplicative power of the cost of care between the two classifications(U.S. classification vs. the one studied) was 64.3%; p=0,000).Conclusions: The generalization of the results must be carefullyconstrued. ACG´s show themselves to be a suitable tool, and themean U.S. RW´s could be used for adjusting capitated payment riskadjustments in view of the difficulty of availing of full, consistentdatabases in our environment. Further research would be required toback up the consistency of the results</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llopart-López, Josep Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sicras-Mainar, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Artieda, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrat-Tarrés, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La mayoría de los sistemas de clasificación depacientes han sido diseñados en Estados Unidos con la finalidad dedisponer de una herramienta que facilite una medida en la utilizaciónde los recursos. El objeto del estudio fue obtener los pesos relativos(PR) medios del coste de la asistencia en varios equipos de atenciónprimaria de salud, en comparación con los americanos, mediante laaplicación de los Grupos Clínicos Ajustados (ACGs), como un posibleajuste de riesgos de pago capitativo.Métodos: Estudio descriptivo. Se incluyeron todas las historiasclínicas generadas por cuatro equipos de atención primaria durante elaño 2003. Las principales mediciones fueron: edad y sexo, recursos(visitas y costes) y casuística. El modelo de costes para cada pacientese estableció diferenciando los costes fijos y variables. Se efectuóun análisis de regresión para la corrección del modelo. El coste relativode cada ACG se obtuvo dividiendo el coste medio de cada categoríaentre el coste medio de toda la población de referencia.Resultados: El número total de historias estudiadas fue de62.311, con una media de 4,8±3,2 diagnósticos y 7,8±7,5visitas/paciente/año. El gasto total fue de 24,1 millones de euros, loscostes fijos o semifijos representan el 28,9% y los variables el71,1%. El promedio de coste total por paciente/año fue de387,34±145,87? (referencia). El poder explicativo corregido delcoste de la asistencia entre las dos clasificaciones (estadounidenserespecto a la estudiada) fue del 64,3%; p=0,000).Conclusiones: La generalización de los resultados debe de interpretarsecon prudencia. Los ACGs se muestran como un instrumentoadecuado y podrían utilizarse los PR medios estadounidenses parael ajuste del riesgo en el pago capitativo, ante la dificultad de tenerbases de datos amplias y consistentes en nuestro medio. Sería necesarioesperar nuevas investigaciones que refuercen la consistencia delos resultados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(1): 55-65, ene.-feb. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048316</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posibilidades de los grupos clínicos ajustados (ajusted clinical groups-acgs) en el ajuste de riesgos de pago capitativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2237</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30327^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
