<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139957</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: dying is, in fact, a most difficult event to confront, and has a psychological impact, releasing an intense flow of emotions both in the patient and his or her family that may cause psychological stress, emotional destructuration, and lots of suffering. This complexity is the reason underlying the need for psychologists in palliative care teams (PCTs). Objective: to identify PCTs including psychologists in their staff, the roles that these professionals play, and cases susceptible of specific psychological interventions. Method: an observational, descriptive study was carried out using a survey that included all PCTs in Spain. Results: 201 of all 262 PCTs surveyed completed the questionnaire (77%); 102 PCTs (51%) included psychologists and 99 lacked them (49%); 71 psychologists completed the survey. Most of them developed their activity in home-oriented PCTs; 46% on a full-time basis. Their main function (100%) was to psychologically care for patients and their relatives. Eighty percent reported advisory activities to their team, and 45% also provided psychological support to prevent burnout. Sixty-two percent performed educational activities too, and 37% used some of their time in research activities. PCTs are the source of 51.44% of cases followed by psychologists, usually regarding complex situations. Conclusions: data collected show that psychologists play a specific role in PCTs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lacasta Reverte, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Batiste, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Toro, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Timoneo Limonero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocafort Gil, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el hecho de morir es uno de los acontecimientos con mayor impacto psicológico. Provoca un intenso flujo de emociones en el enfermo y en la familia, que puede desencadenar en estrés psicológico, destructuración emocional y un gran sufrimiento. Esta posible  complejidad es la que plantea la necesidad del psicólogo en los Equipos de Cuidados Paliativos (ECP). Objetivo: establecer las funciones del psicólogo en los Equipos de Cuidados Paliativos que disponen de esta figura. Método: estudio observacional, descriptivo, mediante encuesta remitida por correo electrónico a todos los ECP de España. Resultados: de los 262 equipos respondieron 201 equipos (tasa de respuesta del 77%). 102 equipos (51%) disponían de psicólogo y 99 no (49%). 71 psicólogos cumplimentaron la encuesta. La mayor parte desarrollaban su actividad en equipos domiciliarios. El 46% de los psicólogos se dedicaba la jornada completa al ECP. La función principal (100%) era la atención psicológica a enfermos y familiares. El 80% referían asesorar a su equipo y el 45% prestaba apoyo psicológico para prevenir el burnout. El 62% realizaban actividades docentes, y el 37% colaboraba en investigación. Los ECP son el origen del 51,44% de los casos atendidos por el psicólogo, éstos atienden habitualmente situaciones complejas. Conclusiones: los datos obtenidos muestran que el psicólogo tiene un papel específico y unas actividades e intervenciones concretas a  realizar en los ECP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;15(1): 39-44, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención psicológica en Cuidados Paliativos. Análisis de los servicios prestados en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55759^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
