<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129587</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term total mortality and cardiovascular morbidity in patients with ischemic cardiac disease who completed a cardiac rehabilitation and secondary prevention program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. To study long-term mortality and cardiovascular morbidity in ischemic patients who completed a cardiac rehabilitation and secondary prevention program by analyzing the factors that may predict the occurrence of these events. Methods. We carried out a retrospective analysis of a prospectively enrolled sample of 342 patients who completed a cardiac rehabilitation and secondary prevention program between 2005 and 2008. We reviewed hospital admissions for cardiovascular causes, type of readmission (emergency unit/hospital), need for revascularization (percutaneous versus surgical) and mortality. The association of the studied factors with morbidity and mortality was determined by univariate analysis and Kaplan-Meier survival curves. Statistical significance was set at p &lt; 0.05. Results. During follow-up (mean 2105 days), 12 patients (3.5%) died. The main cause was cancer. A total of 116 patients (34%) were readmitted for cardiovascular causes, while 10.5% needed revascularization. The most frequent non cardiac vascular event was stroke (4.7%), followed by intermittent claudication (2.3%). One patient required amputation. Predictors associated with morbidity and mortality were age (p = 0.005), smoking (p = 0.016), and risk group (p = 0.002). Diabetes mellitus also increased morbidity and mortality during follow-up. Conclusions. Patients who completed a cardiac rehabilitation and secondary prevention program after a coronary event had low mortality but high cardiovascular morbidity (34% at 5 years). The factors associated with this morbidity and mortality were age over 65 years, belong to a moderate to high risk group, smoking, and diabetes mellitus. These results demonstrate the need for individual strategies to increase adherence to secondary prevention measures for cardiovascular events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano-Plasencia, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares-Gago, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Lozano, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarría-Ruiz-de-Vargas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Expósito-Tirado, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera-Saborido, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo-Carmona, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Praena-Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Estudiar mortalidad total y morbilidad cardiovascular a largo plazo en pacientes isquémicos que han completado un programa de rehabilitación cardíaca y prevención secundaria analizando qué factores pueden predecir la presentación de dicha morbimortalidad. Métodos. Análisis retrospectivo de una muestra recogida prospectivamente de 342 pacientes que completaron un programa de rehabilitación cardíaca y prevención secundaria en el período 2005-2008. Se revisaron ingresos hospitalarios por causa cardiovascular, tipo de reingreso (urgencias/hospitalario), necesidad de revascularización (percutánea/quirúrgica) y mortalidad. La asociación de los factores estudiados con la morbimortalidad fueron analizados mediante análisis univariante y curvas de supervivencia Kaplan-Meier. La significación estadística se establece en p &lt; 0,05. Resultados. Durante el seguimiento (media de 2.105 días) fallecieron 12 pacientes (3,5%). La principal causa fue el cáncer. Reingresaron 116 pacientes (34%). El 10,5% precisó nueva revascularización coronaria. El accidente vascular cerebral fue el evento vascular no cardíaco más frecuente (4,7%), seguido de claudicación intermitente (2,3%). Un paciente precisó amputación. Los factores predictores de morbimortalidad fueron edad (p = 0,005), hábito tabáquico (p = 0,016) y grupo de riesgo (p = 0,002). La diabetes mellitus mostró mayor morbimortalidad durante el seguimiento. Conclusiones. Nuestros resultados muestran baja mortalidad en los pacientes que han completado un programa de rehabilitación cardíaca y prevención secundaria tras sufrir un evento coronario pero con una morbilidad cardiovascular alta (34% a 5 años). Los factores asociados con la aparición de morbimortalidad fueron edad mayor de 65 años, grupo de riesgo moderado-alto, hábito tabáquico y presencia de diabetes mellitus. Estos resultados muestran la necesidad de establecer estrategias individuales para aumentar la adherencia a las medidas de prevención secundaria de eventos cardiovasculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);48(4): 210-218, oct.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129587</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad total y morbilidad cardiovascular a largo plazo en pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica que han completado un programa de rehabilitación cardíaca y prevención secundaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
