<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041884</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vacuum therapy in vascular surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vacuum therapy is a non invasive and active healing system thatemploys a localised and controlled negative pressure to stimulatethe healing of acute and chronic wounds.Since the introduction of such therapy in our medical centre in theyear 2000, the nursing team has showed great interest to becomemore knowledgeable and to learn about the development of abilitiesfor the management of this therapy. This has prompted a needto elaborate a protocol of guidelines to ensure the quality of caregiven to patients who are treated with this vacuum therapy.The follow up of 26 patients treated with vacuum therapy in ourunit in the period of time between September 2001 and August2003 shows that 80.77% made good progress and that this therapyis well tolerated by the patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Martínez, M. Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo Esteban, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Egea González, Silvia Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perales Martínez, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia de vacío es un sistema de cicatrización no invasivo y activo,que utiliza una presión negativa localizada y controlada paraestimular la curación de las heridas agudas y crónicas.Desde la introducción de dicha terapia en nuestro centro hospitalario,en el año 2000, el equipo de Enfermería se ha mostrado muyinteresado en la adquisición de conocimientos y en el desarrollo dehabilidades para su manejo, lo que ha desencadenado la necesidadde elaborar un protocolo de actuación para asegurar la calidadde los cuidados enfermeros que se aplican a los pacientes queson tratados con la terapia de vacío.El seguimiento de 26 pacientes tratados con terapia de vacío ennuestra unidad, en el período comprendido entre septiembre de2001 y agosto de 2003, muestra que el 80,77% evolucionaron favorablementey que es bien tolerada por los pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;8(6): 16-20, jul. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041884</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La terapia de vacío en cirugía vascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2947^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1164^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
