<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043888</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Jehovah's Witnesses refusal of blood: religious, legal and ethical aspects and considerations for anesthetic management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The refusal of Jehovah's Witnesses to agree to bloodor blood product transfusion based on religious beliefs isone of the most challenging conflictive issues health caregivers have to face today. Such conflict is a by product ofthe ideological and religious diversity in society today.The perioperative care of such patients constitutes agenuine challenge for anesthesiologists and surgeonsfrom technical, scientific, ethical, and legal perspectives.We review the reasons why Jehovah's Witnesses refusetransfusion and discuss the ethical, legal, and anestheticaspects of their care. The literature up to August 2005was reviewed by MEDLINE search. The followingsearch terms were used: Jehovah's Witnesses, anesthesia(and anaesthesia), legislation and jurisprudence, ethics,blood transfusion, alternatives, anemia (and anaemia),erythropoietin, trigger, and critical care. To furthercover ethical and legal aspects, we reviewed current lawsin Spain and similar practice settings</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gredilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reinoso Barbero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los conflictos asistenciales que la medicinaactual afronta, consecuencia de la pluralidad ideológicay religiosa de nuestra sociedad, es el rechazo a la transfusiónde sangre y derivados sanguíneos por los Testigosde Jehová a causa de sus creencias religiosas. El tratamientoperioperatorio de estos pacientes supone un retopara anestesiólogos y cirujanos, tanto desde el punto devista técnico y científico, como ético y legal. Revisamoslos fundamentos del rechazo a la transfusión sanguíneapor los Testigos de Jehová, así como los aspectos éticos,legales y consideraciones anestésicas en su tratamientoPara ello hemos revisado la literatura médica existentehasta agosto de 2005 mediante búsqueda en MEDLINE,utilizando los términos de búsqueda "Jehovah&#146;s Witnesses,anaesthesia, legislation and jurisprudence, ethics,blood transfusion, alternatives, anaemia, erythropoietin,trigger, critical care". Para cubrir los aspectos éticos ylegales se ha revisado la legislación vigente en España yen otros países de nuestro entorno</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;53(1): 31-41, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043888</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fundamentos del rechazo a la transfusión sanguínea por los Testigos de Jehová. Aspectos ético-legales y consideraciones anestésicas en su tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30229^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29387^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11252^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1820</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1829^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30229^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37712^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1832</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7592^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7592^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
