<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80631</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with the intention to provide breastfeeding</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: factors associated to the intention to breastfeeding in pregnant women are not well understood. Methodology: Descriptive study based on 150 pregnant women with gestation age of 34 weeks or more, interviewed when attending the control of pregnancy. A questionnaire that collected general information as well as information related to the intention to give breastfeeding and myths existing about this topic was completed. Results: The prevalence of pregnant women with intention to give breastfeeding was 81%. Midwife appears as the main and best informant. In the multivariate analysis the opinion of the partner and the received information on breastfeeding were factors significantly associated with the intention to breastfeed. Conclusions: It is necessary to promote changes in the training of health personnel involved in giving information to pregnant woman about importance of breastfeeding as well as to develop initiatives involving the partner in the pregnant training session(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Falcón, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Andrellucchi, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorca, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Acosta, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Majem, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Estimar la prevalencia de intención de dar lactancia materna y determinar factores asociados a dicha decisión. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo en el que participaron 150 embarazadas con edad gestacional igual o superior a 34 semanas, sin límite de edad, siendo entrevistadas cuando acudían a la consulta de control de embarazo. Se administró un cuestionario que recogió información general de las gestantes como así también información relacionada con la intención de dar lactancia y los mitos existentes sobre el tema. Resultados: La prevalencia de gestantes con intención de dar lactancia materna fue de 81%. Destaca la figura de la matrona como principal y buen informador. En el análisis multivariante la opinión de la pareja y el hecho de haber sido informadas acerca de la lactancia materna se asociaron de manera independientemente con la intención de dar lactancia materna. Conclusiones: Es imprescindible impulsar cambios en la formación de los profesionales de la salud que están implicados en informar a las gestantes acerca de la importancia de la lactancia materna, así como fomentar iniciativas que involucren a la pareja en las clases de preparación al parto(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;15(1): 6-12, ene.-mar.2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados a la intención de proporcionar lactancia materna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
