<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110986</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The assessment of the perceived emotional distress: the neglected side of cancer care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this research was to present the latest development of the The Perceived Emotional Distress Inventory (PEDI) as a brief 15-item self-report measure intended to be used for the assessment of psychological distress in cancer patients. Factor Analyses of Principal Components with promax rotations were performed with a combined male and female sample of 481 cancer patients at St. Joseph&#146;s hospital Cancer Institute in Tampa, Florida, to provide further evidence of construct validity. The factor structure, internal consistency, and Pearson correlation coefficients of the PEDI are presented in this report. The factor analysis identified three factors comparable to those found in previous samples in USA: The first factor, anxiety/depression; second factor, hopelessness; and third factor, anger expression. Global alpha coefficient of 0.92 for the inventory indicates strong internal consistency. Pearson correlations between the subscales of the instrument is impressive for such a brief measure. This study emphasizes the need for a brief, self-report instrument to assess anger expression, anxiety, depression and hopelessness as components of perceived emotional distress in cancer patients, while explicitly excluding the potentially confounding effects of somatic symptoms commonly associated with cancer treatments. Further research will be needed to provide information about the PEDI&#146;s use in populations other than cancer patients including attempts to replicate these findings in more heterogeneous  populations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reheiser, Eric C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moscoso, Manolete S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lengacher, Cecile A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este estudio fue evaluar la estructura factorial del Inventario de Malestar Emocional Percibido (IDEP), un instrumento de medición del malestar emocional de 15 ítems, en una muestra de 481 pacientes con cáncer que iniciaron sus tratamientos con radioterapia y/o quimioterapia en el Instituto de cancer del hospital St. Joseph&#146;s en la ciudad de Tampa, Florida, USA. Se llevó a cabo un análisis factorial de componentes principales y método de rotación promax con autovalores superiores a 1. El primer factor contiene seven ítems correspondientes a síntomas de ansiedad y depresión. El segundo factor está agrupado por cuatro ítems relacionados con sentimientos de desesperanza, mientras un tercer factor presenta cuatro ítems que manifiestan la expresión de ira. Los resultados obtenidos nos indican que el Inventario de malestar emocional presenta una estructura factorial consistente con el marco conceptual en el cual se basó la construcción del instrumento, El coeficiente alpha de Cronbach para el instrumento total del IDEP es de 0,92, lo cual es significativamente elevado, como también los coeficientes alpha para sus cuatro sub-escalas. Los resultados observados demuestran evidencia empírica acerca de la validez de constructo y la consistencia interna del IDEP. Es necesario un mayor esfuerzo con el propósito de replicar estos mismos resultados en pacientes con otros tipos de diagnostico y en culturas diferentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);9(2/3): 277-288, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110986</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación del malestar emocional percibido: la faceta desatendida de la atención del cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
