<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124667</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of a nursing intervention for health training in cardiac surgery patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to evaluate an intervention in order to improve the preparation for hospital discharge in cardiac surgery patients. Materials and methods: a quasi-experimental longitudinal study. Control arm (CA): Patients with cardiac surgery and regular nursing treatment; Intervention arm (IA): Patients with cardiac surgery and health education under protocol before discharge(Appendix I). CA data were collected during the previous months to the intervention in nursing practice, and IA data were collected since three months after introducing the intervention. In both groups, information was collected during hospitalization for the intervention and one month after, coinciding with the examination date. Through validated questionnaires applied by the researchers, the following were measured in patients: satisfaction with care, level of knowledge, and degree of treatment adherence; while the impact of the introduction of the intervention in practice was measured in nurses through an ad hoc questionnaire. Results: the patient sample was homogeneous: (CA= 20) and(IA= 23). Patient satisfaction was high in both arms, with a mean score of 4.6 (on a scale of 1 to 5). At one month of discharge, a significant improvement in knowledge was observed in the IA (CA= 0.22 (0.2) IA= -0.08 (0.31) p&lt; 0.01)); there was a significant improvement in the number of times both groups did some exercise per week, and the time in minutes was higher (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beortegui Urdánoz, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarrola Izura, Sagrario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oroviogoicoechea, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Calatayud, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar una intervención para mejorar la preparación del alta del paciente intervenido de cirugía cardiaca. Material y método: estudio longitudinal cuasi experimental. Grupo control (GC): pacientes con cirugía cardiaca y tratamiento enfermero habitual; grupo intervención (GI): pacientes con cirugía cardiaca y educación sanitaria protocolizada antes del alta(Anexo I). Los datos del GC se recogieron en los meses previos a la introducción de la intervención en la práctica enfermera y los del GC a partir de los tres meses después de la introducción de la intervención. En ambos grupos se recabó información durante el ingreso para la intervención y un mes después de esta, coincidiendo con la fecha de la revisión. Mediante cuestionarios validados administrados por las investigadoras, se midieron en los pacientes la satisfacción con el cuidado, el nivel de conocimientos y el grado de adherencia al tratamiento, y en las enfermeras se midió el impacto de la introducción de la intervención en la práctica mediante un cuestionario ad hoc. Resultados: la muestra de pacientes fue homogénea (GC= 20)y (GI= 23). La satisfacción de estos fue alta en ambos grupos con una puntuación media de 4,6 (en una escala del 1 al 5). Al mes del alta, se observó una mejoría significativa en los conocimientos del GI (GC= 0,22 (0,2) GI=-0,08 (0,31) p&lt; 0,01)); mejoró significativamente el número de veces (..)  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(4): 26-32, mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124667</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de una intervención enfermera para la educación para la salud en pacientes intervenidos de cirugía cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
