<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60502</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nosocomial pneumonia due to Gram-positive microorganisms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reviews aspects related to nosocomialpneumonia due to Gram-positive microorganisms andespecially episodes due to MRSA, because of theirgrowing incidence and poor prognosis. The availabletherapeutic options, their suitability, and the emergenttherapeutic options that aim to improve prognosis inpatients with this kind of infection are evaluated. Giventhe lack of effective alternatives to treat nosocomialpneumonia due to MRSA, the possibility of using linezolidas the best available strategy to date is discussed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rello, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lisboa, Thiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo revisamos aspectos relacionados con laneumonía nosocomial causada por grampositivos, yespecialmente de los episodios causados por Staphylococcusaureus resistenten a meticilina (SARM), por su crecienteincidencia y mala evolución asociada. Evaluaremos lasopciones terapéuticas disponibles, su adecuación y lasopciones terapéuticas emergentes para mejorar el pronósticode los pacientes afectados por este tipo de infecciones. Antela escasez de alternativas eficaces en el tratamiento de laneumonía nosocomial por SARM, discutimos la disyuntiva deconsiderar linezolid como la mejor opción disponible(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.2): 53-60, ene. 2008. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60502</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía nosocomial por grampositivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32073^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6244^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
