<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152229</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mixed Methods Analysis of the offensive tactical behavior in critical moments of game in the high performance in handball: A study Mixed Methods</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyse factors that influence attacking play during critical moments of elite handball matches from a dynamic, ecological perspective within a Mixed Methods research design. We evaluated tactical systems employed during positional attacks and counterattacks by analyzing the last ten-possession ball and actions in offensive sequences during 19 matches from the men&#146;s final stages of the 2011 World Championship, the 2012 European Championship, and the 2012 Olympic Games. We employed a two-stage observation model. In the first, qualitative, stage, we built an observation instrument (SOCTO) based on a descriptive data set and in the second, quantitative, stage, we systematically produced a structured data set comprising the following dimensions: score, type of defence, numerical symmetry, zone in which the offensive sequence ended, and outcome. The 19 matches were observed and coded by trained, expert handball coaches using LINCE recording software. This initial descriptive analysis was complemented by a T-pattern analysis. Our findings confirm that at critical moments at the end of elite handball matches, more effective teams (i.e. winning teams) make greater use of the middle zones of the pitch (between the 6- and 9-meter lines) to complete their attack, while losing teams use the zone further away from the goal (9-meter zone) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Demetrio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hileno, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camerino, Oleguer</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del artículo es analizar las variables que influyen en las fases ofensivas críticas del balonmano de alto rendimiento desde una perspectiva dinámica ecológica y con un planteamiento Mixed Methods. Evaluamos los diferentes sistemas tácticos ofensivos en ataque posicional y en contraataque de las últimas diez posesiones del balón y acciones ofensivas de partidos de balonmano de élite mediante un análisis observacional en dos etapas. Una primera etapa CUALI, materializada en forma de registro descriptivo, que permitieron la construcción de un sistema de observación (SOCTO); y una segunda etapa CUANTI con la que obtuvimos un registro sistematizado posterior mediante las siguientes dimensiones: el marcador, el tipo de defensa, la simetría numérica, la zona de finalización y el tipo de finalización. Utilizando el software de registro LINCE, se observaron 19 partidos de las fases finales masculinas del Campeonato del Mundo 2011, Campeonato de Europa 2012 y Juegos Olímpicos 2012. El análisis descriptivo inicial realizada por entrenadores expertos se ha complementado con un análisis de T-patterns. Los resultados reafirman que en los momentos críticos y de desigualdad del final de los partidos los equipos perdedores utilizan en la fase ofensiva las zonas de finalización más alejadas de la portería contraria (zona de 9 metros) y los equipos ganadores utilizan en la fase ofensiva las zonas de finalización intermedias (entre 6 y 9 metros) aumentando así su eficacia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;16(1): 151-160, ene. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152229</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del comportamiento táctico ofensivo en momentos críticos de juego en el alto rendimiento en balonmano: Un estúdio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
