<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043216</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metastasis to the parotid gland</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Metastatic disease in the parotid        gland has been observed and reported in the literature, and        its treatment is controversial. Material and methods: We review        48 patients with parotid tumors that underwent surgery        during 1997-2004. The clinical and histogical features        are reviewed. Results: Among these 48, there were 12 cases        of metastatic tumors to the parotid (25%). The pathohistological        analysis of these tumors revealed that 8 were epidermoid        carcinoma (66%), 1 patient was a melanoma (8%), 2        lymphomas below clavicules (16%) and 1 patient with a        metastasis of a primary renal cancer. All patients underwent        parotidectomy and 10 also cervical neck dissection (6        cases showed cervical metastases). 8 patients received radiotherapy        after surgery. Conclusions: In our study parotid        metastases are relatively common in patients submitted for        parotid surgery. Often the site of origin of the primary tumor        is the facial skin, and the primary tumors most commonly        are melanomas or squamous-cell carcinomas, but it        is possible distant primary tumors below clavicules</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tapia Risueño, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Villares, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pomar blanco, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Román Carbajo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pello, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La existencia de metástasis parotídeas        ha sido reflejada en la literatura, siendo su tratamiento controvertido.        Material y métodos: Se realiza un estudio retrospectivo        sobre 48 pacientes sometidos a cirugía de parótida entre        los años 1997 y 2004, revisándose aspectos clínicos e histológicos.        Resultados: De los 48 pacientes intervenidos, en 12 casos        se diagnosticó metástasis parotídea de un tumor primario        (25%). El estudio histopatológico identificó: tumor primario        en la piel en 9 pacientes (8 carcinomas epidermoides y 1 melanoma),        2 linfomas de localización inicial infraclavicular y        un carcinoma renal de células claras. Los 12 pacientes fueron        sometidos a parotidectomía, acompañada de vaciamiento        ganglionar cervical en 10 pacientes (en 6 de ellos se identificaron        metástasis ganglionares); 8 pacientes recibieron tratamiento        radioterápico postquirúrgico. Conclusión: En nuestro        estudio las metástasis parotídeas son relativamente frecuentes        en el global de los pacientes intervenidos por tumores de        parótida. En la mayoría de las ocasiones el tumor primario se        encuentra en zonas cutáneas próximas (melanomas o carcinomas        epidermoides), aunque es posible que el tumor primario        se encuentre por debajo de las clavículas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;57(1): 47-50, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043216</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis en la glándula parótida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8384^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
