<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158028</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differential effects of attention and emotional clarity on the perception of academic stressors and stress responses of physiotherapy students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the differential effects of levels of emotional attention and emotional clarity on the perception of academic stressors and stress responses of physiotherapy students. Material and method: Levels of emotional attention and emotional clarity were measured with Difficulties in Emotional Regulation Scale, and perception of academic stressors and stress responses were evaluated with Academic Stress Questionnaire in 500 physiotherapy students from different Spanish universities. Students were classified according to their degree of emotional attention and emotional clarity in high, medium and low, and the perception of stressors and stress responses were compared through analysis of variance. Results: Students with high emotional clarity assess the academic environment as less threatening and show lower psychophysiological stress responses in comparison to students with medium or low levels of emotional clarity. Conversely, students with low emotional attention only assess more stressful situations related to beliefs about the performance and the value of content than students with high emotional attention. Conclusions: While emotional clarity has a moderating role on the valuation of the academic environment as threatening and on the physical and psychological effects of stress, the role of emotional attention is less relevant and only relates with the perception of stressors linked to the beliefs of the student (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Doniz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto Camba, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanach, RG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto Gestal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los efectos diferenciales de los niveles de atención y claridad emocional sobre la percepción de estresores académicos y las respuestas de estrés de estudiantes de fisioterapia. Material y método: Se evaluaron los niveles de atención y claridad emocional con la Escala de Dificultades en la Regulación Emocional y la percepción de estresores académicos y respuestas de estrés con el Cuestionario de Estrés Académico de 500 estudiantes de fisioterapia de diferentes universidades españolas. Los estudiantes fueron clasificados en función de su grado de atención y claridad emocional (alto, medio y bajo), y se compararon la percepción de estresores y respuestas de estrés mediante un análisis de la varianza. Resultados: Los estudiantes con elevada claridad emocional valoran el entorno académico como menos amenazante y muestran menores respuestas psicofisiológicas de estrés en comparación con los estudiantes con niveles medios o bajos de claridad emocional. Por el contrario, los estudiantes con baja atención emocional únicamente valoran como más estresantes aquellas situaciones relacionadas con las creencias sobre el rendimiento y sobre el valor de los contenidos, en comparación con los estudiantes con alta atención emocional. Conclusiones: Mientras la claridad emocional presenta una función moderadora sobre la valoración del entorno académico en términos de amenaza y sobre los efectos físicos y psicológicos del estrés, el papel de la atención emocional resulta menos relevante y únicamente se relaciona con la percepción de estresores vinculados a las creencias del estudiante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);38(6): 271-279, nov.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos diferenciales de la atención y la claridad emocional sobre la percepción de estresores académicos y las respuestas de estrés de estudiantes de fisioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13723^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
