<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046959</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How to achieve patient-centered healthcare: patients&#146;, citizens&#146;, health professionals&#146; Asesores. Universidad Miguel Hernández. Elche. Alicante. España</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze what health professionals, health managers, and the leaders of patient associations understand by "humanization". Material and method: We performed a qualitative study. Participants consisted of 20 representatives of patient or citizens' associations, two presidents of professional associations, 18 representatives of the patient advice and liaison service, 41 health managers (hospitals and primary care). The following questions were analyzed: What does humanizing health care mean? How can personalized patient care (making healthcare more dignified and human) be improved? How has the patient profile changed? What new demands are patients making? Which rights and responsibilities of the patient should be developed in the future? Results: The concept of humanization was defined as communication, empathy, personalized dealings between patients and staff, technical quality, comfort, and good resource management. The main factors for improving healthcare quality were training, patient information, resources, and improvements in infrastructure. Patients currently demand more information (which they check) and new services, and show less respect for medical criteria. The following factors should be stressed: information, free choice, respect, equity, second opinions, emergency care, and participation in decision making. Patients' duty to respect health professionals and collaborate in the sustainability of the system should also be emphasized. Conclusions: Actions encouraging patient autonomy and greater accessibility to health resources should be encouraged. The development of patients rights and respect for their values, and compliance with these elements, also requires responsible resource use by patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nebot, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Jover, Virtudes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira, José Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar qué entienden por "humanización" profesionales y directivos sanitarios y líderes de asociaciones ciudadanas y de pacientes. Material y método: Investigación cualitativa. Participaron: 20 representantes de asociaciones de pacientes o ciudadanas, 2 presidentes de colegios profesionales, 18 profesionales de Servicios de Atención e Información al Paciente, 41 directivos de centros sanitarios (hospitales y atención primaria). Los temas abordados fueron: ¿qué es humanizar la atención sanitaria? ¿Cómo hacer para mejorar la calidad de la atención personal a los pacientes (atención más digna y humana)? ¿En qué ha cambiado el perfil de los pacientes? ¿Qué nuevas demandas están planteando los pacientes? ¿Qué derechos y deberes del paciente deben desarrollarse en el futuro? Resultados: Comunicación, empatía, trato personalizado, calidad técnica, comodidad y una buena gestión de los recursos definen el concepto de humanización. Formación, información al paciente, medios y mejoras en infraestructuras constituyen ejes para mejorar la calidad de la atención. Actualmente, el paciente demanda mayor información (que contrasta), nuevas prestaciones y no respeta igual el criterio médico. Se hace necesario insistir en: información, libre elección, trato respetuoso, equidad, segunda opinión, atención urgente, participación en toma de decisiones, deber de respeto hacia los profesionales y colaborar en la sostenibilidad. Conclusiones: Se deben impulsar acciones que favorezcan la autonomía del paciente y una mayor accesibilidad de los recursos sanitarios. El marco para el desarrollo y el cumplimiento de los derechos del paciente y el respeto a sus valores como persona requiere también de su compromiso para hacer un uso responsable de los recursos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;21(4): 199-206, jul.-ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046959</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Puntos de vista de pacientes, ciudadanos, profesionales y directivos sobre cómo llevar a la práctica una atención sanitaria centrada en el paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6960</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
