<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126921</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An approach to care indicators benchmarking. Learning to improve patient safety</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Improvements in clinical safety can be achieved by promoting a safety culture, professional training, and learning through benchmarking. The aim of this study was to identify areas for improvement after analysing the safety indicators in two public Hospitals in North-West Madrid Region. Material and methods. Descriptive study performed during 2011 in Hospital Universitario Puerta de Hierro Majadahonda (HUPHM) and Hospital de Guadarrama (HG). The variables under study were 40 indicators on nursing care related to patient safety. Nineteen of them were defined in the SENECA project as care quality standards in order to improve patient safety in the hospitals. The data collected were clinical history, Madrid Health Service assessment reports, care procedures, and direct observation. Results. Within the 40 indicators: 22 of them were structured (procedures), HUPHM had 86%, and HG 95% 14 process indicators (training and protocols compliance) with similar results in both hospitals, apart from the care continuity reports and training in hand hygiene. The 4 results indicators (pressure ulcer, falls and pain) showed different results. Conclusions. The analysis of the indicators allowed the following actions to be taken: to identify improvements to be made in each hospital, to develop joint safety recommendations in nursing care protocols in prevention and treatment of chronic wound, to establish systematic pain assessments, and to prepare continuity care reports on all patients transferred from HUPHM to HG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayuso Murillo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revuelta Zamorano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar de la Guerra, r. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Arnedo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés Gimeno, B. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Soria, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mejora de la seguridad clínica puede alcanzarse mediante la promoción de una cultura de seguridad, formación y aprendizaje a través del benchmarking. El objetivo fue identificar áreas de mejora tras analizar indicadores relacionados con la seguridad de 2 hospitales públicos del área noroeste de la Comunidad de Madrid. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo realizado en 2011 en el Hospital Universitario Puerta de Hierro Majadahonda (HUPHM) y en el Hospital de Guadarrama (HG). Las variables fueron 40 indicadores sobre cuidados de enfermería relacionados con la seguridad; 19 habían sido definidos en el Proyecto SENECA como estándares de calidad de cuidados para mejorar la seguridad en los hospitales. Para la recogida de datos se utilizó la historia clínica, los informes de evaluación del Servicio Madrileño de Salud, los procedimientos de cuidados y la observación directa. Resultados. De 40 indicadores 22 eran de estructura (procedimientos), el HUPHM disponía del 86% y el HG del 95%. Hubo 14 indicadores de proceso (formación y cumplimiento de protocolos) con resultados similares en los 2 hospitales, excepto en los informes de continuidad de cuidados y formación en higiene de manos. Los 4 indicadores de resultado (incidencia, y prevalencia de úlceras por presión, caídas y dolor) mostraron resultados dispares. Conclusiones. Analizar indicadores permitió identificar acciones de mejora en cada hospital, elaborar conjuntamente un decálogo de seguridad en los cuidados y un protocolo de prevención y tratamiento de heridas crónicas, instaurar la evaluación sistemática del dolor y la realización de informes de continuidad de cuidados a los pacientes derivados del HUPHM al HG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;29(4): 212-219, jul.-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126921</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una aproximación al benchmarking de indicadores de cuidados. Aprendiendo para mejorar la seguridad del paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
