<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148917</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Individualised dosimetry in patients with differentiated thyroid cancer based on external dose-rate. Optimisation of the number of measurements</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To compare the results of individual dosimetry in differentiated thyroid cancer patients treated with 131I at our centre with the established limits and dosimetry results of published studies. Analysis of the optimal number of measurements necessary to reduce the impact of dosimetry for the comfort of the patient and, secondly, on the workload of health workers. Material and methods. Dosimetry was performed in the Nuclear Medicine Department of the University and Polytechnic Hospital La Fe, on 29 patients suffering from differentiated thyroid cancer and treated with activities between 1.02 and 5.51 GBq (mean 2.68 GBq) of 131I. The Spanish Society of Medical Physics (SEFM) protocol was used, based on measurements of external dose rate adjusted to a bi-exponential curve according to a two compartment model. Different dosimetries were performed on each patient, taking different selections of the available measurements in order to find the optimal number. Results. Results are well below the dosimetry limits, and are consistent with those obtained in other centres. The number of measurements can be reduced from 5, as proposed in the SEFM protocol, to 4 without significant loss of accuracy. Further reducing measures may be justified in individual cases. Conclusions. The values obtained for the dosimetry quantities are significantly below the established limits. A reduction in measurements can be assumed at the cost of a moderate increase in uncertainty, benefiting the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres-Espallardo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bello, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bautista-Ballesteros, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí-Bonmatí, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrelli, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas-Sanchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Comparar los resultados de la dosimetría individual en pacientes de cáncer diferenciado de tiroides tratados con 131I en nuestro centro con los límites dosimétricos establecidos y con resultados obtenidos en estudios publicados. Analizar el número óptimo de medidas a realizar para reducir el impacto de la dosimetría en el bienestar del paciente y, en segundo término, en la carga de trabajo del personal sanitario. Material y métodos.  Se realiza la dosimetría a 29 pacientes del Servicio de Medicina Nuclear del Hospital Universitario y Politécnico La Fe, afectados de cáncer diferenciado de tiroides y tratados con actividades de entre 1,02 y 5,51 GBq (promedio de 2,68 GBq) de 131I. Para ello se utiliza el protocolo de la Sociedad Española de Física Médica (SEFM) basado en medidas de tasa de dosis externa ajustadas a una curva biexponencial, de acuerdo con un modelo de dos compartimentos. Para cada paciente se realizan distintas dosimetrías tomando diferentes selecciones de las medidas disponibles a fin de buscar el número óptimo. Resultados. Los resultados están muy por debajo de los límites dosimétricos y son coherentes con los obtenidos en otros centros. El número de medidas puede reducirse de 5, como propone el protocolo de la SEFM, a 4 sin pérdida de precisión significativa. Una mayor reducción de medidas puede justificarse en casos particulares. Conclusiones. Los valores obtenidos para las magnitudes dosimétricas quedan muy por debajo de los límites establecidos. Se puede asumir la reducción de medidas a costa de un aumento de la incertidumbre moderado beneficiando del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);35(2): 107-114, mar.-abr. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148917</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dosimetría individualizada para pacientes de cáncer diferenciado de tiroides basada en tasa de dosis externa. Optimización del número de medidas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32403^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7619</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
