<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055092</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations from SPNS/GEAM/SENBA/SENPE/AEDN/SEDCA/ GESIDA on nutrition in the HIV-infected patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to make recommendations on the approach        to nutritional problems (malnutrition, cachexia, micronutrient deficiency, obesity, lipodystrophy) affecting HIV-infected patients. Methods: these recommendations have been agreed upon by a group of expertes in the nutrition and care of HIV-infected patients, on behalf of the different groups involved        in drafting them. Therefore, the latest advances in        pathophysiology, epidemiology, and clinical care presented        in studies published in medical journals or at scientific        meetings were evaluated. Results: there is no single method of evaluating nutrition, and diferent techniques &#151;CT, MRI, and DXA&#151; must be combined. The energy requirements of symptomatic patients increase by 20-30%. There is no evidence to support the increase in protein or fat intake. Micronutrient supplementation in only necessary in special circumstances (vitamin A in children and pregnant woman). Aerobic and resistance excercise is beneficial both for cardiovascular health and for improving lean mass and muscular strength. It is important to follow the rules of food safety at every stage in the chain. Therapeutic intervention in anorexia and cachexia must be tailored, by combining nutritional and pharmacological support (appetite stimulants,        anabolic steroids, and, in some cases, testosterone).        Artificial nutrition (oral supplementation, enteral or parenteral nutrition) is safe and efficacious, and improves nutritional status and response to therapy. In children, nutritional recommendations must be made early, and are a necessary component of therapy. Conclusion: appropriate nutritional evaluation and relevant        therapeutic action are an essential part of the care        of HIV-infected patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fumaz, CR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Câncer, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Candela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Benayas, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riobo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miján, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irles, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Álvarez, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mellado, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, JT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cánoves, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Locutura, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Nacher, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: realizar recomendaciones sobre el abordaje        de los problemas nutricionales (malnutrición, caquexia,        déficit de micronutrientes, obesidad, lipodistrofia) presentes en la infección VIH.        Métodos: estas recomendaciones se han consensuado por        un grupo de expertos en nutrición y en atención al enfermo        VIH, en representación de las distintas sociedades firmantes. Para ello se han revisado los últimos avances fisiopatológicos, epidemiológicos y clínicos recogidos en estudios publicados en revistas médicas o presentados en congresos. Resultados: no existe un único método de valoración nutricional, debiendo combinarse cuestionarios y técnicas como TAC, RNM y DEXA. Los requerimientos energéticos en enfermos sintomáticos aumentan en un 20-30%. No existe evidencia que respalde el incremento del aporte proteico o graso. La suplementación de micronutrientes sólo es necesaria en circunstancias especiales (Vitamina A en niños y embarazadas). El ejercicio aeróbico de resistencia es beneficioso tanto para la salud cardiovascular como para mejorar la masa magra y la fuerza muscular. Es importante seguir normas de seguridad en toda la cadena alimentaria. La intervención terapéutica en la anorexia y caquexia debe ser individualizada, combinando soporte nutricional y farmacológico (estimulantes del apetito, agentes anabolizantes y testosterona en algún caso). La nutrición        artificial (suplementación oral, nutrición enteral o        parenteral) es segura y eficaz, mejorando el estado nutricional y la respuesta al tratamiento. En niños, las recomendaciones nutricionales deben ser muy precoces, formando necesariamente parte del tratamiento.        Conclusión: La adecuada valoración nutricional y la        pertinente actuación terapéutica son parte esencial de la        asistencia del enfermo VIH</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;22(2): 229-243, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055092</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones de SPNS/GEAM/SENBA/SENPE/AEDN/SEDCA/GESIDA sobre nutrición en el paciente con infección por VIH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
