<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128941</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protective measures against cerebral ischemia following subarachnoid hemorrhage: part 1</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Cerebral vasospasm following aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage contributes significantly to morbidity and mortality. Many studies on the various treatments aimed at preventing cerebral vasospasm have been carried out, but evidence of efficacy is limited. Our aim was to review the literature on the various therapies for which there is scientific evidence of protection against cerebral vasospasm following aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage. Methods: MEDLINE search (1950 to the october 2009) and review of articles found on the prevention of cerebral vasospasm following aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage. The search was restricted to articles in English, French, and Spanish. The keywords were cerebral vasospasm, subarachnoid hemorrhage, therapy, nimodipine, triple H, clazosentan, statins, and magnesium in addition to the word forms derived from them. We also searched manually for references cited in the selected articles. A title was included if it was a randomized controlled trial, meta-analysis, nonrandomized clinical trial, descriptive study, observational study with statistical analysis, opinion article, or expert review. Results: Part 1 analyzed treatment with calcium antagonists and triple-H therapy (hypertension, hemodilution, and hypervolemia). Part 2 analyzed new therapies such as clazosentan, magnesium, and statins. A total of 597 titles were located; 283 were initially selected. The 61 articles finally selected for review were of the following types: 2 opinion articles, 21 randomized controlled trials, 22 expert review articles, 3 meta-analyses, 4 nonrandomized clinical trials, 1 descriptive study, and 5 observational studies with statistical analysis. Three studies (2 meta-analyses and 1 randomized controlled trial) demonstrated that nimodipine use confers benefits (reduced morbidity and mortality) for patients with aneurysmatic subarachnoid hemorrhage. Statistically significant clinical benefits  ould not be demonstrated for the other drugs (clazosentan, statins, and magnesium). Conclusions: Insufficient evidence is available to support the use of the triple-H therapy, clazosentan, statins, or magnesium sulfate for the prevention of cerebral vasospasm following subarachnoid hemorrhage. Nimodipine is the only preventative treatment that can be recommended(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Kräuchi, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verger Bennasar, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La presencia de vasoespasmo cerebral tras hemorragia subaracnoidea aneurismática contribuye a la importante morbimortalidad de esta entidad. Por ello, se han desarrollado múltiples estudios con diferentes tratamientos dirigidos a su prevención, aunque la evidencia sobre su eficacia es limitada. Nuestro objetivo fue realizar una revisión bibliográfica de las diferentes terapias con evidencia científica para la prevención del vasoespasmo cerebral posthemorragia subaracnoidea aneurismática. Métodos: Búsqueda en MEDLINE (desde 1950 hasta octubre 2009) y revisión bibliográfica de las publicaciones halladas sobre prevención del vasoespasmo cerebral posthemorragia subaracnoidea aneurismática. Se restringió la búsqueda a artículos en inglés, francés y español. Se emplearon las palabras clave [cerebral vasospasm, subarachnoid hemorrhage, therapy, nimodipine, triple h, clazosentan, statins, magnesium] y sus combinaciones. Además se llevó a cabo una búsqueda manual en las referencias de los artículos seleccionados. Se incluyeron artículos que reunieran las siguientes condiciones: estudios controlados aleatorizados, metaanálisis, estudios clínicos no aleatorizados, estudios descriptivos, estudios analíticos observacionales, artículos de opinión y revisión. Resultados: La parte 1 analiza el tratamiento con calcioantagonistas y la triple terapia (hipertensión, hemodilución e hipervolemia) y la parte 2 analiza nuevas terapias como son el clazosentán, el magnesio y las estatinas. Hallamos 597 referencias de las cuales 283 fueron seleccionadas. Se incluyeron finalmente 61, las cuales se distribuyeron en 2 artículos de opinión, 21 estudios controlados aleatorizados, 22 artículos de revisión, 3 metaanálisis, 4 estudios clínicos no aleatorizados, 1 estudio descriptivo y 5 estudios analíticos observacionales. Tres estudios (2 metaanálisis y un estudio controlado aleatorizado) demostraron un beneficio en términos de morbimortalidad del uso del nimodipino en pacientes con hemorragia subaracnoidea aneurismática. Por el contrario en el análisis del resto de fármacos (clazosentán, estatinas y magnesio) no se objetivó un beneficio clínico estadísticamente significativo. Conclusiones: En la actualidad no hay suficiente evidencia para apoyar la utilización de triple terapia, clazosentán, estatinas y sulfato de magnesio para la prevención del vasoespasmo cerebral posthemorragia subaracnoidea aneurismática. El único tratamiento preventivo recomendado es el nimodipino(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(4): 230-235, abr. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128941</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medidas protectoras frente a la isquemia cerebral tras hemorragia subaracnoidea (I)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34270^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34270^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8448^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34270^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23510^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13733^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
