<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159327</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with level of pain in admission and high in victims of trauma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Different factors may be associated with the genesis and maintenance of pain symptoms in trauma. the underevaluation and undertreatment of acute pain in emergency units have called in an unqualified care, increasing morbidity and length of hospital stay. the objective of this investigation was to determine the factors associated with the level of pain on admission and at discharge in trauma. Methodology: Cross-sectional study with 92 trauma victims treated at an emergency unit in southern Brazil. the intensity and location of pain were assessed, respectively, through the numerical pain scale and body diagram. data were analyzed with the aid of non-parametric statistics. Results: The results showed that were associated with more severe pain on admission or discharge characteristics like being male, younger age, non-white skin color, companion presence, burn-like lesions, presence of drug prescription, analgesic administration intravenously and longer than 30 minutes for pain relief with pharmacotherapy. Conclusion: The imposition of protocols or algorithms of measurement and treatment of pain by health professionals in emergency units should consider these characteristics in order to provide a resolutive and quality care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martin, Andrea Regina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>de Arruda, Guilherme Oliveira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soares, Jamyle Rubio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcon, Sonia Silva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreto, Mayckel da Silva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Diferentes factores pueden estar asociados a la génesis y mantenimiento del cuadro de dolor en víctimas de trauma. La baja evaluación y el bajo tratamiento del dolor agudo en las unidades de urgencia han llevado a una atención descalificada, aumentando la morbilidad y el tiempo de internación. El objetivo de esta investigación fue verificar los factores asociados al nivel de dolor en la admisión y en el alta en víctimas de trauma. Metodología: Estudio transversal, realizado con 92 víctimas de trauma atendidas en una unidad de urgencia en el Sur de Brasil. La intensidad y ubicación del dolor fueron evaluadas, respectivamente, por medio de la escala numérica de dolor y diagrama corporal. Los datos fueron analizados con ayuda de la estadística no paramétrica. Resultados: Los hallazgos indicaron asociación del dolor más intenso en la admisión o en el alta a características como: sexo masculino, edad más joven, color de la piel no blanca, presencia de compañero, heridas ocasionadas por quemadura, presencia de prescripción medicamentosa, administración analgésica por vía endovenosa y tiempo superior a 30 minutos para mejora del dolor. Conclusión: La institución de protocolos o algoritmos de medición y tratamiento del dolor por los profesionales de salud en las unidades de urgencia debe considerar tales características a fin de prestar una asistencia resolutiva y de calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;16(45): 130-142, ene. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159327</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados al nivel de dolor en la admisión y en el alta en víctimas de trauma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d289^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37625^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55459^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
