<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-25213</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vesicouterine fistulae. 25 Years of our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To determine the current state of vesicouterine fistulae in our hospital, the factors associated with their development and the findings obtained from the treatments used. MATERIAL AND METHODS: We carry out a retrospective study on a group of patients suffering from vesicouterine fistulae who were treated in our service for the last 25 years with a 2 year minimum follow-up. RESULTS: 6 cases of vesicouterine fistulae were evaluated. In 83,3% (5/6) of the cases occurred following caesarean section. The average age of the patients was 36,5 years old. In 50% of the cases, urinary incontinence immediately after surgery determined an early diagnosis. In 5 patients deferred abdominal surgical approach was carried out. All of the patients remained asymptomatic during the follow-up years. Two pregnancies were recorded 24 months after repair with a full term delivery. CONCLUSIONS: The vesicouterine fistula, despite being infrequent, is no longer an exceptional diagnosis. Currently, the low segmentarian caesareans constitute the major isolated risk factor for fistula development. We recommend a deferred surgical repair without discarding a conservative approach for those cases of small and early fistula (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ene Ediciones, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Determinar el estado actual de las fístulas vesicouterinas en nuestro hospital, los factores asociados a su desarrollo y evaluar los resultados de los tratamientos realizados para su resolución. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo de las pacientes con fístulas vesicouterinas tratadas en nuestro servicio en los últimos 25 años con un seguimiento mínimo de 2 años. RESULTADOS: Se evaluaron 6 casos de fístulas vesicouterinas. En el 83,3 por ciento (5/6) de los casos la causa principal fue la realización de una cesárea. La edad media de las mujeres fue de 36,5 años. En el 50 por ciento de los casos la incontinencia urinaria inmediata a la intervención quirúrgica condicionó el diagnóstico precoz. En 5 pacientes se realizó una reparación quirúrgica diferida de la fístula vía abdominal. Todas ellas permanecieron asintomáticas durante los años de seguimiento. En 2 pacientes se produjo un embarazo a término a partir de los 24 meses de la intervención. CONCLUSIONES: La fístula vesicouterina, aún siendo infrecuente, ha dejado de ser un diagnóstico excepcional. Las cesáreas segmentarias bajas constituyen actualmente el mayor factor de riesgo aislado relacionado con el desarrollo de estas fístulas. Recomendamos una reparación quirúrgica diferida sin descartar una actitud conservadora en los casos de pequeño tamaño diagnosticados precozmente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;27(9): 707-712, oct. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fístulas vesicouterinas. Nuestra experiencia tras 25 años</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Alapont Alacreu, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Gorrea, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arlandis Guzmán, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Cruz, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palmero Martí, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco Bru, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonillo García, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-25213</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d14992</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
