<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62382</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic heart failure (CHF) represents the first cause of hospitalisation in persons older than 60 years in our environment. Besides its incidence and prevalence is increasing although new therapeutic treatments. We think the recommendations of the guidelines of clinical practise are an important instrument to make decisions, although sometimes it is used a numeric language little clear. We do not have either to forget that sometimes patients selected for the clinical trials aren&#146;t really representative. Finally to add that pharmaceutical industry spends a lot of money on investigating active basics, but as company itself is needs to obtain benefits. With all of this, in this article we try to study the role of angiotensin II receptor blockers (ARBs) occupy in the medic strategy for the planifications of a patient&#146;s treatment with chronic heart failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varela Román, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente Cid, R de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia cardíaca crónica (ICC) representa la primera causa de ingresos hospitalarios en personas mayores de 60 años en nuestro medio. Además tanto su incidencia como su prevalencia continúan aumentando a pesar de nuevas estrategias terapéuticas. Consideramos las recomendaciones de las guías de práctica clínica (GPC) un instrumento valioso a la hora de tomar decisiones, aunque en algunas ocasiones utilicen un lenguaje numérico poco claro. Tampoco debemos de olvidar que los pacientes que entran a formar parte de los ensayos clínicos en muchas ocasiones no son representativos de la realidad. Finalmente añadir que la industria farmacéutica, invierte grandes cantidades en investigación de principios activos, pero como empresa que es necesita obtener beneficios. Con todo ello, en este artículo intentamos analizar qué papel ocupan los antagonistas del receptor de la angiotensinaII (ARA-II) en la estrategia médica a la hora de planificar un tratamiento en el paciente con ICC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;24(12): 607-609, dic. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62382</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22640^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
