<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116424</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">School Conflictivity in Chile. A comparison of the perceptions of members of the Educational Community</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents the results of a study on the state of conflict in an intentional sample of eight institutions of primary education in the province of Concepción, Eighth region, Chile, whose students of the second basic cycle have a high level of social vulnerability. To evaluate conflict, we have evaluated all member of educational community: 85 teachers, 1385 students and 686 relatives. The results indicated the presence of statistically significant differences in the perception of the three groups about the conflicts in those centres. In the most of case, the worst opinion about the state of conflicts, was given by students, while the opinion more positive was given by teachers. Finally, we discussed the implication of those results, remarking the need of obtain agreement between members of educational community about state of conflicts, in order to know the true state of conflicts and make necessary strategies to obtain a good scholar coexistence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garretón Valdivia, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Ortiz, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Ruiz, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo presenta los resultados de un estudio sobre el estado de la conflictividad en una muestra intencionada de ocho establecimientos de educación primaria de la provincia de Concepción, Octava región, Chile, cuyos alumnos de cursos del 2° ciclo básico tienen un alto índice de vulnerabilidad social. Para la evaluación de la conflictividad se ha considerando la opinión de la totalidad de los miembros de la comunidad educativa de dichos centros: 85 docentes 1385 estudiantes y 686 familiares. Los resultados señalan la existencia de diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la percepción que los tres colectivos ofrecen de la conflictividad, siendo en la mayoría de los casos el alumnado el que presenta una visión más negativa de esta dimensión y el profesorado la más positiva. Finalmente se discuten las implicaciones de estos resultados, resaltando la necesidad de conseguir un consenso por parte de toda la comunidad educativa en la evaluación de la conflictividad, para conocer el verdadero estado de la misma y así llevar a cabo las estrategias pertinentes que permitan conseguir una adecuada convivencia escolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;31(2): 247-255, mayo-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116424</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conflictividad escolar en Chile. Comparando la percepción de los miembros de la comunidad educativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
