<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94121</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The reduction of the metabolyc syndrome in Navarra-Spain (RESMENA-S) study; a multidisciplinary strategy based on chrononutrition and nutritional education, together with dietetic and psychological control</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The high prevalence of metabolic syndrome (MS) in Spain requires additional efforts for prevention and treatment. Objective: The study RESMENA-S aims to improve clinical criteria and biomarkers associated with MS though an integral therapy approach. Methods: The study is a randomized prospective parallel design in which is expected to participate a total of 100 individuals. The RESMENA-S group (n = 50) is a personalized weight loss (30% energy restriction) diet, with a macronutrient distribution (carbohydrate / fat / protein) of 40/30/30, high meal frequency (7 / day), low glycemic index/load and high antioxidant capacity as well as a high adherence to the Mediterranean diet. The control group (n = 50) is assigned to a diet with the same energy restriction and based on the American Heart Association pattern. Both experimental groups are under dietary and psychological control during 8 weeks. Likewise, for an additional period of 16 weeks of self-control, is expected that volunteers will follow the same pattern but with no dietary advice. Results: Anthropometrical data and body composition determinations as well as blood and urine samples are being collected at the beginning and end of each phase. This project is registered at www.clinicaltrials.gov with the number NCT01087086 and count with the Research Ethics Committee of the University of Navarra approval (065/2009). Conclusions: Intervention trials to promote the adoption of dietary patterns and healthy lifestyle are of great importance to identify the outcomes and nutritional mechanisms that might explain the link between obesity, metabolic syndrome and associated complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zulet, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forga, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bondia-Pons, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abete, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas-Carretero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesia, R de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Legarrea, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La alta prevalencia del síndrome metabólico (SM) en España requiere de esfuerzos adicionales para su prevención y tratamiento. Objetivo: El estudio RESMENA-S tiene como objetivo mejorar criterios clínicos de SM y biomarcadores asociados a través de un tratamiento integral. Métodos: El estudio consiste en un ensayo aleatorizado de diseño paralelo y prospectivo en el que está previsto participen un total de 100 individuos. El grupo RESMENA-S (n = 50) sigue una dieta personalizada de pérdida de peso (restricción energética 30%), con una distribución en macronutrientes (hidratos de carbono/grasas/ proteínas) de 40/30/30, elevada frecuencia de ingestas (7/día), bajo índice/carga glucémica y elevada capacidad antioxidante y adherencia a la dieta Mediterránea. El grupo control (n = 50) sigue una dieta con la misma restricción energética y basada en la Asociación Americana del Corazón. El estudio tiene una duración de 8 semanas bajo control dietético y psicológico en ambos grupos. Durante un periodo adicional de 16 semanas de auto-control, los voluntarios siguen el mismo patrón dietético pero sin ningún asesoramiento específico. Resultados: Datos antropométricos y de composición corporal, así como muestras sanguíneas y de orina están siendo recogidas al inicio y al final de cada fase. Este proyecto está registrado en www.clinicaltrials.gov con el número NCT01087086 y cuenta con la aprobación del Comité de Ética de Investigación de la Universidad de Navarra (065/2009). Conclusiones: Las intervenciones que favorezcan la adopción de patrones dietéticos y de estilo de vida más saludables, son de elevada importancia para identificar los mecanismos que podrían explicar el nexo de unión entre obesidad, SM y complicaciones asociadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(1): 16-26, ene.-feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94121</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El estudio RESMENA-S: reducción del síndrome metabólico; una estrategia multidisciplinar basada en la crononutrición y la educación nutricional, junto con control dietético y psicológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16571</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
