<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166589</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">1977-2017: Nursing research in Spain after 40 years in the University</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nursing research in Spain cannot be understood without analyzing the development of this profession over the last 40 years. The social, political and economic context has determined the evolution of nursing research, and an analysis of the current situation is necessary to confront the immediate challenges the nursing profession has to handle. To offer a global perspective of care research in Spain as a framework for reflection and discussion on possible short and medium-term strategies that guide the planning and decision making of the different stakeholders involved in nursing research in Spain. A multi-method study combining documentary analysis with bibliometric methods was carried out. Some isolated policies to promote nursing research have been identified, a significant increase in doctoral training (49 doctoral programs) and 89 nurse research groups (1.92 groups per million inhabitants) responsible for a scientific production that puts Spain in seventh place in the world ranking of scientific production in the area of nursing. The increase in public expenditure on R &amp; D &amp; Iand the growth in bibliometric impact are associated with a higher density of nursing research groups. Nursing research in Spain is sensitive to research promotion policies and resources, although there is no consolidated and uniform strategy that overcomes current barriers. The impact of the academic development of Spanish nNursing in scientific production is still unknown (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pedro-Gómez, Joan Ernest de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueso Montoro, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bennasar Veny, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Asencio, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación enfermera en España no puede ser entendida sin el análisis de la evolución de la profesión en los últimos 40 años. El contexto social, político y económico ha determinado el devenir de la investigación en cuidados y es necesario un análisis de la situación actual de cara a los retos inmediatos que la profesión enfermera tiene ante sí. Ofrecer una perspectiva global de la investigación en cuidados en España, como marco de reflexión y discusión acerca de posibles estrategias a corto y medio plazo que orienten la planificación y toma de decisiones a los distintos agentes implicados en la investigación enfermera en España. Estudio multimétodo que ha combinado análisis documental, con métodos bibliométricos. Se han identificado algunas políticas aisladas de fomento de la investigación en cuidados, un crecimiento importante de la formación doctoral (49 programas de doctorado) y 89 grupos de investigación enfermera (1,92 grupos por millón de habitantes) responsables de una producción científica que sitúa a España en el séptimo lugar en el ranking mundial de producción científica en el área de Enfermería. El incremento en el gasto público en I+D+I y el crecimiento en impacto bibliométrico se asocian a una mayor densidad de grupos de investigación enfermeros. La investigación enfermera en España es sensible a las políticas y recursos de fomento de la investigación, aunque no hay una estrategia consolidada y uniforme que supere las barreras actuales. Aún se desconoce el impacto del desarrollo académico de la Enfermería española en la producción científica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);27(5): 314-326, sept.-oct. 2017. mapas, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166589</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">1977-2017: La investigación enfermera en España tras 40 años en la Universidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13426^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8063^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
