<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68421</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to evaluate the attitude of the adolescents and the magnitude of the drug consumption, both legal and illegal, through a survey, in order to infer the formative needs and to work on a preventive and health&#146;s promotion program. Subject and methods: an anonymous survey to the students of two Secondary Schools of the health area. Four hundred and forty-five surveys have been made to adolescents between 14 y 18 (mean: 16.04), 13 were excluded because of insufficient information. Results: one hundred and eighty-four adolescents (45%) say that they have smoked in the last 6 months, 217 have drunk alcohol (64%), 111 have taken cannabis (44%), 21 cocaine (9%) and pills (MDMA, amphetamines) (7%). Twenty-two percent of the adolescents have no taken any of these substances. As for the consideration of those products as drugs, they all agree that the heroin is a drug, but that was not so clear in the case of the rest, with the next percentages: cocaine (98%), pills (98%), hashish (96%), tobacco (80%) and finally alcohol (64%). Conclusions: alcohol is the most consumed drug by these adolescents and it is what they consider the least as a drug. The same happens, in a lesser extent, with tobacco and hashish. It&#146;s necessary to give the adolescents true information about the danger and consequences of the "legal drugs" (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano Garcinuño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casares Alonso, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rostami, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar las actitudes de los adolescentes ante las drogas y la magnitud de su consumo, tanto de legales como de ilegales, por medio de una encuesta, con el fin de deducir las necesidades formativas y elaborar posteriormente un programa preventivo y de promoción de la salud. Material y métodos: encuesta anónima a los estudiantes de dos centros de educación secundaria, un instituto y un centro de formación profesional situados en el área de salud. Se han realizado 445 encuestas a adolescentes de entre 14 y 18 años (edad media 16,04), excluyéndose 13 por datos insuficientes. Resultados: 184 adolescentes (45%) afirman que han fumado tabaco en los últimos 6 meses, 217 (64%) que han consumido alcohol, 111 (44%) han tomado cannabis, 21 (9%) cocaína y un 7% pastillas (éxtasis-anfetaminas). Un 22% de los adolescentes entre 14 y 18 años no había tomado ninguna de las sustancias mencionadas. En cuanto a la consideración como droga de los diversos productos, todos estuvieron de acuerdo en que la heroína lo era y en porcentajes decrecientes opinaban que eran drogas la cocaína (98%), las pastillas (98%), el hachís (96%), el tabaco (80%) y en último lugar el alcohol (64%). Conclusiones: el alcohol es la droga más consumida por estos adolescentes y la que menor consideración de droga tiene entre ellos. Lo mismo sucede, en menor medida, con el tabaco y el hachís. Es preciso aportar a los adolescentes una información veraz sobre las consecuencias y peligros de las denominadas "drogas legales" (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;10(39): 409-422, jul.-sept. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68421</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
