<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155329</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a positive psychology intervention combined with cognitive behavioral therapy in university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to design and implement a positive intervention combined with cognitive-behavioral therapy to enhance subjective and psychological well-being and other positive functioning constructs in a convenience sample. Participants analysed were 48 university students (mean age 22.25), 25 assigned nonrandomized to intervention condition and 23 to no-treatment waiting-list control condition. All participants were assessed pre- and post-intervention to test the treatment program effectiveness. Repeated-measures ANCOVAs, controlling baseline differences between the two groups, indicated that the intervention group reported greater social support after the intervention period than the waiting-list control group. Within-group differences were found for happiness, selfacceptance, positive relations with others, optimism, and self-esteem in the intervention group; these differences did not appear in the waiting-list control group. These findings suggest the limited capacity of this intervention program for improving well-being through positive activities combined with cognitive-behavioral therapy. Future research should analyse what kind of activities could be more effective in promoting well-being depending on the characteristics of participants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marrero, Rosario-Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, Sabrina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballeira, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Juan-Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejías, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue diseñar e implementar una intervención positiva combinada con técnicas de terapia cognitivo-conductual para mejorar el bienestar subjetivo y psicológico, así como otras variables de funcionamiento positivo en una muestra de conveniencia. Los participantes analizados fueron 48 estudiantes universitarios (media 22.25 años). Se llevó a cabo una asignación no aleatorizada de los participantes a la condición de intervención (n = 25) y a la condición de control en lista de espera sin tratamiento (n = 23). Todos los participantes fueron evaluados antes y después de la intervención para probar la efectividad del programa de tratamiento. Los ANCOVAs de medidas repetidas, controlando las diferencias de la línea base entre los dos grupos, indicaron que el grupo de intervención mostraba mayor apoyo social después del período de intervención que en el grupo control en lista de espera. Se encontraron diferencias intragrupo en felicidad, auto-aceptación, relaciones positivas con los otros, optimismo y autoestima para el grupo de intervención, mientras que estas diferencias no aparecían en el grupo de control en lista de espera. Estos hallazgos sugieren la capacidad limitada de este programa de intervención para mejorar el bienestar a través de actividades positivas combinado con terapia cognitivo-conductual. Las investigaciones futuras deberían analizar qué tipo de actividades podrían ser más eficaces en la promoción del bienestar en función de las características de los participantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;32(3): 728-740, oct. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155329</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de una intervención en psicología positiva combinada con terapia cognitivo conductual en estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56069^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
