<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117644</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Articulation between culture and individual in the works of Sigmund Freud</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author starts from the premise that the Freudian thought is built around three human dimensions levels: the biological, psychic, and social one. In this way, it inaugurates a new anthropological vision of the human being. Said development is based on the state of helplessness that life initiates with. Helplessness that shall be present throughout existence and arises from the need of feeling included in the human community and at the same time, it shall determine a dynamic that leads to the reality principle incorporation causing a permanent conflict with the pleasure principle, from which a sense of unease in the culture shall be derived (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Genovés, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autor parte de la premisa de que el pensamiento freudiano se construyó en un intento de engarzar tres dimensiones de la experiencia humana: la biológica, la psíquica y la social. De este modo inauguró una nueva visión antropológica acerca del ser humano. Su desarrollo está basado en el desampara con el que se inicia la vida y que lo obliga a desarrollar lazos libidinales con sus semejantes, estableciéndose un conflicto entre el principio de realidad y el del placer del cual derivará el malestar en la cultura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(65): 215-230, jul. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117644</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Articulación entre el individuo y la culture en la obra freudiana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53741</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22845</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
