<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125786</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The analyst´s culture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The paper puts foward the necessity of bearing in mind the theoretical conditioning posed by the historical and personal circumstances at the time of building and developing theories which, in their longing for scientific rigour, are erected ad universal and temporal ones, thus neglecting such conditioning. It is put forward that, in the case of psychoanalysis, this denial sometimes leads to a distorted interpretation of the patients´ psychic reality because of heating them from the viewpoint of parameters founded on contingent historical and social structures (as it is the case with the occidental family) instead of truly essential human conditions. The author thinks that psychoanalysis is at a acrossroads between unholding the theory as a dogma or reviewing and enriching the original concepts, and aligns herself with the position that it is ana attitude of reseatch, much more than a conservative stance, what enriches theory, benefits clinical works and raises the prestige of psychoanalysis among the Human Sciences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cinello, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo propone la necesidad de tener en cuenta los condicionamientos teóricos que suponen las circunstancias históricas y personales a la hora de construir y desarrollar teorías, que, en virtud de un anhelo de rigor científico, se erigen como universales y atemporales, negando dichas determinaciones. Plantea que esta negación, en el caso del psicoanálisis, conduce a una interpretación a veces distorsionada de la realidad psíquica de los pacientes, al escucharlos basándose en parámetros confeccionados en base a estructuras históricas y sociales contingentes (como es la familia occidental) y no a verdaderas condiciones humanas esenciales. Piensa la autora que el psicoanálisis se encuentra en una encrucijada entre el mantenimiento de la teoría en tanto dogma o la revisión y el enriquecimiento de los conceptos originales y se posiciona en la línea que sostiene que una actitud investigadora, mucho más que un talante conservador enriquece la teoría, beneficia a la clínica y prestigia al psicoanálisis dentro de las Ciencias del Hombre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(67): 221-227, nov. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125786</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La cultura del analista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1544^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1544^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
