<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97446</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of pre-operative education in reducing anxiety in surgical patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To evaluate the effectiveness of a structured pre-operative interview conducted by operating room nurses in order to reduce the pre-operative anxiety of patients, and to determine the profile of patients who can benefit from it. Material and Methods A randomised double-blind and prospective trial was conducted on a sample of 335 patients scheduled for surgery in two regional hospitals in the Basque Region of Spain, Alto Deba Hospital and Mendaro Hospital. We compared the alternative of using a structured briefing (test group) with the current situation without any formal intervention (control group). The effectiveness of the procedure was determined using the STAI state anxiety self-assessment questionnaire. The Chi-squared statistic was used to assess the differences in factors and the Student t-test for comparison of means in the continuous variables. Results The impact of the intervention on measures of state anxiety and trait anxiety was found to be not statistically significant, although the mean state anxiety state was slightly lower in the intervention group (18.96) than in the controls (20.03). Women undergoing surgery in the specialty of gynaecology showed the higher state anxiety compared with other specialties. As regards trait anxiety a higher ASA level is associated with higher anxiety. Furthermore, the consumption of psychotropic drugs is also related to a higher level of trait anxiety. Conclusion The preoperative visit can be helpful when patients are selected according to specific characteristics: by type of anaesthesia, gender, or type of surgery. There may also be beneficial effects when preoperative education is tailored according to patient&#145;s anxiety risk. The time immediately before surgery may not be the best time for conducting the visit, as this may make the patients more anxious (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lizaur, Belen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrospide, Arantzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana, Jose M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrañaga, Aintzane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Álvarez, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez, Uzuri</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belaustegi, Alazne</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mar, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Evaluar la efectividad de una entrevista prequirúrgica estructurada llevada a cabo por las enfermeras de quirófano 1 hora antes de entrar los pacientes al quirófano en relación a la disminución de la ansiedad preoperatoria de los pacientes, y establecer el perfil de los pacientes que se pueden beneficiar de ella en relación a la edad, sexo e intervención quirúrgica a realizar. Material y métodos Ensayo clínico aleatorizado simple ciego, realizado con una muestra de 335 pacientes programados para intervenciones quirúrgicas en dos hospitales comarcales: Hospital Alto Deba y en el Hospital de Mendaro. Se comparó la alternativa de utilizar una intervención informativa estructurada (grupo ensayo) con la situación actual en la que no se lleva a cabo ninguna intervención (grupo control). La eficacia del procedimiento fue recogida mediante el cuestionario de autoevaluación STAI ansiedad-estado. En el tratamiento estadístico de los datos se utilizó el estadístico chi-cuadrado en el caso de los factores y la t de Student para la igualdad de medias en el de variables continuas. Resultados El impacto de la intervención sobre las medidas de la ansiedad estado y ansiedad rasgo se mostró como no significativo estadísticamente a pesar de que la media de la ansiedad estado era ligeramente más baja en el grupo de intervención (18,96) que en el control (20,03). Cabe destacar la mayor ansiedad de estado de las mujeres intervenidas en la especialidad de ginecología frente a los demás intervenidos. En el caso de la ansiedad rasgo se observa que un nivel de ASA mayor de 2 supone una mayor ansiedad; además, el consumo de psicofármacos también está relacionado con un mayor nivel de ansiedad de rasgo. Conclusión El preoperatorio inmediato puede no ser el mejor momento para la realización de la visita ya que no facilita que su efecto sea ansiolítico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);22(1): 18-26, ene.-feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de una intervención preoperatoria de enfermería sobre el control de la ansiedad de los pacientes quirúrgicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
