<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111870</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of physical fitness in fire-fighters according to age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction:  Fire-fighters must be in good physical condition to safely perform their activities. The aims of this study were to describe the anthropometric characteristics and physical fitness of two groups of fire-fighters and discuss the differences according to age. Material and methods: A total of 33 fire-fighters from the two groups took part: G1, under 40, and G2, over 40 years. We analysed body composition, jump test, hamstring flexibility, hand dynamometry, strength of upper and lower extremities, and heart rate, estimated maximal oxygen consumption and perceived exertion in Course Navette. Results: Both groups had body composition values as regards weight, and significant differences were only found in height. As regards physical condition, G1 showed better values for all variables than G2. They only significant differences being in the estimated maximal oxygen consumption, rate of perceived exertion, manual strength of the left hand, and maximum dynamic force. Conclusions: Both groups presented characteristics of fitness appropriate for the proper development of their professional activity. However, G1 had higher values than G2 in all variables of physical fitness(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres-Luque, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Franco, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Sánchez, Amador J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zagalaz Sánchez, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los bomberos deben presentar un excelente estado de forma para desempeñar de modo seguro su actividad profesional. Los objetivos de este trabajo son describir las características antropométricas y de condición física en dos grupos de bomberos y discutir sobre las diferencias que existen en función de la edad. Material y métodos: Han participado 33 bomberos: G1, menores de 40 años, y G2, mayores de 40 años. Se ha analizado la composición corporal, el test de salto, la flexibilidad isquiosural, la dinamometría manual y la fuerza de las extremidades superiores e inferiores, así como la frecuencia cardíaca, la estimación del consumo máximo de oxígeno y la percepción subjetiva del esfuerzo en Course Navette. Resultados: Ambos grupos han presentado valores de composición corporal correspondientes a niveles de normopeso, y solamente se han encontrado diferencias significativas en la talla. Respecto a la condición física, G1ha presentado mejores valores que G2 en todas las variables, aunque solo han sido significativas en cuanto a consumo máximo de oxígeno, percepción subjetiva del esfuerzo, fuerza manual de la mano izquierda y fuerza dinámica máxima. Conclusiones: Los grupos analizados muestran características de condición física adecuadas para el buen desarrollo de su actividad profesional. No obstante, G1 ostenta mayores valores que G2 en todas las variables evaluadas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);48(177): 11-16, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la condición física en bomberos en función de la edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
