<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124271</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9572</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tools for measuring excessive daytime sleepiness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Excessive daytime sleepiness is a complex reality because there is a mixture of subjective feeling and objective manifestations. This symptoms id present in a varietry of diseases and their physiopathological mechanisms are multiple. There are currently different tools available for the evaluation of excessive somnolence from an introspective point of view as well as from an objective one, each one studies a field and attempts to make an approximation to a given sleep situation, all have advantages and limitations. The selection of diagnostic tools will depend on the field under study or the possibilities of the Centre of the field. No approach is a gold standard in itself and none are flawless when it comes to legal situations. Legal aspects have acquired greater specific weight because of the implication of somnolence in problems of public health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Sánchez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La somnolencia es un fenómeno complejo en el que se imbrican sensaciones subjetivas con manifestaciones objetivas. Forma parte de diversos síndromes y sus mecanismos fisiopatológicos son múltiples a la vez que controvertidos.Se dispone de diferentes métodos para la evaluación de la somnolencia, tanto desde el punto de vista introspectivo como objetivo, cada uno de ellos valora un campo y hace una aproximación a la situación, todos tienen sus ventajas y desventajas. La elección de una u otra prueba dependerá de los aspectos a estudiar y a veces de las posibilidades del Centro. Ninguna es el "gold standar" y tampoco está suficientemente contrastada para utilizarla ante problemas legales, motivo éste a tener en cuenta dada la importancia que la somnolencia tiene en cuestiones de salud pública (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Vigilia sueño;15(2): 118-124, jul. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124271</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Métodos de evaluación de la excesiva somnolencia diurna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13274^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
