<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86579</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glass maze in women&#146;s leadership</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychological gender discrimination explanations have changed over the past thirty years, becoming more complex in order to obtain a better understanding of the social reality. At the present moment, one of the most interesting research areas is the one referring to the &#145;glass maze&#146; phenomenon in women&#146;s management careers. The main purpose of this work is to reveal the theoretical evolution in an attempt to explain the leadership study from a gender perspective. The consecutive hypotheses, starting with the labour sexual division idea, are becoming more interactive in order to understand the current labour-social situation. Social psychology has underlined the role of beliefs, observed via gender stereotyped roles, prejudiced attitudes against women, sexist and neosexist ideology, or masculine, feminine and androgynous identity development. New psychological interpretations insist on the variability of the gender concept, where gender is sometimes observed through men and women&#146;s behaviours, and other times through those behaviour expectations. But gender is mainly observed though the power relations between men and women during social interactions in labour organizations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barberá Heredia, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos López, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Candela Agulló, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las teorías sobre la discriminación de género han ido evolucionando a lo largo de los treinta últimos años y se han hecho más complejas en un intento por comprender la realidad social. Uno de los ámbitos preferentes de investigación es el referido al laberinto de cristal en la carrera directiva de las mujeres. El objetivo de este trabajo consiste en poner de manifiesto la evolución en las explicaciones del enfoque de género al estudio del liderazgo, incidiendo en las transformaciones desde las hipótesis centradas en la división sexual del trabajo, hasta las formulaciones más recientes de carácter interactivo. La psicología social ha destacado el papel de las creencias, a través de los roles estereotipados, las actitudes prejuiciosas hacia las mujeres, la ideología sexista y neo-sexista o el desarrollo de identidades de género. Las interpretaciones actuales inciden en la variabilidad del concepto de género, que a veces se manifiesta a través de las conductas que realizan los hombres y las mujeres, pero también está presente en la elaboración que se hace de dichas conductas y, sobre todo, se observa en las relaciones de poder en el transcurso de las interacciones sociales de la organización laboral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(2): 173-179, abr.-jun. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86579</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Laberinto de cristal en el liderazgo de las mujeres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4252</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13124</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15329^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15330^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
