<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163623</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of electrolytic lesion of the dorsomedial striatum on sexual behaviour and locomotor activity in rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cortical motor areas are influenced not only by peripheral sensory afferents and prefrontal association areas, but also by the basal ganglia, specifically the striatum. The dorsomedial striatum (DMS) and dorsolateral striatum are involved in both spatial and stimulus-response learning; however, each of these areas may mediate different components of learning. The aim of the study is to determine the effect of electrolytic lesion to the DMS on the learning and performance of sexual behaviour and locomotor activity in male rats. Method: Once the subjects had learned to perform motor tests of balance, maze navigation, ramp ascent, and sexual behaviour, they underwent electrolytic lesion to the DMS. Five days later, the tests were repeated on 2 occasions and researchers compared performance latencies for each test. Results: Average latency values for performance on the maze and balance tests were higher after the lesion. However, the average values for the ramp test and for sexual behaviour did not differ between groups. Conclusions: Electrolytic lesion of the DMS modifies the performance of locomotor activity (maze test and balance), but not of sexual behavior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tamariz-Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranda-Abreu, GE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, LI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coria-Avila, GA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Pulido, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Briones, ZS</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las áreas motoras corticales no solo son influenciadas por aferencias sensitivas periféricas y áreas de asociación prefrontales, sino también por los ganglios basales, específicamente el estriado. El estriado dorsomedial (EDM) y el estriado dorsolateral están involucrados en el aprendizaje espacial y el aprendizaje estímulo-respuesta; sin embargo, cada una de estas zonas pudiera mediar distintos componentes del aprendizaje. El propósito del estudio es determinar el efecto de la lesión electrolítica del EDM sobre el aprendizaje y ejecución de la conducta locomotora y sexual en ratas macho. Método: Una vez que los sujetos aprendieron a ejecutar las pruebas motoras de equilibrio, laberinto, rampa de ascenso y la conducta sexual, se realizó la lesión electrolítica del EDM. Cinco días después se realizaron las pruebas en 2 ocasiones más y se compararon las latencias de ejecución de cada prueba. Resultados: Después de la lesión, los valores promedio de latencia, incrementaron durante la ejecución de las pruebas de laberinto y equilibrio. Sin embargo, los valores promedio en la prueba rampa y conducta sexual, no aportaron efectos contrastantes entre los grupos. Conclusiones: La lesión electrolítica del EDM modifica la ejecución de la actividad locomotora (prueba de laberinto y equilibrio), pero no la ejecución de la conducta sexual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(5): 278-283, jun. 2017. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163623</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la lesión electrolítica del estriado dorsomedial sobre la conducta sexual y actividad locomotora de la rata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32152^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34226^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4644^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8300^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3358^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
