<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147856</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of clinical prediction rules for ruling out deep vein thrombosis in a hospital emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To compare the efficacy of the most familiar clinical prediction rules in combination with D-dimer testing to rule out a diagnosis of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in a hospital emergency department. Methods. Retrospective cross-sectional analysis of the case records of all patients attending a hospital emergency department with suspected lower-limb DVT between 1998 and 2002. Ten clinical prediction scores were calculated and D-dimer levels were available for all patients. The gold standard was ultrasound diagnosis of DVT by an independent radiologist who was blinded to clinical records. For each prediction rule, we analyzed the effectiveness of the prediction strategy defined by &#147;low clinical probability and negative D-dimer level&#148; against the ultrasound diagnosis. Results. A total of 861 case records were reviewed and 577 cases were selected; the mean (SD) age was 66.7 (14.2) years. DVT was diagnosed in 145 patients (25.1%). Only the Wells clinical prediction rule and 4 other models had a false negative rate under 2%. The Wells criteria and the score published by Johanning and colleagues identified higher percentages of cases (15.6% and 11.6%, respectively). Conclusions. This study shows that several clinical prediction rules can be safely used in the emergency department, although none of them have proven more effective than the Wells criteria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Jiménez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Jiménez, Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santoro-Martínez, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreras-Álvarez de Cienfuegos, Amelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano-Rodríguez, Aquiles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duro-López, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Comparar la efectividad de los modelos clínicos más conocidos en combinación con el dímero D para la exclusión de un diagnóstico de trombosis venosa profunda (TVP) en un área de urgencias hospitalarias (AUH).Método: Estudio retrospectivo de serie de casos con análisis transversal a partir de un registro que incluyó a todo paciente atendido por una sospecha clínica de TVP en miembros inferiores en un AUH entre los años 1998 y 2002. Se calcularon los 10 modelos clínicos y se determinó el dímero D a todos los pacientes. La prueba de referencia fue el diagnóstico de TVP realizado por parte de un radiólogo independiente y enmascarado a los datos clínicos mediante la realización de una ecografía. Se analizó la efectividad de la estrategia &#147;baja probabilidad clínica y dímero D negativo&#148; de cada modelo en relación a los resultados ecográficos obtenidos. Resultados: Del total de 861 casos del registro, se seleccionaron 577 pacientes con una edad media de 66,7 (DE 14,2) años. Se realizó el diagnóstico de TVP en 145 pacientes (25,1%). Sólo el modelo de Wells y otros 4 modelos presentaron un porcentaje de falsos negativos inferior al 2%. De ellos, el modelo de Wells seguido del publicado por Johanning seleccionaron a un mayor porcentaje de pacientes (15,6% y 11,6%, respectivamente).Conclusiones: El presente estudio muestra que existen diversos modelos clínicos que se pueden aplicar de forma segura en el ámbito de urgencias, aunque ninguno de ellos ha documentado ser más efectivo que la escala de Wells (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(6): 375-378, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los diferentes modelos clínicos en la exclusión de la trombosis venosa profunda en un área de urgencias hospitalarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
