<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143175</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cancer and cardiovascular disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Survivors of cancer have a shorter survival in the long term partly due to the increase in cardiovascular diseases (CVD). Some chemotherapy drugs, thoracic and cranial radiotherapy and above all the transplantation of hematopoietic cells are associated with an increase in the incidence of cardiovascular events compared with general population. Some of these treatments favor the development of a metabolic syndrome that could be the intermediary between these treatments and the development of CVD. It is recommended for cancer survivors to promote healthy lifestyles and the strict control of cardiovascular risk factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lahoz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Alegre, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estirado, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Iglesias, María Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mostaza, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdivielso, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes que sobreviven a un cáncer tienen una menor supervivencia a largo plazo en parte debida al incremento de las enfermedades cardiovasculares (ECV). Algunos fármacos quimioterápicos, la radioterapia craneal y torácica y, sobre todo, el trasplante de células hematopoyéticas se asocian a un incremento de la incidencia de eventos cardiovasculares comparados con la población general. Algunos de estos tratamientos favorecen el desarrollo de un síndrome metabólico que podría ser el intermediario entre dichos tratamientos y el desarrollo de las ECV. Se recomienda en los supervivientes de un cáncer fomentar estilos de vida saludables y el control estricto de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);27(5): 221-225, sept.-oct. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143175</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer y enfermedad cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32203^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
