<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74782</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tiered skull graft for the management of post-traumatic enophthalmos and dystopia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Almost 90%1 of traumatic injuries to the craniofacialmassif involve the eye sockets, and a large proportion of these injuriesgenerate sequelae, such as post-traumatic enophthalmos anddystopia.The literature contains numerous references to surgical techniquesfor the correction of these sequelae and diverse materials for orbitalreconstruction after trauma. However, few of them have beendesigned to restore the original anatomy of the orbital floor. Forthat reason, it is important to develop a simple and effectivetechnique for correcting orbital damage. The present article describesthe use of a new surgical technique for the management of thesequelae mentioned using a tiered skull graft on the floor of theorbit. It is an excellent option for graft placement because of its lowresorption rate and minimal adverse reactions.Patients. Four patients (1 woman, 3 men), average age 23 years(range 17-27 years) and history of facial trauma with orbitalinvolvement were treated between 2004 and 2007 at the HospitalCentral de la Policía Nacional and Hospital El Tunal (Bogotá,Colombia). All of them authorized the procedure by signing aninformed consent form. The tiered graft technique was used for thepost-traumatic correction of enophthalmos and dystopia. Resultswith a follow-up time of 11 to 42 weeks are reported.Results. All the patients exhibited a reduction in the eye socket andsymmetrical projection of the eyeball in anteroposterior and verticaldirection, as well as complete improvement of the diplopia after thetiered skull graft was used to repair the orbital floor.Conclusion. The technique is simple and inexpensive, with minimalmorbidity and predictable and satisfactory results in the short andintermediate term(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abril Rodríguez, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Páramo Jiménez, V. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Lagos, O. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñuela Balaguera, l. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Casi un 90%1 de los traumatismos del macizo craneofacial involucran lasórbitas, y un alto porcentaje de los mismos generan secuelas como son el enoftalmosy la distopia postraumáticos.Existen en la literatura numerosas referencias de técnicas quirúrgicas para correcciónde dichas secuelas y diversos materiales para la reconstrucción orbitaria posterior altrauma, pero pocas de ellas se han encaminado a devolver la anatomía original alsuelo orbitario, por tal razón se considera perentorio desarrollar una técnica sencillay eficaz para la corrección de los defectos antes descritos. El presente artículo refierela utilización de una nueva técnica quirúrgica para el manejo de las secuelas yamencionadas usando un injerto escalonado de calota en el suelo de la órbita, dadoque este último es una excelente opción para la colocación de injertos, debido a subaja tasa de reabsorción y mínimas reacciones adversas.Pacientes. Cuatro pacientes (1 mujer, 3 hombres) con un promedio de edad de 23años (rango entre 17 y 27 años) con antecedente de trauma facial y compromiso dela órbita, que fueron tratados entre 2004 y 2007, en el Hospital Central de la PolicíaNacional y Hospital El Tunal (Bogotá, Colombia), previa autorización mediantefirma de consentimiento informado. En ellos se utilizó la técnica de injerto escalonadode calota para corrección de enoftalmos y distopia postraumática. Se describenresultados con un tiempo de seguimiento entre 11 y 42 semanas.Resultados. En todos los pacientes se observó disminución del continente orbitario yproyección simétrica del globo ocular en sentido antero-posterior y vertical, así comotambién mejoría completa de la diplopía, luego de la colocación del injerto escalonadode calota en el suelo orbitario.Conclusión. Se trata de una técnica sencilla, de bajo costo, mínima morbilidad, conresultados predecibles y satisfactorios a corto y medio plazo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;30(6): 440-448, nov.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74782</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Injerto escalonado de calota para manejo de enoftalmos y distopia postraumática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5252^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4229^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10097^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24623^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
