<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109141</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personality dimensions and Working Alliance in subjects with Borderline Personality Disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. As yet, the relation between personality traits and working alliance (WA) has not been investigated in subjects affected by borderline personality disorder (BPD). Method. A sample of forty-nine BPD subjects who completed a module of Sequential Brief Adlerian Psychodynamic Psychotherapy (SB-APP) of 40 sessions has been recruited. Before the onset of psychotherapy an assessment was made with Clinical Global Impression (CGI), Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF), Symptom Checklist Revised 90 (SCL-R 90), and with Temperament and Character Inventory (TCI). At the end of their psychotherapy, patients were requested to rate the level of WA by means of the Working Alliance Inventory (WAI-S). Results. Multiple linear regression analysis has identified three variables as independent predictors of WAI-S total score: subjects with lower Harm Avoidance (HA), older patients, and subjects with a higher psychopathology level had a better WAIS total score. Discussion. These preliminary results showed that the pattern of alliance with the therapist in subjects with BPD could be related not only to weakness of character, but also to a temperamental trait typical of inhibited and avoidant subjects. Conclusion. These results suggest that an assessment of temperament in subjects affected by BPD at intake could be useful to detect the subjects who have more difficulties in building a good WA and in order to improve the technical interventions and settings for psychotherapy of BPD subjects with higher HA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cairo, Elisabetta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pierò, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Hasta el momento no se ha investigado la relación entre los rasgos de la personalidad y la alianza terapéutica en individuos con trastorno límite de la personalidad (TLP). Métodos. Se reclutó para el estudio una muestra de 49 individuos con TLP que completaron un módulo de la Sequential Brief Adlerian Psychodynamic Psychotherapy (SB-APP) de 40 sesiones. Antes del inicio de la psicoterapia, se realizó una evaluación con las escalas Clinical Global Impression (CGI), Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF), Symptom Checklist Revised 90 (SCL-R 90), y con el Temperament and Character Inventory (TCI). Al final de la psicoterapia, se pidió a los pacientes que evaluaran el nivel de la alianza terapéutica mediante el Working Alliance Inventory (WAI-S). Resultados. Un análisis de regresión lineal múltiple ha identificado 3 variables como factores predictivos independientes para la puntuación total del WAI-S: los individuos con una evitación del daño menor, los pacientes de mayor edad y los individuos con mayor nivel de psicopatología presentaron una mejor puntuación total del WAI-S. Discusión. Estos resultados preliminares pusieron de manifiesto que el patrón de la alianza con el terapeuta en los individuos con TLP podría estar relacionado no solo con la debilidad de carácter, sino también con un rasgo del temperamento característico de los individuos inhibidos y con tendencia a la evitación. Conclusión. Estos resultados sugieren que una evaluación del temperamento en los individuos que presentan un TLP podría ser útil para detectar a aquellos que tienen más dificultades para establecer una buena alianza terapéutica y para mejorar las intervenciones técnicas y los contextos de la psicoterapia de los pacientes con TLP con una mayor evitación del daño(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);6(1): 17-25, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109141</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dimensiones de la personalidad y alianza terapéutica en individuos con trastorno límite de la personalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
