<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056475</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Helicobacter pylori erradication and its relation to antibiotic resistance and CYP2C19 status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to assess the efficacy of rabeprazole (RPZ), amoxicillin        (Am), and clarithromycin (Cla) (7 vs. 14 days) in the eradication        of H. pylori, and to determine the effect of strain-specific antibiotic        resistance and host CYP2C19 status.        Material and methods: first, we determined the CYP2C19        status of 100 healthy subjects to establish a sample size for the clinical        trial. Then, 59 H. pylori-infected patients were randomized        to receive RPZ (20 mg daily) plus Cla (500 mg b.d.) and Am        (1,000 mg b.d.) for 7 vs. 14 days. The MIC for Am and Cla were        determined using the agar dilution method. The CYP2C19 genotype        was determined by the PCR-RFLP method.        Results: in the per-protocol analysis (PP) eradication rates        were 89.7 and 72% for the 7- and 14-day groups (p = 0.159). In        the intention to-treat analysis (ITT) eradication rates were 86.7        and 62.1% in the 7- and 14-day groups, respectively (p = 0.06).        None of the strains was resistant to Am, and 4 strains were resistant        to Cla: 3 (11.1%) in the 14-day group and 1 (4%) in the 7-        day group. Neither strain-specific antibiotic resistance nor host        CYP2C19 status influenced eradication rates.        Conclusions: both 7- and 14-day therapies were effective for        H. pylori eradication. Strain resistance and CYP2C19 status do        not seem to influence eradication rates in the studied population</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garza González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giasi González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, G. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pérez, G. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado Garza, H. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosques Padilla, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Vázquez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar la eficacia del rabeprazol (RPZ), amoxicilina        (Am) y claritromicina (Cla) (7 vs. 14 días) en la erradicación        de H. pylori y determinar el efecto de la resistencia a los antibióticos        y el genotipo de CYP2C19.        Material y métodos: inicialmente, se determinó el genotipo        de CYP2C19 a 100 sujetos sanos para determinar el tamaño de        muestra del ensayo clínico. Posteriormente, 59 pacientes H. pylori+        recibieron al azar RPZ (20 mg diarios), Cla (500 mg cada 12        horas) y Am (1.000 mg cada 12 horas) (7 vs. 14 días). Se determinó        la CMI para Am y Cla por el método de dilución en agar. El        genotipo CYP2C19 fue determinado por PCR-RFLP.        Resultados: en el análisis por protocolo (PP), las tasas de        erradicación fueron del 89,7 y 72% para los grupos de 7 y 14        días respectivamente (p = 0,159). En el análisis de intención de        tratamiento (IT), las tasas de erradicación fueron del 86,7 y        62,1% en los grupos de 7 y 14 días respectivamente (p = 0,06).        Ninguna cepa presentó resistencia a Am y 4 cepas fueron resistentes        a Cla: 3 (11,1%) en el grupo de 14 días y 1 (4%) en el        grupo de 7 días. Las tasas de erradicación no fueron afectadas        por la resistencia de la cepa o el genotipo de CYP2C19.        Conclusiones: las terapias de 7 y 14 días fueron eficaces        para la erradicación de H. pylori. Al parecer, la resistencia de la        cepa y el genotipo de CYP2C19, no influenciaron las tasas de        erradicación de H. pylori en la población estudiada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;99(2): 71-75, feb. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056475</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Erradicación de H. pylori y su relación con la resistencia a los antibióticos y el estatus de CYP2C19</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30587^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1585^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4871^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30785^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d877^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
