<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050865</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of depression in remissionphase in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE. Depression is the most common problem of psychiatric disorders encountered in Primary Care. Its management can differ from the psychiatrist's management, mainly during the remission phase. This study aimed to explore attitudes on management of depressed patients in remission in Primary Care and evaluate whether full remission is a feasible objective in this setting. METHODS. Part 1: semi-structured interview to Primary Care physicians on the management of depression in remission. Part 2: cross-sectional, multicenter study. Clinical data from depressed patients in remission (according to physician's criterion) were collected. Each physician should collect data on 5 consecutive patients seen over 3 months. The percentage of patients with full remission was evaluated by the Hamilton Depression Rating scale (6 items-short version) (full remission: HDRS-6 &amp;#8804;5). Factors related with a worst clinical condition were evaluated by a lineal regression test. RESULTS. Part 1: most of the physicians agreed with the requirement to continue full-dose maintenance therapy for 6 to 12 months. Low adherence to treatment was reported as the main problem in this period. Part 2: 37% of patients met the full-remission criteria. Age, occupation, episode duration, psychiatric comorbidity, psychiatric antecedents, and treatment satisfaction were related with worst clinical condition. CONCLUSIONS. The long-term management of depression in Primary Care agrees with the current treatment guidelines. The percentage of patients fulfilling remission criteria was similar to the reports in other clinical settings</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Ferrer,  J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fora Eroles, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Fernández de Pinedo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO. La depresión es el problema de salud mental más frecuente en Atención Primaria (AP). Su manejo terapéutico puede ser diferente en AP al del ámbito especialista, sobre todo durante la fase de estabilización. El objetivo del presente estudio fue conocer la actitud del médico de AP frente al paciente depresivo en remisión y evaluar si la resolución total del cuadro es un objetivo factible en este ámbito. MÉTODOS. 1.a parte: encuesta a médicos de AP sobre su experiencia en el manejo de la depresión en remisión. 2.a parte: estudio transversal, multicéntrico, donde se recogieron datos clínicos de pacientes con depresión en fase de remisión, según criterio clínico. Cada médico debía recoger datos de 5 pacientes, de forma consecutiva, durante 3 meses. Se evaluó la proporción de pacientes con remisión total según escala HDRS, versión reducida de 6 ítems (remisión total: HDRS-6 &amp;#8804;5), y los factores relacionados con un peor estado clínico mediante un test de regresión lineal. RESULTADOS. 1.a parte: la mayoría de entrevistados coincidía en la necesidad de un tratamiento prolongado (entre 6 meses y 1 año), con el mismo fármaco y dosis a las que respondió el paciente. La baja adherencia fue referida como el principal problema de esta etapa. 2.a parte: el 37% de pacientes reunían criterios de remisión total. Edad, ocupación, tiempo de evolución, comorbilidad psiquiátrica, antecedentes depresivos o satisfacción al tratamiento se relacionaron con un peor estado clínico. CONCLUSIONES. El manejo clínico de la depresión en fase de remisión en AP coincide con las guías terapéuticas vigentes. La proporción de pacientes con remisión total fue similar a la observada en otros ámbitos clínicos</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(10): 475-478, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050865</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la depresión en fase de remisión en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
