<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108778</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ambulatory blood pressure monitoring and heart failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">High blood pressure is one of the main causes of heart failure (HF) and good control of blood pressure is essential to the prevention and management of HF. Recent works, based on blood pressure levels measured in the medical of&amp;#64257;ce, have shown a signi&amp;#64257;cant correlation between lower BP and worse diagnosis of HF. However, a more common use of the ambulatory blood pressure monitoring (ABPM) demonstrates the existence of alterations in different components of the blood pressure. These make up entities such as nocturnal HBP or masked hypertension, which have been shown to imply worse prognosis of the cardiovascular disease. However, the information we have on the ABPM in patients with HF is scarce and the data we do have come from studies conducted in a very limited number of patients. Furthermore, the most frequent form of HF in the hypertense patient is HF due to diastolic dysfunction and these patients represent a very small part of the studies available. All this gives rise to questions about whether there may be alterations in the ABPM in these early phases of HF or if there are alterations of the circadian patterns of BP in patients with advanced HF, or whether these alterations in the ABPM patients have prognostic value or if the treatment of the HF has any effect on the characteristics of the ABPM. In this article, we have aimed to answer these questions using the limited evidence available (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camafort Babkowski, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipertensión arterial (HTA) es una de las principales causas de la insu&amp;#64257;ciencia cardiaca (IC) y un buen control de la presión arterial es fundamental en la prevención y manejo de la IC. Trabajos recientes, basados en cifras de presión arterial (PA) medidas en la consulta han mostrado una correlación signi&amp;#64257;cativa entre una PA más baja y un peor pronóstico de la IC. Sin embargo, una utilización más habitual de la monitorización ambulatoria de la presión arterial(MAPA) nos ha mostrado la existencia de alteraciones en diferentes componentes de la PA, que constituyen entidades como la HTA nocturna o la HTA enmascarada, que se ha demostrado que implican un peor pronóstico de la enfermedad cardiovascular. Sin embargo, la información de la que disponemos de datos de la MAPA en pacientes con IC es escasa, y los datos de los que disponemos provienen de estudios realizados en un número de pacientes muy limitado. Además, la forma más frecuente de IC en el paciente hipertenso es la IC por disfunción diastólica, y estos pacientes están muy poco representados en los estudios disponibles. Todo ello nos plantea preguntas como si existen en estas fases precoces de la IC alteraciones en la MAPA, o si existen alteraciones de los patrones circadianos de la PA en pacientes con IC avanzada, o si tienen estas alteraciones en los patrones de la MAPA valor pronóstico, o si el tratamiento de la IC tiene algún efecto sobre las características de la MAPA. En este artículo intentamos responder a estas preguntas través de la escasa evidencia disponible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;28(3): 102-107, Mayo - Jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108778</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización ambulatoria de la presión arterial e insuficiencia cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30693^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
