<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138229</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recombinant Human Keratinocyte Growth Factor Induces Akt Mediated Cell Survival Progression in Emphysematous Mice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Emphysema has been associated with decreasedVEGF andVEGFR-2 expression and the presence of high numbers of apoptotic alveolar cells. Keratinocyte growth factor stimulates VEGF synthesis which in turn confers normal lung structure maintenance via the Akt pathway. In this study the potential role of rHuKGF in the improvement of deregulatedAkt mediated cell survival pathway in emphysematous mice was investigated Methods: Three experimental groups, i.e., emphysema, treatment and control groups, were prepared. Lungs of mice were treated on 3 occasions by oropharyngeal instillation of 10 mg rHuKGF per kg body weight after induction of emphysema with porcine pancreatic elastase. Subsequently, lung tissues from mice were collected for histopathology and molecular biology studies. Results and discussion: Histopathology photomicrographs and destructive index analysis have shown that elastase-induced airspace enlargement and loss of alveoli recovered in the treatment group. rHuKGF stimulates VEGF production which in turn induces the Akt mediated cell survival pathway in emphysematous lungs. mRNA expression of VEGF, VEGFR, PI3K and Akt was significantly increased while Pten, Caspase-9 and Bad was notably decreased in treatment group when compared with emphysema group, being comparable with the control group. Moreover, VEGF protein expression was in accordance with that found for mRNA. Conclusion: Therapeutic rHuKGF supplementation improves the deregulated Akt pathway in emphysema, resulting in alveolar cell survival through activation of the endogenous VEGF-dependent cell survival pathway. Hence rHuKGF may prove to be a potential drug in the treatment of emphysema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kumar Tyagi, Amit</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prakash Muyal, Jai</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muyal, Vandana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kumar, Dhananjay</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kotnala, Sudhir</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El enfisema se ha asociado a una disminución de la expresión de VEGF y VEGFR-2 y a la presencia de un número elevado de células alveolares apoptósicas. El factor de crecimiento queratinocítico estimula la síntesis de VEGF, lo cual proporciona, a su vez, un mantenimiento de la estructura pulmonar normal a través de la vía de Akt. En este estudio hemos investigado el posible papel del rHuKGF en la mejora de la falta de regulación de la vía de supervivencia celular mediada por Akt en ratones enfisematosos. Métodos: Se establecieron 3 grupos experimentales: grupos de enfisema, tratamiento y control. Los pulmones de los ratones se trataron terapéuticamente en 3 ocasiones mediante la instilación orofaríngea de 10 mg de rHuKGF/kg de peso corporal tras la inducción del enfisema mediante elastasa pancreática porcina. Posteriormente, se obtuvo tejido pulmonar de los ratones para la realización de exámenes de histopatología y biología molecular. Resultados y discusión: Las microfotografías de histopatología y el análisis del índice de destrucción han mostrado que el agrandamiento del espacio aéreo inducido por la elastasa y la pérdida de alvéolos se recuperaron en el grupo de tratamiento. El rHuKGF estimula la producción de VEGF, que a su vez induce la vía de supervivencia celular mediada por Akt en los pulmones enfisematosos. Se produjo un aumento significativo de la expresión de mRNA de VEGF, VEGFR, PI3K y Akt, mientras que hubo una disminución notable de Pten, caspasa-9 y Bad en el grupo de tratamiento en comparación con el grupo de enfisema, y los resultados fueron comparables a los del grupo de control. Además, la expresión de VEGF a nivel proteico concordaba con la observada a nivel de mRNA. Conclusión: Los suplementos terapéuticos de rHuKGF mejoran la mala regulación de la vía de Akt en el trastorno del enfisema, dando lugar a una supervivencia celular alveolar a través de una activación de la vía de la supervivencia celular dependiente de VEGF endógena. Así pues, el rHuKGF podría ser un posible fármaco para el tratamiento del enfisema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(7): 328-337, jul. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138229</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El factor de crecimiento queratinocítico humano recombinante induce la progresión de la supervivencia celular mediada por Akt en ratones enfisematosos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24758^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37364^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50719^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4722^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33519^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2505^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
