<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053077</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Estimation of the prevalence of attention deficit/hyperactivity disorder among the standard population on the island of Majorca</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To determine the rate of prevalence of attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) in children of school        age (6-11 years) in the Island of Mallorca. Subjects and methods. The epidemiological study was conducted using a        community sample extracted by means of multi-stage stratified sampling according to areas (rural, city and touristy) and        schooling (public, private and concerted) and consisted in 1,509 children of both sexes. The ADHD Rating Scales-IV (ADHD        RS-IV) for home and school setting were used to collect data. The optimal approach to do a diagnostic evaluation, according        with the literature, was using a cut-off point of 90 centil. Results. The estimated prevalence of ADHD was 4.57% (confidence        interval at 99%: 3.0-5.8%) and we also obtained 1.26% for the hyperactive subtype, 1.06% for the disattentional subtype, and        2.25% for the combined subtype. Contrary to what was expected, prevalence was higher for females but no statistically        significant. There were no statistically significant differences between levels, schools or areas. Conclusions. The estimates for        prevalence found in this study are consistent with those reported in the literature (between 3-5%). Using the ADHD RS-IV        which has different cut-off point regarding age, sex and setting and the fact that it was a poblational based study could explain        the higher prevalence in the females. We propose a normalization of the scales in our area in other to confirm our findings</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cardo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Servera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llobera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la tasa de prevalencia del trastorno por déficit de atención con o sin hiperactividad (TDAH)        en escolares de 6 a 11 años de la isla de Mallorca. Sujetos y métodos. Estudio poblacional en el que se aplicó diseño de la        muestra polietápico estratificado (por cursos), proporcional (para el tipo de centro y por zonas sociodemográficas) por conglomerados        (número de vías por curso en cada centro). A partir de una población diana de aproximadamente 30.000 sujetos        se obtuvo una muestra de 1.509 niños. Se utilizaron las Attention-Deficit/Hiperactivity Disorder Rating Scales IV (ADHD RS-IV)        para padres y maestros. Los casos se definieron a partir del percentil 90 en las escalas de inatención, hiperactividad/impulsividad        y total de maestros y padres. Resultados. Indican una tasa global de prevalencia en el nivel esperado el 4,6% (intervalo        de confianza al 99%: 3,0-5,8%), de los cuales el 1,26% fueron del subtipo hiperactivo, el 1,06% del subtipo inatento y el        2,25% del subtipo combinado. Contrariamente a lo esperado la incidencia fue ligeramente superior en niñas. No aparecen        diferencias significativas ni por sexo, ni por cursos, ni por tipo de centro, ni por zona. Conclusiones. Las ADHD RS-IV han        demostrado ser útiles en una población no anglosajona para estimar la prevalencia del TDAH en los valores esperados; sus        puntos de corte diferenciados inciden en que desaparezcan las diferencias por sexo. Se propone normalizar la escala con        muestras de nuestro entorno para poder confirmar los datos hallados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(1): 10-14, ene. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053077</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación de la prevalencia del trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad en población normal de la isla de Mallorca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
