<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99487</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results from the application of a quality management system in the community pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The quality management means the search of the continuous improvement in the activities and processes, with the aim of reaching the full satisfaction of the needs and requirements of our costumers. That is why we have to take management decisions that must be based in objective data and facts. We wanted to know if the application of a Quality Management System in the Community Pharmacy means a significant improvement in the processes related to the management of the pharmacies, the pharmaceutical care given to the costumers / patients, and their satisfaction level. The results of sixteen different processes indicators, obtained from several community pharmacies (1 to 7 depending on the indicator) that have established a Quality Management System according to the ISO 9001 Norm, were normalized. The time trend of every indicator was adjusted to a straight line, and we analysed, with the F test if the slope was different of 0, considering it significant if p &lt;0.05. The improvement percentages in ten of the sixteen indicators (low rotation articles stock, suppliers errors, percentage of valued pharmacy advices, symptoms improvement, patients who received health education, drug-related negative clinical outcomes detected, informed consent obtaining, cosmetics produced, points in the satisfaction questioner and points in the mystery shopping test), showed a positive trend that was statistically significant. All these results prove that the application of a Quality Management System makes it possible to control and measure the most important processes and activities of a community pharmacy, and the satisfaction of its patients/costumers(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arrebola Pascual, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martí, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cremades Alcaraz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La gestión de calidad supone la búsqueda de una mejora continua en las actividades y procesos, con el fin de alcanzar la plena satisfacción de las necesidades y expectativas del cliente. Para ello, se han de tomar las decisiones de gestión basándose en datos y hechos objetivos. Nuestro objetivo fue conocer si la implantación de un Sistema de Gestión de Calidad en la Farmacia Comunitaria supone una mejora significativa en procesos relacionados con la gestión y la atención farmacéutica, así como en la satisfacción de sus clientes/pacientes. Se normalizaron los resultados de dieciséis indicadores diferentes de procesos, obtenidos de distintas farmacias comunitarias (1-7 según indicador) que tienen implantado un Sistema de Gestión de Calidad según la Norma ISO 9001. La evolución temporal de cada indicador se ajustó a una línea recta, y se analizó con el test F si la pendiente era diferente a 0, considerándose significativa esta diferencia sip &lt;0.05. Los porcentajes de mejora de diez de los dieciséis indicadores (stock de artículos de baja rotación, incidencias de proveedores, porcentaje de indicaciones farmacéuticas evaluadas, mejora de los síntomas, pacientes que recibieron educación sanitaria, resultados negativos de la medicación detectados, consentimiento informado en pacientes en seguimiento farmacoterapéutico, cosméticos elaborados, encuesta de satisfacción y puntuación del comprador misterioso), mostraron una tendencia positiva y estadísticamente significativa. Estos resultados demuestran que la implantación de un sistema de gestión de calidad permite un control y una mejora mesurable de importantes procesos de la farmacia comunitaria, así como de la satisfacción de sus clientes/pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 277-283, jul. 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la implantación de un sistema de gestión de calidad en la farmacia comunitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
