<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045903</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognosis for cutaneous melanoma according to surgical department: comparative study at a tertiary care hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Surgical treatment of melanoma is performed by dermatologists and general or plastic surgeons. It is not known whether the type of specialist treating the melanoma results in a different prognosis for these patients.                 Material and methods. A retrospective study was carried out on the epidemiological, clinical/histological and evolutional characteristics of all patients diagnosed with melanoma at Hospital Gregorio Marañón over a 10-year period (1994--2003). The differences by hospital department where the patients were treated (dermatology, general surgery and plastic surgery) were noted.                 Results. Over 90 % of the patients with melanoma were treated by the Dermatology Department. The thickness of the tumors and the presence of histologic ulceration were significantly higher in the melanomas treated by general and plastic surgeons (p &lt; 0.05). The differences in overall average survival (105, 55 and 77 months) and disease-free time (88, 24 and 51.3 months) in the melanomas operated on by dermatologists, general surgeons and plastic surgeons, respectively, were significant (p &lt; 0.001).                 Conclusions. This study confirms that there are significant differences in the clinical and histological characteristics and the life prognosis of patients with cutaneous melanoma treated by different specialists. The melanomas treated by general or plastic surgeons have usually been developing for a longer time, and therefore are thicker and more often ulcerated than those treated by dermatologists, resulting in a lower survival period. With appropriate medical and surgical training, dermatologists are the most suitable specialists for early diagnosis and treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lázaro, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avilés, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El tratamiento quirúrgico del melanoma depende de dermatólogos y cirujanos generales o plásticos. Se desconoce si el tratamiento del melanoma por unos u otros especialistas determina un pronóstico distinto para estos pacientes.                 Material y métodos. Se analizaron de forma retrospectiva las características epidemiológicas, clínico-histológicas y evolutivas de todos los pacientes diagnosticados de melanoma en el Hospital Gregorio Marañón durante un periodo de 10 años (1994-2003). Se observaron las diferencias existentes en función del servicio hospitalario en el que fueron atendidos (dermatología, cirugía general y cirugía plástica).                 Resultados. Más del 90 % de los pacientes con melanoma fueron atendidos por el Servicio de Dermatología. El espesor tumoral y la presencia de ulceración histológica fueron significativamente superiores en los melanomas atendidos por cirujanos generales y plásticos (p &lt; 0,05). Las diferencias en la supervivencia global media (105, 55 y 77 meses) y el tiempo libre de enfermedad (88, 24 y 51,3 meses) en los melanomas operados por dermatólogos, cirujanos generales y plásticos, respectivamente, fueron significativas (p &lt; 0,001).                 Conclusiones. El presente estudio confirma las diferencias significativas en las características clínico-histológicas y el pronóstico vital de los pacientes con melanoma cutáneo atendidos por diferentes especialistas. Los atendidos por cirujanos generales o plásticos suelen ser melanomas de mayor tiempo de evolución y, por tanto, de mayor espesor y frecuencia de ulceración que los atendidos por dermatólogos, lo que determina una supervivencia inferior. Una formación médico-quirúrgica adecuada convierte al dermatólogo en el especialista más adecuado para su diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;97(4): 247-252, mayo 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045903</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pronóstico del melanoma cutáneo según el servicio quirúrgico: estudio comparativo en un hospital de tercer nivel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
