<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111968</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perceived stressors and anxiety of nursing students in their first clinical practice period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nursing students are subject to different situations that cause stress (academic, clinical and external situations). When nursing students perform clinical practices they are faced with multiple stressors (disease, pain...). The aim of this study was to assess perceived stress in nursing students before and after their clinical practice period (2009/2010). Of the 398 registered students, 264 of them answered, both at the beginning and at the end of the clinical placement, the STAI questionnaire (measures anxiety) and the KEZKAK test (identifies stress factors). Before the clinical training period, 28 of the 41 items of the KEZKAK test yielded an average score greater than 1.5 (stress generating situations). At the end of the clinical training, 17 items presented this score. Furthermore, the KEZKAK average score and the anxiety state score were both significantly reduced. The most stressful situations were: &#147;mistaking medication&#148;, &#147;doing my job badly, endangering the patient&#148;, &#147;making mistakes&#148; and &#147;pricking myself with an infected needle&#148;. It appears that the senior students, who have more knowledge and clinical skills, perceived the clinical practice as less stressful. It is advisable to follow the evolution of these students in the third and final year of the Diploma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cobo-Cuenca, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell Gómez de Zamora, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Aguilera, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellanos Rainero, Rosa Mª</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivo Ortega, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Donaire, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudiantes de enfermería están sometidos a distintas situaciones que les producen estrés (académicas, clínicas y externas). Cuando los alumnos de enfermería realizan prácticas clínicas deben hacer frente a múltiples estresores (enfermedad, sufrimiento, muerte...). El objetivo principal de este estudio es conocer los estresores percibidos por los estudiantes de Enfermería antes y después de las prácticas clínicas (2009/2010). De 398 estudiantes matriculados, 264 contestaron al inicio y final de las prácticas a los cuestionarios STAI para medir la ansiedad y KEZKAK para identificar los estresores.   Antes de las prácticas, 28 de 41 items del KEZKAK obtienen puntuación media mayor a 1.5 (situación generadora de estrés). Finalizadas las  prácticas,  17 ítems obtuvieron esta puntuación. La puntuación media del KEZKAK y de ansiedad estado disminuyeron significativamente. Generan más estrés &#147;confundirme de medicación&#148;, &#147;hacer mal mi trabajo y perjudicar al paciente&#148;, &#147;meter la pata&#148; y &#147;pincharme con una aguja infectada&#148;. Parece ser que los alumnos de cursos superiores, que cuentan con más conocimientos y habilidades, perciben las prácticas clínicas como menos estresantes. Se aconseja ver la evolución de estos alumnos en el tercer y último curso de la diplomatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;18(2/3): 91-101, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111968</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estresores y ansiedad de los estudiantes de enfermería en sus primeras prácticas clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
