<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043144</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors for pediatric malignant bone tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cancer is the result of the interaction of two kinds of determinants: genetic (endogenous) and environmental (exogenous). In the last few decades, pediatric oncology as a whole has progressed, including knowledge of malignant osseous tumors (MOT). Although advances have been made in diagnostic and therapeutic aspects, little progress has taken place in our knowledge of the risk factors involved in their etiopathogenesis.                 Objective: This review has three objectives: a) to provide an update on MOT-related risk factors in the child and adult population; b) to disseminate knowledge of the main MOT-related risk factors among our colleagues in order to promote research into these factors, diagnosis and future prevention, and c) to request help from our colleagues in the Environment and Pediatric Cancer research project.                 Material and methods: We performed a systematic review of the literature published in the last 30 years on risk factors implicated in the etiopathogenesis of MOT, using Medline, Cancerlit, Science Citation Index and Embase. The search profiles used were: pediatric/childhood malignant bone tumors, pediatric/ childhood bone cancer/neoplasm, osteosarcoma/bone sarcoma/Ewing's sarcoma and risk factors/etiology/epidemiology. The most interesting articles were selected and the most relevant references contained therein were retrieved.                 Results: MOT represent 6-7 % of all pediatric neoplasms. The most frequent types are osteosarcoma (OS) and Ewing's sarcoma (ES), representing 56 % and 34 % respectively. OS-related risk factors are the following: a) previous osseous disease (Paget's disease); b) familial-genetic factors (hereditary retinoblastoma, Li-Fraumeni syndrome, Rothmund-Thompson syndrome, Bloom syndrome, familial OS, Diamond-Blackfan anemia); c) chemical factors (antineoplastic drugs); d) physical factors (ionizing radiation); e) biologic factors; f) parental occupation, and g) other factors (artificial osseous implants and traumatisms). ES-related risk factors are the following: a) ethnic-cultural (Caucasian race); b) genetic factors; c) parental occupation (herbicide, pesticide and fertilizer exposure); d) maternal obstetric history, and e) other factors (parental smoking and inguinal hernia).                 Conclusions: Most causes of MOT are unknown. Based on different levels of scientific evidence, the main factors implicated in the etiopathogenesis of OS are: Paget's disease, hereditary retinoblastoma, Li-Fraumeni syndrome, antineoplastic drugs, and ionizing radiation. The main factors related to ES are: Caucasian race, parental occupation, parental smoking, and surgery for inguinal hernia. The main obstacles to greater knowledge of MOT-related factors are: a) their multiple origin; b) the low prevalence in the population; c) lack of environmental health training in pediatrics, and d) the low public and private investment in this research field</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martí Perales, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrís i Tortajada, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Casas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García i Castell, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Claudio-Morales, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega García, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berbel Tornero, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El cáncer es el resultado final de la interacción multifactorial de dos clases de determinantes, el genético (endógeno) y el ambiental (exógeno). El progreso evidenciado por la oncología pediátrica, durante las últimas décadas, también se ha reflejado en los tumores óseos malignos (TOM). Estos avances se centran en los aspectos diagnósticos y terapéuticos, pero no en los factores de riesgo (FR) implicados en su etiopatogenia.                 Objetivo: La presente revisión tiene tres objetivos: a) actualizar el conocimiento de los FR asociados con los TOM durante la época pediátrica y adulta; b) divulgar entre todos nuestros compañeros los principales FR relacionados a los TOM, para fomentar su investigación, diagnóstico y futura prevención, y c) solicitar la ayuda de nuestros colegas para el proyecto de investigación Medio ambiente y cáncer pediátrico.                 Material y métodos: Revisión bibliográfica sistemática, de los últimos 30 años, de los FR implicados en la etiopatogenia de los TOM, obtenida del Medline, Cancerlit, Index Citation Science y Embase. Los perfiles de búsqueda utilizados han sido: pediatric/ childhood malignant bone tumors, pediatric/childhood bone cancer/neoplasm, osteosarcoma/bone sarcoma/ Ewing's sarcoma and risk factors/etiology/epidemiology. Se han seleccionado los artículos más interesantes y de sus referencias, las más relevantes.                 Resultados: Los TOM constituyen el 6-7 % de los cánceres pediátricos. Las dos variedades más frecuentes son el osteosarcoma (OTS) y el sarcoma de Ewing (SE), con el 56 y el 34 % de los casos, respectivamente. Los FR asociados con el OTS son los siguientes: a) patologías óseas preexistentes (enfermedad de Paget); b) factores genético-familiares (retinoblastoma hereditario, síndrome de Li-Fraumeni, síndrome de Rothmund-Thompson, síndrome de Bloom, OTS familiar y anemia de Diamond-Blackfan); c) factores químicos (sustancias antineoplásicas); d) factores físicos (radiación ionizante); e) factores biológicos; f) ocupaciones parentales, y g) otros factores (implantes óseos artificiales y traumatismos). Los FR asociados con el SE son los siguientes: a) étnico-culturales (raza blanca); b) factores genéticos; c) ocupaciones parentales (exposiciones laborables a herbicidas, pesticidas y fertilizantes); d) antecedentes obstétricos maternos, y e) otros factores (tabaquismo parental y hernias inguinales).                 Conclusiones: La mayoría de las causas de los TOM son desconocidas. Los principales FR implicados, con mayor o menor evidencia científica, en la etiopatogenia del OTS son: enfermedad de Paget, retinoblastoma hereditario, síndrome de Li-Fraumeni, sustancias antineoplásicas y radiación ionizante. Los principales FR asociados al SE son: raza blanca, exposiciones ocupacionales parentales, tabaquismo parental y antecedente de hernia inguinal intervenida. Las principales dificultades para avanzar en el conocimiento de los FR relacionados con el desarrollo de los TOM son: a) su origen multifactorial; b) la baja prevalencia poblacional; c) la inexistente formación en salud medioambiental pediátrica, y d) los escasos presupuestos económicos públicos o privados destinados a tal finalidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(6): 537-547, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo para los tumores óseos malignos pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1884^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12891^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12891^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1884^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
