<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94170</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurologic deficit following histiocytosis X</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Histiocytoses form a group of rare diseases characterized by the reactive or neoplastic proliferation of histiocytes. Anabnormal immune response may cause these mononuclear phagocytes to proliferate generally or locally within an organ or tissue. These diseases are currently classified in 3 broad groups: Langerhans cell histiocytosis (histiocytosis X); non-Langerhans cell histiocytoses; and malignant histiocytic disorders (acute monocytic leukemia, malignant histiocytosis, and lymphohistiocytosis. When histiocytosis X affects vertebral bodies, usually following subacute lumbar or other backpain, acute neurologic deficits may lead the patient to seek emergency care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Utande Vázquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barra Quílez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente Mateo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se conoce como histiocitosis a un grupo de enfermedades poco frecuentes que se caracterizan por la proliferación, reactiva o neoplásica, de determinadas células del sistema mononuclear-fagocítico, los histiocitos, como una respuesta inmunitaria anómala de forma localizada en un órgano o tejido o de forma generalizada. Actualmente, se clasifican en 3 grandes grupos: la histiocitosis de células de Langerhans (histiocitosis X); las histiocitosis de célulasfagocito-mononucleares diferentes a las células de Langerhans; y los desórdenes histiocíticosmalignos (leucemia monocítica aguda, histiocitosis maligna y linfoma histiocítico). Cuando la histiocitosis X afecta a los cuerpos vertebrales, habitualmente tras una dorsalgia o lumbalgiasubaguda, pueden aparecer déficit neurológicos agudos que hagan consultar al paciente en el servicio de urgencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(2): 112-114, abr. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94170</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Déficit neurológico secundario a histiocitosis X</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28001^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
