<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055438</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-1641</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A management model of consultations in speciality center. Implication and communication of professionals as keys for the success</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of public health care is to provide the residents the best health care as efficiently as possible of those services that best preserve or restore his/her health condition. To do so, interaction between the clinicians and the managers is necessary and good understanding between them should be a fundamental starting point to develop an organization model of consultations that seeks quality health care.         Quality of public health care depends on several elements, standing out among them: a) health care continuity, b) participation of the professionals in the management of the consultations, and c) participation of the patients in the clinical decisions.         The most important element is probably understanding the public health care services as a responsibility of all, always considering the resident's satisfactions as the primary objective</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Nevado, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Cuadra, Amalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Maestre, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Cejudo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de la asistencia sanitaria pública es proveer al ciudadano, en el nivel asistencial más adecuado y de la forma más eficiente posible, de aquellos servicios que mejor preserven o restauren su estado de salud. Para ello, la interacción de clínicos y gestores se hace necesaria, y un buen entendimiento por ambas partes debe ser un punto de partida elemental para desarrollar un modelo de organización de consultas que busca una asistencia sanitaria de calidad.         Varios son los elementos de los que depende la calidad de la atención sanitaria, entre ellos destacamos: a) continuidad asistencial, b) participación de los profesionales en la gestión de las consultas y c) participación de los pacientes en las decisiones clínicas.         Probablemente, el elemento más importante es entender los servicios sanitarios como una responsabilidad de todos, considerando siempre, como principal objetivo la satisfacción del ciudadano</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. adm. sanit. siglo XXI;5(2): 293-309, abr. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un modelo de gestión de consultas en un centro de especialidades: implicación y comunicación de los profesionales como claves del éxito</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8678^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3424^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4725^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29345^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
