<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166982</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The protective effect of two commercial formats of Ginkgo biloba on motor alterations induced by cassava juice (Manihot esculenta Crantz) in Wistar rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: This study evaluated the protective effects of 2 commercial formats of Ginkgo biloba on motor alterations induced by cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz) juice consumption in male Wistar rats. Methods: The effects were evaluated with the open field and swim tests at 0, 7, 14, 21, and 28 days of treatment, one hour after administering the product. Results: Compared to controls, open field crossings increased after day 21 of cassava juice consumption, and lateral swimming in the swim test was reported after day 7. Conclusion: Ginkgo biloba extracts prevented motor alterations associated with cassava juice consumption, probably due to the flavonoid content in both formats of Ginkgo biloba (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mérida-Portilla, CV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivadeneyra-Domínguez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Sobac, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Luna, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Landa, JF</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se evaluó el efecto protector de 2 presentaciones comerciales de Ginkgo biloba sobre las alteraciones motoras inducidas por el consumo de jugo de yuca (Manihot esculenta Crantz) en ratas macho Wistar. Método: Los efectos se evaluaron en las pruebas de campo abierto y nado a los 0, 7, 14, 21 y 28 días de tratamiento, una hora después de la administración correspondiente. Resultados: A partir del día 21 del consumo de jugo de yuca incrementó el número de cuadros cruzados en campo abierto y, en la prueba de nado, produjo el nado lateral a partir del día 7, con respecto al grupo control. Conclusión: Los extractos de Ginkgo biloba previnieron las alteraciones motoras asociadas al consumo de jugo de yuca, probablemente por el contenido de flavonoides presentes en ambas presentaciones de Ginkgo biloba (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(8): 516-522, oct. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166982</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto protector de 2 presentaciones comerciales de Ginkgo biloba sobre las alteraciones motoras inducidas por el jugo de yuca (Manihot esculenta Crantz) en la rata Wistar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1701^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13436^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33519^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13931</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33751</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35652</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
