<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147044</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute pancreatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The concept of acute pancreatitis and its complications is currently changing, and the presence of persistent organ failure is essential to classify patients as severe. In addition, the incidence of acute pancreatitis is increasing throughout the Western world, both that of pancreatitis of any etiology as well as that of biliary origin. In patients with acute idiopathic pancreatitis, cancer of the pancreas is an important cause of the disease, and consequently appropriate etiological study is essential in these patients. In this sense, the role of endoscopic ultrasonography should be highlighted. From the therapeutic point of view, certain drugs that inhibit leukocyte and pancreatic elastase may play an important role in the future, as encouraging results have been found in experimental models. In the acute phase of the disease, oral feeding can be reintroduced with a solid low-fat diet; more gradual reintroduction is not required. Lastly, the present article discusses the latest data on the prevalence of acute pancreatitis following endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Muñoz, J Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El concepto de pancreatitis aguda y sus complicaciones está cambiando, y la presencia de fallo orgánico persistente es esencial para clasificar a un paciente como grave. Por otra parte, la incidencia de la pancreatitis aguda está en aumento en el mundo occidental, tanto global como de pancreatitis de origen biliar. En los pacientes con pancreatitis aguda idiopática, el cáncer de páncreas es una causa importante de enfermedad, por lo que es esencial un estudio etiológico adecuado en los casos de enfermedad idiopática. En este sentido, cabe destacar el relevante papel de la ecografía endoscópica. Desde el punto de vista terapéutico cabe destacar el papel que pueden desempeñar en un futuro determinados fármacos inhibidores de elastasa leucocitaria y pancreática, que han mostrado resultados alentadores en modelos experimentales. Una vez superada la fase aguda, la alimentación oral puede reintroducirse con una comida sólida pobre en grasas, y no es necesaria una reintroducción más paulatina. Por último, se discuten en este artículo las últimas evidencias en la prevención de pancreatitis aguda post-CPRE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;29(supl.3): 77-84, nov. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147044</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pancreatitis aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29357^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29357^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29357^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
