<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94189</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychoeducational approach to depression in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Depression is the most frequent and relevant mental disorder in Primary Care. However, there its management presents difficulties and the clinical outcomes obtained are often not satisfactory. Within the frame work of the development of a multifactor model to improve depression outcomes in Primary Care (INDI project) a psycho educational programme aimed at depressed patients, as well as their loved ones, has been designed. In the INDI model, the implementation of psycho educational activities is managed primarily by the Primary Care nurse. The programme&#146;s contents include educating on the disease itself with a special emphasis on fighting the stigma and prejudices attached to it and providing training on antidepressant treatment and the importance of treatment adherence, on the self-management of associated difficulties, as well as offering advice on the important role that the people close to the depressed patient can/should play (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aragonés Benaige, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Cortacans, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badia Rafecas, Walesca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñol Moreso, Josep LLuis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Alías, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Angueram, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La depresión es el trastorno mental más frecuente y relevante en Atención Primaria. Sin embargo, existen dificultades en su manejo y los resultados clínicos que se obtienen no son a menudo satisfactorios. En el marco del desarrollo de un modelo multifactorial para mejorar los resultados de la depresión en Atención Primaria (el proyecto INDI) se ha diseñado un programa psicoeducativo dirigido a los pacientes deprimidos, así como a sus allegados. En el modelo INDI, la implementación de las actividades psicoeducativas recae principalmente en la enfermera de Atención Primaria. Los contenidos del programa incluyen formación sobre la propia enfermedad, especialmente orientada a combatir el estigma y los prejuicios sobre la misma, sobre el tratamiento antidepresivo y la importancia de la adherencia al mismo, sobre el automanejo de las dificultades asociadas, así como orientaciones sobre el importante papel que pueden/deben desempeñar las personas próximas al paciente deprimido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(4): 62-67, mayo 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94189</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje psicoeducativo de la depresión en Atención Primaria. El modelo INDI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
