<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122292</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological Variables Associated with Suicidal Ideation in Students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Suicide being the second leading cause of death among college students, this article examined differences in psychological variables related to college students (21-34 years) in Psychology with teaching and with high suicidal ideation (BDI&gt; 10). We evaluated the presence of suicidal ideation in these students (n= 40, 70% female, mean age 23.9 years, SD= 3,003) regarding impulse control, depression and hopelessness. The results showed that students with high hopelessness are more likely to have suicidal ideation, and the level of impulse control that prevents the transition from ideation to other more serious stages of suicide. The identification of psychological factors associated with suicidal ideation in college, can help prevent the transition from suicidal ideation to first suicide attempt (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muela Martínez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Teruel, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García León, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Siendo el suicidio la segunda causa de muerte entre los estudiantes universitarios, este artículo examinó las diferencias en algunas variables psicológicas asociadas a estudiantes universitarios (21-34 años) de Psicopedagogía con magisterio y con alta ideación suicida (BDI &gt;10). Se valoró la existencia de ideación suicida en estos estudiantes (n= 40, 70% mujeres, edad media de 23,9 años y DT= 3,003) en relación con el control de impulsos, la depresión y la desesperanza. Los resultados mostraron que los estudiantes con alta desesperanza son más propensos a presentar ideación suicida, siendo el nivel de control de impulsos el que evita el tránsito de la ideación a otras fases más graves del suicidio. La identificación de los factores psicológicos asociados con la ideación suicida en universitarios, puede ayudar a evitar el tránsito de la idea de suicidio a la primera tentativa suicida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);14(2): 277-290, jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variables psicológicas asociadas a la ideación suicida en estudiantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7352^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
