<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83023</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Socio-demographic and health factors associated with the institutionalization of dependent people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The analysis of the effect that different variables have in the probability that dependent people are institutionalized is a topic scantily studied in Spain. The aim of the work is to analyze as certain socio-demographic and health factors can influence probability of dependent person living in a residence. Methods: A cross-section study has been conducted from a representative sample of the dependent population in Cuenca (Spain) in February, 2009. We have obtained information for people with level II and III of dependence. A binary logit regression model has been estimated to identify those factors related to the institutionalization of dependent people. Results: People with ages between 65-74 years old are six times more likely to be institutionalized than younger people (&lt;65 years old); this probability increases sixteen times for those individuals with ages equal or higher than 95 years. The probability of institutionalization of people who live in an urban area is three times the probability of people who live in a rural area. People who need pharmacological, psychotherapy or rehabilitation treatments have between two and four times more probability of being institutionalized that those who do not need those. Conclusions: Age, marital status, place of residence, cardiovascular and musculoskeletal diseases and four times of medical treatment are the principal variables associated with the institutionalization of dependent people(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escribano Sotos, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo Rubio, Raúl del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso Gutiérrez, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El análisis del efecto que diferentes variables tienen en la institucionalización de las personas dependientes es un tema escasamente estudiado en España. El objetivo del trabajo es analizar qué factores sociodemográficos y del estado de salud pueden influir en la probabilidad de que la persona dependiente viva en una residencia. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio transversal de la población dependiente de la provincia de Cuenca, a partir de una muestra representativa de la población baremada como dependiente en febrero de 2009, obteniéndose información de personas con grados II y III de dependencia. Se estimó un modelo de regresión logística binaria para identificar los factores asociados a la institucionalización de las personas dependientes. Resultados: Los individuos con edades comprendidas entre 65 y 74 años tienen prácticamente 6 veces más probabilidad de estar institucionalizados, frente a no estar institucionalizados, que los de edades inferiores a 65 años; probabilidad que aumenta hasta 16 veces para individuos de edad igual o superior a los 95 años. Vivir en zona urbana multiplica por 3 la probabilidad de institucionalización frente a residir en zona rural. Las personas que siguen tratamientos farmacológicos, tratamientos psicoterapéuticos, o tratamientos rehabilitadores, tienen entre 2 y 4 veces más probabilidad de estar institucionalizados que las que no los siguen. Conclusiones: La edad, el estado civil casado, el lugar de residencia, las variables de salud enfermedades del aparato circulatorio y musculoesqueléticas, y los cuatro tipos de tratamiento a seguir se convierten en las principales variables asociadas a la institucionalización de personas dependientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;84(6): 789-798, nov.-dic.2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83023</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores sociodemográficos y de salud asociados a la institucionalización de personas dependientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7499^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7499^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7499^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
