<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72439</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neonatal jaundi Clinical evaluation of a transcutaneous bilirubinometer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Transcutaneous bilirubinometers provide non-invasive data on newborn jaundice. The aim of this study is to evaluate whether the measurement of transcutaneous bilirubin can be correlated with serum bilirubin, and to find out whether gestational age, weight birth, race or hours of life affect those measurements .Method: Descriptive observational cross-sectional study on a sample of 65 simultaneous measurement of transcutaneous (TcB) and serum bilirubin (TSB). Results: The correlation coefficient between both methods was 0.923. Race, gestational age and birth weight tends to not have any effects on the levels of transcutaneous bilirubin. Conclusion: Although bilirubinometer measurements tend to underestimate serum bilirubin, especially in patients with high levels, it is a useful technique as a screening tool in the evaluation of hyperbilirubinaemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alós Muñoz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Torcal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco Lozano, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiles Durá, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vizcaíno Díaz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los bilirrubinómetros transcutáneos actuales han demostrado ser útiles como instrumentos de medida de la ictericia neonatal. En este estudio se evalúa si las medidas de la bilirrubina transcutánea (TCB) se correlacionan con las determinaciones de la bilirrubina sérica (TSB), y si la edad gestacional, peso al nacimiento, raza u horas de vida interfieren en esas medidas. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal, observacional y descriptivo sobre una muestra de 65 determinaciones simultáneas de TCB y de TSB. Resultados: Se obtiene un coeficiente de correlación de 0,923 entre ambos métodos. El análisis de covarianza muestra cómo la edad gestacional, raza y peso parecen no ser contribuidores significativos sobre los valores de la TCB. Conclusiones: Aunque el aparato transcutáneo tiende a infraestimar a la TSB, sobre todo con concentraciones elevadas, es una técnica útil para la medición orientativa de la concentración de la bilirrubina en recién nacidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(2): 157-160, ago. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72439</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ictericia neonatal: evaluación clínica de un bilirrubinómetro transcutáneo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7737^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7112^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13248^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1686^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
