<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041236</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antisense therapy in oncology: present situation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of antisense therapy is to control the regulation ofgenes contributing to cancer progression while sparing normalcell growth, which represents a novel alternative with fewer sideeffects when compared to conventional chemotherapy. Antisenseoligonucleotides control cell proliferation by specifically blockingthe expression of selected genes, and hence they are being developedas molecular drugs with potential activity for cancer treatment.Extensive clinical information and a number of clinical trialsshow encouraging results. This review discusses the most significantaspects of this new therapeutic alternative in oncology. Clinicaltrials performed thus far have demonstrated their short- tomid-term efficacy and safety; however, long-term studies areneeded to definitely define their clinical effectiveness and true toxicprofile</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Gil Hurlé, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morán González, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La finalidad de la terapia antisentido es controlar la regulaciónde los genes que contribuyen a la progresión del cáncer sin afectaral crecimiento de las células normales, por lo que representa unanueva alternativa con menos efectos secundarios que la quimioterapiaconvencional. Los oligonucleótidos antisentido controlan laproliferación celular al bloquear específicamente la expresión dedeterminados genes, por lo que se están desarrollando como fármacosmoleculares con potencial actividad en el tratamiento delcáncer. Se dispone de amplia información preclínica y de algunosensayos clínicos con resultados esperanzadores. En esta revisiónse recogen los aspectos más significativos de esta nueva alternativaterapéutica en oncología. Los ensayos clínicos realizados hastala fecha han puesto de manifiesto su eficacia y seguridad a corto ymedio plazo; sin embargo, son necesarios estudios a largo plazopara terminar de definir su efectividad clínica y su verdadero perfiltoxicológico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;29(4): 269-282, jul.-ago. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041236</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia antisentido en oncología: situación actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10027^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
