<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130924</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Executive functions involve a wide range of processes related to the regulation of thinking, behaviour and the emotional state. Given the variety of components that fall under the umbrella of this construct, it is not surprising that its evaluation often involves some difficulties. In this sense, although numerous studies have shown the relevance of these components as determining factors in the academic achievement and social adaptation of children and young people, as well as demonstrating their usefulness in the diagnosis and intervention of several clinical problems that are typical of these stages, aspects such as the criticized ecological validity of the traditionally used assessment measures impose certain limitations on the validity and generalizability of the information obtained by means of these tools. The present paper analyses the characteristics of the most widely used assessment measures of executive functions and their applicability in clinical and educational settings. A series of practical implications arises from this analysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, Trinidad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Areces, Debora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueli, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Castro, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, Celestino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las funciones ejecutivas implican un amplio rango de habilidades relacionadas con la regulación del pensamiento, el comportamiento y el propio estado emocional. Teniendo en cuenta la variedad de componentes que forman este constructo, no es sorprendente que su evaluación plantee ciertas dificultades. En este sentido, pese a que numerosos estudios han mostrado la importancia de dichos componentes como determinantes del desempeño académico y social, así como su utilidad en el diagnóstico y la intervención en diversas problemáticas durante la infancia y la adolescencia, aspectos como la validez ecológica de las medidas tradicionalmente empleadas para su evaluación, imponen hoy ciertas limitaciones a la validez y generalización de los resultados obtenidos en este ámbito. El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar las características de las medidas de evaluación más ampliamente empleadas y su grado de aplicabilidad en contextos clínicos y educativos, de lo cual se desprenden una serie de implicaciones prácticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;35(3): 215-223, sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130924</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Funciones ejecutivas en niños y adolescentes: implicaciones del tipo de medidas de evaluación empleadas para su validez en contextos clínicos y educativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
