<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163937</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prehospital management of acute childhood poisoning in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This objective was to analyze prehospital management of acute childhood poisonings. Poisonings treated in 59 pediatric emergency departments participating in the Toxicology Observation Project of the Spanish Society of Pediatric Emergency Medicine were registered prospectively between 2008 and 2014. We analyzed consultations made and treatments received before the patient arrived in the emergency department. A total of 902 poisonings were registered; in 870 cases (96.4%) cases whether or not a prehospital consultation had been made was on record. An emergency service of come type was contacted or visited in 312 cases (35.9%). Calls were most often made to the central emergency service (122 cases [14%]), primary care centers (100 cases [11.5%]), or the National Toxicology Institute (60 cases, [6.9%]). Choice of service to call or visit varied greatly according to type of poisoning. Prehospital treatment was more often received if a service had been contacted (26.3%) than if not (6.8%) (P&lt;.001). Treatment was also more specific to the type of poisoning (e.g., decontamination, oxygen therapy, antidotes) if a prehospital service had been contacted. About half the cases that consulted a poisoning service but did not receive treatment before coming to a hospital did receive treatment in the hospital emergency department. We conclude that a substantial percentage of patients who seek care for childhood poisoning from an emergency department have also consulted a prehospital service. Better prehospital management of such cases could facilitate earlier treatment when required and also preempt unnecessary trips to pediatric emergency departments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zubiaur, Oihane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mintegi, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar, June</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azkunaga, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo es analizar las actuaciones prehospitalarias en las intoxicaciones agudas pediátricas. Para ello, se utilizó el registro prospectivo de las intoxicaciones registradas en 59 servicios de urgencias pediátricos (SUP) incluidos en el Observatorio Toxicológico de la Sociedad Española de Urgencias de Pediatría entre 2008 y 2014. Se analizan las consultas prehospitalarias realizadas y los tratamientos recibidos. Se recogieron 902 intoxicaciones, de las que en 870 (96,4%) constaba la existencia o no de una consulta prehospitalaria. Globalmente, 312 pacientes (35,9%) contactaron con algún servicio prehospitalario, principalmente servicio de emergencias (122, 14%), centros de atención primaria (100, 11,5%) y el Instituto Nacional de Toxicología (60, 6,9%). El servicio consultado varió significativamente en relación con el mecanismo de la intoxicación. El grupo que consultó recibió tratamiento prehospitalario con más frecuencia (26,3% vs 6,8% del grupo que no contactó, p &lt; 0,001) y más específico para una intoxicación (descontaminación, oxigenoterapia, antídotos). Alrededor de la mitad de los pacientes que consultaron con un servicio prehospitalario y no recibieron tratamiento antes de llegar al hospital, lo recibieron al llegar a urgencias. Se concluye que un porcentaje alto de pacientes que consultan en los SUP españoles por una intoxicación han consultado previamente con un servicio prehospitalario. Un mejor tratamiento prehospitalario de estas consultas podría facilitar el inicio precoz del tratamiento cuando se requiere y también evitar consultas innecesarias en los SUP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);29(3): 178-181, jun. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163937</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención prehospitalaria en las intoxicaciones agudas pediátricas en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28835^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
