<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99791</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heavy episodic drinking among adolescents: the association with negative mood states and family factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Heavy episodic drinking is widespread among adolescents, with serious health risks, including abuse / dependence in adulthood. The aimof this paper is to analyze the influence of negativemood states and some family variables on this type of drinking behavior among Catalan adolescents. Methods: Cross sectional study of a representative sample of adolescents (age 14-18 years) fromCatalonia (SecondWave, Panel of Families and Children) (2006-2010). Separate logistic regression models are run for women (n = 1,459) and men (n = 1,105) to assess whether negative mood states (self-perceived) are associated with heavy episodic drinking measured as binge drinking at least twice a month or more in the last year. It is estimated to what extent these effects are attributable to familial factors. Results: Feelings of sadness are associated with binge drinking among male adolescents (OR 2.7). Feeling pressured by parents keeps also a positive association with binge drinking among both sexes (OR 1.8 for males and OR 2.1 for women). Women from low-middle and high income groups are more likely to engage in binge drinking (OR 1.6 and OR, 1.7 respectively). Migrant family background (OR 0.4) and parental control of arrival home on weekend (OR 0.6) are negatively related to binge drinking among female adolescents. Conclusions: Negative mood states are associated with heavy episodic drinking. Socio-economic and family factors have stronger effect on women than on men(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escapa, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Hernáez, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Julià, ALbert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marí-Klose, Marga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marí-Klose, Pau</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El consumo episódico excesivo de alcohol (CEEA) es una práctica extendida en la población adolescente con graves riesgos para la salud, incluyendo el abuso/dependencia en la edad adulta. El objetivo de este artículo es analizar su asociación con los estados de ánimo negativos y algunas variables familiares entre los adolescentes catalanes. Métodos: Estudio transversal de una muestra representativa de adolescentes (edad 14-18 años) de Cataluña (Segunda oleada del Panel de Familias e Infancia) (2006-2010). Se realizan modelos de regresión logística para mujeres (n = 1.459) y hombres (n= 1.105) para estimar si los estados de ánimo negativos auto-percibidos (tristeza, presión parental, etc.) están asociados con el CEEA, capturado como haberse emborrachado por lo menos dos veces al mes durante el último año. Se estima en qué medida esos efectos son atribuibles a algunos factores familiares. Resultados: El sentimiento crónico de tristeza está asociado con el CEEAentre los varones (OR 2,7), al igual que sentirse presionado/a por los progenitores en ambos sexos (OR 1,8 hombres y OR 2,1 mujeres). Las mujeres de rentas medio-bajas y altas son más proclives al CEEA (OR 1,6 y OR 1,7 respectivamente). La existencia de progenitores de origen inmigrante (OR 0,4) y la fijación parental de un horario de retorno a casa los fines de semana (OR 0,6) presentan una asociación negativa con el CEEA entre las mujeres. Conclusiones: Los estados de ánimo negativos (EAN) están asociados al CEEA. Los efectos de los factores socio-económicos y familiares sobre el CEEA son más relevantes en mujeres que en varones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;86(1): 101-114, ene.-mar.2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99791</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo episódico excesivo de alcohol en adolescentes: su asociación con los estados de ánimo negativos y los factores familiares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29823^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34350^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
