<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135015</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fecal microbiota transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bacteria can no longer be seen as an enemy. Nowadays, there is enough evidence to place the microbiota as a key element in human homeostasis. Despite initial skepticism, fecal microbiota transplantation (FMT) is a real therapeutic alternative for patients with recurrent Clostridium difficile infection. Moreover, this procedure has shown promising results in ulcerative colitis and other non-gastrointestinal disorders. There is still a lack of knowledge and clinical trials with long- term follow-up. Therefore, the available data should be interpreted with caution. In this document we provide a detailed review of the literature on the intestinal microbiota and FMT (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-García-de-Paredes, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Sanromán, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferre-Aracil, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-de-Santiago, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera-Castro, Lara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No podemos seguir viendo a las bacterias como un simple enemigo. Hoy en día disponemos de suficiente evidencia como para comprender que la microbiota es un elemento clave en la homeostasis humana. A pesar del escepticismo inicial, el trasplante de microbiota fecal (TMF) es hoy una alternativa terapéutica real para pacientes con enfermedad recurrente por Clostridium difficile. Además, se han obtenido resultados prometedores en la colitis ulcerosa y en otros trastornos. Aún son incompletos nuestros conocimientos, y no hay un seguimiento adecuado a largo plazo. Por lo tanto, los datos disponibles deben ser interpretados con cautela. En este documento aportamos una revisión detallada de la literatura sobre la microbiota intestinal y el TMF (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;38(3): 123-134, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135015</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante de microbiota fecal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55394^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7292</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28890^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3041^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
