<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149199</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health care based on cooperation between professionals and affected people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this article is to support the need for a change of care, based on cooperation between those who provide care and those who receive it. This article develops the decisive factors for change: the investee cooperation, the reference in case management, the concept of recovery and terminal care, the reduction of suffering and the value of change reflected in the &#145;win-win&#146;. In each of them a questioning of the current situation, a methodological analysis and an input of tools and consequences of the change is made. To conclude, the article incorporates the &#145;itinerary of shared care&#146; as a resource and one of the ways to bring these changes to the reality of day-to-day care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muriel-Fernández, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Gómez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Domínguez, José-Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagués-Amadó, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objeto del artículo es fundamentar la necesidad de un cambio de la atención, basado en la cooperación entre los que prestan la atención y los que la reciben. Este artículo desarrolla los factores decisivos para el cambio: la cooperación participada, la referencia en la gestión de casos, el concepto de recuperación y la atención terminal, la reducción del sufrimiento y el valor del cambio reflejado en el «todos ganan». En cada uno de ellos se realiza un cuestionamiento de la situación actual, un análisis metodológico y la aportación de instrumentos y consecuencias del cambio. Finalmente, se incorpora el recurso del «itinerario de atención compartida» como una de las formas de llevar estos cambios a la realidad de la atención en el día a día (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);26(1): 85-90, ene.-feb. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149199</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La atención sanitaria basada en la cooperación entre profesionales y personas afectadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
