<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116793</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spinal fractures after hormone therapy during menopause: a 20-year follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The role of hormone replacement therapy in preventing spinal fracture after treatment cessation is controversial. The aim of this study was to assess the incidence of spinal fractures after 20 years of follow-up in patients treated between 1990 and 1995. Subjects and methods: A total of 177 patients were included in a prospective study to evaluate the effect of hormone replacement therapy on bone metabolism and bone mineral density. After 20 years, 49 patients were successfully contacted: 32 were treated for a mean of 5 years and 17 belonged to the control group. We analyzed clinical and demographic data and performed a radiological evaluation to observe the incidence of fractures by Genant&#146;s semiquantitative method. Results: The fracture rate was significantly higher in the group receiving hormone replacement therapy (P&lt;.05). Conclusion: Hormone replacement therapy administered at the beginning of menopause does not appear to have a protective effect against spinal fractures in the long term (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Serrano, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perelló, María F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castelo-Branco, Camil</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peguero, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La persistencia del efecto protector sobre fracturas vertebrales (FV) de la terapia hormonal (TH) tras dejar el tratamiento es tema de debate. El objetivo del estudio es evaluar la incidencia de FV en un grupo de pacientes tratadas durante el período 1990-1995, comparado con otro que durante ese mismo periodo no recibió TH, tras 20 años de seguimiento. Sujetos y métodos. Un total de 177 pacientes fueron incluidas en un estudio prospectivo para evaluar el efecto de la TH en el metabolismo y densidad mineral ósea. Del total, transcurridos 20 años, se recupera a 49 pacientes: 32 tratadas durante una media de 5 años y 17 pertenecientes al grupo control. Se analizan datos clínicos, demográficos y radiológicos, evaluando incidencia de FV mediante el método semicuantitativo de Genant. Resultados. Se observa un mayor índice de fracturas en el grupo que recibió TH, siendo estas diferencias estadísticamente significativas (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusión. La TH utilizada en los primeros años de la menopausia no presenta efecto protector ante FV a largo plazo tras abandonar el tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(9): 462-466, nov. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116793</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas vertebrales tras tratamiento hormonal en la menopausia: 20 años de seguimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24823^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6885^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13507^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
