<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123236</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents a new tool for three-dimensional measurement of mood: the POMS -VIC . It´s a psychological measurement resource formed from three scales: intensity, valence or pleasure, and control. The instrument was administered to a sample of 87 water polo players (67% men). Reliability of the scales and the normality of the variables was analyzed. The correlation coefficient was performed by Spearman rank nonparametric and groups . The three scales showed high internal consistency and high reliability alpha coefficients . The values and direction of the correlations to identify emotional states two groups : one consisting of tension, depression , anger , fatigue and confusion , and another consisting of force and  friendship. Women had higher scores on all three scales force . The level of competition in which athletes participate was not associated with mood thereof. We conclude that the POMS -VIC allows to know in addition to  the intensity of the different moods , the level of satisfaction that motivate the athlete and their perception of control over them. It therefore considers that the instrument has an important new practical implications for sport  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>De la Vega Marcos, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Tabanera, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Barquín, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández López, Jose Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Pese al reconocimiento público y científico del papel que desempeñan las diferentes variables psicológicas en el rendimiento deportivo, existen pocos datos que permitan evidenciar cuál es la percepción que tienen los máximos responsables de la coordinación del trabajo y del entrenamiento deportivo, es decir, los entrenadores, sobre el rol que desempeña el psicólogo del deporte en un deporte tan extendido como es el fútbol. En el presente trabajo, se ha diseñado el Cuestionario de Evaluación de las Ideas Previas de los Entrenadores de Fútbol, aplicándolo a dos muestras de un total de 198entrenadores de fútbol, durante las temporadas 2003 y 2011. La comparación de los resultados, permite evidenciar cierto patrón de estabilidad en los resultados, si bien se profundiza en las diferencias encontradas, así como en la importancia de superar las barreras manifestadas por los técnicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;14(2): 37-46, jul.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123236</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo perciben los entrenadores de fútbol el rol del psicólogo del deporte?: un estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
