<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63197</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The endoscopic treatment (ET) of vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) is considered by many urologic and pediatric surgeons as the first treatment option in the event of being required, because it is a minimally invasive procedure, of short duration, ambulatory in many cases, with good results and few complications. Ureteral obstruction is the most serious but less frequent complication. The objective is know the incidence, treatment and evolution of patients with ureteral obstruction as complication of the ET of VUR. Methods: Evaluation of the medical literature using Pubmed and Ovid. Revision of the clinical report of children (CH) under ET of VUR between March of 1998 and July of 2007, to find those cases that presented ureteral obstruction after ET. Results: A total of 377 children (CH) with VUR in 598 ureters (U), were treated with TE, during the mentioned period of 9 years, between March 1998 and July 2007. Only 2 U (0.33%), in 2 CH (0.5%) presented Ureteral Obstruction with dilatation of the upper urinary tract that need open surgical ureteral reimplantation, with good results in both patients. Conclusion: The risk of ureteral obstruction after ET of VUR is low, less than 0.5% of U. The treatment of this complication can be endoscópic or by open surgery both of them with good results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Mérida, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Román, Jairo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mieles Cerchar, Moisés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Míguelez Lago, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galiano Duro, Eulogio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El tratamiento endoscópico (TE) del reflujo vesicoureteral (RVU), está considerado por muchos urólogos y cirujanos pediátricos como la primera opción de tratamiento en caso de requerirse, debido a ser un procedimiento mínimamente invasivo, de corta duración, ambulatorio en muchos casos, con buenos resultados y escasas complicaciones; entre ellas la obstrucción ureteral es la mas grave pero la menos frecuente. Conocer la incidencia, manejo y evolución de los pacientes que presentaron obstrucción ureteral como complicación del TE del RVU. Método: Revisión de la literatura médica utilizando como buscadores Pubmed y Ovid. Revisión de los casos tratados con TE en el período comprendido entre Marzo de 1998 y Julio de 2007, un total de 377 niños (N) y 598 uréteres (U), para identificar los casos que presentaron obstrucción ureteral como complicación del TE. Resultados: Sólo 2 uréteres (0.33%), en dos niños (0.5%), presentaron Obstrucción Ureteral con repercusión en el TUS que precisó tratamiento. Conclusión: El riesgo de obstrucción ureteral en el postoperatorio del tratamiento endoscópico antirreflujo es muy bajo y en caso de presentarse existen varias alternativas para su manejo todas ellas con resultados satisfactorios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;61(2): 323-327, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63197</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12140^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14916^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3576^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14916^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2547^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14916^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1007^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7022^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
