<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82117</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prion diseases: prion encephalopathies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Prion diseases or prion encephalopathies are a group of rare disorders that share a similar pathophysiology with different clinical characteristics. Sporadic Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) is best known. It presents as a rapidly progressive dementia, ataxia and extrapyramidal symptoms. Although accurate diagnosis is by histopathological examination, a diagnosis can be probably achieved using the criteria established by the World Health Organization. We are currently discussing the possibility of integrating the nuclear magnetic resonance into this criteria for increasing the sensitivity of diagnosis. Molecular techniques for studying proteins in cerebrospinal fluid have an increasingly significant role in aiding diagnosis. The diagnosis of other prion encephalopathies is not as advanced as that of CJD. The treatment of these diseases remains palliative (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trillo-Sánchez-Redondo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ares-Blanco, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arranz-Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las prionpatías o encefalopatías por priones son un grupo de enfermedades poco frecuentes que comparten una fisiopatología similar con distintas características clínicas. La enfermedad de Creutzfeldt-Jakob (ECJ) esporádica es la más conocida. Se manifiesta con una demencia rápidamente progresiva, ataxia y sintomatología extrapiramidal. Aunque el diagnóstico de certeza es anatomopatológico se puede llegar al diagnóstico probable empleando los criterios establecidos por la Organización Mundial de la Salud. Se está discutiendo en la actualidad la posibilidad de integrar la resonancia magnética nuclear en dichos criterios para aumentar la sensibilidad del diagnóstico. Las técnicas moleculares de estudio de proteínas en el líquido cefalorraquídeo tienen un peso creciente y colaboran en el diagnóstico. El diagnóstico de las otras encefalopatías por priones no es tan avanzado como el de la ECJ. El tratamiento de todas estas enfermedades continúa siendo paliativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(8): 443-448, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prionpatías: las encefalopatías por priones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37279^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7905^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29254^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29254^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19524^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19524^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29254^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19524^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7905^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
