<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038237</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assistential variability in attending traffic accident polytraumatised patients. A multicentre study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: Cross-sectional multicentre study assessing the existence of assistential variability in some aspects of basic pre-hospitalary care to traffic accident polytramatised patients according to the information recorded a trauma patient registry. Method: Five hundred and eight patients fulfilled the following inclusion criteria: traffic accident victim, of full age, injury severity score (ISS)&gt;10 and either ICU admission or death in hospital, at five Catalonian hospitals in the 1999-2000 period. Results: (1) Statistically significant differences have been observed in the duration of pre-hospitalary care considering both the pre-hospital care entily involved and the receiving hospital. (2) The acting medical team varies among the various hospitals and patients and is usually composed of two to four specialists. Anaesthesia, Intensive Care or Emergency Care may direct the reanimation/resuscitation team, the orther components of the team being usually General Surgery, Orthopaedic Surgery and Neurosurgery. (3) No statiscally significant differences were observed among the various hospitals in preforming a cranial CT scan in patients with Glasgow Coma Score (GCS) &lt;12, althought a greater delay and scatter was seen when considering the time elapsed since the place of the accident. (4) Forty-five percent of the patients with lesions in the AIS 1 and 2 zones (cranium, face, neck) on hospital discharge carried a neck collar on arrival at the hospital. (5) No statiscally significant differences were observed among the various hospitals in the assessment of the time elapsed until management of visceral lesions or open fractures. Conclusions: Assistential variability exists in the care of traffic accident polytraumatised patients attended in the participating hospitals. It is convenient to establish clinical guidelines for treatment, as well as to develop a polytraumatism registry system and to homogenise the assistential systems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prat-Fabregat, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marti Valls, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echeverria, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plasencia Taradach, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gahete, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garreta Anglada, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Rubi, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuan Castillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudio multicéntrico transversal que evalúa la existencia de variabilidad asistencial en algunos aspectos de la asistencia básica prehospitalaria y hospitalaria a pacientes politraumatizados, por accidente de tráfico, en base a información recogida en un registro de pacientes traumáticos. Métodos: 508 pacientes han cumplido los siguientes criterios de inclusión: lesionado en accidente de tráfico, mayor de 18 años, Injury severity score (ISS) &gt; 10, así como ingreso en UCI o fallecido en el hospital, en cinco centros sanitarios de Catalunya durante los años 1999-2000. Resultados: 1. Se han apreciado diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el tiempo de asistencia prehospitalaria tanto si se toma en cuenta la entidad prehospitalaria actuante como el centro hospitalario receptor. 2. El equipo médico actuante varía según centros y pacientes, estando compuesto habitualmente por dos a cuatro especialistas. Anestesiología, Intensivos o Emergencias pueden dirigir la renimación, mientras que Cirugía general, Cirugía ortopédica y Neurocirugía suelen ser el resto de componentes del equipo. 3. No se han observado diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre centros en el tiempo de práctica de la TAC craneal a pacientes con Glasgow Coma Score (GCS) &lt;12, aunque se aprecia mayor retardo y dispersión cuando se toma en cuenta el tiempo desde el lugar del accidente. 4. El 45% de pacientes con diagnósticos de lesión en zona AIS 1 y 2 (cráneo, cara, cuello) al alta hospitalaria llevaban collarín cervical a la llegada al hospital. 5. No se aprecian diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre centros al evaluar el tiempo hasta el tratamiento de lesiones viscerales o fracturas abiertas. Conclusiones: Existe variabilidad asistencial en los pacientes politraumáticos por accidente de tráfico atendidos en los hospitales participantes. Es conveniente la implantación de guías clínicas de tratamiento, así como el desarrollo de un sistema de registro de politraumatizados y la homogeneización de los sistemas asistenciales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);17(1): 17-23, feb. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038237</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad asistencial en la atención a politraumatizados por accidente de tráfico. Un estudio multicéntrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29040^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
