<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058164</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical audit of skull radiography in pediatric head injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Implementation of a diagnostic protocol, developed after consensus and adapted to the local setting, could reduce the frequency of radiography in the management of pediatric head injury and could improve healthcare quality and resource utilization. Patients and method: A clinical audit, with two 12-month phases, before and after the implementation of a diagnostic protocol, was performed. The audit was based on a literature review and was adapted to local conditions. Results: After the implementation of the protocol, the use of skull radiography decreased from 45.8% to 38.9% and inappropriate use fell from 25.1% to 14.7%. No statistically significant differences were found in the use of computerized tomography, but hospital admissions were reduced. Conclusions: Implementation of the protocol reduced the number of radiographies and increased appropriate use of this resource. Clinical audits of pediatric emergency units should be carried out systematically to produce changes that improve the appropriateness of healthcare</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcalá Minagorre, Pedro Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores Serrano, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranaz Andrés, Jesús María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La aplicación de un protocolo diagnóstico, consensuado de manera interdisciplinaria y adaptado localmente, puede disminuir la frecuencia de uso de la radiografía en el manejo del traumatismo craneal infantil y mejorar la calidad asistencial y el consumo de recursos. Pacientes y método: Auditoría clínica con dos fases, de 12 meses cada una, antes y después de la aplicación de un protocolo diagnóstico basado en las recomendaciones disponibles en la bibliografía y adaptado al medio asistencial. Resultados: Tras la aplicación del protocolo, la frecuencia de uso de la radiografía pasó del 45,8 al 38,9% y la proporción de inadecuación de la prueba se redujo del 25,1 al 14,7%. No hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la utilización de la tomografía computarizada y se observó una reducción del número de ingresos. Conclusiones: La aplicación del protocolo no sólo redujo el número total de radiografías solicitadas, sino que su utilización se adecuó mejor a la situación clínica del paciente. Se deben realizar de forma sistemática auditorías clínicas de la actividad desarrollada en las unidades de urgencias y favorecer la puesta en marcha de cambios que permitan una mejora continua de la calidad asistencial</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;22(5): 249-255, sep.2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058164</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Auditoría clínica sobre la utilización de la radiografía en el abordaje del traumatismo craneal pediátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8655</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
