<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79233</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Born to read: review of the first three years of this initiative in 30 municipalities in Catalonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Born to Read (Nascuts per Llegir) initiative was started in 2005in 20 municipalities of Catalonia. It is based on the transversalwork between pediatricians, pediatric nurses, midwives, librarians,and other individuals involved in child education and children'sliterature. In this article, we review the results of the evaluationperformed on the 20 pilot municipalities and we discuss the futurechallenges. Pediatric primary care centers, public libraries, andfamilies completed the questionnaires that formed the basis forthe evaluation. Based on the results of this analysis, we havedefined a new set of objectives that should help consolidate theBorn to Read initiative and present it as a network program thatpromotes reading, strengthens the relationship between parentsand children, and facilitates the development of young childrenbetween 0 and 3 years of age. We have made significant progress;however, major challenges are still ahead, particularly thoserelated to health care administration. A stronger institutional andadministrative support is needed, and the professionals devotedto this program require recognition(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trias Folch, Elisenda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig Pagès, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nascuts per llegir (NPL) comienza el 2005 en 20 municipios deCataluña y se basa en el trabajo transversal entre pediatras, enfermeraspediátricas, comadronas, bibliotecarios y otros agentes delmundo de la educación y la literatura infantil. El objetivo delartículo es presentar los resultados de la evaluación de los 20 municipiospiloto y los retos de futuro. Para ello se han valorado losNascuts per llegir: balanç dels tres primers anys.Experiència en funcionament a 30 municipis de CatalunyaElisenda Trias Folch 1, Marta Roig Pagès 21 Pediatra. CAP Sant Andreu. 2 Coordinadora del Nascuts per llegirresultados de las encuestas pasadas a los equipos de los CAPS y delas bibliotecas, y a las familias. A partir del análisis de estos datosse definen los nuevos objetivos que deben permitir consolidar elNPL y proyectarlo como un programa en red, de promoción delgusto por la lectura, y que se constituye como una herramientapara fortalecer los vínculos emocionales entre padres e hijos y favorecerel desarrollo integral del niño, en la franja de los 0 a los 3años. Y es que, pese al largo camino ya recorrido, se plantean retosimportantes vinculados sobre todo al sector sanitario, que necesitade un contacto más directo y constante con la coordinación,y de un respaldo institucional que facilite su implicación y reconozcala tarea de los profesionales que participan(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;69(6): 272-280, nov.-dic. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79233</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nascuts per llegir: balance de los tres primeros años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8175^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10564^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10564^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10564^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33983</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8175^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
