<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-37911</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urban use of yajé (ayahuasca) in Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Yajé, a hallucinogenic substance, has been employed for centuries by the indigenous populations of South America, within a mystic and religious context. Recently, the use of yajé has spread from indigenous communities and permeated urban areas, acquiring a different meaning and special characteristics. The motivations for using yajé within an urban context are explored in this study. To this end, a scale was created to measure these motivations, which was validated by experts, and applied to 40 people in Bogotá (Colombia) who had taken yajé on two or more occasions. In addition, there were semistructured interviews of four of the individuals taking part, with the objective of complementing and broadening the information obtained from the scale It was found that the primary motivations in this group for the repeated use of yajé were those of a therapeutic kind at an emotional level, where the subject hopes by taking yajé to reach psychic well-being, characterised by feelings of tranquillity, inner peace and mental clarity, in addition to the ability to resolve personal problems and find alternatives to dealing with personal situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Socidrogalcohol</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El yajé es una sustancia alucinógena, que ha sido usada desde tiempos inmemoriales en las comunidades indígenas de Sur América con fines místicos, adivinatorios y religiosos. En la actualidad, esta sustancia empieza a salir de los contextos indígenas y se filtra en el contexto urbano, en donde su consumo se reviste de un significado y características propias. En el presente estudio se analizan las motivaciones asociadas al consumo de yajé en el contexto urbano. Para tal fin se diseñó una escala de evaluación de motivaciones, la cual fue validada por jueces y aplicada a 40 personas de la ciudad de Bogotá (Colombia) que han consumido el yajé en dos o más ocasiones. También se realizaron entrevistas semiestructuradas a cuatro de los sujetos participantes, con el fin de complementar y enriquecer la información obtenida por la escala.Se encontró que en este grupo de personas las principales motivaciones que impulsan a que el consumo de yajé se repita son las de tipo terapéutico a nivel emocional, en donde el sujeto espera obtener tras el consumo bienestar psíquico, caracterizado por sentimientos de tranquilidad, paz interior, y claridad mental, así como resolver el estancamiento y encontrar soluciones y alternativas de manejo a situaciones personales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);16(4): 323-332, dic. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo urbano de yajé (ayahuasca) en Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Vélez Cárdenas, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Gómez, Augusto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-37911</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6366^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36945</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33100</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
