<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99436</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orbital and nasal complications secondary to inhaled cocaine abuse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The abuse of inhaled cocaine causes chemical sinus pathology by secondary midfacial destruction and necrosis. When midfacial necrosis is already established, other complications may occur related to the proximity of structures such as the orbit or optic nerve. We present the evolution of a young cocaine addict with midfacial destruction, who has had a subperiosteal abscess and optic neuritis over the course of the years. Differential diagnosis and management of these complications are also discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Contreras Molina, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Palza, Carlos Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tenor Serrano, Rafael Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores Carmona, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El abuso de cocaína por vía intranasal provoca una sinusopatía química por destrucción y necrosis mediofacial secundaria. Cuando esta necrosis mediofacial ya está establecida, pueden aparecer otras complicaciones relacionadas con la proximidad de estructuras como la órbita o el nervio óptico. Presentamos la evolución de un joven cocainómano con destrucción mediofacial, que en el trascurso de los años ha padecido un absceso subperióstico y una neuritis óptica. Planteamos el diagnóstico diferencial y el manejo de estas complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;63(3): 233-236, mayo-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones nasales y orbitarias secundarias al abuso de cocaína inhalada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28199^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27729^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10095^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d41^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10711^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
