<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056797</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommended diagnostic imaging tests in urinary tract infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article reviews the scientific evidence available on diagnostic imaging tests in urinary tract infections in childhood. There is sufficient information on the technical validity of the various imaging tests. Through calculating probabilities, this information can be used in the process of diagnostic decision making. Nevertheless, the diagnostic yield offered by these tests is unclear; some of the estimations of costs, efficacy and risks suggest that certain diagnoses have little clinical importance. The current strategy of routine use of imaging tests should probably be replaced by an individually-tailored approach, in which tests are indicated by taking into account the information available at each stage of the process, patients' and relatives' opinions, and clinicians' judgment on the probability of the diagnoses and the risks and benefits of each test</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Sangrador, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Formigo Rodríguez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta una revisión de la evidencia científica disponible sobre las pruebas diagnósticas de imagen en la infección urinaria en la infancia. Contamos con suficiente información sobre la validez técnica de las distintas pruebas de imagen disponibles, que puede ser utilizada, mediante cálculo de probabilidades, en el proceso de toma de decisiones diagnósticas. Con todo, el rendimiento de los diagnósticos que estas pruebas nos ofrecen no está claro; algunas de las estimaciones de costes, eficacia y riesgos nos permiten asumir que ciertos diagnósticos tienen escasa trascendencia clínica. Es probable que la estrategia actual de uso habitual de pruebas de imagen deba ser sustituida por otra personalizada, en la que las pruebas sean indicadas tras considerar la información disponible en cada momento, la opinión de pacientes o familiares y nuestro juicio sobre la verosimilitud de los diagnósticos y los riesgos y beneficios de cada prueba</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(5): 498-516, nov. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056797</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pruebas diagnósticas de imagen recomendadas en la infección urinaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
