<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59986</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Spanish parent satisfaction questionnaire with neonatal hearing screening programs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Although measuring parent satisfaction has been recommended as one of the important outcome measures in assessing the effectiveness of neonatal hearing screening programs, there are few published studies investigating this issue. Objectives: To validate the Spanish version of the Parent Satisfaction Questionnaire with Neonatal Hearing Screening Program (PSQ-NHSP). Methods: 112 parents whose children had received hearing screening participated in this study. Results: High levels of satisfaction were reported with more than 90 % of parents satisfied with all aspects of the program. The psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the PSQ-NHSP were analyzed and demonstrated good internal consistency (&amp;#945; = 0.75). Construct validity was indicated by a significant positive relationship between overall satisfaction and the three specific dimensions in the questionnaire. Discussion: The development of a valid and reliable parent satisfaction questionnaire is important for improving hearing screening programs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carro-Fernández, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antuña-León, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez-Batalla, Faustino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Trelles, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Aunque se recomienda tener en cuenta la satisfacción de los padres como una de las valoraciones importantes para la evaluación de la efectividad de los programas de cribado auditivo neonatal, hay pocos estudios publicados que investiguen este tema. Objetivos: Validación de la versión en español del Cuestionario de Satisfacción de los Padres con el Programa de Cribado Neonatal de la Hipoacusia (PSQ-HNSP). Métodos: Participaron 112 padres de niños cribados para la hipoacusia. Resultados: Se encontraron unos grados de satisfacción importantes, más del 90 % de los padres mostraron su satisfacción con todos los aspectos del programa. Se analizaron las propiedades psicométricas de la versión en español del PSQ-HNSP, que demostraron una buena consistencia interna (&amp;#945; = 0,75). La validez de su construcción queda demostrada por la correlación significativa hallada entre la satisfacción general y las tres dimensiones específicas del cuestionario. Discusión: Es importante el desarrollo de un cuestionario válido y fiable que valore la satisfacción de los padres con el fin de usar este dato para mejorar los programas de cribado de la hipoacusia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;60(2): 109-114, mar.-abr. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59986</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación del cuestionario de satisfacción de los padres con los programas de cribado auditivo neonatal en español</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6472^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
