<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154179</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of detraining on body composition, vertical jumping ability and sprint performance in young elite soccer players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyze the effects of detraining on body composition, vertical jumping and speed abilities. Methods. Twenty two under&amp;#8208;17 soccer players (16.4±0.4 years; 70.0±7.1kg; 175.9±6.9cm) were evaluated before and after two weeks of detraining. Anthropometric measurements, countermovement (CMJ) and squat jumps (SJ) and sprint speed tests were performed. Results. There was a significant increase in body fat (p&lt;0.001) and despite the fact that the decrease in the speed was no significant (p&gt;0.05), an increase of 2.24% in the 0&amp;#8208;5m time (ES=0.78) and 0.97% in the 0&amp;#8208;20m time (ES=0.41) were observed. In addition, there was an upward trend in the SJ (p=0.056). Conclusion. Two weeks of detraining resulted in significant alterations of the body composition and in speed performance (from 0 to 5m) in young elite soccer players (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuniyochi, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nakamura, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loturco, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kobal, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascoto, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar los efectos del desentrenamiento sobre el salto vertical, la velocidad de desplazamiento y la composición corporal en futbolistas jóvenes. Método. Veintidós jugadores (16.4±0.4 años, 70.0±7.1kg, 175.9±6.9cm) se sometieron a evaluaciones de composición corporal, saltos verticales y velocidad (carreras de 20 metros), antes y después de 2 semanas de desentrenamiento. Resultados. Se encontraron aumentos significativos en el porcentaje de grasa corporal (p&lt;0.001) y a pesar de que la disminución de la velocidad no fue significativa (p&gt;0.05), hubo una reducción del 2.24% (ES=0.78) y del 0.97% (ES=0.41) en los tiempos en 5 y 20m, respectivamente. Igualmente, se observó una tendencia al aumento del salto sin contramovimiento (p=0.056). Conclusión. Dos semanas de desentrenamiento produjeron alteraciones significativas en la composición corporal y en la velocidad (entre 0&amp;#8208;5m) de los jóvenes futbolistas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;9(3): 124-130, sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154179</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del desentrenamiento sobre la composición corporal, la capacidad de salto vertical y la velocidad de jóvenes futbolistas de élite</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11240^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28453^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
