<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82425</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe flare of Behcet's disease with intense mucucutaneous manifestations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Behcet's disease is a multisystemic inflammatory disease with various manifestations at the skin level, especially in the form of acne-like lesions or erythema nodosum. Susceptibility to this disease is strongly linked to the presence of the HLA_B51 allele, although certain environmental factors such as infectious agents have also been implicated in its pathogenesis. We present the case of a patient with Behcet's disease who developed a severe flare characterized by lesions similar to those seen in Sweet's syndrome. Histologically we observed granulomatous vasculitis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, Elisabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteagudo, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordá, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Behçet es un trastorno inflamatorio multisistémico que se manifiesta de forma muy variada a nivel cutáneo, especialmente en forma de lesiones acneiformes o de eritema nodoso. La susceptibilidad a padecer esta enfermedad se halla fuertemente ligada con la presencia del alelo HLA-B51, aunque determinados factores ambientales como agentes infecciosos también se han implicado en la patogénesis. Presentamos el caso de una paciente con una enfermedad de Behçet que desarrolló un brote severo con lesiones cutáneas análogas a las que se aprecian en el síndrome de Sweet. Histológicamente se apreciaron fenómenos de vasculitis granulomatosa(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);6(6): 303-305, nov.-dic.2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82425</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote severo de la enfermedad de Behçet con manifestaciones mucocutáneas intensas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4980^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9526^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9526^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28255^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22622^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
