<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156638</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multiple sclerosis: a diagnostic challenge in pediatrics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Multiple sclerosis (MS) is the most common primary demyelinating disease of the central nervous system (CNS). It usually manifests with episodes of neurological deficits that follow a relapsing-remitting course, and approximately 2-5% of the cases have an onset during childhood. We describe a case of primary demyelinating disease of the CNS suggestive of MS, we emphasize the importance of a proper differential diagnosis, and highlight the new diagnostic criteria for pediatric MS. Case report. A 12-year old girl presented with a one-week history of hypoesthesia in the left trigeminal dermatome and the right upper extremity, and active cold sores. There was history of hepatitis B and human papilloma virus immunization eight months prior. A brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) showed demyelinating lesions in the left hemisphere and right medulla oblongata; some of them enhanced with gadolinium. Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) showed normal protein and absence of pleocytosis, but with oligoclonal bands of intratechal synthesis. Polymerase chain reaction for herpes virus was negative. The clinical and MRI lesions suggested the diagnosis or a primary CNS demyelinating disease, with high suspicion for MS. Comments. Demyelinating diseases of the CNS include a broad differential diagnosis. The presence of positive serology may suggest the diagnosis of acute disseminated encephalomyelitis (ADEM), which is a post-infectious process. Neuroimaging may be very useful in the diagnosis of demyelinating diseases. In addition, oligoclonal bands, anti-AQP4/NMO (neuromyelitis optica) antibodies, and anti-MOG (myelin oligodendrocyte) antibodies may be helpful in the diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bras-Boqueras, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayats-Vidal, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mañé-Martínez, M Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán-Ballén, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Arnaldich, Salomé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez-Pérez, Amalui</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La esclerosis múltiple (EM) es la enfermedad desmielinizante primaria del sistema nervioso central (SNC) más común. Suele manifestarse con episodios de focalidad neurológica con curso remitente-recurrente. Entre el 2 y el 5% de los casos debutan en la infancia. Se describe un caso de enfermedad primaria del SNC sugestivo de EM, remarcando la importancia de hacer un buen diagnóstico diferencial y resaltando los nuevos criterios diagnósticos de EM pediátrica. Caso clínico. Niña de 12 años que se presenta con clínica de una semana de evolución de hipostesia en territorio trigeminal izquierdo y extremidad superior derecha. Herpes labial activo. Vacunada de virus de la hepatitis B y de virus del papiloma humano ocho meses antes. Estudio de neuroimagen con resonancia magnética nuclear (RM) cerebral que muestra lesiones desmielinizantes en sustancia blanca de hemisferio cerebral izquierdo y hemiprotuberancia derecha, algunas con signos de actividad. Líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR) sin proteinorraquia ni pleocitosis, con bandas oligoclonales de IgG de síntesis intratecal. Reacción en cadena de polimerasa (PCR) de herpes virus en LCR negativa. El cuadro clínico y las lesiones de la RM orientan al diagnóstico con alta sospecha de EM. Comentarios. Las enfermedades desmielinizantes del SNC plantean un amplio diagnóstico diferencial. La presencia de serologías positivas en suero orienta a una enfermedad desmielinizante como la encefalomielitis aguda diseminada (EMAD), en que es frecuente un mecanismo post-infeccioso. La neuroimagen es muy útil en el diagnóstico de las enfermedades desmielinitzantes. Las bandas oligoclonales, los anticuerpos anti-AQP4/NMO (neuromielitis óptica) y los anticuerpos anti-MOG (mielina del oligodendrocito) podrían ser de gran ayuda en el diagnóstico de enfermedades desmielinizantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;76(2): 74-78, abr.-jun. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esclerosis múltiple: un reto diagnóstico en pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7165^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34309^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6719^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
