<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75874</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">General philosophy of organ-preserving treatment. Distinct therapeutic approaches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Organ preservation in advanced carcinomas of the head and neck has aroused enormous interest in the last few years and important studies and clinical trials have been published. For years, the only available options for preservation of the larynx or other head and neck organs were partial surgery and radiotherapy. New techniques have been added to partial surgery and, with the recent introduction of laser, continue to play a role in preservation. Radiotherapy has become more effective by modifying fractionation. However, the real revolution began in the 1980s with the introduction of chemotherapy, which greatly increased the options available. Induction chemotherapy followed by radiotherapy in patients with good response allows laryngeal preservation in approximately 50 % of cases, without compromising survival. Concomitant chemoradiotherapy provides even higher preservation rates and induction chemotherapy followed by concomitant chemoradiotherapy is under study. Finally, molecular therapies have opened up a new line of investigation and progress. With so many and such highly diverse options and the lack of overall consensus, multidisciplinary studies are required to define the optimal strategy in specific patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quer, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La preservación de órgano en los carcinomas avanzados de cabeza y cuello ha sido un tema que ha suscitado un enorme interés en los últimos años, y a él se han dedicado importantes estudios y ensayos clínicos. Durante años, la cirugía parcial y la radioterapia (RT) fueron las únicas opciones para intentar preservar la laringe u otros órganos de cabeza y cuello. La cirugía parcial ha ido incorporando nuevas técnicas y últimamente con la introducción del láser sigue teniendo su papel en la preservación. La RT ha buscado y hallado mayor eficacia modificando los fraccionamientos. Sin embargo, la autentica revolución surgió a partir de los años ochenta con la introducción de la quimioterapia (QT), que multiplicó las opciones. La QT de inducción seguida de RT cuando hay buena respuesta ha permitido conservar la laringe en alrededor del 50 % de los casos, sin perder supervivencia. La quimiorradioterapia concomitante permite aún mayores tasas de preservación, y la QT de inducción seguida de quimiorradioterapia concomitante está en estudio. Finalmente, las terapias moleculares abren una nueva vía de investigación y progreso. Ante tantas y tan diversas opciones y la falta de un consenso global, son necesarios estudios multidisciplinares para intentar defi nir la mejor estrategia para cada paciente concreto(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;60(supl.2): 2-7, oct. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Filosofía general del tratamiento preservador de órgano. Diferentes aproximaciones terapéuticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
