<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75714</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infrainguinal reconstructive suergery. Follop-up to the 7 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. The antiquity of the atherosclerosis has settled down by Egyptian studies in momias. The obliterants atherosclerosisthis caused by you narrow or atherosclerotic obstruction of arteries of greater and medium size than irrigates theextremities. The symptoms and signs depend on the stenosis degree of the artery. OBJECTIVE. To determine the main factorsof risk of the patients of our sample and of evaluating in which stages of the disease obtain the best operating results postand of comparing the results in the long term. MATERIAL AND METHOD. I am made a retrospective study in the Hospital &#147;Manuel Ascunce Doménech &#148; from January 1999 to April 2006. The sample was constituted by 27 patients taken part surgicallyby femoropoplíteal stenoclusives injuries of the sector and were evaluated to the 7años. The data were gathered of clinicalhistories and the interrogation and examination of the patient. These data were spilled in a personal survey, pathologicalantecedents, factors of risk: HTA, diabetes mellitus, I live to smoke, the age and sanguineous hyperviscosity. Results: Ofthe total of cases, 21 was masculine and single 6 were feminine. The age average was of 63,54 year, I live to smoke 100% ofour patients were smokers, 63,5% were hypertense, and a 54,2% had hyperviscosity and a 14% were diabetic. To the 7 yearsin the IIb stage the permeability is of 60%, the permeability to the 7 years according to the surgical technique used with bypass with safena vein in situ was the permeability of 77,3% with 11 cases, while with the inverted safena vein it was of 23,1%with 3 cases. Conclusions: The habit to smoke, the arterial hypertension and sanguineous hyperviscosity were the main factorsof risk in our series, the best long term permeability profit with the vein bypass technique &#147;in situ &#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Varela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés Nápoles, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta Vásquez, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. La antigüedad de la aterosclerosis se ha establecido por estudios en momias egipcias,. La aterosclerosis obliteranteesta causada por estreches u obstrucción arteriosclerótica de arterias de mayor y mediano tamaño que irrigan lasextremidades. Los síntomas y signos dependen del grado de estenosis de la arteria. OBJETIVO. Determinar los principales factoresde riesgo de los pacientes de nuestra muestra y evaluar en que estadios de la enfermedad se obtienen los mejores resultadospost operatorios y comparar los resultados a largo plazo. MATERIAL Y MÉTODO. Se realizo un estudio retrospectivo en elHospital &#147;Manuel Ascunce Doménech&#148; desde Enero 1999 hasta Abril 2006. La muestra estuvo constituida por 27 pacientesintervenidos quirúrgicamente por lesiones estenoclusivas del sector femoropoplíteas y fueron evaluados a los 7años. Los datosfueron recogidos de las historias clínicas y del interrogatorio y examen del paciente. Estos datos fueron vertidos en unaencuesta, antecedentes patológicos personales, factores de riesgo: HTA, diabetes mellitus, habito de fumar, la edad y la hiperviscosidadsanguínea. RESULTADOS. Del total de casos, 21 eran masculinos y solo 6 eran femeninas. La edad promedio fue de63.54 año, El habito de fumar el 100% de nuestros pacientes eran fumadores, el 63.5% eran hipertensos, y un 54.2% teníanhiperviscosidad y un 14% eran diabéticos. A los 7 años en el estadio IIb la permeabilidad es del 60%, La permeabilidada los 7 años según la técnica quirúrgica empleada con el by pass con safena in situ fue la permeabilidad del 77.3% con 11casos, mientras con la safena invertida fue de23.1% con 3 casos. CONCLUSIONES. El hábito de fumar, la hipertensión arterialy la hiperviscosidad sanguínea fueron los principales factores de riesgo en nuestra serie, la mejor permeabilidad a largo plazose logro con la técnica de safena &#147;in situ&#148; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;11(1): 14-16, ene.-mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75714</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía infrainguinal revascularizadora, evolución posquirúrgica a los 7 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5367^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11592^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
