<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054143</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-811X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hydrops fetalis secondary to parvovirus B19 infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intrauterin infection with parvovirus B19 is associated with non-immune hydrops fetalis, spontaneous abortion and fetal death. Recent improvements in diagnosing parvovirus infections and the availability of intrauterine transfusion have reduced the overall rate of fetal loss after maternal exposure.     We present a case of non-immune hydrops fetalis diagnosed by antenatal ultrasound at 21 weeks of gestation associated with maternal hypertension, edemas and proteinuria. Cordocentesis demonstrated by PCR in fetal blood the presence of parvovirus. The pregnancy finished in therapeutic miscarriage due to the worsening maternal status</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maroto Páez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gasch López, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldecoa Álvarez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección intrauterina por parvovirus (B19) se asocia con hidropesía fetal no inmune, aborto espontáneo y muerte fetal. Las recientes mejoras en el diagnóstico de la infección por parvovirus y la disponibilidad de la transfusión intrauterina han reducido mucho la incidencia de pérdida fetal tras la exposición materna.     Presentamos un caso de hidropesía fetal no inmune diagnosticado por ecografía prenatal en la semana 21 de gestación asociada a hipertensión arterial materna, edemas y proteinuria. La cordocentesis demostró la presencia de parvovirus en sangre fetal mediante PCR. La gestación finalizó en aborto terapéutico debido al empeoramiento del estado materno</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. diagn. trat. prenat. (Ed. impr.);18(1): 41-44, ene.-mar. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054143</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hidropesía fetal secundaria a infección por parvovirus B19</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11691^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23685^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31886^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23685^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
