<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143178</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aerobic capacity and quality of life in school children from 8 to 12</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aerobic capacity is a powerful physiological indicator of the overall health status. The objective of this study was to analyse the relationship between aerobic capacity and quality of life in a sample of 298 (159 girls) school children aged 8-12 years. Aerobic capacity was tested using the Course-Navette test. Quality of life was assessed using the KIDSCREEN-10 Index scale. Males showed higher performance in the Course-Navette test and highest values of VO2max (P &lt; .001 for both). ANOVA statistical analysis showed that the quality of life was significantly higher in school children with increased level of aerobic capacity compared to those with a low level (P = .001). Children with high aerobic capacity showed higher quality of life scores in relation to their peers with low scores (P &lt; .001). As for the females, significant differences were found among those with high aerobic capacity level and their peers low levels (P &lt; .031). The results of this study suggest that school children with higher level of aerobic capacity show better results in the quality of life index. Long-term intervention studies are needed to verify if an aerobic capacity development programme may upgrade the quality of life of children and adolescents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tarraga Marcos, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, Pedro L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillamón, Andrés Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez Casas, Arancha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cantó, Eliseo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Soto, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarraga Lopez, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La capacidad aeróbica es un potente indicador fisiológico del estado general de salud. El propósito de este estudio fue analizar la relación entre capacidad aeróbica y calidad de vida en una muestra de 298 (159 niñas) escolares de 8-12 años de edad. La capacidad aeróbica se evaluó mediante el test de Course-Navette. La calidad de vida se valoró mediante la escala KIDSCREEN-10 Index. Los varones presentaron un rendimiento superior en el test de Course-Navette y valores más altos de VO2máx (p &lt; 0,001 para ambos). El análisis ANOVA mostró que los niveles de calidad de vida eran significativamente mayores en los escolares con un nivel alto de capacidad aeróbica comparados con aquellos con un nivel bajo (p = 0,001). Los niños con un nivel alto de capacidad aeróbica mostraron niveles de calidad de vida superiores con relación a sus pares con un nivel bajo (p &lt; 0,001). Con respecto a las niñas, se detectaron diferencias significativas entre aquellas que presentaban un nivel alto de capacidad aeróbica y sus pares con un nivel bajo (p = 0,031). Los resultados del presente estudio evidencian que los escolares con un nivel superior de capacidad aeróbica tienen un mayor nivel de calidad de vida. Es necesario realizar estudios longitudinales de intervención para corroborar si un programa orientado al desarrollo de la capacidad aeróbica puede mejorar la calidad de vida de niños y adolescentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);27(5): 239-245, sept.-oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Capacidad aeróbica y calidad de vida en escolares de 8 a 12 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6487^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
