<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155955</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transversus abdominal plane block as a sole anesthetic technique for abdominal wall hematoma drainage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Transversus abdominal plane (TAP) block is a known and useful technique, widely used for postoperative pain management of abdominal wall incisions. During the past years, and following the expansion of ultrasound guided techniques, its use has even gained more adepts. It is usually used as an adjuvant technique, primarily in order to control postoperative pain and reduce opioids consumption. We report the case of an 82 years old patient admitted for drainage of a postoperative abdominal wall hematoma after correction of a McBurney incisional hernia. The corrective surgery had gone on without incident, under general anesthesia with laryngeal mask. Two weeks later, the patient came back to our emergency department with a clear hematoma of the abdominal wall. Surgery was decided. A sole local anesthetic technique was achieved, using a TAP block. The block was performed under ultrasound guidance, using a subcostal approach. The surgery went on without complications. Therefore, TAP block offers a hemodynamic stability, appropriate intra-operative anesthesia and post-surgical analgesia of the abdominal wall (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monedero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Golvano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El bloqueo del plano transverso abdominal (TAP) es una técnica conocida y de demostrada utilidad, ampliamente usada en el contexto del manejo del dolor postoperatorio tras una incisión abdominal. Durante los últimos años, y gracias a la expansión de la ecografía en el ámbito de la anestesia, ha aumentado aún más la frecuencia de su utilización. Es frecuentemente usado como técnica adyuvante para el control del dolor postoperatorio y con el fin de disminuir el consumo de opioides u otros analgésicos. Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 82 años de edad intervenida para drenar un hematoma de pared abdominal tras la corrección de una hernia de McBurney. La herniorrafia había transcurrido sin incidencias, bajo anestesia general con mascarilla laríngea. Dos semanas después, la paciente acude a Urgencias con un hematoma franco en la pared abdominal. Se decidió realizarle un drenaje urgente. Dicho drenaje se realizó utilizando únicamente un TAP block ecoguiado. La cirugía cursó sin incidencias. Consideramos, por ello, que el TAP block ofrece una opción efectiva y hemodinámicamente estable para la anestesia de la pared abdominal, y para el posterior control del dolor postoperatorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;63(8): 487-490, oct. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155955</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueo del plano transverso abdominal como única técnica anestésica para el drenaje de un hematoma abdominal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
