<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80322</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reference values of the Spanish version of the SF-12v2 for the diabetic population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivePerceived health status questionnaires provide important information for health outcomes research. Reference measures are required to interpret the health-related quality of life questionnaires belonging to the short form (SF) health survey family. Previous studies have provided these reference measures for the Spanish general population, but not for specific disease conditions. The aim of the present study was to obtain diabetic population-based norms for the Spanish version of the 12-item short form health survey version II (SF-12v2) in the region of Murcia (Spain).MethodsWe performed a cross-sectional telephone survey in 1,500 non-institutionalized patients with type 1 or 2 diabetes, aged 18 years or older and representative of the region of Murcia. The central position, dispersion statistics and percentiles were calculated for each of the eight SF-12v2 scales and summary components (physical and mental).ResultsThe mental component summary (MCS) (mean: 50.5±12.8) was higher than the physical component summary (PCS) (42.5±11.8). By sex, men had more favorable MCS (53.6±11.6) and PCS (44.9±11.2) scores than women (MCS: 47.7±13.2; PCS: 40.3±11.9). The dimension with the highest score was vitality (men: 57.2±11.1; women: 51.9±12.1), while that with the lowest score was general health (men: 39.0±9.7; women: 35.8±10.0). When the groups were stratified by age, scores continued to be higher in men than in women.ConclusionsThe results of the present study should be taken as the diabetic population-based norms for the Spanish version of the SF-12v2 in the region of Murcia. These results may be useful to establish therapeutics targets, as well as for comparisons with the general, healthy and ill populations(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernando Arizaleta, Lauro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomar Rodríguez, Joaquín A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteagudo Piqueras, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoLos cuestionarios de salud percibida son instrumentos que proporcionan información importante para la investigación en resultados de salud. La familia de cuestionarios SF requiere valores de referencia para interpretar el impacto en calidad de vida relacionada con la salud. Estudios previos han proporcionado estos valores para la población general española, pero no para condiciones específicas de enfermedad. El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido obtener, para la versión española del SF-12v2, los valores de referencia de la población diabética de la Región de Murcia.MétodosEstudio transversal con encuesta telefónica a 1.500 personas representativas de los diabéticos tipo 1 y 2, no institucionalizados, de 18 años y más, de la Región de Murcia. Se calcularon medidas de tendencia central, dispersión y percentiles de las ocho dimensiones, e índices resumen (físico y mental), del SF-12v2.ResultadosEl índice de salud mental (ISM) medio (50,5±12,8) fue superior al físico (ISF) (42,5±11,8). En función del sexo, los hombres obtuvieron un ISM (53,6±11,6) y un ISF (44,9±11,2) mejores que las mujeres (ISM: 47,7±13,2; ISF: 40,3±11,9). La dimensión mejor valorada fue la vitalidad (hombres: 57,2±11,1; mujeres: 51,9±12,1), y la peor la salud general (hombres: 39,0±9,7; mujeres: 35,8±10,0). Estratificando por grupos de edad, los hombres seguían presentando mejores puntuaciones que las mujeres.ConclusionesEstos resultados deben ser considerados como valores de referencia de la población diabética de la Región de Murcia de la versión española del SF-12v2, y pueden ser útiles para establecer objetivos terapéuticos, comparar con población general, sana y con otras enfermedades(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(6): 526-532, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80322</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores de referencia de la población diabética para la versión española del SF-12v2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
