<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87386</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-4723</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Between January 2005 and June 2006, 2075 pregnant women from &#147;A.I. de Llano &#147; and &#147;J. R. Vidal&#148; Hospitals from Corrientes were studied. Indirect Hemaglutination (HAI) and ELISA test were performed. In seropositive patients&#146; newborn direct parasitologic methods (DPM) of Microstrout and bulk drop, and PCR amplification were made. Every sample with the specific band of 330pb of the kinetoplastide DNA was considered positive. Confirmed cases were treated during 60 days with Beznidazole. From total of pregnant women, 130 were seropositive (6,26%).From 104 newborn studied, 8 were positives by the DPM (7,7%) and 12 were positives by PCR (11,5%). From all diagnosed patients, only7 cases received treatment due to the impossibility to locate them. The prevalence of Chagas infection found in pregnant women of the Province of Corrientes is the usual for endemic areas of Latin America(between 2% and 51%), whereas the prevalence of congenital infection (11.5%) is significantly greater than the recorded one in other endemic areas of Argentina. Our results as well as others reported in the literature, show that the optimized PCR protocol used here was more sensitive in detecting the presence of Trypanosoma cruzi in Congenital Chagas&#146; Disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Gustavo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crenna, Ernesto C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brusés, Bettina L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, Daniel E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucero, Raúl H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre Enero de 2005 y Junio de 2006 se estudiaron 2075 embarazadas de los Hospitales &#147;A. I. de Llano&#148; y &#147;J. R. Vidal&#148; de la Ciudad de Corrientes. Se les efectuó Hemoaglutinación Indirecta (HAI) y test de ELISA. En los recién nacidos de aquellas pacientes que resultaron ser reactivas se les practicaron métodos parasitológicos directos (MPD) de Microstrout y Gota Gruesa, y amplificación por PCR y se consideró positiva toda muestra que presentara la banda específica de 330pb del ADN kinetoplastídico. Del total de embarazadas, 130 resultaron seropositivas (6,26%). Se estudiaron 104 recién nacidos, detectándose 8 positivos por los MPD (7,7%) y 12 positivos por PCR (11,5%).Los casos confirmados fueron tratados con Beznidazol durante 60 días. La prevalencia de la infección chagásica encontrada en embarazadas de la Provincia. de Corrientes está dentro de la esperada para áreas endémicas de Latinoamérica (entre 2% y 51%), mientras que la prevalencia de infección connatal hallada del 11,5% es significativamente mayor que la registrada en otras áreas endémicas de Argentina. Nuestros resultados demuestran, como otros reportados anteriormente en la literatura, que un protocolo de PCR optimizado como el usado aquí fue más sensible en la detección de Trypanosoma cruzien pacientes con Chagas congénito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. emerg;9(3): 121-124, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Chagas congénito en Hospitales de la ciudad de Corrientes-Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14748^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
