<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123714</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arrhythmias and Cardiac Electrophysiology: Main Developments in 2005</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac electrophysiology laboratories deal with a wide range of pathological conditions, diagnostic techniques, and treatments. Since a huge quantity of material has been published in recent months, this article will be limited to discussion of the most significant developments in the prognostic evaluation of arrhythmias, hereditary disease, syncope, atrial fibrillation, implantable cardioverterdefibrillators, cardiac resynchronization therapy, and catheter ablation. Even within these areas, discussion will be restricted to specific concrete topics and to a limited number of publications that were judged to have important implications for clinical practice. Our principal aim was to provide clinical cardiologists with an overview of the latest developments in cardiac electrophysiology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lozano, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Llorens, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La arritmología clínica abarca una gran cantidad de enfermedades, técnicas diagnósticas y de tratamiento. Son muchos los artículos publicados durante los últimos meses, por lo que en esta revisión nos limitaremos a comentar los avances más significativos en las técnicas de estratificación pronóstica, en las enfermedades hereditarias, el síncope, la fibrilación auricular, los dispositivos implantables, la resincronización cardíaca y la técnicas de ablación con catéter. Incluso en estos campos nos ceñiremos a algunos ámbitos concretos y un número limitado de publicaciones, las que consideramos tienen una mayor repercusión en la práctica clínica. Nuestro interés se centra, sobre todo, en aportar al cardiólogo clínico un boceto de los últimos avances en arritmología clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(supl.1): 20-30, 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123714</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Temas de actualidad 2005: electrofisiología y arritmias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54223^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52886^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
