<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042292</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methicillin resistant Staphylococcus aureus infection postoperatory complications and prognosis of patients with lower extremity amputatio</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) is associated with an increasing morbimortality when compared with other microorganisms. The aim of this study was to examine the complications and prognosis of the presence of MRSA in vascular patients with amputation of lower limbs. Patients and method: We included patients who had lower extremity amputation in our department in 2004 and displayed positive surgical wounds cultures. We compared patients with MRSA positive cultures with other microrganisms. We evaluated general characteristics, operative indications, surgical wounds microbiology, reamputations, morbimortality and mean time of stay in hospital. Results: 117 patients (median age 73, 68% male) underwent lower extremity amputation. 82 of them had positive cultures and MRSA were isolated in 30% cases. Two two groups were comparable and no statistical differences were found in relation to reamputation rate, morbimortality and mean time of stay in hospital. Conclusion: Presence of MRSA does not represent an additional risk of reamputation or an increase of postoperative complications. Careful wound surveillance, through wound debridement and optimal administration of antibiotics must be applied to all patients, regardless of the bacterial flora</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Alonso, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera-Díaz, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Norberto-García, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Fajardo, Josá A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río-Solá, M. Lourdes del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Puerta, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El aumento de la incidencia y la gravedad de las infecciones es actualmente un importante problema terapéutico. Staphylococcus aureus resistente a la meticilina (SARM) se asocia a un aumento en la morbimortalidad cuando se compara con otras infecciones bacterianas; sin embargo, esta asociación no resulta clara debido a peores condiciones de comorbilidad en los pacientes con SARM. El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar las complicaciones postoperatorias y la mortalidad asociada a la presencia de SARM en pacientes con enfermedad vascular sometidos a amputación (mayor o menor) de la extremidad inferior. Pacientes y método: Pacientes consecutivos sometidos a la amputación de la extremidad inferior en nuestro Servicio durante el año 2004 que presentaron cultivo microbiológico positivo de la herida. Se comparó a los pacientes con SARM frente a los que tenían un germen diferente. Se evaluaron sus características generales, la indicación quirúrgica, la microbiología de la herida quirúrgica, la tasa de reamputación, la morbimortalidad y la estancia media. Resultados: Se amputó a un total de 117 pacientes (edad media 73 años, 68% varones) durante este período. De ellos, 82 mostraron cultivo positivo y en el 30% de éstos se aisló SARM. Ambos grupos fueron comparables y no registraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en relación con la tasa de reamputación, morbimortalidad y estancia media. Conclusiones: La presencia de SARM no predispone a un riesgo adicional de reamputación ni a un incremento de las complicaciones postoperatorias. Hay que realizar la vigilancia de la herida, el desbridamiento quirúrgico y la antibioterapia racional en todos los pacientes amputados, con independencia de la flora bacteriana ai</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(4): 129-131, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la presencia de Staphylococcus aureus resistente a la meticilina en las complicaciones postoperatorias y en el pronóstico de los pacientes con amputación de extremidad inferior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d687^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
