<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101025</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of physical and psychological distress in occupational accidents in agriculture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Agriculture is one of the sectors with more occupational accidents; nevertheless, its psychosocial risks have not been sufficiently studied. The objective of this research is to analyze the relationship between different job stressors, physical and psychological distress and the number of occupational accidents in a sample of 261 Spanish farmers. Job stressors were measured using an adapted version of Hurrel and McLaney´s (1988) Job Stress Questionnaire; distress was measured through the Occupational Stress Indicator (OSI; Cooper, Sloan &amp; Williams, 1988). Results show that distress does not have a direct influence over the number of accidents, but it does modulate the effect of different job stressors. The study concludes indicating some measures that can be taken to reduce the rate of occupational accidents and improve farmers´ quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oscar Segovia, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Araújo, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La agricultura es uno de los sectores con más accidentes laborales, sin embargo, no se ha profundizado suficiente en el estudio psicosocial de sus riesgos. El objetivo de esta investigación es analizar la relación entre diferentes estresores del puesto, el malestar (físico y psicológico) y el número de accidentes laborales en una muestra de 261 agricultores españoles. Para la medida de los estresores laborales se usó una versión adaptada del Cuestionario de Estrés Laboral de Hurrel y McLaney (1988) y para el malestar las escalas correspondientes del Occupational Stress Indicator (OSI; Cooper, Sloan &amp; Williams, 1988). Los resultados muestran que el malestar no influye directamente en los accidentes, pero sí modula el efecto de los diferentes estresores. El estudio concluye indicando algunas medidas para la reducción de la siniestralidad labora y la mejora de la calidad de vida de los agricultores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;15(2/3): 249-261, dic. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101025</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel del malestar físico y psicológico en los accidentes laborales en la agricultura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d387^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
