<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156636</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyperinsulinism in a newborn unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hyperinsulinism (HI) is the most frequent cause of sustained neonatal hypoglycemia; it can be transient (secondary) or persistent (congenital). We describe four cases of neonatal HI seen in a neonatal unit over a seven-year period. Clinical observation. Three of the four cases were transient or secondary, and the other was persistent. Loss of fetal wellbeing and gestational diabetes were the predisposing factors in the three transient cases. The case of persistent HI had normal brain magnetic resonance imaging and genetics; it did not respond to treatment wth diazoxide (DI) but improved with continuous feeding and dextrinomaltose. All four cases recovered with no neurological sequelae. Comments. Our fours cases met the diagnosis criteria for HI. Over the seven-year period, the overall incidence of HI was 1 in 4,500 live births, while the incidence of persistent HI was 1 in 20,000 live births. Transient or secondary HI is related to birth asphyxia, intrauterine growth retardation, and gestational diabetes. The initial treatment of HI is with glucose and DI. Persistent or congenital HI seldom responds to treatment and it can be the result of focal or diffuse pancreatic disease, the first of which anomalies could benefit from surgery. Prevention of neurological sequelae is the main objective of the treatment. A multidisciplinary management with endocrinology is recommended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capdevila, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porta, Roser</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caravaca, M Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gussinyé, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clemente, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El hiperinsulinismo (HI) es la causa más frecuente de hipoglucemia neonatal mantenida. Se puede dividir en transitorio o secundario y persistente o congénito. Se presenta una revisión del tema, a partir de cuatro casos diagnosticados en nuestra unidad durante siete años. Observación clínica. De los cuatro casos, tres son transitorios o secundarios y uno persistente. Los factores predisponentes de los transitorios son la pérdida del bienestar fetal y la diabetes gestacional. El persistente, con una resonancia magnética (RM) craneal y un estudio genético normales, no respondió al diazóxido (DI) y mejoró con dextrinomaltosa y alimentación continua. Ningún caso presentó secuelas neurológicas. Comentarios. Nuestros casos cumplen los criterios diagnósticos de HI. La incidencia de HI en nuestro centro es de 1/4.500 nacidos vivos y la de HI persistente de 1/20.000 nacidos vivos en siete años. El HI transitorio o secundario se relaciona con la asfixia neonatal, el retraso del crecimiento intrauterino y la diabetes gestacional. Los casos descritos presentan pérdida del bienestar fetal y diabetes. El tratamiento inicial es el aporte de glucosa. Después, el fármaco de primera linea es el DI. El HI persistente acostumbra a no responder al tratamiento y puede ser focal o difuso, el primero de los cuales puede beneficiarse de cirugía. El máximo objetivo es la prevención de secuelas neurológicas. Es fundamental el manejo conjunto con un especialista endocrinólogo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;76(2): 67-70, abr.-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156636</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperinsulinismo en una unidad neonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7127^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7127^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7127^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4010^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
