<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59821</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Final size attained in type 1 diabetes children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the final height and height-gain in relation to target height, in children with type 1 diabetes mellitus, and analyse their relationship to different variables. Patients and methods: Retrospective analysis of the growth data of 52 children (27 girls) diagnosed with type 1 diabetes mellitus before 14 years old, and followed up until their final height was attained. Main variables: final height, target height, illness duration, glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c), insulin dose, BMI, and other autoimmune diseases. Results: The height SDS (standard deviation scale) at diagnosis was slightly higher (0.734 in boys and 0.563 in girls). During the development of the disease, a growth reduction was seen, which was significantly higher in boys of prepubertal age (p=0.016). The mean final height attained was 173.14±5.28cm in boys and 161.9±6.97cm in girls. Height gain was 1.56±3.66 in boys (SDS=&amp;#8722;0.034) and 2.26±6.13 in girls (SDS=0.385). The only variable significantly related to height gain was mean glycated-haemoglobin (growth reduction of 2cm for every increment of 1% in mean glycated-haemoglobin). Conclusions: At onset, diabetic children were slightly taller than the general population. A growth reduction was shown as the disease developed, significantly higher in boys of prepubertal age. The final height in boys was slightly lower than the mean, but in girls was similar to the general population. Both sexes attained their target height, although the height gain was less in boys. Poorer metabolic control was associated with reduced height gain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gámez Gómez, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonillo Perales, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Fernández, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Llorente, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galera Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: describir la talla final y la ganancia sobre la talla diana, en un grupo de niños diabéticos tipo 1 y analizar su relación con distintas variables. Pacientes y métodos: estudio retrospectivo de 52 pacientes (27 mujeres) diagnosticados de diabetes tipo 1 antes de los 14 años y seguidos hasta la talla final. Variables principales: talla final, talla diana, tiempo de evolución de la diabetes, glucohemoglobina (HbA1c) media, requerimiento insulínico, índice de masa corporal, enfermedades autoinmunes asociadas. Resultados: al inicio de la diabetes la escala de desviación estándar (EDE) de talla se encontraba ligeramente por encima de la media (0,734 en varones y 0,563 en mujeres). A lo largo de la evolución se produce un pérdida de talla generalizada, más acusada en varones en etapa prepuberal (p=0,016). La talla final alcanzada fue 173,14±5,28cm en varones (EDE=&amp;#8722;0,034) y 161,9±6,97cm en mujeres (EDE=0,385). La ganancia de talla fue 1,56±3,66cm en varones y 2,26±6,13cm en mujeres. La única variable relevante relacionada significativamente con la ganancia de talla fue la HbA1c media (pérdida de 2cm por cada aumento del 1% de HbA1c media a igualdad del resto de las variables). Conclusiones: nuestros resultados indican que, aunque al inicio de la diabetes los niños tienen una talla algo mayor que la de la población de referencia, se produce una pérdida de talla durante la evolución de la enfermedad, más acusada en varones en periodo prepuberal. Ello produce que la talla final de los varones se encuentre ligeramente por debajo de la media, mientras que las mujeres alcanzan una talla final similar a la de la población de referencia. Ambos sexos alcanzaron su talla diana, pero en varones la ganancia sobre ésta fue escasa. El mal control metabólico se relacionó con la menor ganancia de talla en niños diabéticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(3): 235-240, mar. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59821</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Talla final en diabéticos tipo 1 diagnosticados en la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1852</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
