<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136439</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Professional deontology and medical practices in prisons</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study knowledge of professional deontology amongst doctors in prisons. Materials and Method: Descriptive, transversal and multi-centre study. Labour, collegiate, social, demographic and deontological variables were collected. A descriptive analysis of the variables was performed. A bivariant analysis was made by binar y logistic regression models, attending to the odds ratio, and assuming a 95% confidence interval. Data is processed by SPSS v.20 software. Results: 118 doctors replied. 68 men (57.6%), average age 51 years (50-53). 100 know about the Deontology Commission (84.7%), but just 77 (65.3%) know its functions properly. 42 (35.6%) know about the existence of the Deontological Code, and 37 (31,3%) have read and apply it. Those who made a correct definition of deontology do find more deontological issues in theirdaily work [23(46.9%) vs 18(26.1%); OR: 2.506; IC95%: 1.153-5.451; p=0.020] and would denounce a colleague more often to the Medical Association [40(81.6%) vs 42 (60.9%); OR: 2.857; IC95%: 1.197-6.819; p=0.018]. Older ones know more about the deontology commissions&#146; functions [54(73%) vs 23(52.3%); OR: 2.465; IC95%: 1.127-5.394; p=0.024] and have already denounced situations to the Medical Association [27(36.5% vs 5(11.4%); OR: 4.481; IC95%: 1.577-12.733; p=0.005], but think that a different Care Ethics Committee is unnecessary [57(77%) vs 42(95.5%); OR: 0.160; IC95%: 0.035-0.729; p=0.018].Conclusions: Prison doctors know little about what professional deontology really is. This knowledge increases with age in the profession and is associated with increased perception of deontological issues in daily practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vera-Remartínez, E. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Guerrero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar el conocimiento sobre la deontología profesional entre los médicos de prisiones. Material y Método: Estudio descriptivo, transversal y multicéntrico. Se recogieron variables laborales, colegiales, sociodemográficas y de cuestiones deontológicas. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo de las variables. Se hizo un análisis bivariante mediante modelos de regresión logística binaria con las odds ratio e intervalos de confianza al 95%. Los datos se procesaron con el programa SPSS v.20. Resultados: Contestaron 118 médicos. 68 hombres (57,6%), con mediana de edad de 51 años (50-53). Conocen qué es la Comisión Deontológica 100 (84,7%), pero sólo 77 (65,3%) conocen bien sus funciones. 42 (35,6%) conocen la existencia del Código de Deontología y 37 (31,3%) lo han leído y lo acatan. Los que definieron correctamente la Deontología profesional encuentran más problemas deontológicos en su ejercicio diario [23(46,9%) vs 18(26,1%); OR: 2,506; IC95%: 1,153-5,451; p=0,020] y denunciarían más a un colega ante su Colegio [40(81,6%) vs 42 (60,9%); OR: 2,857; IC95%: 1,197-6,819; p=0,018]. Los más antiguos conocen mejor las funciones de las Comisiones deontológicas [54(73%) vs 23(52,3%); OR: 2,465; IC95%: 1,127-5,394; p=0,024] y han denunciado situaciones ante su Colegio [27(36,5%) vs  5(11,4%); OR: 4,481; IC95%: 1,577-12,733; p=0,005], pero creen menos en la necesidad de un Comité ético asistencial propio de prisiones [57(77%) vs 42(95,5%); OR: 0,160; IC95%: 0,035-0,729; p=0,018].Conclusiones: Los médicos de prisiones conocen poco qué es la deontología profesional. Este conocimiento aumenta con la antigüedad en el ejercicio y se asocia a mayor percepción de problemas deontológicos en el ejercicio diario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;17(2): 47-53, jul.-oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136439</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deontología profesional y ejercicio médico en prisiones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5086</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36364</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
