<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054498</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The "awareness climbing". an educational board game for improving self-awareness following acquired brain injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To establish the effectiveness of an educational board game for improving self-awareness following acquired        brain injury. Patients and methods. The &#145;awareness climbing&#146; is a board game format intervention for improving awareness of        patients with acquired brain injury (ABI) and for facilitating the use of anticipatory and compensatory strategies. 17 patients        with ABI (traumatic brain injury, 10; stroke, 5; others, 2) were included in a self-awareness rehabilitation program using the        &#145;awareness climbing&#146;. Self-awareness was assessed with the Self-Awareness of Deficit Interview (SADI) before and after game        intervention. According to the SADI self-awareness consists of three-interdependent levels: intellectual awareness (impairments),        emergent awareness (disability) and anticipatory awareness, which involve the client predicting when impairments will affect his        or her performance. Results. Initially five patients showed impaired intellectual awareness, four patients had difficulties on        emergent awareness and nine patients showed deficits on anticipatory awareness. Intellectual awareness improved in 10        patients, while six patients experienced improvements in emergent awareness over the intervention period. The most striking        change was an improvement in 70% of the sample (n = 11) in anticipatory awareness after game sessions. Conclusion.        According to SADI scores we suggest that the &#145;awareness climbing&#146; may be a useful tool for improving self-awareness after        acquired brain injury</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Blázquez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri-Campos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Renau-Hernández, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero-Coulon, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noé-Sebastián, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirivella-Garrido, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri-Salvador, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la eficacia de una herramienta lúdico-terapéutica (&#145;escalada de la conciencia&#146;) como método        para rehabilitar la conciencia de enfermedad en sujetos con daño cerebral adquirido (DCA). Pacientes y métodos. La &#145;escalada        de la conciencia&#146; es una herramienta lúdica que facilita la adquisición de conocimientos necesarios para la adecuada percepción        de las deficiencias y pone en práctica estrategias de afrontamiento y compensación de las diferentes limitaciones funcionales        generadas tras un DCA. Se incluyó a 17 pacientes con DCA (traumatismo craneoencefálico, 10; ictus, 5; otros, 2). El        grado de conciencia de los déficit y de sus implicaciones funcionales se valoró mediante la Self-Awareness of Deficit Interview        (SADI) antes y después de un programa de intervención que incluía esta herramienta. La entrevista SADI mide tres        aspectos de la conciencia: autoconciencia de los déficit, conciencia de las consecuencias funcionales y capacidad de establecer        metas realistas. Resultados. Inicialmente, cinco pacientes presentaban problemas de autopercepción de sus déficit; cuatro,        problemas de autopercepción de su discapacidad, y nueve tenían dificultades para establecer metas realistas de futuro. A lo        largo del proceso de seguimiento, la percepción de los déficit mejoró en diez pacientes, y la percepción de las dificultades        generadas por tales déficit, en seis. El cambio más significativo fue que, tras las sesiones de entrenamiento, el 70% de los sujetos        (n = 11) aprendió a establecer metas realistas en función de los problemas generados por su patología. Conclusión. Los        resultados obtenidos en la entrevista SADI convierten la &#145;escalada de la conciencia&#146; en un instrumento válido y útil en el proceso        rehabilitador de la conciencia de enfermedad en pacientes con DCA</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(6): 334-338, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054498</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">&#145;Escalada de la conciencia&#146;: un instrumento para mejorar la conciencia de enfermedad en pacientes con daño cerebral adquirido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12416</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
