<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154537</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prospective study in 2 hospitals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. The purpose of this study is to know the incidence rate of medication reconciliation at admission and discharge in patients of La Rioja and to improve the patient safety on medication reconciliation. Material and methods. An observational prospective study, part of the Joint Action PaSQ, Work Package 5, European Union Network for Patient Safety and Quality of Care. The study has taken into account the definitions of the Institute for Safe Medication Practices. Any unintended discrepancy in medication between chronic treatment and the treatment prescribed in the hospital was considered as a reconciliation error. Results. A total of 750 patients were included, 9 (1.2%) of whom showed at least one discrepancy. The patients had a total of 3,156 mediations registered: 2,313 prescriptions (73.4%) showed no differences, while 821 prescriptions (26%) were intended discrepancies and 21 prescriptions (0.6%) unintended discrepancies were considered by the physician as reconciliation errors. A percentage of 1.2 of the patients, which represents 0.6% of the medicines (one in 166 medications registered) had reconciliation errors during their hospital stay. Conclusions. A proceeding has been implemented by means of the physician doing the medication reconciliation and reviewing it with the help of a medication reconciliation form. The medication reconciliation is a priority strategic objective to improve the safety of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Diego, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sáenz, MS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo-García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cestafe-Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Buñuales, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo-Anciano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. El objetivo del estudio es conocer la incidencia de los errores de conciliación en el ingreso y al alta hospitalaria en pacientes de La Rioja y mejorar la seguridad del paciente en conciliación de la medicación. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional prospectivo que forma parte del proyecto de la Acción Conjunta de la Red de la Unión Europea para la Seguridad del Paciente y la Calidad de la Asistencia Sanitaria, Paquete de Trabajo 5. Se han tenido en cuenta las definiciones del Instituto para el Uso Seguro de los Medicamentos. Cualquier discrepancia no justificada entre el tratamiento crónico y el prescrito en el hospital se consideró error de conciliación. Resultados. Se incluyeron 750 pacientes, de los cuales 9 (1,2%) presentaron al menos un error de conciliación. De las 3.156 prescripciones, 2.313 (73,4%) no mostraron discrepancias, mientras que 821 (26%) fueron discrepancias justificadas y 21 (0,6%) discrepancias no justificadas que fueron consideradas por el médico como errores de conciliación. El 1,2% de los pacientes tuvieron errores de conciliación durante su estancia en el hospital, lo que implicó al 0,6% de los medicamentos (uno de cada 166 medicamentos prescritos). Conclusiones. Se ha establecido un procedimiento en el que el médico revisa la prescripción al ingreso y al alta basado en criterios de conciliación de la medicación, utilizando como herramienta un formulario de conciliación de la medicación. La conciliación de la medicación es un objetivo estratégico prioritario para mejorar la seguridad de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(supl.1): 4-10, jun. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio prospectivo en dos hospitales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6896^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54220^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6896^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
