<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118922</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Memory failures of Everyday (MFE): Factor Analysis with Spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the most frequently used instruments to study everyday memory failures is the Memory Failures of Everyday Questionnaire (MFE). The objectives of the present study were: a) to examine the factor structure of the MFE, and b) to explore the relationship of the resulting factors with performance in tests of objective memory (Word Lists and Family Pictures of the Wechsler Memory Scale-III) and mood state (Goldberg Depression and Anxiety Scale), as well as with two general questions about memory complaints. Data were collected from a sample of 647 young adults (19-64 years). Factor analysis revealed three factors which explained 29.3 % of the total variance: Activities Recall, Communication Monitoring, and Recognition. The first two factors showed a higher positive correlation between them and a higher association with mood state and general memory complaints. In contrast, the recognition factor shows positive correlation with age and negative with objective memory performance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sueiro-Abad, Manuel J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huertas, Evelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montenegro, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los instrumentos más utilizados para valorar los olvidos cotidianos es el Cuestionario de Fallos de Memoria de la Vida Cotidiana (MFE). Los objetivos del presente estudio fueron: a) examinar la estructura factorial del MFE, b) explorar las relaciones de los factores resultantes con el rendimiento objetivo de memoria (Listas de Palabras y Escenas de la Es-cala de Memoria de Wechsler - III), el estado de ánimo y la ansiedad (Escala de Depresión y Ansiedad de Goldberg) y con dos preguntas generales sobre quejas de memoria. Los datos se recogieron de una muestra de 647 adultos jóvenes (19-64 años). Los resultados mostraron la existencia de una estructura de tres factores, que explicaban el 29.3 % de la varianza: Recuerdo de Actividades, Monitorización de la Comunicación y Reconocimiento. Los dos primeros factores mostraron una correlación positiva más alta en-tre ellos y una asociación mayor con el estado de ánimo y las quejas genera-les de memoria. Por el contrario, el factor Reconocimiento presentó una correlación positiva más alta con la edad y negativa con el rendimiento objetivo de memoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(1): 320-328, ene.-abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118922</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuestionario de Fallos de Memoria de la Vida Cotidiana (MFE). Análisis de factores con población española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
