<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045082</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of scientific production of health care professionals: a proposal</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the imminent establishment of a professional career for all the Health Care staff in the entire national territory, it is important to have a tool that helps to assess the research merits that are contemplated in it and that contribute to their homogeneous evaluation by the different boards. A proposal is present in this article for the evaluation of varied scientific production of Health Care professionals, separately analyzing the characteristics and minimum requirements needed for the contributions in journals, books, communications at a congress and doctorate thesis. Each one of them is weighted, considering aspects of quality and dissemination</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Valero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez Vázquez, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con la inminente instauración de la carrera profesional para el personal sanitario en todo el territorio nacional, es importante disponer de una herramienta que ayude a la valoración de los méritos de investigación que en ella se contemplan, y contribuya a su evaluación homogénea por los distintos tribunales. En este artículo se presenta una propuesta para la valoración de la variada producción científica de los profesionales sanitarios, analizando de forma separada las características y requisitos mínimos que deben reunir para ser tenidas en cuenta las contribuciones en revistas, los libros, las comunicaciones a congresos y la tesis doctoral, y se pondera cada uno de ellos teniendo en cuenta aspectos de calidad y difusión</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(2): 68-72, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045082</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la producción científica de los profesionales sanitarios: una propuesta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24960</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12077^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
