<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95570</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk stratification in diabetic foot</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diabetic foot is a chronic complication of diabetes mellitus and constitutes asanitary problem which causes not only enormous expenses for the sanitary system but also provokes emotional repercussions for the person who suffers the illness and for the family. The sanitary education in taking care of the feet of diabetics and the identification of the health risk are both aspects that the nurse must include in the healthcare planning of diabetic patients. The detection of the possible risk factorsis an essential previous step in nursing. The purpose of this study is to detect the presence of certain risk factors in diabetic foot in the diabetic population of Triana Healthcare Centre to be able to carry out a stratification of the risk. For this research, there was chosen an observational, descriptive and transversal study.The analyzed sample was constituted by 96 diabetic subjects belonging to the Healthcare Centre. For the data collection, we use different systems such as interviews,physical exams and the available records (clinical history of the patients).The information has been recorded in a questionnaire of the diabetic foot. The existence of risk factors was determined by analyzing the relationship between them allowing the risk stratification of the studied sample (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana Lorenzo, M. Luana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Fernández, Abián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perdomo Pérez, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de la Torre, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pie diabético es una complicación crónica de la diabetes mellitus y constituye una problemática sanitaria al conllevar un enorme gasto económico a losservicios sanitarios y provocar a las personas que lo padecen y a su entorno familiar enormes repercusiones emocionales. La educación sanitaria en el cuidado de los pies de los diabéticos, así como la cuantificación del riesgo son aspectos que el enfermero debe incorporar en los planes de cuidados de los pacientes diabéticos. La detección de los posibles factores de riesgo es un paso previo imprescindible para estos cometidos. Este estudio tiene como finalidad analizar la presencia de determinados factores de riesgo en pie diabético en la población diabética del Centro de Salud de Triana, con el objetivo de poder realizar, así, una estratificación del riesgo. Para ello, se optó por la realización de un estudio observacional descriptivo. La muestra analizada estaba constituidapor 96 sujetos diabéticos pertenecientes a dicho centro de salud. Para la recogida de datos se utilizó un sistema de tres niveles consistente en entrevista,exploración física y consulta de registros disponibles (a través de las historias clínicas de los sujetos). Los datos se registraron en un formulario de recogida de datos para pie diabético. Se determinó la existencia de factores de riesgo, analizando las relaciones entre éstos y permitiendo la estratificación del riesgo en la población estudiada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);21(4): 172-182, dic. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95570</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estratificación de riesgo en pie diabético</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
