<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78427</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Does early treatment of Rheumatoid Arthritis lead to a better long-term prognosis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Time is a crucial dimension in most chronic diseases, especially in inflammatory rheumatic disease, which it affects in many ways. Early treatment in rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is an essential issue, as joint damage occurs within the first weeks or months of the disease process and inflammatory activity maintained over time is responsible for all of the consequences of the disease. The introduction of new drugs with faster and more effective action, such as tumor necrosis factor (TNF) inhibitors, has represented a major shift in the strategy of RA treatment, allowing the clinician to aim for remission and prevention of structural damage as realizable goals(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villaverde García, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balsa Criado, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tiempo es una dimensión de importancia capital en la mayoría de las enfermedades crónicas y, especialmente, en las enfermedades reumáticas inflamatorias, donde influye en muchos aspectos. El tratamiento precoz de la artritis reumatoide es esencial, debido a que el proceso destructivo articular comienza muy pronto, en las primeras semanas o meses, y la actividad inflamatoria mantenida en el tiempo es responsable de todas las consecuencias de la enfermedad. La introducción de fármacos nuevos con una acción más rápida y eficaz, como los fármacos biológicos anti-TNF, ha supuesto un cambio radical en la estrategia de tratamiento de la artritis reumatoide, permitiendo, incluso, que la inducción de la remisión y la detención del proceso destructivo articular sean unos objetivos posibles(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);6(2): 106-110, mar.-abr.2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78427</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿El control precoz de la artritis reumatoide augura un mejor pronóstico a largo plazo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38737^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
