<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115735</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of quality standards in inflammatory bowel disease management and design of an evaluation tool of nursing care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and aims: nursing management of inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) is highly relevant for patient care and outcomes. However, there is evidence of substantial variability in clinical practices. The objectives of this study were to develop standards of healthcare quality for nursing management of IBD and elaborate the evaluation tool &#147;Nursing Care Quality in IBD Assessment&#148; (NCQ-IBD) based on these standards. Methods: a 178-item healthcare quality questionnaire was developed based on a systematic review of IBD nursing management literature. The questionnaire was used to perform two 2-round Delphi studies: Delphi A included 27 IBD healthcare professionals and Delphi B involved 12 patients. The NCQ-IBD was developed from the list of items resulting from both Delphi studies combined with the Scientific Committee&#146;s expert opinion. Results: the final NCQ-IBD consists of 90 items, organized in 13 sections measuring the following aspects of nursing management of IBD: infrastructure, services, human resources, type of organization, nursing responsibilities, nurse-provided information to the patient, nurses training, annual audits of nursing activities, and nursing research in IBD. Using the NCQ-IBD to evaluate these components allows the rating of healthcare quality for nursing management of IBD into 4 categories: A (highest quality) through D (lowest quality). Conclusions: the use of the NCQ-IBD tool to evaluate nursing management quality of IBD identifies areas in need of improvement and thus contribute to an enhancement of care quality and reduction in clinical practice variations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfaro, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oltra, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Sampelayo, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrejón, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Sánchez, Valle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casellas, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: el manejo de la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (EII) por enfermería es muy relevante, sin embargo, existe una gran variabilidad en su práctica clínica. El objetivo de esta investigación es desarrollar estándares de calidad asistencial del manejo de la EII por enfermería, para elaborar un &#147;Instrumento de Evalua - ción de la Calidad Asistencial de la EII por Enfermería&#148; (IEC-EII). Métodos: tras una búsqueda bibliográfica del manejo de la EII por enfermería se elaboró un cuestionario de 178 ítems de calidad asistencial. Con este cuestionario, se realizaron dos estudios Delphi a dos rondas: Delphi A dirigido a 27 profesionales sanitarios en EII y Delphi B a 12 pacientes. Con los ítems de ambos estudios Delphi, se elaboró una lista que, junto con la opinión experta del Comité Científico, contribuyó a desarrollar el IEC-EII. Resultados: el IEC-EII se compone de 90 ítems, subdivididos en 13 dimensiones que miden aspectos del manejo de la EII por enfermería como: infraestructura, servicios, recursos humanos, tipo de organización, competencias asumidas por enfermería, información de enfermería al paciente, formación de enfermería, revisiones anuales de la actividad de enfermería e investigación de enfermería de EII. La evaluación de estos aspectos mediante el IEC-EII permite clasificar la calidad asistencial en EII por enfermería en 4 categorías de la A a la D. Siendo A el nivel de calidad superior y D el inferior. Conclusiones: el IEC-EII puede contribuir a aumentar la calidad asistencial de enfermería en EII y reducir su variabilidad, puesto que la evaluación ayudará a detectar sus deficiencias mejorables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(5): 262-271, mayo -jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115735</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de estándares de calidad para la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal y diseño de un instrumento de evaluación de los cuidados de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17227^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9925^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9925^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17227^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
