<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84913</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pyomyositis of the piriformis muscle</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Unfortunately, diagnosis of deep pelvic muscle infection is often delayed since they usually present with non-specific physical signs suggesting other more common diseases. The authors communicate a case of a previously healthy 12-year-old male whot practiced dancing regularly and suffered acute pain in the lumbar and right gluteal regions irradiated to the posterior side of the thigh for 1 week. He initially received symptomatic treatment with no success. He continued with diarrhea, fever and malaise. When he was admitted to hospital he suffered severe septic shock and multi-organ failure. Pelvis magnetic resonance imaging showed pyomyositis of the piriformis muscle. Multi-sensitive Staphylococcus aureus was isolated in blood cultures. Antibacterial treatment and multi systemic support were administered, resulting in a good outcome. Pyomyositis of the piriformis muscle is a rare condition that demands a high index of suspicion to make an adequate diagnosis and prompt treatment, including antibacterial treatment and drainage, particularly in case of abscess formation. This treatment should be established promptly since its outcome may be potentially lethal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Donoso Fuentes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriagada Santis, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones profundas de músculos pélvicos son difíciles de diagnosticar por ocasionar signos físicos inespecíficos que sugieren otras patologías más comunes. Comunicamos el caso de un paciente de 12 años, sexo masculino, sano, con el antecedente de practicar danza. Consultó por dolor en región lumbar y glútea derecha, irradiado por cara posterior del muslo, de siete días de evolución. Recibió tratamiento sintomático sin respuesta. Presentó diarrea, fiebre y compromiso del estado general, evolucionando con shock séptico durante su estadía hospitalaria. La resonancia nuclear magnética pélvica fue compatible con piomiositis de músculo piriforme. Se aisló en sangre Staphylococcus aureus multisensible. Recibió apoyo multisistémico y tratamiento antibiótico, evolucionando satisfactoriamente. La piomiositis del músculo piriforme es una entidad poco frecuente, que requiere un elevado índice de sospecha, para un adecuado diagnóstico y tratamiento, siendo la terapia antibiótica y drenaje en caso de abscesos los pilares de éste último. Este tratamiento debe instaurarse en forma precoz, ya que su evolución puede ser potencialmente letal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);55(1): 50-53, ene.-feb. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Piomiositis del músculo piriforme</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23504^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23201^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12966^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2475^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12966^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12966^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12966^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
