<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048225</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Causes and impact of hyponutrition and cachexia in the oncologic patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The maximal expression of hyponutrition in cancer is tumoral cachexia, which will direct or indirectly account for mortality in one third of cancer patients. Causes of hyponutrition in cancer are related with the tumor, the patient, or therapies, and summarily we may differentiate four main mechanisms by which hyponutrition may occur in cancer patients: &#149; Poor energy and nutrients intake &#149; Impairments of nutrient digestion and/or absorption &#149; Increased demands &#149; Impairments of nutrient metabolism. Any modality of oncologic therapy induces hyponutrition occurrence, especially in those cases in which several therapies are administered to cure cancer(surgery,radiotherapy, chemotherapy). Hyponutrition in cancer patients produces a decrease in muscle mass, which leads to strength loss, having important consequences on functional status of the individual since it increases dependence on others (relatives, caregivers) and decreases quality of life. Besides, hyponutrition is associated to poorer response to radiotherapy and chemotherapy, or poorer tolerability of such therapies. Hyponutrition also impairs scarring mechanisms and increases the risk for surgical complications such as suture dehiscence or infections. Both infectious complications and surgically derived complications entail longer hospital staying, which contributes to increase management costs. Finally, effects of hyponutrition on mortality should not be neglected, with severe weight loss being associated to lower survival (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Luna, PP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Cunill, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parejo Campos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La expresión máxima de desnutrición en el cáncer es la caquexia tumoral, que será responsable directa o indirecta de la muerte en un tercio de los pacientes con cáncer. Las causas de desnutrición en el cáncer están relacionadas con el tumor, con el paciente o con los tratamientos y de forma resumida podemos diferenciar 4 grandes mecanismos por los que puede aparecer desnutrición en el paciente canceroso: &#149; Escaso aporte de energía y nutrientes. &#149; Alteraciones de la digestión y/o absorción de nutrientes. &#149; Aumento de las necesidades. &#149; Alteraciones en el Metabolismo de los nutrientes. El tratamiento oncológico, en cualquiera de sus vertientes induce la aparición de desnutrición, sobre todo en aquellos casos en que se administran varios tratamientos para la curación del cáncer (cirugía, radioterapia y quimioterapia). La desnutrición en el paciente neoplásico produce una disminución de masa muscular que conlleva una pérdida de fuerza que tiene importantes consecuencias sobre el estado funcional del individuo, pues aumenta la dependencia de cuidados por terceros (familiares o cuidadores) y disminuye su calidad de vida. La desnutrición se asocia, además, a una menor respuesta a la radioterapia y a la quimioterapia, o a una peor tolerancia a éstas. La desnutrición también altera los mecanismos de cicatrización y aumenta el riesgo de complicaciones quirúrgicas tales como la deshiscencia de suturas e infecciones. Tanto las complicaciones infecciosas como las derivadas de la cirugía comportan un aumento de la estancia hospitalaria, circunstancias que contribuyen a elevar los costes de los tratamientos. En último término, no deben olvidarse los efectos de la desnutrición sobre la mortalidad, asociándose la pérdida de peso severa a una menor supervivencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(supl.3): 10-16, 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048225</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Causas e impacto clínico de la desnutrición y caquexia en el paciente oncológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2134^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
