<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036767</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Main components in neuropsychiatric inventory in Alzheimer's disease: definition of behavioral syndromes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Behavioral disturbances are an important part of the clinical picture of Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD). Behavior is usually assessed considering each symptom one by one. Few studies have tried a more comprehensive approach. We assessed behavior in AD patients in order to define patterns of behavioral disturbances, thereby improving its classification. Patients and methods. Ninety consecutive AD patients were evaluated from November 1997 to November 2000. All patients meet the NINCDS-ADRDA criteria for probable or possible AD. Patients with atypical clinical features were not included. Clinical evaluation included of the Neuropsychytric Inventory ("chronic" scores), Mini-Mental State Examination, RDRS-2 and CDR. Statistical analysis was performed with factor analysis (SPSS-Copyright). Results. Factor analysis rendered a three-factor solution. Each factor can be considered a behavioral syndrome: the psychotic syndrome (hallucinations and delusions), the affective syndrome (depression, euphoria and anxiety) and the dyscontrol syndrome (agitation, irritability and disinhibition). A relevant number of patients had mild behavioral disturbances, not meeting statistical criteria for the syndromes defined above. Conclusions. Behavioral disturbances in AD can be classified into four groups or syndromes. Our results are in accordance with and expand the results of previous reports, using different behavior scales and statistical analysis. Future studies must be aimed at better characterizing the extensive group with mild behavioral disturbances, not sufficiently defined by the methods applied in the present and previous studies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Soriano, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña, A. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amer-Ferrer, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los trastornos de conducta constituyen una manifestación clínica relevante en la enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA). Habitualmente se evalúan considerando los síntomas uno a uno. Pocos estudios van más allá del síntoma aislado e intentan un análisis de los trastornos de conducta en su conjunto. Nos proponemos evaluar los trastornos de conducta en la EA para identificar patrones que permitan su sistematización y clasificación. Pacientes y métodos. Evaluamos 90 pacientes consecutivos desde noviembre de 1997 a noviembre de 2000 con criterios NINCDS-ADRDA para demencia tipo Alzheimer probable o posible. Se han excluido los pacientes con clínica atípica. La evaluación clínica incluye el Inventario Neuropsiquiátrico (puntuaciones "crónicas"), Mini-Mental, RDRS-2 y CDR. Se ha efectuado análisis estadístico de agrupación de variables (análisis factorial, SPSS-Copyright). Resultados. Se obtiene una solución de tres factores, que pueden considerarse como síndromes de conducta: síndrome psicótico (alucinaciones, delirios), afectivo (depresión, euforia, ansiedad) y discontrol (agitación, irritabilidad, desinhibición). Una proporción importante de pacientes tiene trastornos de conducta escasos, sin alcanzar las características de los síndromes mencionados. Conclusión. Los trastornos de conducta en la EA pueden sistematizarse en cuatro grupos o síndromes. Nuestros resultados son congruentes y amplían los obtenidos en estudios previos efectuados con instrumentos y análisis estadístico distintos. Los estudios futuros deben dirigirse a definir mejor el amplio grupo de pacientes con trastornos de conducta escasos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;20(1): 9-16, ene.-feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036767</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Componentes principales del inventario neuropsiquiátrico en la enfermedad de Alzheimer: definición de síndromes de conducta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
