<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-26611</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of the spring fountain water in the basic healthcare area of Sigüenza, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Spring fountains undergo few or no analytical checks, especially those located far away from centers of population, which poses a health risk due to the possibility of disease-causing microorganisms and undesirable substances being in the water. This study is aimed at studying the spring contamination risk factors and determining the spring fountain water fitness for drinking. Method: A cross-sectional, descriptive study, with investigation of the frequency and spread of the contamination risk factors depending upon the developed or undeveloped location of the spring. Two analytical checks, conducted six months apart, of the physicochemical and microbiological parameters selected for assessing the fitness for drinking of the water of 38 fountains included in the study. Results: The most frequent contamination risk factors were: for fountains located in developed areas, grazing (53.8%), weeds (53.8%) and crossing wastewater (53.8%); for those located in undeveloped areas, grazing (72%), weeds (32%) and falling debris (32%). A total of 53.8% of the fountains located in developed areas and 60% of those in undeveloped areas were found fit for drinking in the first test; 76.9% and 68% having respectively been found fit in the second test. Solely 47.4% of the total were found fit for drinking in both of the tests. Microbiological contamination was found in 44.7% of the springs, and the physicochemical contamination in 13.1%. Conclusions: The contamination risk factors can have a bearing on a spring when sufficient protection is lacking, and the study thereof will provide keys as to the possibility and source of the contamination. When two analytical checks were made, there was a decrease in the percentage of fountains having water fit for drinking, which reveals the risk and susceptibility of these water supplies and the need and importance of regular health department checks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Las fuentes de manantial tienen un control analítico escaso o inexistente, especialmente las alejadas de los núcleos urbanos, lo que supone un riesgo sanitario por la posibilidad de la presencia en el agua de microorganismos patógenos y sustancias indeseables. El objetivo de este trabajo fue estudiar los factores de riesgo contaminante de los manantiales y determinar la potabilidad del agua de los mismos. Método: Estudio descriptivo transversal, con investigación de la frecuencia y distribución de los factores de riesgo contaminante según la ubicación urbana o rústica del manantial. Realización de dos controles analíticos, separados seis meses, de los parámetros fisicoquímicos y microbiológicos elegidos para evaluar la potabilidad del agua de 38 fuentes incluidas. Resultados: Los factores de riesgo contaminantes más frecuentes fueron: en fuentes urbanas pastoreo (53,8 por ciento), maleza (53,8 por ciento) y cruce con aguas residuales (53,8 por ciento); en rústicas pastoreo(72 por ciento), maleza (32 por ciento) y escorrentías(32 por ciento). Fueron potables en el primer control el 53,8 por ciento de fuentes urbanas y 60 por ciento de rústicas; en el segundo el 76,9 por ciento y 68 por ciento respectivamente. Sólo el 47,4 por ciento del total fueron potables en los dos controles. La contaminación microbiológica apareció en el 44,7 por ciento de manantiales y la físico-química en el 13,1 por ciento. Conclusiones: Los factores de riesgo contaminante pueden afectar un manantial ante la falta de protección suficiente, y su estudio proporcionará claves sobre la posibilidad y procedencia de la contaminación. Al realizar dos controles analíticos se produce una disminución del porcentaje de fuentes potables, lo que revela el riesgo y susceptibilidad de estos abastecimientos y la necesidad e importancia de controles sanitarios periódicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;77(3): 423-432, mayo 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad del agua de fuentes de manantial en la zona básicade salud de Sigüenza</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Hernández Vizcaino, Domiciano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas Veguillas, Jesús de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Muñoz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acevedo de Pedro, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, Rita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-26611</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23127</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
