<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122367</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of biofeedback intervention for the conservative management of post-prostatectomy urinary incontinence. A systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the effectiveness of biofeedback for the treatment of post-prostatectomy urinary incontinence. Materials and methods. A systematic review was conducted in the CENTRAL, Pubmed/MEDLINE, EMBASE and CINAHL data bases. Risk of bias in the studies included was assessed with the PEDro scale (Rating Quality of Randomized Controlled Trials). Study selection. Randomized controlled trials with adult patients diagnosed of post-prostatectomy urinary incontinence involving biofeedback for the conservative management were included. Results. Eight studies met the inclusion criteria. Biofeedback interventions included verbal and written instructions, electromyography and anal catheter. Conclusions. There is limited evidence supporting the effectiveness of biofeedback on the treatment of post-prostatectomy urinary incontinence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ocampo-Trujillo, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meneses-Echavez, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Vélez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la efectividad de las intervenciones con biofeedback en el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria posprostatectomía. Materiales y métodos. Se realizó una revisión sistemática en las bases de datos de CENTRAL, Pubmed/MEDLINE, EMBASE y CINAHL. El riesgo de sesgo en los estudios incluidos fue evaluado mediante la escala PEDro (Scale for Rating Quality of Randomized Controlled Trials). Selección de los estudios. Fueron incluidos ensayos controlados aleatorios, con pacientes adultos, con diagnóstico de incontinencia urinaria posprostatectomía que incorporaran el uso de biofeedback dentro del tratamiento conservador. Resultados. Ocho estudios cumplieron los criterios de inclusión. Las intervenciones con biofeedback incluyeron el uso de instrucciones verbales y escritas, electromiografía y sonda rectal. Conclusiones. Existe evidencia limitada a favor de la efectividad del biofeedback en el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria posprostatectomía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);48(2): 93-103, abr.-jum. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la intervención con biofeedback en el tratamiento conservador de la incontinencia urinaria posprostatectomía. Una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1700^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53821^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
