<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93582</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life assessment in patients with dementia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Quality of life (QoL) is one of the most important outcome variables in the study of the efficacy of interventions with people with dementia. However, its assessment is difficult 1) because it is a complex construct for which there is no unified theoretical or conceptual approach, and 2) because of the inherent difficulties in the cognitive impairments of the people under study. In this work different methods and instruments to this end are reviewed, and related findings are discussed. It is important to take into account the subjective view of the assessed person, as assessments done by proxies tend to underestimate QoL. In spite of the need for further development in this field, it is concluded that the instrument of choice is the QOL-AD, as it is change-sensitive, it correlates with health measurements, it is translated into several languages and it can be administered to people with low MMSE scores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hornillos Jerez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo López, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernaldo De Quirós Aragón, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gutiérrez, M. Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La calidad de vida (CV) es una de las variables resultado más importantes para estudiar la eficacia de intervenciones en personas con demencia. Sin embargo, su evaluación es difícil porque: a) este es un constructo complejo para el que no existe una aproximación teórica o conceptual unificada, y b) porque al tratarse de personas con deterioro cognitivo se complica enormemente la obtención de información fiable. En este trabajo se revisan diferentes métodos e instrumentos dirigidos a este fin. Es importante tener en cuenta la visión subjetiva de la propia persona evaluada pues las evaluaciones de personas próximas tienden a subestimar la CV. A pesar de que el campo necesita más desarrollo, se concluye que el instrumento de elección es el QOL-AD, por ser sensible al cambio, correlacionar con medidas de salud, estar traducido a varios idiomas y poder administrarse a personas con puntuaciones bajas en el MMSE(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);46(6): 319-324, nov.-dic.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93582</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la calidad de vida en personas con demencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
