<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056219</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The increasing proportion of elderly citizens        worldwide is leading to the development of a new        professional group of people who are specialized in        elderly personal care. They may have an increased        risk of occupational skin damage due to the characteristics        of their work that is often associated with        regular exposure to skin irritants and constant wetwork.        Skin disease studies within this group are rare.        Aims: The aim of this study was to describe and        analyse the characteristics and dermatologic diagnosis        of the patients that work taking care of elderly        people studied in our department.        Methods: We studied retrospectively all 41        patients who work as elder care-taker who attended        our department in a 11-year period.        Results: We found an absolute female predominance.        The most common location affected was the        hands. Of the skin diseases clinically diagnosed,        endogenous eczema showed the highest prevalence        (39,6%) followed by irritant contact dermatitis (ICD)        (27,1%), allergic contact dermatitis (ACD) (12,5%),        asymptomatic (10,4%), allergy to natural rubber        latex (NRL) (4,2%) and others.        Conclusions: Elderly care-taker workers are        emerging and they have a great social importance.        They are at increased risk of occupational skin disease        due to contact with several substances and wet        work. In our study, endogenous eczema, represented        by atopic dermatitis, is the most important diagnosis.        It could be concluded that irritants, occlusion and        wet work favoured the development of dermatitis in        vulnerable patients that would be remained asymptomatic        avoiding this work. New further studies are        needed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heras Mendazay, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Manzano, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Fernández, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde-Salazar Gómez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barchino Ortiz, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El progresivo envejecimiento de la población está        provocando el desarrollo como grupo profesional de        los cuidadores profesionales de ancianos, los auxiliares        de geriatría. Puede considerarse un grupo de riesgo        para el desarrollo de dermatosis ocupacional        debido a las características del trabajo que desempeñan,        con una regular exposición a irritantes cutáneos        y a trabajo húmedo. Los estudios centrados en la        patología cutánea de este colectivo son escasos.        Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio es describir        y analizar las características y los diagnósticos clínicos        dermatológicos de los pacientes que trabajan        como cuidadores de ancianos valorados en nuestro        servicio.        Material y métodos: Se ha llevado a cabo un estudio        observacional retrospectivo de los datos de 41        pacientes cuidadores de ancianos estudiados en nuestro        servicio durante un periodo de 11 años.        Resultados: Encontramos un predominio total de        mujeres. El lugar de afectación más frecuente fueron        las manos. Los diagnósticos más frecuentemente        establecidos fueron: Eczema endógeno (39,6%), dermatitis        de contacto irritativa (DCI) (27,1%), dermatitis        de contacto alérgica (DCA) (12,5%), Sin lesiones        (10,4%), urticaria de contacto al látex (4,2%) y otros.        Conclusiones: El colectivo de cuidadores de        ancianos es un grupo en aumento y de gran importancia        social. Al desempeñar una labor que implica un        trabajo húmedo se debe considerar un grupo de riesgo        para el desarrollo de dermatosis profesionales. En        nuestro estudio destaca que el diagnóstico de eczema        endógeno, representado por la dermatitis atópica, sea        el más frecuente, explicándose esto porque una irritación        provocada por un trabajo húmedo y la oclusión        pueden desencadenar un eczema en el individuo con        un fondo atópico, que en otras condiciones se habría        mantenido latente. Son necesarios futuros estudios        más extensos en este sector profesional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;53(207): 35-46, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056219</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatosis profesionales en cuidadores de ancianos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5991</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30939^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30939^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
