<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055196</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prescription and type of exercise recommended for patients with diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Regular physical exercise is recommended as one of the most important    aspects in the treatment of diabetes mellitus. In the case of    the diabetic patient, the correct prescription of physical exercise is    essential to maximize the benefits, while decreasing the risks associated    with each type of activity. This prescription must be fractionated    to focus on the different components of physical performance,    such as cardiorespiratory fitness, muscle strength-resistance training    and flexibility. Traditionally, cardiorespiratory fitness exercises have    been those most often prescribed in the treatment of diabetes. They    include aerobic activities such as walking, running or swimming for    20 to 60 minutes, three to five times a week. The intensity should be    moderate-to-low to ensure the best balance between benefits and    risks. In recent years, muscle strength-resistance exercises, performed    two or three times a week, have been shown to be effective    and safe in the treatment of diabetes. These exercises require training    and mo nitoring on an individual basis to avoid risks. In addition,    stretching exercises should be carried out before and after each exercise    session to enhance flexibility</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Novials, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La práctica habitual de ejercicio físico se recomienda como uno de    los pilares básicos en el tratamiento de la diabetes mellitus. En el    caso del paciente con diabetes, es imprescindible una correcta prescripción    del ejercicio físico, que intentará conseguir los mayores beneficios    posibles así como disminuir el riesgo asociado a cada tipo    de actividad. Esta prescripción debe fraccionarse para poder incidir    sobre los distintos elementos de la condición física a trabajar: la resistencia    cardiorrespiratoria, la fuerza-resistencia muscular y la flexibilidad.    Los ejercicios de resistencia cardiorrespiratoria han sido tradicionalmente    prioritarios en el tratamiento de la diabetes. Se    incluyen aquellas actividades de carácter aeróbico como caminar,    correr o nadar, realizadas en 3-5 sesiones semanales de 20 a 60    minutos. Se recomendarán intensidades moderadas o bajas, pues    son las que ofrecen un mejor balance entre beneficios y riesgos. En    los últimos años, los ejercicios de fuerza-resistencia muscular han    demostrado su efectividad y seguridad en el tratamiento de la diabetes,    por lo que serán incluidos en 2-3 sesiones semanales; con el    fin de evitar riesgos, el paciente deberá realizar un aprendizaje y una    monitorización personalizada de los ejercicios prescritos. Como    complemento, se realizarán trabajos de flexibilidad antes y después    de cada sesión de actividad física mediante la ejecución de ejercicios    de estiramiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;23(1): 33-39, ene.-feb. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055196</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prescripción y tipo de ejercicio físico recomendado para pacientes con diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15057^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
