<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95027</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biopsychosocial evaluation in patients with breast cancer surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The versatility in surgical therapy of breast cancer, requires the identification of differences in psychological impact. Thus, psychological interventions should be closely associated with the results form investigations to identify training needs. The sample of this study consists of 438 women diagnosed with breast cancer gene mutation carriers undergoing surgery. The dependent variables studied were sociodemographic and medical, anxiety-depression (HADS), quality of life (QLQ-C30), quality of life in breast cancer (QLQ-BR23) and body image (BIS). The results of this study are similar to those proposed in the current literature in this area of knowledge. Patients undergoing radical surgery had a higher level of anxiety symptoms and worse body image. Women who received reconstructive surgery, however, showed better quality of life levels, both overall and in the scale of emotion. Women who underwent conservative surgery showed higher levels in the scale of the role of quality of life. Finally, women undergoing prophylactic surgery had higher scores on symptoms as fatigue, pain, symptoms in the breast and arm, the worst levels on role and social scales, and greater sexual enjoyment. Surgeries involving the use of prosthesis (prophylactic and restorative), were used in younger women, showing higher levels of anxiety and better sexual functioning,. Patients who received medical treatment before the actual surgery, had more side effects, worse body image and a higher number of radicals surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Román, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Arazaru</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, María Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dolores Martín, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La versatilidad en la terapéutica quirúrgica oncológica de la patología mamaria, obliga a identificar las diferencias en cuanto a la repercusión psicológica. Por ende, las intervenciones psicológicas  deberían estar estrechamente de las investigaciones en identificación de necesidades. La muestra del presente trabajo está constituida por 438 mujeres diagnosticadas de cáncer de mama o portadoras de mutación genética en fase quirúrgica. Las variables dependientes estudiadas fueron: socio demográficas y médicas, ansiedad- depresión (HADS), calidad de vida (QLQ-C30), calidad de vida en mama (QLQ-BR23) e imagen corporal (BIS). Los resultados que de este trabajo se derivan son similares a los propuestos en la literatura actual en esta área de conocimiento. Las pacientes sometidas a cirugía radical presentaron un nivel más elevado de síntomas de ansiedad y una peor imagen corporal. Las mujeres que recibieron cirugía reconstructiva, por el contrario, presentaron mejores niveles en calidad de vida, tanto global, como en la escala de emoción. A las mujeres que se les practicó cirugía conservadora mostraron mejores niveles en la escala de rol de calidad de vida. Por último, las mujeres sometidas a la cirugía profiláctica, presentaron mayores puntuaciones en síntomas como fatiga, dolor, síntomas en la mama y el brazo, peores niveles en las escalas de rol y social, y mayor disfrute sexual. Las cirugías que implican el uso de prótesis (profilácticos y de reparadora), fueron utilizadas en mujeres más jóvenes, mostrando mayores niveles de ansiedad y mejor funcionamiento sexual. Los pacientes que recibieron tratamiento médico previo al quirúrgico actual, presentaron más efectos secundarios, peor imagen corporal y presentaban mayor número de cirugías radicales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);7(1): 81-92, jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95027</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración biopsicosocial en pacientes con patología mamaria oncológica quirúrgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
