<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82226</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tako Tsubo&#146;s syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Tako Tsubo syndrome or transient apical dyskinesia syndrome was first described in Japan in the 1990s1. Is a rare condition 1% of all the patients with suspicion of acute coronary syndrome2. It generally appears in post menopausal women with few cardiovascular risk factors3. It is characterized by anginal chest pain, electrocardiographic changes, elevation of the enzymes of myocardial injury2, no coronary obstruction on angiography and a characteristic left ventricular antero apical dyskinesia that recovers to normal in a few days4. Severe emotional stress is the most common trigger for this syndrome5. The aethiopatogenesis of this syndrome has yet to be defined(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Llanos, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alonso, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hernández, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río Cordovés, Irene del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Tako Tsubo (STS) o síndrome de disquinesia apical transitoria (SDAT) se describió por primera vez en la década de los noventa en Japón1. Es una entidad poco frecuente cercana al 1% de todos los pacientes con sospecha de síndrome coronario agudo (SCA)2. Generalmente afecta a mujeres postmenopaúsicas con pocos factores de riesgo cardiovascular (FRCV)3. Se caracteriza por dolor precordial anginoso, cambios electrocardiográficos, elevación de las enzimas de daño miocárdico2, ausencia de obstrucción coronaria en la angiografía y una característica disquinesia antero apical del ventrículo izquierdo que se normaliza en unos pocos días4. El estrés emocional severo es el desencadenante más común5. La etiopatogénesis de este síndrome está aún por definir(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;3(2): 127-130, jun.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82226</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Tako Tsubo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52615^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31983^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52615^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31983^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31983^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
