<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-34508</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epilepsy beginning in the neonatal period and early infancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. In this study we analyse several epileptic syndromes that begin in the neonatal period or early infancy, up to two years of age, and we also define their clinical, neurophysiological and progressive aspects as well as their differential diagnoses. Both neonatal and febrile convulsions are excluded. Development. The different syndromes are classified according to the predominant type of seizures, which is the one that identifies them, although it is not the only type of seizure presented. In line with this reasoning, the syndromes were divided into four main groups: 1. Epileptic spasms: infantile spasms (West's syndrome), periodic spasms as described by Gobbi and bouts of epileptic seizures without hypsarrhythmia. 2. Tonic seizures: Lennox-Gastaut syndrome. 3. Myoclonias: benign myoclonic epilepsy in infancy, Dravet&#146;s severe myoclonic epilepsy, myoclonic-astatic epilepsy and a myoclonic state in non-progressive encephalopathies; and 4. Partial seizures: non-idiopathic location-related epilepsies, malign epilepsy with migratory partial seizures and benign infantile familial and non-familial seizures. Conclusions. Thus, it will be possible to establish a plan of studies, differential diagnoses and a rational therapeutic approach depending on the clinical manifestations, while at the same even enabling us to distinguish between the idiopathic, cryptogenic and symptomatic forms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. En este trabajo se analizan diversos síndromes epilépticos de comienzo en la lactancia y la infancia temprana, hasta los 2 años, y se definen sus aspectos clínicos, neurofisiológicos y evolutivos, así como sus diagnósticos diferenciales. Se excluyen las convulsiones neonatales y las convulsiones febriles. Desarrollo. Los diferentes síndromes se clasifican de acuerdo al tipo de crisis predominante, por la cual se los reconoce, aunque no sea el único tipo de episodios presente en los mismos. De acuerdo con este razonamiento, se han dividido en cuatro grandes grupos: 1. espasmos epilépticos -espasmos infantiles (síndrome de West), espasmos periódicos de Gobbi y espasmos epilépticos en salvas sin hipsarritmia-; 2. crisis tónicas -síndrome de Lennox-Gastaut-; 3. mioclonías -epilepsia mioclónica benigna de la infancia, epilepsia mioclónica grave de Dravet, epilepsia mioclonicoastática y estado mioclónico en encefalopatías no progresivas-, y 4. crisis parciales -epilepsias no idiopáticas relacionadas con la localización, epilepsia maligna con convulsiones parciales migratrices y convulsiones familiares y no familiares infantiles benignas-. Conclusión. De acuerdo con las manifestaciones clínicas se podrá plantear un plan de estudios, diagnósticos diferenciales y un abordaje terapéutico racional, y se pueden incluso diferenciar las formas idiopáticas, criptogénicas y sintomáticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(3): 251-262, ago. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epilepsias de comienzo en la lactancia y la infancia temprana</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Ruggieri, VL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-34508</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30333</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30326</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
