<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119336</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptive disorder: effectiveness of psychotherapeutic support in the early phases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Adaptive disorders are one of the most common psychopathology problems today with a high prevalence in sick leave, which brings high social and economic costs. During in 2011, were recorded in our organization, processes in which 547 were on sick leave for common disease (IDC-9 300, 309 and 311). The average duration for of all of them were for 179 days. Our study has evaluated the effectiveness of psychological support during the beginning of their sick leave due to such processes. This has made an analytical (cause-effect), prospective, longitudinal, experimental study in a twelve months period, on a sample of 73 patients, with the aim to improve the patient&#146;s attention and reduce the duration of temporary disability through a support psychotherapeutic plan (Cognitive-Behavioral Therapy) during the early stages with adaptive disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Muñoz, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noales Asensio, Ana Belen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos adaptativos son uno de los problemas psicopatológicos más frecuentes hoy día, con una alta prevalencia en bajas laborales, lo que ocasiona elevados costes sociales y económicos. Durante el año 2011, se registraron en nuestra organización, 547 procesos de baja laboral por contingencia común (CIE-9 300, 309 y 311). La duración media de los mismos fue de 179 días. Nuestro estudio ha valorado la efectividad del apoyo psicológico en los primeros momentos de las bajas laborales debidas a este tipo de procesos. Para ello se ha realizado un estudio analítico (causa-efecto), longitudinal, prospectivo y experimental en un período de 12 meses, sobre una muestra de 73 pacientes, con el objetivo de mejorar la atención del paciente y reducir la duración de los procesos de incapacidad temporal mediante un plan de apoyo psicoterapéutico (terapia cognitivo-conductual) en fases tempranas de trastornos adaptativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;22(4): 208-215, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119336</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno adaptativo: efectividad del apoyo psicoterapeutico en fases tempranas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d282^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
