<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70840</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">University is the first choice of many people with disability when finishing Secondary Education. They don&#146;t only look for professional training but personal fulfillment. The access to the university buildings plays a fundamental role in the integration of students with disability, being necessary to adapt and eliminate architectural obstacles. Starting with that idea, the descriptive study presented in this article has been carried out, where the physical access is evaluated in the University of Málaga through analyzing the architectural obstacles in eleven educational institutions, those affecting the physically and sensory disabled persons. Such investigation has been carried out with the objective of sitting down the bases for a future investigation. The description the current characteristics of the situation is also the first step to future investigation and experience in the field of accessibility in the university studies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Pérez, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Parra, Diego Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Infante, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Universidad es la opción elegida por muchas personas con discapacidad al término de la Educación Secundaria, buscando con ello, no sólo una formación profesional sino también, un enriquecimiento personal. En la integración de los estudiantes con discapacidad juega un papel fundamental la accesibilidad física en los edificios universitarios, siendo necesaria la adaptación y eliminación de las barreras arquitectónicas. Partiendo de esta idea, se ha realizado el estudio descriptivo presentado en este artículo, donde se evalúa la accesibilidad física en la Universidad de Málaga, analizando las barreras arquitectónicas en 11 edificios docentes, tanto aquellas que afectan a las personas con discapacidad motora, como las que afectan a las personas con discapacidad sensorial. Dicha investigación se ha realizado con el objetivo de sentar las bases para una futura intervención, al describir las características de la situación actual, pretendiendo además, ser un primer paso a futuros proyecto y experiencias en el campo de la accesibilidad en la Universidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;14(2): 209-222, mayo-ago. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70840</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1111</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13035^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14893^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
