<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164787</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Actual concept of the pathogenesis of the periimplantitis and the role that bacterial have</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">With the intention of clarifaying the current concept of the pathogenesis of the periimplantitis and the implications that bacteria could have in it, an extensive literature review has been made. Till the date, different longuitudinal and cross-sectional studies have identified some of the periimplantitis risk factors or risk indicators. Factors as history of periodontitis, diabetes, genetic traits, poor oral hygiene, smoking, alcohol consumption, absence of keratinized mucosa and implant surface have been analyzed in detail.  The colonization of the surgical implanted new surfaces act as a risky situation for partial edentulous patients, where periodontopathogenic bacteria of the residual pocket have and important role (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Vigón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Mendoza, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A través de una extensa revisión de la literatura, nuestro objetivo será esclarecer el concepto actual que existe sobre la patogénesis de la periimplantitis, así como las implicaciones que pueden tener las bacterias sobre la misma. Hasta la fecha diferentes estudios longitudinales y transversales han identificado algunos de los factores de riesgo o indicadores de riesgo de la periimplantitis.  Historia previa de enfermedad periodontal, diabetes, carga genética, pobre higiene oral, tabaco, consumo de alcohol, ausencia de encía queratinizada y la superficie de los implantes son algunos de factores que han sido analizados en detalle en la literatura.  La colonización de nuevas superficies implantadas quirúrgicamente suponen una situación de riesgo en pacientes parcialmente edéntulos, donde las bacterias periodontopatógenas de la bolsa residual tienen un importante papel (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;29(1): 31-42, abr. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concepto actual de la patogénesis de la periimplantitis y el papel que ocupan las bacterias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53959^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
