<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92397</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Confabulations (II): Explicative models</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Confabulations, or the production of false memories without deliberate intent to lie, is an intriguing phenomenon for which an attempt has been made to explain it since they were first described. Confabulations are a good example for illustrating there constructive character of memory. Nevertheless, their exact nature and the way in which they are produced are still controversial. Objective. To review the different models proposed to explain the appearance of confabulations. Development. Neuropsychological models that currently have some theoretical development and empirical evidence are reviewed. In addition, a brief reference to motivational models, that have recently begun to recover popularity, are presented. We conclude by presenting the last version of the strategic retrieval model that makes it possible to integrate the relevant elements from the others. Conclusions. Early models of confabulations, which considered them a result of the need to fill memory gaps, are outdated nowadays. Nevertheless, emotional processes are taken into account to explain their content. From neuropsychological approaches, it is possible to distinguish models that consider confabulation as a result of a temporal or contextual problem, and those which consider that the main problem is on the memory retrieval process. More specifically, the strategic retrieval hypothesis states that confabulations are the result of a dysfunction in a complex system of monitoring the recovered information. This model would make it possible to integrate explanations and evidences coming from the other proposals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorente-Rovira, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrios, German E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villagrán-Moreno, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>McKenna, Peter J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moro-Ipola, Micaela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las confabulaciones o la producción de falsos recuerdos, sin la intención de mentir de forma deliberada, resultan un fenómeno intrigante que se ha intentado explicar desde que fueran descritas por primera vez. El fenómeno de las confabulaciones es un buen ejemplo del carácter reconstructivo de la memoria, sin embargo, aún es controvertida su naturaleza exacta y la forma en que se producen. Objetivo. Revisar los diferentes modelos propuestos para explicar la aparición de confabulaciones. Desarrollo. Se revisan los modelos neuropsicológicos que en la actualidad cuentan con cierto desarrollo teórico y evidencia empírica. También se hace referencia a modelos motivacionales, que han empezado a recuperar su popularidad recientemente, para terminar desarrollando la última versión del modelo de recuperación estratégica, que permite integrar los elementos relevantes de los otros. Conclusiones. Los primeros modelos sobre confabulaciones, que las consideraban resultado de la necesidad de rellenar lagunas de memoria, están hoy día superados, aunque los elementos emocionales se están teniendo en cuenta para explicar su contenido. Dentro de la neuropsicología, podríamos distinguir aquellos modelos que consideran la confabulación como resultado de un problema temporal o contextual, y aquellos que ponen el problema en los procesos de recuperación de la memoria. En concreto la hipótesis de recuperación estratégica plantea que las confabulaciones son el resultado de una disfunción de complejos sistemas de monitorización de la información recuperada. Este modelo permitiría integrar explicaciones y evidencias procedentes de otras propuestas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;39(6): 384-392, nov.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92397</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Confabulaciones (II): Modelos explicativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12374</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
