<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88850</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Partial jejunal volvulus due to a mesenteric cystic lymphangioma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mesenteric cysts are unusual benign tumours thatinclude lymphangioma. Their clinical presentation is variable and acute symptoms can be produced due to complications. This tumour appears especially in childhood, and its prognosis after surgical removal is excellent. We present the case of a 15 year old female patient with symptoms of postprandial abdominal pain and palpation of smooth mass in hypogastrium. Radiological studies showed a big polilobular mass of cystic substance that included a portion of jejune within complete volvulus. The treatment was the removal of the cyst and a je junal portion and the pathological diagnosis was mesenteric cyst lymphangioma. The patient is asymptomatic more than three years after the intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escalante, B. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivera, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Val-Carreres, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castiella, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morandeira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los quistes mesentéricos son tumoraciones benignas poco frecuentes entre las que se encuentran los linfangiomas. Su presentación clínica es variable y pueden producir síntomas agudos debido a complicaciones. Se diagnostican sobre todo en edad pediátrica y su pronóstico, tras exéresis completa, suele ser excelente. Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 15 años con dolor abdominal postprandial y palpación de masa blanda en hipogastrio. Los estudios radiológicos mostraron una gran masa polilobulada de contenido quístico que englobaba un asa de yeyuno con volvulación incompleta. El tratamiento fue la exéresis del quiste y del asa de yeyuno y el diagnóstico anatomopatológico fue de linfangiomaquístico mesentérico. La paciente está asintomática después de más de 3 años de la intervención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;33(3): 323-326, sept.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88850</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vólvulo yeyunal incompleto por linfangioma quístico mesentérico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8816^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8816^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38048^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13667^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31330^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31330^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31330^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13667^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8816^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13667^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
