<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76157</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use and maintenance of a peripheral venous catheter for more than three days</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of vascular access in a frequent procedure in the field of hospital practice. Nonetheless, vascular access is not bereft of complications, phlebitis being the most common. Following the Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommendations, in our internal medicine service, changing a peripheral venous catheter is systematically carried out every 48-72 hours. The objective of this present study is to evaluate the need to change the vein accessed systematically every 48-72 hours, following the Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommendations, in those patients who have a catheter inserted in a peripheral vein blocked by the administration of medication as part of the treatment of their pathology; or to evaluate the need to establish a new operational protocol since, according to other studies, its utility has not been demonstrated in a convincing manner. As a final conclusion, and while awaiting the results obtained in this study, the authors believe it is possible to amplify the established periods for changing peripheral venous catheters while guaranteeing the security and comfort of patients having peripheral venous catheters inserted(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>César Sola, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virto Pejenaute, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Abad, M. Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Aizpun, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban Fernández, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcés Tapia, Amaya</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilización de accesos vasculares es un procedimiento frecuente en el ámbito de la práctica hospitalaria. Sin embargo no está exento de complicaciones, siendo la flebitis la más frecuente. Siguiendo las recomendaciones del Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), en nuestra unidad el cambio de catéter venoso periférico (CPV), se realiza de forma sistemática cada 48-72 horas. El objetivo del presente estudio es valorar la necesidad de cambio de vía de forma sistemática cada 48-72 horas según las recomendaciones del CDC, en aquellos pacientes a los que se les coloca una vía periférica obturada para la administración de medicación como tratamiento de su patología; o evaluar la necesidad de establecer un nuevo protocolo de actuación ya que, según otros estudios, no se ha demostrado de forma convincente su utilidad. Como conclusión final, y a la vista de los resultados obtenidos en el estudio, creemos posible ampliar los plazos establecidos para el cambio de CVP garantizando la seguridad y confortabilidad del paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;32(5): 326-330, mayo 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76157</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mantenimiento del Catéter Venoso Periférico (CPV) durante más de tres días</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4948^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4948^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9905^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11757^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11757^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
