<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83284</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inflammatory Response of Rapid Onset Asthma Exacerbation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The association between onset of asthma exacerbation and the inflammatory response has not been sufficiently studied.ObjectiveTo determine the differential mechanisms of the rapid onset (RO) asthma exacerbation.MethodsWe designed a prospective, multicentre study that included 34 patients who suffered from asthma exacerbation. They were distributed into three groups of asthmatics, depending of the time of onset: from 0 to 24h, from 25 to 144h and more than 145h. We collected clinical data, sputum, blood and urine samples when first seen at the clinic and the next 24h later, and differential cell counts and biomarkers were determinedResultsThe asthmatics who suffered a RO exacerbation showed a higher elastase concentration, (1.028±1.140; 310±364; 401±390ng/ml) (P&lt;0.05) and albumin (46.2±4.3; 42±3.4; 39.9±4.8g/l) (P&lt;0.05) in the blood sample. Neutrophils, eosinophils (blood or sputum), eosinophil cationic protein (ECP) (blood), interleukin 8 (IL8) (blood) and leukotriene E4 (LTE4) (urine) were high in the three groups (P&gt;0.05). We demonstrated an association between the onset of exacerbation and the severity of obstruction (FEV1) (r=&amp;#8722;0.360; P=0.037), eosinophils in sputum (r=&amp;#8722;0.399; P=0.029), albumin (r=&amp;#8722;0.442; P=0.013), and IL8 in sputum (r=0.357; P=0.038).ConclusionsThe results suggest a rapid inflammatory response, both neutrophilic and eosinophilic, in the asthmatic exacerbation. However, the swelling in the bronchi may play an important role in the initial inflammatory response in the exacerbations depending of time of onset(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Picado, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Brú, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrejón, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido-Casado, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perpiñá, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bardagí, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaza, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No se ha estudiado suficientemente la asociación entre la rapidez de instauración de la crisis de asma y la respuesta inflamatoria desencadenada.ObjetivoDeterminar los mecanismos inflamatorios que caracterizan la exacerbación asmática de instauración rápida.MétodoSe diseñó un estudio prospectivo y multicéntrico en los servicios de urgencias hospitalarias, que evaluó a 34 pacientes que se distribuyeron en tres grupos en función de las horas de instauración de la exacerbación asmática: (menos de 24h), instauración intermedia (25&#150;144h), e instauración lenta (145 o más horas). Se recogieron datos clínicos, de esputo, sangre y orina en el momento de la primera atención y pasadas 24h, determinándose celularidad inflamatoria y marcadores solubles.ResultadosLos pacientes con exacerbación rápida presentaron una significativa mayor concentración de elastasa (1.028±1.140; 310±364; 401±390ng/ml) y albúmina (46,2± 4,3; 42±3,4; 39,9±4,8g/l) en sangre. El número de neutrófilos, eosinófilos, (tanto en sangre como en esputo), los niveles de proteína catiónica del eosinófilo (PCE) (sangre), interleuquina 8 (IL8) (sangre) y leucotrieno E4 (LTE4) (orina) estaban elevadas en los tres grupos (p&gt;0,05). Se constataron asociaciones lineales entre el tiempo de instauración de la exacerbación y la intensidad de la obstrucción (FEV1) (r=&amp;#8722;0,360; p=0,037), los eosinófilos en esputo (r=&amp;#8722;0,399; p=0,029), la albúmina (r=&amp;#8722;0,442; p=0,013); y con la IL8 (r=0,357; p=0,038).ConclusionesLos resultados sugieren una activación precoz de la respuesta neutrofílica y eosinofílica en la exacerbación asmática. No obstante, es posible que el edema bronquial juegue un papel importante en la respuesta inicial inflamatoria de las exacerbaciones dependiendo del tiempo de instauración(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;46(11): 587-593, nov. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83284</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta inflamatoria de la exacerbación asmática de instauración rápida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13610^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22673^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4884^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9692^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
