<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158164</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of diabetes education on type 1 diabetes mellitus control in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Diabetes education is an essential tool to achieve treatment objectives in type1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM). The aim of this study was to determine if understanding of diabetes by caregivers/patients or sociodemographic factors affect blood glucose control in children and adolescents with T1DM. Patients and methods: The level of knowledge of 105 caregivers of children and adolescents with T1DM was assessed using a survey adapted to the type of treatment used (multiple dose insulin [MDI] or continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion [CSII]). Mean HbA1c levels in the previous year was considered as metabolic control marker. Results: Mean HbA1c levels were similar in both treatment groups, with slightly higher values in children over 12years of age. Patients on CSII had a longer time since disease onset and had poorer results, maybe because the items were more difficult due to the higher level of knowledge required for this treatment modality (P=.005). Caregivers with lower educational levels achieved poorer scores in the survey, but mean HbA1c levels of their children were lower, probably because of their greater involvement in disease care. Conclusions: The level of knowledge of caregivers and/or patients with T1DM was high, and this was associated to good metabolic control. Studies to assess the impact of caregiver knowledge on metabolic control of children are needed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Martín, Daniel E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yelmo Valverde, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roldán Martín, M Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Castellanos, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Frías, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Blanco, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Gómez, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En la diabetes mellitus tipo1 (DM1) la educación diabetológica es fundamental para lograr los objetivos de tratamiento. El objetivo de este estudio es determinar si el nivel de conocimientos diabetológicos de cuidadores/pacientes o los factores sociodemográficos afectan al control glucémico de niños y adolescentes con DM1. Pacientes y métodos: Se analiza el nivel de conocimientos de 105 cuidadores de niños y adolescentes con DM1 o de los pacientes adolescentes mediante una encuesta adaptada a la modalidad de tratamiento (múltiples dosis de insulina [MDI] o bomba de infusión subcutánea continua de insulina [ISCI]). Se considera la HbA1c media en el último año como marcador del control metabólico. Resultados: La media de HbA1c fue similar en ambos grupos de tratamiento (6,6±0,5 para MDI y 6,5±0,5% para ISCI, p=0,63), siendo discretamente más alta en niños mayores de 12años. Los pacientes con bomba tenían un mayor tiempo de evolución de la diabetes y obtuvieron peores resultados porque además la exigencia teórica de la encuesta fue superior por la mayor complejidad de manejo (p=0,005). Los cuidadores con nivel de estudios más bajos obtuvieron peores puntuaciones, si bien las cifras de HbA1c de sus hijos fueron más bajas, en probable relación con una mayor dedicación al cuidado de la enfermedad. Conclusiones: El nivel de conocimientos analizados fue alto, y esto se asoció con un buen control metabólico. Son necesarios estudios que evalúen la influencia de los conocimientos de los cuidadores en pacientes con diferentes grados de control metabólico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(10): 536-542, dic. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158164</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la educación diabetológica en el control de la diabetes mellitus tipo 1 en la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
