<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144628</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of generic skills in graduates of Medical Technology, University of Talca, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Generic skills refer to professional performance components linked to interpersonal relationships and attitudes that can be developed through education. The University of Talca defined a fundamental line of training aimed at developing generic skills, dividing them into instrumental, interpersonal and those related to active citizenship. In this paper, we seek to determine the level in which university graduates actually acquired these competences, through a survey applied to graduates themselves and their employers. Subjects and methods. Thirty-one subjects participated in a total of 56 graduates of Medical Technology under the model curriculum &#145;competency-based education&#146; and seven employers. This survey was based on performance indicators corresponding to the five generic competences declared in the professional profile. The results were analyzed by categories related to the achievement of competencies, expressed as a percentage. Results. It was found that in four out of five competences, over 70% of graduates consider to have attained them in a high/very high degree, while over 70% of employers pointed out that all five are demonstrated in this category. Conclusion. The results show that the curriculum has been successful in developing the competencies declared thus offering a comprehensive professional training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maldonado-Rojas, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo-Urrizola, Paulina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Urrutia, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal-Flores, Sylvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las competencias genéricas se refieren a componentes del desempeño profesional que se vinculan a relaciones interpersonales y actitudes que pueden ser cultivadas en la formación. La Universidad de Talca ha definido una línea de formación orientada al desarrollo de éstas, divididas en dos competencias instrumentales, dos interpersonales y una ciudadana. El objetivo fue conocer, a través de egresados y empleadores, el nivel de logro de estas competencias. Sujetos y métodos. Participaron 31 sujetos de un total de 56 egresados de tecnología médica bajo el modelo del rediseño curricular &#145;educación basada en competencias&#146; y siete empleadores de un total de 11. Se aplicaron encuestas consultando por desempeños de las cinco competencias genéricas declaradas por la universidad para todos sus egresados. Los resultados fueron analizados por categorías y expresados en porcentaje que refieren al logro de las competencias. Resultados. Se encontró que para cuatro de cinco competencias, cerca del 70% de los egresados señalan haberlas alcanzado en un grado alto/muy alto, en tanto sobre el 70% de los empleadores señalan que las cinco competencias son demostradas en esa categoría. Conclusión. Los resultados demuestran que el currículo de formación estaría desarrollando las competencias declaradas, lo que permite la formación de un profesional integral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);18(5): 353-359, sept.-oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de competencias genéricas en egresados de tecnología médica de la Universidad de Talca, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29563^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6432^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9975^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
