<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036839</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-3465</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New advances in the Human Papillomavirus (HPV) vaccines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives: To describe cervical cancer epidemiology, its  association with human papiloma virus (HPV), and to know the present situation of HPV vaccines. Methods: We consulted some electronic data bases (Medline, The Cochrane Library, EMBASE, etc), web sites from Doyma, National Cancer Institute, etc, and the abstracts of 21ª Papillomavirus Internacional Conference Epidemiology: HPV infection is the main cause of cervical cancer. Cervical cancer is the second malignant  tumour. About 470.000 cases of this illness are diagnosed every year and 230.000 women die all over the world. Vaccines: Three types of HPV vaccines are in study: prophylactic, therapeutic and combined. The prophylactic vaccines are in phase III. The different studies have demonstrated that all of the mare sure, well tolerated and highly inmunogenicity, and specially, the vaccine bivalent VLP HPV-16/18.There are multiple strategies designed for the development of therapeutics vaccines. Some of the mare in phase I and phase II. They a sure vaccines, though the results of the inmunogenicity are not conclusive. Finally, the combined (prophylactic - therapeutic)vaccines also are in phase I and II. There has been demonstrated that they are well tolerated and immunogenicity before the lack of information on the clinical response that it unleashes. With all probability, the prophylactic vaccines soon will be available and with it one will manage to reduce significantly the effect of cervical cancer in the whole world</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palomo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Losana, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Describir la situación actual del cáncer de cérvix, su relación con el Virus del Papiloma Humano (VPH), y conocer el estado actual de las vacunas profilácticas y terapéuticas frente al VPH. Metodología: Se consultaron algunas bases de datos electrónicas (Medline, The Cochrane Library, EMBASE, etc), páginas web (Doyma, National Cancer Institute, etc) y los abstracts de la 21ª Conferencia Internacional del Virus del Papiloma Humano. Epidemiología: La infección por el VPH es la principal causa del cáncer cervical. Éste es el segundo cáncer femenino más frecuente de todo el mundo. Cada año se estima que se producen 470.000 casos nuevos en todo el mundo y 230.000 muertes por esta causa. Vacunas: Se encuentran en estudio tres tipos de vacunas frente al VPH: profilácticas, terapéuticas y combinadas. Las vacunas profilácticas se encuentran en fase III. Los distintos estudios han demostrado que todas ellas son seguras, bien toleradas y altamente inmunógenas, y especialmente, la vacuna bivalente VLPVPH-16/18. Son múltiples las estrategias diseñadas para el desarrollo de vacunas terapéuticas. Algunas de ellas, ya se encuentran en fase I y fase II. Se tratan de vacunas seguras, aunque los resultados sobre su inmunogenicidad no son concluyentes. Por último, las vacunas combinadas (profilácticas-terapéuticas) también se encuentran en fase I y II. Se ha demostrado que son bien toleradas e inmunogénasante la falta de datos sobre la respuesta clínica que desencadena. Con toda probabilidad, las vacunas profilácticas pronto estarán disponibles y con ello se conseguirá reducir significativamente la incidencia de cáncer cervical en todo el mundo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediátrika (Madr.);25(4): 169-180, abr. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036839</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos avances en las vacunas frente al Virus del Papiloma Humano (VPH)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23826^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23126^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30985^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
