<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144364</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Further validity evidence of the Behavioral Inhibition Observation System (BIOS)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The Behavioral Inhibition Observation System (BIOS) is a brief clinician-report scale for detecting behavioral inhibition (BI) from direct observation. This study aims to compare the validity coefficients obtained in the natural context of use of the BIOS (i.e., a clinical situation) with those obtained using the BIOS after standardized observation. Method: The participants were 74 randomly selected preschool children who were exposed to systematic observation. Results: The results indicate excellent internal consistency (&amp;#945; = .91) and moderate to good inter-rater reliability for all items (ICC from .55 to .88). The correlations with observational measures of BI ranged from .40 to .70, and were mostly equivalent to those of the previous study. The correlations with parents&#146;, teachers&#146;, and clinicians&#146; measures of BI and related constructs ranged from .30 to .60, and were also equivalent to those obtained in the natural context of use of the BIOS (i.e., clinical situation). Conclusions: The validity coefficients obtained with the BIOS in a non-structured natural observation are mostly equivalent to those obtained in an experimental situation, thus supporting that the BIOS is a cost-efficient instrument for measuring BI from observation in a clinical situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riba Lloret, Maria Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballespí Sola, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jané Ballabriga, Maria Claustre</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El Protocolo de Observación de la Inhibición Conductual (BIOS) es una breve escala para clínicos destinada a detectar la inhibición conductual (behavioral inhibition o BI) mediante observación directa. El objetivo de este estudio es comparar los coeficientes de validez obtenidos en el contexto natural de aplicación del BIOS (i.e., en situación clínica) con los obtenidos al utilizar el BIOS tras una observación estandarizada. Método: Los participantes fueron 74 preescolares seleccionados aleatoriamente y expuestos a observación sistemática. Resultados: Los resultados indican una excelente consistencia interna (&amp;#945;=.91) y fiabilidad inter-jueces de moderada a buena para todos los ítems (ICC de .55 a .88). Las correlaciones con medidas observacionales de BI oscilaron entre .40 y .70 y en su mayoría fueron equivalentes a las del estudio anterior. Las correlaciones con las medidas de BI y constructos afines de padres, maestros y clínicos oscilaron entre .30 y .60 y también fueron equivalentes a las obtenidas en el contexto natural de uso del BIOS (i.e., en situación clínica). Conclusiones: Los coeficientes de validez obtenidos con el BIOS en observación natural no estructurada son mayoritariamente equivalentes a los obtenidos en situación experimental, demostrando así que el BIOS es un instrumento coste-eficiente para medir BI a partir de la observación en situación clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);27(4): 416-423, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144364</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencias adicionales de validez del Behavioral Inhibition Observation System (BIOS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
