<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91144</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopic transvaginal cholecystectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Transluminal  endoscopic surgery through natural orifices (NOTES) allows  intraperitoneal surgical procedures with minimal access to the abdominal wall. Currently it is not yet possible to perform these interventions without laparoscopic assistance, so these procedures are hybrids, fusion of minilaparoscopy and transluminal endoscopic surgery. We present a prospective clinical series of patients undergoing surgery for gallstones, with hybrid NOTES  transvaginal cholecystectomy with a nursing  care plan adapted to this new approach. Methods. Prospective clinical series of consecutive patients, nonrandomized, with transvaginal NOTES cholecystectomy. The surgery was performe with the assistance of two parietal entryports, one of umbilical 5 mm and 3 mm right upper quadrant of the abdomen. Analysis of nursing care plan with particular attention to safety of the procedure parameters and anxiety associated to the surgery. Results. There were no serious systemic complications. The  main problem with this type of surgery is the fear of patients in relation to the new ways for a non-gynecological transvaginal procedures as ckolecystectomy and the risk of vaginal bleeding and urinary infection. Discussion. Hybrid transvaginal cholecystectomy is a good surgical model of minimally invasive surgery. Its implementation is possible in groups with habit laparoscopic surgery, using standard instrumentation of endoscopy and laparoscopic surgery. The surgical team, doctors and nurses, must be well prepared for this new approach, because special and innovative cares are demanded (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Noguera Aguilar, José F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tortajada Collado, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La cirugía endoscópica transluminal a través de orificios naturales (NOTES) permite realizar procedimientos quirúrgicos intraperitoneales con mínimos accesos en la pared abdominal. Actualmente todavía no es posible realizar estas intervenciones sin asistencia desde puertas de entrada en la pared abdominal, por lo que los procedimientos realizados son híbridos, fusión de minilaparoscopia y cirugía  endoscópica transluminal. Se presenta una serie clínica prospectiva de pacientes intervenidas por colelitiasis, a las que se practicó colecistectomía híbrida transvaginal, con un plan de cuidados de colecistectomía laparoscópica adaptado al nuevo abordaje endoscópico transvaginal. Métodos. Serie clínica prospectiva de pacientes consecutivas, no aleatorizada, intervenidas por colelitiasis mediante abordaje de fusión NOTES transvaginal y minilaparoscópico con dos puertas de entrada, umbilical de 5 mm y en hipocondrio derecho de 3 mm. Análisis del plan de cuidados de enfermería, prestando especial atención a parámetros de seguridad del procedimiento y ansiedad relacionada con la cirugía. Resultados. No existieron complicaciones generales graves. El principal problema relacionado con este tipo de cirugía es el miedo de las pacientes en relación a las nuevas vías de abordaje transvaginal para procedimientos no ginecológicos y el riesgo de sangrado vaginal y de infección urinaria. Discusión. La colecistectomía híbrida transvaginal constituye un buen modelo  quirúrgico de cirugía mínimamente invasiva. Su implantación es posible en grupos quirúrgicos que tengan hábito laparoscópico, empleando instrumentación habitual de endoscopia y cirugía laparoscópica. El equipo quirúrgico -facultativos y enfermeros- debe estar bien preparado para este tipo de abordajes, pues precisan unos cuidados específicos y novedoso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;34(10): 686-692, oct. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colecistectomía endoscópica transvaginal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30788^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5843^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30788^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15025^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30788^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5843^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5844^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22847^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
