<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164590</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Postsurgical bleeding in hysterectomy due to benign pathoogy unicentric experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: the hysterectomy is the most frequent surgical procedure in gynecology. It is a low risk procedure, but infections and post-operative bleeding are their main complications. Our aim has been to evaluate the post-operative bleeding in our environment in the context of hysterectomies due to benign pathology. Material and methods: during 2 years we have been prospectively recruiting all of the hysterectomies performed in our centre due to benign pathology. We did a descriptive study of the main features of these patients and a univariate analysis of significant post-operative bleeding (lost of hemoglobin more than 2 g/dl). Results: among 256 hysterectomies, 125 (48.8%) have been total hysterectomies and 131(51.2%) subtotal hysterectomies. Mean age of patients was 49.1 ± 8,7 years old and the rate of significant post-operative bleeding was 62.5% (n=160). The unique predictor of significant bleeding was the open operative surgical procedure (95 vs 87.5%, p=0,05), without significant differences among the type of hysterectomy, the concomitant annexectomy or the surgery duration. Need of transfusion was greater (4.4 vs 0%, p=0.048) but not the need of new intervention (3.8 vs 5.2%, p=0.752). There were no deaths. Conclusion: significant postoperative bleeding defined by the lost of haemoglobin greater than 2g/dl is a frequent complication of hysterectomy in the context of benign pathology, being the open operative surgical procedure one of its predictors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Tejero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azpeitia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schineider, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la histerectomía es la intervención quirúrgica más frecuente en el ámbito de la ginecología. Si bien se trata de un procedimiento de bajo riesgo, las infecciones y la hemorragia post-operatoria son sus principales complicaciones. Nuestro objetivo ha sido evaluar la hemorragia post-operatoria en nuestro medio durante la realización de histerectomías por patología benigna. Material y métodos: durante 2 años se ha realizado una recogida prospectiva de todos los casos de histerectomía realizados en contexto de patología benigna en único centro. Realizamos un estudio descriptivo de las características de los pacientes y un análisis univariado de la hemorragia post-operatoria significativa (pérdida de hemoglobina mayor a 2g/dl). Resultados: de un total de 256 histerectomías; 125 (48.8%) han sido totales y 131 (51.2%) subtotales. La edad media de los pacientes era de 49.1 ± 8,7 años y la tasa de hemorragia significativa ha sido del 62.5% (n=160). El único predictor de hemorragia significativa ha sido la cirugía abierta (95 vs 87.5%, p=0,05), sin diferencias significativas en el tipo de histerectomía, la realización de anexectomía concomitante o en el tiempo de cirugía. La necesidad de transfusión ha sido mayor (4.4 vs 0%, p=0.048) pero no la necesidad de reintervención (3.8 vs 5.2%, p=0.752). No se han producido exitus. Conclusión: La hemorragia significativa definida por la pérdida de 2 g/dl de hemoglobina es una complicación frecuente de la histerectomía por patología benigna, siendo uno de sus predictores la vía quirúrgica abierta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;20(2): 55-58, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia postoperatoria en histerectomía por patología benigna: Estudio unicéntrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32645^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14992^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
