<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122420</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dopaminergic agonists in Parkinson&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Non-ergoline dopamine agonists (DA) are effective treatments for Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD). This review presents the pharmacology, evidence of efficacy and safety profile of pramipexole, ropinirole, and rotigotine, and practical recommendations are given regarding their use in clinical practice. Results: Extended-release formulations of pramipexole and ropinirole and transdermal continuous delivery rotigotine patches are currently available; these may contribute to stabilizing of plasma levels. In early PD, the three drugs significantly improve disability scales, delay time to dyskinesia and allow a later introduction of levodopa. In late PD they reduced total &#146;off&#146;-time, improved Unified Parkinson&#146;s Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) in both &#146;on&#146; and &#146;off&#146; state and allowed a reduction in total levodopa dosage. A significant improvement in quality of life scales has also been demonstrated. Extended-release formulations have proved to be non-inferior to the immediate release formulations and are better tolerated (ropinirole). Despite a generally good safety profile, serious adverse events, such as impulse control disorder and sleep attacks, need to be routinely monitored. Although combination therapy has not been addressed in scientific literature, certain combinations, such as apomorphine and another DA, may be helpful. Switching from one DA to another is feasible and safe, although in the first days an overlap of dopaminergic side effects may occur. When treatment with DA is stopped abruptly, dopamine withdrawal syndrome may present. Suspending any DA, especially pramipexole, has been linked to onset of apathy, which may be severe. Conclusions: New non-ergotine DAs are a valuable option for the treatment of both early and late PD. Despite their good safety profile, serious adverse effects may appear; these effects may have a pathoplastic effect on the course of PD and need to be monitored (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Cánovas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez del Val, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Arillo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ruiz Espiga, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linazasoro, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Castrillo, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burguera, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luquín Piudo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los agonistas dopaminergicos no ergoticos (AD) son tratamientos útiles en la enfermedad de Parkinson (EP). Revisamos la farmacología, el grado de evidencia en cuanto a eficacia y tolerabilidad de pramipexol, ropinirol y rotigotina, y proponemos algunas recomendaciones para su uso en la practica clínica. Desarrollo: En el momento actual se dispone de formas de liberacion prolongada (LP) de pramipexol y ropinirol y de administración transdermica de rotigotina, que contribuyen a una mayor estabilidad plasmatica de los valores del fármaco. En la EP inicial los 3 fármacos mejoran de forma significativa las escalas de incapacidad de los pacientes, retrasan la aparición de discinesias y permiten retrasar la introducción de levodopa. En la EP avanzada reducen el tiempo off, mejoran la Unified Parkinson&#146;s Disease Rating Scale (UPDRS) en on y en off y permiten reducir la dosis total de levodopa. Además, los 3 han sido capaces de inducir una mejora significativa en las escalas de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud. Las formulas de LP han demostrado la no inferioridad frente a las de liberación inmediata, e incluso una mejor tolerabilidad (ropinirol). A pesar de su buen perfil de seguridad, entre los efectos adversos graves cabe destacar el trastorno de control de impulsos, cuya aparición puede ser precoz, y los accesos de sueño (sleep attacks). Aunque la terapia combinada no ha sido estudiada específicamente, algunas asociaciones (como la de apomorfina y otros AD) pueden ser beneficiosas. El cambio de un AD a otro es factible de un día para otro, aunque en los primeros días puede haber una sumación de efectos adversos dopaminergicos que debe tenerse en cuenta. La suspensión brusca del tratamiento con AD puede inducir un síndrome de deprivacion dopaminergica. La retirada de cualquier AD, en particular pramipexol, se ha asociado a aparición de apatía que puede ser grave. Conclusiones: Los nuevos AD no ergoticos constituyen una opción valida de tratamiento de la EP tanto inicial como avanzada. A pesar de su buen perfil de tolerabilidad, no están exentos de efectos adversos graves, que pueden tener un efecto  atoplastico en la EP y que deben monitorizarse (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;29(4): 230-241, mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122420</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Agonistas dopaminérgicos en la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32116^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3706^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
