<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055773</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Planning, management and results of the implantation of laparoscopic surgery of the colon and rectum in a general hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The introduction of laparoscopic surgery  in a hospital is a slow process requiring the involvement  of a multidisciplinary team.  Patients and method. We performed a prospective,        descriptive study of all patients who underwent laparoscopic  surgery of the colon and rectum in the Mataró Hospital between 2003 and 2006.We also describe   the model used to introduce laparoscopic surgery   of the colon and rectum in our center.  Results. Between 2003 and 2006, 166 patients with        colorectal disease underwent laparoscopic surgery.  Patients included for rectal disease represented 36%        of the total. The conversion rate was 7% of the mean  in all the periods studied, with a complications rate of        13.25%. Conclusions. The controlled development of laparoscopic  surgery allows satisfactory results to be obtained  in colorectal disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almenara, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bas, Marta del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suñol, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heredia, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La introducción de la cirugía laparoscópica  avanzada en un hospital es un proceso lento        que requiere la implicación de un equipo multidisciplinario. Pacientes y método. Presentamos un estudio prospectivo  y descriptivo de todos los pacientes intervenidos   por laparoscopia de colon y recto en el Hospital        de Mataró entre los años 2003 y 2006. Conjuntamente se describe el modelo de implantación        de la cirugía laparoscópica de colon y recto en nuestro centro.  Resultados. Entre 2003 y 2006 se intervino por laparoscopia   a 196 pacientes con enfermedad colorrectal.  El porcentaje de pacientes intervenidos por   afección rectal alcanzó en el último período el 36% del total. La media del índice de conversión en todos        los períodos estudiados fue el 7%, con una tasa de   complicaciones del 13,25%.   Conclusiones. El desarrollo de la técnica laparoscópica   de forma controlada permite obtener unos resultados  satisfactorios en la cirugía de colon y recto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);82(2): 99-104, ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055773</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Planificación, gestión y resultados de la implantación de la cirugía laparoscópica de colon y recto en un hospital general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16616</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6925</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
