<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167773</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cybergossip and cyberbullying during primary school years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of social networking sites and instant messaging apps, despite playing a key role in building social relations, poses a risk, such as cybergossip. This research focused on the study and measurement of the cybergossip phenomenon and the psychometric properties of the Cybergossip-Q-Primary instrument. Cybergossip involvement in the development of cyberbehaviours performed in cyberbullying was analyzed. The European Cyberbullying Intervention Project Questionnaire (ECIPQ) was adapted to primary school-age children. The sample comprised 866 students (52.9% girls) with ages ranging from 10 to 13years (M = 11.21, SD = 0.90). Using both exploratory and confirmatory factor analyses, the fit of a one-dimensional structure for the cybergossip instrument and a two-dimensional structure for cyberbullying (cyberaggression and cybervictimization) were contrasted. A structural equations analysis revealed a significant relationship between cybergossip and cyberbullying. The results in relation to cybergossip, cyberaggression, cybervictimization, and the consequences of misinterpreting information are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romera, Eva M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pradas, Inés C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Ruiz, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de que la utilización de redes sociales y de aplicaciones de mensajería instantánea juega un papel muy importante para establecer relaciones sociales, supone riesgos como el cibercotilleo. Esta investigación se ha centrado en el estudio y medición de este fenómeno y de las propiedades psicométricas del cuestionario de cibercotilleo, Cybergossip-Q-Primary. Se analiza la implicación del cibercotilleo en la formación de los cibercomportamientos presentes en el ciberacoso. Se adaptó el Cuestionario del Proyecto Europeo de Intervención en el Ciberacoso a niños en edad escolar. La muestra constaba de 866 alumnos (el 52.9% niñas) en edades comprendidas entre los 10 y 13 años (M = 11.21, DT = 0.90). Mediante análisis factoriales exploratorio y confirmatorio se contrastó el ajuste de una estructura unidimensional en el instrumento de cibercotilleo y bifactorial en el de ciberacoso (ciberagresión y cibervictimización). El análisis de ecuaciones estructurales mostró una relación significativa entre el cibercotilleo y el ciberacoso. Se comentan los resultados relativos al cibercotilleo, la ciberagresión y la cibervictimización, así como las consecuencias que conlleva malinterpretar la información (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);23(2): 73-80, jul.-dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167773</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cibercotilleo y el ciberacoso en la enseñanza primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54836^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
