<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101484</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of human immunodeficiency virus-1 infected children receiving Highly active antiretroviral therapy: a cross-sectional study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Since 1996, when HAART became available, there has been a change in the course of HIV-infection, leading it to become a chronic disease. Our aim was to describe the characteristics of the children followed up in our hospital. Patients and methods: A cross-sectional study was conducted on 32 HIV-infected children followed up until December-2010, at the University-Hospital de Getafe. Clinical and laboratory information from the last visit was collected for the evaluation of patients. Results: Thirty-two children with HIV-1 were evaluated, 29 infected through vertical-transmission. The median age was 14 years. According to the CDC classification, 56% (18/32) of children were in category A, 28% (9/32) B and 16% (5/32) C. Immunological class was 3 in 75% of children, class 2 in 9% and class 1 in 16%. The median nadir of CD4 was 337 cells/ml (12%). The median current CD4 was 749 (31%). Only one adolescent had a CD4% below 200 cells/ml due to lack of adherence. Twenty-eight patients (87%) were receiving HAART, and 4 patients were off antiretroviral treatment. Among the patients treated, 26 (93%) had viral loads &lt;200copies/ml. The median viral-load was&lt;20 copies/ml. Median time on antiretroviral treatment was 10 years. The combination more frequently used was two nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTI) and one protease inhibitor (PI), that was given to 15 patients (47%), followed by 2 NRTI, and one non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NNRTI) in 8 patients (29%). Two children received rescue therapy including raltegravir, one with tipranavir and the other with darunavir. A total of 12 patients (43%) received medication once a day, 7 of them with fixed-dose combinations in a single tablet (25%). There were metabolic complications, including hyperlipidaemia or lipodystrophy were observed in 17 children (53%). Conclusions: Most of our patients are receiving HAART, with good virological and immunological control. The prevalence of metabolic abnormalities was high. Strategies to improve adherence and decrease toxicities are needed in perinatally-acquired HIV-infected children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guillen, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bermejo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Amador, J. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badillo, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Desde 1996, cuando se inició el tratamiento antirretroviral de gran actividad (TARGA), se ha producido un cambio en el curso de la infección por el VIH, convirtiéndose en una enfermedad crónica. Nuestro objetivo fue describir las características de los niños seguidos en nuestro hospital. Pacientes y métodos: Se realizó un estudio de corte transversal, de 32 niños infectados por VIH, seguidos hasta diciembre de 2010, en el Hospital Universitario de Getafe. La evaluación de los pacientes se efectuó con datos clínicos y de laboratorio, recogidos de la última visita. Resultados: Se siguió a 32 niños con infección por VIH, 29 de ellos infectados por transmisión vertical. La edad media fue de 14 años. De acuerdo con la clasificación de los CDC, el 56% (18/32) de los niños estaban en la categoría A, el 28% (9/32) en la B y el 16% (5/32) en la C. Dentro de la categoría inmunológica, 24 (75%) se encontraban en la categoría 3, 3 (9%) en la categoría 2 y 5 (16%) en la categoría 1. La mediana del nadir de CD4 fue de 337 (12%). La mediana de CD4 en la última determinación fue de 749 (31%). Solo una adolescente con mala adherencia tenía un recuento absoluto de CD4 menor de 200 células/ml. Veintiocho pacientes (87%) recibían TARGA y 4 estaban sin tratamiento antirretroviral. De los pacientes en tratamiento, 26 (93%) presentaban cargas virales &lt;200 copias/ml. La mediana de carga viral fue &lt;20 copias/ml, y la mediana del tiempo de tratamiento antirretroviral fue de 10 años. La combinación más frecuente fue la de dos inhibidores de la transcriptasa inversa análogos de nucleósidos (ITIAN) y un inhibidor de la proteasa (IP), que la recibieron 15 pacientes (47%), seguida de 2 ITIAN y un inhibidor de la transcriptasa inversa no análogo (ITINN), que la recibieron 8 pacientes (29%). Dos niños con terapia de rescate recibieron raltegravir, uno con tipranavir y el otro darunavir. Un total de 12 pacientes (43%) recibían pautas una vez al día, de ellos con pautas fijas combinadas en un único comprimido se encontraron 7 pacientes (25%). Se observaron complicaciones metabólicas como hiperlipidemia o lipodistrofia en 17 niños (53%). Conclusiones: La mayoría de nuestros pacientes reciben TARGA, con un buen control inmunovirológico. La prevalencia de alteraciones metabólicas es elevada. Es necesario desarrollar estrategias para mejorar la adherencia y disminuir la toxicidad en los niños con infección por VIH de transmisión vertical (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);76(6): 317-323, jun. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101484</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de niños con infección por virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana-1 que reciben tratamiento antirretroviral de gran actividad: estudio de corte transversal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
