<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157628</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of obesity: pros and cons</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity is a first magnitude public health problem. Because of its multifactorial pathogenesis, treatment of obesity is complex and requires a multidisciplinary approach. The first step is an adjustment and re-education of eating habits and healthy lifestyle. Diet and physical activity are pillars so that, once achieved weight loss, it remains within the normal range. As alternatives for severe cases there are pharmacological, endoscopic and surgical treatments that can achieve significant weight reductions and maintained over time. In this sense, the surgery has proven, in combination with changes in lifestyle and dietary adjustments, the best available treatment for morbid obesity, achieving significant improvement in health status and quality of life of these patients for their great general health benefits. However, it should be borne in mind the possibility of negative effects arising such as global nutritional deficiencies, as well as specific vitamin and mineral deficiencies, and even an increased risk of alterations in bone mineral density and alcoholism. Both a weight re-gain as an increased risk of suicide after some time of surgery have been described and should be considered. In women of childbearing age necessary to add the possible problems arising from an increased prevalence of preterm birth and low birth weight (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moncada, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frühbeck, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landecho,  Manuel F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valentí, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad representa un problema de salud pública de primera magnitud. Debido a su patogenia multifactorial, el tratamiento de la obesidad es complejo y requiere un abordaje multidisciplinar. El primer paso consiste en un ajuste y re-educación de los hábitos dietéticos y estilo de vida saludable. La dieta y la actividad física son pilares para que, una vez conseguida la pérdida de peso, ésta se mantenga dentro de la normalidad. Como alternativas para los casos graves existen tratamientos farmacológicos, endoscópicos y quirúrgicos que permiten conseguir reducciones de peso más importantes y mantenidas en el tiempo. En este sentido, la cirugía ha demostrado ser, en combinación con los cambios de estilo de vida y ajustes dietéticos, el mejor tratamiento disponible para la obesidad mórbida, logrando alcanzar mejoría importante en el estado de salud y en la calidad de vida de estos pacientes por sus grandes beneficios en todo el organismo. Sin embargo, debe tenerse presente la posibilidad de que surjan efectos negativos tales como carencias nutricionales globales, así como déficits minerales y vitamínicos específicos e, inclusive un mayor riesgo de alteraciones en la densidad mineral ósea y de alcoholismo. Tanto una reganancia ponderal como un aumento del riesgo de suicidio transcurrido algún tiempo de la cirugía han sido descritos y deben ser tenidos en cuenta. En mujeres en edad fértil resulta necesario añadir los posibles problemas derivados de una mayor prevalencia de parto prematuro y bajo peso al nacer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;82(n.extr): 225-233, 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de la obesidad: pros y contras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3690^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
