<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73316</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dental health of children and adolescents of Navarra, 2007 (4th edition)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. With five years having passed since the lastsurvey (2002), a new survey was carried out, the 4th since1987. The aim is to determine the state of oral health of childrenand adolescents in Navarre and its evolution.Population and methods. The sample (n=1.397) was selectedthrough multistage probability sampling, taking as aunit the classrooms of the 1st and 6th year of Primary Educationand the 2nd of Compulsory Secondary Education. Thefieldwork was carried out in the months of April and May2007 by two calibrated teams of examiners.Health variables studied: caries (measured with WHOcriterion and extended criterion), periodontal state andmalocclusion. The data were computerised with Access XP2003 SP3; the statistical analysis with SPSS Windows v.15.0.Results. Ten point eight percent of the sample is of foreignorigin. The prevalence of caries in temporary dentition at6 years is 35.9% with a dft of 1.26; in permanent dentition,28.5% and 46.4% at 12 and 14 years; the average of affectedteeth 0.63 and 1.28 respectively. The index of restorationis 26.1% in temporary dentition and 68.9 and 74.1% in permanent;those of foreign origin show more caries (p&lt;0.05)and less treatment (p&lt;0.05) than those of Spanish origin.Sixty-two point eight percent of 14 year olds show gingivalbleeding and 16.8%, calculus; 14.7% malocclusion and 19.1%wear orthodontic appliances.Conclusions. Caries are stabilised in temporary dentition inthe general population, but fall significantly amongst natives(those of Spanish origin); in permanent dentition they continuetheir tendency to fall, although more moderately. Navarreis amongst the regions with a lower level of caries and a higherindex of restoration. Immigrants show significantly morecaries. The index of restoration falls slightly with respect toprevious years. The periodontal health figures are poor. Malocclusionand orthodontic appliance wearers are stabilised(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asenjo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosel, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáinz de Murieta, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artázcoz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Transcurridos 5 años desde la última encuesta(2002), se procede a una nueva edición que supone la 4ªdesde 1987. El objetivo es conocer el estado de salud oral deniños y adolescentes de Navarra y su evolución.Población y métodos. La muestra (n=1.397) fue seleccionadamediante muestreo probabilístico polietápico, tomandocomo unidad las aulas de 1º y 6º de Enseñanza Primaria y de2º de Enseñanza Secundaria Obligatoria. El trabajo de campose realizó entre los meses de abril y mayo de 2007 pordos equipos examinadores calibrados.Variables de salud estudiadas: caries (medida con criterioOMS y con criterio ampliado), estado periodontal y maloclusión.Los datos fueron informatizados con Access XP 2003SP3; el análisis estadístico, con SPSS Windows v.15.0.Resultados. El 10,8% de la muestra es de origen extranjero.La prevalencia de caries en dentición temporal a los 6 añoses 35,9% con cod 1,26; en dentición permanente, 28,5% y46,4% a los 12 y 14 años; la media de dientes afectados 0,63y 1,28 respectivamente. El índice de restauración es 26,1%en dentición temporal y 68,9 y 74,1% en permanente; los deorigen extranjero presentan más caries (p&lt;0,05) y menostratamiento (p&lt;0,05) que los de origen español. El 62,8% de14 años presentan sangrado gingival y el 16,8%, cálculo; el14,7% maloclusión y el 19,1% lleva ortodoncia.Conclusiones. La caries está estabilizada en denticióntemporal en población general, pero desciende significativamenteentre los autóctonos (origen España); en denticiónpermanente continúa con su tendencia descendente,aunque más moderada. Navarra está entre las regiones conmenor nivel de caries y más alto índice de restauración. Losinmigrantes presentan significativamente más caries. El índicede restauración desciende ligeramente respecto a añosanteriores. Las cifras de salud periodontal son pobres. Maloclusióny portadores de ortodoncia están estabilizados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;32(2): 199-215, mayo-ago. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73316</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La salud dental de los niños y adolescentes de Navarra, 2007 (4ª edición)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14468^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28452</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3808^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3973^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
