<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040538</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coping strategies and hardy personality in palliative care patients. A preliminary study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of pallíative medicine is to take care of patients who are suffering from terminal diseases. In Spain, there are many pallíative care units although not all of them carry out multídisciplinary interventions, which are very relevant for the successful relief of suffering and for improving patient qualíty of Me. The aim of this study is to analyze coping strategies used by patients in pallíative care units who had accepted their terminal disease and their relation with hardy personalíty type. For this purpose, a short interview form was applied. Results show that patients use posítíve coping strategies including planned problem-solving, seeking alternative reward and posítíve reappraisal. One interesting finding was that challenge was a component of hardy personalíty. This could mean that these patients take this experience as an opportunity for personal growth</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrosa Hernández, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñacoba Puente, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Furlong, Lilian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Gutiérrez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>fr</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La medicina paliativa se dedica al cuidado de los pacientes con enfermedades en fase terminal. En España, existen varias unidades de cuidados paliativos, sin embargo, no en todas se lleva a cabo una intervención multidisciplinaria lo cual es esencial para conseguir que una persona muera en una situación dé bienestar y con la mejor calidad posible. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar las estrategias de afrontamiento existentes en los enfermos ingresados en unidades de cuidados paliativos en fase de aceptación y su relación con la personalidad resistente. Para ello, se administró un instrumento corto en forma de entrevista. Los resultados encontrados muestran que este tipo de pacientes utilizan estrategias de afrontamiento positivas como acción para resolver problemas, búsqueda de recompensas alternativas y reevaluación positiva. Por otro lado, un aspecto de la personalidad resistente encontrada en estos pacientes es el reto lo cual indica que estos pacientes viven esta experiencia como una oportunidad de desarrollo personal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;16(1): 65-89, ene. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040538</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias de afrontamiento y personalidad resistente en pacientes de cuidados paliativos. Un estudio preliminar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14105^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
