<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058154</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the impact of a clinical pathway for kidney transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To reassess the impact of a clinical pathway for kidney transplantation in a university hospital after a 4-year period. Material and method: We performed an experimental "before and after" study with a retrospective control group. The experimental group was composed of patients who underwent kidney transplantation after the starting date of implementation of the clinical pathway (1999) at the Hospital La Paz (Madrid, Spain). The control group included a selection of patients who underwent the same procedure before 1999. Results: There were 32 patients in the control group and 121 in the experimental group. The length of stay before discharge was reduced from 20 days in the control group to 14 days in the experimental group. The surgical site infection rate decreased from 12.5% to 1.7%. No differences were found in the development of other surgical complications or undesired events after discharge. The reduction observed in antibiotic use was non-significant, whilst a significant reduction was found in the use of gastric protectors. Moreover, the time elapsed from kidney transplantation to withdrawal of the vesical and central catheters diminished in both groups (from 12 to 8 days). Conclusions: The clinical pathway has proved to be an effective and efficient tool to reduce the length of hospital stay and the development of undesired events, thus improving health care quality</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maeso, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selgas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Vega, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Caballero, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda, J. Jonay</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Revaluar el impacto asistencial de una vía clínica (VC) de trasplante renal en un hospital universitario tras 4 años de implantación. Material y método: Estudio experimental tipo antes-después con control retrospectivo. El grupo de estudio estuvo formado por los pacientes sometidos a trasplante renal con posterioridad a la implantación de la VC en 1999 en el Hospital Universitario La Paz y como grupo control, los pacientes trasplantados antes de su establecimiento. Resultados: Se estudió a 32 pacientes del grupo control y 121 del grupo de estudio. La estancia se redujo de 20 días del primer grupo a 14 días del segundo. Se observó una reducción en la incidencia de infección de localización quirúrgica (el 12,5 contra el 1,7%). No hubo diferencias en las complicaciones quirúrgicas ni en los eventos posteriores al alta. La reducción observada en el uso inadecuado de antimicrobianos no fue significativa, mientras que ésta sí lo fue con los protectores gástricos. También disminuyó entre ambos grupos el tiempo transcurrido entre el trasplante y la retirada de la sonda vesical y la vía central (de 12 a 8 días en ambos casos). Conclusiones: La VC ha demostrado ser una herramienta efectiva y eficiente, pues con su implantación se observó una reducción en la estancia hospitalaria y de otros efectos adversos para el paciente, con lo que se estima una mejora en la calidad asistencial</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;22(4): 184-190, jul.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058154</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del impacto asistencial de una vía clínica de trasplante renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
