<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051269</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of herbal medicinal products must be based on their efficacy and safety profile as an essential part of Phytotherapy knowledge. The content of active principles in herbal drugs determines not only its therapeutic activity, but al so their adverse effects, toxicity, drug interactions as well as the limitations of their use.    Even though the great majority of the herbal drugs used today in Phytotherapy have wide safety margins, it is important to point out that many active principles may present adverse effects, which can be toxic if they exceed specific plasmatic concentrations. Even when such phytoproducts are taken correctly, they can interact with drugs, some of which have a very strict safety margins.    The misuse of herbal drugs and their preparations may lead to situations that potentiate their limitations and disadvantages against the attainment of the therapeutic efficacy that in many cases has been clinically demonstrated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Guijarro, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilización de los medicamentos a base de plantas debe basarse en su eficacia y su perfil de seguridad como parte esencial del conocimiento de la Fitoterapia.    Si bien la mayoría de drogas vegetales que se utilizan habitualmente en Fitoterapia tienen unos márgenes de seguridad amplios, hay que tener en cuenta que muchos principios activos pueden presentar efectos secundarios, que pueden llegar a ser tóxicos si se sobrepasan determinadas concentraciones plasmáticas, e incluso cuando las preparaciones vegetales se toman de forma correcta pueden interaccionar con medicamentos, algunos de ellos con márgenes de seguridad muy estrechos.    El uso incorrecto de las drogas vegetales y sus preparados puede dar lugar a situaciones que potencian más sus limitaciones e inconvenientes frente a la consecución de la eficacia terapéutica, que en muchos casos ha sido clínicamente contrastada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;5(2): 117-133, dic. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051269</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los parámetros de seguridad en Fitoterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4365</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
