<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124814</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Negotiating in a context of economic crisis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The research on negotiation in the last 50 years has only considered that negotiation occurs in a stable economic environment. This paper analyses negotiation in changing contexts with a focus on two aspects: first, examining the psychological processes affecting negotiation in a changing environment, whether one of prosperity or economic crisis; second, collective bargaining is studied, focusing on the role of union representatives in a context of economic crisis. The first line of research is highly experimental; the second is applied and based on field studies using interviews and focus groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Elgoibar, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, Jimena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación realizada sobre negociación en los últimos 50 años solo ha considerado como esquema de investigación la negociación en un contexto económico estable. En este trabajo se analiza la negociación en contextos cambiantes, con dos vertientes, en la primera se estudian los procesos psicológicos que afectan a la negociación en un contexto cambiante, bien de bonanza o bien de crisis económica, en la segunda se estudia la negociación colectiva, profundizando en el papel de los representantes sindicales en un contexto de crisis económica. La primera línea de investigación es eminentemente experimental, la segunda es aplicada y basada en estudios de campo mediante entrevistas y grupos de discusión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;35(2): 130-137, jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124814</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Negociar en un contexto de crisis económica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53789^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2363</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3129^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
