<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162817</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is urgent CT angiography necessary in cases of acute lower gastrointestinal bleeding?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute lower gastrointestinal bleeding usually presents as hematochezia, rectal bleeding or melena and represents 1-2% of the medical appointments in the Emergency Services. Mortality reaches the 30-40% and it is highly related with the severity and associated comorbidity. Most clinical practice guidelines include colonoscopy at some point in the diagnostic and therapeutic process (urgent for severe cases and ambulatory for mild ones) and look for predictors of severity. In the last years, there have been numerous studies where is clear the relevance and complementarity of advanced diagnostic imaging techniques, gradually incorporated as an alternative or second step in severe cases. Therefore, we have made a review of current scientific evidence to establish a clinical prediction rule for optimal indication of CT angiography in these patients. However, future studies providing greater robustness and level of evidence are necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Díaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rodríguez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí de Gracia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemorragia digestiva baja aguda se presenta en forma de hematoquecia, rectorragia o melenas, y constituye el 1-2% de los motivos de consulta en los servicios de urgencia. La mortalidad alcanza el 30-40%, en relación con la gravedad y la comorbilidad. La mayoría de las guías de práctica clínica incluyen la colonoscopia en algún momento del proceso diagnóstico-terapéutico (precoz en las graves y programada en las leves), y buscan factores predictores de gravedad. En los últimos años se han publicado numerosos estudios en los que queda patente la relevancia y la complementariedad diagnóstica de las técnicas de imagen avanzadas, incorporadas paulatinamente como alternativa o de segundo escalón en los casos graves. Por ello, hemos realizado una revisión de la evidencia científica actual que permita establecer una regla de predicción clínica para la óptima indicación de la angiografía por tomografía computarizada en estos pacientes. Son necesarios, no obstante, futuros estudios que aporten mayor robustez y nivel de evidencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);59(3): 249-252, mayo-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es necesario realizar una angiografía por tomografía computarizada urgente en la hemorragia digestiva baja aguda? Proyecto MAPAC-IMAGEN</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
