<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72667</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Molecular basis of leukocyte&#150;endothelium interactions during the inflammatory response</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The process of leukocyte extravasation, a critical step in the inflammatory response, involves the migration of leukocytes from the bloodstream towards target tissues, where they exert their effector function. Leukocyte extravasation is orchestrated by the combined action of cellular adhesion receptors and chemotactic factors, and involves radical morphological changes in both leukocytes and endothelial cells. Thus, it constitutes an active process for both cell types and promotes the rapid and efficient influx of leukocytes to inflammatory foci without compromising the integrity of the endothelial barrier. This article provides a review of leukocyte extravasation from both molecular and mechanical points of view, with a particular emphasis on the most recent findings on the topic. It includes a description of newly revealed steps in the adhesion cascade, such as slow rolling motion, intraluminal crawling and alternative pathways for transcellular migration, and discusses the functional role of novel adhesion receptors, the spatiotemporal organization of receptors at the plasma membrane, and the signaling pathways that control different phases of the extravasation process. for transcellular migration, and discusses the functional role of novel adhesion receptors, the spatiotemporal organization of receptors at the plasma membrane and the signaling pathways that control different phases of the extravasation process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barreiro, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Madrid, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El proceso de extravasación leucocitaria, un paso crucial de la respuesta inflamatoria, implica la migración de los leucocitos desde la corriente sanguínea hasta los tejidos diana donde ejercen su función efectora. La extravasación de los leucocitos está orquestada por la acción conjunta de receptores de adhesión celular y factores quimiotácticos, e implica cambios morfológicos drásticos tanto en leucocitos como en células endoteliales. De este modo, constituye un proceso activo para ambos tipos celulares que promueve la rápida y eficiente llegada de los leucocitos a los focos inflamatorios sin comprometer la integridad de la barrera endotelial. Este artículo revisa la extravasación leucocitaria, con especial hincapié en los hallazgos más recientes en este campo, tanto desde el punto de vista molecular como mecanístico. Incluye la descripción de nuevos pasos en la cascada de adhesión tales como el enlentecimiento del rodamiento, la locomoción intraluminal o la ruta alternativa de migración transcelular, así como el papel funcional de nuevos receptores de adhesión, la organización espaciotemporal de los receptores en la membrana plasmática y las rutas de señalización que controlan los diferentes estadios del proceso de extravasación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;62(5): 552-562, mayo 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72667</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases moleculares de las interacciones leucocito-endotelio durante la respuesta inflamatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22891^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24746^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32612^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2500^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2483^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2500^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
