<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137552</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Verbal forward digit span in Spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Older people complain of difficulties in recalling telephone numbers and being able to dial them in the correct order. This study examined the developmental trend of verbal forward digit span across adulthood and aging in a Spanish population, as an index of one of the components of Baddeley&#146;s working memory model- the phonological loop-, which illustrates these two aspects. Method: A verbal digit span was administered to an incidental sample of 987 participants ranging from 35 to 90 years old. The maximum length was defined that participants could recall of at least two out of three series in the same order as presented with no errors. Demographic variables of gender and educational level were also examined. Results: The ANOVA showed that the three main factors (age group, gender and educational level) were significant, but none of the interactions was. Verbal forward digit span decreases during the lifespan, but gender and educational level affect it slightly. Conclusion: Phonological loop is affected by age. The verbal forward digit span in this study is generally lower than the one reported in other studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sebastián,  María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Las personas mayores se quejan con frecuencia de las dificultades que tienen para recordar números de teléfono o para marcarlos en el orden correcto. Este estudio investiga el desarrollo de la amplitud verbal de dígitos en orden directo en adultos y personas mayores en población española, como índice de uno de los componentes del modelo de memoria operativa de Baddeley: el lazo fonológico, que precisamente ilustra estos dos aspectos. Método: la tarea verbal de amplitud de dígitos en orden directo se administró a una muestra incidental de 987 participantes, entre 35 y 90 años. Se definió como la longitud mayor de series de dígitos repetidas correctamente en, al menos, dos de las tres series. Variables demográficas, género y nivel educativo también se examinaron. Resultados: el ANOVA mostró que los tres factores principales (grupo de edad, género y nivel educativo) fueron significativos, pero ninguna de las interacciones alcanzó la significación. La amplitud verbal de dígitos en orden directo desciende durante el ciclo vital, pero tanto género como nivel educativo afectaron ligeramente. Conclusiones: el lazo fonológico está afectado por la edad. La amplitud verbal de dígitos en orden directo fue, en general, menor que la encontrada en otros estudios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);27(2): 93-98, mayo 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137552</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Amplitud verbal de dígitos en orden directo en población española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54302^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54302^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27926^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15111^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15111^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15111^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8740^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8740^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
