<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115470</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tirotropine reference intervals during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Overt and subclinical maternal hypothyroidism is known to have serious adverse effects for both mother and fetus. Given the complex physiology of thyroid function during pregnancy, hormone assessment should be performed according to reference values for each gestational trimester and generated locally in each reference laboratory. If trimester-specific references intervals are not available in the laboratory, the following reference ranges of tirotropine are recommended: first trimester &lt; 2,5 mUI/L; second and third trimesters &lt; 3,0 mUI/L(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfayate Guerra, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Donnay Candil, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hipotiroidismo materno clínico y el subclínico tienen consecuencias graves tanto para la madre como para el feto. Debido a la compleja fisiología de la función tiroidea durante el embarazo, debería realizarse la evaluación hormonal según valores de referencia para cada trimestre de gestación y para cada zona y con las técnicas propias de cada laboratorio. Si no se dispone en el laboratorio de estos valores de referencia trimestrales propios, se recomiendan los siguientes valores de referencia de tirotropina: primer trimestre &lt; 2,5 mUI/L; segundo y tercer trimestres &lt; 3,0 mUI/L(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;6(3): 132-134, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115470</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores de referencia de tirotropina durante la gestación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22697</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3427^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3427^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31094^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3427^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19329^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
