<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116093</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of drugs related to the treatment of diabetes mellitus and other cardiovascular risk factors in the spanish population. The Di@bet.es study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. To assess the patterns of use of 8 therapeutic drug groups for the treatment of diabetes mellitus and other cardiovascular risk factors, and to identify sociodemographic and health determinants of their use in the overall Spanish population. Methods. A representative sample of the Spanish population within the Di@bet.es study, a cross-sectional population-based survey, was included. Study variables: sociodemographic, clinical, and lifestyle data; physical examination, and an oral glucose tolerance test in patients without known diabetes mellitus. Furthermore, patients were systematically queried about current medication use, and 8 pharmacotherapeutic groups were evaluated: lipid-lowering therapy, antihypertensives, oral hypoglycemic agents, insulin, thyroid hormone, uricosurics, psychoactive drugs, and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs. Results. Sixty-six percent of the Spanish population was taking at least one medication. Therapeutic drug use was associated with age, independently of the higher prevalence of diabetes mellitus, hypertension, or hyperlipidemia in older patients. Sex disparities were found in the use of lipid-lowering agents, allopurinol, levothyroxine, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, and psychoactive drugs. Use of psychoactive drugs was related to education level, work status, physical activity, smoking, and alcohol consumption. Almost 30% of patients with diabetes mellitus were taking 6 or more medications daily. Diabetes mellitus was associated with greater use of antihypertensives, lipid-lowering agents, and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs. Conclusions. Age and sex are the most important factors determining therapeutic drug use. Lifestyle patterns and sociocultural factors have an impact only on psychoactive drug use. Diabetes mellitus is associated with greater use of antihypertensives, lipid-lowering agents, and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red de Diabetes y Enfermedades Metabólicas Asociadas (CIBERDEM)</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Evaluar el patrón de consumo de ocho grupos de fármacos para el tratamiento de la diabetes mellitus y otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular; identificar en la población española los determinantes sociodemográficos y de salud asociados al consumo de aquellos. Métodos. El estudio Di@bet.es es una encuesta poblacional transversal que comprende una muestra significativa de la población adulta española. Variables de estudio: datos sociodemográficos, clínicos y de estilo de vida; exploración física, y sobrecarga oral de glucosa. Además, se preguntó sistemáticamente la medicación consumida y se analizaron ocho grupos de fármacos: hipolipemiantes, antihipertensivos, antidiabéticos orales, insulina, hormona tiroidea, uricosúricos, psicofármacos y antiinflamatorios no esteroideos. Resultados. El 66% de la población toma alguno de los fármacos estudiados. El consumo de dichos medicamentos se asocia con la edad, independientemente de la prevalencia de diabetes mellitus, hipertensión o dislipemia. Se han encontrado diferencias significativas entre sexos en el consumo de hipolipemiantes, hormona tiroidea, uricosúricos, antiinflamatorios no esteroideos y psicofármacos. El consumo de psicofármacos se asoció significativamente con nivel educativo, situación laboral, actividad física y consumo de tabaco y alcohol. El 30% de los sujetos con diabetes mellitus tomó más de seis fármacos diarios. La diabetes mellitus se asoció significativamente con un mayor consumo de antihipertensivos, hipolipemiantes y antiinflamatorios no esteroideos. Conclusiones. La edad y el sexo son los factores más importantes que determinan el consumo de fármacos. El estilo de vida y el nivel sociocultural afectan solo al uso de psicofármacos. La diabetes mellitus se asocia a un mayor consumo de antihipertensivos, hipolipemiantes y antiinflamatorios no esteroideos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;66(11): 854-863, nov. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116093</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de fármacos relacionados con el tratamiento de la diabetes mellitus y otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular en la población española. Estudio Di@bet.es</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4294^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
