<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043914</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of extra-hospital emergency system in the treatment of acute stroke in the region of murcia. Possible repercussions on the urgent care of stroke patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To examine the use of extra-hospital emergency systems in the urgent care of stroke patients in our region andtheir influence on the time required to reach hospital, the time needed to perform an urgent computerised axial tomography(CAT) scan and the delay in receiving attention from the specialist. Patients and methods. Samples were collected from 232stroke patients out of the total number admitted to our hospitals. Data about the stroke were collected prospectively, andincluded the arrival time, the time required to perform the CAT scan and the time the specialist devoted to attending the patient.Data were also gathered about the different extra-hospital transport and emergency systems. A statistical analysis wasperformed to determine the effect of using the extra-hospital emergency procedures on the different variables. Results. A total of53.6% of patients arrived within the first three hours. 38.7% went straight to hospital, 25% visited extra-hospital EmergencyServices first, and 18.5% made a prior visit to Primary Care. 51.5% found their own way to the hospital and 46.7% arrived byambulance. Mean time taken to perform an urgent CAT scan: 190.4 minutes; mean time required for specialist attention: 25.65hours. The only statistically significant relation was the use of extra-hospital emergency systems and health care transportaccording to the type of stroke: both were more likely to be used in cases of haemorrhagic stroke. Conclusions. In hospitals in theMurcia region, the use of the extra-hospital emergency system and the means of transport utilised do not affect the time strokepatients take to reach hospital or the time needed to perform an urgent CAT scan or the delay in receiving attention from aspecialist; the aetiology of the stroke does, however, influence the use of such services</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín-Marín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Navarro, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fages, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Espuch, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Escribano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Medina, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano-Soriano, J. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Ortiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde-González, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín-Muñoz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Utilización en nuestra región de los sistemas deurgencias extrahospitalarias en la atención urgente del ictus y suinfluencia en el tiempo de llegada al hospital, el de realización de latomografía axial computarizada (TAC) urgente y demora de la atenciónpor el especialista. Pacientes y métodos. Se recogieron muestrasde 232 pacientes con ictus del total de los ingresados en nuestroshospitales. Prospectivamente se recogieron datos sobre el ictus,con inclusión de los tiempos de llegada, tiempo de realización de laTAC y tiempo de atención por el especialista. Se recogió el uso delos distintos sistemas de urgencias y transporte extrahospitalarios.Estadísticamente se analizó la influencia del uso de los dispositivosde urgencia extrahospitalarios en las distintas variables recogidas.Resultados. 53,6% de los pacientes llegaron en las tres primerashoras. 38,7% acudieron directamente al hospital, el 25% acude primeroal Servicio de Urgencias extrahospitalarias y 18,5% consultapreviamente con Asistencia Primaria. El 51,5% llegaron por suspropios medios y el 46,7% en ambulancia. Tiempo medio de TACurgente: 190,4 minutos; tiempo medio de atención por el especialista:25,65 horas. La única relación estadísticamente significativa fueel uso del sistema de urgencias extrahospitalarias y transporte sanitariosegún el tipo de ictus, con más tendencia a utilizarlos en losictus hemorrágicos. Conclusiones. En los hospitales de Murcia, eluso del sistema de urgencias extrahospitalarias y el medio de transporteempleado no influyen en el tiempo de llegada del ictus al hospital,en el tiempo de realización de TAC urgente ni en la demora deatención por el especialista, y sí influye en la utilización de dichosservicios la etiología del ictus</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(2): 68-72, ene. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043914</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización del sistema de emergencias extrahospitalario en el tratamiento del ictus agudo en la región de Murcia. Posible repercusión en la asistencia sanitaria urgente del ictus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10537</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28837</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
