<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051272</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nowadays, the use of traditional herbal remedies in Veterinary medicine is very small in Europe, mainly due to the shift to the synthetic pharmaceutical compounds. In spite of the fact that these traditional practices persist in the Mediterranean area, they have been not much studied. In this paper, the authors study for the first time the natural remedies that are still used in the central zone of Sardinia (Nuorese region) as dietary supplements for livestock, in order to ameliorate the quality of the ovine, bovine and porcine meat, as well as the quality of the milk of ovine and bovine livestock</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mura, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mongiano, Patricio Demian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lancioni, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maxia, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad la aplicación de remedios tradicionales en veterinaria es muy poco frecuente en Europa, al haber sido desplazada por los productos farmacéuticos de síntesis. A pesar de que estas prácticas perduran en el entorno mediterráneo, han sido poco estudiadas. En este artículo se analizan por primera vez los remedios naturales que se siguen utilizando en el centro de Cerdeña (región del Nuorese) como complemento de la dieta de animales para mejorar la calidad de la carne ovina, bovina y porcina, así como de la leche de ovinos y bovinos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;5(2): 155-161, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051272</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plantas usadas en la práctica etnoveterinaria en el Nuorese (Cerdeña, Italia)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11377^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13933</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22672</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d835</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
