<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139988</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Design and validation of an image for dissemination and implementation of Chilean dietary guidelines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Food-Based Dietary Guidelines (FBDG) are usually accompanied by an image for dissemination and implementation. Objective: to design and validate an image to represent the variety and proportions of the new Chilean dietary guidelines, include foods high in critical nutrients that should be avoided and physical activity guidelines. Method: a panel of experts tested seven graphics and selected three that were validated with 12 focus groups of people aged 10-14 and 20-40 years, of both sexes, from different socioeconomic groups and from both rural and urban areas. We analyzed the perception of variety and proportions of the food groups for daily intake and motivation for action in diet and physical activity. We utilized the METAPLAN method used previously in the validation of FBDG. Results and discussion: the final image was a circle that showed the variety and proportions of each food group for daily consumption (in pictures), included physical activity guidelines in a strip around the middle of the circle and a rectangle towards of bottom of the image with examples of foods high in critical nutrients in black and white. The chosen picture was modified using input from participants and validated with three additional focus groups, improving its understanding and acceptance. Conclusion: most participants understood that the image represented the relationship between healthy eating and daily physical activity, correctly identifying the food groups for which increased intake was suggested and those groups in which intake should be reduced or avoided (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Osiac, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zacarías Hasbún, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinheiro Fernandes, Anna Christina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca Morán, Lilian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González González, Carmen Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mediano Stoltze, Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares Cortés, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: las Guías Alimentarias Basadas en Alimentos (GABA) generalmente van acompañadas de una imagen para su difusión e implementación. Objetivo: diseñar y validar una imagen que represente la variedad y proporcionalidad de las nuevas guías alimentarias para la población chilena, incluyendo los alimentos altos en nutrientes críticos que es necesario evitar y la actividad física. Método: un panel de expertos analizó siete propuestas gráficas y seleccionó tres que fueron validadas con 12 grupos focales de personas de 10-14 y 20-40 años, distinto sexo, nivel socioeconómico y sector urbano/rural. Se analizó la percepción de la variedad y proporcionalidad de los grupos de alimentos a comer diariamente y la motivación a la acción en alimentación y actividad física. Se trabajó con METAPLÁN, método ya utilizado en la validación de las GABA. Resultados y discusión: la imagen definitiva es un círculo que presenta la variedad y proporcionalidad de los grupos de alimentos a consumir durante el día (en fotografías), incluye la actividad física en una franja que rodea la mitad del círculo y un rectángulo inferior con ejemplos de alimentos altos en nutrientes críticos en blanco y negro. La imagen elegida fue modificada con las aportaciones de los participantes y validada con tres nuevos grupos focales, mejorando su comprensión y aceptación. Conclusión: la mayoría de los participantes comprendió que la imagen representaba la relación entre la alimentación saludable y la actividad física diaria, identificando los grupos de alimentos de los que se sugiere comer más y de los que se necesita reducir o evitar su consumo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(2): 582-589, ago. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño y validación de la imagen para la difusión e implementación de las guías alimentarias para la población chilena</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5774</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19150^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19295^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4601^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3630^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15076</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15075^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50310</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
