<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94798</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of neuropsychological performance according to the age of onset in subjects with parkinson´s disease and parkinsonism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disorder after Alzheimer&#146;s disease, and it is characterised by tremor, bradykinesia, rigidity and postural instability. The most frequent cognitive disorder is executive dysfunction, although global deficits associated to late onset of the disease have also been reported. Aims. To describe and to compare cognitive performance in three groups with PD and one with Parkinsonism. Patients and methods. A neurological and neuropsychological evaluation was carried out on 175 patients with idiopathic PD and Parkinsonism. The data analysis was performed by comparing the results of the tests carried out on the four groups: three with PD (age of onset: juvenile, adult and late) and one with Parkinsonism, while controlling for age, schooling and time of progression. Results. In  the juvenile PD group, alterations were observed in the number of intrusions in verbal memory; in the adult PD and late PD groups, there were alterations in time in continuous visual execution. These differences disappeared when the groups were compared to each other while also controlling for age. The Parkinsonism group obtained results that were lower than those of all the groups with PD for most of the cognitive and functional variables. Conclusions. Idiopathic PD would not be the cause of multiple cognitive impairment, but of a specific alteration, mainly involving the speed of processing and information recall.  Age of onset would not be a decisive factor in the degree of impairment of cognitive functioning; important cognitive impairment was only present in the group with Parkinsonism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Acevedo, D. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tirado, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Carrilolo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Rizzo, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. La enfermedad de Parkinson (EP) es el trastorno neurodegenerativo más común después de la enfermedad de Alzheimer, y se caracteriza por temblor, bradicinesia, rigidez e inestabilidad postural. El trastorno cognitivo más común es disfunción ejecutiva, aunque también se han informado déficit globales asociados al inicio tardío de la enfermedad. Objetivos. Describir y comparar el desempeño cognitivo en tres grupos con EP y uno con parkinsonismo. Pacientes y métodos. A 175 pacientes con EP idiopática y parkinsonismo se les realizó una valoración neurológica y neuropsicológica. El análisis de datos se hizo comparando resultados de las pruebas para cuatro grupos: tres con EP (edad de inicio: juvenil, del adulto  y tardía) y uno con parkinsonismo, y controlando por edad, escolaridad y tiempo de evolución. Resultados. En el grupo conEP juvenil se encontró alteración en el número de intrusiones en memoria verbal; en los de EP del adulto y EP tardía, se encontró  alteración en el tiempo en ejecución continua visual. Comparados entre sí los grupos y controlando por edad, las diferencias desaparecieron. El grupo con parkinsonismo obtuvo resultados inferiores a todos los grupos con EP para la mayoría de variables cognitivas y funcionales. Conclusiones. La EP idiopática no sería causante de deterioro cognitivo múltiple, sino de una alteración específica, principalmente en velocidad de procesamiento y evocación de la información. La edad de inicio no sería un factor decisivo en el grado de deterioro del funcionamiento cognitivo; sólo existe un deterioro cognitivo importante en el grupo con parkinsonismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;49(3): 123-130, jul. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación del desempeño neuropsicológico según la edad de inicio en sujetos con enfermedad de Parkinson y parkinsonismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34223^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34223^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
