<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160348</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics and course of chronic hepatitis B e antigen-negative infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the epidemiological, analytical and histological characteristics and clinical course of hepatitis B virus (HBV) carriers with negative HBe antigen.  Material and methods: Observational, retrospective cohort study of HBV carriers with negative HBe antigen (2005-2012), with no other causes of liver disease. Results: One hundred and thirty-eight patients were included, with mean age 40.5±12.2 years; 54% were women, and 38% were of foreign origin; the number of foreign patients significantly increased (P&lt;.001) over the years. Transaminases were normal in nearly 75% and HBV-DNA was &lt;2,000IU/ml in 56% of patients at diagnosis. There was a gradual decrease in HBV-DNA levels in inactive carriers over the study period. Fibrosis study was performed in 47% of patients by Fibroscan® or liver biopsy: 55.4% normal histology and 6.1% cirrhosis. Just over three quarters of patients (77.77%) were inactive carriers. Treatment was required in 15.5% of patients (20% because of cirrhosis and 80% HBeAg-negative chronic hepatitis B). Five patients cleared HBsAg (annual rate .94%), all of whom presented HBV-DNA &lt;2,000IU/ml at diagnosis. Five patients developed complications (3.6%), 4 of them hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), of which only 2 had cirrhosis. There was 1 HBV-related death (.72%). Conclusion: Among HBV carriers with negative HBe antigen, inactive HBs-Ag carriers are predominant. HBV-DNA gradually decreases in the first few years after diagnosis. Morbidity and mortality are low, especially if glutamic pyruvic transaminase (GPT) is normal and HBV-DNA levels are low at diagnosis. Treatment is needed in a considerable number of patients. HCC is the most frequent complication, even in the absence of cirrhosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Simón, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vela, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban, Eva María Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Hernando, Cesar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Gutiérrez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Moreno, Ana Zaida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardiola Arévalo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Rodríguez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las características epidemiológicas, analíticas, histológicas y evolutivas de pacientes con infección crónica por VHB AgHBe-negativo. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional de cohorte retrospectivo de pacientes diagnosticados de infección crónica VHB AgHBe-negativo (2005-2012) sin otras hepatopatías. Resultados: Se incluyeron 138 pacientes con edad media de 40,5±12,2 años, de los cuales el 54% eran mujeres. El 38% eran extranjeros, con incremento de estos en los últimos años (p&lt;0,001). Las transaminasas en el momento del diagnóstico eran normales en casi el 75% y el ADN-VHB &lt;2.000UI/ml en el 56%. En los portadores inactivos existe una disminución progresiva de los niveles de ADN-VHB en el periodo de estudio. En el 47% se evaluó la fibrosis hepática por Fibroscan® o biopsia hepática: el 55,4% resultó normal y el 6,1% reportó cirrosis. El 77,77% eran portadores inactivos. Precisaron tratamiento el 15,5% (20% por cirrosis y 80% por HBC AgHBe-negativo). Aclararon el AgHBs 5 pacientes (tasa anual 0,94%), presentando todos al diagnóstico ADN-VHB &lt;2.000UI/ml. Cinco pacientes desarrollaron alguna complicación (3,6%), 4 de ellos carcinoma hepatocelular (CHC) (solo 2 presentaban cirrosis). Hubo un fallecimiento relacionado con el VHB (0,72%). Conclusión: Entre los enfermos con infección crónica por VHB AgHBe-negativo predominan los portadores inactivos. Se produce un progresivo descenso de ADN-VHB en los primeros años tras el diagnóstico. Desarrollan poca morbimortalidad, especialmente si existe GPT normal y ADN-VHB bajo al diagnóstico. Un número no despreciable de pacientes precisa tratamiento. El CHC es la complicación más frecuente, incluso en pacientes sin cirrosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;40(2): 59-69, feb. 2017. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160348</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características y evolución de la infección crónica por virus de la hepatitis B antígeno e negativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22163^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33343^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6668^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1226^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28093^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31855^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
