<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101096</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative neuropsychological study in the child and adult age and gender differences in the Down syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is well known that Down syndrome (DS) is associated to neuropsychological deficits. However, less is known about their evolution from childhood to adulthood and the neuropsychological differences between the masculine and feminine sex. To study differences in the neurophysiological state in DS in two different age groups between boys and girls. We performed a descriptive and comparative study of the 105 children and adults with DS and without DS. It was evaluated in neuropsychological tests. It was examined the differences in neuropsychological states (NS) in two dimensions: age and gender. We found significant differences between in neuropsychological test between DS patients and control subjects in childhood and adulthood. In addition, we found no differences in NS of DS subjects of the masculine and feminine sex. Deterioration of NS was observed in childhood and adulthood in DS. We found similar NS in subjects with Ds between masculine and feminine sex (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Alba, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portellano Pérez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Down (SD) es desconocido el papel de la evolución entre la edad infantil y edad adulta, y las diferencias de género en el rendimiento neuropsicológico (RN). Por otro lado, es determinante conocer qué áreas cognitivas están más preservadas y cuáles más deficitarias. Se estudia de forma comparativa el RN en función del género en edad infantil y adulta en personas con SD. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo y comparativo entre 105 sujetos con SD y comparación en edad infantil y edad adulta. Dichos grupos se separaron y compararon por sexo a través de pruebas neuropsicológicas. Se estudiaron las puntuaciones obtenidas en las pruebas neuropsicológicas por grupo, edad, y sexo. Se hallaron diferencias significativas en todas las variables neuropsicológicas entre los grupos SD y comparación. No todas las variables estudiadas presentaron el mismo grado de afección. Las puntuaciones de los sujetos con SD de sexo masculino fueron similares  a las de los sujetos de sexo femenino en todas las áreas cognitivas valoradas. Existen déficit neuropsicológicos en SD en edad infantil y adulta. Sin embargo, existe un grupo de áreas cognitivas menos afectadas. El RN en SD no varía en función del sexo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;67(1): 22-27, ene.-feb. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101096</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo neuropsicológico en edad infantil y adulta y diferencias de género en síndrome de Down</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
