<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98752</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">G and P genotypes of rotavirus circulating among children with diarrhea in the Colombian northern coast</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A study on the prevalence of rotavirus G and P genotypes was carried out based on 253 stool specimens obtained from children living in the Colombia northern coast region who were less than 3-years-old and who suffered from acute diarrhea. A previous study had detected the presence of rotavirus A in 90 (36.5%) of the 246 samples tested by enzyme immunoassay (EIA), and these strains were investigated in the present study. Of these, 50 strains yielded an RNA electropherotype, most of which (80.0%) had long profiles and 20.0% of which had short profiles. Genotyping of 84 positive samples indicated that 67.9% of the strains could be typed. G1 (57.9%), was the most predominant VP7 genotype, followed by G3 (21.1%), G9 (15.8%) and G2 (5.3%). Among the VP4 genotypes, P[4] (49.1%) was the most prevalent, followed by P[6] 36.4% and P[8] (14.5%). Neither G4 nor G8 nor P[9] types were detected. The most common G-P combinations were G3 P[4] (8.8%) and G9 P[6] (7.0%), followed by G1 P[4] and G1 P[8] (5.3% each). All G1 P[8] strains showed long RNA profiles, whereas G3 P[4] and G9 P[6] displayed both long and short patterns. Mixed infections involved 21.0% of strains. There was a marked diversity among strains collected, and novel strains, including G9, as well as other atypical combinations of G and P genotypes, such as G9 P[6] and G3 P[4], were found (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urbina, Delfina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Raimundo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arzuza, Octavio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portillo, Patricia del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra, Edgar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Juan G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Young, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo describe un estudio de la prevalencia de los genotipos G y P de rotavirus en 253 muestras fecales de niños menores de 3 años afectados de diarrea aguda que vivían en la costa norte de Colombia. Un estudio anterior reveló la presencia de rotavirus A en 90 (36.5%) de las 246muestras sometidas a inmuno ensayo y dichas muestras fueron las usadas en este estudio. En 50 de las 90 muestras usadas se obtuvo un electroferotipo, un 80.0% de perfil de RNA largo y un 20.0% de perfil de RNA corto. De 84muestras sometidas a genotipificación, se logró tipificar 67.9%. El genotipo G1(57.9%) fue predominante entre los asociados a VP7, seguido de G3(21.1%), G9 (15.8%) y G2 (5.3%). Entre los genotipos VP4, el P[4] (49.1%)fue el de mayor prevalencia, seguido de P[6] 36.4% y de P[8] (14.5%). No se detectaron los genotipos G4, G8 o P[9], y las combinaciones G-P más frecuentes fueron G3 P[4] ( 8.8%) y G9 P[6] (7.0%), seguidas de G1 P[4] y G1P[8], con 5.3% cada una. Todas las cepas G1 P[8] tenían perfil de RNA largo, mientras que G3 P[4] y G9 P[6] los tenían tanto largos como cortos. Se detectaron infecciones mixtas en el 21.0% de las cepas. Se observó una marcada diversidad en las cepas recolectadas y se identificaron cepas nuevas, como G9, y también combinaciones atípicas, como G9 P[6] y G3P[4] (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;7(2): 113-120, jun. 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Genotipos G y P de rotavirus encontrados en niños aquejados de diarrea en la costa norte de Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22286^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12776^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
