<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113712</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic yield of pancreatic percutaneous puncture depending on the size of the lesion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The aim of the present study was to study the diagnostic efficacy of the percutaneous puncture of pancreatic tissue. Material and methods A retrospective study was conducted on patients with suspicion of pancreatic neoplasm, and with a percutaneous biopsy of pancreatic tissue, from 2000 to 2011. For the statistical comparative analysis, the sample was stratified by tumour size: &amp;#8804; 3 cm and &gt; 3 cm. Results A total of 90 biopsies were performed. Pancreatic neoplasm diagnosis was made in 47 cases (52%), with 16 false negatives (18%), no false positives, and chronic pancreatitis in 24 cases (27%). The efficacy of the test results were: an overall sensitivity of 75% (95% CI: 62%-85%), a specificity of 100% (95% CI: 87%-100%), a positive predictive value of 100% (95% CI: 92%-100%), and a negative predictive value of 63% (95% CI: 46%-77%). For tumour sizes &amp;#8804; 3 cm the sensitivity was 70% (95% CI: 45%-88%), with a specificity of 100% (95% CI 66%-100%), a positive predictive value of 100% (95% CI: 76%-100%, and a negative predictive value 60% (95% CI: 32%-83%). For tumours greater than 3 cm, the sensitivity was 88% (95% CI: 70%-98%), the specificity was 100% (95% CI: 75%-100%), with a positive predictive value of 100% (95% CI: 85%-100%) and a negative predictive value of 81% (95% CI: 54%-96%).Conclusions Pancreatic percutaneous biopsy efficacy was strongly determined by lesion size. For tumour sizes less than 3 cm, the sensitivity and negative predictive value are unacceptably low, as negative results would not reliable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Quiles, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granel-Villach, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escrig Sos, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ramos, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador-Sanchis, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paiva-Coronel, Gabriel Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queralt-Martín, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarín-Rodríguez, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortea-Sanchis, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El objetivo del presente estudio fue analizar la eficacia diagnóstica de la punción percutánea de tejido pancreático. Material y métodos Estudio retrospectivo de pacientes con sospecha de neoplasia de origen pancreático, con biopsia percutánea de tejido pancreático, desde el 2000 hasta el 2011. Para el análisis estadístico comparativo se estratificó la muestra por tamaño, en menores o iguales a 3 cm frente a mayores. Resultados Se realizaron un total de 90 biopsias. Se llegó al diagnóstico de neoplasia pancreática en 47 casos (52%), 16 falsos negativos (18%), 0 falsos positivos y al de pancreatitis crónica en 24 casos (27%). Los resultados de rendimiento de la prueba fueron: sensibilidad (S) global del 75% (intervalo de confianza [IC] 95%: 62-85%), especificidad (E) del 100% (IC 95%: 87-100%), valor predictivo positivo (VPP) del 100% (IC 95%: 92-100%) y valor predictivo negativo (VPN) del 63% (IC 95%: 46-77%). En masas &amp;#8804; 3 cm la S fue del 70% (IC 95%: 45-88%), la E del 100% (IC 95%: 66-100%), el VPP del 100% (IC 95%: 76-100%) y el VPN 60% (IC 95%: 32-83%). Frente a masas mayores de 3 cm que presentaron una S del 88% (IC 95%: 70-98%), una E del 100% (IC 95%: 75-100%), un VPP del 100% (IC 95%: 85-100%) y un VPN del 81% (IC 95%: 54-96%).Conclusiones La rentabilidad de la biopsia percutánea pancreática está fuertemente condicionada por el tamaño de la lesión. Para tamaños tumorales menores de 3 cm la sensibilidad y el valor predictivo negativo son inaceptablemente bajos, porque lo que resultados negativos no serían fiables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);91(6): 361-365, jun.-jul. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rentabilidad diagnóstica de la punción percutánea pancreática en función del tamaño de la lesión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10370^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24296^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
