<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63712</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical or applied research is a procedure whose objective is to resolve questions established on each one of the stages of the care procedure to be able to improve both the daily clinical practice and quality of care given to the patients. The starting point of all research procedures is the statement of an uncertainty that is formed by formulating a research question. This allows for the development of a scientific strategy and work protocol that will lead us to solve our initial uncertainty. The questions generally arise on three main scenarios: to substitute or improve actions or interventions of the daily care practice when there are knowledge gaps or in the teaching field. To formulate a question correctly, a series of characteristics on structure and content must be gathered. The question should be correctly made operative so that its structure should contain the information necessary to make it possible to define and differentiate the type of patients and/or disease to be studied, the intervention that we are going to conduct if this is an intervention study and the measurements of the outcome that we want to know. To obtain useful results it is also desirable to gather the characteristics of feasibility, interest, novelty and relevance. A well-formulated question will help to develop other research procedure stages and will also facilitate the obtaining of results adapted to our initial question and the subsequent management of these results for both the conduction of secondary investigations and to adequately satisfy the individuals needs of knowledge</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, J. L. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seoane, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz-Pardo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Moreno, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación clínica o aplicada, es un proceso cuyo objetivo es resolver cuestiones planteadas en cada una de las etapas del proceso asistencial para poder mejorar tanto la práctica clínica diaria, como la calidad de la atención prestada a los pacientes. El punto de partida de todo proceso de investigación es el planteamiento de una incertidumbre, que toma forma mediante la formulación de una pregunta de investigación. Ésta permitirá el desarrollo de una estrategia científica y un protocolo de trabajo que nos conducirán a resolver nuestra incertidumbre inicial. Las cuestiones suelen surgir en tres escenarios principales: para sustituir o mejorar actuaciones o intervenciones de la práctica asistencial diaria, ante la existencia de lagunas de conocimiento, o en el campo de la docencia. Para formular una pregunta correctamente es necesario que reúna una serie de características en cuanto a estructura y a contenido; debe estar correctamente operativizada, de tal modo que en su estructura ha de contener la información necesaria que permita definir y diferenciar el tipo de pacientes y/ o patología a estudiar, la intervención que vamos a realizar, si se trata de un estudio de intervención y las medidas de resultado que deseamos conocer. Para la obtención de resultados útiles es deseable, además, reunir las características de factibilidad, interés, novedad y relevancia. Una pregunta bien formulada ayudará al desarrollo de otras etapas del proceso de investigación, y además, facilitará la obtención de resultados ajustados a nuestra cuestión inicial y el posterior manejo de éstos, tanto para la realización de investigaciones secundarias, como para satisfacer adecuadamente las necesidades individuales de conocimiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(3): 149-153, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63712</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5204</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28085</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
