<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123149</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Updated critical review of the obturation with the Thermafil System and its successor: GuttaCore</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The root filling system Thermafil is based on a plastic carrier covered by gutta-percha. Its successor, GuttaCore, consists of a cross linked gutta-percha core with the purpose offacilitate its removal keeping the good properties offered by the thermoplastic gutta-percha. The aim of this review is to describe both based - in - carrier root filling systems Thermafil and GuttaCore and analyze some of the most important aspects of the endodontic obturation such as the sealing ability, the easiness of retreatment and the apical leakage. For this we have carried out a literature search through Medline using publications after the year2002, except for the inclusion of older articles because of its importance. As a result, we found that Thermafil System achieves hermetic and tridimensional obturations in all kinds of root canals except in resorptivecavities and in the absence of the apical constriction. Its learning curve is fast as well as the time of its performance. The disadvantages of this system are the longer time for the removal of the carrier and the often overextended obturations. The GuttaCore system seems to facilitate the retreatment&#146;s (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Algar Pinilla, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez Luaña, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia de Pablo, Óliver</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sueiras, Marta Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Cabello, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sistema de obturación Thermafil se basa en un vástago de plástico recubierto de gutapercha. Su evolución, GuttaCore, consta de un núcleo de gutapercha entrelazada con el objetivo de facilitar la remoción de éste manteniendo a la vez las buenas propiedades ofrecidas por la gutapercha termoplástica. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir ambos sistemas y analizar algunos de los aspectos más importantes de la obturación endodóntica como la capacidad desellado, la facilidad de retratamiento y la filtración apical. Para ello se ha efectuado un búsqueda bibliográfica a través de Medline utilizando publicaciones posteriores al año2002, exceptuando la inclusión de artículos más antiguos dada su relevancia. Como resultado, hemos observado que el sistema Thermafil consigue obturaciones herméticas y tridimensionales en todo tipo de conductos a excepción de reabsorciones internas o ausencia de constricción apical. Su curva de aprendizaje es rápida, así como su tiempo de ejecución. Los inconvenientes de este (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);11(1): 21-31, ene.-abr. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123149</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión crítica actualizada sobre la obturación con el Sistema Thermafil y su sucesor: GuttaCore</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12762^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12538^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3778^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3808^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
