<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128059</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family history of epilepsy resistant to treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Family aggregation can help determine the risk of epilepsy among relatives. Our aims are to describe the prevalence of family precedents of epilepsy among the diagnosed patients&#146; relatives of the first and second degree, and to look for an association with diverse clinical variables. Patients and methods. Market descriptive prospective study in a transverse cohort of a Spanish population. The study included 71 patients who, besides fulfilling the clinical diagnostic criteria, had a video-electroencephalogram compatible with epilepsy and drug resistance. The following variables were gathered: the first or second degree of family history, the location (temporal lateral, temporal mesial, parietal, frontal) of the epileptic abnormality, age at diagnosis, and type of epilepsy. The frequency and percentage were calculated of every variable. The probability of recurrence in a relative of the first or second degree was calculated by means of the relative risk (RR). Results. On the whole, the gender distribution was 34 (47.9%) males and 37 (52.1%) females, with ages of 28.3 ± 10.3 years and 34.3 ± 10.2 years, respectively. The prevalence of family aggregation of epilepsy was 28 (34.9%). Familyaggregation was more probable among males (RR = 2.5), when the diagnosis of epilepsy was realized between 13 and 18 years old (RR = 1.7), or when the epileptogenic area is located in the temporal mesial zone (RR = 1.9). Conclusions. Our study supports the existence of increased risk of epilepsy among relatives of drug-resistant epileptic patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Cerezo, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando-Requejo, Virgilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios-Espichan, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Millares, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera-Peco, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola, Rafael G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Guillermo J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La agregación familiar puede ayudar a determinar el riesgo de epilepsia entre los familiares. Se plantea como objetivo la descripción de la prevalencia de antecedentes familiares de primer y segundo grado de epilepsia entre los familiares de los pacientes diagnosticados, y para buscar una asociación con diversas variables clínicas. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio prospectivo descriptivo en una cohorte transversal. Se estudiaron 71 pacientes epilépticos farmacorresistentes que cumplían los criterios diagnósticos clínicos, así como las pruebas diagnósticas (electroencefalografía, videoelectroencefalografía) compatibles con epilepsia. Se recogieron las variables: antecedentes familiares de primer o segundo grado, la localización (lateral temporal, mesial temporal, parietal, frontal) del área epileptógena, la edad en el momento del diagnóstico y el tipo de epilepsia. Se calculó la frecuencia y el porcentaje. La probabilidad de recurrencia de un familiar de primer grado o segundo se calculó mediante el riesgo relativo (RR). Resultados. En general, la distribución por sexos fue de 34 (47,9%) hombres y 37 (52,1%) mujeres, con edades de 28,3 ± 10,3 años y 34,3 ± 10,2 años, respectivamente. La prevalencia de la agregación familiar de epilepsia fue 28 (34,9%). La agregación familiar fue más probable entre los hombres (RR = 2,5), cuando el diagnóstico de la epilepsia se realizó entre los 13 y 18 años de edad (RR = 1,7) o cuando el área epileptógena se encontraba en la zona temporal mesial (RR = 1,9). Conclusiones. Nuestro estudio apoya la existencia de mayor riesgo de epilepsia entre los familiares de los pacientes epilépticos farmacorresistentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;52(9): 522-526, mayo 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128059</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antecedentes familiares en epilepsias refractarias al tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6702^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
