<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119178</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">False positive results of trisomy 21 prenatal screening as a surrogate marker for adverse pregnancy outcome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Hypertensive disorders of pregnancy, intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR) and preterm delivery are pathologies associated with significant fetal and maternal morbidity and mortality. This study evaluates the usefulness of false positive results for trisomy 21 prenatal screening and isolated changes in biochemical screening markers for the identification of increased risk for those pregnancy complications. Method: Two case&#150;control studies were performed: the association of those pathologies with a false positive screening (Integrated or Double) and the distribution of the biochemical markers, PAPP-A, free beta-hCG and alpha-Fetoprotein (AFP), in affected and unaffected pregnant women. The population included all the 4224 pregnant women who underwent prenatal screening for trisomy 21 in Hospital S. Francisco Xavier, Lisbon, between March 2003 and August 2007. Results: The association was significant (P &lt; 0.05) between IUGR and false positives for Integrated and 2nd trimester screening and between IUGR and isolated changes in the three biochemical markers. Isolated changes of PAPP-A and AFP were significantly associated with preterm delivery and hypertensive disorders of pregnancy, respectively. Conclusion: Screening false positive results or isolated changes in biochemical screening markers are surrogate markers of increased risk for placental pathology. This information is available before 20 weeks of gestation and can be used in follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvalho Rodrigues, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La hipertensión del embarazo, el retraso del crecimiento intrauterino (RCIU) y el parto prematuro son enfermedades asociadas a morbimortalidad maternofetal significativa. Este estudio evalúa la utilidad de los falsos positivos y de los cambios aislados en los marcadores bioquímicos del cribado prenatal de la trisomía 21 para la identificación de un mayor riesgo para estas enfermedades. Método: Se hicieron 2 estudios caso-control: uno de la asociación entre los falsos positivos por el cribado (integrado y del segundo trimestre) y aquellas enfermedades y otro de la distribución de los marcadores bioquímicos, PAPP-A, fracción libre de la beta-hCG y alfa-fetoproteína (AFP), en mujeres embarazadas afectadas y no afectadas. La población de estudio incluyó todos los 4.224 cribados realizados en el Hospital S. Francisco Xavier (Lisboa), entre marzo de 2003 y agosto de 2007. Resultados: La asociación fue significativa (p &lt; 0,05) entre el RCIU y los falsos positivos del cribado integrado y del segundo trimestre y entre el RCIU y los cambios aislados de los 3 marcadores bioquímicos. Los cambios aislados de PAPP-A y AFP se asociaron significativamente con el parto prematuro y la hipertensión del embarazo, respectivamente. Conclusión: Los falsos positivos en el cribado o cambios aislados en los marcadores bioquímicos son marcadores indirectos de un mayor riesgo de efermedad placentaria. Esta información está disponible antes de las 20 semanas de gestación y puede ser utilizada en el seguimiento del embarazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);24(4): 135-140, oct.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los falsos positivos del cribado prenatal de la trisomía 21 como marcador sustituto para complicaciones del embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5290</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
