<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121068</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Goals. Perform a comparative evaluation on the smoking condition on the house staff of the Carmen Hospital (province of Mendoza) with national surveys of the general population (Argentina) during a 15-yearperiod.Equipment and methods. Observational and retrospective study, between 1997 and 2012. A survey regarding smoking was performed in three specific periods (1997-2004-2012). They were compared with each other and also with national surveys. Results: A decrease in the percentage of Current Smokers was observed in the health care staff as well as in the general population (13.5 and 17.7, respectively). A decrease in the percentage of former smoker was also observed in the health care staff (8.3%) as well as the general population (10.1%). Among health care workers, a statistically significant increase in the number of people who never smoked was noted (p=0.0067), at 21.8%, and in the general population it was 27.8%.Conclusions. A positive generation change was noted in the increase of the number of people who have never smoked, reason why the prevention policies should be maintained, so the changes will endure over time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Di Giorgi, L. di</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grañana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lisanti, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delaballe, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gatica, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Realizar una evaluación comparativa de la condición de tabaquismo en el personal de planta del Hospital del Carmen (provincia de Mendoza) con encuestas nacionales de la población general (Argentina) durante un período de 15 años. Material y métodos. Estudio observacional y retrospectivo, comprendido entre 1997 y 2012. Se realizó una encuesta sobre tabaquismo en tres períodos puntuales (1997-2004-2012), fueron comparadas entre sí y a su vez con las encuestas nacionales. Resultados. Se observó una disminución en el porcentaje de fumadores actuales, tanto en el personal de salud como en la población general (13,5 y 17,7% respectivamente);a su vez se observó un reducción del porcentaje de extabaquistas en el personal de salud (8,3%) y la población general (10,1%). En el personal de salud se observó un aumento del número de personas que nunca fumaron estadísticamente significativo (p=0,0067) del 21,8% y en la población general del 27,8%. Conclusiones. Se ha producido un cambio generacional positivo, observándose un aumento del número de personas que nunca fumaron; por lo tanto, se deben mantener las políticas de prevención para que los cambios sean perdurables en el tiempo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;16(1): 21-27, ene.-mar. 2014. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121068</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación del tabaquismo en Argentina entre el personal de salud y población general (periodo 1997 a 2012)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
