<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131418</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Support to families of critically ill patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The hospitalization of the sick person in the family creates anxiety, stress, etc... The families in this situation have no tools to face reality and ignore their needs. Objective. To identify the relationship between family needs and nursing interventions. Methods. We conducted a literature review in the databases Pub- Med, CINAHL, Cuidatge, Cuiden and ScienceDirect. After including items that meet the selection criteria were selected 18 items Results and discussion. In selected items were analyzed the necessities generated by the hospitalization of a family member in the ICU, performances, interventions and proposals for improvement that are proposed to meet the needs and constraints and reluctance that occur in practice. Conclusions. Although the literature identifies the needs of the family, the problems encountered and solutions proposed, the nurses do not integrate these needs into their operations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coromina Pérez, Susanna G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hospitalización de la persona enferma genera en la familia ansiedad, estrés, etc. Los familiares, en esta situación, no tienen herramientas para afrontar la realidad y desatienden sus necesidades. Objetivo. Identificar la correlación entre las necesidades de la familia y las intervenciones enfermeras. Metodología. Se realizó una revisión bibliográfica en las bases de datos Pubmed, CINAHL, Cuidatge, Cuiden y ScienceDirect. Después de incluir los artículos que cumplían los criterios de selección, se seleccionaron 18 artículos. Resultados y discusión. En los artículos escogidos se analizaron las necesidades que genera la hospitalización de un familiar en la UCI, las actuaciones, intervenciones y propuestas de mejora que se proponen para satisfacer las necesidades y las limitaciones y reticencias que se producen en la práctica. Conclusiones. A pesar de que en la literatura se identifican las necesidades de la familia, los problemas que se plantean y las soluciones que se proponen, las enfermeras no integran estas necesidades en sus intervenciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(1): 22-30, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131418</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acompañamiento a la familia del paciente crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35418^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10548^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10548^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
