<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106150</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of coagulation and anti-Xa factor using a heparin-coated AN69ST® dialyser</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Haemodialysis systems are potentially thrombogenic, so anticoagulation is routinely used. Its prescription involves certain risks, despite which the recommendations regarding dosage are still based on very disparate criteria. Methods: We performed a randomised, crossed pilot study. Six patients underwent six sessions of post-dilution haemodiafiltration with a polysulfone HF80® dialyser and standard anticoagulation with nadroparin, and six sessions with heparincoated poliacrylonitrile AN69ST® membrane without the administration of systemic anticoagulation therapy. The coagulation level of the dialyser and extracorporeal circuit was evaluated every hour using a visual scale along with variation in clotting parameters such as anti-Xa factor. Our primary objective was to assess anti-Xa activity in the absence of differences in the rate of massive coagulation between the two groups. Results: No complete or grade 4 dialyser clotting occurred in any of the 36 sessions with either dialyser. Partial clotting of the dialyser occurred below 25% (grade 1-2) in 32 (88.9%) AN69ST® sessions and 35 (97.2%) sessions using the standard dialyser, and partial clotting surpassed 25% (grade 3-4) in 4 (11.1%) AN69ST® sessions and 1 (2.8%) dialysis session with heparin. Arterial chamber blood clotting did not surpass 25% (grade 3 and 4) in any of the studied sessions, and venous chamber coagulation occurred in only 1 (2.8%) session with the usual dialyser and in 3 (8.4%) sessions with the AN69ST®, with no significant differences between the two  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvetti, M. Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamarit, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Canel, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villatoro, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Gordo, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons-Prades, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Alba, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seores, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los sistemas de hemodiálisis tienen capacidad trombogénica, por lo que se utiliza de forma rutinaria la anticoagulación. Su prescripción no se encuentra exenta de riesgos, a pesar de lo cual las recomendaciones respecto a la dosis pautada siguen basándose en criterios muy diversos. Métodos: Se realizó un estudio experimental aleatorizado y cruzado. Seis pacientes realizaron seis sesiones de hemodiafiltración posdilución con el dializador de polisulfona HF80® y anticoagulación habitual con nadroparina, y seis sesiones con el dializador AN69ST® de poliacrilonitrilo con una cubierta de heparina sin el uso de anticoagulación sistémica. Evaluamos cada hora el grado de coagulación del dializador y del circuito extracorpóreo mediante una escala visual y las variaciones en los parámetros de coagulación, entre los que se incluyó el factor anti-Xa. Nuestro objetivo primario fue valorar las variaciones en la actividad del factor anti-Xa en ausencia de diferencias en la tasa de coagulación masiva entre los dos grupos. Resultados: No se coaguló el dializador de forma completa o grado 4 en ninguna de las 36 sesiones realizadas con cada dializador. Se produjo una coagulación parcial del dializador inferior del 25% (grado 1-2) en 32 (88,9%) sesiones con AN69ST® y 35 (97,2%) con el dializador habitual, y superior del 25% (grado 3-4) en 4 (11,1%) sesiones con AN69ST® y en 1 (2,8%) sesión con el dializador con heparina. La coagulación del atrapaburbujas arterial no fue superior al 25% (grados 3 y 4) en ninguna de las sesiones estudiadas, y la cámara venosa en sólo 1 (2,8%) sesión con el dializador habitual y 3 (8,4%) con AN69ST® sin diferencias entre los dos dializadores. El  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;32(5): 605-612, sept.-oct. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106150</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración del grado de coagulación y del factor anti-Xa al introducir el dializador AN69ST® con heparina impregnada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23606^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24646^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
