<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113404</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evacuation jeans in the spanish Infantería de Marina. Sanitary lessons learned from Bosnia-Herzegovine, Iraq, Haitiand Lebannon</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to the recently presence of the spanish Infantería de Marina in several Operations&#146; Theatres, the Sanidad Militar was deployed supporting this force with personnel, materials and vehicles. This article intends to show the sanitary lessons learned with the use od PINANHA IIIC 8x8 Ambulance, Ambulance Truck IVECO 40.10.wm  «stretcher-porter» version and «mobile ICU») and Stretcher-porter Hummer M-1035 in FIMAR (Bosnia-Herzegovine), Sierra Juliet Operative (Iraq), FIMEX-H (Haiti) and FIMEX-L (Lebannon)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Redondo Castán, L. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plaza Torres, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Suay, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mota Ortega, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Manzanedo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Moreno, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Debido a la reciente presencia de la Infantería de Marina Española en diversos Teatros de Operaciones, la Sanidad Militar se ha desplegado apoyando a este Cuerpo con personal, material y vehículos. Este artículo pretende mostrar las lecciones sanitarias aprendidas tras el empleo del PINANHA IIIC 8x8  ambulancia, Camión Ambulancia IVECO 40.10.wm (versión «portacamillas» y «UCI móvil») y Hummer Portacamillas M-1035 en FIMAR (Bosnia-Herzegovina), Operación Sierra Juliet (Irak), FIMEX- H (Haití) y FIMEX-L (Líbano)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;64(1): 31-40, ene.-mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113404</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medios de evacuación en la Infantería de Marina Española. Lecciones sanitarias aprendidas de Bosnia-Herzegovina, Irak, Haití y Líbano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34704</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28835^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22766^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54373^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
