<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87937</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical characteristics of patients under treatment for osteoporosis in a Primary Care Centre. Who do we treat?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesTo find out the clinical and demographic features of patients in treatment for osteoporosis, look for risk factors for osteoporosis and bone fractures, and assess whether treatment is indicated.DesignDescriptive study of a series of cases.LocationPrimary Care Centre, Madrid.Participants216 patients on treatment for osteoporosis during 2007.Principal measuresSociodemographic variables, osteoporosis risk factors, risk of falling, prescription and treatment related information. To evaluate if treatment is indicated we have used principal medical guidelines.ResultsMost of our patients were Caucasian women with a mean age of 66.14 years. A total of 39.5% had suffered an osteoporotic fracture and 16.12% had family history of osteoporotic fracture. The majority of our registers,73.15%, do not report information on Dual-Energy X-ray Absorptiometry (DEXA), and 73.13% do not make any reference to bone mineral density. Risk factors are not recorded in most of the clinical histories. Only 51.85% of the treatments were well indicated, and 44% of them began at a primary health care centre.ConclusionsNearly 50% of treatments are not well indicated and a high percentage of our clinical histories do not record risk factors correctly. We should improve our clinical histories, as we are responsible for identifying, studying, evaluating, treating and controlling the progress of osteoporosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Felipe, Ricardo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cimas, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávila, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cáceres, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosConocer las características demográficas y clínicas de los pacientes con tratamiento para la osteoporosis; identificar los factores de riesgo y de fractura y valorar la indicación del tratamiento.DiseñoEstudio descriptivo de una serie de casos.EmplazamientoCentro de Atención Primaria de la Comunidad de Madrid.ParticipantesDoscientos dieciséis pacientes con algún tratamiento para la osteoporosis durante el año 2007.Mediciones principalesVariables sociodemográficas, factores de riesgo para osteoporosis, riesgo de caídas e información relacionada con la prescripción y el tratamiento. Para valorar la indicación de tratamiento nos basamos en las recomendaciones de las principales guías clínicas.ResultadosLa mayoría de las pacientes eran mujeres caucásicas con edad media de 66,1 años (DE: 12,2). El 39,3% tiene registrado un antecedente personal de fractura y en un 16,1% existe la fractura como antecedente familiar. El 73,1% de las historias no tiene ninguna referencia a la densitometría ósea. La existencia de factores de riesgo no está reflejada en un altísimo porcentaje de historias clínicas. Solo el 51,8% cumplía criterios para iniciar tratamiento. El 44% de los tratamientos se inician en Atención Primaria.ConclusionesCasi el 50% de los tratamientos no están correctamente indicados y en un alto porcentaje de las historias no se registran correctamente los factores de riesgo. Debemos mejorar la calidad de nuestras historias clínicas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;42(11): 559-563, nov. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87937</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características clínicas de los pacientes con tratamiento para la osteoporosis en un centro de Atención Primaria: ¿a quién tratamos en nuestras consultas?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
