<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051834</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish version of the Coping Strategies Inventory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of the present study was to adapt the Coping Strategies Inventory (CSI) to the Spanish setting. This need is justified on the one hand by the shortage and limitations of the instruments available in our language and, on the other, by the excellent potentialities that the CSI offers.        Method. It was translated and applied to a sample of 337 adults, with diverse demographic characteristics, recruited from different teaching activities by the authors in the province of Seville (Spain).                Results. The results showed excellent psychometric properties surpassing those of the original study: eight factors accounted for 61 % of variance with only 40 items (as opposed to the 72 that accounted for 47% in the original study) and obtained Alpha coefficients between 0.63 and 0.89. The convergent validity was verified using intercorrelations between scales, correlations with personality dispositions (NEOFFI) and with the coping efficacy.                Discussion. The CSI was a valid and reliable measure of coping strategies used in many stressful situations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Franco, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano García, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En el presente trabajo acometimos la adaptación del Inventario de Estrategias de Afrontamiento (CSI) al ámbito español. Esta necesidad se justifica, por una parte, por la escasez y las limitaciones de los instrumentos disponibles en nuestro idioma, y por otra, por las excelentes potencialidades que ofrece el CSI.        Método. Fue traducido y aplicado a una muestra de 337 personas adultas de características sociodemográficas diversas, recogida de forma incidental en actividades formativas en la provincia de Sevilla.                Resultados. Los resultados mostraron unas excelentes propiedades psicométricas superando incluso las del estudio original: ocho factores explicaron un 61 % de la varianza con sólo 40 ítems (frente a los 72 que explicaban un 47% en el instrumento original) y obtuvieron coeficientes de consistencia interna entre 0,63 y 0,89. La validez convergente se comprobó utilizando las intercorrelaciones entre escalas y las correlaciones con disposiciones de personalidad (NEO-FFI) y eficacia percibida del afrontamiento.                Conclusiones. El CSI se comportó de forma válida y fiable en la evaluación de la utilización de estrategias de afrontamiento en una amplia variedad de situaciones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;35(1): 29-39, ene.-feb. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051834</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación española del Inventario de Estrategias de Afrontamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
