<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122089</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urinary incontinence during pregnancy and postpartum. Associated risk factors and influence of pelvic floor exercises</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To determine the prevalence of urinary incontinence (UI) before pregnancy, in the third trimester and postpartum. To analyze its influence on quality of life and associated potential risk factors and the efficacy of pelvic floor exercises. METHODS: Prospective study in 413 pregnant women. The modified ICIQ-SF incontinence questionnaire was given to the pregnant women at the end of the third quarter. This questionnaire was administered by telephone at 3 and 6 months postpartum. The influence of several risk factors for UI in pregnancy and postpartum were analyzed. Patients with persistent UI at 6 months postpartum were trained to do pelvic floor exercises. RESULTS: Patients with UI before pregnancy were excluded from the study. UI in the third trimester was 31%. Analyzed risk factors did not condition a higher percentage of UI. Prevalence of UI was 11.3% at 3 months postpartum and 6.9% at 6 months. 70% of the incontinent patients already had it during pregnancy and it appeared de novo post-delivery in 30% of the patients. Prevalence of UI after delivery was higher in women with UI in pregnancy and lower in caesarean cases. Most women improved with pelvic floor exercises. CONCLUSIONS: Analysed risk factors did not significantly increase UI in pregnancy. Prevalence of UI after delivery is higher in women with UI in pregnancy and lower in caesarean cases. Postpartum pelvic floor exercises for three months in patients with persistent stress UI at 6 months postpartum clearly improved the degree of continence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Martín, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Moreno, Marifé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Colomo, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortiñas-González, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual-Férnandez, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-González, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Determinar la prevalencia de incontinencia urinaria (IU) previa a la gestación, en el tercer trimestre y en el postparto. Analizar su influencia en la calidad de vida, los posibles factores de riesgo y la eficacia de los ejercicios del suelo pélvico. MÉTODOS: Estudio prospectivo a 413 gestantes. Se entregó el cuestionario de incontinencia ICIQ-SF modificado a las gestantes al final del tercer trimestre y a los 3 y 6 meses postparto. Se analizó la influencia de varios factores de riesgo de IU en el embarazo y en el postparto. Las pacientes con persistencia de IU a los 6 meses del parto fueron instruidas para realizar ejercicios de suelo pélvico. RESULTADOS: Las pacientes con IU previa a la gestación fueron excluidas. La prevalencia de incontinencia en el tercer trimestre en gestantes fue del 31%. Ningún factor de riesgo condicionó un mayor porcentaje de IU. La prevalencia de IU fue de 11.3 % a los tres meses del parto y del 6.9% a los 6 meses. De las pacientes incontinentes un 70% ya la sufría en el embarazo y en el 30% apareció de novo tras el parto. El porcentaje de IU postparto fue más elevado en mujeres con IU en la gestación y más bajo en aquellas con cesárea. La mayoría de las mujeres mejoraron con ejercicios de suelo pélvico. CONCLUSIONES: Ningún factor de riesgo aumenta el riesgo de IU en gestantes de forma significativa. La prevalencia de IU tras el parto es mayor en aquellas mujeres con IU en el embarazo y más baja en aquellas con cesárea. La mayoría de las puerperas mejoraron con ejercicios de suelo pélvico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(4): 323-330, mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122089</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incontinencia urinaria en embarazo y postparto. Factores de riesgo asociados e influencia de los ejercicios del suelo pélvico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54529^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
