<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129438</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the Spanish version of the Cardiff Anomalous Perceptions Scale in the general population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Interest in the existence of anomalous perceptions in the general population has increased greatly over recent years. Because of this, it has been possible to extend the knowledge regarding the theory of psychosis as a dimensional model. This study has aimed to validate the Spanish version of the Cardiff Anomalous Perceptions Scale (CAPS) the general population. Method: A descriptive, controlled and cross-sectional study was performed. It evaluated 324 participants from the general population with the Spanish translation of the CAPS, the 21-item Peter et al. Delusions Inventory, the Revised Launay-Slade Hallucinations Scale and the reduced Oxford-Liverpool Inventory of Feelings and Experiences (O-LIFE).Results. The results indicate that the Spanish version of the CAPS has good internal consistency and test-retest reliability. Analysis of the relationship with other scales indicates evidence of good convergent and divergent validity and the exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis of the CAPS showed a structure with three consistent factors. Conclusions: The Spanish version of the CAPS is a valid and reliable psychometric measure of the anomalous perceptual experiences in the general population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jaén-Moreno, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Díaz, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bell, Vaughan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque-Luque, Rogelio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: En los últimos años se ha incrementado el interés por la existencia de alteraciones de la percepción en la población general, esto ha contribuido a profundizaren la teoría de la psicosis como un modelo dimensional. El objetivo del presente estudio es el de validar la versión española de la escala de Percepciones Anómalas de Cardiff (CAPS) en población general. Método: Estudio descriptivo, controlado y transversal en el que se evaluó a 324 sujetos de población general con la CAPS, el Inventario de Ideas Delirantes de Peters de 21 ítems, con la Escala revisada de Alucinaciones de Launay-Slade y el Inventario reducido de Oxford-Liverpool de Sentimientos y Experiencias. Resultados: Los resultados demuestran que la CAPS en su versión española posee buena consistencia interna y una adecuada fiabilidad test-retest. Las correlaciones con las demás escalas proporcionan evidencia de una buena validez convergente-divergente y el análisis factorial exploratorio y confirmatorio de la CAPS reflejaron una estructura de tres factores consistente. Conclusiones: La versión española de la CAPS es un instrumento de evaluación psicométrica fiable y válido para la medición de las experiencias anómalas en población general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;42(1): 1-8, ene.-feb. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión española de la Escala de Percepciones Anómalas de Cardiff en población general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
