<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136247</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rest gated-SPECT myocardial perfusion post 99mTc-MIBI injection in a patient with acute chest pain and with no medical history of ischemic heart disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gated-SPECT myocardial perfusion imaging is a widely used technique indicated for assessment of patients with no clear diagnosis of ischemic heart disease. Early rest gated-SPECT myocardial perfusion study in patients with acute chest pain has high sensitivity and high negative predictive value for ruling out coronary disease. We report a case of a patient admitted for the study of her chest pain. She underwent a myocardial perfusion stress-rest whose interpretation could have been equivocal due to the clinical status of the patient during the injection of the radiotracer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marin-Buriticá, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferran-Sureda, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bassaganyas-Vilarrasa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muntaner-Muñoz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Negre-Busó, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubió-Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio gated-SPECT de perfusión miocárdica es una técnica utilizada e indicada para la valoración de los pacientes con un diagnóstico no claro de cardiopatía isquémica. El estudio gated-SPECT de reposo precoz en fase aguda tiene una alta sensibilidad y alto valor predictivo negativo para descartar enfermedad coronaria. Presentamos el caso de una paciente ingresada para el estudio de dolor torácico, a la que se le realizó un estudio de perfusión miocárdica de esfuerzo-reposo, cuyo resultado podría haber sido equívoco debido al estado clínico de la paciente durante la inyección del radiofármaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);34(3): 191-196, mayo-jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136247</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gated-SPECT de reposo tras inyección intradolor de 99mTc-MIBI en paciente sin antecedentes de cardiopatía isquémica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53211^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30483</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
