<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77143</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Terrorism, Public Health and Health Services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Today the terrorism is a problem of global distribution and increasing interest for the international public health. The terrorism related violence affects the public health and the health care services in an important way and in different scopes, among them, increase mortality, morbidity and disability, generates a context of fear and anxiety that makes the psychopathological diseases very frequent, seriously alters the operation of the health care services and produces important social, political and economic damages. These effects are, in addition, especially intense when the phenomenon takes place on a chronic way in a community. The objective of this paper is to examine the relation between terrorism and public health, focusing on its effects on public health and the health care services, as well as to examine the possible frames to face the terrorism as a public health concern, with special reference to the situation in Spain.To face this problem, both the public health systems and the health care services, would have to especially adapt their approaches and operational methods in six high-priority areas related to: (1) the coordination between the different health and non health emergency response agencies; (2) the reinforcement of the epidemiological surveillance systems; (3) the improvement of the capacities of the public health laboratories and response emergency care systems to specific types of terrorism as the chemical or biological terrorism; (3) the mental health services; (4) the planning and coordination of the emergency response of the health services; (5) the relations with the population and mass media and, finally; (6) a greater transparency in the diffusion of the information and a greater degree of analysis of the carried out health actions in the scope of the emergency response (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro Delgado, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuartas Álvarez, Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcos González, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Berrocal Alonso, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El terrorismo es hoy un problema de distribución global e interés creciente para la salud pública internacional. La violencia que comporta afecta a la salud pública y los servicios sanitarios de manera importante y en diferentes ámbitos, entre ellos, aumenta la mortalidad, morbilidad y discapacidad, genera un contexto de miedo y ansiedad que hace muy frecuentes los trastornos psicopatológicos, altera gravemente el funcionamiento de los servicios sanitarios y produce importantes daños sociales, políticos y económicos. Estos efectos son, además, especialmente intensos cuando el fenómeno se produce de manera crónica en una comunidad. El objetivo de este trabajo es examinar la relación entre terrorismo y salud pública, particularmente en cuanto a sus efectos sobre esta y sobre los servicios sanitarios, así como examinar los posibles marcos de abordaje del terrorismo como problema de salud pública, con especial referencia a la situación en España.Frente a este problema, tanto los sistemas de salud pública como los servicios sanitarios, deberían adaptar sus enfoques y funcionamiento especialmente en seis ámbitos prioritarios relacionados con: (1) La coordinación entre las diferentes agencias de respuesta sanitaria y no sanitaria; (2) El refuerzo de los sistemas de vigilancia epidemiológica; (3) La mejora de las capacidades de los laboratorios de salud pública y de los sistemas de respuesta sanitaria a tipos específicos de terrorismo como son el terrorismo químico o biológico; (3) Los servicios de salud mental; (4) La planificación y coordinación de la respuesta de emergencia de los servicios sanitarios; (5) Las relaciones con la población y los medios de comunicación y, finalmente; (6) Una mayor transparencia en la difusión de la información y un mayor grado de análisis de las acciones sanitarias llevadas a cabo en el ámbito de la respuesta de emergencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;83(3): 361-370, mayo - jun. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77143</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terrorismo, Salud Pública y Sistemas Sanitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2666</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13323^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32497</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52889^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35430</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35431</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
