<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-19281</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The evolution of the social representations regarding health of women from Madrid, Spain, 1993-2000</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In 1993, initial research was conducted among the women in Madrid. In 2000, a second research was conducted for the purpose of analyzing the possible evolution of the social representations related to health among women and, if necessary, to therefore reorient the health programs set forth in 1993 in terms of the new results of the research. The aim was therefore to analyze the possible advancement of the opinions stated, of the health-related social representations which each one of the five types encountered in 1993 might express throughout the 1993-2000 period. Methods: The qualitative research conducted in 2000 was based on the holding of 10 discussion groups defined according to the women's "typologies" which had been set out in the 1993 research. The types in question were characterized in terms of different sociodemographic variables and of the role which they had stated as most important in 1993. The analysis of the stated opinions was put into graphic and topological form in order to display the aforementioned trend in the social representations. Result: This research revealed some major changes having taken place throughout the 1993-2000 period. the predominant stated opinion-related perspective had evolved out of the "housewife" role to the "working woman" role in 2000. the predominant social representations stressed a dimension more nearing a persona balance in 2000, in which the role of women themselves, outside the bounds of their families, is of major importance. The scope of their concerns also evolved to a concern related to the stress involved in being a working woman plus a housewife. Conclusions:. This study made it possible to reach conclusions of a methodological type related to the ability of the qualitative methodology to make comparative, time-based studies and to conclusions of a more pragmatic type which afforded the possibility of changing the orientation of certain health programs aimed at women along a line more closely in keeping with their true concerns (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: En 1993 se realizó una primera investigación entre las mujeres madrileñas. En el año 2000 se llevó a cabo una segunda con el objetivo de analizar la posible evolución de las representaciones sociales sobre la salud en las mujeres y, en consecuencia, reorientar, si fuese necesario, los programas de salud definidos en 1993 en función de los nuevos resultados de la investigación. De esta forma, se pretendía analizar la posible evolución de los discursos, de las representaciones sociales sobre la salud que pudiera expresar entre 1993 y el 2000 cada uno de los cinco tipos encontrados en el 1993. Métodos: La investigación cualitativa en el 2000 se basó en la realización de 10 grupos de discusión, definidos en función de las 'tipologías' de mujeres que se habían construido en la investigación de 1993. La caracterización de los tipos se realizó en función de las distintas variables sociodemográficas y de rol que se habían expresado más importantes en 1993. El análisis de los discursos se tradujo en una forma gráfica, topológica para visualizar la citada evolución de las representaciones sociales. Resultados: La investigación puso de manifiesto importantes cambios entre 1993 y el 2000. En el 2000 la citada perspectiva discursiva había evolucionado del rol de 'ama de casa' al rol de 'mujer trabajadora'; en el 2000 las representaciones sociales dominantes hacían hincapié en una dimensión más cercana al equilibrio personal en lo que el papel de la propia mujer, más allá de su familia, tiene mucha importancia; el ámbito de la preocupaciones también evolucionaba, pasando al estrés por la doble jornada laboral. Conclusiones: El estudio permitió obtener conclusiones de tipo metodológico, vinculadas a la capacidad de la metodología cualitativa para hacer estudios comparativos y temporales, y conclusiones de carácter más pragmático, que permitieron reorientar determinados programas de salud orientados a las mujeres en una línea más cercana a sus preocupaciones  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;76(5): 493-507, sept. 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evolución de las representaciones sociales sobre la salud de las mujeres madrileñas, 1993-2000</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Conde, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gabriel, Concha</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-19281</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29154</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
