<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76065</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differential aspects in children and adult patients with medulloblastoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Medulloblastoma is the more frequent malignant cerebral tumor in childhood. Patients and methods: This is an observational study of a retrospective cohort in which there were included all the patients diagnosed of medulloblastoma in the last 19 years (1989&#150;2007) in Hospital de Cruces of Baracaldo, Vizcaya, Spain. Results: There were included 37 patients, 20 men and 17 women, with ages between 1 and 48 years (average age 13.7 years with standard deviation 11.4). Tumor site and mortality according to initial dissemination were variables of statistic significance. Metastases were detected at diagnosis in two patients. The surgical resection was total in 75% of the patients. A relapse was diagnosed in the follow-up in 59.5% of the patients, with a positive spinal fluid in 27%. Sequelae were detected in 100% of the survivors, mainly with cerebellar and ocular alterations. One patient developed a meningioma and a maxillary sarcoma at the long term follow-up. It is important to emphasize the aggressiveness of medulloblastoma in both children and adults, with a global mortality of 56.8% and 48,6% at 5 years. Conclusions: It is considered necessary a multidisciplinary treatment and a long term monitoring of the patients and the sequelae of the survivors, including the possibility of second tumours (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Echebarría Barona, Aizpea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urberuaga Pascual, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Casales, Zuriñe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navajas Gutiérrez, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgos Bretones, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astigarraga Aguirre, Itziar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El meduloblastoma es el tumor cerebral maligno más frecuente en la infancia. El objetivo de este estudio es describir datos clínicos, diagnósticos, terapéuticos, pronósticos y de supervivencia de pacientes adultos y niños con meduloblastoma. Pacientes y método: Se trata de un estudio observacional de una cohorte retrospectiva formada por todos los pacientes diagnosticados de meduloblastoma cerebral en los últimos 19 años (1989&#150;2007) en el Hospital de Cruces del municipio de Baracaldo, Vizcaya. Resultados: Se incluyó a 37 pacientes: 20 varones y 17 mujeres, con edades comprendidas entre 1 y 48 años (edad media de 13,7 años y desviación típica de 11,4). Se encontraron diferencias significativas en la localización tumoral y en la mortalidad según diseminación inicial. Presentaron metástasis al diagnóstico 2 pacientes. La resección quirúrgica tumoral fue total en el 75% de los casos. Se observó recaída en la evolución del 59,5% de los pacientes, con afectación del líquido cefalorraquídeo en el 27%. Se detectaron secuelas en la evolución del 100% de los supervivientes, entre las que destacaron las alteraciones cerebelosas y oculares. En uno de los pacientes se diagnosticó una segunda neoplasia (meningioma y sarcoma maxilar). Se puede destacar de el presente estudio la agresividad del meduloblastoma tanto en el niño como en el adulto, con una mortalidad global del 56,8% y, a los 5 años del diagnóstico, del 48,6%. Conclusiones: Se considera necesario un tratamiento multidisciplinario y un seguimiento a largo plazo de los pacientes y de las secuelas de los supervivientes, teniendo en cuenta la posibilidad de segundas neoplasias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);133(12): 454-459, oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76065</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Meduloblastoma: aspectos diferenciales entre el tumor infantil y del adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8695^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8695^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2565^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2565^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2565^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8695^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
