<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150253</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cannabinoid hyperemesis syndrome. A report of six new cases and a summary of previous reports</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cannabinoid hyperemesis syndrome (CHS) is a medical condition which was identified for the first time in 2004 and affects chronic users of cannabis. It is characterized by cyclic episodes of uncontrollable vomiting as well as compulsive bathing in hot water. The episodes have a duration of two to four days. The vomiting is recognizable by a lack of response to regular antiemetic treatment, and subsides only with cannabis abstinence, reappearing in periods of consumption of this substance. The etiology of this syndrome is unknown. Up until June 2014, 83 cases of CHS were published worldwide, four of them in Spain. The first patient of CHS at Mataró Hospital was diagnosed in 2012. Since then, five new cases have been identified. The average duration between the onset of acute CHS episodes and diagnosis is 6.1 years, similar to that observed in previously published cases, an average of 3.1 years. This &#147;delay&#148; of CHS diagnosis demonstrates a lack of awareness with respect to this medical condition in the healthcare profession. With the objective of providing information concerning CHS and facilitating its timely diagnosis, a series of six new cases of CHS diagnosed in Mataró Hospital is presented along with a summary of cases published between 2004 and June 2014 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mola Gilbert, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras Narváez, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giné Serven, Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batlle de Santiago, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañete Crespillo, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bigas Farreres, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sindrome de hiperemesis cannabinoide (SHC) es una entidad clínica descrita por primera vez en 2004, la cual afecta a consumidores crónicos de cannabis y se caracteriza por episodios cíclicos de vómitos incoercibles acompañados por baños en agua caliente compulsivos. Estos episodios tienen una duración de 2 a 4 días. Los vómitos se caracterizan por no responder al tratamiento antiemético habitual, cediendo unicamente con la abstinencia de cannabis, reapareciendo en períodos de consumo de esta sustancia. Hasta Junio de 2014 fueron publicados 83 casos de SHC en el mundo, 4 de ellos en España, siendo la etiología de este sindrome aún desconocida. En el hospital de Mataró se diagnosticó un primer paciente de SHC en 2012. Desde entonces se han identificado cinco nuevos casos. Destaca en ellos un tiempo promedio de 6,1 años entre el inicio de los episodios agudos de SHC y el diagnóstico (3,1 años en los casos previos publicados). Este tiempo de &#147;retraso&#148; del diagnóstico de SHC evidencia un desconocimiento respecto a esta entidad clínica en los servicios de salud. Con el objetivo de aportar información respecto al SHC y facilitar con ello su diagnóstico oportuno, se presenta esta serie de seis nuevos casos de SHC diagnosticados en el Hospital de Mataró y un resumen de los casos publicados entre 2004 y Junio de 2014 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);28(2): 90-98, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150253</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de hiperemesis cannabinoide. Reporte de seis nuevos casos clínicos y resumen de casos previos publicados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d939</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d939^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7119^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7119^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7119^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
