<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161020</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mitochondrial dysfunction associated with nitric oxide pathways in glutamate neurotoxicity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Multiple mechanisms underlying glutamate-induced neurotoxicity have recently been discussed. Likewise, a clear deregulation of the mitochondrial respiratory mechanism has been described in patients with neurodegeneration, oxidative stress, and inflammation. This article highlights nitric oxide, an atypical neurotransmitter synthesized and released on demand by the post-synaptic neurons, and has many important implications for nerve cell survival and differentiation. Consequently, synaptogenesis, synapse elimination, and neurotransmitter release, are nitric oxide-modulated. Interesting, an emergent role of nitric oxide pathways has been discussed as regards neurotoxicity from glutamate-induced apoptosis. These findings suggest that nitric oxide pathways modulation could prevent oxidative damage to neurons through apoptosis inhibition. This review aims to highlight the emergent aspects of nitric oxide-mediated signaling in the brain, and how they can be related to neurotoxicity, as well as the development of neurodegenerative diseases development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manucha,  Walter</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recientemente se han evaluado múltiples mecanismos que subyacen a la neurotoxicidad inducida por el glutamato. En este sentido, pacientes con neurodegeneración presentan disfunción mitocondrial, estrés oxidativo e inflamación. Cabe destacar que el óxido nítrico, un neurotransmisor atípico sintetizado y liberado según demanda por las neuronas postsinápticas, ejerce también la regulación de la apoptosis modulando la sinaptogénesis, la eliminación de sinapsis y la liberación de neurotransmisores. El papel emergente de las vías de óxido nítrico asociado a la apoptosis se ha discutido en la neurotoxicidad inducida por glutamato. Estos hallazgos muestran que la modulación de las vías de óxido nítrico podrían prevenir el daño oxidativo neuronal mediante la inhibición de la apoptosis. La presente revisión pretende destacar los aspectos emergentes de la señalización mediada por óxido nítrico en el cerebro, y la forma en que se puede relacionar con la neurotoxicidad, así como con el desarrollo de enfermedades neurodegenerativas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);29(2): 92-97, mar.-abr. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disfunción mitocondrial asociada a las vías del óxido nítrico en la neurotoxicidad por glutamato</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9117^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9753^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32219^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34349^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
