<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73266</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive factors for survival in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To determine the median survival and determinants of survival in patients with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF). Patients and method: We retrospectively evaluated 29 IPF patients who died in the pneumology department between 2001 and 2006. Data from the time of diagnosis until death were analysed. Determinants of survival including age at diagnosis, gender, history of cigarette smoking, fibrosis-emphysema association, and lung function tests were analysed. Results: The mean age at diagnosis was 69.7, 16 patients were men (55.2%). The median survival time, from the time of diagnosis, was 28.47 months (20.44&#150;36.5 IC95%). There was a significant difference in survival between age groups. The median survival time in patients older than 65 years was 22.40 months and in patients younger than 65 years it was 56.37 months (p&lt;0.001). There was no significant difference in survival when other determinants of survival. were evaluated. Conclusion: The median survival of IPF patients is low. It is necessary to continue investigating to find more effective and selective therapeutic strategies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xaubet, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ancochea, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Determinar la supervivencia y los factores predictivos de supervivencia en un grupo de pacientes fallecidos por fibrosis pulmonar idiopática (FPI). Pacientes y método: Se incluyó en el estudio a 29 pacientes con FPI controlados en una unidad monográfica y que fallecieron entre los años 2001 y 2006. Se analizó el tiempo transcurrido desde la fecha del diagnóstico hasta el fallecimiento. Los factores predictivos analizados fueron edad al diagnóstico, sexo, hábito tabáquico, asociación de enfisema a la fibrosis y parámetros funcionales respiratorios al diagnóstico. Resultados: Los pacientes tenían una edad media de 69,7 años, 16 eran varones (55,2%) y la mediana de supervivencia desde el diagnóstico fue de 28,47 meses (intervalo de confianza del 95%: de 20,44 a 36,5). Sólo hubo diferencia estadísticamente significativa entre la mediana de supervivencia de los pacientes mayores de 65 años (22,40 meses) frente a los menores de 65 años (56,37 meses) (p&lt;0,001). Conclusión: La mediana de supervivencia de los pacientes con FPI es baja, lo que implica la necesidad de seguir investigando y encontrar estrategias terapéuticas más selectivas y eficaces que las actuales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);133(9): 333-336, sept. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictivos de supervivencia en pacientes con fibrosis pulmonar idiopática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12095^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
