<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043834</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alzheimer&#146;s disease and brain evolution: is Alzheimer's disease an example of antagonistic pleiotropy?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Alzheimer&#146;s disease (AD) appears to be exclusive to our species. This suggests a relationship betweenthe disease and genetic, functional and structural changes that have taken place throughout the evolution of the human brain.Development. The expression of genes linked to neurotransmission, neuroplasticity, axonal transport, aerobic metabolism andneuroprotection seems to have increased within the human cerebral cortex and such phenomena represent adaptations thatinduce greater neuronal activity throughout a long lifespan. High levels of neuroplasticity increase neuronal vulnerability tofactors capable of triggering the lesions that are typically found in AD. Several genes related to increased neuronal activityare extremely vulnerable to factors related to old age, such as oxidative stress. Some kind of dysfunction in such genes candisrupt proper regulation of a number of pathways (neuroplasticity, axonal transport) and promote the abnormal accumulationof peptides that is characteristic of AD. Possessing certain polymorphisms of neuroprotective genes or of the electrontransport chain could afford protection against AD. Increased intake of animal fats could alter the balance of polyunsaturatedfatty acids in the neuronal membrane and favour a higher susceptibility to oxidative stress. Conclusions. AD could constitutean example of antagonistic pleiotropy: the increased expression of advantageous genes at an early age could turn out to beharmful at an advanced age</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bufill, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blesa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA) pareceser exclusiva de nuestra especie. Ello sugiere una relación entre laenfermedad y cambios genéticos, funcionales y estructurales ocurridosdurante la evolución cerebral humana. Desarrollo. En el córtexcerebral humano parece haberse producido un incremento de expresiónde genes relacionados con la neurotransmisión, neuroplasticidad,transporte axonal, metabolismo aerobio y neuroprotección,que constituyen adaptaciones inductoras de una mayor actividadneuronal durante una larga vida. Los niveles elevados de neuroplasticidadaumentan la vulnerabilidad neuronal respecto a factorescapaces de provocar las lesiones propias de la EA. Varios genesrelacionados con el incremento de actividad neuronal son extremadamentevulnerables a factores que tienen que ver con la edadavanzada, como el estrés oxidativo. La disfunción de dichos genespuede llevar a la desregulación de diversas vías (neuroplasticidad,transporte axonal) y promover el acúmulo de péptidos anormalescaracterístico de la EA. La posesión de determinados polimorfismosde genes neuroprotectores o de la cadena transportadora de electronespodría proteger contra la EA. El aumento del consumo de grasasanimales podría alterar el balance de ácidos grasos poliinsaturadosen la membrana neuronal, y favorecer una mayor susceptibilidadal estrés oxidativo. Conclusiones. La EA podría constituir unejemplo de pleiotropía antagónica: el incremento de expresión degenes ventajosos a una edad temprana podría resultar dañino a unaedad avanzada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(1): 25-33, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043834</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Alzheimer y evolución cerebral: ¿es la enfermedad de Alzheimer un ejemplo de pleiotropía antagónica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4651^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11759</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22880</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9665^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1521</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24601^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22156^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
