<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88230</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vaccination schedule of the Spanish Association of Paediatrics: recommendations 2011</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Advisory Committee on Vaccines of the Spanish Paediatric Association updates annually the immunization schedule, taking into account epidemiological data as well as evidence of the effectiveness and efficiency of vaccines. This vaccination schedule includes grades of recommendation. The committee has graded as universal vaccines those that all children should receive, as recommended, those with a profile of universal vaccines of childhood and as are desirable those that all children may receive, but that can be prioritized based on public funding resources and for risk groups, targeting those groups of people in epidemiological situations of risk. The Committee considers as a priority to achieve a common immunization schedule for Spain. The Committee reaffirms the recommendation to include pneumococcal vaccination in the routine vaccination schedule. Vaccination against varicella in the second year of life is an effective strategy and therefore a desirable goal. Given the morbidity and high burden on the health care system, vaccination against rotavirus is recommended for all infants. Due to the current problems of availability of both vaccines, associated with the recent finding of circovirus, the committee urges that rotavirus vaccination is restarted as soon as possible as it is considered a desirable health benefit for all children in our country. The Committee adheres to the recommendations of the National Health Coordination Council in reference to routine vaccination against HPV for all girls aged 11 to 14 years and stresses the need to vaccinate all patients with risk factors for these diseases against influenza and hepatitis A. Finally, it stresses the need to update incomplete immunizations using accelerated immunization schedules (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esso Arbolave, D. van</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Contreras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Hachero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortigosa del Castillo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cilleruelo Ortega, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arístegui Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Corrales, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marès Bermúdez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Moína, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez García, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Comité Asesor de Vacunas (CAV) de la Asociación Española de Pediatría actualiza anualmente el calendario de vacunaciones teniendo en cuenta tanto aspectos epidemiológicos, como de efectividad y eficiencia de las vacunas. El presente calendario incluye grados de recomendación. Se han considerado como vacunas sistemáticas aquellas que el CAV estima que todos los niños deberían recibir, como recomendadas las que presentan un perfil de vacuna sistemática en la edad pediátrica y que es deseable que los niños reciban, pero que pueden ser priorizadas en función de los recursos para su financiación pública, y dirigidas a grupos de riesgo aquellas con indicación preferente para personas en situaciones epidemiológicas de riesgo. El CAV considera como objetivo prioritario la consecución de un calendario de vacunaciones único para toda España. El CAV se reafirma en la recomendación de incluir la vacunación frente a neumococo en el calendario de vacunación sistemática. La vacunación universal frente a varicela en el segundo año de vida es una estrategia efectiva y por tanto un objetivo deseable. La vacunación frente a rotavirus, dada la morbilidad y la elevada carga sanitaria, es recomendable en todos los lactantes. Debido a los problemas actuales de disponibilidad de las vacunas, relacionados con la presencia de circovirus, el CAV insta a que, tan pronto como sea posible, se reinicie la vacunación frente a rotavirus por considerarla una oferta de salud deseable para todos los niños en nuestro país. El CAV se adhiere a las recomendaciones del Consejo Interterritorial del Sistema Nacional de Salud en referencia al la vacunación sistemática frente al virus del papiloma humano de todas las niñas de 11 a 14 años e insiste en la necesidad de vacunar frente a la gripe y hepatitis A, a todos los que presenten factores de riesgo para dichas enfermedades. Finalmente, se insiste en la necesidad de actualizar las vacunaciones incompletas con las pautas de vacunación acelerada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);74(2): 132-132[e1-e19], feb. 2011. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88230</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calendario de vacunaciones de la Asociación Española de Pediatría: recomendaciones 2011</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
