<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117619</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health professionals´ perceptions of prevalence of malingering in temporary disability in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In spite of the economic and social relevance of the prevalence of malingering in temporary incapacity, there are very few studies in Spain dealing with this problem. The aim of the present paper is to address this matter by looking into those pathologies that according to professionals show the highest rates of malingering in the medico-legal context. For this purpose, we used an incidental sample of 161 doctors (56% of them were women) from 26 different Spanish provinces, with an age range of 30 to 59 (M = 43.6, SD = 6.5) and an average seniority on the job of 17 years (SD = 6.3). They were asked to complete a brief questionnaire indicating those pathologies in which they thought malingering was more frequent, what percentage of these conditions they thought was simulated, the sociodemographic profile of malingerers (age, income, occupation, etc.), and what data they considered to be an indication for suspicion. The results showed that the doctors perceived the highest rates of malingering to be associated with chronic pain conditions (cervical sprain, lumbago, neck and shoulder pain, fibromyalgia) and affective/emotional conditions (anxiety and depression). The prototypical sociodemographic profile was a middle-aged person, with an unstimulating job and a low or moderate income, and who once had an injury or disorder and decided to prolong it over time in order to maintain the benefits obtained. These results are presented within the frame of the adaptive malingering model and linked to the need to develop specific malingering protocols which minimize the risk of false positives and false negatives in the assessment process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santamaría, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capilla Ramírez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ordi, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de su relevancia económica y social, apenas existen estudios en España que aborden la prevalencia de la simulación en la incapacidad temporal. El objetivo de este estudio ha sido abordar esta cuestión indagando en qué patologías se percibe que hay mayor presencia de simulación en el contexto médico-legal por parte de los profesionales que trabajan en su determinación. Para ello se ha dispuesto de una muestra incidental de 161 médicos (56% mujeres) procedentes de 26 provincias distintas, con edades comprendidas entre los 30 y los 59 años (M = 43.6, DT = 6.5) y con un promedio de 17 años de ejercicio profesional (DT = 6.3). Mediante un breve cuestionario se les pidió que indicaran qué patologías eran más simuladas, cuál creían que era el porcentaje de simulación en las mismas, cuál era el perfil sociodemográfico (edad, nivel de ingresos, profesión, etc.) y qué datos consideraban indicativos de sospecha. Los resultados mostraron que los profesionales percibían como con mayores tasas de simulación los trastornos por dolor crónico (esguince cervical, lumbalgia, cervicalgia, fibromialgia) y los afectivos y emocionales (ansiedad y depresión). El perfil sociodemográfico prototípico era el de personas de mediana edad, con trabajos poco estimulantes y bajos o moderados ingresos, que comienzan sufriendo originalmente algún tipo de lesión o trastorno y deciden prolongarlo en el tiempo para mantener los beneficios obtenidos. Estos resultados se presentan encuadrados dentro del modelo adaptativo de simulación y se asocian a la necesidad de desarrollar protocolos específicos de simulación que minimicen los posibles falsos positivos y falsos negativos en el proceso de evaluación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;24(3): 139-151, nov. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117619</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de simulación en incapacidad temporal: percepción de los profesionales de la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8479^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55021^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
