<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82606</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical Exercise as complementary treatment in prostate cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IntroductionThis article presents how physical exercise can be considered as a complementary treatment in prostate cancer. The article presents the design and implementation of a strength-endurance physical exercise program adapted to prostate cancer. The initial model corresponds to the guidelines of the American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM 1998). Adapting and transforming the program included the most common symptoms relating to the illness and its treatments.Material and methodsThe study design is quasi-experimental. The sample consisted of 33 subjects in treatment phase. Study variables were anthropometric measures, strength-endurance, hypertension, fatigue, incontinence, pain and quality of life.ResultsAfter 24 weeks of the program, a significant improvement in the strength-endurance capacity was observed. This result was more evident in lower limbs. There were also improvements in hypertension, urinary incontinence and pain. In conclusion, the improvement in quality of life is due to the improvement of the functional and physical capacity of ill person(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serdà, Bernat C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monreal, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle, Arantza del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónEste artículo presenta como el ejercicio físico es una terapia complementaria en el tratamiento del cáncer próstata. En concreto presentamos el diseño e implementación de un programa de ejercicio físico de fuerza-resistencia adaptado al cáncer de próstata. El modelo base corresponde a la guía de la American College Sports Medicine Position Stand (ACSM 1998). La adaptación y transformación del programa incluye los síntomas más habituales relativos a la enfermedad y sus tratamientos.Material y métodosEl diseño del estudio es casiexperimental la muestra es de 33 participantes en fase de tratamiento. Las variables de estudio son las variables antropométricas, fuerza-resistencia, tensión arterial, fatiga, incontinencia, dolor y Calidad de Vida.ResultadosAl finalizar 24 semanas de programa, se observa una mejora significativa de la capacidad de la fuerza-resistencia, más evidente en las extremidades inferiores. También mejora la hipertensión arterial, la incontinencia urinaria y dolor.ConclusionesEstos resultados demuestran que la mejora de la Calidad de Vida viene mediada por la mejora de la capacidad física y funcional del enfermo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);45(166): 81-93, abr.-jun. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82606</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El ejercicio físico como terapia complementaria en el cáncer de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
