<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106544</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antidepressant management strategy from the patient perspective: Struggling internally and externally</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify the consumption pathway and strategies of coping with antidepressants use from the patients perspective. Design: Qualitative research. Setting: Tenerife. Sampling: Theoretical sampling until saturation. Method: A total of 17 open interviews with patients who consumed antidepressants whether combined with tranquilisers or not. The age range was between 35-85 years, and there were 13 women. Ten lived in a more urban setting and the rest in rural areas. Interviews were audio-recorded, transcribed verbatim and analysed using a modified Grounded Theory supported by the software program ATLAS. ti. Results: The process identified as coping with antidepressants, was called &#147;struggling internally and externally.&#148; It consisted of the individual assessment of the benefits and risks of medication use (internal struggle), addressing stigma and social pressure (external struggle). The outcome of the assessment made by patients may lead to different strategies for adjusting to drug treatment: &#147;unconditional acceptance&#148;, &#147;resigned acceptance&#148; or &#147;forced acceptance&#148;. Conclusions: Understanding the evaluation process that the patient needs to go through, given the internal and external struggle in which they are immersed, can be useful to develop interventions that improve medication use. In fact, physicians have an important role, although not always explicitly sought in resolving the dilemma posed by patients using antidepressant drugs and, therefore, reducing the length of patient suffering(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Alvarez, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mahtani-Chugani, Vinita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas-Castresana, Carlos de las</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar la trayectoria de consumo y las estrategias de manejo de los antidepresivos desde la perspectiva de los pacientes. Diseño: Estudio cualitativo. Emplazamiento: Tenerife. Participantes y/o contextos: Muestreo teórico hasta alcanzar la saturación. Método: Se incluyeron 17 entrevistas abiertas a personas que consumían antidepresivos con o sin ansiolíticos. El rango de edad osciló entre 35-85 años, de los cuales 13 eran mujeres. Diez vivían en un contexto más urbano y el resto en zona rural. Las entrevistas se grabaron en audio, fueron transcritas verbatim y analizadas según el método de Grounded Theory modificado con el apoyo del programa ATLAS. ti. Resultados: El proceso identificado de manejo de los antidepresivos se denominó «luchando interna y externamente». Consiste en la evaluación personal de los beneficios y riesgos del consumo del medicamento (lucha interna), frente al estigma y presión ambiental (lucha externa). El resultado del proceso de evaluación que realizan los pacientes puede dar lugar a diferentes estrategias de adaptación al tratamiento farmacológico: «aceptación incondicional», «aceptación resignada» o bien «aceptación forzada». Conclusiones: Entender el proceso de evaluación que el paciente necesita hacer, dada la lucha interna y externa en la que se ve inmerso, es útil para poder realizar intervenciones que mejoren el consumo de medicamentos. De hecho, los médicos tienen un papel muy relevante, aunque no siempre explícitamente buscado, en la resolución del dilema que se plantean los pacientes acerca del consumo de los fármacos antidepresivos; y, por tanto, en la reducción del tiempo de sufrimiento de los pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;44(8): 463-470, ago. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106544</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias de manejo de los antidepresivos desde la perspectiva de los pacientes: luchando interna y externamente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
