<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039466</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To characterize temporary disability during        pregnancy, in connection with the evolution of birthrate        and employment.        Methods: Study of 77.941 cases of temporary        disability due to common illness and non-occupational        accident in the population of Navarra between        the ages of 16 and 45, in the years 1999 and 2000.        3.169 women were pregnant and produced 3.707        cases. We compared women and men episodes and        calculated the days of medical absenteeism attributable        to pregnancy. The evolutions of birthrate and        employment in the past twenty years in Navarra were        analysed and they were correlated.        Results: 6% of women under 45 had at least one        pregnancy. The highest proportion given in the service        sector, with permanent contracts and high-level        jobs. With the exception of pregnancy complications,        bony and articulate diseases in pregnancy are outstanding        due to their frequency. The incidence rate of        temporary disability in the period studied is 81,4 processes        out of 100 in men and 65,3 in women. In each        full term pregnancy an average of 38 days of temporary        disability can be expected. Birthrates don't guarantee        population stability, female employment rates        are lower than male ones.        Conclusions:: To maintain the welfare state it is        necessary to adopt pronatalist and female employment        policies. Excluding absence due to pregnancy,        women under 45 present lower temporary disability        rates than men the same age, it is groundless to        affirm that absenteeism in women is higher than in        men and that temporary disability due to pregnancy        has high social costs, subjects that can mean discrimination        for access of women to the labour market</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artieda,  Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Extramiana, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cipriain, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Josu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: caracterizar la incapacidad temporal        durante el embarazo, en relación con la evolución de        natalidad y empleo.        Metodología: Estudio de 77.941 procesos de incapacidad        temporal por enfermedad común y accidente        no laboral en la población laboral Navarra con edad        entre 16 y 45 años, en 1999 y 2000. 3.169 mujeres se        embarazan y generan 3.707 procesos. Se estiman los        días de absentismo por causa médica atribuibles al        embarazo y se compara frecuencia y duración entre        hombres y mujeres, en relación con natalidad y        empleo.        Resultados: 6% de la mujeres menores de 45 años        tuvieron algún embarazo. Mayor proporción en el        sector servicios, con contrato fijo y puesto de trabajo        de alto nivel. Excluyendo las complicaciones del        embarazo, destacan por su frecuencia las enfermedades        osteomioarticulares en embarazadas. La tasa de        incidencia de incapacidad temporal en el período de        estudio es 81,4 procesos por 100 en hombres y 65,3        en mujeres. En cada embarazo a término es esperable        una pérdida media de 38 días por incapacidad temporal.        Los índices de natalidad no garantizan la estabilidad        de la población. La tasa de empleo femenino        es más baja que la de los hombres.        Conclusiones: Para mantener el estado de bienestar        es preciso adoptar políticas de estímulo de la natalidad        e incremento de empleo femenino. Suprimidas        las bajas médicas del embarazo, las mujeres menores        de 45 años presentan tasas de incapacidad temporal        inferiores a las de los hombres de igual edad, es        infundado afirmar que la mujer es más absentista que        el hombre y que la incapacidad temporal debida al        embarazo tiene un alto coste social, cuestiones que        pueden suponer discriminación para la entrada de la        mujer al mercado laboral</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;51(198): 29-39, mar. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039466</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La incapacidad temporal durante el embarazo, ¿elemento de discriminación laboral?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15330^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29909^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
