<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132526</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of emesis induced by chemotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nausea and vomiting are the most frequent secondary effect in patients receiving chemotheraphy treatment, to such a degree that they can result in the treatment being suspended. The physiology of the vomiting induced by chemotherapy is not well known, but it is related to localised receptors of Chemoreceptor Trigger Zone (CTZ), which will be the target of the treatments. The principal factor in unleashing the vomiting is the chemotherapy drug, which, depending on its emetogenic strength, is classified as: high, intermediate or low risk. Other factors depend on the patient himself. Depending on the time of the appearance of the vomit, reference is made to acute emesis when it occurs in the first 24 hours; delayed emesis when it occurs in after the after the first 16-54 hours, or anticipatory emesis, which occurs before the administration of the chemotherapy and is due to a conditioned reflex. The most efficient medicines in the treatment of vomiting related to chemotherapy are the antagonists of the serotonin receptors (ondansetron, granisetron, dolasetron), alone or in combination with corticoids. The dopamine antagonist (metoclopramide), are less efficient at normal close. They require high doses and show greater secondary effects. Aprepitant has recently come onto the market, which is a selective antagonist of the NK1 receptors of the neurokonis. This medicine, associated with a standard therapy of corticoids and serotonin receptors antagonists is able to increase the anti-emetic response in patients subjected to higly emetogenic chemotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Láinez,  N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Illarramendi, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albístur, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgado,  E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las náuseas y los vómitos son el efecto secundario más frecuente en los pacientes en tratamiento quimioterápico, hasta el punto que pueden llegar a hacer que se suspenda el tratamiento. La fisiología del vómito inducido por quimioterapia no está bien conocida, pero se relaciona con receptores localizados en la Chemoreceptor Trigger Zone (CTZ), y que van a ser la diana de los tratamientos. El principal factor desencadenante del vómito es el fármaco quimioterápico, que según su potencia emetógena se clasifican en: riesgo alto, intermedio o bajo. Otros factores son dependientes del propio paciente. Según el momento de aparición de los vómitos se habla de emesis aguda, si ocurre en las primeras 24 horas; de emesis retardada, si ocurre tras las primeras 16-24 horas, o de emesis anticipatoria, que se produce antes de la administración de quimioterapia, y se debe a un reflejo condicionado. Los fármacos más eficaces en el tratamiento de los vómitos relacionados con quimioterapia, son los antagonistas de los receptores de serotonina (ondansetrón, granisetrón, dolasetrón), solos o en combinación con corticoides. Los antagonistas de los receptores de dopamina (metoclopramida), son menos eficaces a las dosis habituales. Precisan de dosis altas y presentan mayores efectos secundarios. Recientemente se ha comercializado el aprepitant, un antagonista selectivo de los receptores NK1 de las neurocininas. Este medicamento, asociado a una terapia estándar de corticoides y antagonistas de los receptores de serotonina, es capaz de incrementer la respuesta antiemética en pacientes sometidos a quimioterapia altamente emetógena (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;27(supl.3): 117-123, 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132526</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la emesis inducida por quimioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d939^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
