<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043832</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in the way parents and teachers identify the symptoms of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder in mexican children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Parents and teachers have been considered as reliable sources to identify attention deficit hyperactivitydisorder (ADHD) symptoms in children, Conners scales have been useful for that purpose. Aim. To determine howparents and teachers attest ADHD behaviors in children, as well as to analyze if there are differences between them attendingto school grade and/or genre. Subjects and methods. A total of 13 teachers (12 women and 1 man), that teach over the threefirst grades of elementary school and 139 mothers participated, their age ranged between 21 and 58 years old. All of themanswered the Conners scales of 139 children; in an individual way with the mothers and in a grouped one with teachers.Results and conclusions. Research results indicate that teachers so as mothers attest ADHD behaviors more in boys than ingirls, especially on those of second grade, they also pointed out in a significantly way the hyperactivity and inattentionbehaviors more than behavior disturbances. Discrepancies between mothers and teachers were observed in respect the schoolgrade of children</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acle-Tomasini, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Luna, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los padres y profesores son fuentes fiablespara la identificación de síntomas del trastorno por déficit de atencióncon hiperactividad (TDAH), cuya información se obtiene dediferentes escalas, y la más conocida y estudiada es la de Conners.Objetivo. Estudiar la manera en que los profesores y los padrescalifican las conductas del TDAH, y establecer si los profesores olos padres califican más alto conductas del TDAH según el gradoescolar y/o sexo del menor. Sujetos y métodos. La muestra se conformópor 13 profesores (12 mujeres y un hombre) que impartíanclases en tres grados de primaria, cuya población era de 139 niños,además de 139 madres, con un intervalo de 21-58 años de edad. Alos profesores se les entregó la escala y a los padres se les aplicó demanera grupal. Resultados y conclusiones. Tanto los profesorescomo las madres califican más alto a los niños, y en particular a losde segundo grado; asimismo, ambos califican más alto los factoresde hiperactividad y desatención que al de trastorno de conducta.Las diferencias se observaron en la manera en que las dos fuentescalifican según el grado escolar en que se encuentre el niño</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(1): 17-21, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043832</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias entre padres y maestros en la identificación de síntomas del trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad en niños mexicanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
