<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051501</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation and improvement in the quality of the programme of preventive activities and health promotion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To confirm that the use of the programme of preventive activities and health promotion (PPAHP) for adults in a health district has improved over time.                 Design. Retrospective and transversal descriptive study.                 Setting. Primary care, Molina la Ribera Health District, Murcia, Spain.                 Patients and participants. The target population was the health district´s patients between 18 and 79 years old seen during the 2 periods of study: 16 236 from 1-05-1995 to 30-04-1996 and 17 377 from 1-07-2003 to 30-06-2004. Randomised sampling stratified for age and sex of the clinical records of the target population gave these samples: 140 at the first evaluation and 250 at the second (95% CI).                 Measurements. Two internal-audit, retrospective evaluations were made, by means of review of clinical records by health professionals at the centre (peer review). The variables reviewed were activities of PPAHP for adults.                 Results. The overall improvement attained was 64.45% (Pareto Diagram). All PPAHP activities (except Anamnesis for Metrorrhagia) showed significant improvement in compliance (P&lt;.05). The PPAHP activity with the highest degree of improvement was Mammography, which went up from 3.70% (±7.12) of compliance (first evaluation) to 83.87% (±12.95) (second evaluation).                 Conclusions. Degree of compliance with PPAHP improved with time, except for anamnesis on metrorrhagia. The activity with the greatest degree of improvement was mammography</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escribano Sabater, M. Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bañón Arias, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Pina, J. Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Valera, José J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomis Cebrián, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Comprobar que la aplicación de las actividades del Programa de Actividades Preventivas y Promoción de la Salud (PAPPS) del adulto sobre la población de una zona de salud ha mejorado con el tiempo.                 Diseño. Estudio descriptivo, retrospectivo y transversal.                 Emplazamiento. Atención primaria, zona de Salud Molina la Ribera.                 Pacientes y participantes. La población diana fueron los pacientes de la zona de salud, de 18-79 años de edad, atendidos durante los 2 períodos de estudio: 16.236 del 1 de mayo de 1995 al 30 de abril de 1996, y 17.377 del 1 de julio de 2003 al 30 de junio de 2004.                 Las muestras se obtuvieron por muestreo aleatorio estratificado por edad y sexo, de las historias clínicas de la población diana: 140 en la primera evaluación y 250 en la segunda (intervalo de confianza del 95%).                 Mediciones. Se realizaron las 2 evaluaciones por auditoría interna y retrospectiva, mediante revisión de historias clínicas por parte de profesionales sanitarios del centro (peer-review). Las variables revisadas fueron las actividades del PAPPS del adulto.                 Resultados. El área de mejora global alcanzada fue del 64,45% (gráfico de Pareto). Todas las actividades del PAPPS (excepto la anamnesis por metrorragia) tuvieron una mejora significativa en su cumplimiento (p &lt; 0,05). La actividad del PAPPS con mayor grado de mejora fue la mamografía, que pasó del 3,70% ± 7,12 de cumplimiento en la primera evaluación al 83,87% ± 12,95 en la segunda.                 Conclusiones. El grado de cumplimiento de las actividades del PAPPS ha mejorado con el tiempo, excepto la anamnesis sobre metrorragia. La mamografía fue la actividad con mayor grado de mejora</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;38(5): 283-287, sept. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051501</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación y mejora de la calidad del Programa de Actividades Preventivas y Promoción de la Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
