<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123972</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality and innovation in nursing Web pages over the period 2010&#150;2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Assess the web pages of Spanish registered nurse associations and nursing scientific societies for quality and innovation. Methods: Descriptive observational study conducted in July&#150;September periods of 2010 and 2012. We used the Bermúdez-Tamayo questionnaire to assess the quality and tools Google PageRank and Alexa TrafficRank for measuring visibility and popularity respectively. To assess the degree of adaptation to the Web 2.0, we analyzed the presence of: Blogs, forums, communities, search engines, RSS, multimedia contents, opinion comments, all tools that facilitate interaction with users. Results: The mean score ± standard deviation on the questionnaire quality in 2010 was 6.6 (SD 2.4) points and 8.2 (SD 2.9) in 2012. In general the visibility and popularity of the web analyzed is low, while it has increased the presence of 2.0 tools up to the 89.4% in the second periods of the study, being scientific societies which developed mainly use. Discussion: There is high variability in the quality of the websites studied, although with a growing interest in the same in most of the assessed organizations. The nursing web pages should improve the visibility and popularity to efficiently disseminate their content and services.The process of adaption to the web 2.0 is at an expansive stage, in fact, the 89,4% of web pages studied used some web 2.0 tool (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estepa Luna, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pardo Martínez, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>de la Torre Barbero, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la calidad y la innovación de las páginas web de colegios oficiales y sociedades científicas de enfermería en España. Métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo realizado en dos periodos: Julio-Septiembre de 2010 y Julio-Septiembre de 2012. Se ha utilizado el cuestionario de Bermúdez&#150;Tamayo para evaluar la calidad y las herramientas PageRank de Google y Alexa TrafficRank para medir la visibilidad y popularidad respectivamente. Para valorar el grado de adaptación de las páginas web al entorno 2.0, se han  analizado la presencia de: Blog, foros, comunidades, buscadores, RSS, contenidos multimedia, comentarios de opinión, herramientas todas ellas, que facilitan la interrelación con los usuarios. Resultados: La puntuación media + desviación estándar en el cuestionario de calidad en 2010 fue de 6,6 (DE 2,4) puntos y de 8,2 (DE 2,9) en 2012. En general, la visibilidad y popularidad de las web analizadas es escasa, mientras se ha incrementado la presencia de herramientas 2.0 hasta alcanzar el 89,4% en la segunda fase del estudio, siendo las sociedades científicas las que desarrollaron mayoritariamente su uso. Conclusiones: Existe una alta variabilidad en la calidad de los sitios web estudiados, aunque con un creciente interés por la misma en gran parte de las organizaciones evaluadas. Las páginas web de enfermería deben mejorar la visibilidad y popularidad para difundir de manera eficiente sus contenidos y servicios. El proceso de adaptación a la web 2.0 está en fase expansiva, de hecho, el 89,4% de las web estudiadas utiliza alguna herramienta 2.0 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;13(35): 197-210, jul. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123972</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad e innovación de las páginas Web de enfermería en el periodo 2010-2012</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29491^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10114</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50124</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
