<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100867</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Theories and models in clinical nursing practice. An impossible relationship?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In the last few decades, Spanish Nursing has suffered several changes that have contributed to a lesser or greater extent to the development of this discipline. However, today there is still a barrier that hinders and delays this development: the equation consisting of theory and practice. Development of the subject. There are several factors which influence the feedback between these two elements and have an impact on the growth that nursing itself undergoes. Nowadays, we are in a period of inflection in which it is necessary to combine both aspects with a dual objective: to put into daily practice the current theoretical models which are available and to base the clinical decisions on scientific evidence which can support our proceedings. Moreover, it is intended that nursing uses its own corpus of knowledge to learn and profit from it in order to develop in all its areas. Conclusions: Nowadays, nursing is immersed in a complex process of conceptualization of its own discipline. There is a wide range of possibilities which must inevitably be accompanied by the acceptance of certain challenges for which individuals must be trained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sancho Cantus, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Contreras, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En las últimas décadas la Enfermería española ha sufrido numerosos cambios que han contribuido en mayor o menor medida al desarrollo de la disciplina. No obstante sigue existiendo en la actualidad una barrera que dificulta y retrasa este desarrollo: la ecuación compuesta por teoría y práctica. Desarrollo del tema. Son diversos los factores que influyen en la retroalimentación entre estos dos elementos, y que repercuten en el crecimiento que experimenta la propia Enfermería. Estamos en la actualidad en un periodo de inflexión en el que es necesario imbricar de una forma efectiva estas dos vertientes, y todo ello con un doble objetivo: aplicar a la práctica diaria los modelos teóricos existentes y disponibles, y fundamentar las decisiones clínicas en evidencias científicas que respalden nuestras actuaciones. Con todo ello se pretende que la Enfermería utilice su corpus propio de conocimientos y sea capaz de nutrirse y de aprovecharlos para su desarrollo en todos sus ámbitos competenciales. Conclusiones: En estos momentos la Enfermería se halla inmersa en un complejo proceso de reconceptualización de la propia disciplina, y se abre un abanico de posibilidades que deberán ir acompañadas inevitablemente de la asunción de ciertos desafíos para los cuales será necesario estar correctamente formados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(27): 292-298, jul. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100867</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Teorías y modelos en la práctica enfermera. ¿Un binomio imposible?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11653^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
