<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99942</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">My child doesn&#146;t grow, and you say this is normal?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Genu varum is a physiologic finding in children p to 2 years old that sometimes becomes genu valgum. However, it may present accompanying systemic conditions that must be ruled out in order to treat them or not. The relatives of children with genu varum should be reassured and doctors should assume an expectant management due to its favourable natural history. We show the case of two brothers with a pronounced genu varum, one of them with a temporary stop in growth. Both evolved in a right way without treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado Sánchez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El genu varum es un proceso fisiológico en los dos primeros años de vida, evolucionando en ocasiones hacia genu valgum. No obstante, su diagnóstico diferencial abarca patologías importantes que deben ser descartadas para decidir el tratamiento. En los niños con genu varum se debe tranquilizar a la familia y adoptar una actitud expectante, dado que no reviste gravedad y es un proceso autolimitado. Presentamos el caso de dos hermanos con genu varum extremo, llegando incluso a producir un estacionamiento de la talla en uno de ellos. Ambos han evolucionado a la normalidad sin intervención médica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;14(53): 31-33, ene.-mar. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99942</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mi hijo no crece, ¿y dice usted que esto es normal?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22898^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53491^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38857^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1874^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53491^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53492^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53492^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
