<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111970</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Burnout and work engagement in teachers: are sex and level taught important?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although there is substantial research exploring the relationships between background variables (e.g., sex and level taught) and teacher burnout, the research on these dimensions and engagement is much sparser. The purpose of the present study is to explore the potential differences in levels of engagement and burnout in a large sample of teachers depending on their sex and level taught. Responses from 727 Spanish primary and secondary teachers (436 females and 291 males) were analysed. Correlation analyses showed negative and moderate associations among both constructs. In addition, although relatively small, analyses showed significant differences by sex and level taught. Female teachers showed higher scores in all three dimensions of engagement and males reported higher depersonalization. Secondary teachers also reported higher depersonalization and lower personal accomplishment, while primary teachers exhibited higher vigor, dedication and absorption. Further research on burnout and engagement in teachers should consider potential differences according to sex and teaching level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rey, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Extremera, Natalio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pena, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunque la literatura ha explorado las relaciones entre variables antecedentes (ie., sexo y nivel de impartición) y el burnout docente, la investigación sobre estas variables y engagement es inexistente. El objetivo del presente estudio es explorar las diferencias en engagement y burnout en una muestra docente en función del sexo y el nivel de impartición de la docencia. Se evaluaron 727 profesores de primaria y secundaria (436 mujeres y 291 hombres). Las correlaciones mostraron relaciones moderadas y negativas entre ambos constructos. Además, aunque relativamente pequeñas, los análisis mostraron diferencias significativas en sexo y nivel de impartición. Las mujeres mostraron mayores puntuaciones en engagement y los hombres mayores puntuaciones en despersonalización. Además, los profesores de secundaria informaron mayor despersonalización y menor realización personal, mientras que los de primaria exhibieron mayor vigor, dedicación y absorción. Futuras investigaciones sobre burnout y engagement docente deberían considerar posibles diferencias de género y del nivel de impartición de la enseñanza (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;18(2/3): 119-129, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Burnout y Engagement en el profesorado: ¿son el sexo y el nivel de impartición importantes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3881^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
