<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118610</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of dispositional and contextual variables in educational settings: IEPA and AYES scales</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Despite the fact that there are a few instruments designed to measure dispositional and contextual variables in educational contexts, the goal of this study is to elaborate and validate two questionnaires to measure learning interest, effort and progression as dispositional (IEPA) and contextual (AYEs) variables in secondary education students. Method: An initial version of both scales was developed. They were reviewed by a panel of experts and tested on two pilot studies. The final versions were administered to the described sample and their psychometric properties were tested. Factor analyses (exploratory and confirmatory) were conducted on three sets of data: Mathematics (n = 290), Spanish Language and Literature (n = 283), and Physical Education (n = 289). Results: Both final scales had three dimensions with four items in each dimension. All standardized loads and critical values of t were overwhelmingly positive, while alpha coefficients ranged from .85 to .91. Both scales showed adequate construct validity, convergent validity, discriminant validity and concurrent validity. Conclusions: Results showed that these new scales have adequate psychometric properties, allowing a valid and reliable assessment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Méndez-Giménez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Río, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González González-Mesa, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Pienda, Julio A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Losa, Jorge L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cecchini Estrada, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: si bien existen en la literatura instrumentos diseñados para evaluar variables disposicionales y contextuales en ámbitos educativos, la finalidad de este estudio es elaborar y validar dos cuestionarios que permitan medir el interés, el esfuerzo y la progresión en el aprendizaje en el alumnado de Educación Secundaria como variables disposicionales (IEPA) y contextuales (AYES). Método: tras elaborar una primera versión, que fue sometida sucesivamente a un juicio de expertos y a dos estudios piloto previos, se comprobaron las medidas psicométricas de la versión definitiva. Se realizaron análisis factoriales (exploratorios y confirmatorios) en tres conjuntos de datos: Matemáticas (n = 290), Lengua Castellana y Literatura (n = 283) y Educación Física (n = 289). Resultados: las escalas definitivas están compuestas por tres dimensiones de cuatro ítems cada una. Todas las cargas estandarizadas y los valores críticos de t superaron ampliamente los niveles mínimos recomendados, el coeficiente alfa osciló entre ,85 y ,91. Ambos cuestionarios mostraron una adecuada validez de constructo, validez convergente, validez discriminante y validez concurrente. Conclusiones: estos resultados indican que las nuevas escalas poseen adecuadas propiedades psicométricas, lo que permite una evaluación válida y fiable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);26(1): 69-75, ene.-abr. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La afabilidad y extroversión de los seguidores y su lealtad hacia el liderazgo auténtico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
