<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124127</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish psychiatry and Jacques Lacan before 1975</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article aims to analyse the presence of Jacques Lacan in the domain of Spanish psychiatry before 1975. Firstly, it addresses this question through an examination of the psychiatric press and an analysis of all references made to Lacan (origin, features and development in quantitative and qualitative terms). Secondly, it addresses the history, the context and the consequences of the two lectures that Jacques Lacan gave in Barcelona in 1958 and 1972, at the invitation of some Spanish psychiatrists (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Druet, Anne Cécile</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este artículo es estudiar la presencia de Jacques Lacan en el ámbito psiquiátrico español antes de 1975. Se aborda en un primer momento esta cuestión a través del escrutinio de la prensa psiquiátrica y del análisis de las referencias a Lacan que aparecen en ella (origen, características, y evolución en términos cuantitativos y cualitativos). Se aborda a continuación la historia, el contexto y las consecuencias de las dos conferencias que Jacques Lacan, invitado por los psiquiatras españoles, dio en Barcelona en 1958 y 1972 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;66(1): 1-10[p36], ene.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124127</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La psiquiatría española y Jacques Lacan antes de 1975</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
