<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129883</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of human papillomavirus testing in anal intraepithelial neoplasia screening in a risk behaviour population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The incidence of intraepithelial anal neoplasia is increasing in certain risk behaviour groups, and human papillomavirus (HPV) infection is involved in its pathogenesis. The systematic use of anal cytology, and more recently HPV detection by hybrid capture and genotyping, have been introduced into screening programs in recent decades. Material and methods A retrospective cohort study was carried out on individuals with risk behaviours of developing intraepithelial anal neoplasia and who attended Sexually Transmitted Infections clinics in the Dermatology area of the Hospital Costa del Sol from January 2010 to December 2012. The intraepithelial anal neoplasia screening was performed using anal cytology and HPV genotyping. Results Half (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereda, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas-Ruiz, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla-España, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo, Maximino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frieyro-Elicegui, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Repiso-Jiménez, Bosco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Sánchez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Morano, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>de-Troya Martín, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La incidencia de la neoplasia intraepitelial anal está en aumento en determinados grupos con conductas de riesgo, y en su etiopatogenia está implicada la infección por el virus del papiloma humano (VPH). Dentro de los programas de cribado implementados en las últimas décadas se encuentra el uso sistemático de la citología anal y, más recientemente, la detección del VPH mediante captura de híbridos y genotipado. Material y método Estudio de cohortes retrospectivo de la población con conductas de riesgo de desarrollar neoplasia intraepitelial anal atendida en la consulta de Infecciones de Transmisión Sexual del área de Dermatología del Hospital Costa del Sol desde enero de 2010 a diciembre de 2012, a la que se le realizó cribado de neoplasia intraepitelial anal mediante toma de citología anal y genotipado de VPH. Resultados El 50% de la población estudiada tenía infección por VIH. Se encontró una alta frecuencia de displasia anal y presencia de VPH en la (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(9): 560-564, nov. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129883</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la detección del virus del papiloma humano en el cribado de neoplasia intraepitelial anal en pacientes con conductas de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1011^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31753^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5289</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
