<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2193</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of Imperfect Osteogenesis: a rare disease in the Valencia Region</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Osteogenesis imperfecta (OI) is a rare connective tissue and bone disease that results in a bone fragility of varying severity. The objective was to determine and describe the OI in the Valencia Region (VR) during the period 2004 to 2014. Methods: From the Rare Diseases Information System of the VR (SIER-CV) patients from 2004 to 2014 with the codes of the International Classification of Diseases for the OI were identified: 756.51 from the 9th Revision-Clinical Modification and Q78.0 from the 10th Revision. The information was validated by reviewing clinical documentation (mainly electronic health records) and a descriptive analysis of the confirmed cases (diagnosis of OI in the clinical documentation) was performed. Results: 162 patients were identified with a code for OI. 145 of the 161 patients with available clinical documentation were confirmed as cases. The prevalence was 0.29 per 10.000 inhabitants. 93.1% were Spanish, 54.5% were women and they were treated in 25 different hospitals in the VR. The type of OI was known in the 26.4% of the cases and type I was the most common (9.7%). 6.2% of the patients died with an average death age of 60.8 years. 44.8% of patients received treatment with bisphosphonates and 10.4% had affected relatives. Conclusion: The real situation of the OI in the VR has been established, which will allow a better planning in the health actions to improve the quality of life of the affected ones and their families (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gimeno-Martos, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cavero-Carbonell, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Riera, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardiola-Vilarroig, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La Osteogénesis Imperfecta (OI) es una enfermedad rara del tejido conectivo y óseo que resulta en una fragilidad ósea de diversa severidad. El objetivo fue determinar y describir la situación de la OI en la Comunitat Valenciana (CV) durante el periodo 2004-2014. Métodos: A partir del Sistema de Información de Enfermedades Raras de la CV (SIER-CV) se identificaron los pacientes con los códigos de la Clasificación Internacional de Enfermedades pertenecientes a la OI: el 756.51 de la 9ª y/o el Q78.0 de la 10ª revisión, durante el período 2004-2014. Se validaron los datos mediante la revisión de documentación clínica (historia clínica electrónica principalmente) y de los casos confirmados (diagnóstico de OI presente en la documentación clínica) se elaboró un análisis descriptivo. Resultados: Se identificaron 162 pacientes con código de OI. Se confirmaron 145 casos de los 161 con la documentación clínica accesible. La prevalencia fue de 0,29 por 10.000 habitantes. El 93,1% eran españoles, el 54,5% mujeres y fueron atendidos en 25 hospitales diferentes de la CV. Se identificó el tipo de OI en el 24,8% de los casos, siendo el tipo I el más habitual (9,7%). Fallecieron el 6,2% con una edad media al fallecimiento de 60,8 años. El 44,8% de pacientes recibió tratamiento con bifosfonatos y el 10,4% tenían familiares afectados. Conclusión: Se ha establecido la situación real de la OI en la CV, lo que permitirá una mejor planificación en las acciones sanitarias para mejorar la calidad de vida de los afectados y sus familiares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;91: 0-0, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de la Osteogénesis Imperfecta: una enfermedad rara en la Comunitat Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
