<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168631</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic factors after a traumatic hip dislocation. A long-term retrospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Traumatic hip dislocations can have devastating complications such as osteoarthritis or osteonecrosis. The aim of this study was to identify the variables and prognostic factors associated with clinical and radiological outcome after a traumatic hip dislocation at long-term follow-up. Material and methods. A review was performed of all dislocations and fracture-dislocations of the hip from January 1999 to December 2012. A computed tomography scan was performed after reduction in all cases. The Harris Hip Score and modified Merle-d'Aubigné-Postel method were used for clinical evaluation and radiological assessment was performed according to the Thompson and Epstein classification. Results. There were 30 cases in 29 patients with a mean follow-up of 11 years (range, 4-17). The great majority were simple dislocations (21; 70%) vs. complex dislocations (9; 30%). Closed reduction was performed in less than 6h in all except one case (29; 96.7%). All of the patients with simple dislocations had an excellent outcome without radiological signs of osteoarthritis at the end of the follow-up (P&lt;.01). Overall, arthritic signs had developed in 4 patients (13.3%) and avascular necrosis was noted in 3 patients (10%). Five patients with intraarticular fragments were treated non-operatively, and 3 of them developed arthritic changes (P&lt;.05). Conclusion. Our study suggests that complex dislocations are associated with poorer functional and radiological outcomes than simple dislocations. We also found a strong association between intraarticular fragments and osteoarthritis, so surgical fragment removal could be considered in these cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Foruria, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las luxaciones o fracturas-luxaciones de la cadera pueden suponer severas complicaciones como la artrosis o la necrosis. El objetivo de este estudio fue identificar las variables y los factores pronósticos asociados con resultados clínicos y radiológicos a largo plazo tras una luxación traumática de cadera. Material y métodos. Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo de todas las luxaciones y fracturas-luxaciones tratadas desde enero de 1999 a diciembre de 2012. Una tomografía axial computerizada fue realizada tras la reducción en todos los casos. Para la evaluación de los resultados clínicos se utilizó el Harris Hip Score y la escala Merlé-d'Aubigné-Postel, mientras que los resultados radiológicos se evaluaron con la clasificación de Thompson-Epstein. Resultados. Se identificaron 30 casos en 29 pacientes, con un seguimiento medio de 11 años (rango 4-17). Existió una mayor frecuencia de luxaciones simples (21; 70%) respecto a luxaciones complejas (9; 30%). Se realizó una reducción cerrada en menos de 6h en todos los casos excepto en uno (29; 96,7%). Todos los pacientes con luxaciones simples tuvieron excelente resultado sin signos radiológicos de artrosis al final del seguimiento (p&lt;0,01). Del total de la muestra, 4 pacientes desarrollaron signos artrósicos (13,3%) y 3 pacientes presentaron necrosis avascular (10%). Cinco pacientes con fragmentos intraarticulares fueron tratados de forma conservadora, y 3 de ellos desarrollaron artrosis (p&lt;0,05). Conclusión. Nuestro estudio muestra que las luxaciones complejas tienen peores resultados funcionales y radiológicos que las luxaciones simples. Hemos encontrado una fuerte asociación entre cuerpos libres intraarticulares y artrosis, por lo que la extracción de esos fragmentos podría ser considerada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);61(6): 367-374, nov.-dic. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores pronósticos tras una luxación traumática de cadera. Estudio retrospectivo a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6776^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5369^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
