<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057047</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The need of a nursing report at discharge or transfer to a geriatric residence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: As people get older, certain changes happen in the brain that become even more pronounced when the elderly person falls ill. Therefore it is very important to carry out exercises that stimulate the brain of elderly hospitalised people with special focus on the main cerebral functions of orientation and language. Our aims will be directed towards enhancing, stimulating and exercising two main cognitive functions: orientation and language in their diverse forms.         Methods and resources: This work was developed in the San Rafael University hospital in Granada. The activities carried out were of orientation and language. Variables: age, sex, main diagnostic, Barthel Index and the Lobo (MEC) mini cerebral test.         Results: The sample is constituted by 20 patients with an average age of 84.5 years old. We can note two main predominances: a greater number of women (75% from the total sample) and significant prevalence of neurological diseases (40%). During the initial MEC, before accomplishing the exercises, 35% of the sample showed a moderate cognitive deterioration, whereas minor deterioration prevailed during the subsequent MEC after the exercises, with a 35%. Within orientation exercises, patients obtained higher marks in the temporal-spatial ones. Concerning language exercises, marks reached an acceptable standard overall.         Discussions and conclusions: The aged patients showed an acceptable level in temporal and spatial orientation and verbal repetition. It is essential the periodical practice of stimulating cognitive activities to improve aged patients&#146; life standards</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Royano Reigadas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Calderón, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mundet Riera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barquín Arribas, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martínez-Esparza, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Frecuentemente el personal de enfermería se encuentra que al ingreso de un anciano la transmisión de información es deficiente o escasa para el abordaje integral e individualizado de éste. Con el objetivo de salvaguardar este problema y mejorar la continuidad asistencial de los ancianos dados de alta a su domicilio o trasladados a otro centro asistencial, el equipo de enfermería de la Residencia Clínica &#147;Los Robles&#148; ha elaborado un instrumento de registro que denominamos &#147;Informe de enfermería al alta o traslado de una residencia geriátrica&#148;. En el mismo se pretende recoger de una forma esquemática, ágil y completa la realidad y situación biopsicosocial del anciano garantizando una adecuada transmisión de la información y la continuidad de los cuidados de enfermería. Dicha hoja se elaboró basándonos en gran medida en el Modelo de Necesidades de Virginia Henderson (1). En ella se recogen los aspectos básicos del anciano a través de una serie de ítems cerrados y abiertos, abarcando tanto el estado basal del anciano como los procesos agudos si los hubiere, estando dirigida tanto al personal sanitario del centro asistencial de destino como a los propios cuidadores del anciano en el caso de traslado a domicilio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);17(3): 132-139, jul.-sep.2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057047</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La necesidad de un informe de enfermería al alta o traslado en una residencia geriátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28202^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28845^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
