<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124165</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical features of 149 patients with facio-auriculo-vertebral spectrum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Facio-auriculo-vertebral (FAV) spectrum, also known as Goldenhar syndrome or first and second branchial arch syndrome, is a complex of mainly craniofacial and vertebral anomalies. Microtia is a principal malformation in this complex; it can be unilateral or bilateral. We performed an observational, retrospective, transverse descriptive clinical study, reviewing 149 records of patients with a diagnosis of microtia treated in the Genetics Department. There was no significant difference in the sex of the individuals involved. The mean age was 6.97 years, with a range of 1&#150;52 years. We founded a positive inbreeding in 14 patients and consanguinity in 1 case. There was a family history of microtia in 37 cases. The most frequent malformations, besides microtia, were facial, costo-vertebral, limb, cardiac, genital, eye and other defects. Patients had a high percentage of family history, which could suggest an autosomal dominant inheritance with reduced penetrance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arenas-Sordo, María L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Pedroza, Liliana A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El espectro facio-aurículo-vertebral, también denominado síndrome de Goldenhar, o síndrome del primer y segundo arcos branquiales, es un complejo de anomalías craneofaciales y vertebrales principalmente. La malformación eje de este complejo es la microtia, uni o bilateral. Se realizó una investigación clínica observacional, retrospectiva trasversal y descriptiva, revisando 149 expedientes de pacientes con diagnóstico de microtia. No hubo diferencia significativa en cuanto al sexo de los afectados. La edad promedio fue de 6,97 años, con un rango de 1 a 52 años. Endogamia positiva en 14 pacientes y consanguinidad en un caso. Antecedentes familiares de microtia en 37 casos. Además de la microtia, las malformaciones más frecuentes fueron: faciales, costo-vertebrales, de extremidades, cardíacas, de genitales, oftalmológicas y otras. Los pacientes tuvieron un porcentaje elevado de antecedentes heredo familiares, lo que podría evidenciar un tipo de herencia autosómica dominante con penetrancia reducida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;64(5): 359-362, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124165</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones clínicas de 149 pacientes con espectro facio-aurículo-vertebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5247^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52522^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1960^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6200^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
