<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72547</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fistula following total laryngectomy. Retrospective study and bibliographical review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The pharyngocutaneous fistulae is troublesome and the most common complication following total laryngectomy. Our objetive was to determine the incidence of pharingocutaneous fistulae after the total laryngectomy in our serie and to make review of the medical literature. Methods: We made a retrospective study of a serie of 81 consecutive cases of laryngeal carcinoma treated between 1995 and 2008 in our section. Total laryngectomy was performed in 29 cases and 52 patients treated with organ preservation approach, were excluded. In 14 cases, the procedure was combined with radical neck dissection, pharyngeal resection or myocutanenous flaps. Nasogastric tube for feeding in the postoperative period was used in all patients and surgical gastrostomy was performed in 5 cases. Results: Our incidence of fistulas when total laryngectomy was the alone procedure is 20 % and 34.5 % when simultaneous surgical proceedings were associated. Spontaneous closure was noted in 80 % of the cases and the mean hospitalization time was 23 days. Conclusions: Most of the fistulas can be managed with conservative treatment. Pectoralis major myocutanenous flap is appropriate when conservative treatment has failed. In small fistulas, nasogastric or gastrostomy tube for feeding can be successfully managed in the ambulatory follow up. The cost-benefit relation must be better analyzed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Da Silva, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Valea, Mariela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bitar, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarra, Luis D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La fístula faringocutánea es la complicación más frecuente de la cirugía del cáncer de laringe y hay escasa literatura sobre el tema. Nuestro objetivo es analizar la experiencia de más de una década en un hospital zonal y realizar una revisión bibliográfica. Métodos: Entre los años 1995 y 2008, se diagnosticó a 81 pacientes con cáncer de laringe. Se excluyó a 52 pacientes que ingresaron a protocolos de quimiorradioterapia o fueron tratados con cirugía conservadora. Se practicó laringectomía total como tratamiento primario a 29 pacientes. En 14 casos se asoció faringectomía parcial o total, vaciamientos de cuello o colgajos. Utilizamos alimentación por sonda nasogástrica en todos los casos, como mínimo, durante 8 días. Resultados: Cuando la laringectomía total fue el único tratamiento, la incidencia de fístulas alcanzó el 20 %, mientras que cuando se asociaron otros procedimientos, la incidencia fue del 34,5 %. El tiempo de internación promedio de los pacientes fistulizados fue de 23 días. Cerraron espontáneamente el 80 % de las fístulas y debimos reintervenir a 2 pacientes. Se realizó gastrostomía en 5 oportunidades y alimentación enteral domiciliaria en 8 pacientes. Conclusiones: Nuestra frecuencia de fístulas es similar a la publicada y coincidimos en que el tratamiento inicial debe ser conservador. Cuando es necesario reoperar, preferimos el colgajo miocutáneo de pectoral mayor. En pacientes seleccionados, la alimentación enteral domiciliaria reduce el tiempo de internación y mejora la calidad de vida. Queda pendiente el análisis del impacto de esta complicación en los costos de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;60(3): 186-189, mayo-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72547</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fístula tras laringectomía total. Estudio retrospectivo y revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12508^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8004^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
