<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83976</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A proposed guideline for economic evaluation of health technologies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the last few years, economic evaluation of health technologies has become a major tool used by European health policy decision-makers to create strategies for prioritizing the allocation of health resources and the approval of new technologies. Spain was a pioneer in proposing the standardization of methodology applicable to economic evaluation studies. However, because health policy decision-makers refused to support the initiative, the methodology was never put into practice.AbstractIn the medium term, evidence of the economic value of new health technologies financed by the national health system will probably be increasingly required. At that time, stakeholders and decision-makers will have to agree upon a clear and concise set of rules on the technical and methodological issues that must be followed by economic evaluations of health technologies. Consequently, we have provided guidelines and recommendations for producing first-rate economic evaluations. The recommendations appear under seventeen headings or sections. In each case, the recommended requirements to be satisfied by an economic evaluation of health technologies are provided and each recommendation is followed by a commentary, providing a justification and comparing and contrasting the proposal with other available alternatives(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Altés, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig-Junoy, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva , Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Bastida , Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antoñanzas, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gisbert, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mar, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación económica de tecnologías sanitarias se ha convertido en los últimos años en Europa en una herramienta de primer orden para los gestores sanitarios en sus estrategias de asignación de recursos sanitarios y de adopción de nuevas tecnologías. España fue uno de los países pioneros en realizar propuestas de estandarización metodológica aplicable a estudios de evaluación económica. No obstante, la falta de decisión política y de apoyo de los gestores sanitarios a este tipo de herramientas hizo que las propuestas cayeran en desuso. Sin embargo, lo esperable es que a medio plazo sea cada vez más habitual que las nuevas tecnologías sanitarias financiadas por el Sistema Nacional de Salud deban aportar una adecuada evidencia de su valor terapéutico y social en comparación con su coste. Llegado ese momento, los actores del sistema requerirán una serie de reglas claras y consensuadas por parte de los agentes del sistema sobre las cuestiones técnicas o metodológicas que deben respetar los estudios de evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias. Por este motivo, las presentes recomendaciones orientan sobre cómo realizar y analizar los estudios de evaluación económica de calidad. Las recomendaciones aparecen bajo 17 encabezamientos o dominios, y bajo cada recomendación hay además un comentario, en el cual se justifican y discuten las propuestas en relación con otras opciones posibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(2): 154-170, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83976</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta de guía para la evaluación económica aplicada a las tecnologías sanitarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34589^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
