<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104268</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The protocol develops the main criteria on which the design of the intervention in this type of centre is based, as well as the areas, programs and workshops held to carry out the intervention. For this purpose, it has been considered that &#145;miniresidencias&#146; (Group Homes) are rehabilitation resources where the person has to keep on progressing in the goals related to his personal and social competence and his occupational performance, without loosing the perspective that it is a place where they are going to carryout their daily life. It has been intended to develop a design to enable the people who access the resource to be able to carry out activities and tasks which allow them to participate in those roles which form their identity, to feel useful and socially integrated and to have a satisfying quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arguinzoniz Moraleda, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manrique Araque, Amaya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Del Moral, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Macías, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamorro Mera, Leonor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Risueño, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Manzanares, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portacelli Gutiérrez, Valle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Torralba, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellanos Redondo, Amanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Lepe, Inés María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso Martín, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El protocolo recoge los criterios fundamentales en base a los cuales se ha diseñado la intervención en este tipo de recurso, así como las áreas, programas y talleres mediante los que dicha intervención se lleva a cabo. Para ello se ha considerado que las miniresidencias son recursos de rehabilitación en los que la persona ha de ir progresando en los objetivos relacionados con su competencia personal, social y su funcionamiento ocupacional, sin perder la perspectiva de que es un lugar en el que van a llevar a cabo su vida cotidiana. Se ha pretendido elaborar un diseño que favorezca que las personas que acceden al recurso, puedan llevara cabo actividades y tareas que les permitan participar en aquellos roles que configuran su identidad, sentirse útiles e integrados socialmente y tener una vida gratificante y de calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(201): 285-299, jul.-sept. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104268</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protocolo de intervención en miniresidencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12533^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
