<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050228</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exploration techniques of sensibility in foot pathology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetic neuropathy can be detected with a simple feet neurologic examination involving the use of the 128-Hz tuning fork, the pin-prick testing and the achilles reflex. Using these techniques it is possible to obtain a composite score such the modified Neuropathy Disability Score. A semiquantitative assessment of the vibration-perception threshold assessed by the neurothensiometer, and the 10 g-monofilament can be used in order to predict the risk of foot ulcers. A substantial reduction in lower extremity amputation rate in diabetic patients might be achieved with an earlier neuropathy screening and intervention based on a continuing and well structured treatment and education programmes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Pérez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle Pascual, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Runkle Vega, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Pérez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Hervada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La polineuropatía en pacientes con diabetes puede ser detectada realizando una exploración neurológica básica de los pies utilizando el diapasón de 128 Hz, el palillo y valorando el reflejo aquíleo. Con ello se obtiene una puntuación en cuestionarios como el Neuropathy Disability Score, ó semejantes. La utilización de un neurotensiómetro que permite la evaluación del umbral de sensibilidad vibratoria, ó el monofilamento de 10 g, que predicen la aparición de úlceras en los pies de una forma mas precisa. En los pacientes con diabetes se podría alcanzar una reducción importante en la tasa de amputaciones de miembros inferiores con un programa de cribaje precoz de la polineuropatía, así como con programas de intervención basados en una educación continuada y en la instauración de un tratamiento adecuado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;22(1): 42-49, ene.-mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050228</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnicas de exploración de la sensibilidad en la patología del pie</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9652^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
