<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045105</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dementia with Lewy bodies: diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lewy body dementia is the second cause of degenerative dementia. The diagnosis is made through clinical history and extensive physical examination, together with complementary tests (blood analysis and neuroimaging tests). Criteria for the clinical diagnosis of this disease are divided into central, nuclear and suggestive traits, the number of nuclear traits existing being essential. The differential diagnosis must be done with Alzheimer's disease (that may present the same signs and symptoms and both diseases may coexist) and with Parkinson's disease. Regarding the most characteristic pathological finding of the disease, this is the presence of cortical Lewy bodies, with predominance in the frontal and temporal region and paralimbic areas. Symptomatic treatment of the disease is made up of two drug groups: acetylcholinesterase (tacrine, donepezil, rivastigmine, galantamine) and menantine, the last drug of them marketed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Calle, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La demencia por cuerpos de Lewy es la segunda causa de demencia degenerativa. El diagnóstico se realizará mediante historia clínica y exploración física exhaustiva, junto con pruebas complementarias (analítica de sangre y pruebas de neuroimagen). Los criterios para el diagnóstico clínico de esta enfermedad se dividen en rasgos centrales, nucleares y sugestivos, siendo fundamental el número de rasgos nucleares existentes. El diagnóstico diferencial hay que realizarlo con la enfermedad de Alzheimer (pueden presentar los mismos signos y síntomas y coexistir ambas enfermedades) y con la enfermedad de Parkinson. En cuanto al hallazgo anatomopatológico más característico de la enfermedad, es la presencia de cuerpos de Lewy corticales, con predominio en la región frontal y temporal y áreas paralímbicas. El tratamiento sintomático de la enfermedad lo componen dos grupos de fármacos: los inhibidores de la acetilcolinesterasa (tacrina, donepezilo, rivastigmina, galantamina) y la memantina, último fármaco comercializado de ellos</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(4): 167-171, abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045105</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demencia con cuerpos de Lewy</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24240^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34224^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30008^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
