<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140722</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adverse events caused by activated charcoal in an emergency services survey</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. There are few studies in Spain on the use of activated charcoal (AC) in acute poisoning via the digestive tract, and more specifically on its protocol and adverse events following its administration. The aim of this article is to know the experience in the use of AC by doctors and nurses of the Spanish emergency services. Method. Survey developed using Google Docs to health professionals in emergency services. Results. Three hundred and sixty-four questionnaires were received, 52% of them from doctors. Catheterization prior to the use of AC in 74.5% of patients was performed, and did not use a catheter in 13%. The application of AC was considered correct in 37.4%, and overall it was used in 92.4% of cases. The lateral safety position was used in 46.2%, antiemetics in 86.5% and isolation of the airway in case of coma (GCS&lt;8) in 60%. The most described adverse events were vomiting of AC (61%), epixtasis when the catheter was positioned (51.1%), and its incorrect positioning (36%). Inhaling vomit occurred in 11.8% and inhaling carbon in 4.7%. Seven point one percent stated that the adverse events had been life-threatening to patients. No relation was found between the protocol and serious or life-threatening adverse events, nor between these latter and clinical safety measures. Conclusions. The incidence of adverse events according to the information provided by professionals in this survey of clinical practice might be higher than the incidence found in the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burillo Putze, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Acosta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Duarte, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Sosa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito Lozano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente García, C de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Expósito Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matos Castro, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jurado Sánchez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Existen pocos estudios en España sobre el uso de carbón activado (CA) en las intoxicaciones agudas  por vía digestiva, y más concretamente sobre su protocolización y eventos adversos tras su administración. Este trabajo tiene como objetivo conocer la experiencia en el uso de CA, por los médicos y enfermeros de los servicios de urgencias y emergencias españoles. Método. Diseño de una encuesta a profesionales sanitarios de urgencias y emergencias, mediante la aplicación informática Google Docs. Resultados. Ser recibieron 364 encuestas, de ellas un 52% procedentes de facultativos. Contestaron realizar sondaje previo al uso de CA el 74,5%, y no utilizar sonda en el 13% de los pacientes. Se consideró correcta la aplicación de CA en un 37,4%, usándose globalmente en un 92,4% de los casos. La posición lateral de seguridad manifestaron usarla el 46,2%, antieméticos el 86,5% y aislaban la vía aérea en caso de coma (GCS&lt;8) el 60%. Los eventos adversos más descritos fueron los vómitos de CA (61%), la epixtasis al colocar la sonda (51,1%) y la incorrecta colocación de la misma (36%). La broncoaspiración de vómitos les ocurrió al 11,8% y de carbón al 4,7%. Un 7,1% manifestó que los eventos adversos habían supuesto riesgo vital para los pacientes. No se halló relación entre protocolización de la asistencia y eventos adversos graves o riesgo vital, ni entre éstos y las medidas de seguridad clínica. Conclusiones. La incidencia de eventos adversos, en función de lo manifestado por los profesionales en esta encuesta sobre su práctica clínica, podría ser superior a las que se encuentran en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;38(2): 203-211, mayo-ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140722</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta sobre los eventos adversos relacionados con el uso de carbón activado en urgencias y emergencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d939^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25039^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25039^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
