<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050816</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Structural model for evaluating indicators of psychological well-being predictors in healthcare workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Recent data indicate a prevalence 28% for stress at work among European workers. The main aim of this        paper is to estimate and test an a priori model of job stress, based on previous models developed by Parkes, Karasek and        Theorell, and Warr. The model is multidimensional, both in terms of predictors and effects on workers' sense of wellbeing.        Methods. This is a cross-sectional survey conducted in May 2003 among workers in three hospitals located in Valencia.        The analyses include the specification, estimation and testing of structural models with latent variables.        Results. Results show that working conditions that could collectively lead to job satisfaction and good mental health        are low demand, high job control and low role conflict. Social support plays an important, but indirect, role.        Conclusions. In the future, panel studies should help to further investigate the understanding of associations found in        this study from a cause-effect perspective. The measurement of personality variables in this study (such as self-esteem)        could also be improved in future research</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tomás, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Layunta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Según estadísticas recientes, la prevalencia del estrés laboral en Europa es del 28%. El objetivo general de este        trabajo es poner a prueba un modelo a priori del estrés en el trabajo basado en los modelos de Parkes, Karasek y Theorell,        y Warr. Este modelo es de naturaleza multidimensional, no sólo en los predictores sino también en sus efectos sobre el        bienestar de los trabajadores.        Métodos. El diseño de investigación es transversal. Se llevó a cabo una encuesta, realizada durante mayo de 2003, sobre        trabajadores de tres hospitales de Valencia. Los análisis realizados incluyen la especificación y puesta a prueba de        modelos estructurales recursivos con variables latentes.        Resultados. Los resultados muestran que las condiciones del trabajo que simultáneamente llevarían hacia el bienestar        psicológico y la satisfacción laboral serían una baja demanda, control del trabajo y bajo nivel de conflicto de rol. El        apoyo social juega un papel importante, pero indirecto.        Conclusiones. En el futuro, estudios de panel permitirían profundizar en la interpretación causal de las asociaciones        encontradas. Se deberían mejorar también las medidas de personalidad utilizadas, como la autoestima</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);9(2): 61-66, abr.-jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050816</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo estructural para evaluar los predictores del bienestar psicológico en trabajadores del sector sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16385</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
