<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109625</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Wnt pathway and sclerostin as new targets for assessment and treatment of osteoporosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The increasing knowledge of bone biology has allowed the identi&amp;#64257;cation of new intracellular pathwaysinvolved in the regulation of remodelling and osteoblast activity. In this respect, the characterization ofthe Wnt pathway has been a breakthrough for its involvement and role in disorders of mineralmetabolism.A better understanding of these signaling pathways may allow the development of new diagnosticmarkers and new drugs for metabolic bone disease, where despite extensive available therapies, unmetneeds still persist. In this review, we make an approach to the discovery and functions of the Wntpathway with a focus on bone effects. Next, we brie&amp;#64258;y review the main data about their endogenousantagonist, sclerostin, precisely where drug research is more advanced (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Torres, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Martín, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El creciente conocimiento de la biología ósea ha permitido la identificación de nuevas vías intracelulares que participan en la regulación del remodelado y de la actividad de los osteoblastos. En este aspecto, la caracterización de la vía Wnt ha supuesto un gran avance por su implicación y relevancia en alteraciones del metabolismo mineral.El mejor conocimiento de estas vías de señalización puede permitir desarrollar nuevos marcadores diagnósticos, así como nuevos fármacos para las enfermedades metabólicas óseas, donde a pesar del amplio arsenal terapéutico disponible aún persisten necesidades no cubiertas. En la presente revisión realizamos una aproximación al descubrimiento y funciones de la vía Wnt con especial atención a sus efectos óseos. A continuación, revisamos brevemente los datos principales acerca de su antagonista endógeno, la esclerostina, por ser donde la investigación farmacológica está más avanzada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);139(14): 634-639, dic. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109625</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vía Wnt y esclerostina como nuevas dianas para la evaluación y el tratamiento de la osteoporosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10184^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50759^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30227^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
