<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113384</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationships between parenting styles and psychopathic traits in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During the last decade, a growing interest has been generated in the analysis and understanding of etiological mechanisms related to the development of psychopathic traits in childhood. Although contextual factors have been poorly studied, some approaches suggest that certain environmental factors, namely parenting practices, may play an important role in the development and expressions of psychopathic personality. In this line, this study aims to analyze, firstly, the relationship between psychopathic traits and parenting practices and, secondly, to what extent the different styles of parental socialization are related to psychopathic personality in childhood. To achieve this objective, data were collected from parents (173) and teachers (113) about 192 children (aged 6-11 years). The results show the existence of statistically significant relationships between parenting practices/styles, and the presence of psychopathic traits, both affective-interpersonal and behavioral, at early ages</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Romero, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante la última década se ha generado un interés creciente por el análisis y comprensión de los mecanismos etiológicos relacionados con el desarrollo de rasgos psicopáticos en la infancia. A pesar de que los factores contextuales han sido escasamente analizados, ciertos planteamientos proponen que determinadas variables ambientales, entre las que cabe destacar las prácticas educativas parentales, juegan un papel relevante en la evolución y manifestación de la personalidad psicopática. En esta línea, el presente trabajo pretende analizar, por una parte, la relación existente entre rasgos psicopáticos y prácticas educativas parentales y, por otra, en qué medida los diversos estilos de socialización parental se relacionan con la personalidad psicopática. Para ello se han empleado los datos proporcionados por padres (173) y profesores (113) de 192 niños entre 6 y 11 años. Los resultados muestran la existencia de relaciones estadísticamente significativas entre prácticas y estilos de socialización parental y la presencia de rasgos psicopáticos a edades tempranas, tanto de tipo afectivo-interpersonal como conductual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;20(3): 603-623, sept.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones entre estilos educativos parentales y rasgos psicopáticos en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
