<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151457</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-6266</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genetic testing for chemothepary in non-small cell lung cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The most commonly used chemotherapy strategy in advanced Non small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) today is the combination of two drugs, mainly cisplatin with another drug (gemcitabine, vinorelbine, taxanes, irinotecan). In the last decade attempts have been made to overcome chemotherapy resistance without benefit in outcomes. There is a &#147;plateau&#148; in the results which seems unable to progress beyond the frontier of 8-10 months of median survival. At present, research in cancer survival is focused on translational pharmacogenomics, with the goal of providing individualized CT based on different genetic traits, such a polymorphisms, gen mutation and overexpresion of drug target gene transcripts, and several molecular assays can been used to tailor chemotherapy in the care of lung cancer patients. Accumulated evidence indicates that many genetic markers are related to chemotherapy resistance. One of the most important goals in translational research is to investigate the clinical use of the DNA repair pathways. Several genes such as ERCC1, XPD polymorphisms. RRM1, BCRA1, etc are related to cisplatin and other drugs resistance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrabal, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, JL de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pagés, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estrategia de tratamiento más utilizada en el cáncer de pulmón no microcítico (CPNM) avanzado es la quimioterapia, concretamente la combinación de dos drogas, principalmente cisplatino con gemcitabina, vinorelbina, taxanos, irinotecan. En el pasado se han hecho intentos en vano de revertir la resistencia a la quimioterapia. La supervivencia en este estadio no suele superar los 8-10 meses con el tratamiento convencional. En el presente, intentos para superar estos resultados se focalizan en la farmacogenómica, con el objetivo de individualizar la quimioterapia basado en aspectos de biología molecular, como los polimorfismos, mutaciones genéticas, y sobreexpresión de genes que pueden funcionar como dianas de los fármacos. La evidencia indica que algunos marcadores genéticos pueden ser predictivos de resistencia a la quimioterapia. Uno de los objetivos en investigación translacional es investigar la aplicación clínica de los sistemas de reparación del DNA. Algunos genes como ERCC1, XPD polymorphisms. RRM1, BCRA1, etc se relacionan con resistencia a cisplatino y otras drogas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neumosur (Sevilla);18(4): 204-211, 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151457</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de la biología molecular en el tratamiento del cáncer de pulmón no microcítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10788^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31722^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31722^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
