<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123253</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tuberculosis mortality in El Puerto de Santa María (1923-1926)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main cause of mortality in El Puerto de Santa María (Cádiz) between 1923 and 1926 was tuberculosis. Our aim is to analyse the tuberculosis mortality rate in this town between 1923 and 1926 and to link it to the principal epidemiological determinants in order to describe the health and sanitary conditions in those years.Descriptive and longitudinal study of the tuberculosis mortality in El Puerto de Santa María between 1923 and 1926. Our information sources were the entries in the register of deaths. A statistical analysis of the variables was carried out (death cause, sex, age, etc&#133;), with the programme SPSS15.0. The total amount of deaths caused by tuberculosis was 217 (13,7 %) and the specific mortality rate was 28,22 in 10,000 inhabitants. 54% (117) were males and 46% (100) females. We can conclude:1. Tuberculosis was the first cause of death in El Puerto between 1923 and 1926.2. The tuberculosis mortality standards are similar in the rest of the province of Cadiz. 3. It would be necessary to perform a deeper study to know whether the cause of the decrease in the mortality rate in 1926 was a consequence of an improvement in health and sanitary policies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muriel, J César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López León, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáinz Otero, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La principal causa de mortalidad en El Puerto de Santa María (Cádiz) durante 1923-1926 es la tuberculosis. El objetivo es analizar la mortalidad por Tuberculosis en dicha localidad durante 1923 a 1926, relacionándola con los principales determinantes epidemiológicos, contribuyendo a la interpretación de la realidad sanitaria de la época. Estudio descriptivo, longitudinal de la mortalidad por tuberculosis en El Puerto durante 1923 a 1926. Las fuentes fueron los libros de Actas de defunción del registro civil. Se realizó el análisis estadístico de las variables (causa de defunción, sexo, edad, etc..), con el programa SPSS 15.0. El total de defunciones por tuberculosis fueron 217 (13,7%) y la Tasa de Mortalidad específica de 28,22 por diez mil habitantes. Atendiendo al sexo, el 54% (117) corresponden a hombres y el 46% (100) a mujeres. Las conclusiones son: 1. La Tuberculosis es la primera causa de mortalidad en El Puerto entre 1923-1926. 2. El patrón que sigue la mortalidad por tuberculosis en El Puerto es superponible al del resto de la provincia. 3. Es necesario una serie temporal más amplia para poder asignar la causa del descenso de las defunciones en 1926 a las mejoras de las condiciones higiénico-sanitarias derivadas de la actuación institucional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;18(38): 71-76, ene.-abr. 2014. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123253</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La mortalidad por tuberculosis en El Puerto de Santa María (1923-1926)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54398^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28029^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
