<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057683</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The aggressive clinical course of pneumococcal endocarditis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A retrospective study was conducted between 2000 and 2005 in five patients with pneumococcal endocarditis were diagnosed at our center. Three female and 2 males, 13 to 76 year-old, were attended. Most of them had left valve endocarditis and were suffering from predisposing conditions. All of them developed distant complications as embolism or septic metastases. Two patients were successfully operated. Surgery was considered in another one but it was discarded due to her poor general condition. This was the only death in the series</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merino de Lucas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella Ortiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero Novella, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reus Bañuls, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo de cinco casos diagnosticados de endocarditis neumocócica en nuestro hospital entre 2000 y 2005. Se trata de tres mujeres y dos varones con edades entre 13 y 76 años. La mayoría tuvieron afectadas las válvulas izquierdas y presentaron enfermedades predisponentes. Todos los pacientes presentaron enfermedad neumocócica a distancia en forma de embolismo o metástasis séptica. En dos pacientes se llevó a cabo cirugía cardíaca con éxito y en otro se desestimó por la mala situación clínica, siendo el único caso que falleció</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(4): 183-186, abr.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057683</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El curso clínico agresivo de la endocarditis neumocócica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31474</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
