<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59195</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atelectasis in general anesthesia and alveolar recruitment strategies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Atelectasis occurs in most patients during generalanesthesia and is the main cause of hypoxemia. Theobjective of this review is to examine the causes anddiagnosis of atelectasis and the different strategies forreducing or preventing this complication and improvingoxygenation. Pulmonary atelectasis is mainly caused by 3factors: compression, gas absorption, and lack ofsurfactant. Compression and gas absorption are, however,the 2 most commonly implicated factors. Lung collapse isaccentuated if pure oxygen is inhaled during induction orif the patient is morbidly obese. Laparoscopic, thoracic,and upper abdominal interventions also carry risk of lungcollapse. Various techniques may be used to preventatelectasis or to reopen collapsed lung tissue. Theseinclude using positive end-expiratory pressure or a hightidal volume&#151;thus providing a higher airway pressure(vital capacity maneuver)&#151;or both in combination.Alveolar recruitment strategies have been tried inbariatric surgery, single-lung ventilation, laparoscopy,and adult respiratory distress syndrome. Theirapplication has reduced or prevented atelectasis, therebyreducing postoperative pulmonary complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las atelectasias están presentes en la mayoría de lospacientes durante la anestesia general y son la principalcausa de hipoxemia. Esta revisión pretende hacer hincapiéen las causas, el diagnóstico y en las diferentes estrategiaspara reducir o evitar la formación de atelectasias.Las atelectasias pulmonares pueden ser causadas principalmentepor tres factores: compresión, absorción de gasy déficit de surfactante, siendo la compresión y la absorciónde gas los mecanismos más implicados. El colapsopulmonar es más acentuado con el uso de oxígeno al100% durante la inducción, en obesos mórbidos, en cirugíalaparoscópica, torácica y abdominal alta. Hay diferentestécnicas que pueden usarse para prevenir las atelectasiaso reabrir el tejido pulmonar colapsado; como laaplicación de presión positiva al final de la espiración(PEEP), el uso de volumen corriente alto o presión altaen la vía aérea (maniobra de capacidad vital-MCV) yMCV combinada con PEEP. Estas estrategias de reclutamientoalveolar (ERA) han sido probadas en cirugíabariátrica, ventilación unipulmonar, laparoscopia y síndromede distrés respiratorio del adulto. Las ERA podríanreducir o evitar la aparición de atelectasias y así disminuirlas complicaciones pulmonares postoperatorias(CPPO) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;55(8): 493-453, oct. 2008. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atelectasias en anestesia general y estrategiasde reclutamiento alveolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38345^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12087</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
