<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-28248</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors related to the short-term remission of tics in children with Tourette syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Tourette syndrome shows a fluctuating evolution, often masked by its comorbidity. Objective. To study the clinical factors predicting the initial remission of tics in children with Tourette syndrome. Patients and methods. All patients attended during the last 5 years at a Child Neurology hospital-based out-patient clinic, with the diagnosis of Tourette syndrome according to DSM-IV criteria, were selected. Outcome measure: total remission of tics during at least 3 months, evaluated during the patient&#146;s second visit to our clinic. Demographic, clinic and therapeutic variables were studied. Statistical analysis was based on the Student t test or non parametric tests, as necessary. Results. 53 patients, 44 males and 9 females. Age at starting tics: 6.9 ± 2.2 years, time of evolution: 2 years (range: 1-9.4). Comorbidity in 51%: 34% with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), 17% with obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD) and school underachievement: 26%. Familial antecedents of tics, OCD, or ADHD: 49%. Tics remission at second visit to our clinic: 41.5%. Patients without remission were those with an earlier onset of tics (p = 0.085), longer time of evolution (p &lt; 0.05), or school underachievement (p = 0.024). Remission was not statistically associated with treatment. OCD and ADHD were associated with school failure but were not related to the tics evolution. Conclusion. The short-term (at second visit), temporal (minimum 3 months) total remission of Tourette syndrome was not related to treatment but to previous duration of the syndrome and to factors (other than OCD and ADHD) that lead to school failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Gilles de la Tourette (SGT) tiene una evolución fluctuante, frecuentemente enmascarada por la comorbilidad que presenta, y de difícil predicción. Objetivo. Estudiar los factores que puedan predecir la remisión inicial, transitoria o no, del SGT. Pacientes y métodos. Se seleccionaron los pacientes con SGT, según los criterios del DSM-IV, atendidos en la consulta de Neuropediatría durante los últimos cinco años. La variable de interés fue la remisión de los tics durante al menos tres meses, evaluada en la segunda visita y analizada en relación con los parámetros demográficos, clínicos y terapéuticos. El método estadístico utilizado se basó en la t de Student cuando la distribución fue normal, y en pruebas no paramétricas en caso contrario. Resultados. De los 53 pacientes, 44 eran varones y nueve mujeres. La edad media de inicio de los tics fue de 6,9 ñ 2,2 años y el tiempo de evolución, de dos años (intervalo: 1-9,4). Asociaban trastornos comórbidos el 51 por ciento de ellos: el 34 por ciento presentó trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad (TDAH), el 17 por ciento, trastorno obsesivo compulsivo (TOC), y mal rendimiento escolar, el 26 por ciento. Encontramos antecedentes familiares de tics, TOC o TDAH en el 49 por ciento. Los tics habían remitido en la segunda visita en el 41,5 por ciento del total de pacientes, y fue menos frecuente dicha remisión en los de inicio más temprano (p = 0,085), mayor tiempo de evolución (p &lt; 0,05) y mal rendimiento escolar (p = 0,024). La remisión no se asoció a la instauración del tratamiento. El TDAH y el TOC se asociaron al mal rendimiento escolar, pero no a la remisión/persistencia de los tics. Conclusión. En la remisión temporal (mínimo: 3 meses) y a corto plazo (segunda visita) del SGT no influye la administración de tratamiento, sino la duración previa del síndrome y factores (aparte del TDAH y el TOC) que condicionen un mal rendimiento escolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(10): 901-903, nov. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores que influyen en la remisión a corto plazo de los tics en niños con síndrome de Gilles de la Tourette</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Garaizar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Carrera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prats Viñas, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ribes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-28248</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30227</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24820</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1887</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10188</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19333</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
