<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83152</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Overactive bladder symptons in pregnancy and puerpery: Is there a relationship between the symptoms score and quality of life?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: During pregnancy, hormonal change, increase in the body mass index and the pressure caused by the enlarged uterus over the bladder and pelvic floor, are some factors involved in lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS). This study was made to evaluate the correlation between pregnancy and delivery way with LUTS. Material and method: This open prospective study was carried out using the overactive bladder questionnaire short form (OABq-SF). A total of 60 patients enrolled this study. The mean age was 24 year, raging from 14 to 40 years. The patients were evaluated during the third trimester and 6 months after delivery. Statistical analysis of the OABq-SF scores was made using the Pearson method. Results: Mean OABq-SF score during pregnancy was 35.2 and 6 months after delivery decreased to15. Quality of life was 82.9 during pregnancy and increased to 88.4 at 6 month after delivery. Patient's perception, that is correlation, was 55.02 (p=0.0001) during pregnancy and 36.1% (p=0.0046). Clinical correlation index was 6.7%. Conclusions: Our study demonstrated that in spite of LUTS being more important during pregnancy, there is no significant clinical correlation in patient's perception (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gome, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brisola, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bigozzi, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riccetto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrmann, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botelho, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palma, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: Los síntomas del tracto urinario bajo durante la gravidez pueden ser influenciados por factores, como adaptaciones hormonales, aumento de peso corporal y sobrecarga de presión por el útero grávido sobre la vejiga y el suelo pélvico. La propuesta fue evaluar la correlación de esos síntomas con la calidad de vida en las fases gestacional y puerperal. Material y método: Estudio prospectivo utilizando el Overactive Bladder Questionnaire Short Form (OABq-SF). Participaron 60 gestantes, edad media de 24 años (14&#150;40), evaluadas durante el último trimestre gestacional y revaluadas 6 meses después del parto. El análisis estadístico correlacionó historia obstétrica, síntomas miccionales y calidad de vida con el método Spearman, utilizando el método de Pearson para la correlación del score de OABq-SF. Resultados: La media del score del OABq-SF durante la gravidez fue de 35,2, en tanto que 6 meses después del parto declinó a 15,0. Para la calidad de vida se verificó una media de 82,9 durante la gravidez y de 88,4 6 meses después del parto. La percepción de las pacientes fue del 55,02% (p=0,0001) durante la gravidez y del 36,01% (p=0,0046) durante el puerperio. La correlación clínica fue del 6,7%. Conclusión: Nuestro estudio demostró que a pesar de que los síntomas del tracto urinario bajo se encuentran presentes durante la gravidez, no hay correlación clínica en la percepción de las gestantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(9): 794-797, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas de vejiga hiperactiva en mujeres en fase gestacional y puerperal: ¿existe correlación entre los síntomas y la percepción de la calidad de vida?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12080^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52129^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
