<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166122</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social context and hardiness in the Central American athlete</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objectives of this study are to identify the factors of social context that influence resistance to stress in high-performance athletes; and to determine which social context factor athletes perceive as the most influential for hardiness. Participants were 405 athletes from 23 sports disciplines, selected from national teams of 9 countries participating in the XII Central American and Caribbean Sports Games held in Boca del Rio Veracruz, Mexico, in 2014. The age range was 18 to 47 years (M = 24.2, SD = 5.07). Athletes answered two questionnaires assessing their perception of social context factors that influence athletic performance and traits of hardiness. The results showed that, from athletes&#146; point of view, themselves and their skills, as well as coaches, are the factors of social context that mostly influence hardiness. This indicates that athletes&#146; involvement in their sport widely depends on their internal characteristics and traits, besides of their coaches&#146; abilities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Jiménez, Nallely</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaenes Sánchez, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponce-Carbajal, Nancy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tristán, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos de este trabajo son la identificación de los factores del contexto social que influyen en la resistencia al estrés de los deportistas de alto nivel y a su vez determinar el factor del contexto social que perciben los atletas como de mayor influencia para la personalidad resistente. Los participantes fueron 405 deportistas seleccionados nacionales de 9 países y 23 deportes, durante los XII Juegos Deportivos Centroamericanos y del Caribe, llevado a cabo en Boca del Rio Veracruz, en México, en el 2014. El rango de edad fue de 18 a 47 años (M = 24.2, DT = 5.07). Los deportistas contestaron dos cuestionarios para evaluar la percepción de su contexto social influyente en el rendimiento deportivo y rasgos de personalidad resistente. Los resultados encontrados evidencian desde la perspectiva del deportista, a él mismo y sus habilidades y al entrenador como los factores del contexto social que influye más en la personalidad resistente, lo que demuestra que la implicación en su deporte depende en su mayoría por las propias características y rasgos de los deportistas además de las habilidades de su entrenador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.2): 91-97, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166122</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contexto social y personalidad resistente en el deportista de Centroamérica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2524</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
