<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98777</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Information and communication technologies in health systems. A new challenge for the nurse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At present, many countries are incorporating Information and Communication Technology (ICT) in their care processes, opening a new perspective in the management of health information. The importance gained by ICT is determined by the possibility to improve the efficiency of resources devoted to the health care of the population. In this process of change the human factor must be taken into account and regarded as a crucial element of the health sector, since despite the health workload and the level of demand by the people, a level of professional excellence must be ensured in order to advance in the implementation of ICT. Therefore, in this new context of care, nursing professionals have a key role, raising the need for specific training to enable them to respond to this new situation. The incorporation of information and communication technologies in health care involves a process of adjustment as well asa social structural change, both on the part of professionals and on the part of the users. This article aims to analyze the process of incorporating ICT in health systems and some of the most important implications this has for the nurses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galimany Masclans, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca Roger, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girbau García, M. Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad, diversos países están incorporando las Tecnologías dela Información y la Comunicación (TIC) en sus procesos asistenciales, abriendo una nueva perspectiva en la gestión de la información sanitaria. La importancia que adquieren las TIC viene determinada por la posibilidad de poder mejorar la eficiencia de los recursos dedicados al cuidado de la salud de la población. En este proceso de cambio hay que tener en cuenta el factor humano como elemento crucial del sector salud, ya que a pesar de la presión asistencial y el nivel de exigencia de la población, debe garantizar un nivel de excelencia profesional que permita avanzaren la implantación de las TIC. Por todo ello, en este nuevo contexto asistencial, los profesionales enfermeros tienen un papel clave, lo que plantea la necesidad de disponer de una formación específica que les permita dar respuesta a esta nueva situación. La incorporación de las TIC en el ámbito sanitario implica un proceso de adaptación, así como un cambio estructural y social tanto de los profesionales como de los usuarios. El presente artículo tiene como objetivo analizar el proceso de incorporación de las TIC en los sistemas sanitarios y algunas de las implicaciones más destacadas que ello supone para las enfermeras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;15(3): 6-10, abr. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las tecnologías de la información y la comunicación en los sistemas sanitarios. Un nuevo reto para la enfermera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19134^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
