<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80088</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypoactive sexual desire disorder: comparison of two questionnaires (the brief profile of female sexual function and the health and female sexual dysfunction in primary care) in women with hysterectomy plus bilateral oophorectomy versus normal women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To study hypoactive sexual desire disorder (HSDD) with two questionnaires of sexual function in a sample of women with surgical menopause compared with normal women. Material and methods We present a series of 98 cases, 56 with total hysterectomy plus bilateral oophorectomy (group I) and 42 normal women (group II). All women completed the Brief Profile of Female Sexual Function (BPFSF) questionnaire, while 52 women (13 in group I and 39 in group II) completed the Health and Female Sexual Dysfunction- Primary Care (HFSD-PC) questionnaire. Results After both questionnaires were administered, testosterone patches (Intrinsa) were provided to 7/56 women in group I (12.5%) and 20/42 in group II (47.61%) (p&lt;0.001), which was the opposite of what was expected, with much higher interest among normal women. Results The correlation between reported sexual desire and the BPFSF was positive in 36 women in group I (64.28%) and in 35 in group II (82.33%) (p&lt; 0.05), with a higher correlation in group II. Results Sexual problems were found in 14 women (25%) in group I, consisting of abstinence in 10/14 women for distinct reasons. The mean BPFSF score was 13.69 in group I and 11.83 in group II, indicating HSDD in both groups but with no statistically significant differences. There was no statistically significant difference in the mean age of the two groups (58.48 years in group I versus 50.88 years in group II). Results The findings of the HFSD-PC were as follows: 80.76% were in a stable relationship, 82.69% were married, 59.61% had attended primary school, 57.69% were in paid employment, 51.92% engaged in physical exercise (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Olmos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Estudio del trastorno del deseo sexual hipoactivo (TDSH) con 2 cuestionarios de función sexual en una muestra de mujeres con menopausia quirúrgica y su comparación con mujeres normales. Material y métodos Presentamos una serie de 98 casos, 56 operadas de histerectomía y anexectomía bilateral (grupo Q) y 42 casos normales (grupo N). Realizaron el cuestionario BPFSF (brief profile of female sexual function &#145;breve perfil de la función sexual femenina&#146;). El cuestionario sobre salud y disfunción sexual femenina en atención primaria (SyDSF-Ap) lo realizaron 52 casos, 13 del grupo Q y 39 del grupo N. Resultados Tras la realización de ambos cuestionarios, la intención de tratamiento con parches de testosterona (Intrinsa) fue: 7 de 56 (12,5%) en el grupo Q y 20 de 42 (47,61%) en el grupo N (p&lt;0,001). Curiosamente, al revés de lo esperado, hubo más interés en las mujeres no operadas. Resultados Con el BPFSF, la correlación en deseo sexual oral y el cuestionario fue positiva en 36 casos del grupo Q (64,28%) y en 35 casos del grupo N (82,33%) (p&lt;0,05), hubo mayor correlación en el grupo N. Resultados En el grupo Q hubo problemas sexuales en 14 casos (25%). En 10 de esos casos no se practicaban relaciones sexuales por diferentes causas. Las puntuaciones con BPFSF medias fueron de 16,39 (grupo Q) frente a 11,83 (grupo N), indicando ambas TDSH pero sin diferencias significativas, como tampoco en la edad media de ambos grupos: 58,48 años frente a 50,88 años (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);37(1): 14-26, ene.-feb. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno del deseo sexual hipoactivo: comparación de 2 cuestionarios (breve perfil de la función sexual de la mujer y salud y disfunción sexual femenina en atención primaria) en 2 grupos de mujeres (ovariectomizadas e histerectomizadas, y normales)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33534^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23534</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
