<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166182</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of heart failure. Surgical ventricular restoration and mitral surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The efficiency of the heart as a pump is intimately linked to the structure and function of heart muscle fibers. The process of ventricular remodeling that occurs following myocardial damage must be regarded as an etiopathologic factor in heart failure. In this situation, the development of mitral regurgitation triggers symptoms and worsens prognosis. In recent years, the technique of surgical ventricular restoration has been introduced as a novel diagnostic and therapeutic approach in patients with heart failure. Magnetic resonance imaging has become the principle exploratory technique for diagnosis and follow-up in these patients. From a surgical point of view, we must adopt a three-pronged approach to these patients: the coronary vessels must be dealt with, the mitral valve must be repaired if there is at least moderate regurgitation, and ventricular volume must be reduced (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuenca Castillo, José J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La eficiencia del corazón como bomba esta íntimamente ligada a la estructura y la disposición de sus fibras musculares. Debemos considerar el proceso de remodelado ventricular, tras un daño miocárdico, como un elemento etiopatogénico de la insuficiencia cardiaca. En este contexto, el desarrollo de insuficiencia mitral funcional dispara la sintomatología del paciente y empeora su pronóstico. En los últimos años se ha introducido el concepto de restauración ventricular como una nueva aproximación diagnóstica y terapéutica en el paciente con insuficiencia cardiaca. La resonancia magnética se ha convertido en la exploración princeps para el diagnóstico y el seguimiento de estos pacientes. Desde el punto de vista quirúrgico debemos entender el abordaje de estos pacientes como una trilogía: hay que actuar sobre las arterias coronarias, reparar la válvula mitral si hay una insuficiencia al menos moderada, y realizar una reducción del volumen ventricular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);6(supl.F): 71f-81f, 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de la insuficiencia cardiaca. Restauración ventricular y cirugía de la válvula mitral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9132^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9133^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13706^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
