<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77914</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The helicopter health as a resource medicalized, it hasbeen using since a few years ago as a component of the networkpre-hospital medical care. This mode of transportationalready known and used mainly in war events, is havingan exponential growth since its introduction a few yearsago as a regular element of assistance and transportationmedicalized in civil society. For what should be interpretedas complementary support to assistance with prehospitalland resources, and on rare occasions where it has beenused as a single resource assistance. This concept that entrymay seem detrimental to that resource air, far from it isactually a justification of the need for air support in the prehospitalmedical care, and especially urgent.This article intends to give the most appropriate careapproach and describe protocols activation of this resourceas part of systems prehospital emergency care, being separateappeal but integrated within them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cid Dorribo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Rubio,  J.  M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Udi Campo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El helicóptero sanitario, como recurso medicalizado, seviene utilizando desde hace pocos años como elementointegrante de la red asistencial médica prehospitalaria. Estemedio de transporte ya conocido y utilizado sobre todo eneventos bélicos, está teniendo un crecimiento exponencialdesde su implantación hace pocos años como elementohabitual de asistencia y transporte medicalizado en la sociedadcivil. Por lo que se debería interpretar como un apoyocomplementario a la asistencia prehospitalaria con recursosterrestres, siendo en contadas ocasiones dónde se ha de utilizarcomo único recurso asistencial. Este concepto que deentrada puede parecer que vaya en detrimento de dichorecurso aéreo, lejos de ello es realmente una justificación dela necesidad del apoyo aéreo en la asistencia médica prehospitalaria,sobretodo la urgente.Este artículo pretende darle el enfoque asistencial másadecuado y describir los protocolos de activación de dichorecurso formando parte de los sistemas de urgencia asistencialesprehospitalarios, siendo un recurso independientepero integrado dentro de los mismos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;8(1): 26-32, ene.-mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77914</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión de recursos aéreosmedicalizados: el helicópterosanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22322</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50257</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
