<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99845</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Literature review of the subject of a research project</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It can be very complicated to obtain relevant information through searching the medical literature if you do not know how it is organized and indexed or if you do not know how to use the specialized databases. For a successful review of the literature, you need to know what you are looking for and the key words for an effective search of the specialized databases and libraries and especially of the internet. It is essential to critically evaluate the information selected. Finally, using a reference manager can facilitate the gathering, organization, systematization, and integration of the bibliographic references in the documents generated in the study. This article aims to provide guidelines for efficient searching for information and for accurate, critical use of the literature. It makes recommendations about strategies for managing references to help to ensure the success of a research project (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vilanova, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hacer una búsqueda de la literatura médica para obtener información puede ser realmente complicado sin conocer de forma básica cómo se halla organizada o indexada la bibliografía; y si se desconoce cómo utilizar las bases de datos. Una revisión bibliográfica debe partir de saber lo que se busca y con el conocimiento e identificación de las palabras clave que nos conducirán a una búsqueda efectiva en las bases de datos, bibliotecas específicas y especialmente en Internet. Será imprescindible realizar una evaluación crítica de la información seleccionada. Finalmente, disponer de un gestor bibliográfico puede facilitar la recopilación, organización, sistematización e integración de las referencias bibliográficas en los documentos generados en la investigación. El objetivo del artículo es proporcionar una guía para la búsqueda eficaz de la información y la utilización crítica y precisa de la bibliografía y hacer recomendaciones acerca de estrategias de gestión de referencias para poder desarrollar con éxito un proyecto de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);54(2): 108-114, mar.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión bibliográfica del tema de estudio de un proyecto de investigación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53809^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31204</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50213</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
