<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90617</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-invasive diagnosis of posttraumatic thoracic splenosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intrathoracic splenosis is a generally asymptomatic entity incidentally diagnosed after the completion of an Rx, CT scan or MRI for another reason. The performance of scintigraphy with 99mTc-labelled heat-denatured erythrocytes allows the noninvasive diagnosis of this entity and avoids more aggressive diagnostic techniques such as FNAP or thoracotomy. Because this splenic tissue may be partially or fully functioning and therefore may have some beneficial immune function for the patient, the management of this entity should be conservative. Radioisotopic scintigraphy with 99mTc labelled heat-denatured erythrocytes is the technique with the greatest specificity in the demonstration of splenic tissue. The presence of subpleural pulmonary nodules, associated or not with intra-abdominal nodules, together with the existence of previous partial or total splenectomy, traumatic or not, with or without associated rupture of the diaphragm, should raise suspicion of the presence of intrathoracic splenosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balsa Bretón, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alonso, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez Tineo, S. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillejos Rodríguez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Valle, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariana Monguía, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Penín Gonzalez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pey Illera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Paulini, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paniagua Correa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esplenosis intratorácica es una entidad generalmente asintomática que se diagnostica de forma incidental tras la realización de una radiografía, TAC o RM por otro motivo. La realización de una gammagrafía con hematíes desnaturalizados marcados con 99mTc permite el diagnóstico no invasivo de esta entidad y evita técnicas de diagnóstico más agresivas. Dado que este tejido esplénico puede ser parcial o totalmente funcionante, y por tanto tener cierta función inmunológica beneficiosa para el paciente (suficiente para brindar protección frente a la sepsis postesplenectomía), el manejo de esta entidad debe ser conservador. La técnica radioisotópica de gammagrafía con hematíes desnaturalizados marcados con 99mTc es la que presenta mayor especificidad para la demostración de tejido esplénico. La presencia de nódulos pulmonares subpleurales, asociados o no a nódulos intraabdominales, junto con la existencia de antecedentes de esplenectomía parcial o total, traumática o no, deben hacer sospechar la presencia de una esplenosis intratorácica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;30(5): 311-313, sept.-oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90617</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico no invasivo de la esplenosis torácica postraumática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31028^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31028^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4999^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31028^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
