<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107961</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up of the patients in the program of self-management of oat</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Development in the implementation of the programme of the anticoagulated patient self-management concludes with the follow-up. Your objective is to guide, support, advise and provide the patient with the necessary support material and training and improve their autonomy and quality of life. Contacts are established through both scheduled and unscheduled visits and phone calls. The article describes this phase interspersed, so serve as a practical example, with the experience which has resulted in our unit. Relates the workloads of different professionals and the most the recurrent causes of consultation. Also lists the contents that must be observed in the contacts: practical problems in the puncture or tables of dosing, assessment of the implementation of the programme, dump the data registered in the coagulometer to the computer system, revision of the autoanalyzer, material supply and treatment settings. Reviews of records that help us detect and assess problems that are resolved by a continuous and permanent health education almost in its entirety should periodically conduct. Finally, we present a study on the incidence of adverse effects occurring in self-controlled patients that we are witnessing in our unit(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segovia Gómez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro Fernández, Francisco de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abejón Arroyo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Martínez, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Casanova,  Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo Marín, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco García, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta Cuesta, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Vázquez, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erasto Villar Rojas, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las heridas crónicas representan una carga para el sistema sanitario español; hoy en día es necesaria una optimización de los recursos empleados y por esto debe justificarse el uso de unos productos, en detrimento de otros, a través de estudios de coste-efectividad que demuestren beneficio económico para los profesionales y calidad de vida para el paciente. El presente artículo compara el uso de una nueva tecnología aplicada en formato de espuma de poliuretano, la TLC-NOSF, con los productos de uso más habitual en el tratamiento de heridas. Dicha comparativa se realiza mediante un modelo de coste- efectividad (Modelo Markov). Los resultados demuestran que los tratamientos con apósito de espuma de poliuretano con TLC-NOSF son coste-efectivos versus los realizados con espumas de poliuretano de uso más habitual en España(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;35(11): 747-752, nov. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107961</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Coste-Efectividad de un apósito de espuma de poliuretano con TLC-NOSF. Estudio en el tratamiento de las úlceras venosas de pierna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15050^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
