<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167677</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioral activation for the control of depression in cancer patients: a review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Behavioral activation (AC) is defined as a therapeutic process focused in increasing patient&#146;s behaviors through an environment that provides the patient reinforcing contingencies. This therapy is empirically validated as a non-pharmacological treatment for depression because of its flexibility and its patient-tailored focus. The purpose of this work was to do a literature review about behavioral activation and major depressive disorder in cancer patients. We conducted a systematic review into seven databases using the PICO system in order to identify the articles. Studies in both English and Spanish published between 2000-2016 were included; the keywords "depression", "behavioral activation therapy" and "cancer patients" were used in the search. 373 articles were found, however only 10 fulfilled the required criteria. The studies were carried out with non-hospitalized ambulatory patients; all the interventions were conducted individually. Results showed the relevance of behavioral activation as the main treatment of Major Depressive Disorder in an oncological population. We suggest to perform a clinical evaluation before applying AC considering: the tumor characteristics, clinical stage, type of treatment, collateral or adverse effects, cumulative toxicity and the natural story of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo González, María Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerra Gálvez, Ana Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reynoso Erazo, Leonardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordaz Carrillo, Maetzin Itzel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Activación Conductual (AC) se define como un proceso terapéutico focalizado a incrementar conductas que coloquen al paciente en un ambiente que proporcione contingencias reforzantes. Este tipo de terapia está validada empíricamente como tratamiento no farmacológico para la depresión y se caracteriza por ser flexible y estar centrada en las necesidades únicas del paciente. El objetivo de este trabajo fue revisar la literatura disponible relacionada a los efectos de la terapia de activación conductual sobre el Trastorno Depresivo Mayor en pacientes con cáncer. Se realizó una revisión bibliográfica sistemática en siete bases de datos, utilizando el sistema PICO para la identificación de los artículos. Se incluyeron estudios en idioma inglés y español publicados en el período 2000-2016 localizados con los descriptores "depresión", "terapia de activación conductual" y "pacientes con cáncer". Se encontraron un total de 373 artículos, de los cuales sólo diez cumplieron con los criterios establecidos para esta revisión. Los estudios se realizaron en pacientes con cáncer no hospitalizados, atendidos en la consulta externa y la intervención se realizó de manera individualizada. Los estudios reportan la utilidad de la AC para el tratamiento del Trastorno Depresivo Mayor en población oncológica. Se sugiere realizar una evaluación clínica para implementar la AC, considerando: la biología del tumor, el estadio clínico, la modalidad de tratamiento y los efectos adversos derivados del mismo, la toxicidad acumulada y la historia natural de la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);14(2/3): 203-216, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167677</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Activación conductual para el control de la depresión en pacientes oncológicos: una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3240</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
