<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98771</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Virulence genes and intimin types of Shiga-toxin-producing Escherichia coli isolated from cattle and beef products in Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A total of 153 Shiga-toxin-producing Escherichia coli (STEC) isolates from feces of cattle and beef products (hamburgers and ground beef) in Argentina were characterized in this study. PCR showed that 22 (14%) isolates carried stx1 genes, 113 (74%) possessed stx2 genes and 18 (12%) both stx1 and stx2. Intimin (eae), enterohemolysin (ehxA), and STEC autoagglutinating adhesin (saa) virulence genes were detected in 36 (24%), 70 (46%) and in 34 (22%) of the isolates, respectively. None of 34 saa-positive isolates carried the gene eae, and 31 were ehxA-positive. Fourteen (7 of serotype O26:H11 and 4 of serotype O5:H-) isolates had intimin b1, 16 isolates possessed intimin g1 (11 of serotype O145:H- and 5 of serotype O157:H7), 5 isolates had intimin type e1 (4 of serotypes O103:H- and O103:H2), and one isolate O111:H- showed intimin type q/g2. Although the 153 STEC isolates belonged to 63 different seropathotypes, only 12 accounted for 58% of isolates. Seropathotype ONT:H- stx2 (18 isolates) was the most common, followed by O171:H2 stx2 (12 isolates), etc. The majority (84%) of STEC isolates belonged to serotypes previously found in human STEC and 56% to serotypes associated with STEC isolated from patients with hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS). Thus, this study confirms that cattle are a major reservoir of STEC pathogenic for humans. To our knowledge, this is the first study that described the presence of saa gene in STEC of serotypes O20:H19, O39:H49, O74:H28, O79:H19, O116:H21, O120:H19, O141:H7, O141:H8, O174:H21, and ONT:H21. The serotypes O120:H19 and O185:H7 were not previously reported in bovine STEC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, Enrique A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardez, Maria Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, Guillermo H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Marcelo E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Jesus E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, Azucena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucchesi, Paula MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parma, Alberto E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padola, Nora L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kruger, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dahbi, Ghizlane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Etcheverria, Analia I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio hemos caracterizado un total de 153 Escherichia coli productores de toxinas Shiga (STEC) aisladas de las heces de ganado bovino y de carne picada y hamburguesas de vacuno en Argentina. Los ensayos de PCR mostraron que 22 (14%) aislamientos llevaban el gen stx1, 113 (74%) presentaban el gen stx2 y que 18 (12%) tenían ambos genes. Los genes de virulencia para la intimina (eae), la enterohemolisina (ehxA) y la adhesina autoaglutinante de STEC (saa) fueron detectados en 36 (24%), 70 (46%) y 34 (22%) de los aislamientos, respectivamente. Ninguno de los 34 aislamientos saa-positivos llevaba el gen eae, pero 31 eran ehxA-positivos. Catorce aislamientos (7 del serotipo O26:H11 y 4 del serotipo O5:H-) tenían la intimina b1, 16 poseían la intimina g1 (11 del serotipo O145:H- y 5 del serotipo O157:H7), 5 aislamientos eran positivos para la intimina tipo &amp;#949;1 (4 de los serotipos O103:H- y O103:H2), y un aislamiento O111:H- mostró la intimina tipo &amp;#952;/g2. Aunque los 153 aislamientos de STEC pertenecían a 63 seropatotipos, sólo 12 constituían el 58% de los aislamientos. El seropatotipo ONT:H- stx2 (18 aislamientos) fue el más común, seguido por el O171:H2 stx2 (12 aislamientos), etc. La mayoría de los aislamientos (84%) de STEC pertenecían a serotipos encontrados previamente en seres humanos y el 56% a serotipos asociados con STEC aislados de pacientes con el síndrome urémico hemolítico (HUS). Por tanto, este estudio confirma que el ganado bovino es un importante reservorio de STEC patógenos para humanos. Según nuestra información, este es el primer estudio que describe la presencia del gen saa en STEC de los serotipos O20:H19, O39:H49, O74:H28, O79:H19, O116:H21, O120:H19, O141:H7, O141:H8, O174:H21, y ONT:H21. Los serotipos O120:H19 y O185:H7 tampoco habían sido descritos previamente en STEC de origen bovino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;7(4): 269-276, dic. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98771</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Genes de virulencia y tipos de intiminas de Escherichia coli productoras de toxinas Shiga aisladas de ganado bovino y carne de vacuno en Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37540</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52551^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2457^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8629^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32888^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
