<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76203</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A descriptive study of the child and adolescent new cases attended at a mental health service during one year</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a descriptive study of the children and adolescents attended for the first time at the Mental Health Services of Aranjuez (Area 11, Community of Madrid) during the year 2004. A total of 314 new patients were reviewed. The aim of this study is double: on one hand, to describe the socio-demographic characteristics of these new patients and, on the other, to study the distribution of the diagnostic categories with respect to sex and age variables. In order to collect the data, we used the computerised program of the Mental Health Services of the Community of Madrid (Accumulated Registry of Cases)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Belloso Ropero, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espín Jaime, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se presenta un estudio descriptivo de los niños y adolescentes nuevos vistos en el Servicio de Salud Mental de Aranjuez (Área 11 de la Comunidad de Madrid) durante el año 2004. La muestra clínica consta de 314 pacientes nuevos. El propósito del estudio es doble: por un lado presentar algunas características sociodemográficas de los niños y adolescentes nuevos vistos y, por otro, mostrar los diagnósticos y las diferencias en función de la edad y el sexo. Se ha recurrido al programa informático de los Servicios de Salud Mental de distrito de la Comunidad de Madrid (Registro Acumulado de Casos: R. A. C.) para la obtención de los datos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;29(104): 329-354, jul.-dic. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76203</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo de los niños y adolescentes nuevos vistos en un servicio de salud mental en el periodo de un año</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d556^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d299^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
