<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037061</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mercury and neurotoxicity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aims. Mercury is a metal that is widely used in hundreds of applications nowadays. This metal has proved to be extremely toxic in humans, especially for the central nervous system, both in cases of exposure from everyday applications (e.g. dental fillings) and from environmental exposure. Unfortunately, most of the research carried out on this metal is relatively recent and many questions remain unanswered. The aim of this work is to review all the knowledge we have at the present time about the mechanisms of action of this metal.     Development. To do so, we discuss the latest scientific findings about the toxic processes that are activated, as well as its effects on the cellular cytoskeleton, its genotoxicity or the production of compounds that have been linked to neurodegeneration. Conclusions. Its prolonged period of latency, ambiguous symptoms and the activation of generalised toxic mechanisms call for urgent efforts to be made in basic research to help determine as clearly as possible the way this metal acts in the body. This knowledge will provide us not only with the way to obtain therapies but also with the hope of developing biomarkers that make it possible to carry out early and reliable diagnoses of the damage done and of individual susceptibility</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herculano, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nascimento, J. L. Do</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corvelo, T. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo-López, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo. El mercurio es un metal ampliamente utilizado hoy día en cientos de aplicaciones. Este metal ha demostrado ser sumamente tóxico para el ser humano, especialmente para el sistema nervioso central, tanto por la exposición a sus aplicaciones cotidianas (p. ej., las amalgamas dentales), como por exposiciones ambientales. Desdichadamente, la mayor parte de la investigación desarrollada sobre este metal es relativamente reciente, y quedan todavía muchos interrogantes por responder. El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar todo lo que se conoce hasta ahora sobre los mecanismos de acción de este metal.     Desarrollo. Para ello, se discuten los hallazgos científicos más recientes sobre los procesos tóxicos activados, como las alteraciones en el citoesqueleto celular, la toxicidad genética o la producción de compuestos relacionadas con la neurodegeneración.     Conclusiones. Un prolongado período de latencia, una sintomatología esquiva y la activación de mecanismos tóxicos generalizados, demandan urgentemente la aplicación de grandes esfuerzos en investigación básica para ayudarnos a discernir lo más claramente posible la forma de actuación de este metal. Este conocimiento nos proporcionará no sólo el camino para la obtención de terapias, sino la esperanza de desarrollar biomarcadores que posibiliten un diagnóstico precoz y fiable del daño producido y de la susceptibilidad individual</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;40(7): 441-447, abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037061</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mercurio y neurotoxicidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8804^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9058^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34357^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24529^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
