<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149489</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contributions to the development of a public health information system SESPAS Report 2010</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">New public health laws are a conceptual and methodological adaptation of public health to current social needs, their common link being the incorporation of health in all policies. This represents a new strategic approach that will require different information systems, which should incorporate the rapid advances made in the field of information technology and communication. The aim of this article was to identify the most important aspects to be taken into account in information systems in public health from a technological perspective, both in their development and in the elements that compose them. To overcome the fragmentation of information systems in public health, these systems must be successfully integrated among themselves and with other health and non-health systems. To achieve this task, technical, semantic and organizational interoperability must be ensured. Emerging technologies should be considered to support these new strategies, especially Web 2.0 tools. This new strategic development will pose additional challenges because of its size and the diversity of the departments involved. It is proposed that information systems will include the elements of Web 2.0 and support systems for decision-making technologies in addition to the traditional operational systems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Merino, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García León, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las leyes de salud pública aprobadas o en tramitación suponen una adecuación conceptual y metodológica de la salud pública a las necesidades sociales actuales, y tienen en común la incorporación de la salud en todas las políticas. Ello significa un nuevo enfoque estratégico que requerirá unos sistemas de información distintos, que además deberán incorporar los rápidos avances en el campo de las tecnologías de la información y la comunicación. El objetivo de este trabajo es identificar los aspectos más relevantes a tener en cuenta en los sistemas de información en salud pública desde la perspectiva tecnológica, tanto en su desarrollo como en los elementos que los componen. Para superar la fragmentación de los sistemas de información en salud pública es fundamental conseguir la integración de ellos entre sí y con los sistemas asistenciales y extrasanitarios, para lo que es preciso avanzar en la interoperabilidad técnica, semántica y organizativa. Habrá que tener en cuenta las tecnologías emergentes como apoyo a las nuevas estrategias, entre las que destacan las herramientas soporte a la Web 2.0. El desarrollo de los sistemas de información de apoyo a la nueva estrategia presentará dificultades añadidas por su tamaño y por la diversidad de organismos que intervendrán. Se propone que los sistemas de información, además de los ya tradicionales sistemas transaccionales, incluyan los elementos de la Web 2.0 y los sistemas de soporte a la toma de decisiones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(supl.1): 96-100, dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149489</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportaciones al desarrollo de un sistema de información en salud pública. Informe SESPAS 2010</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
