<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153110</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sociodemographic factors that influence the anxiety of death in nursing students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To measure the fear of their own death, and that of another person, by nursing students, and analyze its relationship with sociodemographic variables and their training in palliative care. Method: An observational, descriptive and cross-sectional study. The participants were 188 nursing students who responded to a questionnaire with sociodemographic variables and the Collet-Lester fear of death scale (CLFDS). The means and standard deviations, Student t test, ANOVA, and Pearson correlation coefficient were calculated. Results: Significantly higher scores were obtained in subscales 'Fear of death of another', and for the following variables, a woman (p = 001), believer in God (p &lt; 05) and someone who made no other studies on palliative care (p &lt; 05). No significant differences in terms of relational contact with death and dying, or in the practice of belief, or as regards wishing to be professionally devoted to palliative care. Significant differences in three subscales were observed depending on the academic year. Age or religion variables did not correlate with Collet-Lester subscales. Conclusions: The training of nursing students in specific skills for end of life support, managing personal fear of death, as well as the spiritual and/or religious needs of students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morillo-Martín, María Socorro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Rodríguez, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Serrano, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán González-Serna, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Medir el miedo de la propia muerte y la de otra persona en estudiantes de Enfermería y analizar sus relaciones con variables sociodemográficas y con la formación realizada sobre cuidados paliativos. Método: Diseño observacional, descriptivo y transversal. Participaron 188 estudiantes de Enfermería, que respondieron a un cuestionario con variables sociodemográficas y a la escala de miedo a la muerte de Collet-Lester (CLFDS). Se calculan medias y desviaciones típicas, prueba t de Student, ANOVA y coeficiente de correlación de Pearson. Resultados: Puntuaciones significativamente más altas se obtienen en la subescala miedo a la muerte de otros (MMO) y para las variables: mujer (p = 0,001), creyente (p &lt; 0,05) y persona que no realizó otros estudios sobre cuidados paliativos (p &lt; 0,05). No existen diferencias significativas en cuanto al miedo según contacto relacional o no con la muerte y el morir, respecto a la práctica o no de creencias, ni respecto a los deseos de dedicarse profesionalmente a los cuidados paliativos. Se observan diferencias significativas según el curso académico en 3 de la subescalas. Las variables edad o religiosidad no correlacionan con las subescalas de Collet-Lester. Conclusiones: La formación de los estudiantes de Enfermería en competencias específicas para el acompañamiento al final de la vida ha de incluir habilidades tanto del manejo del propio duelo como de autocuidados espirituales y/o religiosos de los alumnos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;23(3): 113-121, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153110</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores sociodemográficos que influyen sobre la ansiedad ante la muerte en estudiantes de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
