<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054285</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular mortality in mercury miners</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: To study the mortality from cardiovascular diseases after long-term exposure to inorganic mercury. Population and method: 3,998 workers exposed to mercury in Minas de Almadén y Arrayanes S.A. were studied. The follow-up period was a century, since 1895 to 1994. The study was completed assessing the vital status and the basic cause of death, in case of fatalities. Standardized mortality ratios (SMR) by age, sex and calendar period were calculated. Expected deaths were obtained from age, sex and calendar period specific from rates for the Spanish and regional populations. Results: A significant increase in mortality due to circulatory diseases was found (SMR 1.11, 95% confidence interval [CI], 1.02-1.20), especially for hypertension (SMR 2.78, 95% CI, 1.89-3.95), cerebrovascular diseases (SMR 1.17, 95% CI, 1.01-1.35), and other diseases of the heart (SMR 1.51, 95% CI, 1.29-1.76). Ischemic heart disease showed a significant decrease in these workers, with an SMR 0.69, and a CI between 0.57 and 0.84. Cerebrovascular diseases showed a trend over the time since first exposure, duration of exposure and with the accumulated expected exposure, while none of the exposure variables was lineally associated with mortality due to ischemic heart diseases. There was also a trend over the time since first exposure for mortality due to hypertension and other heart diseases. Conclusions: This study suggests an association between long-term exposure to inorganic mercury in workers of mercury mines and an increased risk of circulatory mortality, especially mortality due to hypertension and cerebrovascular diseases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Español, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Gómez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Klink, José Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boffetta, Paolo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Quintana, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Estudiar la mortalidad por enfermedades cardiovasculares de los mineros de mercurio. Población y método: Se ha realizado un seguimiento de 3.998 trabajadores de Minas de Almadén y Arrayanes, S.A., desde 1895 hasta 1994. Se determinaron el estado vital y la causa básica de defunción. Se calcularon las razones de mortalidad estandarizadas (RME) según edad, sexo y período de calendario. Las muertes esperadas se obtuvieron a partir de las tasas específicas de la población española y la castellano-manchega. Resultados: Se encontró un aumento de la mortalidad por enfermedades circulatorias (RME = 1,11; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 1,02-1,20), y en particular se observaron excesos de mortalidad para la hipertensión (RME = 2,78; IC del 95%, 1,89-3,95), enfermedades cerebrovasculares (RME = 1,17; IC del 95%, 1,01-1,35) y otras enfermedades del corazón (RME = 1,51; IC del 95%, 1,29-1,76). La cardiopatía isquémica presentó una disminución significativa en estos trabajadores (RME = 0,69, IC del 95%, 0,57-0,84). En el caso de las enfermedades cerebrovasculares, se observó una tendencia con el tiempo transcurrido desde la primera exposición, con la duración de la exposición y con la exposición acumulada esperada, mientras que ninguna de las variables de exposición apareció asociada linealmente con la mortalidad por enfermedades isquémicas. Los datos también evidenciaron una tendencia con el tiempo transcurrido desde la primera exposición para la mortalidad por hipertensión y por otras enfermedades del corazón. Conclusiones: El estudio indica que existe asociación entre la exposición a largo plazo al mercurio inorgánico experimentada por los trabajadores de las minas de mercurio y el aumento del riesgo de mortalidad cardiovascular, en particular, del riesgo de muerte por hipertensión y por enfermedad cerebrovascular</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(20): 766-771, mayo 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad por enfermedades cardiovasculares en los mineros de mercurio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9094^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8804^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2600^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
