<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112884</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Numb Chin syndrome: a clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Numb Chin Syndrome o Malignat mentoniana neuropathy is a disease quite unknown by the general dentist but familiar to specialist in oncology. The patients present a uni-or-bilateral numbness of the areas innervated by the mentonian nerves, symptom which is not usually related with tumors in this area. We report a case of a man who suffered since he was 82 years old, in November of 2005, a mild fever and anesthesia in the area innervated by the right mentonian nerve. He also presented an endodontic treatment of the first lower right molar. After multiple studies the patient was diagnosed from a lung cancer which had spread to the bones, in which, until his death in May of 2008 we did not observe a tumor in the jaw area. On the other hand, the treatment of metastatic cancers with bisphosphonates I. V. can cause osteonecrosis, which can make difficult a correct diagnosis of jaw pain or numbness. In the case we find a combined presence of osteonecrosis for this reason and pain and numbness of the same area (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Maroto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Román Aragón, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle González, A del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Rivas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome del mentón entumecido o neuralgia mandibula maligna es un cuadro poco conocido por el odontólogo general pero con el que están bastante familiarizados los especialistas en Oncología. El paciente afecto presenta, dentro de un cuadro oncológico, un entumecimiento uni o bilateral de las áreas inervadas por los nervios mentonianos, sin relación, en muchos casos, con una tumoración a ese nivel. Presentamos un caso de un varón de 82 años que padecía, en noviembre de 2005, un cuadro febril leve y anestesia en el territorio inervado por el mentoniano derecho y un molar 46 con tratamiento de conductos obturados años atrás. Tras múltiples estudios, resultó padecer un cáncer pulmonar con diseminación ósea en el que, hasta su fallecimiento (mayo- 2008) no se puedo constatar masa tumoral en el territorio mandibular. Por otro lado, el tratamiento de los cánceres metastáticos o primitivamente óseos con bisfosfonatos I. V que pueden provocar osteonecrosis, aún pueden confundir más a la hora de llegar a un correcto diagnóstico del dolor o entumecimiento maxilar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);27(3): 127-130, jul.-sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112884</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome del mentón entumecido. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24222^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29338^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7165^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
