<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161441</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: from parents to children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Multiple studies of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) have recognised a heritability factor in that a higher frequency of the disorder is observed in children with an affected relative. Our aim was to determine the association between ADHD symptoms in young children enrolled in five schools in Bogota and a history of ADHD symptoms in their parents using the Wender-Utah Rating Scale. Methodology. Case-control study of participants selected according to DSM-IV criteria for ADHD and the Behavioral Assessment System for Children (BASC) completed by parents and teachers; the WISC-IV scale was used to exclude children with cognitive deficit. Parents completed the Wender-Utah Rating Scale to retrospectively identify any ADHD symptoms in childhood. A score of 36 was used as a cutoff point. Results. The study included 202 children: 117 cases and 85 controls. A positive history of ADHD symptoms in childhood was identified for 16% of 175 mothers and 20.6% of 141 fathers. The presence of symptoms in either parent, especially the mother, constitutes a significant risk factor for ADHD in children and this relationship persists after controlling for different variables. If both parents have the disorder, the risk tends to increase. Conclusion. Although ADHD has been linked to a genetic component, other environmental factors may be involved in the disorder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamora-Miramón, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vélez-van-Meerbeke, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán-Ramírez, GM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Talero-Gutiérrez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En el trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad (TDAH), la heredabilidad ha sido reconocida en múltiples estudios. En este sentido, se ha observado una mayor frecuencia del trastorno en niños con familiares afectados. El objetivo fue determinar la asociación entre la presencia de síntomas de TDAH en niños escolares de 5 instituciones educativas de Bogotá y el antecedente de síntomas de TDAH en sus padres utilizando el cuestionario de Wender-Utah. Metodología. Estudio de casos y controles seleccionados de acuerdo con los criterios DSM-IV para TDAH, la escala multifuncional de la conducta (BASC) para padres y maestros y WISC-IV para descartar déficit cognitivo. A los padres se les aplicó un cuestionario de Wender-Utah para identificar de manera retrospectiva síntomas de TDAH en su infancia. Un score de 36 fue tomado como punto de corte. Resultados. De 202 niños disponibles, 117 fueron casos y 85 controles. Un 16% de 175 madres y un 20,6% de 141 padres tuvieron antecedentes positivos para síntomas de TDAH en la infancia. La presencia de síntomas en alguno de los progenitores, principalmente en la madre, es un factor de riesgo significativo para la presencia de TDAH en los niños y esta relación persiste si se controla por diferentes variables. Si los 2 progenitores tienen el cuadro, existe una tendencia a que el riesgo aumente. Conclusión. A pesar de que el TDAH se ha asociado a un componente genético, otros factores del entorno pueden estar involucrados en la génesis del trastorno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(3): 158-165, abr. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad: de padres a hijos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
