<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115888</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between drug use and psychopathological variables of risk in university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Research has been studying the relationships between drug use and the risk of suffering psychopathological disorders. This study analyzed the relationships existing between this use and certain psychotic disorder risk variables: hallucination, schizotypy and cognitive fusion. Method: Several screening questionnaires on drug use (CAGE), a questionnaire on «cognitive fusion» (TAFS), another on hallucination proneness (LSHS-R) and another on schizotypy (O-LIFE-R) were given to a sample of 308 students at the University of Almería with a mean age of 19.51 years (SD= 2.11). Results: The results found show how cognitive fusion is positively related to use of cannabis and cocaine, the scores on the schizotypy scale correlated positively with use of alcohol and cannabis, and the scores on a hallucination proneness correlated positively to use of cannabis. Regression equations were found that predicted the use of these substances from the variables of vulnerability to suffering from schizophrenia spectrum disorders. Conclusions: The results show an association between drug use and the risk variables studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Montoya, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Montes, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores Cubos, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaldívar Basurto, Flor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la investigación ha venido estudiando las relaciones entre el consumo de sustancias y el riesgo de padecimiento de trastornos psicopatológicos. En este estudio se han analizado las relaciones existentes entre dicho consumo y determinadas variables de riesgo para los trastornos psicóticos: alucinaciones, esquizotipia y fusión cognitiva. Método: se administraron diversos cuestionarios de screening relativos al consumo de drogas (CAGE), un cuestionario de «fusión cognitiva» (TAFS), otro de predisposición a las alucinaciones (LSHS-R) y otro de esquizotipia (O-LIFE-R), a una muestra de 308 estudiantes universitarios de la Universidad de Almería, con una media de edad de 19,51 años (DT= 2,11). Resultados: los resultados hallados muestran cómo la fusión cognitiva se relaciona positivamente con el consumo de cannabis y cocaína; cómo las puntuaciones en la escala de esquizotipia correlacionan positivamente con el consumo de alcohol y cannabis y cómo las puntuaciones en una escala de predisposición a las alucinaciones correlaciona positivamente con el consumo de cannabis. Se establecieron ecuaciones de regresión que predecían el consumo de dichas sustancias a partir de las variables de vulnerabilidad al padecimiento de trastornos del espectro esquizofrénico. Conclusiones: los resultados muestran una asociación entre el consumo de sustancias y las variables de riesgo estudiadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);25(4): 433-439, oct.-dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115888</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones entre el consumo de drogas y variables de riesgo psicopatológicas en jóvenes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22937^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
