<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83049</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessing coping strategies in alcoholics: Comparison while controlling for Personality disorders, Cognitive impairment and Benzodiazepine misuse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Better coping skills are related to greater capacity for dealing with stressful situations. This relationship could be relevant for the prevention of alcohol-misuse relapse. Relapse rate is higher among severe alcoholics. The current study examines whether this may be due to a lack of coping skills in those cases. The COPE (Coping Orientations to Problems Experienced) is a questionnaire used for assessing coping strategies. Method: COPE scores of 216 alcohol inpatients are compared while controlling for personality disorders (PDs), cognitive impairment (CI) and benzodiazepine misuse (BM).Results: Patients with PDs score higher on the scales of Humor, Venting emotions, Substance use and Use of instrumental support. However, there are no differences in COPE scores attributable to CI or BM. Conclusions: Alcoholics with Personality disorders use maladaptive coping strategies. Patients presenting CI or BM have low capacity for introspection and are unable to properly evaluate their own abilities, so that they tend to give a socially favorable but unrealistic image of themselves. Longitudinal studies are needed to evaluate the predictive validity of the coping skills before training alcoholics, who are especially difficult to assess due to their lower capacity for objective self-observation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monras, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mondon, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jou, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Un mejor uso de las estrategias de afrontamiento esta relacionado con una mayor capacidad para enfrentarse a situaciones difíciles y estresantes. Esta relación podría ser relevante en la prevención de las recaídas en el consumo de alcohol. Los alcohólicos más graves tienen mayor tasa de recaídas. Se estudia si ello es debido a que disponen de menos estrategias de afrontamiento. El COPE (Coping Orientations toProblems Experienced) es un cuestionario que las evalúa. Metodología: Se comparan las puntuaciones del COPE en 216 pacientes alcohólicos ingresados, según la existencia de trastornos de la personalidad (TP), deterioro cognitivo (DC) y abuso de benzodiacepinas (BZD). Resultados: Los pacientes con TP tienen mayor puntuación en las escalas de Humor, Desahogo emocional, Uso de alcohol y drogas y en el factor de Búsqueda de Ayuda. Sin embargo los pacientes que padecen DC o BZD casi no se diferencian de los que no lo padecen. Conclusiones: Los alcohólicos con TP utilizan estrategias de afrontamiento más desadaptativas y dependientes de elementos externos. Sin embargo los pacientes con DC o BZD tienen muy poca capacidad de introspección y no evalúan objetivamente sus propias habilidades, tendiendo a ofrecer una imagen socialmente favorable, pero no realista. Antes de entrenar a los pacientes alcohólicos graves en estrategias de afrontamiento debería contrastarse la validez predictiva de éstas con estudios de seguimiento, teniendo en cuenta que son pacientes con dificultades en evaluar objetivamente sus propias habilidades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);22(3): 191-198, jul.-sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83049</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias de afrontamiento en enfermos alcohólicos. Diferencias según el consumo de benzodiacepinas, los trastornos de la personalidad y el deterioro cognitivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
