<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136058</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multimodal analgesia for postoperative pain in the renal failure: Metamizole, oral fentanyl and fentanyl patch</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic kidney failure (CKF) is a clinical situation with an increasing prevalence due to the high incidence of hypertension and diabetes both of them considered as risk factors, and also due to the rise on life expectancy. These patients need a carefully anaesthetic management in order not to aggravate their renal function. Postoperative analgesia becomes a key point at this end. Fentanyl´s pharmacokinetic totally fits in handling pain in CKF´s patients. Thanks to the great commercial display on fentanyl´s presentation we are able to develop suitable strategies to offer high quality postoperative analgesia. We describe a case of a severe CKD patient undergoing hip arthroplasty following this analgesia plan during the first 48 hours postoperative: Continuous infusion of metamizol (6 g/24 hours) + transdermal fentanyl (25 µg/h) + transmucosal fentanyl (200 µg) if necessary. With this analgesia approach we obtained a satisfactory pain control without vomits, itching or constipation; the patient had a proper rest at night (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neira Reina, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesa Suárez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portilla Huerta, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Forte, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aceña Fabián, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad renal crónica (ERC) es una situación clínica cada vez más prevalente. Esto se debe en gran medida al aumento de la esperanza de vida y al incremento de la incidencia de la diabetes mellitus (DM) y la hipertensión arterial (HTA). Estos pacientes requieren un manejo cuidadoso de la analgesia postoperatoria. El fentanilo es un fármaco cuya farmacocinética encaja en el manejo del dolor en la ERC. Sus diferentes presentaciones comerciales permiten elaborar estrategias adecuadas para brindarles una analgesia postoperatoria de gran calidad. Presentamos el esquema de analgesia postoperatoria de un paciente en fallo renal severo sometido a artroplastia de cadera: metamizol (6 gramos/24 horas) en perfusión durante 48 horas, fentanilo transcutáneo TTS 25 microgramos/hora durante 48 horas y fentanilo oral transmucosa 200 microgramos en caso de exacerbación del dolor. Este tratamiento analgésico permitió el control satisfactorio del dolor sin que se presentaran vómitos, prurito ni estreñimiento; la calidad del sueño y el descanso nocturno fueron buenos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;22(2): 59-61, mar.-abr. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136058</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analgesia multimodal para el postoperatorio en la enfermedad renal crónica: fentanilo transcutáneo, fentanilo oral transmucosa y metamizol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33577</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
