<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126333</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fracture of the Pelvis. A complex fracture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of a young patient with a fractured pelvis due to a traffic accident. The patient had a positive FAST scan and transient response to fluid therapy. Due the biomechanics of the accident we suspected the existence of lesions that could not be observed with basic X-ray procedures. A 3-D image study revealed the lesions that were not visible by X-ray but suspected due to the nature of the trauma. This case enables us to review the A-B-C-D-E approach to the assessment of a polytraumatised patient and to emphasis the importance that a fractured pelvis could have for these patients as it is a cause of shock due to massive internal haemorrhage. Patients with a suspected fracture of the pelvis should be moved in block, maintaining the head-neck-trunk in line and once stabilised the pelvis should then be immobilised using a pelvic binder or other specific devices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torralba Melero, Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gallego, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de un paciente joven con fractura de pelvis por accidente de tráfico. La fractura se presentó con una clínica abdominal y ECO FAST positivo con respuesta transitoria a la fluidoterapia. La biomecánica del accidente permitió sospechar la existencia de lesiones no observables con la proyección radiológica básica. El estudio de imagen diferido en 3D reveló la existencia de lesiones no visibles en la radiografía inicial, pero sospechadas por los antecedentes traumáticos. El presente caso nos permite repasar la sistemática de actuación ante un paciente politraumatizado (A-B-C-D-E), así como destacar la importancia que las fracturas de pelvis pueden tener en estos pacientes, ya que son causa de shock por pérdida de sangre masiva a nivel interno. Los pacientes con sospecha de fractura pélvica deben ser movilizados en bloque, manteniendo la alineación del eje cabeza-cuello-tronco, y una vez comprobada la estabilidad se debe proceder a la inmovilización de la pelvis, bien mediante un fajado pélvico o bien mediante dispositivos específicos para ello (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;4(1): 85-87, feb. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126333</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura de Pelvis. Una fractura compleja</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23481</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38643^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38643^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38643^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38643^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
