<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116471</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Saccharomyces cerevisiae infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Saccharomyces cerevisiae is an ubiquitous yeast widely used in industry and it is also a common colonizer of the human mucosae. However, the incidence of invasive infection by these fungi has significantly increased in the last decades. Aims: To evaluate the infection by S. cerevisiae in a hospital in southern Brazil during a period of 10 years (2000-2010). Methods: Review of medical records of patients infected by this fungus. Results: In this period, 6 patients were found to be infected by S. cerevisiae. The age range of the patients was from 10 years to 84. Urine, blood, ascitic fluid, peritoneal dialysis fluid, and esophageal biopsy samples were analyzed. The predisposing factors were cancer, transplant, surgical procedures, renal failure, use of venous catheters, mechanical ventilation, hospitalization in Intensive Care Unit, diabetes mellitus, chemotherapy, corticosteroid use, and parenteral nutrition. Amphotericin B and fluconazole were the treatments of choice. Three of the patients died and the other 3 were discharged from hospital. Conclusions: We must take special precautions in emerging infections, especially when there are predisposing conditions such as immunosuppression or patients with serious illnesses. The rapid and specific diagnosis of S. cerevisiae infections is important for therapeutic decision. Furthermore, epidemiological and efficacy studies of antifungal agents are necessary for a better therapeutic approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Souza Goebel, Cristine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mattos Oliveira, Flavio de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Severo, Luiz Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Saccharomyces cerevisiae es una levadura ubicua muy utilizada en la industria y también presente en la microbiota humana. Sin embargo, en las últimas décadas ha habido un aumento significativo de infecciones fúngicas invasivas causadas por este hongo. Objetivos. Hacer un estudio retrospectivo de las infecciones por S. cerevisiae en un período de 10 años (2000-2010) en un hospital del sur de Brasil. Métodos. Revisión de las historias clínicas de los pacientes infectados por este hongo. Resultados. En este período, se encontraron 6 pacientes infectados por S. cerevisiae. El rango de edad de los pacientes oscilaba entre los 10 y los 84 años. Las muestras analizadas procedían de orina, sangre, líquido ascítico, fluido de diálisis peritoneal y biopsia de esófago. Las infecciones por S. cerevisiae estaban relacionadas con neoplasias, trasplantes, procedimientos quirúrgicos, insuficiencia renal, uso de catéter venoso central, ventilación mecánica, internación en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos, diabetes mellitus, quimioterapia, corticosteroides y nutrición parenteral. El fluconazol y la anfotericina B fueron los antifúngicos más utilizados en el tratamiento. Tres de los 6 pacientes presentaron mejoría clínica y fueron dados de alta, y los otros 3 fallecieron. Conclusiones. Hay que poner especial atención en las infecciones emergentes, especialmente cuando existan factores predisponentes, tales como inmunosupresión o enfermedades graves. El diagnóstico rápido y específico de la infección por S. cerevisiae es importante para la decisión terapéutica. Son necesarios estudios epidemiológicos y de eficacia de los agentes antifúngicos con el fin de obtener un mejor enfoque terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;30(3): 205-208, jul.-sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección por Saccharomyces cerevisiae</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24654^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15401^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12815^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d950</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12815^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27953^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15401^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15401^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
