<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148825</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Group violence in young people: A critical review. This article presents a critical review of existing knowledge about psycho-social factors related to group violence in young people. Considering empirical evidence on the extent and development of this phenomenon in Western society, results related to individual factors and to primary and secondary socialization sources are reviewed. Given that this type of violence is stimulated and maintained within the peer-group context, it is necessary to understand the predispositional role of individual factors in relation to the influence of primary socialization sources. In this regard, the capacity of the peer group to respond adaptively to developmental, circumstantial and structural challenges is of particular relevance. The article also discusses possible interpretations of some contradictory and controversial results, and offers suggestions for future lines of research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San José, M del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scandroglio, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Jorge S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, M Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo presenta una revisión crítica del conocimiento existente acerca de los factores psico-sociales que se relacionan con la violencia grupal juvenil. Partiendo de un breve análisis de la evidencia empírica sobre la dimensión y evolución que el fenómeno de la violencia juvenil mantiene en el ámbito occidental, se revisan los resultados referidos a los factores individuales y a lo ámbitos de socialización primaria y secundaria. Al hallarse dicha conducta propiciada y mantenida en el contexto grupal, se pone de manifiesto la necesidad de interpretar la capacidad predisponente de los factores individuales en función de la influencia de los ámbitos de socialización, cobrando especial importancia la capacidad del grupo de iguales para responder adaptativamente a los desafíos evolutivos, cincunstancias o estructurales. El trabajo plantea diferentes reflexiones que facilitan la interpretación de los resultados contradictorios o polémicos generados en relación con algunos factores y ofrece, a su vez, diversas sugerencias para el desarrollo de futuras investigaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(supl.1): 6-15, 2002.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Violencia grupal juvenil: una revisión crítica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7773^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
