<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89419</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Morphometric analysis of corneal endothelium after intravitreal ranibizumab (Lucentis®) in age-related macular degeneration treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PurposeTo determine the effect of intravitreal injection of 0.5mg ranibizumab on the corneal endothelium in patients with age-related macular degeneration (AMD).MethodsObservational, prospective case series pilot study. Twenty-six eyes of 26 consecutive patients with AMD were evaluated. All participants received one monthly intravitreal injections of 0.5mg ranibizumab for three consecutive months. The follow-up period was 6 months. Central corneal specular microscopy was performed before injection and at 7 days and 6 months after the first intravitreal injection. The endothelial cell density, coefficient of variation of cell size, and percentage of hexagonal cells were analyzed and the central corneal thickness was measured.ResultsThere were no significant differences in the endothelial cell densities, coefficients of variation of cell size and percentages of hexagonal cells before injection and at 7 days and 6 months after the first intravitreal ranibizumab injection (P&gt;0.5). There was also no significant difference in central corneal thickness measurements through the follow-up period (P&gt;0.5).ConclusionsRepeated intravitreal injections of 0.5mg ranibizumab do not seem to cause substantial changes in the corneal endothelium(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro-Rebollo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Herreros, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Rico, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-San Gil, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teus, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoEvaluar el efecto de la inyección intravítrea de 0,5mg ranibizumab sobre el endotelio corneal en pacientes con degeneración macular asociada a la edad (DMAE).MétodoEstudio piloto de serie de casos, observacional y prospectivo con observador enmascarado. Veintiséis ojos (26 pacientes) con DMAE fueron evaluados. Todos los pacientes recibieron 1 inyección intravítrea mensual de 0,5mg de ranibizumab durante 3 meses consecutivos. El periodo de seguimiento fue de 6 meses. El endotelio corneal central fue evaluado antes, a los 7 días y a los 6 meses de la primera inyección de ranibizumab con microscopía especular. La densidad de las células endoteliales, coeficiente de variación del tamaño celular y porcentaje de hexagonalidad celular fueron analizados. También fue medido el espesor corneal central.ResultadosNo se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los valores preinyección y postinyección a los 7 días y 6 meses de la primera inyección de ranibizumab en las densidades de células endoteliales, coeficientes de variación del tamaño celular y porcentajes de hexagonalidad celular (p&gt;0,5). Tampoco se encontraron modificaciones significativas en el espesor corneal central a lo largo del periodo de seguimiento (p&gt;0,5).ConclusionesInyecciones intravítreas repetidas de 0,5mg ranibizumab no parecen causar cambios importantes sobre el endotelio corneal a los 6 meses de seguimiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;85(10): 329-332, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89419</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis morfométrico del endotelio corneal tras ranibizumab intravítreo en la degeneración macular asociada a la edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22889^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22889^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22889^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28920^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28920^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33559^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
