<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97105</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience with regional anesthesia for reduction of shoulder dislocation in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the effective use of the suprascapular nerve block for anesthesia-analgesia during reduction of shoulder dislocation in the emergency department. Cases: We performed suprascapular nerve blocks in the emergency department on 10 patients with glenohumeraldis l ocation in whom treatment had not been possible under other techniques for sedation or anesthesia-analgesia. The block was performed following anatomical reference points. The suprascapular nerve blocks were highly effective inreducing pain and facilitated a high rate of successful repair of the glenohumeral dislocations. Conclusions: The suprascapular nerve block was effective for reduction of shoulder dislocation and offered numerous advantages over other techniques. It was feasible for emergency department use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Alcaraz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belinchón De Diego, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belinchón De Diego, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogués Tomás, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Describir la eficacia del bloqueo supraescapular frente a otras técnicas de analgesia-anestesia en la reducción de las luxaciones de hombro en urgencias. Casos clínicos: Se utilizó el bloqueo supraescapular en el área de urgencias en diez pacientes con luxación glenohumeral que no había sido posible reducir mediante diferentes técnicas de sedoanalgesia/anestesia. Realizamos la técnica de este bloqueo siguiendo las referencias anatómicas. El bloqueo supraescapular fue muy efectivo en la disminución del dolor y consiguió una alta tasa de éxito en la reducción de la luxación glenohumeral. Conclusiones: El bloqueo supraescapular es una técnica eficaz en la reducción de la luxación de hombro con numerosas ventajas sobre otras, y es muy asequible al urgenciólogo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(4): 303-306, ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97105</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia en el empleo de anestesia regional para la reducción de las luxaciones de hombro en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13167^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13164^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
