<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103849</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Omalizumab for the Treatment of Atopic Dermatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Atopy is almost always associated with an elevated immunoglobulin (Ig) E production. Omalizumab is a monoclonal anti-IgE antibody that is currently indicated for the treatment of cases of asthma that satisfy certain criteria. A number of studies have been published on the usefulness of omalizumab in the treatment of atopic dermatitis, and the results have been variable. We present our experience in the treatment of 9 patients with severe atopic dermatitis refractory to at least 2 systemic drugs. All patients reported a decrease in pruritus and an improvement in quality of life. Good control of the skin disease was achieved with omalizumab in monotherapy in 2 patients, and there was a slight improvement in the eczematous lesions in 4 patients. Those patients who also had asthma achieved good control of their respiratory symptoms and did not require additional therapy. Omalizumab is a well-tolerated and safe drug that can be useful for the treatment of severe atopic dermatitis refractory to other systemic therapies. This monoclonal anti-IgE antibody is a major therapeutic advance as it opens the door to the management of atopic dermatitis using systemic immunomodulating therapies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ramón, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paravisini, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leis-Dosil, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfageme-Roldán, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Antón Martínez, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La atopia se acompaña de forma casi constante de una producción elevada de inmunoglobulina E (IgE). Omalizumab es un anticuerpo monoclonal anti-IgE, que actualmente está indicado en pacientes con asma que cumplen determinados criterios. Se han publicado algunos estudios sobre la utilidad del omalizumab en el tratamiento de la dermatitis atópica (DA), con resultados variables. Presentamos nuestra experiencia en 9 pacientes con dermatitis atópica grave, refractaria al menos a dos fármacos sistémicos. Todos los pacientes tratados referían una disminución del prurito y una mejoría en su calidad de vida. Los que presentaban asma consiguieron un buen control desde el punto de vista respiratorio, sin precisar otros tratamientos adicionales. En dos casos se consiguió un buen control en monoterapia, apreciándose una discreta mejoría de las lesiones de eccema en 4 de ellos. El omalizumab es un fármaco bien tolerado y seguro. Puede ser útil en el tratamiento de pacientes con DA grave, refractaria a otros tratamientos sistémicos. Este anticuerpo monoclonal anti-IgE abre la puerta a los tratamientos inmunomoduladores sistémicos para el manejo de la DA, lo que supone un gran avance terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;103(7): 624-628, sept. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103849</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Omalizumab en el tratamiento de la dermatitis atópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11976</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22210</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3893^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50345</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
