<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046666</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of ambulatory blood pressure monitoring at initial evaluation and in the follow-up of patients with diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prevalence of arterial hypertension in diabetes is very high.    Several interventional studies have demonstrated the benefits of    blood pressure (BP) control in diabetes, because diabetic patients    are especially vulnerable to elevations of BP. Then, an appropriate    and accurate evaluation of BP is mandatory. The ambulatory BP    monitoring is a technique which permits frequent determination    of BP during normal activities of subjects. This method has shown    more information on the risk of end-organ lesion by elevations    of BP and the clinical relevance of an appropriate and sustained    BP control during 24 h. In the diabetic patient there is a marked    systolic BP elevation besides an augmented pressure pulse in relation    to an early and severe disruption of large vessels elasticity and    the frequent alteration of circadian variability. Indications for the    ambulatory blood pressure monitoring both in type 1 and type 2    diabetes are proposed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Redón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prevalencia de hipertensión en la diabetes es muy elevada    y diversos estudios de intervención han demostrado el beneficio    que comporta el control de la presión arterial ya que el diabético    es un paciente altamente vulnerable a las elevaciones de    PA, por lo que se precisa de una evaluación adecuada y de la    mayor precisión. La monitorización ambulatoria de PA permite realizar    múltiples medidas durante las actividades normales del individuo.    Este método ha proporcionado una mayor información respecto    al riesgo de sufrir daño orgánico por la elevación de la PA    y a la importancia clínica de establecer un control adecuado y mantenido    de los mismos a lo largo de las 24 horas. En el paciente diabético    existe un predominio marcado de la elevación a expensas    de la PA sistólica que se acompaña de una gran amplitud en la    presión del pulso como consecuencia de una alteración precoz y    severa de la elasticidad de los grandes vasos y frecuente alteración    de la variabilidad circadiana. Se proponen indicaciones para el uso    de la monitorización ambulatoria de la presión arterial tanto en    diabetes mellitus tipo 1 como tipo 2</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;21(4): 275-280, oct.-dic. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046666</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la monitorización ambulatoria de presión arterial en la evaluación inicial y en el seguimiento del paciente diabético</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d422^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
