<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15584</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychosocial support and type a behaviour pattern in dealing with sports competition related stress</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychosocial support has a particular influence on the adaptation of young athletes to competition. One manner of dealing with stress in these developmental stages is made up of the Type-A Behaviour pattern (TABP). This paper deals with the relationship among perceived competitive stress, worry about the sport competition and TABP in secondary school pupils of both sexes oriented towards high performance sport, with grants form the Castellón Center for Techniucal Spoerting Inititation (Centro de Iniciación Técnico-Deportiva de Castellón). The relationship between the variables has been put to the test using a structural equation model, considering perceived psychosocial support as an idependent variable, TABP as a dependent variable and the grade of worry about sport competition as a modulator variable. The results confirm the hypothesis and de signs of the coefficients obtained are coherent with the substantive aspects of the model (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosel, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallarés, Jacinto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la adaptación de los deportistas jóvenes a la competición cobra especial influencia el apoyo proveniente de los agentes psicosociales. Un estilo de enfrentamiento al estrés en esas etapas evolutiva se encuentra formado por conductas típicas de Patrón de Conducta Tipo- A (PCTA). Se investiga la relación entre el apoyo psicosocial percibido, la preocupación excesiva por la competición y la aparición de PCTA en una muestra de deportistas jóvenes de un Centro Técnico-Deportivo de Castellón, con una clara orientación al rendimiento deportivo. Dicha relación ha sido puesta a prueba mediante un modelo de ecuaciones estructurales, considerando como variable independiente el apoyo psicosocial percibido, como variable dependiente el PCTA y como variable moduladora el grado de preocupación manifestado antes de la competición deportiva. Los resultados confirman la hipótesis, y los signos de los coeficientes obtenidos son coherentes con los aspectos substantivos del modelo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(1): 147-151, feb. 2001. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón de conducta tipo-A y estrés en deportistas adolescentes: algunas variables mediadoras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
