<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101168</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life after biochemical recurrence in patients with prostate cancer. How and how long do patients live after biochemical recurrence?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Routine monitoring of PSA in patients with localized prostate cancer radically treated permits to identify those with biochemical recurrence only. Treatment options for biochemical failure include observation, surgery, radiotherapy alone or combined with hormonal therapy, brachytherapy, cryotherapy and hormone therapy exclusively. These treatments determine a specific pattern of changes (urinary function, bowel, sexual and hormonal) that can negatively impact the quality of life, so that the indication must be made in a judicious way and always in consonance with patient&#146;s expectations and preferences. Decisions on how and when to treat biochemical failure are complicated and the impact of salvage therapy on clinical outcome is unknown. Rates of prostate cancer control after salvage therapy with prostatectomy, brachytherapy or cryotherapy vary between 20-80% of cases according to selected patient characteristics. Because individuals with BF may be clinically asymptomatic for many years without treatment, it is essential that physicians and patients have a clear understanding of the potential impact of these on the quality of life(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Taboada Valladares, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballo Castro, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Caamaño, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peleteiro Higuero, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Crespo, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Mateos, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La monitorización rutinaria de PSA en pacientes con cáncer de próstata localizado tratados radicalmente permite identificar aquellos con recurrencia bioquímica exclusiva. Las opciones de tratamiento para el fallo bioquímico incluyen observación, cirugía, radioterapia externa sola o asociada a hormonoterapia, braquiterapia, crioterapia y hormonoterapia exclusiva. Estos tratamientos determinan un patrón específico de cambios (función urinaria, intestinal, sexual y hormonal) que puede impactar negativamente sobre la calidad de vida, de manera que su indicación debe realizarse de una manera juiciosa y siempre en consonancia con las expectativas y preferencias de los pacientes. Las decisiones sobre cómo y cuándo tratar un fallo bioquímico son complicadas y el impacto de las terapias de rescate sobre el resultado clínico final es desconocido. Las tasas de control del cáncer de próstata tras tratamiento de rescate con prostatectomía, crioterapia ó braquiterapia oscilan entre el 20-80% de los casos en función de las características de los pacientes seleccionados. Dado que los individuos con fallo bioquímico pueden estar clínicamente asintomáticos durante muchos años sin tratamiento es esencial que médicos y pacientes dispongan de un claro conocimiento del potencial impacto de las mismas sobre la calidad de vida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(1): 193-206, ene.-feb. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101168</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida después recidiva bioquímica en los pacientes con cáncer de próstata. ¿Cómo y cuánto viven los pacientes después de recidiva bioquímica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50290</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6885^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1944^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
