<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165801</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recessive aggressive vulvar angiomixoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aggressive angiomyxoma of the vulva is a dermal and subcutaneous rare benign neoplasm. Its most common location is the pelvic and/or genital area. It presents slow growth and high rate of relapse, although no metastatic potential. Its incidence is very low, 250 cases have been collected out of the world literature. The definitive diagnosis is based on histological and immunohistochemical study. A wide local resection should be the surgical treatment as to completely remove the diseased tissue with cleanmargins. We report the case of a 35-year-old woman affected by an aggressive angiomyxoma of the vulva who has been treated at our hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez González, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Cardenal, Marta de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coronel Villarán, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El angiomixoma vulvar agresivo es una neoplasia benigna dérmica y subcutánea, infrecuente. Su localización más frecuente es la zona pélvica y/o genital. Presenta un crecimiento lento y alto índice de recidiva, aunque sin potencial metastático. Su incidencia es muy baja, habiéndose recogido en la literatura 250 casos a nivel mundial. El diagnóstico definitivo se basa en el estudio histológico e inmunohistoquímico. El tratamiento deberá ser quirúrgico mediante resección amplia, siendo el objetivo extirpar por completo la lesión con bordes libres de enfermedad. Presentamos un caso de angiomixoma agresivo de localización vulvar de una mujer de 35 años atendido en nuestro centro hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);60(4): 351-354, jul.-ago. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165801</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Angiomixoma vulvar agresivo recidivante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15245^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13890^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15247^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15245^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15245^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
