<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145386</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stenotrophomonas maltophilia keratitis treated with trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: An 84 year-old woman with persistent epithelial defect and a dense stromal infiltrate post-corneal transplantation. According to the microbiological results, it was due to a Stenotrophomonas maltophilia (S. maltophilia) resistant to all antibiotics except trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (TMP/SMX). Healing was achieved after three weeks of treatment with oral and topical TMP/SMX. Discussion: S. maltophilia is an opportunistic microorganism rarely described in ophthalmology. It is associated with conjunctivitis, keratitis, scleritis, dacryrocystitis, cellulitis, and endophthalmitis with significant morbidity. Treatment is complicated because of its resistances to broad-spectrum antibiotics. TMP/SMX monotherapy can be considered an option of treatment for this type of keratitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lumbreras-Fernández, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Álvarez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pérez, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Mujer de 84 años con defecto epitelial persistente e infiltrado estromal denso tras trasplante corneal. El análisis microbiológico reveló una Stenotrophomonas maltophilia (S. maltophilia), resistente a todos los antibióticos salvo a trimetoprima-sulfametoxazol (TMP/SMX) Se consiguió su resolución tras 3 semanas de tratamiento con TMP/SMX tópico y oral. Discusión: S. maltophilia es un microorganismo oportunista raramente descrito en oftalmología. Se asocia con conjuntivitis, queratitis, escleritis, dacriocistitis, celulitis y endoftalmitis, con importante morbilidad. El tratamiento es complicado por sus múltiples resistencias a antibióticos de amplio espectro. El TMP/SMX en monoterapia puede considerarse como una opción de tratamiento para estas queratitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;90(11): 539-541, nov. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Queratitis por Stenotrophomonas maltophilia tratada con trimetoprima-sulfametoxazol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4926^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27872^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27872^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4926^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27842^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7803^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7803^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7803^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27842^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7803^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
