<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155102</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical status of a cohort of patients with type 1 diabetes diagnosed more than 2 decades before. Results of a specific clinical follow-up program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The clinical course of type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) has changed in recent decades. The aim of our study was to assess the long-term (&gt; 20 years) clinical status of a patient cohort with T1DM under a specific treatment and follow-up program. Patients and methods: A single center, observational, cross-sectional study was conducted of a patient cohort diagnosed with T1DM in the 1986-1994 period at our tertiary university hospital. Clinical characteristics, metabolic parameters, and occurrence of chronic complications and comorbidities after &gt; 20 years of follow-up were collected. All subjects entered our specific program for patients with newly-diagnosed T1D and were followed up using the same clinical protocol. Data are shown as mean (standard deviation) or as number of patients and percentage. The appropriate test was used to compare quantitative and qualitative data. A Pvalue &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. Results: A total of 279 patients were recorded, of whom 153 (53.6% women; mean age 46.6±8.6 years; age at onset 23.3±8.8 years; disease duration, 23.3±2.6 years) continued to attend our diabetes unit at the time of the analysis. Of these patients, 24.8% were administered continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII). Mean HbA1c in the past 5 years and in the last year were7.8±0.9% and 7.7±1.1% respectively (7.3±1.5% in those given CSII). Smoking was reported by 19.6% of patients, while 15.7% had high blood pressure and 37.9% dyslipidemia. Diabetic retinopathy was diagnosed in 20.4%, and 11.3% of the total cohort had nephropathy. Only 1.3% of our patients had a history of CVD. Conclusions: Data collected from a cohort of patients with T1DM for more than 2 decades regularly followed up with a specific program in a tertiary university hospital suggest a remarkably low prevalence of diabetic complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amor, Antonio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vinagre, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conget, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrer, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, Marga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo: El curso clínico de la diabetes tipo 1 (DT1) ha cambiado en las últimas décadas. Nos propusimos describir las características de una población con DT1 de más de 20 años de evolución bajo el mismo programa de seguimiento desde el inicio. Pacientes y método: Estudio observacional de corte transversal en el que incluimos los pacientes del registro de inicios de DT1 entre 1986 y 1994 de nuestra Unidad de Diabetes. Desde 1986 todos siguen el mismo protocolo de seguimiento y tratamiento. Recogimos la presencia de complicaciones micro- y macrovasculares, factores de riesgo cardiovascular, control metabólico y tratamiento. Los datos se obtuvieron de la historia clínica informatizada. La comparación entre variables cuantitativas y cualitativas se realizó con el test apropiado en cada caso. Se consideró estadísticamente significativa una p&lt;0,05. Resultados: De 279 pacientes del registro, 153 continuaban en nuestro centro (edad media±desviación estándar: 46,6±8,6 años) con una duración media de la DT1 de 23,3±2,6 años. De estos, un 53,6% eran mujeres. El 24,8% estaba en tratamiento con infusión subcutánea continua de insulina (ISCI). La media de HbA1c en el último año fue de 7,7±1,1% (7,3±1,5% en el grupo de ISCI) y de 7,8±0,9% en los últimos 5 años. Un 19,6% fumaban, 15,7% tenían hipertensión arterial y 37,9% dislipidemia. Un 20,4% presentaban retinopatía diabética y el 11,3% nefropatía. Únicamente un 1,3% presentaba antecedentes de enfermedad cardiovascular. Conclusiones: Tras más de 2 décadas de evolución de la DT1, consideramos que la prevalencia de complicaciones micro- y macrovasculares en nuestros pacientes con DT1 en un programa específico de seguimiento desde el inicio de la enfermedad es baja o, en algún caso, sustancialmente inferior a la esperada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(7): 339-344, ago.-sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155102</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación clínica de una cohorte de pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 más de 2 décadas después del inicio. Resultados de un programa específico de seguimiento en una unidad de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3948^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
