<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136517</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advances in the efficacy. optimization and safety of treatments for inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In Digestive Disease Week 2012, numerous studies were presented on the treatment, monitoring and safety of drugs in inflammatory bowel diseases. New indications for previously approved treatments were evaluated, mainly in perianal disease and the prevention of postsurgical recurrence. New data were provided on biological markers that could help in the follow-up of patients with inflammatory bowel disease. Several studies were presented on the safety of thiopurine drugs and anti-tumor necrosis factor (TNF) agents during pregnancy. However, much of the meeting was centered on studies determining levels of anti-TNF agents and antibodies against them, evaluating new techniques with greater accuracy in determining levels of these agents and antibodies against them, their correlation with clinical response and their utility in optimizing the treatment of patients with inflammatory bowel disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chaparro, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la Digestive Disease Week 2012 se han presentado numerosos trabajos sobre el tratamiento, la monitorización y la seguridad de los fármacos en la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal. Se han evaluado nuevas indicaciones de los tratamientos previamente aprobados, principalmente en la enfermedad perianal y en la prevención de la recurrencia posquirúrgica. Además se han aportado nuevos datos sobre marcadores biológicos que podrían ayudarnos en el seguimiento de los pacientes con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal. Se han presentado diversos estudios sobre la seguridad de los fármacos tiopurínicos y anti-TNF durante el embarazo. Pero, sin duda, gran parte de la atención se ha centrado en los estudios que determinan los valores de fármacos anti-TNF y anticuerpos contra dichos fármacos, evaluando nuevas técnicas con mayor exactitud diagnóstica, su correlación con la respuesta clínica y su utilidad en la optimización del tratamiento de los pacientes con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;35(supl.1): 57-67, sept. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136517</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Novedades sobre la eficacia. optimización y seguridad de los tratamientos de la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
