<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139126</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish versions of the Simplified Motor Score and the Glasgow Coma Scale in out-of-hospital treatment of head injury in adults: a preliminary study of each scale&#146;s ability to predict adverse events</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To determine the ability of the modified (Spanish) version of the Simplified Motor Score (mSMS) to predict adverse events during hospitalization and to compare its predictive ability to that of the Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) in adults with head injuries treated outside the hospital. Methods. Observational study of retrospective cohorts including all patients over the age of 14 years attended for head injuries occurring within 24 hours of treatment by an advanced life-support unit staffed by nurses between May 1, 2013, and May 1, 2014. The mSMS was a translation of the English original, created through a process of discussions of direct and back translations to arrive at consensus. Out-of-hospital patient records were searched to find GCS and mSMS scores. To predict the ability of each scale to predict brain injuries, neurosurgery, intubation, and/or inhospital death, we calculated the area under the receiving operator characteristic curves (AUCs). Results. Of the total of 115 head-injury patients attended, 64 met the inclusion criteria. The mean (SD) age was 47 (24) years. Twelve (18.8%) patients developed some form of adverse event during hospitalization; 91.6% had brain damage, 58.3% required intubation, 8.3% required surgery, and 41.6% died. The AUC for the GCS was 0.907 (95% CI, 0.81&#150;1.00; P&lt;.001); the AUC for the mSMS was 0.796 (95% CI, 0.64&#150;0.95; P=.001). Conclusions. Although the ability of the mSMS to predict in-hospital adverse outcomes is good, it is inferior to the GCS in adults with head injuries attended outside the hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casajuana, Edgar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayol, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca, Guillem</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la capacidad predictiva de resultados adversos durante la hospitalización de la escala Simplified Motor Score (SMS) adaptada al español (Puntuación Motora Simplificada modificada, PMSm), y compararla con la Escala del Coma de Glasgow (ECG) en los pacientes adultos atendidos por traumatismo craneoencefálico en el ámbito extrahospitalario. Metodología. Estudio observacional de cohortes retrospectivo que incluyó a todo paciente mayor de 14 años atendido por un traumatismo craneoencefálico de menos de 24 horas de evolución en una unidad de soporte vital avanzado con enfermería entre el 1 de mayo de 2013 y el 1 de mayo de 2014. Se realizó una traducción directa-inversa de la SMS por consenso formal obteniendo la PMSm. Se recogieron a partir de las historias clínicas de la atención extrahospitalaria los datos de la ECG desglosada y la PMSm. Se calculó el área bajo la curva (ABC) COR de la PMSm y la ECG para la predicción de lesión cerebral, necesidad de intervención neuroquirúrgica y/o de intubación y mortalidad durante la hospitalización. Resultados. Del total de 115, se incluyeron finalmente 64 pacientes con una edad media de 47 (DE 24) años. Doce pacientes (18,8%) presentaron algún resultado adverso (91,6% lesión cerebral, 58,3% necesidad de intubación, 8,3% necesidad de intervención quirúrgica y 41,6% fallecieron) durante la hospitalización. El ABC COR de la puntuación ECG fue 0,907 (IC 95%: 0,81-1,00; p &lt; 0,001) y de la PMSm fue 0,796 (IC 95%: 0,64-0,95; p = 0,001). Conclusiones. La capacidad predictiva de resultados adversos durante la hospitalización de la PMSm es buena pero inferior a la ECG en los pacientes adultos atendidos por traumatismo craneoencefálico en el ámbito extrahospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(3): 185-188, jun. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139126</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo preliminar entre la Puntuación Motora Simplificada modificada y la Escala de Coma de Glasgow en pacientes adultos atendidos por traumatismo craneoencefálico en el ámbito extrahospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9682^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24697^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55051</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34373^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
