<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74529</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effect of amitriptyline on inhibitory avoidance in mice is dose dependent</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of the present work was to study the dose-effect relationship of the antidepressant amitriptyline on inhibitory avoidance in male and female mice. Subjects received physiological saline or 2.5, 5, 10 or 20 mg/kg of amitriptyline hydrochloride 30 min before the training phase, and were subjected to the test phase 24 h later. Results showed a clear impairing effect of amitriptyline on inhibitory avoidance in both male and female mice, and that the effect is dose-dependent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monleón, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer-Añó, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urquiza, Adoración</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vinader-Caerols, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito del presente trabajo fue estudiar la relación dosis-efecto del antidepresivo amitriptilina sobre la evitación inhibitoria en ratones machos y hembras. Los sujetos recibieron suero salino o 2.5, 5, 10 ó 20 mg/kg de clorhidrato de amitriptilina 30 min antes de la fase de entrenamiento, y fueron sometidos a la fase de test 24 h más tarde. Los resultados mostraron un claro efecto deteriorante de la amitriptilina sobre la evitación inhibitoria tanto en los ratones machos como en las hembras, y que el efecto es dependiente de dosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);21(4): 528-530, 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El efecto de la amitriptilina sobre la evitación inhibitoria en ratones es dependiente de dosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4365</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d652^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d652^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37778^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
