<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112540</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coronary vasospasm in general anaesthesia induction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Coronary artery vasospasm in the induction of general anaesthesia is a rarely reported complication in our environment, owing to its low incidence or due to having disappeared. We present a case of a previously healthy woman, scheduled for shoulder arthroscopy, who in the anaesthetic induction had a ventricular tachycardia, which spontaneously reverted to sinus rhythm with ST elevation on the left side, and which was diagnosed and treated immediately by using angiography. The importance of the case is based on the lack of references found, and on being rarely reported in health patients during the induction of general anaesthesia, and with an immediate diagnosis and resolving using angiography(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pelegrí Grau, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novas Brach, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boada Pie, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig Bitrià, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El vasoespasmo de la arteria coronaria en la inducción de la anestesia general es una complicación poco documentada en nuestro entorno, por su baja incidencia o por pasar desapercibida. Presentamos el caso de una mujer previamente sana, programada para artroscopia de hombro, que en la inducción anestésica presentó taquicardia ventricular, que revirtió espontáneamente a ritmo sinusal con elevación de ST en cara lateral, y que se diagnosticó y trató con una angiografía inmediata. La importancia del caso se basa en la escasa bibliografía encontrada y en ser de los pocos comunicados en pacientes sanos durante la inducción de la anestesia general y, con diagnóstico y resolución angiográfico inmediato(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(4): 233-236, abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112540</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vasoespasmo coronario en la inducción de la anestesia general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3344^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3344^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3344^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
