<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141256</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bacterial endocarditis prophylaxis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bacterial endocarditis (BE) is a disease resulting from the association of morphological alterations of the heart and bacteraemia originating from different sources that at times can be indiscernible (infectious endocarditis). It is classified on the basis of the morphological alteration involved, depending on the clinical manifestations and course of illness, which varies according to the causative microorganism and host conditions (for example, it is characteristic in I.V. drug users). The most common microorganisms involved are: Streptococcus viridans (55%), Staphylococcus aureus (30%), Enterococcus (6%) and HACEK bacteria (corresponding to the initials: Haemophilus, Actinobacillus, Cardiobacterium, Eikenella and Kingella), although on occasions it can also be caused by fungi. The oral microbiological flora plays a very important role in the aetiopathogenesis of BE, given that the condition may be of oral or dental origin. This paper will deal with the prevention of said bacteraemia. Prophylaxis will be undertaken using amoxicillin or clindamycin according to action protocols, with special emphasis placed on oral hygiene in patients with structural defects of the heart (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Carrión, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La endocarditis bacteriana (EB) es una enfermedad producida por la asociación de alteraciones morfológicas del corazón y una bacteriemia proveniente de distintos orígenes, a veces sin descubrir (endocarditis infecciosas). Se clasifica dependiendo de la alteración morfológica, por el cuadro clínico y la evolución, que varía según el microorganismo y las condiciones del huésped (es característica en drogadictos de vía i.v.). Los microorganismos más frecuentes son: el Streptococcus viridans (55%), el Staphylococcus aureus (30%), el Enterococcus (6%) y bacterias de HACEK (corresponde a las iniciales: Haemophilus, Actinobacillus, Cardiobacterium, Eikenella y Kingella), en ocasiones puede estar producido también por hongos. La flora microbiológica oral juega un papel muy importante en la etiopatogenia de la EB, dado que el origen de la bacteriemia puede ser bucodental. La profilaxis de dicha bacteriemia será lo que analizaremos en este tema. La efectuaremos con amoxicilina o clindamicina siguiendo unos protocolos de actuación, además de hacer hincapié en la higiene bucal en pacientes con defectos de la estructura cardiaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);9(supl): 37-51, dic. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Profilaxis de la endocarditis bacteriana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31516</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23201^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
