<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127795</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personality and anxiety sensitivity as a vulnerability factors in panic disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Personality and psychopathology differences were explored among a clinical sample of 52 patients with Panic Disorder (PD), with Agoraphobia (PDA) or without Agoraphobia, and two nonclinical samples, one with 45 participants with high anxiety sensitivity (AS) scores, and 55 with low AS scores. The clinical sample was evaluated according to DSM-IV-TR (APA, 2000) criteria. The participants in nonclinical samples were assigned depending on the «Anxiety sensitivity index» (ASI; Reiss, Peterson, Gursky, &amp; McNally, 1986) scores. The «Brief symptom inventory» (BSI; Derogatis &amp; Melisaratos, 1983) was used to assess general psychopathology and the «NEO personality inventory- revised» (NEO-PI-R; Costa &amp; McCrae, 1992) was used to measure personality, both in the three samples. The results show that the only statistically significant differences between the participants with high AS scores and PD/PDA patients were in the psychopathological scales, phobic anxiety and paranoid ideation, and in the personality facet, social anxiety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Palacios, Azucena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrada, Juan Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osma, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se estudiaron las diferencias psicopatológicas y de personalidad entre una muestra clínica, 52 pacientes con trastorno de pánico (TP) con agorafobia (TPA) o sin agorafobia y dos muestras no clínicas, una con 45 participantes con alta sensibilidad a la ansiedad (SA) y otra con 55 participantes con baja SA. La muestra clínica fue evaluada siguiendo criterios del DSM-IV-TR (APA, 2000). Los participantes fueron asignados a los grupos no clínicos en función de sus puntuaciones en el «Inventario de sensibilidad a la ansiedad» (ASI; Reiss, Peterson, Gursky y McNally, 1986). Los tres grupos fueron evaluados en psicopatología general utilizando el «Inventario breve de síntomas» (BSI; Derogatis y Melisaratos, 1983) y en personalidad con el «Inventario de personalidad NEO revisado» (NEO-PI-R; Costa y McCrae, 1992). Los resultados muestran que únicamente existen diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre las personas con puntuación alta en SA y los pacientes con TP/TPA en las escalas psicopatológicas, ansiedad fóbica e ideación paranoide, así como en la faceta de personalidad ansiedad social (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;22(2): 185-201, mayo-ago. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127795</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Personalidad y sensibilidad a la ansiedad como factores de vulnerabilidad en el trastorno de pánico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d383^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
