<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113963</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of correlation between clinical and biomechanical variables in patients with fibromyalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To perform a biomechanical analysis of balance and gait in patients with fibromyalgia to establish  a correlation with perceived functional status. Material and methods: A cross-sectional study of 42 patients diagnosed with fibromyalgia (40 women and 2 men). Subjects with concomitant conditions affecting balance and gait were excluded. Functional status results measured by the Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire (FIQ) were compared with the biomechanical assessments of balance measured with the NedSVE/IBV application and gait kinetics with the NedAMH/IBV system. Results: Forty-three percent of subjects had abnormalities on the overall assessment of the Romberg eyes closed (REC) test. A significant correlation was found between FIQ and lateral medial stability on the REC test (p=0.020). Gait kinetics assessment of all subjects obtained parameters within the normal range. No correlations were found between variables in the gait kinetics analysis and the FIQ result. Conclusion: Our findings indicate a good correlation of the FIQ with fibromyalgia and postural balance measured with posturography, but not with the results of gait kinetics analysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez Hernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marí i Cerezo, F. X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Germes Esteve, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaman, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giacotti, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Jaén, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar un análisis biomecánico del equilibrio y la marcha en pacientes con fibromialgia para establecer una correlación con el estado funcional percibido. Material y método: Estudio transversal con 42 pacientes diagnosticados de fibromialgia (40 mujeres y 2 hombres). Se excluyeron personas con patologías concomitantes que alterasen la marcha y equilibrio. Se compararon los resultados del estado funcional medido mediante el Cuestionario de Impacto de la Fibromialgia (FIQ), con sus valoraciones biomecánicas del equilibrio medido con la aplicación NedSVE/IBV y cinética de la marcha con el sistema NedAMH/IBV. Resultados: Un 43% de los sujetos presentaba alteración en la valoración global de la prueba de Romberg Ojos Cerrados (ROC). Se encontró una correlación significativa entre el FIQ y la estabilidad medio lateral en la prueba de ROC (p=0,020). La valoración cinética de la marcha de todos los sujetos obtuvo parámetros dentro de la normalidad. No se encontraron correlaciones entre las variables del análisis cinético de la marcha y el resultado de la FIQ. Conclusión: Los hallazgos indican una buena correlación entre la FIQ con fibromialgia y su equilibrio postural medido con posturografía, pero no con los del análisis cinético de la marcha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);24(2): 87-92, abr.-jun. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113963</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de correlación entre variables clínicas y biomecánicas en pacientes con fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
