<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137507</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Integration into the workforce of midwives graduated between 2001 and 2005</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To characterize the integration into the workforce of midwives graduated between 2001 and 2005. Participants and method: A descriptive, observational, cross-sectional study was performed. It included all the midwives who graduated  from 18 Midwifery Teaching Units in 15 Spanish autonomous communities from 2001 to 2005. A questionnaire prepared by the research team and distributed by postal or electronic mail was employed. Results: We received 328 completed questionnaires, 44.14% of those sent out. All the responders had worked as a midwife and 89.3% (293) had found work within less than a month. Thirty-eight (12.2%) had found permanent jobs, while 136 (43.9%) had substitute positions and the remainder had temporary jobs. In all, 84.8% (n=263) were working in a hospital. Seventy-four (24.2%) held more than one job. Eighteen (5.4%) were not working as midwives. The number of midwives who were working in the same  autonomous community in which they had received their training was less.  Than 50% among those who had studied in the communities of Canary Islands, Castilla La Mancha, Catalonia, Galicia and the Basque Country. Conclusions: Midwives are integrated rapidly into the workforce and many work in more than one place, an indication of the shortage of these professionals. Most of the midwives work in hospitals. There are units that train more midwives from outside their community. Consequently, the number of midwives working in these communities is lower than the number who studied midwifery there (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plata, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Mª Angeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avellaned, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seguranyes, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las características de la inserción laboral de las matronas que se graduaron entre los años 2001 y 2005. Personas y método: Estudio observacional, descriptivo y transversal. Se estudiaron todas las matronas que se graduaron en España entre los años 2001 y 2005, en 18 Unidades Docentes de Matronas pertenecientes a 15 Comunidades Autónomas. Se utilizó un cuestionario elaborado por el equipo investigador que se envió por correo postal o electrónico. Resultados: Se recibieron 328 cuestionarios cumplimentados, un 44,14% de los enviados. Todas las matronas que respondieron habían trabajado como matrona, y el 89,3% (293) consiguió trabajo en menos de un mes. Tenía un contrato fijo el 12,2% (38), lo tenía interino el 43,9% (136), y el resto tenía un contrato eventual. El 84,8 (263) desarrollaba su actividad asistencial en el hospital. Un 24,2% (74) estaba en situación de pluriempleo. El 5,4% (18) no trabajaban como matronas. El número de matronas que estaba trabajando en la misma CC.AA. que se había formado era inferior al 50% de las matronas formadas en Canarias, Castilla-La Mancha, Cataluña, Galicia y País Vasco. Conclusiones: La inserción laboral se realiza rápidamente y la situación de pluriempleo es alta, lo que indica escasez de profesionales. La mayoría de las matronas desarrolla su actividad asistencial en hospitales. Hay unidades que forman a más matronas procedentes de otra comunidad que de la propia, como consecuencia de esto son menos las matronas que trabajan en estas comunidades que las que se formaron en ellas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;8(2): 5-12, abr.-jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inserción laboral de las matronas graduadas entre los años 2001 y 2005</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17570^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50276</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
