<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048832</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mindfulness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mindfulness could be understood as consciousness encompasses both attention and awareness; it is paying reflexive attentionto the present moment. It is an intentional way, with a purpose but no judgmentally and none interfering the sensationsand perceptions of experience moment to moment. As a therapeutic procedure find the acceptation in his owner manner of theemotional experiences and any other nonverbal processes, so these experiences must be living it not to avoid o to control. Thecontrol of uncontrolled experiences, automatic control processes, required his owner experimentation and the natural exposureto this success with no interferences. The mindfullnes is well know in USA in relationship with the oriental values of meditation,but referred to some aspects knew in psychology: exposure, self-regulation in biofeedback training or in the use of hypnosiswhere there are a way to leave the sensorial and perceptive experiences as their own. The principal utility of mindfulness is itsinterest to claim against control, and refuse of emotional negative material. The wide psychological discourse fighting againststress, anxiety, etc., required the contrast offered by midnfulness, without the natural experimentation of these emotions the clinicalproblems could be perpetuated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vallejo Pareja, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mindfulness puede entenderse como atención y conciencia plena, como presencia atenta y reflexiva a lo que sucede en elmomento actual. Pretende que la persona se centre en el momento presente de un modo activo, procurando no interferir ni valorarlo que se siente o se percibe en cada momento. Como procedimiento terapéutico busca, ante todo, que los aspectosemocionales y cualesquiera otros procesos de carácter no verbal, sean aceptados y vividos en su propia condición, sin ser evitadoso intentar controlarlos. El control sobre sucesos incontrolables, sujetos a procesamiento automático, requiere de la meraexperimentación y exposición natural con la menor interferencia posible. Aunque el mindfulness ha adquirido una cierta notoriedad,sobre todo en USA, de mano de los valores orientales, refiere a algunos aspectos ya conocidos en psicología: la exposicióny la autorregulación basadas en las técnicas de biofeedback o en el uso de la hipnosis, donde hay un dejar que losfenómenos perceptivos y sensoriales se muestren como ellos son. Su principal utilidad, más allá de las técnicas concretas queofrezca, tal vez sea el contrastar con una psicología que propugna el control, el bienestar, la eliminación del estrés, la ansiedad,etc., mediante procedimientos que, a falta de esa experimentación natural, pueden contribuir a perpetuarlos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;27(2): 92-99, jul. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048832</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mindfulness</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32693^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1148</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
