<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161829</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Familial exudative vitreoretinopathy: A report of an asymptomatic case with autosomal dominant inheritance detected using FZD4 molecular analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To report a familial case of Familial Exudative Vitreoretinopathy (FEVR) with an autosomal dominant inheritance pattern identified with the molecular analysis of FZD4. Case report: The proband is a 13 year-old boy who consulted for low vision. Fundus examination revealed a peripheral avascular zone and macular dragging, consistent with FEVR. Molecular analysis demonstrated a mutation of FZD4 in DNA from both the patient and his asymptomatic mother. Discussion: This familial case was identified with the molecular analysis of FZD4 and shows the importance to explore first degree relatives in a sporadic FEVR case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sepúlveda Vázquez, HE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zenteno, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montecinos Contreras, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelcastre Luna, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Mendoza, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Reportar un caso familiar de vitreorretinopatía exudativa familiar (VREF), con herencia autosómica dominante, identificado por el análisis molecular de FZD4. Caso clínico: El caso índice tiene 13 años y consulta por baja visión. Al examen de fondo de ojo se demuestran zonas periféricas avasculares y tracción macular, diagnosticándose VREF. El análisis molecular de FZD4 demuestra una mutación patológica en el paciente y en su madre asintomática. Discusión: El presente caso familiar fue identificado mediante el análisis molecular de FZD4, y demuestra la importancia de explorar a los familiares de primer grado en los casos esporádicos de VREF (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(4): 189-192, abr. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vitreorretinopatía exudativa familiar, reporte de un caso asintomático con herencia autosómica dominante, detectado mediante análisis molecular de FZD4</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31976^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23247^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53531^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24635^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12587^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
