<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050572</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a program to improve the quality of nursing records in an obstetrics and gynecology unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate the effect of a program to improve nursing documentation on the quality and quantity of the nursing records in the Obstetrics and Gynecology Units of the Hospital Clínico San Carlos (Madrid, Spain). Method. A quasi-experimental, pretest-posttest study was performed. The medical records of patients in the Obstetrics and Gynecology Unit were analyzed. The intervention was developed from January to May, 2005. The medical records of discharged patients were evaluated from January to December 2004 and from January to May 2005. In addition, the medical records of 50% of the patients admitted in December 2004 and June 2005 were randomly selected and audited. The variables analyzed were: 1) the number of records with a nursing discharge report, nursing care plan, and evaluation of the aims set, and 2) the number of nursing care plans and the coherence of these plans. Results. Statistically significant differences were found in obstetrics (OBS) and gynecology (GYN) in the following variables: "discharge with evaluation of the aims set": OBS, 2004 (20.6%), 2005 (57.6%), p &lt; 0.001; GYN, 2004 (14.4%) and 2005 (54.6%), p &lt; 0.001; "patients discharged with nursing care plans": OBS, 2004 (95.5%), 2005 (98.8%), p &lt; 0.001; GYN, 2004 (84.2%), 2005 (88.8%), p &lt; 0.001; "coherence of the nursing care plan": OBS, December 2004 (15.4%), June 2005 (93.7%), p &lt; 0.001; GYN, December 2004 (28,6%), June 2005 (73%) p &lt; 0.02. Conclusions. The intervention was effective. Variables indicating quality (discharge with evaluation of the aims set and coherence of the nursing care plan) were significantly increased. The number of patients discharged with a nursing care plan also increased</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olmo-Núñez, Sonia del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celis-Portillo, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Sánchez, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo-Pablos, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejías-Delgado, M. Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamorro-Veneros, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón-García, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lanza-Barrena, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Valorar la efectividad de un programa de mejora acerca de la calidad y cantidad de los registros de enfermería de las unidades de ginecología y obstetricia del Hospital Clínico San Carlos. Método. Se realizó un estudio cuasi experimental pretest-postest. La población de estudio fueron las historias clínicas de las pacientes de la unidad de ginecología (GINE) y obstetricia (OBS). El programa de mejora se desarrolló de enero a mayo de 2005. Las historias de las pacientes dadas de alta se evaluaron de enero a diciembre de 2004 y de enero a mayo de 2005; y además, de forma aleatoria se auditaron el 50% de las historias de las pacientes ingresadas en diciembre de 2004 y en junio de 2005. Las variables analizadas fueron: 1) el número de historias con informes de enfermería al alta, con planes de cuidados (PC) y con objetivos evaluados; 2) el número de PC y la concordancia de éste. Resultados. Hubo diferencias significativas en OBS y en GINE en las siguientes variables: "altas con objetivos evaluados" en OBS un 20,6% en 2004 y un 57,6% en 2005, p &lt; 0,001; en GINE un 14,4 y un 54,6% en 2004 y 2005, respectivamente, p &lt; 0,001. En "altas con PC" en la unidad de OBS un 95,5% en 2004 y en 2005 un 98,8%, p &lt; 0,001; en GINE un 84,2 y un 88,8% en los años 2004 y 2005, respectivamente, p &lt; 0,001. En "grado de concordancia del PC" en OBS un 15,4% en diciembre de 2004, un 93,7% en junio de 2005, p &lt; 0,001; GINE un 28,6% en diciembre de 2004 y un 73% en junio de 2005, p &lt; 0,02. Conclusiones. El programa de mejora fue efectivo. Se incrementaron de forma significativa variables indicadoras de calidad, evaluación de objetivos y concordancia en los PC. Asimismo, hubo un incremento en el número de pacientes de alta con PC</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(6): 300-305, nov. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de un programa de mejora para la calidad de los registros enfermeros en ginecología y obstetricia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9917^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29040^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17116^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28202^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
