<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149673</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors associated with intra-hospital mortality in patients requiring non-invasive mechanical ventilation: A reallife study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to analyze prognostic demographic, clinical and patients requiring noninvasive ventilation (NIV) during admission ward and identify variables associated with increased hospital mortality. Methods: prospective observational study of hospitalized patients requiring treatment with NIV by the Service of Pneumology. Results: 222 patients were included, 55% male, mean age 71.8 +/- 15.7 years. PH, pO2 and pCO2 NIV start was 7,28 +/- 0,09, 70,6 +/- 19,9 mmHg (mean +/- standard deviation). The average score was 13.29 Glasgow scale and the Charlson scale of 3.0. Diagnostics presented to establish NIV, in order of frequency, were: congestive heart failure (52%), exacerbation of COPD (32%), obesity hypoventilation syndrome (OHS) (22%), pneumonia (13%), pneumonia in immunosuppressed (12%) and use of sedatives (10%). Patients could have one or more than one diagnosis. 69 patients died, with hospital mortality of 31%. The mean hospital stay was 9.16 days. Those variables associated with increased hospital mortality were (adjusted odds ratio [95%]) the presence of SOH (0.20 [0.07 to 0.51]), pneumonia (1.99 [1.01 to 4,00]), pneumonia in immunocompromised patients (3.90 [1.69 to 8.94] (p = 0.001), neoplasia (2.78 [1.28 to 6.01] and the start of NIV in patients with a Glasgow score&lt; 11 (2.60 [1.75 to 3.83]). Conclusions: Our work makes evident the usefulness of NIV in a ward for patients not candidates for ICU or with non-intubation order. As clinical trials, studies in real life can generate hypotheses and planning areas for improvement, especially in patients who are not subsidiary to clinical trials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrot Cortés, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jara Palomares, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Barrera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillo Guerrero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Oro Gómez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Eraso, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: analizar características demográficas, clínicas y pronósticas, en pacientes que requirieron de ventilación mecánica no invasiva (VMNI) durante su ingreso en planta de hospitalización e identificar variables asociadas a mayor mortalidad intrahospitalaria. Material y métodos: estudio observacional prospectivo sobre pacientes hospitalizados que requirieron tratamiento con VMNI por parte del servicio de Neumología. Resultados: se incluyeron 222 pacientes, 55% varones, con edad media de 71,8 +/- 15,7 años. El pH y la PCO2 de inicio de VMNI fue de 7,28 +/- 0,09, 70,6 +/- 19,9 mmHg, respectivamente (media +/- desviación estándar). La puntuación media de la escala de Glasgow fue 13,29 y de la escala de Charlson 3,0. Los diagnósticos presentes al inicio de la VMNI, por orden de frecuencia, fueron: insuficiencia cardíaca congestiva (52%), agudización de EPOC (32%), síndrome obesidad hipoventilación (SOH) (22%), neumonía (13%), neumonía en inmunodeprimido (12%) y toma de sedantes (10%). Los pacientes podían tener uno o más de un diagnóstico. Fallecieron 69 pacientes, siendo la mortalidad intrahospitalaria del 31%. La estancia media hospitalaria fue de 9,16 días. Aquellas variables asociadas a una mayor mortalidad intrahospitalaria fueron (odds ratio ajustada [IC del 95%]) la presencia de SOH (0,20 [0,07 - 0,51]), neumonía (1,99 [1,01 - 4,00]), neumonía en paciente inmunodeprimido (3,90 [1,69 - 8,94] (p = 0,001), neoplasia (2,78 [1,28 - 6,01] y el inicio de VMNI en pacientes con un Glasgow &lt; 11 (2,60 [1,75 - 3,83]). Conclusiones: nuestro trabajo permite evidenciar la utilidad de la VMNI en una planta de hospitalización en pacientes no candidatos a UCI o con orden de no intubación. Al igual que los ensayos clínicos, los estudios en vida real permiten generar hipótesis y planificar áreas de mejora, sobre todo en aquellos pacientes que no son subsidiarios de participar en ensayos clínicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;28(1): 16-25, ene. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149673</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo asociados a mortalidad intrahospitalaria en pacientes que requieren ventilación mecánica no invasiva. Estudio en vida real</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53505^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
