<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106707</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Costs and associated factors with optimal and suboptimal responses to the treatment of major depressive disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the compliance, persistence and costs of the treatment of major depressive disorder (MDD) in the setting of Primary Care, placing emphasis on the different aspects of those patients with an initial suboptimal response to antidepressant treatment. Design: A retrospective observational study using the population registers of Badalona Healthcare Services. The inclusion criteria consisted of; age &amp;#8805;18 years, initial episode during 2008-2009, and to be on antidepressant treatment for at least 8 weeks after the first prescription. The follow-up was 12 months. Two study groups were formed, patients with suboptimal response, and remission. Main measurements: Sociodemographic data, compliance and adherence to treatment, health costs (direct and indirect).ResultsA total of 2,260 subjects were analysed (mean age 58.8 years, 74% women). Just under half (42.7%, 95% CI; 40.0-46.4%) had a suboptimal response to the treatment. These patients had a higher mean age, a higher proportion of women, and pensioners, as well as higher comorbidity, compared to the remission group. They also had poorer compliance percentages (65.1% vs. 67.7%) and treatment persistence at 12 months (31.8% vs. 53.2%), respectively, P&lt;0.001. The annual health costs were, 826.1&#128; for patients with a suboptimal response vs. 451.2&#128; in patients in remission; loss of productivity 1,842.0&#128; vs. 991.4&#128;, respectively; P&lt;0.001. The factors associated to a suboptimal response were; lack of compliance (OR=1.7), years with the disorder (OR=1.2), age (OR=1.1) and presence of comorbidity (OR=1.1). Conclusions: The patients with an initial suboptimal response to antidepressant treatment had a higher comorbidity, lower therapeutic compliance, and incurred higher total costs, particularly in losses in work productivity(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mauriño, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sicras-Mainar, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanca-Tamayo, Milagrosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Artieda, Ruth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el cumplimiento, la persistencia y los costes del tratamiento del trastorno depresivo mayor (TDM) en el ámbito de atención primaria, haciendo énfasis en aspectos diferenciales de aquellos pacientes con una respuesta subóptima al tratamiento antidepresivo (AD) inicial. Diseño: Diseño observacional retrospectivo realizado a partir de registros poblacionales de Badalona Serveis Assistencials. Criterios de inclusión: edad &amp;#8805; 18 años, inicio del episodio durante 2008-2009 y estar en tratamiento AD al menos 8 semanas tras la primera prescripción. El seguimiento fue de 12 meses. Dos grupos de estudio: pacientes con respuesta subóptima/remisión. Principales mediciones: sociodemográficas, cumplimiento y persistencia del tratamiento, costes sanitarios (directos e indirectos). Resultados: Se analizaron 2.260 sujetos (media edad: 58,8 años, 74% mujeres). El 42,7% (IC95%: 40,0-46,4%) presentó respuesta subóptima al tratamiento. Estos pacientes tenían una media de edad mayor, mayor proporción de mujeres y de pensionistas respecto al grupo de remisión, así como de comorbilidad. También peores porcentajes de cumplimiento (65,1 frente a 67,7%) y persistencia del tratamiento a los 12 meses (31,8 frente a 53,2%), respectivamente; p&lt;0,001. Los costes sanitarios/anuales fueron de 826,1 &#128; para pacientes con respuesta subóptima frente a 451,2 &#128; en los pacientes en remisión; pérdidas de productividad de 1.842,0 frente a 991,4 &#128;, respectivamente; p&lt;0,001. Los factores asociados a la respuesta subóptima fueron: falta de cumplimiento (OR=1,7), años de enfermedad (OR=1,2), edad (OR=1,1) y presencia de comorbilidad (OR=1,1). Conclusiones: Los pacientes con respuesta subóptima al tratamiento AD inicial presentaron mayor comorbilidad, menor cumplimiento terapéutico y ocasionaron mayores costes totales, especialmente en pérdidas de productividad laboral(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;44(11): 667-675, nov. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106707</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Costes y factores asociados a las respuestas óptima y subóptima al tratamiento del trastorno depresivo mayor en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3376^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
