<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151734</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Circulating PCSK9 in patients with type 2 diabetes and related metabolic disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: PCSK9 is a pivotal molecule in the regulation of lipid metabolism. Previous studies have suggested that PCSK9 expression and its function in LDL receptor regulation could be altered in the context of diabetes. The aim was to assess PCSK9 plasma levels in patients with type 2 diabetes (T2DM) and other related metabolic disorders as well as its relation to the metabolomic profile generated by nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) and glucose homeostasis. Methods: There were recruited a total of 457 patients suffering from T2DM and other metabolic disorders (metabolic syndrome (MetS), obesity and atherogenic dyslipidaemia (AD) and other disorders). Anamnesis, anthropometry and physical examinations were conducted, and vascular and abdominal adiposity imaging were carried out. Biochemical studies were performed to determine PCSK9 plasma levels 6 weeks after lipid lowering drug wash-out in treated patients. A complete metabolomic lipid profile was also generated by NMR. The rs505151 and rs11591147 genetic variants of PCSK9 gene were identified in patients. Results: The results showed that PCSK9 levels are increased in patients with T2DM and MetS (14% and 13%;p &lt; 0.005, respectively). Circulating PCSK9 levels were correlated with an atherogenic lipid profile and with insulin resistance parameters. PCSK9 levels were also positively associated with AD, as defined by lipoprotein particle number and size. The rs11591147 genetic variant resulted in lower levels of circulating PCSK9 and LDL cholesterol (LDL-C). Conclusions: PCSK9 plasma levels are increased in T2DM and MetS patients and are associated with LDL-C and other parameters of AD and glucose metabolism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Masana, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferré, Raimón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guaita, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabré, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarretxe, Daiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plana, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amigó, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mallol, Roger</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girona, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: PCSK9 es una molécula clave en la regulación del metabolismo lipídico. Estudios previos sugieren que la expresión y función de PCSK9 entorno a la regulación del receptor LDL puede alterarse en la diabetes. El objetivo del estudio fue determinar los niveles circulantes de PCSK9 en pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 (DM) y otras enfermedades metabólicas y su relación con las lipoproteínas estudiadas mediante resonancia magnética nuclear (RMN) y la homeostasis de la glucosa. Métodos: Se estudiaron un total de 457 pacientes, afectos de DM y otras alteraciones metabólicas (síndrome metabólico [SMet], obesidad y dislipidemia aterogénica [DA] y otros). Se realizó anamnesis, antropometría, exploración física y estudio vascular de carótidas y adiposidad abdominal. Se realizó bioquímica incluyendo PCSK9 circulante (tras 6 semanas de lavado en pacientes con hipolipemiantes). Se estudió mediante RMN el perfil de lipoproteínas. Se determinaron las variantes genéticas rs505151 y rs11591147 del gen PCSK9. Resultados: Los niveles circulantes de PCSK9 están aumentados en pacientes con DM y SMet (14 y 13%; p&lt;0.005, respectivamente). Los niveles circulantes de PCSK9 se correlacionaron de forma positiva con el perfil lipídico aterogénico y parámetros de resistencia insulínica. Los niveles circulantes de PCSK9 también se asociaron positivamente a DA, definida mediante el número y el tamaño de lipoproteínas analizado mediante RMN. Los portadores de la variante genética rs11591147 mostraron niveles inferiores de PCSK9 plasmática y cLDL. Conclusiones: Los niveles circulantes de PCSK9 están aumentados en pacientes con DM y SMet junto con parámetros de DA y metabolismo de la glucosa, más allá del cLDL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);28(2): 71-78, mar.-abr. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151734</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentraciones circulantes de PCSK9 en población con diabetes tipo 2 y alteraciones metabólicas asociadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53360^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2380</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
