<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92028</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience with ketogenic diet as treatment for refractory epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Epilepsy is a disease where most patients have a good control with pharmacological antiepileptic treatment. Nevertheless, 25% of the patients have a refractory epilepsy to usual antiepileptic drugs. Ketogenic diet is one of the treatment options for this type of epilepsy. In spite of the increased popularity of it as an antiepileptic treatment, it does not exist an international consensus of its indications and management. Aim. To evaluate the response, tolerance and adverse effects of the patients with refractory epilepsy at our hospital during the last 20 years. Patients and methods. We reviewed the data of 30 patients with ketogenic diet and the follow-up at the Neurology and Nutrition Services in our Hospital. Results. Ten patients (35.7%) had a positive response with reduction of their seizures for more than six months; five of them had a 50-75% decrease in seizures and five of them had more than 75% of seizure reduction. The most common short term adverse effects were diarrhea, vomiting and hypoglicemia whereas long term adverse effects were constipation and weight gain. Conclusions. We recommend to use ketogenic diet as treatment in refractory epilepsy since there is a positive response in  seizure control in some cases. The adverse effects seen could be prevented or treated without complications. It is a preferabletreatment option before using other aggressive therapeutical measures or when surgery is not feasible (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catalán, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campistol, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meavilla,  S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Camacho, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La epilepsia es una enfermedad neurológica que se controla con fármacos antiepilépticos en la mayoría de casos. Sin embargo, aproximadamente un 25% de epilepsias son refractarias al tratamiento farmacológico. La dieta cetogénica es una de las opciones terapéuticas para este tipo de epilepsia. A pesar del aumento en los últimos años de la popularidad de ésta como tratamiento anticonvulsivo, no se ha establecido un consenso internacional para sus indicaciones y manejo. Objetivo. Evaluar la respuesta, tolerancia y efectos secundarios en los pacientes con epilepsias refractarias que han recibido dieta cetogénica en nuestra institución en un período de 20 años. Pacientes y métodos. Se revisaron las historias clínicas de 30 pacientes que utilizaron dieta cetogénica como coadyuvante al tratamiento de epilepsia refractaria seguidos en nuestro centro. Se obtuvo información completa para el estudio en 27 casos. Resultados. Diez pacientes (35,7%) presentaron una respuesta positiva en la reducción del número de crisis por más de seis meses; cinco de ellos con una disminución del 50-75% de las crisis y cinco de más del 75%. Los efectos adversos más frecuentes a corto plazo fueron diarrea, vómitos e hipoglucemias, y a largo plazo, estreñimiento y aumento de peso. Conclusiones. Existe una respuesta positiva con la dieta cetogénica en una tercera parte de nuestros pacientes con epilepsia refractaria. La tolerancia es aceptable y los efectos adversos existentes pueden prevenirse o corregirse. Puede considerarse una opción terapéutica frente a epilepsias refractarias antes de iniciar otras medidas más agresivas o cuando no es factible la opción quirúrgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;53(9): 524-530, nov. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia con la dieta cetogénica como tratamiento en la epilepsia refractaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53233^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30333^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
