<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160675</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">False trauma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The theoretical and clinical interest of the concept of traumatism is undeniable. However, it is important to define the concept and avoid incorrect generalizations. I believe that there is a universal fantasy that manifests itself as a need to believe in traumas, and that this tendency prompts diagnostic and conceptual mistakes that hinder efforts at prevention and have negative consequences for the theory and practice of psychotherapy and psychoanalysis. We present our understanding of the origin and nature of this underlying fantasy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manzano, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El interés teórico y clínico de la noción de trauma es innegable. Sin embargo, es importante precisar el concepto y evitar generalizaciones abusivas. En mi opinión, la existencia de una fantasía universal que se manifiesta como una necesidad de creer en traumas facilita errores diagnósticos o conceptuales, con repercusiones para la prevención y la teoría y práctica en psicoterapia y psicoanálisis. Presentamos nuestra comprensión del origen y de la naturaleza de esta fantasía subyacente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(28): 41-43, nov. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160675</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El falso trauma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3395</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52949^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14559</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33540</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
