<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91751</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Empathy and tonic dialogue: the seminal work of Julian Ajuriaguerra</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper summarises recent attempts to find neuronal bases to concepts such as empathy and intersubjectivity. Empathy intervenes as an &#147;intersubjective dialogue&#148; between the mother and her child, the patient and the therapist, and in all human relations. This intersubjective empathic dialogue, already described by Julián Ajuriaguerra in the 1950´s  as &#147;tonic dialogue&#148; has found an attractive physiological base in the recent findings on &#147;mirror neurons&#148; although it still cannot be totally extrapolated to human beings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guimón, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo resume los intentos realizados recientemente para encontrar una base neurofisiológica a conceptos tales como empatía e intersubjetividad. La empatía interviene como un &#147;diálogo intersubjetivo&#148; entre la madre y su niño, el psicoterapeuta y el paciente y en las interrelaciones humanas en general. Ese diálogo intersubjetivo, que había ya sido descrito por Julián Ajurriaguerra a partir de 1950 ha encontrado en los recientes hallazgos sobre las &#147;neuronas espejo&#148; una base fisiológica atractiva, aunque todavía no es totalmente extrapolable a los seres humanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(15): 43-52, abr. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91751</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Empatía y diálogo tónico: el trabajo precursor de Julián Ajuriaguerra</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9672^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9667^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
