<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163063</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Deception detection; state of the art and future prospects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Deception detection has been a longstanding concern throughout human history. It has also interested scientists, who have explored psychological and behavioral differences between liars and truth tellers, as well as ways to improve detection accuracy. Method: In recent years, substantial advances have been made in the field. Some of these advances are briefly reviewed in the current article. Results: A description is provided of (a) research and contemporary theories on how people (try to) detect deception; (b) recent advances on strategic interviewing to detect deception; (c) the integrative findings of recent meta-analyses on systematic verbal lie detection approaches; and (d) several important aspects concerning psychophysiological detection of deception. Also, some emerging trends and research needs for the future are outlined at the end of the article. Conclusions: Deception detection research is a lively and dynamic area of applied psychology that has experienced substantial developments in recent times. Much (though not all) of these research efforts have focused on developing empirically-based lie-detection procedures to be used by practitioners (e.g., the police) in applied settings. A number of new topics are just starting to be examined. These novel research avenues will surely yield interesting new findings in the future (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Masip, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la detección de mentiras ha interesado a la humanidad a lo largo de la historia. También a los científicos, quienes han explorado diferencias psicológicas y conductuales al mentir vs. decir la verdad, así como modos de aumentar la precisión de la detección. Método: recientemente se han hecho avances sustanciales en esta área. En el presente artículo se revisan algunos de ellos. Resultados: se describen (a) las investigaciones y teorías contemporáneas sobre cómo la gente (intenta) detecta(r) mentiras; (b) los avances en procedimientos estratégicos de entrevista para detectar mentiras; (c) los hallazgos de meta-análisis recientes sobre aproximaciones sistemáticas para la detección verbal del engaño; y (d) algunos aspectos importantes de la detección psicofisiológica de la mentira. Al final del artículo se esbozan algunas tendencias emergentes y necesidades de investigación de cara al futuro. Conclusiones: el área de investigación de la detección de mentiras ha experimentado grandes desarrollos en tiempos recientes. A menudo (aunque no siempre) se ha centrado en desarrollar procedimientos de detección de mentiras de base empírica para su utilización en contextos aplicados (p. ej., por la policía). Algunas vías de indagación novedosas están empezando a explorar temas nuevos y, seguramente, darán lugar a futuros hallazgos nuevos e interesantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);29(2): 149-159, mayo 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Detección de mentiras: estado de la cuestión y perspectivas de futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8190^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
