<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-25677</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Iatrogenic retinal breaks during vitrectomy: retrospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To establish the incidence and characteristics of iatrogenic retinal breaks occurring during vitrectomy and to propose a protocol for their management. Methods: Retrospective study of 195 consecutive vitrectomies performed in 2001. Minimum follow up was 3 months for all cases. Results: 13 patients with iatrogenic retinal breaks (6.6%) have been detected. In 8 cases the breaks affected the peripheral retina, in 4 cases they were located in the posterior pole and there was one retinal dialysis. In 4 cases there were more than one retinal break. 9 patients (70%) were vitrectomized for diabetic retinal complications. In 12 cases, the breaks were detected during surgery and treated with endolaser and/or cryoretinopexy (3 cases located inferiorly). Nevertheless 7 cases (54%) developed a retinal detachment, 2 of which could be reattached. Conclusions: Among iatrogenic retinal breaks produced during vitrectomy, the peripheral ones are slightly more frequent than the breaks in the posterior pole. Iatrogenic breaks occur more frequently in diabetic patients, having a bad prognosis and often developing a retinal detachment despite endolaser or cryoretinopexy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Audiovisual y Marketing, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Establecer la incidencia y las características de las roturas retinianas iatrogénicas que se han producido en vitrectomías y proponer un protocolo de actuación. Métodos: Se han revisado de forma retrospectiva 195 vitrectomías consecutivas realizadas en 2001. El seguimiento mínimo de todos los casos ha sido de 3 meses. Resultados: Se han detectado roturas retinianas en 13 pacientes (6,6 por ciento). El tipo más frecuente han sido las roturas periféricas con 8 casos. Hubo 4 casos de roturas posteriores y una diálisis retiniana. En 4 casos se produjo más de una rotura. En 9 casos (70 por ciento) la vitrectomía se indicó por lesiones derivadas de la diabetes mellitus. La mayoría (12) fueron detectadas durante la intervención y todas tratadas con endoláser y/o frío (3 casos de localización inferior). En el postoperatorio, 7 casos (54 por ciento) desarrollaron un desprendimiento de retina de los que 2 pudieron ser reaplicados. Conclusiones: De las roturas retinianas iatrogénicas producidas por la vitrectomía, los desgarros periféricos son un poco más frecuentes que los producidos en polo posterior. Son más frecuentes en diabéticos y tienen mal pronóstico ya que evolucionan con frecuencia a un desprendimiento de retina a pesar del tratamiento con endoláser o frío  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;78(9): 487-492, sept. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Roturas retinianas iatrogénicas en las vitrectomías: estudio retrospectivo</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Pastor Jimeno, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente Salinero M. A. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coco Martín, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rola, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baílez Fidalgo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de la Rúa Franch, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-25677</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12794</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
