<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154705</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of websites on soponsorship: PLS-Pos segmentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sponsorship is among the unconventional marketing techniques that attract the most investment in the sports field. Along with webs, sponsorship is one the main sources of income for sports entities and organizations. Following Gwinner&#146;s theory (1997), this study applies a predictionoriented unobserved segmentation (PLS-POS) with the aim of exploring the impact of websites on the image transfer process. We gathered 225 surveys by displaying a banner in a tennis international event. The variable &#145;attitude towards sport&#146; is the best one for segmenting the sample according to the results of the PLS-POS method and the CHAID decision tree technique. The study introduces two significant developments: on one hand, it analyzes the impact of websites on the effect of sponsorship, while on the other hand it applies an unprecedented methodology to the study of sponsorship (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Dos Santos, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez Pomar, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Hervás, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calabuig Moreno, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El patrocinio es una de las técnicas de marketing no convencionales que más inversión atrae en el área deportiva. Junto con el sitio web, es una de las principales fuentes de ingresos de las entidades y organizaciones deportivas. Este estudio aplica una segmentación no observada orientada a la predicción (PLS-POS) con el objetivo de examinar el efecto del sitio web sobre el proceso de transmisión de imagen según la teoría propuesta por Gwinner (1997). Obtuvimos 225 encuestas insertando un cuestionario creado ad hoc en un banner de un evento internacional de tenis. La variable actitud hacia el deporte es la mejor variable para segmentar la muestra según los resultados del PLS-POS y la técnica de árbol de decisión CHAID. El estudio aporta dos importantes novedades, por un lado examina la influencia del sitio web sobre el efecto del patrocinio, y por otro, aplica una metodología inédita en el estudio del patrocinio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(supl.1): 55-58, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154705</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la website sobre el patrocinio: Segmentación PLS-POS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
