<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83234</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy and tolerability of levodropropizine in the treatment of non productive cough</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Various clinical trials have evaluated the antitussive efficacy and tolerability of levodropropizine (a dropropizine enantiomer)versus the most prescribed/marketed antitussive agents: dextromethorphan, dihydrocodeine and cloperastine. These studies were carried out with patients complaining of non-productive cough due to various a etiologies and using, in all cases, the double-blind method. The results confirm that the antitussive properties of levodropropizine are at least equivalent to those of the reference drugs and, in some cases, superior. As for tolerability, clinical trials have shown that its peripheral mechanism of action gives levodropropizine a substantial advantage over other drugs. The incidence of adverse reactions is significantly lower in treatments with levodropropizine than in treatments with the other antitussives, whose mechanism of action directly affects the central nervous system. In summary, levodropropizine has been shown to have the same or greater clinical efficacy than its competitors and better tolerability, leading international experts to recommend the use of levodropropizine for the symptomatic relief of coughing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villar del Fresno, Á. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Distintos estudios clínicos han evaluado la eficacia antitusígena y la tolerabilidad de la levodropropizina (enantiómero de la dropropizina) frente a los antitusivos más prescritos/comercializados: dextrometorfano, dihidrocodeína y cloperastina. Estos estudios se realizaron en pacientes aquejados de tos improductiva de distintas etiologías y utilizando, en todos los casos, el método doble ciego. Los resultados confirman que las propiedades antitusígenas de la levodropropizina son, al menos, equiparables a las de los fármacos de referencia y, en algún caso, superiores. En el apartado de la tolerabilidad, las pruebas clínicas demuestran que su mecanismo de acción periférico confiere a la levodropropizina una sustancial ventaja sobre el resto de fármacos. La incidencia de los efectos adversos es significativamente menor en los tratamientos con levodropropizina que en las terapias con los demás antitusivos, cuyo mecanismo actúa directamente sobre el sistema nervioso central. En síntesis, la levodropropizina ha demostrado tener una eficacia clínica igual o superior a la de sus competidores y una mejor tolerabilidad, lo que ha llevado a los expertos internacionales a recomendar su uso para el alivio sintomático de la tos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;68(9): 462-462[1-5], oct. 2010. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83234</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y tolerabilidad de la levodropropizina en el tratamiento de la tos no productiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1000^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3386^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3936^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2020^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
