<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126292</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of a subchronical exposure to a modified clay and its migration extract in the spleen of Wistar rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The technological advantages of the incorporation of modified clays into polymers for food packaging are well known. However, there are still many uncertainties about the safety of these materials. The Technological Institute of Packaging, Transport and Logistic has developed Clay1, a modified clay with a quaternary ammonium salt. This organoclay is incorporated into the polymer (polylactic acid), giving a nanocomposite material and reinforcing the bulk material. The aim of this study is to evaluate the activity of several oxidative stress biomarkers in the spleen of rats exposed for 90 days to Clay1 (40 mg/kg/day) and its migration extract obtained from the resultant nanocomposite material. The parameters evaluated were lipid peroxidation and superoxide dismutase and catalase activities. Moreover, the characteristic metallic components of the organoclay (Al, Ca, Fe, Mg, Si) were also analyzed to test the possible accumulation. In this study, three groups of Wistar rats (n=10) were used: control (standard food + water), Clay1 (food with Clay1+water) and Clay1 extract (standard food+ Clay1 extract as water). After the exposure the spleen was removed. In general, no significant differences were observed in any of the parameters evaluated compared to the control group, therefore Clay1 showed a good toxicologic profile regarding the biomarkers assayed for its use in the food industry (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aucejo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maisanaba, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pichardo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordá, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cameán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las ventajas tecnológicas de la incorporación de arcillas modificadas en polímeros para el envasado de alimentos son bien conocidas, pero aún quedan muchas incertidumbres sobre la seguridad de estos materiales. El Instituto Tecnológico del Embalaje, Transporte y Logística ha desarrollado una arcilla, Clay1, modificando una montmorillonita con una sal de amonio cuaternario. Esta organoarcilla, incorporada al polímero (ácido poliláctico), da lugar a un material nanocompuesto, reforzándose así el material de partida. El principal objetivo de este estudio es evaluar la actividad de biomarcadores de estrés oxidativo en bazo de ratas expuestas durante 90 días a Clay1 (40 mg/kg/día) y al extracto de migración obtenido a partir del material nanocompuesto resultante. Los parámetros evaluados fueron la peroxidación lipídica y las actividades enzimáticas superóxido dismutasa y catalasa. Además, se realizó un análisis del contenido en bazo de los metales más característicos que componen la organoarcilla (Al, Ca, Fe, Mg, Si) para comprobar su posible acumulación. En dicho estudio se trabajó con tres grupos de ratas Wistar (n=10): control (comida estándar + agua como bebida), Clay1 (comida estándar mezclada con 40mg/kg/día de arcilla + agua) y extracto de Clay1 (comida estándar + extracto como bebida). Tras el tiempo de exposición los animales se sacrificaron y se extrajo el bazo. De forma general, no se observaron diferencias significativas en ninguno de los parámetros evaluados con respecto al grupo control, por lo que Clay1 muestra un buen perfil toxicológico respecto a los biomarcadores ensayados con vistas a su uso en la industria alimentaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;30(2): 138-143, jul.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la seguridad de una arcilla modificada y su extracto de migración en bazo de ratas Wistar expuestas de forma subcrónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54736^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54736^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54736^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54736^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54736^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54736^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
