<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102496</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lymphoma-like lesion of the cervix with monoclonal immunoglobulin heavy chain gene rearrangement in PCR analysis. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lymphoma-like lesion of the cervix is an uncommon benign lymphoid proliferation that mimics large B-cell lymphoma (LBCL) and hence is a potential cause of misdiagnosis. We report a 24 year-old woman with an abnormal PAP smear and a subsequent cervical biopsy that showed an atypical lymphoid proliferation. Histopathologically, it was characterized by a superficial polymorphic lymphoid infiltrate with numerous scattered large cells, with no necrosis or sclerosis. Surface epithelium showed erosion and mild dysplasia. Immunohistochemically, the large atypical cells were positive for CD20 and the scattered large cells for CD30, with no expression of light chains. In situ hybridization for EBV was positive in a few isolated large cells. PRC amplification of the FR3 region of the IgH heavy chain showed 2 monoclonal bands. Two years later the patient is alive and well(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zoroquiain, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Marcela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valbuena, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La lesión «lymphoma-like» del cérvix es una proliferación linfoide benigna que simula un linfoma B difuso de células grandes, por ello es causa de potencial error diagnóstico. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 24 años con PAP atípico y conización subsecuente, identificándose una proliferación linfoide atípica. El infiltrado linfoide era polimórfico, con numerosas células grandes entremezcladas, sin necrosis ni esclerosis. El epitelio presentó displasia epitelial moderada. Las células grandes fueron inmunorreactivas para CD20, sin expresión de cadenas ligeras de inmunoglobulinas. La hibridación in situ para el virus de Epstein-Barr resultó positiva en escasas células grandes aisladas. Mediante técnica de PCR, para amplificación de la región FR3 de la cadena pesada de la IgH, se observaron 2 bandas monoclonales. Hasta el último seguimiento (24 meses), no se encontró evidencia de enfermedad sistémica/progresión(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;45(3): 181-185, jul.-sept.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesión «lymphoma-like» del cérvix con reordenamiento monoclonal del gen de cadena pesada de inmunoglobulina por PCR. Comunicación de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29014^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29014^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33083^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30362</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
