<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59231</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuous glucose monitoring system in the screening of glucose disorders in cystic fibrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Diabetes mellitus (DM) is an increasing complication of cystic fibrosis (CF). It is associated with enhance morbidity. Continuous glucose monitoring system (CGMS) could detect glucose disorders earlier than other screening tests usually used. Aims: To compare oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT), HbA1c and CGMS in patients with CF and recent disorders of glucose homeostasis and to analyse changes in nutritional status and/or pulmonary function. Patients and methods: Thirteen patients with CF (11&#150;22 years, 7 males) were studied using OGTT, HbA1c and CGMS. All of them had newly diagnosed glucose disturbances. They were not receiving steroid therapy or had an underlying illness. In all subjects we compared: HbA1c levels (%), fasting and 2-hours glucose OGTT (mg/dl) and glucose CGMS values (overall, fasting, 2-hours post mean-meals and excursions &gt;140mg/dl at any time). Furthermore, body mass index, forced expiratory volume in the first second (%) and forced vital capacity (%) were evaluated in the previous year and at the time of the study. We also analysed exocrine pancreatic function and CF-mutation. Results: Mean age at diagnosis of glucose disturbance was 16.4 years. All patients had insufficient exocrine pancreatic function and 11/13 presented &amp;#916;F508 CF-mutation. Only one patient was diagnosed with DM using OGGT and 7/13 (53.8%) with CGMS. A total 77% of patients had poor nutritional status and/or pulmonary function at time of diagnosing the glucose disorder. Only 4 patients had abnormal HbA1c levels. Conclusions: CGMS allows a better detection of glucose disorders than OGTT. Glucose homeostasis abnormalities are associated with a decrease in nutritional status and/or pulmonary function. HbA1c does not aid in the early diagnose of glucose disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yelmo Valverde, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lamas Ferreiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colino Alcol, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Gómez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Castellanos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Frías, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: las alteraciones hidrocarbonadas (AHC) en fibrosis quística (FQ) suelen ser asintomáticas pero conllevan gran morbilidad. Su diagnóstico precoz puede prevenir el deterioro del estado nutricional y de la función pulmonar (FP). Objetivos: comparar los resultados de la monitorización continua de glucosa (CGMS) con los de la sobrecarga oral de glucosa (SOG) en pacientes con FQ. Evaluar la utilidad de la hemoglobina glicosilada (HbA1c) para el diagnóstico precoz de AHC. Analizar los cambios del estado nutritivo y función pulmonar al diagnóstico de AHC. Pacientes y métodos: en 13 pacientes púberes (7 varones) con FQ y AHC, diagnosticada por SOG, implantamos CGMS. Analizamos: edad, sexo, mutación relacionada con FQ, insuficiencia pancreática exocrina, HbA1c (%), glucemia en ayunas y 2h tras SOG. En el CGMS valoramos: glucosa global, en ayunas y posprandial, y excursiones de glucosa &gt;140mg/dl. Además, comparamos el estado nutricional (índice de masa corporal) y la FP (capacidad vital forzada y volumen espiratorio forzado en el primer segundo) en ese momento y en el año previo. Resultados: media de edad al diagnóstico de AHC de 16,4 años (11-22); 11 pacientes tenían mutación &amp;#916;F508. Todos tenían insuficiencia pancreática exocrina. Cumplían criterios de diabetes 1/13 con SOG y 7/13 (53,8%) con CGMS. Se evidenció una declinación del estado nutricional y/o de la FP en el 77%. Sólo 4 pacientes tenían HbA1c patológica. Conclusiones: el CGMS detecta mejor la diabetes relacionada con FQ que la SOG. La presencia de AHC tiende a relacionarse con un empeoramiento nutricional y/o de FP. La HbA1c no permite el diagnóstico precoz de AHC en FQ (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(2): 120-125, feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59231</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización continua de glucosa para cribado de alteraciones hidrocarbonadas en fibrosis quística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
