<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051760</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A naturalistic study: 100 consecutive episodes of acute agitation in a psychiatric emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Psychomotor agitation is a common event in psychiatric emergency services (PES) with a prevalence of approximately 10 %. There is no general consensus on to how to manage psychomotor agitation; benzodiazepines, typical antipsychotics and now atypical antipsychotics have demonstrated similar efficacy. The aim of our study was to describe the epidemiology and clinical management of agitation in «real-life» in a psychiatric emergency service. Methods. A naturalistic study was performed in acutely agitated patients recruited consecutively in a psychiatric emergency service. Demographics, clinical and therapeutic characteristics were analyzed. Efficacy was assessed by the Excitement Component of the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS-EC) and the Agitation-Calmness Evaluation Scale (ACES). Pragmatic variables such as the need for second pharmacological intervention and the need for physical restraints were assessed. Results. The study included 100 patients with psychomotor agitation. Mean age was 36.2 % and 54% were women. The most prevalent diagnoses were psychotic disorder (48 %) and personality disorder (24 %). Physical restraint was required in 39 % of patients and 52 % accepted oral treatment. Haloperidol was the most frequent oral treatment and olanzapine was the most frequent intramuscular treatment. Conclusions. A naturalistic approach provides data based on clinical reality in psychiatric emergency services. Strict research designs of clinical trials of efficacy imply sample selection biases and are generally distanced from the clinical reality. Atypical antipsychotics have become the first-line treatment in acute agitation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faus, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madre, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corripio, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puigdemont, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oller, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La agitación psicomotriz es una situación frecuente en urgencias de psiquiatría con una prevalencia aproximada del 10 %. No hay un consenso total respecto a su manejo; benzodiazepinas, antipsicóticos típicos y, más recientemente, los atípicos han demostrado una eficacia similar. El objetivo del presente estudio es describir las características epidemiológicas y el manejo clínico de los pacientes agitados en la práctica clínica en un servicio de urgencias psiquiátricas.Métodos. Estudio naturalístico de los episodios de agitación psicomotriz recogidos consecutivamente en un servicio de urgencias psiquiátricas. Se recogieron variables demográficas, clínicas y terapéuticas. Las variables de eficacia fueron determinadas mediante la escala Excitement Component of the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS-EC) y la Agitation-Calmness Evaluation Scale (ACES). Se analizaron variables pragmáticas como la necesidad de sucesivas intervenciones farmacológicas o la necesidad de contención física.Resultados. Fueron incluidos 100 episodios de agitación psicomotriz. La edad media fue de 36,2 años y el 54% eran mujeres. Los diagnósticos más frecuentes fueron de trastorno psicótico (48 %) y de trastorno de la personalidad (24 %). El 39 % requirió contención física y el 52 % aceptó el tratamiento por vía oral. El haloperidol fue el fármaco más utilizado por vía oral y la olanzapina por vía intramuscular.Conclusiones. Una aproximación naturalística permite obtener datos de la práctica real en los servicios de urgencias psiquiátricas. Los estrictos diseños de investigación de los ensayos clínicos de eficacia implican sesgos de selección de la muestra y se suelen alejar de la realidad clínica. Los antipsicóticos atípicos se están convirtiendo en fármacos de primera línea en el tratamiento de la agitación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;34(4): 239-244, jul.-ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051760</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio naturalístico: 100 episodios de agitación psicomotriz consecutivos en urgencias psiquiátricas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4712^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3437^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12032^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
