<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038111</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Professional Burnout in dentists and stomatologists of the Galician Health Service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To analyse the degree of professional burnout in primary care dentists of the Galician Health Service (GHS)                 Design. Descriptive, cross-sectional study.                 Setting. Dental care units of the GHS primary care network.                 Subjects. All primary care dentists of the new primary care model of the GHS (N=79). Response rate: 50% (N=35).                 Measurements. Annonymous self-applied questionnaire: the Maslach Burnout Inventory, that evaluates emotional exhaustion, depersonalization, and personal achievements; a social and personal questionnaire. Sudent's t test, ANOVA, *2         or Fisher's exact test were used.                 Main results. Mean age: 46.58±9.47; sex: 74.3% males; temporary job: 82.9%; years in the GHS: 15.25±8.34. High values were detected in: emotional exhaustion 54.3%; depersonalization 55.6%; personal achievements 6.9%. No statistically significant differences were identified in terms of age, sex, marital status, type of contract, rural vs urban areas, number of patients treated, or years in the GHS, apart from the "personal achivements" subscale, that was rated, significantly higher (P=.046) by those who had shorteer experience at for the GHS.                 Conclusion. GHS dentists show a degree of professional burnout close to the one described for family doctors at the Spanish National Health System</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fontao Valcárcel, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pita Babío, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valín Liz, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela-Centelles, P. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Analizar el grado de desgaste profesional de los odontólogos y estomatólogos del Servicio Gallego de Salud.                 Diseño. Estudio transversal, descriptivo.                 Emplazamiento. Unidades de salud bucodental de atención primaria de Galicia.                 Sujetos. Todos los odontólogos y estomatólogos del nuevo modelo de atención primaria del SERGAS (n = 70). Tasa de respuesta del 50% (n = 35).                 Mediciones. Cuestionario anónimo autoadministrado, Maslach Burnout Inventory, en el que se valoran el cansancio emocional, la despersonalización y los logros personales. Variables sociodemográficas. Análisis mediante la prueba de la t de Student, ANOVA, *2 o prueba exacta de Fisher.                 Resultados principales. La edad media de los particiapantes era de 46,58 ± 9,47 años y un 74,3% era varones. Tenía contrato temporal el 82,9% y los años trabajados eran 15,25 ± 8,34. Se obtuvieron valores altos de cansancio emocional (54,3%) y despersonalización (55,6%), y la realización personal fue del 6,9%. No se han hallado diferencias en estos parámetros en función de la edad, el sexo, el estado civil, el tipo de contrato o el ámbito de ejercicio, excepto para el componente «logros personales», que se acumulan significativamente en los primeros años de trabajo (p = 0,046).                 Conclusiones. Los odontólogos y estomatólogos del Servicio Gallego de Salud presentan un grado de desgaste profesional comparable al descrito en médicos de atención primaria del Sistema Nacional de Salud</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;35(6): 301-305, abr. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038111</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desgaste profesional entre los odontólogos y estomatólogos del Servicio Gallego de Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3830^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
