<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128287</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Red Cell Distribution Width and Additive Risk Prediction for Major Bleeding in Non&#150;ST-segment Elevation Acute Coronary Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives Red cell distribution width has been linked to an increased risk for in-hospital bleeding in patients with non&#150;ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome. However, its usefulness for predicting bleeding complications beyond the hospitalization period remains unknown. Our aim was to evaluate the complementary value of red cell distribution width and the CRUSADE scale to predict long-term bleeding risk in these patients. Methods Red cell distribution width was measured at admission in 293 patients with non&#150;ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome. All patients were clinically followed up and major bleeding events were recorded (defined according to Bleeding Academic Research Consortium Definition criteria). Results During a follow-up of 782 days [interquartile range, 510-1112 days], events occurred in 30 (10.2%) patients. Quartile analyses showed an abrupt increase in major bleedings at the fourth red cell distribution width quartile (&gt; 14.9%; P = .001). After multivariate (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Cuenca, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras-Gómez, Ignacio de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Januzzi, , James L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez -Martínez, Marianela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Galian, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzano-Fernández, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés-Chávarri, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Blanco, Pedro J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Narbon, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos El ancho de distribución eritrocitaria se ha relacionado con incremento del riesgo hemorrágico intrahospitalario en pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del ST. Sin embargo, se desconoce su utilidad para predecir complicaciones hemorrágicas tras el ingreso hospitalario. El objetivo fue evaluar el papel complementario del ancho de distribución eritrocitaria sobre la escala CRUSADE en la predicción del riesgo a largo plazo de hemorragias en estos pacientes. Métodos Se midió el ancho de distribución eritrocitaria al ingreso en 293 pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del ST; a todos se les dio seguimiento clínico y se registró la aparición de hemorragias mayores, definidas según los criterios del Bleeding Academic Research Consortium. Resultados Durante un seguimiento de 782 [intervalo intercuartílico, 510-1.112] días, 30 pacientes (10,2%) presentaron eventos hemorrágicos. El análisis por cuartiles reveló un incremento abrupto de hemorragias a partir del cuarto cuartil(..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;67(10): 830-836, oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128287</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ancho de distribución eritrocitaria y predicción adicional del riesgo de hemorragia mayor en el síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del ST</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6626^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4998</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
