<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89231</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work one studies the new &#147;Ley Orgánica&#148; 10/2007 where it regulates the data base police on identifiers obtained from the DNA. And, particularly, the procedural aspects that the same one contains. With this new regulation, the Spanish legislator completes the dispositions on the use of the criminal identification from the DNA techniques, that they were already contained in the Spanish law of Criminal Judgment. Thus Spain to the rest of countries of our surroundings adds itself in which already it was counted on this type of data bases, very useful and effectiveness for the investigation of certain crimes with special gravity. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reverón Palenzuela, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se estudia la nueva Ley Orgánica 10/2007 reguladora de la base de datos policial sobre identificadores obtenidos a partir del ADN. Y en  particular, los aspectos procesales que contiene la misma. Con esta nueva regulación, el legislador español completa las disposiciones sobre la utilización de la identificación criminal a partir de las técnicas de ADN, que ya se contenían en la Ley de Enjuiciamiento Criminal española. Se suma así España al resto de países de nuestro entorno en los que ya se contaba con este tipo de bases de datos, de gran utilidad y eficacia para la investigación de determinados delitos con especial gravedad. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(29): 67-109, jul.-dic. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89231</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La nueva Ley Orgánica 10/2007, de 8 de octubre, reguladora de la base de datos policial sobre identificadores obtenidos a partir del ADN. Aspectos procesales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29881^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22152^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24673</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
