<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75925</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Asbestos-Related Diseases in a Population Neara Fibrous Cement Factory</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objective: The first fibrous cement factory in Spain was setup in Cerdanyola, Barcelona, in 1907 and was a source of pollution there untilit was closed in 1997. The aim of this study was to determine the clinical and epidemiologic characteristics of the population with by asbestos-related diseases who had worked in the factory and/or lived in the vicinity.          Material and Methods: We retrospectively collected information available on patients with asbestos-related diseases who at the time of diagnosis had resided in the are an ear the fibrous cement factory. Information was obtained from the medical records of the primary care centers of the 12 surrounding towns and the sole referral hospital in the area for cases diagnosed between January 1, 1970 and December 31, 2006.                     Results: In the 559 patients diagnosed, 1107 cases of asbestos-related diseases were identified. Between 2000 and 2006, the average annual incidence was 9.5 cases per 100000 inhabitants for the entire study area and 35.5 cases per 100000 for the area nearest the factory. The prevalence of asbestos-related diseases as of December 31, 2006 was 91 cases per 100000 inhabitants in the entire study area and 353.4 cases per 100000 in the area nearest the factory. Of the 1107 asbestos-related disease cases identified, 86.5% were benignand 8.4%pleural mesothelioma.            Conclusions: The factory introduced an important area-wide risk  factor for asbestos-related diseases for both workers and for the nearby population. The number of cases of asbestos-related diseases detected annually showed an up ward trend. The incidence was extremely high in the period studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tarrés, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albertí, Constança</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abós-Herràndiz, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantarell, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orriols, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell-Murphy, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Krier, Illona</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Artés, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Allas, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En 1907 se instaló en Cerdanyola (Barcelona) la primera fabrica de fibrocemento de España, que actuó como foco contaminante hasta su cierre en 1997. El objetivo del estudio ha sido conocer las características clinico epidemiológicas de la población afectada por enfermedades relacionadas con el amianto (ERA) que había trabajado o/y vivía en el entorno de esta fábrica.                                    Material y métodos: Se trata de un estudio retrospectivo que reúne la información disponible de los pacientes afectados de ERA que residían en el momento del diagnóstico en la zona cercana a la factoría de fibrocemento. La información se obtuvo a partir de la documentación médica de los centros de atención primaria de las 12 poblaciones circundantes y del único hospital de referencia de la zona, para los casos diagnosticados entre el 1 de enero de 1970 y el 31 de diciembre de 2006.        Resultados: En los 559 pacientes diagnosticados se identificaron 1.107 casos de ERA. La incidencia anual media entre 2000 y 2006 fue de 9,5 pacientes por 100.000 habitantes para toda la zona, y de 35,5 para la más próxima a la fábrica. La prevalencia de pacientes con ERA a fecha de 31 de diciembre de 2006 fue de 91 por 100.000 personas en toda la zona y de 353,4 en la más próxima a la fábrica. De los 1.107 casos, el 86,5%correspondía a enfermedad benigna y el 8,4%a mesotelioma pleural. Conclusiones: En lazona estudiada, la fábrica supuso un factor de riesgo importante de ERA para sus trabajadores y la población cercana. La detección de casos mostró una tendencia ascendente. La incidencia de ERA fue muy elevada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;45(9): 429-434, sept. 2009. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad por amianto en una población próxima a una fábrica de fibrocemento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32759</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4867</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32392</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1200</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11424</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28484</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
