<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93852</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-2074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Postural analysis: prevention from physical therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The physiotherapist is one of the first professionals who work with girls and boys with Down syndrome (DS) from birth. Due to the inherent characteristics of DS, should perform a preventative role from physiotherapy. Material and methods. There has been studied a population of 14 persons with DS, 6 were girls and 8 were boys, with an average of age between 10 and 11 years. All of them have received as minimum 4 years of treatment physical therapy during his step along the early attention in Granadown. The postural analysis was observations and was realized in three planes of the space. Results. 10 (71.42%) had a lateral tilt of the head, 11 (78.57%) elevation of one of the two shoulders, 8 (57.14%) alterations of the pelvic girdle , 13 (92.85%) suffering from calcaneal valgus, 4 (28.57%) had chest abnormalities, 8 (57.14%) knee valgus, 2 (14.28%) had hallux valgus, 11 (78.57%) antepulsion head, 10 (71.42%) antepulsion right shoulder, 10 (71.42%) cervical kyphosis, 6 (42.85%) dorsal kyphosis, 3 (21.42%) back plane, 11 (78.57%) lumbar lordosis, 9 (64.28%) were hypotonic abdominal muscles and 8 (57.14%) shortening of the hamstrings. Conclusions. We see the need to conduct longitudinal studies where it is evident from the long-term effectiveness of physiotherapy treatments in early attention. We should conduct periodic reviews in order to prevent alterations of the spine and to counsel families about the type of exercises and activities to be undertaken to prevent future children orthopedic deformities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caballero Blanco, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Padilla, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Cabezas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Garrido, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El fisioterapeuta es uno de los primeros profesionales que trabajan con los chicos/as con síndrome de Down (SD) desde su nacimiento. Debido a las características intrínsecas del SD, es conveniente realizar un papel preventivo desde la fisioterapia. Material y métodos. Se ha estudiado a una población de 14 personas con SD, 6 eran chicas y 8 eran chicos, con una media de edad entre los 10 y los 11 años. Todos ellos han recibido como mínimo 4 años de tratamiento fisioterápico durante su paso por la atención temprana en Granadown. El análisis postural se basó en observaciones y se realizó en los tres planos del espacio. Resultados. Diez personas (71,42%) tenían alguna inclinación lateral de la cabeza; 11 (78,57%), elevación de alguno de los dos hombros; 8 (57,14%), alteraciones de la cintura pélvica; 13 (92,85%) presentan valgo de calcáneo; 4 (28,57%) tienen alteraciones de tórax; 8 (57,14%), valgo de rodilla; 2 (14,28%) tenían hallux valgus; 11 (78,57%), antepulsión de la cabeza; 10 (71,42%), antepulsión del hombro derecho; 10 (71,42%), hipercifosis cervical; 6 (42,85%), hipercifosis dorsal; 3 (21,42%), dorso plano; 11 (78,57%), hiperlordosis lumbar; 9 (64,28%) tenían los abdominales hipotónicos, y 8 (57,14%), acortamientos de isquiotibiales. Conclusiones. Vemos la necesidad de realizar estudios longitudinales donde se ponga de manifiesto la eficacia a largo plazo de los tratamientos de fisioterapia en atención temprana. Creemos conveniente realizar revisiones periódicas con el fin de prevenir alteraciones del raquis y poder orientar a las familias sobre el tipo de ejercicios y actividades que deben realizar sus hijos para evitar futuras deformidades ortopédicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SD, Rev. med. int. Síndr. Down (Ed. castell.);15(3): 41-44, nov. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis postural: prevención desde la fisioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
