<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141845</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety, depression and self-esteem in homeless, general population, and substance users</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Substance use disorders coexist in some patients with different clinical manifestations of anxiety and mood, in turn variables as self-esteem keep a narrow relation in the course and evolution of these. The present study investigates the relationship between the substance use disorders, the homelessness and the levels of anxiety, depression and self-esteem. Research is carried out in the city of Castellón, with a total of 258 subjects, divided into a clinical group subdivided into cocaine, heroin, heroin combined with cocaine, cannabis, alcohol users and patients in methadone maintenance program (MMP), an general population group and a group of homeless, evaluated through the questionnaire STAI, BDI, RSES and an interview that gathers biopsychosocial and clinical aspects. Results showed a more severe clinical depression and trait anxiety in consumers of inhaled heroin, as well as increased state anxiety and lower self-esteem in the group of homeless. It can be inferred from the results that the substance use correlates with higher levels of trait anxiety and depression and social exclusion with a lower perception of self-esteem and increased anxiety state (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dalae, Mihaela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francés Olmos, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baquero Escribano, Abel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Orenga , Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester Arnal, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro Cortés, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos por uso de sustancias coexisten en algunos pacientes con diferentes manifestaciones clínicas de ansiedad y del estado de ánimo, a su vez variables como la autoestima guardan una estrecha relación en el curso y evolución de éstos. En el presente estudio se investiga los trastornos por consumo de sustancias, el transeuntismo y los niveles de ansiedad, depresión y autoestima. La investigación se desarrolla en la ciudad de Castellón con un total de 258 sujetos, divididos en un grupo clínico subdividido en consumidores de cocaína, heroína, heroína combinada con cocaína, cannabis, alcohol y sujetos en programa de mantenimiento con metadona (PMM), un grupo de población general y otro grupo de transeúntes, evaluados mediante el cuestionario STAI, BDI, RSES y una entrevista que recoge aspectos biopsicosociales y clínicos. Los resultados mostraron una mayor gravedad clínica en depresión y ansiedad rasgo en consumidores de heroína inhalada, así como una mayor ansiedad estado y menor autoestima en el grupo de transeúntes. Se puede desprender de los resultados que el consumo de sustancias correlaciona con mayores niveles de ansiedad rasgo y depresión, así como la exclusión social con una menor percepción de autoestima y mayor ansiedad estado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;40(2): 24-39, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad, depresión y autoestima en población general, transeúntes y consumidores de sustancias adictivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
