<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152441</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utility of rapid on-site evaluation (ROSE) by a pathologist during endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine needle aspiration cytology: a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">New imaging techniques, allowing the visualization and minimally invasive sampling of organs that are difficult to access, are being used more and more frequently. A suitable, accompanying cytological study is required, as in the majority of cases the caliber of the needle used is not sufficient to obtain a histological sample. Therefore, endoscopic ultrasound is generally associated with fine-needle aspiration (FNA). The performance of FNA on palpable nodules is a cost-effective procedure. However, the cost-effectiveness of using FNA with endoscopic ultrasound guidance is controversial, due to interobserver variability and increase in costs. The object of this study is to determinate if rapid-on site evaluation by a pathologist during endoscopic ultrasound-guided FNA improves diagnostic accuracy (correlated with biopsy), what is the best methodology, who should do it and the cost-effectiveness of the procedure. Because of the lack of Spanish data, we reviewed the pertinent international literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estrada Muñoz, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Aceñero, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz del Arco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Medina, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Numerosas técnicas de imagen permiten visualizar y obtener material de órganos de difícil acceso de forma mínimamente invasiva. Es preciso un estudio citológico adecuado, porque el calibre habitual de las agujas no permite obtener material histológico. Por ello, ligado al uso de la ecoendoscopia se debe hablar de punción aspiración con aguja fina (PAAF). La PAAF es una técnica económica cuando se realiza sobre lesiones palpables, pero con control por técnicas de imagen su rentabilidad es dudosa por la variabilidad entre centros y el aumento del coste. El objetivo de este estudio es determinar si el control por el patólogo del material obtenido en PAAF con ecoendoscopia mejora la precisión diagnóstica (en relación con la biopsia), cuál es la mejor estrategia para esta prueba, quién debe hacerla y si resulta económicamente rentable. Dada la escasez de datos a nivel nacional sobre este tema, hemos optado por una revisión bibliográfica de la literatura publicada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;49(2): 96-105, abr.-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del control por parte del patólogo del material obtenido por punción aspiración con aguja fina bajo guía de ecoendoscopia: revisión de la bibliografía acerca de un tema controvertido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29170^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3603^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29170^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16645</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
