<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128112</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurological manifestations of hunter syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Mucopolysaccharidosis type II, or Hunter syndrome, often presents neurological manifestations. This study examines the differences between severe and mild Hunter syndrome and between central and peripheral nervous system as well as auditory and visual manifestations; it also looks at the alterations observed in magnetic resonance imaging of the head. Development. The difficulties involved in distinguishing between severe and mild forms of Hunter syndrome, above all in the &#145;intermediate&#146; phenotypic forms, are also discussed. The study also reports the most notable clinical manifestations and the diagnostic and therapeutic management of the cognitive and behavioural disorders, hydrocephalus, epileptic seizures, spinal cord compression, visual and hearing disorders, and carpal tunnel syndrome. Finally, the limited, heterogeneous findings from magnetic resonance imaging of the head are analysed. Conclusions. In severe Hunter syndrome, the lead factors during the period of neurodegeneration are cognitive disorders and conduct disorders. Hypoacusis and carpal tunnel syndrome are frequent in both severe and mild Hunter syndrome. Some complications (hypoacusis, hydrocephalus, spinal cord compression, carpal tunnel syndrome) offer a better prognosis if they are detected and treated at an early stage. Currently there is no clear correlation between neuroimaging alterations and the clinical features. Systematic study and monitoring, together with early symptomatic and enzyme treatment are likely to change the natural history of many patients with Hunter syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Solana, L. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La mucopolisacaridosis tipo II, o síndrome de Hunter, presenta con frecuencia manifestaciones neurológicas. Se revisan las diferencias entre el síndrome de Hunter grave y atenuado, las manifestaciones del sistema nervioso central y periférico, auditivas y visuales, así como las alteraciones observadas en la resonancia magnética craneal. Desarrollo. Se exponen las dificultades para diferenciar las formas graves y atenuadas de síndrome de Hunter, sobre todo en las formas fenotípicas &#145;intermedias&#146;. Se recogen las manifestaciones clínicas más destacadas y el manejo diagnóstico y terapéutico de la afectación cognitiva y conductual, la hidrocefalia, las crisis epilépticas, la compresión medular, los trastornos de la visión y la audición y el síndrome del túnel carpiano. Se analizan los resultados limitados y heterogéneos de los estudios de resonancia magnética craneal. Conclusiones. En el síndrome de Hunter grave, las alteraciones cognitivas y los trastornos de conducta protagonizan el período de neurodegeneración. La hipoacusia y el síndrome de túnel carpiano son frecuentes en el síndrome de Hunter grave y atenuado. Algunas complicaciones (hipoacusia, hidrocefalia, compresión medular, síndrome del túnel carpiano) presentan un mejor pronóstico si se detectan y tratan precozmente. En la actualidad no existe una clara correlación entre las alteraciones en la neuroimagen y la clínica. El estudio y seguimiento sistematizado y el tratamiento precoz sintomático y enzimático muy probablemente cambiarán la historia natural de muchos pacientes con síndrome de Hunter (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;47(supl.2): s9-s13, nov. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128112</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestaciones neurológicas del síndrome de Hunter</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29956^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29956^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53690^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29956^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
