<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93828</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fibromialgia is a disease that is accompanied with generalized spontaneous pain, chronic fatigue, muscular rigidity, disruptive sleep and neuroinmunological, endocrinological and affective alterations. This condition makes the diagnosis difficult and frustrates the doctor and the patient, since the diversity and the swings in the symptoms often escape the etiopatogenic justification. With the objective to clarify in a schematic way the factors that can exist due to the development of the disease, to be able to facilitate its clinical understanding, we expose briefly the different hypotheses on this matter (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibromialgia es una enfermedad que cursa con dolor espontáneo generalizado, fatiga crónica, rigidez muscular, trastornos del sueño y alteraciones neuroinmunológicas, endocrinológicas y afectivas. Esta condición dificulta el diagnóstico y frustra al médico y al paciente, ya que la diversidad y lo cambiante de la sintomatología a menudo se escapan a la justificación etiopatogénica. Con objeto de clarificar de una manera esquemática los factores que pueden subyacer bajo el desarrollo de la enfermedad, para así facilitar su comprensión clínica, exponemos someramente las distintas hipótesis descritas al respecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;18(6): 342-350, nov.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93828</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fibromialgia. Consideraciones etiopatogénicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7164^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7164^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19622^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19622^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
