<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159510</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiological characteristics of patients evaluated with fibromyalgia in the Assessment of Disability Unit of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the epidemiological characteristics of patients with fibromyalgia requiring assessment of incapacity for work. Method. A descriptive study was conducted on the patients evaluated in the Medical Unit of the National Institute of Social Security in Madrid in the period from 2005 to 2014 with the diagnosis of fibromyalgia. A study was made on the variables: age, sex, marital status, comorbidity (hypothyroidism, neck pain, psychiatric disorders, and carpal tunnel syndrome), professional occupation, level of education, and type of affiliation to the National Institute of Social Security. Result. The total number of patients studied was 5,501. The median age was 53 years. Compared to the general working population in our area there were 47% more women, 12% less married people, 25% less workers with higher education, and 23% more unskilled occupations. As regards the working population in our area, there is a markedly increased prevalence of neck pain (prevalence ratio: 2.0), hypothyroidism (prevalence ratio 2.4), and carpal tunnel syndrome (prevalence ratio: 3.0). More than half (58%) of the sample presented with psychiatric disorders. Conclusion. It can be concluded that the profile of the patient with fibromyalgia assessed in the UMEVI is a woman, aged 46-60 years, mostly with a relatively unskilled job, and with primary level education. More than half of the cases had associated psychiatric disorders, and often associated with neck pain diagnoses, carpal tunnel syndrome, and hypothyroidism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Regal Ramos, RJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer las características epidemiológicas de los pacientes con fibromialgia que solicitan la valoración de una incapacidad laboral. Método. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo en el que se incluyeron los pacientes valorados en la Unidad Médica de la Dirección Provincial del Instituto Nacional de la Seguridad Social de Madrid entre los años 2005 a 2014, en cuyo informe de valoración figurase el diagnóstico de fibromialgia. Estudiamos las variables: edad, sexo, estado civil, comorbilidad (hipotiroidismo, cervicalgia, enfermedad psiquiátrica mayor o menor y síndrome de túnel carpiano), ocupación profesional, nivel de capacitación y régimen de afiliación a la seguridad social. Resultado. El total de pacientes estudiados fue de 5.501. La mediana de edad fue de 53 años. Respecto a la población general activa de nuestro entorno, observamos un 47% más de mujeres, un 12% menos de casados, un 25% menos de trabajadores con estudios superiores y un 23% más de empleos no cualificados. Respecto a la población en edad laboral de nuestro entorno, obtenemos una prevalencia marcadamente aumentada de cervicalgia (razón de prevalencia: 2,0), hipotiroidismo (razón de prevalencia: 2,4) y de síndrome del túnel carpiano (razón de prevalencia: 3,0). El 58% de la muestra presenta enfermedad psiquiátrica. Conclusión. Podemos concluir que el perfil del paciente con fibromialgia valorado en la UMEVI es una mujer, de entre 46-60 años, mayoritariamente con un trabajo poco cualificado y un nivel de estudios primario, que en más de la mitad de los casos asocia enfermedad psiquiátrica y que con frecuencia asocia los diagnósticos de cervicalgia, síndrome del túnel carpiano e hipotiroidismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);43(1): 28-33, ene.-feb. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159510</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características epidemiológicas de los pacientes evaluados por fibromialgia en la Unidad Médica de Valoración de Incapacidades de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
