<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73246</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of urinary cortisol levels in women with Fibromyalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: We propose a comparative study of urinary cortisol in a controlled simple group of patients diagnosed with fibromyalgia (FM) during a minimum time frame (3 years) vs. a normal group with the same characteristics of age and gender. Our objective is to demonstrate if urinary cortisol at lower levels than those found in the normal population, as long as FM is regarded, could help to evaluate the fatigue. Methods: We determined the urinary cortisol in a group of 47 women with a clinical diagnosis of FM using the criteria from the American College of Rheumatology (ACR) 1990, with ages between 29 and 64 years, in whom an accurate sample was collected and cortisol was determined using an FPIA method. The results were compared with the urinary cortisol obtained in a group of 88 healthy women within the same age range as those with FM. Results: Urinary cortisol in FM was 65.0¼g/l (median), which was significantly lower than that of the healthy group (80.0¼g/l), p&lt;0.001.Conclusion: 33.4% of patients with FM displayed urinary cortisol concentrations significantly lower than the group of women without FM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alegre de Miguel, Cayetano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pérez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bocos Terraz, Julia Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bancalero Flores, Jose Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Ostariz, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Álvarez, Siliva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Los autores del presente artículo se proponen un estudio comparativo del cortisol urinario en una muestra poblacional representativa con diagnóstico de fibromialgia (FM) con evolución prolongada (mínimo 3 años) frente a una población normal con iguales características de edad y sexo, con el objetivo de demostrar si la cortisoluria con valores menores que los encontrados en la población normal en relación con su FM podría explicar su fatiga. Pacientes y método: Se determinó la cortisoluria en un grupo de 47 mujeres con diagnóstico según criterios de FM de la American College of Rheumatology (ACR) 1990, con edades comprendidas entre 29 y 64 años, previa condición de una correcta recogida de la muestra, mediante un FPIA (fluorescence polarization immunoassay  inmunoanálisis de polarización de la fluorescencia ). Se compararon los resultados con la cortisoluria obtenida en un grupo de 88 mujeres sanas incluidas en el mismo rango de edades que las mujeres fibromiálgicas. Resultados: El valor mediano del cortisol urinario en las mujeres fibromiálgicas fue de 65¼g/l, significativamente inferior al de las mujeres sanas, en las que el valor fue de 80¼g/l; p&lt;0,001. Conclusión: Un 33,4% de las mujeres con FM estudiadas presenta una concentración de cortisol urinario significativamente inferior al grupo de mujeres sin FM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);133(7): 255-257, jul. 2009. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73246</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la cortisoluria en mujeres diagnosticadas de fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22498</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22498^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
