<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101569</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral Acitretin and Topical Imiquimod as Neoadjuvant Treatment for Giant Basal Cell Carcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Giant basal cell carcinoma (BCC) is defined as a tumor with a diameter of 5cm or more. Surgery, the treatment of choice for any type of BCC, can cause considerable anatomical damage in large tumors. In 2 patients with giant BCC we therefore provided neoadjuvant treatment with a combination of oral acitretin and topical 5% imiquimod. Acitretin is a systemic retinoid used for primary prevention of nonmelanoma skin cancer. Imiquimod is an immunomodulator whose approved indications include treatment of non facial superficial BCC less than 2cm in diameter. Previous studies have demonstrated a synergic anticancer effect of both drugs in vitro and in vivo. This combination produced a marked reduction in tumor mass in our patients. Later we were able to provide definitive treatment, which achieved complete remission of the tumors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanmartín, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baradad, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El carcinoma basocelular (CBC) gigante se define como aquel que mide 5cm o más. Aunque la cirugía se considera el tratamiento de elección para cualquier tipo de CBC, en los de gran tamaño, puede ser altamente destructiva. Así, utilizamos la combinación de acitretino oral e imiquimod 5% tópico como tratamiento neoadyuvante en dos pacientes afectos de un CBC gigante. El acitretino es un retinoide sistémico que se utiliza en la prevención primaria del cáncer cutáneo no melanoma. El imiquimod es un inmunomodulador aprobado para el tratamiento, entre otros, de CBC superficiales no faciales menores de 2cm. Estudios previos han demostrado una acción sinérgica anticarcinogénica de ambos fármacos, tanto in vivo como in vitro. Dicha combinación produjo en nuestros pacientes una gran reducción de la masa tumoral, lo que nos permitió aplicar posteriormente un tratamiento definitivo con la remisión completa de los CBC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;103(2): 149-152, mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101569</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento neoadyuvante con acitretino oral e imiquimod tópico en el carcinoma basocelular gigante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4671^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4671^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30033^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
