<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79433</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: the total number of harvested lymph nodeshas been demonstrated to be of prognostic significance forcolon cancer. Differences can occur in the total number of harvestedlymph nodes between different specialists (surgeons andpathologists).Objective: the aim of this study was to analyse if, in our centre,the number of analysed lymph nodes in patients with coloncancer that are classified as pN0 is also related to survival.Material and methods: a retrospective study was designed,where 148 patients with colon adenocarcinoma (pN0 of TNMclassification) who underwent elective surgery between 1 January1995 and 31 December 2001, with curative intent were included.Three groups were created according to the number of analysedlymph nodes (&lt; 7, 7-14, &gt; 14 lymph nodes). For survival analysisthe Kaplan-Meier and CUSUM curves methods were used.Results: the total number of analysed lymph nodes was1,493 (mean 10.1 lymph nodes per patient). The rate of 5-years survival was 63.0% in the group with &lt; 7 lymph nodes;7-14 lymph nodes: 80.6% and those with &gt; 14 lymph nodes:91.8% (p &lt; 0.01). Prognostic significance was also present formultivariate analysis.Conclusion: in our centre, harvesting a larger number oflymph nodes is related to improved rates of 5-years survival forpatients with colon cancer staged as pN0. It seems reasonableto recommend obtaining as many lymph nodes as possible, andnot to establish a minimum number of lymph nodes to be harvested(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Daroca José, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortea Sanchís, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivadulla-Serrano, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armengol-Carrasco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escrig-Sos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paiva Coronel, G. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ramos, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador-Sanchis, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el número total de ganglios analizados ha demostradosu influencia pronóstica en el cáncer de colon. Puedenexistir grandes diferencias en el número de ganglios obtenidos pordiferentes especialistas (cirujanos y anatomopatólogos).Objetivo: el objetivo del presente estudio fue analizar si, ennuestro medio, el número de ganglios analizados en pacientes concáncer de colon clasificados como pN0 se relaciona también conla supervivencia.Material y métodos: estudio retrospectivo, con inclusión de148 pacientes con adenocarcinoma de colon (pN0 de la clasificaciónTNM) intervenidos de forma programada con intención curativaentre 1 de enero de 1995 y 31 de diciembre de 2001. Se establecieron3 grupos según el número de ganglios analizados (&lt; 7,7-14, &gt; 14 ganglios). Para el análisis de la supervivencia se utilizaronel método de Kaplan Meier y las gráficas CUSUM.Resultados: el número total de ganglios analizados fue 1.493(media 10,1 ganglios por paciente). La supervivencia a 5 años fuedel 63,0% en el grupo con &lt; 7 ganglios; del 80,6% en el grupocon 7-14; y del 91,8% en el grupo con &gt; 14 ganglios analizados(p &lt; 0,01). La influencia pronóstica se mantuvo en el análisis multivariante.Conclusión: en nuestro medio, la obtención de un mayor númerode ganglios analizados se relaciona con una mayor supervivenciaa los 5 años en pacientes con cáncer de colon clasificadoscomo pN0. Parece razonable recomendar la obtención de tantosganglios como sea posible en este tipo de cirugía y no recomendarun número mínimo de ganglios que se deberían analizar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;102(5): 296-301, mayo 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79433</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del número total de ganglios analizados tras cirugía de resección en el cáncer de colon sobre la supervivencia en pacientes sin afectación ganglionar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8375^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50290</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
