<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118107</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexual risk behavior and demand for prophylaxis for sexually transmitted diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the characteristics of patients coming to the emergency room seeking postexposure prophylaxis for sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) after high-risk sex. Methods: Over a 6-month period, emergency requests for postexposure STD prophylaxis were reviewed. We recorded epidemiologic variables, type of sexual risk behavior, reason for coming to the emergency room, STD prophylaxis prescribed, and cost. Results: A total of 189 patients with a mean (SD) age of 32.5 (8.3) years were included; 162 (85.7%) were men and67.2% were Spanish. One hundred thirteen (59.8%) were men who had sex with men; the partner was seropositive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) in 30.7% of the cases or of unknown serostatus in 61.9%. Condoms were used by49.7%, but 45.5% reported breakage. The most frequent practice was anal penetration (active or passive) (53.4%).Twenty-eight days of preventive HIV antiretroviral therapy was prescribed for 85.2%; 77.2% also received prophylactic antibiotics for other STDs, and 22.8% started immunization against hepatropic viruses. The mean cost per visit and preventive treatment administered or prescribed in the emergency department was &#128;858 (&#128;275).Conclusions: Sexual risk behavior is a frequent reason for emergency department visits, particularly among men who have sex with men. A large proportion of patients come because a condom has broken, but nearly half do not use a condom even when they do not know the serostatus of the partner or know the partner is seropositive for HIV. Emergency care and pharmacologic treatment for these patients are costly (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nogué Xarau, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amigó Tadín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Guillermo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar las características de las consultas a urgencias en demanda de profilaxis para las infecciones de transmisión sexual (ITS) tras una práctica sexual de riesgo. Método: Durante 6 meses se han revisado las demandas de profilaxis atendidas en el servicio de urgencias tras una práctica sexual de riesgo. Se utilizaron como variables datos epidemiológicos, tipo de práctica, motivo de consulta, tratamiento profiláctico y coste económico. Resultados: Se han incluido 189 pacientes con una edad media de 32,5 (8,3) años. De ellos, 162 eran hombres (85,7%). El 67,2% eran españoles. Ciento trece casos (59,8%)eran hombres que tuvieron sexo con otros hombres (HSH), con pareja VIH positiva(30,7%) o de estatus serológico desconocido (61,9%). Usaron preservativo el 49,7%de pacientes, pero consultaron por su rotura o pérdida el 45,5%. La penetración anal, activa o pasiva, fue la práctica sexual más frecuente (53,4%). El 85,2% recibió tratamiento profiláctico para el VIH con antirretrovirales durante 28 días, el 77,2% recibió también profilaxis antibiótica para otras ITS y un 22,8% inició inmunización para virus hepatotropos. El coste medio de la visita y de la profilaxis administrada o prescrita en urgencias fue de 858 (275) euros por paciente. Conclusiones: La práctica sexual de riesgo como motivo de consulta a urgencias es frecuente, principalmente entre un hombre que practica sexo con otro hombre. La mayoría de pacientes acude por una rotura del preservativo, pero casi la mitad no lo usan a pesar de desconocer el estado serológico de la pareja o ser ésta portadora del VIH. La consulta a urgencias y el tratamiento farmacológico generan un coste económico elevado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);25(6): 437-444, dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118107</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demanda al servicio de urgencias de profilaxis para infecciones de transmisión sexual tras prácticas sexuales de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11729^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38864^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
