<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111202</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a group educational intervention in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The aim of this study was to evaluate the feasibility in our environment of a multidisciplinary health education program, on both an individual and group basis, in outpatients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and to determine the effectiveness of this strategy. A prospective, interventional study was performed for one year. Patients with moderate/severe COPD, followed-up in the Pneumology Outpatient Clinic of the Hospital Complex of Ourense (Spain), were evaluated. Two groups of patients, aged between 50 and 75 years old, were randomly chosen (8 patients per group). The intervention group took part in a health education program. Clinical variables and breathing function were measured and quality of life was evaluated using the St. George questionnaire (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Este estudio se plantea con el objetivo de evaluar la factibilidad en nuestro entorno de una estrategia multidisciplinaria de educación sanitaria individual y grupal en pacientes ambulatorios con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) y conocer la efectividad de dicha estrategia. Material y métodos. Se trata de un estudio prospectivo de intervención a un año con pacientes con EPOC moderada/severa, controlados en consultas externas de Neumología del Complejo Hospitalario de Ourense. Se eligieron al azar 2 grupos de 8 personas cada uno, con edades comprendidas entre los 50 y 75 años. En el grupo de intervención se llevó a cabo un programa de Educación para la Salud. El estudio mide (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);13(3): 131-136, mayo-jun. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de una intervención educativa individual y en grupo, en pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
