<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167855</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric properties of the somatic complaints scale in Spanish children and adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The aim of this study was to analyse the psychometric properties of the Somatic Complaints List (SCL) in Spanish child and adult populations. This instrument assesses the frequency with which people experience and feel pain such as stomach ache and headache, among others. It has been validated in different countries and languages (Dutch, English, and Persian), showing adequate psychometric properties. Nevertheless, it has never been validated in a Spanish context. Method: For the adaptation and validation, we used two different samples: 1423 children, age ranging from 8 to 12 years old, selected from 12 primary and secondary schools at 7 locations in the Valencian Community, Spain (age = 9.11 years, SD = 1.27; 52.4% female); and 940 adults, age ranging from 18 to 56 years old (age = 32.3 years, SD = 11.62; 64% female). Results: The Spanish adaptation of the SLC showed adequate levels of reliability and validity. Conclusions: The empirical evidence seems sufficient to justify using this diagnostic tool with Spanish children and adults (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Barrón, Remedios</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Badenes, Lidón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Górriz Plumed, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado-Gascó, Vicente Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el objetivo de este estudio fue analizar las propiedades psicométricas de la escala de quejas somáticas (SCL) en una población infantil y adulta española. Este instrumento evalúa la frecuencia con que las personas experimentan y sienten dolor, como dolor de estómago y dolores de cabeza, entre otros. Se ha validado en diferentes países con diferentes idiomas (holandés, inglés y persa), que muestran propiedades psicométricas adecuadas. Sin embargo, nunca ha sido validado en contexto español. Método: en la adaptación y validación utilizamos dos muestras diferentes: una muestra de 1.423 niños, entre 8 y 12 años, seleccionados de 12 escuelas primarias y secundarias en 7 localidades de la Comunidad Valenciana, España (edad = 9,11 años, SD = 1,27; 52,4% mujeres). Además, una muestra de 940 participantes de 18 a 56 años de edad (edad = 32,3 años, SD = 11,62; 64% mujeres). Resultados: los resultados obtenidos muestran niveles adecuados de fiabilidad y validez de la adaptación de la SCL en el contexto español. Conclusiones: la evidencia empírica obtenida parece suficiente para justificar el uso de esta herramienta de diagnóstico con los niños y los adultos españoles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);27(3): 269-276, ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167855</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades psicométricas de la Escala de Quejas Somáticas en niños y adultos españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54524^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
