<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052618</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The vocational choice and the carrer planning. Spanish adaptation of Holland&#146;s Self-Directed Search (SDS-R)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Self-Directed Search is a career-planning guide that works similarly to a vocational and professional interests inventory. A preliminary study allows detection of 68 ítems that need to be rectified, since they do not meet psychometric and semantic criteria. The current study demonstrates reliability and validity of the new adaptation. It is applied to a sample of 1460 subjects from different educational levels. As for reliability, the discrimination index of the items and internal consistency of the scales have improved. Additionally, procedures performed to verify validity (content, construct and concurrent) demonstrate that the instrument has acceptable validity. On balance, we can conclude that the instrument has sufficient scientific and technical credibility for application to the Spanish population</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valls Fernández, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Vicente, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Self-Directed Search es una guía para la planificación de la carrera que funciona de forma similar a un inventario de intereses vocacionales y profesionales. Un estudio preliminar permite detectar 68 ítems que necesitan ser rectificados por no ajustarse a criterios psicométricos y semánticos. En el presente estudio se comprueba la fiabilidad y la validez de la adaptación realizada. Para ello se aplica a una muestra de 1.460 sujetos de diferentes niveles educativos. En cuanto a la fiabilidad se ha mejorado el índice de discriminación de los ítems y la consistencia interna de las escalas. Por otra parte, los procedimientos realizados para verificar su validez (contenido, constructo y concurrente) demuestran que el instrumento cuenta con una validez aceptable. Por lo que podemos concluir que este instrumento goza de la suficiente garantía científica y técnica para aplicarlo a la población española</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(1): 117-122, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052618</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La elección vocacional y la planificación de la carrera. Adaptación española del self-directed search (SDS-R) de Holland)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1248</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1084^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9975^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
