<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146454</identifier>
<setSpec>0377-4732</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoprosthesis and the new Scale in traffic accidents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The new scale in traffic accidents modifies the current valuation of the sequels on the injured and as the simple numerical assessment of them should be added the foreseeable future healthcare costs. This section is particularly important in injuries related to the specialty of Orthopedics and Traumatology, especially in the field of joint endoprosthesis (hip replacements, knee, shoulder and ankle). The aim of this study is to provide valid data for the damage assessment with the new traffic scale in patients with posttraumatic arthritis necessitating a prosthesis implant surgery and in patients who have been implanted a prosthesis and will require revision surgery in the future (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galeote Rodríguez, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco Martínez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manrique Gamo, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sayed Ávila, Sausan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea Pérez, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardoso Cita, Zulema</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El nuevo Baremo en accidentes de tráfico modifica la actual valoración de las secuelas en los lesionados, ya que a la simple valoración numérica de las mismas se deben añadir los gastos previsibles de asistencia sanitaria futura. Este apartado adquiere una especial importancia en las lesiones relativas a la especialidad de Cirugía Ortopédica y Traumatología, especialmente en el ámbito de las endoprótesis articulares (artroplastias de cadera, rodilla, hombro y tobillo). El objetivo del presente trabajo es proporcionar datos válidos para realizar la valoración del daño corporal con el nuevo Baremo de tráfico en pacientes con artrosis postraumática que precisarán una cirugía de implante de prótesis y en pacientes a los que ya se les ha implantado la prótesis y precisarán una cirugía de recambio en el futuro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. legal;41(4): 222-229, oct.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146454</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endoprótesis articulares y el nuevo Baremo de tráfico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24885^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7760^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24885^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22748^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7763^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22748^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
