<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63027</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main objective of this study was to analyze emotional response to a set of everyday emotional visual stimuli unrelated to drug use. Two groups of prescribed opiate drug abusers (heroin+methadone vs. methadone-only groups) currently participating in the Andalusian Experimental Prescribed Drug Program (Programa Experimental de Prescripción de Estupefacientes de Andalucía, PEPSA) were studied, and comparisons made between them, within them for different phases, and between them and a normative group of nonusers. For this purpose we used the I.C.E.R.E., an instrument based on the I.A.P.S. (International Affective Picture System) and on Peter Lang's S.A.M. (Self-Assessment Manikin). The results showed patterns of emotional response in the opiate users, compared to the non-users, characterized by a lower rating of the everyday natural stimuli of a pleasant nature and a greater sensitivity to the stimuli of a neutral and negative nature. These patterns were quite stable even in different clinical situations and stages of development of the P.E.P.S.A</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arráez Sánchez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montañez Pareja, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Juárez, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verdejo García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Jiménez, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar de Arcos, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la respuesta emocional ante estímulos visuales afectivos cotidianos no relacionados con las sustancias y su consumo, en dos grupos de sujetos dependientes de opiáceos en situación de consumo prescrito y controlado (heroína y metadona vs metadona), participantes en el P.E.P.S.A. (Programa Experimental de Prescripción de eStupefacientes de Andalucía) tanto entre los dos grupos, como en cada uno de ellos en diferentes fases y también en comparación con un grupo normativo de sujetos no consumidores. Para ello, se usó el I.C.E.R.E., instrumento basado en el I.A.P.S. (International Affective Picture System) y en el S.A.M. (Self- Assessment Manikin) de Peter Lang. Los resultados muestran patrones de respuesta emocional en los sujetos consumidores de opiáceos, en relación a sujetos no consumidores, caracterizados por una menor valoración de los estímulos naturales cotidianos de naturaleza apetitiva y una mayor sensibilidad a los de naturaleza negativa y neutra, muy estables ante diferentes situaciones clínicas y de evolución en el desarrollo del P.E.P.S.A</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);20(1): 27-36, ene.-mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63027</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
