<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050515</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inclusion of the ring into the stomach pouch after gastric bypass: diagnosis and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At present the Gastric Bypass (GB), is the surgical techniquemore frequently realized, for treatment of the morbidobesity. Some surgeons add to the gastric pouch aring of different materials, with the purpose of maintainingthe rate of the lost overweight, for longer period oftime. However; besides adding a higher complexity tothe technique, it can generate a higher morbidity. Theinclusion of the ring in the pouch is an uncommon complication.We report a 35 year-old woman who developedinclusion of ring into the stomach pouch. The patientpresented picture clinic of the intestinal occlusion. Thediagnosis was made by endoscope. The patient requiredsurgery for resolution of symptoms after failure of theendoscopic treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carvajal Balaguera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mártin García-Almenta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliart Delgado de Tórres, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Isabel, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Gamarra, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Maestro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camuñas Segovia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerquella Hernádez, C. M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viso Ciudad, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Bypass Gástrico (BG), es en la actualidad el procedimientoquirúrgico más frecuentemente realizado, en el tratamientode la obesidad mórbida. Algunos cirujanos añadenal reservorio gástrico una anilla de diversos materiales, conel propósito de mantener en el tiempo el porcentaje delsobrepeso perdido, sin embargo; además de añadir unamayor complejidad a la técnica, puede generar una mayormorbilidad. La inclusión de la anilla en el reservorio es unacomplicación infrecuente. Publicamos el caso de unapaciente de 35 años de edad, que presentó inclusión de laanilla en el reservorio gástrico tras el BG por obesidad patológica.El cuadro clínico debutó como una oclusión intestinal.El diagnóstico se confirmó tras realizar tránsito intestinalcon contraste y endoscopia. La paciente requirió cirugíatras fracasar el intento endoscópico</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;17(4): 292-297, abr. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050515</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inclusión de la anilla en el reservorio tras bypass gástrico: diagnóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23640^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
