<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124710</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the efficacy of aquatic exercise during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: currently, there has been an increase in the number of pregnant women who are interested in doing physical exercise during pregnancy, and particularly in the aquatic setting. The results of studies published on this matter are very few, and therefore more studies are required in order to clarify the benefits and risks of these activities, both for the mother and the foetus. Objective: assessment of the efficacy of moderate aquatic exercise during pregnancy in their physiology, and outcomes in maternal and foetal health. Method: systematic review based on evidence-based clinical practice guidelines (CPGs), systematic reviews (SRs), randomized controlled clinical trials (CTs), and quasi-experimental studies (QESs), with interventions where moderate aquatic exercise during pregnancy was compared with any other physical exercise, or with no intervention. The databases analyzed were: Guía Salud, National Guidelines Clearinghouse(NGC), TripDatabase, PubMed (Medline) and Embase. The search period was limited from January, 2003 to January, 2013.Results: after eliminating duplicates, 23 references located were analyzed, 11 of which were selected for critical reading, and subsequently became part of the study. Those selected for critical reading included three systematic reviews, three randomized clinical trials, one clinical practice guideline, and four quasi-experimental studies. Conclusions: moderate aquatic exercise during pregnancy is a safe and effective alternative for the binomial mother-child. Due to the scarcity and heterogeneity of the data found, additional research is required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Constante, Sonsoles María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: en la actualidad, ha habido un aumento en el número de mujeres embarazadas interesadas en la realización de ejercicio físico durante el embarazo y, particularmente, en el medio acuático. Los resultados de los estudios publicados sobre el tema son escasos, por lo que son necesarios más estudios para aclarar los beneficios y los riesgos de estas actividades, tanto para la madre como para el feto. Objetivos: evaluación de la efectividad del ejercicio moderado acuático durante el embarazo en su fisiología y resultados de salud maternos y fetales. Método: revisión sistemática a partir de guías de práctica clínica(GPC) basadas en la evidencia, revisiones sistemáticas (RS), ensayos clínicos (EC) aleatorios controlados y estudios cuasi experimentales(ECE), con intervenciones en las que se comparaba el ejercicio acuático moderado durante el embarazo con cualquier otro ejercicio físico o con ninguna intervención. Las bases de datos analizadas fueron: GuíaSalud, National Guidelines Clearinghouse (NGC), TripDatabase, PubMed (Medline) y Embase. Se limitó el periodo de búsqueda entre enero de2003 y enero de 2013.Resultados: tras eliminar duplicados, se analizaron 23 referencias localizadas, de las cuales 11 fueron seleccionadas para una lectura críticay posteriormente pasaron a formar parte del estudio. De los seleccionados para la lectura crítica, tres fueron revisiones sistemáticas, tres ensayos clínicos aleatorizados, una guía de práctica clínica y cuatro estudios cuasi experimentales. Conclusiones: el ejercicio acuático moderado durante el embarazo es una alternativa segura y efectiva en el binomio madre-hijo. Debido a la escasez y heterogeneidad de los datos encontrados, son necesarias investigaciones adicionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(3): 64-68, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124710</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de la efectividad delejercicio acuático durante el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8600^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
