<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98144</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Young women with recurrent infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract. Common variable immunodeficiency (CVID) is the primary immunodeficiency frequently found in the clinical practice. Clinically, it is defined as the presence of recurrent infections and a reduction in IgG serum (at least 2 standard deviations before the reference values for the subject&#146;s age) and at least another one of the Ig (IgA or IgM) and a reduction or absence of the production of antibody titers protectors for polysaccharide vaccines and protein antigens. The clinical manifestations of these patients are multiple sinopulmonary infections, systemic bacterial infections and gastrointestinal complications, the sinopulmonary infections being the clinical manifestations found most. The principal basis  of the CVID treatment is the immunoglobulin replacement treatment, together with antibiotics for the infections and adequate treatment of the non-infectious complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caballero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Romero de Tejada, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Punter, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Carbajo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segrelles, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. La inmunodeficiencia común variable (CVID) es la inmunodeficiencia primaria que con más frecuencia encontramos en la práctica clínica. Clínicamente se define como la presencia de infecciones recurrentes y una reducción en suero de IgG (al menos 2 desviaciones estándar por debajo de los valores de referencia para su edad) y al menos otra de las Ig (IgA o IgM) y una reducción o ausencia de producción de títulos protectores de anticuerpos para vacunas de polisacáridos y antígenos proteicos. La clínica que presentan estos pacientes son múltiples infecciones sinopulmonares, infecciones  bacterianas sistémicas y complicaciones gastrointestinales, siendo las infecciones sinopulmonares la manifestación clínica con que se presenta mayoritariamente. El pilar principal del tratamiento de la CVID es el tratamiento sustitutivo con inmunoglobulinas, junto con los antibióticos para las infecciones y el tratamiento adecuado de las complicaciones no infecciosas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;12(4): 168-170, oct.-dic. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mujer joven con infecciones de repetición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22206^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30688^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
