<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61756</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between the triglyceride/high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol ratio, insulin resistance index and cardiometabolic risk factors in women with polycystic ovary syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective:To evaluate the relationship between the triglyceride/high density lipoprotein cholesterol (TG/HDL-c) ratio, insulin resistance index and cardiometabolic risk factors in women with polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS). Patients and method: The present cross-sectional study analyzed 62 women with PCOS and 48 healthy women (control group) aged 1735 years old. Body mass index (BMI), waist circumference (WC) and blood pressure were registered. Plasma concentrations of glucose, insulin, triglycerides, total cholesterol and HDL-c were measured. The TG/HDL-c ratio, homeostasis model assessment for insulin resistance (HOMAIR) and quantitative insulin sensitivity check index (QUICKI) were calculated. Results: Women with PCOS showed significantly higher values of the TG/HDL-c ratio and HOMAIR, and a significantly lower QUICKI value. These differences were related to BMI and WC, with the highest values being observed in obese patients. The 50th percentile for the TG/HDL-c ratio was 3.64; the TG/cHDL ratio was positively correlated with BMI, WC and HOMAIR (r = 0.48, p &lt; 0.001; r = 0.58, p &lt; 0.001; r = 0.43, p &lt; 0.001 respectively) and was negatively correlated with the QUICKI (r = ¿0.51; p &lt; 0.001). Women with PCOS showed a higher frequency of fasting glucose &gt; 100 mg/dl (10% vs 3%; p &lt; 0.05), triglycerides &gt; 150 mg/dl (55% vs 20%; p &lt; 0.05) and WC &gt; 80 cm (82.3% vs 43.8%; p &lt; 0.001). Metabolic syndrome was also more frequent in women with PCOS than in controls (31% vs 10%). The independent variable with the strongest influence on TG/HDL-c was WC (p &lt; 0.001). Conclusions: This cross-sectional study demonstrates that women with PCOS show significantly higher values of the TG/HDL-c ratio, which is closely related to WC and insulin resistance and sensitivity indexes (HOMAIR, QUICKI). The TG/HDL-c ratio could be considered as a useful and practical method to identify an increased risk of cardiovascular disease in patients with PCOS(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valeri, Lenin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velázquez-Maldonado, Elsy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roa Barrios, Marlene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>,Arata-Bellabarba, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la interrelación entre el cociente triglicéridos/colesterol de las lipoproteínas de alta densidad (TG/cHDL), índices de resistencia a la insulina y factores de riesgo cardiometabólico en pacientes con síndrome de ovario poliquístico (SOPQ). Pacientes y método: En este estudio transversal se estudió a 62 mujeres con SOPQ y 48 mujeres sanas (grupo control), con edades de 17-35 años. Se registró el índice de masa corporal (IMC), el perímetro de cintura y la presión arterial. Se cuantificó la glucemia, la insulinemia, los triglicéridos, colesterol total y cHDL. Se calcularon los índices de resistencia HOMAIR (homeostasis model assessment), y sensibilidad a la insulina QUICKI (quantitative insulin sensitivity check index) y el cociente TG/cHDL. Resultados: Las pacientes con SOPQ mostraron valores significativamente más altos del HOMAIR y del cociente TG/cHDL, y un valor significativamente más bajo del índice QUICKI, los cuales se relacionaron con el IMC y el perímetro de cintura, con valores máximos en las mujeres obesas. El percentil 50 del cociente TG/cHDL fue 3,64. El cociente TG/cHDL se correlacionó positivamente con el IMC, el perímetro de cintura y el HOMAIR (r = 0,48; p &lt; 0,001; r = 0,58, p &lt; 0,001; r = 0,43; p &lt; 0,001 respectivamente) e inversamente con el QUICKI (r = ¿0,51; p &lt; 0,001). El grupo con SOPQ mostró una mayor frecuencia de glucosa en ayunas &gt; 100 mg/dl (el 10 frente al 3%; p &lt; 0,05), y triglicéridos &gt; 150 mg/dl (el 55 frente al 20%; p &lt; 0,05) y perímetro de cintura &gt; 80 cm (el 82,3 frente al 43,8%; p &lt; 0,001). La frecuencia de síndrome metabólico fue más alta en el grupo con SOPQ (el 31 frente al 10%). El perímetro de cintura fue la principal variable independiente que influyó en el valor del TG/cHDL (p &lt; 0,001) Conclusiones: Este estudio demuestra que las mujeres con SOPQ presentan valores significativamente más altos del cociente TG/cHDL, lo cual está estrechamente relacionado con el perímetro de la cintura y los índices de resistencia y sensibilidad a la insulina (HOMAIR, QUICKI). El cociente TG/cHDL se podría considerar como un método útil y práctico para identificar un riesgo cardiovascular aumentado en las pacientes con SOPQ (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;56(2): 59-65, feb. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61756</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el cociente triglicéridos/cHDL, índices de resistencia a la insulina y factores de riesgo cardiometabólico en mujeres con síndrome del ovario poliquístico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11519^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
