<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042620</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Case report, with reference to an affected family</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cowden&#146;s syndrome is a rare genodermatosis characterized by multiple hamartomas in several tissues and organs derived from all three embryonic layers.Clinical features of Cowden&#146;s disease are explained by the mutation of the PTEN tumour suppressor gene, whose modification leads to an uncoordinated growth of tissues.The importance of this disease lies in the increased susceptibility to malignization of some lesions, specially breast, thyroid and genito-urinary tract lesions. As a result, the disease has been considered a preneoplasic condition. Despite its varied phenotypic expression, this disease is generally unknown. Consequently, many cases are undiagnosed or diagnosis comes at a late stage, what points out the importance of an early diagnosis of the disease so the patient can have periodic check-ups to prevent malignant diseases.A family case is presented here, whose diagnosis was based upon oral clinical findings and which most distinct systemic alteration is the presence of hamartomatous polyps in the digestive tract in several family members</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Keochgerián, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Cowden es una rara genodermatosis caracterizada por múltiples hamartomas ubicados en tejidos y órganos diversos derivados de las tres hojas embrionarias.Las manifestaciones clínicas de la enfermedad de Cowden se explican especialmente por la mutación de un gen supresor tumoral, el PTEN cuyo cambio induce al crecimiento incoordinado de los tejidos.La importancia de esta enfermedad radica en la tendencia a la malignización de algunas de sus lesiones especialmente las de mama, tiroides y tracto génito-urinario. Esto ha determinado que se la considere como una entidad preneoplásica. A pesar de su variada expresión fenotípica esta entidad es generalmente desconocida. Esto determina que muchos casos pasen desapercibidoso sean diagnosticados tardíamente, de ahí la importancia del diagnóstico precoz de esta enfermedad que lleve al paciente a revisiones periódicas para prevenir enfermedades malignas.Se presenta aquí un caso familiar cuyo diagnóstico surge por los hallazgos clínicos detectados en la cavidad bucal y cuya alteración sistémica mas destacada es la presencia de pólipos hamartomatosos en el tracto digestivo en varios miembros de la familia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(1): 12-16, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042620</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Cowden. A propósito de una familia afectada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28109^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19179^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19179^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19179^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
