<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79048</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">QUALYPOLL.®. Questionnaire which measures the quality of life for patients who have undergone an intestinal or urological ostomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors publish the first precise, specific, valid questionnaire in Spanish which measures the quality of life related to health for patients who have undergone an intestinal or urological ostomy; furthermore, this questionnaire has been validated in a sample of Spanish population. The OPM Division of B. Braun Medical was the sponsor of the study which led to the creation of this QUALYPOLL® questionnaire. Statistical validation of the data complied was performed by Health Outcomes Research Europe which carried out a multi-centric national study to evaluate the measuring properties of the aforementioned QUALYPOLL® questionnaire on patients who have undergone an intestinal or urological ostomy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cantarino, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, Fuensanta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana, Paloma de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encina Arias, M. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Adelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada, M. Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poca, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalba, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el primer cuestionario en castellano, preciso, específico, válido y validado en población española que mide la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en pacientes ostomizados. La División OPM de B. Braun Medical fue el promotor del estudio que facilitó la elaboración del cuestio-nario de calidad de vida QUALYPOLL®. La validación estadística de los datos estuvo a cargo de la empresa Health Outcomes Research Europe, que puso en marcha un estudio multicéntrico a nivel nacional para evaluar las propiedades de medición de dicho cuestionario en pacientes ostomizados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;31(4): 282-288, abr. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79048</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">QUALYPOLL ®. Cuestionario que mide la calidad de vida en los pacientes ostomizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22955^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
