<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117124</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antimicrobial effects of sodium hipochlorite and clorhexidine against Enterococcus faecalis. A in vitro study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive. To investigate in vitro the antimicrobial activity of sodium hypochlorite (NaCIO) and clorhexidine (CHX) in different concentrations against Enterococcus faecalis, compared with the efficacy of the combination of the same irrigating substances. Material and methods. The substances tested wre: 2,5% warm NaCIO 5,25% NaCIO, 2% liquid CHX 2,5 warm NaCIO with 2% liquid CHX, 5,25% NaCIO with 2% liquid CHX. Sterile saline was used as control Analyzed times: 15&#148;, 30&#148;, 1´, 3´, 5´, 10´, 15´, 30´ and 1 hour. For the bacterial identification we have used two different methods: the agar diffusion test and a biochemical identification kit (API 20 Strep, Biomereux, Madrid). Statistical analysis was conducted with the Student´s t test. Differences were considered statistically significant when p&lt;=0.05. Results. Inferential analysis revealed a statistically significant difference in the reduction of bacteria between CHX liquid 2% and the rest of irrigants, except with NaCIO 5,25% + liquid CHX 2%. Conclusions. The association of NaCIO and CHX did not improve the antimicrobial activity of CHX alone (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Córdoba del Moral, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Arrevola, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mena Álvarez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Lapeña, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Morós, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rico Romano, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El propósito principal de esta investigación in vitro es comparar el efecto antimicrobiano de la clorhexidina (CHX) y del hipoclorito de sodio (NaCIO) a diferentes concentraciones contra el E. faecalis, analizando a la vez distintos tiempos de acción de cada una de las sustancias de estudio. Material y método. Las sustancias de estudio han sido: NaCIO caliente al 2,5%, NaCIO al 5,25%, CHX líquida al 2% NaCIO caliente al 2,5% junto al CHX líquida al 2%, NaCIO al 5,25% junto a CHX líquida al 2% y suero salino como grupo control Los tiempos analizados: 15&#148;, 30&#148;, 1´, 3´, 5´, 10´, 15´, 30´y 1 hora. Para la identificación bacteriana hemos empleado dos métodos diferentes: la tinción diferencial de Gram y la diferencias estadísticamente significativas valores de p&lt;=0,05. Resultados. Mayor eficacia en la erradicación de bacterias de la CHX líquida 2% frente al resto de irrigantes, hallando diferencias estadísticamente significativas con todos, excepto con NaCIO 5,25% + CHX líquida 2%. Conclusiones. La combinación del NaCIO y la CHX no supera la acción antimicrobiana de la CHX aislada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);30(3): 103-110, jul.-sept. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117124</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio in vitro de la eficacia del hipoclorito de sodio y la clorhexidina contra el enterococcus faecalis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13358^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2755^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27987^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30421^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
