<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154836</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spinal anesthesia in Ambulatory Surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recently, we have witnessed a drop of spinal anesthesia as a routine technique in outpatients by the rise of general anesthesia. This is due to the adverse effects typically associated with its employment and delayed discharge home. However, the introduction of new local anesthetics of short duration and the use of selective spinal anesthesia in orthopedic procedures has led to a growing interest in the anesthetic technique. We intend with this article to make a review of spinal anesthesia, including indications and contraindications and associated technical side effects. Finally, we provide a brief summary of the new short-acting local anesthetics and recommendations for the proctologic and lower limb surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanjuan Álvarez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Bertos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Engel Espinosa, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herva Pintor, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensio Merino, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años hemos asistido a un abandono de la anestesia espinal como técnica habitual en pacientes ambulatorios por el auge de la anestesia general. Esto se debe a los efectos adversos clásicamente asociados a su empleo y al retraso en el alta domiciliaria. Sin embargo, la irrupción en el mercado de los nuevos anestésicos locales de corta duración y la utilización de la anestesia subaracnoidea selectiva en procedimientos ortopédicos ha suscitado un interés creciente por esta técnica anestésica. Con este artículo pretendemos hacer una revisión de la anestesia espinal, de las indicaciones, contraindicaciones y de los efectos adversos asociados a la técnica. Finalmente, proponemos un resumen breve de los nuevos anestésicos locales de acción corta y unas recomendaciones para la cirugía proctológica y del miembro inferior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;20(1): 33-40, ene.-mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154836</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anestesia espinal y cirugía ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d786^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13734^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13734^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
