<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90304</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gender violence in higher education: predictors factor analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The consideration of violence against women as a social problem and its inclusion on political agenda in Spain has taken a great force in ultimate years. Among the actions that are indicated like important in this context is to include this subject in college education of future professionals that should confront it. In the framework of a large investigation, we analyze prediction factors that differentiate between university students that has studied subjects with domestic violence contents of them has not in a sample of 1395 university students. We administered them an ad hoc interview and the "Inventario de Pensamientos Distorsionados sobre la Mujer y la Violencia". The results show that among prediction variables of this circumstance there is so much socio demographic variables, as of prior education, perception of the frequency and causes of the problem and beliefs around him. Likewise, these results show that the variables that better predict to have studied this type of matters they differ between men and women. The implications of these results are analyzed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro Guzmán, Capilla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch Fiol, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Pérez, Victoria A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La consideración de la violencia contra las mujeres como problema social y su inclusión en la agenda política en España ha tomado una gran fuerza en los últimos años. Entre las actuaciones que se señalan como relevantes en este contexto está incluir esta temática en la formación universitaria de los/as futuros/as profesionales que deberán afrontarla. En el marco de una investigación más amplia, se analizan los factores predictores que diferencian al alumnado universitario que ha cursado asignaturas con estos contenidos de aquel que no las ha cursado en una muestra de 1395 estudiantes universitarios/as a quienes se administró una entrevista ad hoc y el &#147;Inventario de Pensamientos Distorsionados sobre la Mujer y la Violencia&#148;. Los resultados muestran que entre las variables predictoras de esta circunstancia hay tanto variables sociodemográficas, como de educación previa, percepción de la frecuencia y causas del problema y creencias en torno a él. Igualmente, estos resultados muestran que las variables que mejor predicen haber cursado este tipo de materias difieren entre alumnas y alumnos. Se analizan las implicaciones de estos resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(2): 435-446, mayo-ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90304</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La violencia de género en la formación universitaria: análisis de factores predictores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
