<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131260</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The treatment of suicide in the spanish press: ¿werther effect or papageno effect?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Suicide is the cause of death of one million per year. In Spain , 3180 people has been died for this reason in 2011. People are unaware of the risk factors associated with suicide. The media have a great influence on the attitudes , beliefs and behaviors in society. Among the media, the press is considered the most influential. A considerable amount of literature suggest that the media could lead to acts to imitation suicide. This kind of phenomenon is known as 'Werther effect' or 'Copycat'. On the other hand, the content of the news could have a preventive effect called 'Papageno effect'. The WHO (World Health Organization) has developed a series of recommendations to the media as part of the program 'suicide prevention' (SUPRE). Aim: This current study analyse whether the press has considered the recommendations of the WHO to publish news about suicide. Methodology: News about suicide of five spanish newspapers (El País, El Mundo del Siglo Veintiuno, ABC, El Comercio de Asturias y La Nueva España) were collected during a year. From 01/09/2011 to 30/10/2012. Results: Most news give details about of used method; background in mental health are not taken into account; there are no reports on aid and community resources; sometimes they consider suicide something unexplainable. Conclusions: Most part of the newspaper don&#146;t have into account the WHO recommendations for publish news abut suicide (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Jambrina, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Ramírez, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ures Villar, María Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El suicidio causa un millón de muertes cada año en todo el mundo. En España fallecieron 3180 personas en 2011 por este motivo. Los medios de comunicación ejercen gran influencia sobre las actitudes, creencias y comportamientos de la comunidad. Entre los medios de comunicación, la prensa es calificada como el medio de mayor influencia. Una considerable cantidad de literatura sugiere que los medios de comunicación podrían inducir a actos de imitación del suicidio, este fenómeno se conoce como efecto Werther. Por el contrario, el contenido de las noticias también puede constituir un efecto preventivo, denominado efecto Papageno. La O.M.S. ha elaborado unas recomendaciones dirigidas a los medios de comunicación como parte del programa de prevención del suicidio (SUPRE). Objetivo: En el presente estudio se analiza si la prensa tiene en cuenta las recomendaciones de la OMS para la publicación de las noticias sobre el suicidio. Metodología: Se recogen las noticias relacionadas con el suicidio aparecidas en la edición digital de cinco diarios españoles, (El País, El Mundo del Siglo Veintiuno, ABC, El Comercio de Asturias y La Nueva España), desde el 01/09/2011 hasta el 30/10/2012. Resultados: En la mayor parte de las noticias se dan detalles sobre el método; no se tienen en cuenta los antecedentes en salud mental; no se informa sobre ayudas y recursos comunitarios; se informa acerca del suicidio como algo inexplicable o simplista. Conclusiones: La mayoría de las noticias recogidas no tienen en cuenta las directrices de la OMS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;35(125): 123-134, ene.-mar. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131260</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El tratamiento del suicidio en la prensa española: ¿efecto werther o efecto papageno?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50135</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3177^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
