<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057176</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family phisician´s role in the HIV infection management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection is a disease with    great sociosanitary impact. Since 1981, when the first cases of AIDS    were described, more than 60 million people have become infected. During    these 25 years there have been a lot of advances in the infection management    and we know that prevention and early diagnosis are crucial.    Family Physician&#146;s role is essential since this is a privileged point of    global attention, counseling and support for these patients. The main    objective is to reduce the new HIV infections incidence. In addition, other    objectives are: primary prevention and health promotion, early diagnosis,    recruitment infected patients, monitoring and end-of-life caring.    It is important to know that all of us are susceptible to contract the    virus and, although the HIV testing is voluntary, there are screening recommendations    from the CDC: persons with signs or symptoms that suggest    infection, pregnant women, persons at high risk for infection and all    patients aged 13-64 years, as a part of routine clinical care. The communication    of the result is a key point in the therapeutic relation. If it is negative    we must make intervention on risk attitudes. If it is positive we must    inform and support the patient, to convince him about the need to be followed    up by an specialized level.    The AIDS terminal patient is a very immunodeficient one and needs    palliative cares like other terminal disease. Another challenge is prevention    and control of HIV infection among the immigrant community.    In conclusion, Family Physicians must investigate risk practices,    inform, prevent new cases and, in the infected people, monitor the evolution,    supporting and comforting</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bachiller Luque, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios Martín, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briongos Figuero, L. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eiros Bouza, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) es    una enfermedad con gran impacto sociosanitario. Desde 1981, cuando se    describieron los primeros casos de sida, se han infectado más de 60    millones de personas. En estos 25 años se han realizado muchos avances    en cuanto a su manejo y sabemos que la prevención y el diagnóstico precoz    son fundamentales.    El papel del médico de familia es esencial ya que es un punto privilegiado    de atención global, counseling y apoyo para estos pacientes. El    principal objetivo es disminuir la incidencia de nuevas infecciones por    VIH. Además, otros objetivos son: prevención primaria y promoción de    la salud, diagnóstico precoz, captación de pacientes infectados, seguimiento    y cuidados al paciente terminal.    Es importante conocer que todos somos susceptibles de contraer el    virus y, aunque la realización de la serología de VIH es voluntaria, existen    recomendaciones de los CDC: sujetos con signos o síntomas sugestivos    de infección, mujeres embarazadas, sujetos con situaciones de riesgo    y entre los 13 y 64 años de manera rutinaria. La comunicación del resultado    es un punto clave en la relación terapéutica. Si es negativo se debe    hacer intervención sobre las conductas de riesgo. Si es positivo debemos    informar y apoyar al paciente, además es importante una buena captación    y valoración para su derivación a la consulta especializada.    El paciente terminal de sida está muy inmunodeprimido y necesita    cuidados paliativos como otra enfermedad terminal. Otro reto es la prevención    y control de la infección VIH en la población inmigrante.    En conclusión, el médico de familia debe investigar prácticas de riesgo,    informar, prevenir nuevos casos y, en la población infectada, seguimiento    de la evolución, apoyando y confortando</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;24(8): 399-403, ago. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057176</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel del médico de familia en el manejo de la infección por VIH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24719^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29422^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
