<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85687</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dyslipidemia and cardiovascular risk in the adult population of Castile-Leon (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">bjectiveHypercholesterolemia is one of the cardiovascular risk factors more sensitive to preventive and control interventions. This study aims to determine the epidemiological pattern of dyslipidemic people in Castilla y Leon.MethodsA representative stratified two-stage sample of the population resident in Castilla y León (Spain) was obtained. A total of 4,013 people age 15 years and older were interviewed. Cardiovascular disease related variables were gathered from clinical records and medical examination. Total cholesterol, HDL-c, LDL-c, and triglycerides were measured.ResultsTotal cholesterol, HDL-c, LDL-c and triglycerides increase with age and, all but total cholesterol present gender differences. LDL-c and triglycerides are higher in men than in women under the age of 60, and lower from that age on, while HDL-c is always higher in women. Total cholesterol was &amp;#8805;250mg/dl in 14.6% of the sample and &amp;#8805;200mg/dl in the 56.3%. Only 49.6% of people with total cholesterol &amp;#8805;250mg/dl had been diagnosed and only 15.2% were under treatment. Age-adjusted total cholesterol was positively correlated with all cardiovascular risk factors. Furthermore, over 70% of the population presented, at least, one cardiovascular risk factor.ConclusionsThe results above shows high levels of total cholesterol and LDL-c, low levels of HDL-c in males and the under diagnosis in clinical records. The association between hypercholesterolemia and other cardiovascular risk factors is similar to previous studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano Alonso, José Eugenio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Alonso, Agustín Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano Hernández, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álamo Sanz, Rufino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castrodeza Sanz, José Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lleras Muñoz, Siro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoLa hipercolesterolemia es uno de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular más sensible a las medidas de prevención y control. Este estudio pretende conocer las características clínicas y epidemiológicas de las personas dislipidémicas en Castilla y León.MétodosSe realizó un muestreo bietápico-estratificado y se obtuvieron datos de 4.013 personas, representativas de la población de 15 o más años de edad en Castilla y León. Se recogieron las variables relacionadas con la enfermedad cardiovascular de la historia clínica, la anamnesis y la exploración. Se determinaron el colesterol total y las distintas fracciones lipídicas (c-HDL, c-LDL y triglicéridos).ResultadosEl colesterol total, el c-HDL, el c-LDL y los triglicéridos aumentan con la edad, y todos excepto el primero presentan diferencias según el sexo. El c-LDL y los triglicéridos están más elevados en los hombres que en las mujeres hasta los 60 años de edad, pero luego el patrón se invierte, mientras que el c-HDL siempre es más alto en las mujeres. El 14,6% de la población tiene un colesterol total &amp;#8805;250mg/dl y un 56,3% lo tiene &amp;#8805;200mg/dl. Sólo el 49,6% de las personas con &amp;#8805;250mg/dl tenían antecedentes en su historia clínica, y únicamente un 15,2% recibían tratamiento. El colesterol total ajustado por la edad se correlacionaba positivamente con todos los demás factores de riesgo cardiovascular. Además, más del 70% de la población presenta al menos un factor de riesgo cardiovascular.ConclusionesDestacan los altos valores de colesterol total y c-LDL, así como los bajos de c-HDL en los hombres, y el infradiagnóstico en las historias clínicas. La asociación de hipercolesterolemia con otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular es similar a la observada en otros estudios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(4): 282-287, jul. -agos. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85687</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dislipidemias y riesgo cardiovascular en la población adulta de Castilla y León</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
