<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85099</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early diagnosis of streptococcal pharyngitis in paediatric practice: Validity of a rapid antigen detection test</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo determine the validity of the rapid antigen test for the diagnoses of acute pharyngitis caused by group A beta-haemolytic Streptococcus (GABHS) compared with culture.DesignObservational study of a consecutive sample of paediatric patients.SettingTwo primary care centres (PCC) from the metropolitan area of Barcelona.ParticipantsChildren aged 1&#150;14 years with sore throat of no more than 5 days duration were chosen at PCC.Principal measurementsOropharyngeal samples were collected from tonsillar bed and posterior pharynx. A rapid diagnostic test was performed, as well as a throat culture.ResultsA total of 211 patients were studied. The overall prevalence of pharyngitis due to Streptococcus was 34.1%. Compared with the throat culture, the sensitivity of the rapid test was 90.3% (95% CI: 81.0&#150;96.0), the specificity was 78.4% (95% CI: 70.6&#150;84.9). The percentage of false negatives was 9.7% and the false positives was 21.6%. Spectrum bias was present, inasmuch as the rapid test sensitivity increased with Centor scores.ConclusionsThe diagnostic value of a rapid antigen test for the diagnosis of streptococcal pharyngitis in paediatric patients at PCC is high. However, the percentage of false positives and negatives is too high, and also the sensitivity is too low in patients with fewer symptoms to support the use of rapid antigenic test without culture confirmation and bacterial sensitivity test(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzalo Santos, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aliaga, Arantxa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baba, Zeki</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores Mateo, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conejero, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barredo, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrau, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echasabal, Mildrey</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grenzner Martinel, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoEstudiar la validez de una técnica de diagnóstico antigénico rápido (TDAR) del estreptococo betahemolítico del grupo A para el diagnóstico de la faringitis aguda en comparación con el cultivo del exudado faríngeo.DiseñoEstudio observacional en una serie consecutiva de pacientes.EmplazamientoDos centros de atención primaria del área metropolitana de Barcelona.ParticipantesNiños entre 1&#150;14 años que presentaban dolor faríngeo de menos de 5 días de evolución y que acudían a las consultas de pediatría.Mediciones principalesA todos los participantes se les recogieron 2 muestras de la faringe posterior y del área tonsilar, una para la realización de la TDAR y otra para el cultivo.ResultadosEn 211 pacientes estudiados la prevalencia de faringitis estreptocócica fue del 34,1%. La sensibilidad de la prueba fue del 90,3% (IC del 95%: 81,0&#150;96,0) y la especificidad fue del 78,4% (IC del 95%: 70,6&#150;84,9). El porcentaje de falsos negativos fue del 9,7% y el porcentaje de falsos positivos fue del 21,6%. Se observó un sesgo del espectro en el que la sensibilidad de la TDAR se incrementó con los criterios de Centor.ConclusionesEl valor diagnóstico de la TDAR para la faringitis estreptocócica en pacientes de pediatría atendidos en las consultas de atención primaria fue alto. Sin embargo, el porcentaje de falsos positivos y negativos fue muy alto y mostró una baja sensibilidad en pacientes con una clínica menos grave, por lo que la TDAR debe complementarse con la realización del cultivo, que además nos aportará información sobre la sensibilidad antibiótica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;42(7): 356-361, jul. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85099</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico precoz de faringitis estreptocócica en pediatría: validación de una técnica antigénica rápida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13683^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
