<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138132</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of thiopurine agents in ulcerative colitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Thiopurine agents have been shown to be effective in maintaining remission in patients with Crohn's disease. There is less evidence for the efficacy of these treatments in ulcerative colitis. Consequently, the effect of thiopurines in the latter disease continues to be the subject of debate and controversy remains on whether these drugs are equally effective in both diseases. The present article aims to review, from a practical point of view, the evidence of the efficacy of thiopurines in ulcerative colitis, current indications for this treatment, safety in patients with inflammatory bowel disease and the treatment optimization strategies proposed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chaparro, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gisbert, Javier P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los fármacos tiopurínicos han demostrado ser eficaces en el mantenimiento de la remisión en los pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn. La evidencia sobre la eficacia de estos tratamientos en la colitis ulcerosa es más escasa. Por este motivo, el efecto de los fármacos tiopurínicos en la colitis ulcerosa está debatido y persiste la controversia sobre si son tan eficaces como en la enfermedad de Crohn. Los objetivos del presente artículo serán revisar, desde un punto de vista práctico, la evidencia sobre la eficacia de los tiopurínicos en la colitis ulcerosa, las indicaciones actuales de dicho tratamiento, la seguridad de estos fármacos en los pacientes con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal y las estrategias propuestas para la optimización del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;34(supl.3): 30-35, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de los fármacos tiopurínicos en la colitis ulcerosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
