<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150335</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics and quality of intra-operative cell salvage in paediatric scoliosis surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the haematological and microbiological characteristics of blood recovered by using a cell saver with a rigid centrifuge bowl (100 ml) in paediatric scoliosis surgery and to determine whether it conforms to the standard expected in adult patients. Material and methods. A cross-sectional, descriptive cohort study was performed on 24 consecutive red blood cell (RBC) units recovered from the surgical field and processed by a Haemolite® 2+ (Haemonetics Corp., Braintree, MA, EE. UU.) cell saver. Data were collected regarding age, weight, surgical approach (anterior or posterior), processed shed volume and volume of autologous RBC recovered, full blood count, and blood culture obtained from the RBC concentrate, and incidence of fever after reinfusion. Results. The processed shed volume was very low (939 ± 569 ml) with high variability (coefficient of variation = 0.6), unlike the recovered volume 129 ± 50 ml (coefficient of variation = 0.38). A statistically significant correlation between the processed shed volume and recovered RBC concentrate haematocrit was found (Pearson, r=.659, P=.001). Haematological parameters in the recovered concentrate were: Hb 11 ± 5.3 g dl&amp;#8722;1; haematocrit: 32.1 ± 15.4% (lower than expected); white cells 5.34 ± 4.22 × 103 ul&amp;#8722;1; platelets 37.88 ± 23.5 × 103 ul&amp;#8722;1 (mean ± SD). Blood culture was positive in the RBC concentrate recovered in 13 cases (54.2%) in which Staphylococcus coagulase (&amp;#8722;) was isolated. Conclusions. Cell salvage machines with rigid centrifuge bowls (including paediatric small volume) do not obtain the expected haematocrit if low volumes are processed, and therefore they are not the best choice in paediatric surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perez-Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz-Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gredilla-Díaz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Suay, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Sánchez, J de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar las características hematológicas y microbiológicas de la sangre recuperada mediante el uso de un recuperador celular con campana centrifugadora pediátrica rígida (100 ml) en cirugía de escoliosis en pediatría y comprobar si se ajusta al estándar esperado en el paciente adulto. Material y método. Estudio de cohorte transversal, descriptivo, sobre 24 unidades consecutivas de sangre recuperada del campo quirúrgico procesadas mediante un recuperador de sangre modelo Haemolite® 2+ (Haemonetics Corp., Braintree, MA, EE. UU.). Se recogieron los datos referentes a edad, peso, abordaje (anterior o posterior) de la cirugía de escoliosis, volumen procesado y volumen de concentrado de hematíes (CH) autógeno recuperado, hemograma y hemocultivo del concentrado obtenido y la incidencia de fiebre tras la reinfusión. Resultados. El volumen procesado fue muy escaso (939 ± 569 ml) con gran variabilidad (coeficiente de variación = 0,6), a diferencia del volumen recuperado 129 ± 50 ml (coeficiente de variación = 0,38). Se estableció correlación estadísticamente significativa entre el volumen procesado y el hematocrito del CH recuperado (Pearson, r = 0,659; p = 0,001) que fue menor del esperado. Los parámetros hematológicos más relevantes de los concentrados recuperados fueron: Hb 11 ± 5,3 g dl&amp;#8722;1; HTO: 32,1 ± 15,4%; leucocitos 5,34 ± 4,22 × 103 &amp;#956;l&amp;#8722;1; plaquetas 37,88 ± 23,5 × 103 &amp;#956;l&amp;#8722;1 (media ± DE). El hemocultivo del CH recuperado fue positivo en 13 casos (54,2%) en los que se aisló Staphylococcus coagulasa (&amp;#8722;). Conclusiones. Los recuperadores celulares con campana centrifugadora de volumen fijo (incluso pediátrica) no obtienen la concentración esperada si se procesan bajos volúmenes, por lo que no son la mejor opción en el niño (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;63(2): 78-83, feb. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150335</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características y calidad de la sangre autóloga recuperada del campo quirúrgico durante cirugía de escoliosis en pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4999^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4999^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1832^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12980^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22189^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27923^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8140^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22189^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8140^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27923^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12980^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1832^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
