<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140875</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic factors of a satisfactory functional result in patients with unilateral amputations of the upper limb above the wrist that use an upper limb prosthesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. The purpose of this study is to determine the prognostic factors of a satisfactory functional outcome in patients using upper extremity prosthetics with a proximal third forearm stump, and above, level of amputation. Materials and methods. All patients with longitudinal deficiencies and traumatic amputations of upper extremity with a level of amputation of proximal third forearm and above were included. A total of 49 patients with unilateral upper extremity amputations that had used the prosthetic for a minimum of 2 years were included in the protocol. The Disability arm shoulder hand (DASH) scale was used to determine a good result with a cut-off of less than 40%. The independent variables were the level of amputation, the etiology for its use, initial age of use and number of hours/day using the prosthesis. Results. It was found that patients with a congenital etiology and those that started using the prosthetic before 6 years of age had better functional results. Discussion. It was found that when adapting a patient with an upper extremity prosthetic, which has a high rejection rate of up to 49%, better functional outcomes are found in those who started using it before 6 years of age, and preferably because of a congenital etiology. It was also found that the number of hours/day strongly correlates with a favorable functional outcome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Capdevila-Leonori, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dabaghi-Richerand, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haces-García, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo de este artículo es evaluar los factores pronósticos para una adecuada adaptación protésica de extremidad superior y qué variables condicionan un resultado funcional satisfactorio en pacientes con una amputación por encima del tercio proximal del antebrazo. Material y método. Se incluyó en el estudio a 49 pacientes con deficiencias longitudinales o amputaciones traumáticas de extremidad superior de antebrazo proximal hasta desarticulación de hombro, con un tiempo mínimo de utilización de la prótesis de 2 años. Se utilizó la escala de Disability arm shoulder hand (DASH), tomando como un resultado satisfactorio un valor de menos de 40%. Las variables independientes fueron etiología del uso, nivel de la amputación, inicio de uso y h/día de uso. Resultados. Se consideró de buen pronóstico a aquellos pacientes con una etiología congénita y cuando el inicio del uso de la prótesis era antes de los 6 años, mostrando una diferencia significativa entre los grupos. Discusión. Se encontró que la etiología congénita es de buen pronóstico, al igual que el caso de aquellos que utilizan la prótesis más de 6 h/día. Por medio de este trabajo se pudieron demostrar mejores resultados funcionales en los pacientes a los que se les adapta una prótesis de extremidad superior antes de los 6 años y preferentemente por una etiología congénita. También se encontró que el número de horas de uso al día correlaciona con un resultado funcional favorable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);59(5): 343-347, sept.-oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores pronósticos de un resultado funcional satisfactorio en pacientes con amputaciones unilaterales de extremidad superior por arriba de la muñeca que utilizan próstesis de extremidad superior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4248^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4248^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d688^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d230^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d688^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
