<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137803</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of being the organizer of a handball world championship in team performance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">When a team plays at home seems to get some advantage. This effect is called home advantage (HA) and has been widely studied in league competitions, but little in competitions in a single venue. 4.340 games played in all Handballl World Championships since 1936 to 2011 were analyzed. The variables registered were games won, games drawn, games lost, the number of goals scored and goals against and the gender of the competitors. The HA (mean±sd) in the World Handball Championships is 67.9±0.23, for the male category and 71.2±0.27 for the female. A significant association exists between HA, the points obtained in a competition and the final classification of a team (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Aguilar, Ó</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saavedra García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Romero, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cuando un equipo actúa como local parece tener cierta ventaja. Este hecho se denomina home advantage (HA) y ha sido muy estudiado en competiciones de liga, pero poco en competiciones de sede única. Se analizaron 4.340 partidos disputados en todos los Campeonatos del Mundo de balonmano disputados hasta 2011. Las variables registradas fueron: partidos ganados, empatados, perdidos, número goles marcados y recibidos y sexo de los competidores. La HA en los Campeonatos del Mundo de balonmano es de 67,9±0,23 para la categoría masculina y de 71,2±0,27 para la femenina. Existe una asociación entre la HA, los puntos obtenidos y la clasificación final del equipo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;15(57): 139-150, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137803</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de organizar un campeonato del mundo de balonmano en el rendimiento del equipo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
