<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76863</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cefditoren in the respiratory tract infections of the community</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cefditoren is a third-generation oral cephalosporinwith good activity against respiratory tract pathogens, includingpenicllin&#150;intermediate and &#151;resistant strains of S. pneumoniae, and &amp;#946;-lactamase producing strains of H. influenzaeand M. catarrhalis. Its bacterial activity, measuredby minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), is similar orsuperior to that of many other commonly used antibiotics(penicillins, cephalosporins and fluoroquinolones). Consideringthe target attainment of T &gt; MIC of &amp;#8805; 40% a more reliablepredictor of clinical and microbiologic outcomes, cefditorencovers strains of S. pneumoniae with MIC values &amp;#8804; 0.5&amp;#956;g/mL and &amp;#8804; 1 &amp;#956;g/mL in the case of doses of 200 mg and400 mg, respectively, and all strains of H. influenzae. Cefditorenhas been associated with high rates of bacteriologicresponse among the main causative pathogens in lower respiratorytract infection (~&#150;85% against H. influenzae and~&#150;90% against S. pneumoniae, including penicillin-intermediateand penicillin-resistant strains). It is a reliable optionfor switch therapy in case of treatment with third-generationintravenous cephalosporin. Cefditoren is currentlyapproved in Spain for the treatment of adults and adolescentswith acute exacerbations of chronic bronchitis(AECB) and community-acquired pneumonia (CAP), two ofthe lower respiratory tract infections most commonly encounteredin clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barberán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mensa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cefditoren es una cefalosporina oral de tercera generacióncon buena actividad frente a los patógenos respiratorios,incluidos S. pneumoniae con sensibilidad disminuida y resistentea penicilina, y H. influenzae y M. catarrhalis productoresde betalactamasas. Su actividad antibacteriana, medidapor concentración mínima inhibitoria (CMI), es similar o superiora otros antibióticos habitualmente utilizados (penicilinas,cefalosporinas y fluoroquinolonas). El parámetro T &gt; CMIpor encima del 40% entre dosis consecutivas, que es el quemejor predice los resultados clínicos y microbiológicos, se logracon cefditoren para S. pneumoniae con CMI &amp;#8804; 0,5 &amp;#956;g/mly &amp;#8804; 1 &amp;#956;g/ml con dosis de 200 mg y 400 mg, respectivamente,y en el 100% de los casos de H. influenzae y M. catarrhalis.Cefditoren produce una alta tasa de erradicación bacteriológicaentre los principales patógenos causales de las infeccionesdel tracto respiratorio inferior (~&#150;85% frente a H. influenzaey ~&#150;90% frente a S. pneumoniae, incluidos los desensibilidad intermedia y resistentes a penicilina). Es una opciónmuy apropiada para la terapia secuencial en caso de tratamientocon cefalosporinas de tercera generación intravenosa.Cefditoren está actualmente aprobada en España para eltratamiento de las infecciones del tracto respiratorio inferiordel adulto y adolescente: exacerbación de la enfermedad pulmonarobstructiva crónica (EPOC) y neumonía comunitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;22(3): 144-150, sep. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76863</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cefditoren en las infecciones de víasrespiratorias bajas adquiridas en lacomunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2547^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2547^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13683^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6344^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6344^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36322</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28319^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
