<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105058</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">AC® Therapy in pediatric patient with bone exposition after  purpura fulminans</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Meningococcal sepsis is associated with a high mortality rate. These patients may show severe disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) and skin, subcutaneous tissue and muscle necrosis due to poor tissue perfusion. It is rare that early surgical intervention be required, as it is relatively difficult to determine the degree of tissue loss early on. Once the patient is stable, debridement of all necrotic tissue is essential, and the goals are still to preserve as much tissue as possible, specially the joints. Many children survive the disease, but suffer major morbidities such as extremities amputation, which may result of complications like bone exposure. There is very little published experience regarding the non-surgical treatment of this complication. We report anew possible application of the vacuum-assisted closure system (VAC®) in very young patients with loss of tissue as a result of purpura fulminans secondary to meningococcemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luque López, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Llerena, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Cecilia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sepsis meningocóccica se asocia con un alto índice de mortalidad. Los pacientes afectados pueden mostrar signos de coagulación intravascular diseminada (CID) y necrosis de partes blandas debidas a baja perfusión tisular. Los procedimientos quirúrgicos precoces suelen demorarse  en estos casos, pues inicialmente es difícil determinar el grado de la lesión. Una vez que el paciente está estable, es esencial el desbridamiento de todo tejido necrótico, teniendo como objetivo el preservar la máxima cantidad de tejido posible, especialmente las articulaciones. Muchos niños sobreviven a esta patología, pero sufren gran morbilidad: amputación de una o varias extremidades y otras complicaciones derivadas como exposiciones óseas. Existen pocas publicaciones que hagan referencia al tratamiento no quirúrgico de este tipo de lesiones. Presentamos un caso de aplicación del sistema de terapia depresión negativa VAC ® en paciente en edad pediátrica tras pérdida de sustancia como resultado de una púrpura fulminans secundaria a meningococcemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;37(supl.1): s58-s63, dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105058</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de Terapia VAC® en paciente pediátrico con exposición ósea postamputación traspúrpura fulminans</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9538^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53099^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d686^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
