<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051255</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9512</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the anxiety in the disorders of the food conduct by means of the STAIC</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to asses the association between eating disorders and anxiety. A comparison has been conducted between level of anxiety in adolescent patients with eating disorders and a control group paired by age, sex and education level. Differences in the same variable between anoretic and bulimic patients have also been analyzed. The Stait-Trait Anxiety Inventory for Children (Spielberger, 1998) has been used to study this subject. The results of the investigation noted that patients with eating disorders showed higher levels of anxiety than the control group. Significant differences between anorexia and bulimia nervosa were not identified</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Vázquez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz López, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guijarro Granados, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio se centra en examinar la relación entre los trastornos de alimentación y la ansiedad. Se comparan los niveles de ansiedad entre adolescentes diagnosticadas de trastorno de la conducta alimentaria y un grupo de estudiantes de la misma edad. Además, se analizan las diferencias en la misma variable entre pacientes diagnosticadas de anorexia y bulimia. Para ello, se utiliza el Cuestionario de autoevaluación ansiedad estado/rasgo en niños (STAIC), de Spielberger. Los resultados obtenidos indican que adolescentes diagnosticadas de trastorno de la conducta alimentaria obtienen niveles más altos de ansiedad. N o se observan diferencias significativas entre anorexia y bulimia nerviosas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. infanto-juv;22(3): 74-83, jul.-sept. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051255</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la ansiedad en los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria mediante el STAIC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24007^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29912^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
