<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048571</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Structural features of the sinus of Valsalva and the proximal portion of the coronary arteries: their relevance to retrograde aortocoronary dissection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Retrograde aortocoronary dissection is an unusual complication of coronary angioplasty. Our study provides new structural details of the aortic sinuses and the proximal portions of the coronary arteries, which enable better understanding of several clinical features associated with this complication. Methods. We studied eight aortic sinus specimens from patients with structural ischemic heart disease using dissection, histologic analysis, and scanning electron microscopy, and compared findings with those in eight control specimens. Results. We observed the following features: a) in 10 specimens (71%), the left coronary artery diameter was greater than the right; b) the angle that the ascending aorta made with the left coronary artery was acute, whereas that with the right coronary artery was closer to a right angle, thereby possibly providing a better approach for catheterization; c) in contrast to those of the right coronary artery, the periostial wall and sinotubular junction of the left coronary artery were formed by more smooth muscle cells and by a dense matrix of collagen type-I fibers, and d) the aortic sinuses and coronary arteries in structural ischemic heart disease specimens displayed structural alterations that affected the aortic tunica media and the collagen distribution at the sinotubular junction. Conclusions. The morphological and structural differences observed between right and left sides suggest that the left aortic sinus is more resistant to traction and is, therefore, less prone to iatrogenic dissection. Structural ischemic heart disease is a risk factor that increases the likelihood of aortocoronary dissection</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Fernández, Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Mínguez, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Quintana, Damián </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yen-Ho, Siew</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogales-Asensio, Juan M </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La disección retrógrada aortocoronaria es una complicación poco frecuente que sigue a la angioplastia coronaria. Nuestro estudio proporciona nuevos detalles estructurales de los senos aórticos y la porción proximal de las arterias coronarias para un mejor entendimiento de aspectos relacionados con esta complicación. Métodos. Hemos analizado mediante técnicas de disección, histológicas y de microscopia electrónica de barrido los senos aórticos de 8 especímenes con cardiopatía isquémica estructural y se comparan con 8 especímenes control. Resultados. Hemos observado las siguientes características: a) el diámetro de la arteria coronaria izquierda en 10 especímenes (71%) fue mayor que el de la derecha; b) el ángulo que forma la coronaria izquierda con la aorta ascendente es agudo, mientras que el de la coronaria derecha tiende a ser recto, por lo que puede presentar un mejor abordaje para la cateterización; c) la pared periostial y la unión sinotubular de la coronaria izquierda contiene, a diferencia de la derecha, más células musculares lisas y una densa matriz de colágeno tipo I, y d) los senos aórticos y coronarias de los especímenes con cardiopatía estructural presentan alteraciones estructurales que alteran la túnica media aórtica y la distribución del colágeno de la unión sinotubular. Conclusiones. Las diferencias morfológicas y estructurales observadas indican que el seno aórtico izquierdo es más resistente a las tracciones y, por lo tanto, menos propenso a la disección iatrogénica. La cardiopatía isquémica estructural es un factor de riesgo que incrementa la predisposición a la disección aortocoronaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(7): 696-702, jul. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048571</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características estructurales de los senos de Valsalva y porción proximal de las arterias coronarias. Su relevancia durante la disección retrógrada aortocoronaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3346^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13231^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13231^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3346^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
