<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050482</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethical criteria for substitute decision-making in people without capacity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nowadays healthcare relationships rest on the recognition of theright of patients to take part in the decisions about their health. Thisidea is the foundation of the informed consent theory. Nevertheless,problem arises when the patient cannot take part in these decisionsbecause he hasn't enough capacity. Then, another person, a substitute,must decide for him. In Spain does not exist enough clarity aboutthe criteria that must guide the decisions of the proxy. The presentwork deals with the three criteria developed by the North Americanjurisprudence. These criteria are: the subjective criterion, the criterionof the substitute judgment and the best interest or major benefitcriterion. The subjective criterion is based on the statement of theown patient, usually written in an advance directive or living will.The criterion of the substitute judgment tries to rebuild the decisionthat the own patient had taken if he remained capable. The criterionof the major benefit tries to protect the well-being of the patient. Traditionallythe «better interest» has been to defend the life at anyexpense, without attending to another type of considerations. Probablyit is the moment to look for a new consensus on what today thesociety has to consider the «better interest» of a patient. Surely thisnew definition meaning would not stem exclusively from the right tolife, but from the conjunction between quantity and quality of lifeconsiderations and the freedom of patients, all interpreted in the lightof the respect person's dignity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrio Cantalejo, Inés M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón Lorda, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente las relaciones sanitarias se apoyan en el reconocimientodel derecho de los pacientes a participar en las decisionessobre su salud. Esta idea es el fundamento del consentimiento informado.Sin embargo, problema surge cuando el paciente no puedeparticipar en estas decisiones porque se halla en una situación deincapacidad. Es otro, un representante, quien debe decidir por él. EnEspaña no existe claridad sobre qué criterios deben orientar las decisionesque ha de tomar el representante. El presente artículo presentalos criterios de decisión en pacientes incapaces desarrollados porla jurisprudencia norteamericana: el criterio subjetivo, el criterio deljuicio sustitutivo y el criterio del mejor interés o mayor beneficio. Elcriterio subjetivo consiste en seguir las directrices que el pacientedictó antes de perder la capacidad. El criterio del juicio sustitutivotrata de deducir la decisión que hubiese tomado el propio paciente sipudiera, a partir de lo que conocemos de él. El criterio del mayorbeneficio intenta proteger el bienestar del paciente. Tradicionalmenteel «mejor interés» ha sido defender la vida a toda costa, sin atendera otro tipo de consideraciones. Quizás sea el momento de buscar unconsenso sobre lo que socialmente hoy en día se considera «mejorinterés». Su significado no podrá derivarse exclusivamente del derechoa la vida, sino de la conjunción entre éste &#150;en cantidad y calidadsuficientes&#150; y la libertad, interpretados a la luz del respeto a la dignidadde la persona</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(4): 303-315, jun.-jul. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050482</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Criterios éticos para las decisiones sanitarias al final de la vida de personas incapaces</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29986</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8196^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29108^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33917^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19340^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30381^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
