<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048312</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence and prevalence of ischaemic heart disease and cerebrovascular disease in Spain: a systematic review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease morbidity is not well documented inSpain, due to the fact that there is no comprehensive and reliabledata source. This study sought to describe the population frequencyof ischaemic heart disease and cerebrovascular disease in Spain. Weused bibliographic search strategies in four different databases toidentify scientific studies published in Spanish medical journals orby Spanish authors after 1990. We then selected studies drawn frompopulation-based registers, prevalence surveys and cohort studies,from which age-adjusted incidence and/or prevalence rates could beextracted. We identified 19 papers published in the period 1993-2005, containing valid information on cardiovascular diseases populationincidence or prevalence in Spain. Acute myocardial infarctionincidence rates per 100,000 population ranged between 135-210 and29-61 new cases annually for men and women aged 25-74 years, respectively.Acute myocardial infarction prevalence rates were notavailable, but a study of prevalence of angina showed rates of 7,3%in men and 7,5% in women. Cerebrovascular disease incidence ratesper 100,000 population ranged between 364 for men and 169women, in aged 69 years and over rising to 2.371 in men and 1.493in women. Prevalence rates in population aged 65 years and overwould be estimated in 7% in men and 6% in women. Conclusions:Although currently available information may serve as an initialreference, monitoring of the incidence and prevalence of these diseaseswill nevertheless call for an effort which exceeds the capacity ofisolated research teams</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Santa-Pau, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerrato Crespán, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medrano Albero, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boix Martínez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La morbilidad de las enfermedades cardiovasculares no es bienconocida en España. Esta carencia de información se debe a que noexiste una fuente de datos que sea estable, exhaustiva y fiable. Elobjetivo de este trabajo es describir la frecuencia poblacional de cardiopatíaisquémica y enfermedad cerebrovascular en España. Seidentificaron como fuentes de información los estudios científicospublicados en revistas médicas españolas o por autores españolescon fecha posterior al año 1990, mediante estrategias de búsquedabibliográfica en cuatro bases de datos distintas. Se seleccionaron losestudios derivados de registros poblacionales, encuestas de prevalenciay estudios de cohortes de los que fue posible extraer tasas deincidencia y/o prevalencia ajustadas por edad. Se identificaron 19trabajos publicados entre 1993 y 2005, con información válida sobreincidencia o prevalencia de cardiopatía isquémica o enfermedadcerebrovascular en España a nivel poblacional. Morbilidad por cardiopatíaisquémica: Las tasas de incidencia de infarto agudo de miocardiooscilaron entre 135-210 nuevos casos anuales por cada100.000 varones y entre 29-61 por cada 100.000 mujeres entre 25 y74 años. No existen datos de prevalencia de cardiopatía isquémica,solamente hay un estudio de prevalencia de angina en la que ésta seestima en el 7,3% en hombres y 7,5% en mujeres. Las tasas de incidenciade enfermedad cerebrovascular por 100.000 habitantes seestiman en 364 en hombres y 169 en mujeres. Si la incidencia semidiera en población mayor de 69 años las tasas se elevarían a 2.371en hombres y 1.493 en mujeres. La prevalencia de ictus en poblaciónmayor de 65 años en España podría estimarse en un 7% en hombresy un 6% en mujeres. La información disponible en la actualidad puedeservir como referencia inicial, pero sería necesario un esfuerzo deestandarización metodológica y de coordinación que excede la capacidadde grupos de investigación aislados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(1): 5-15, ene.-feb. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048312</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia y prevalencia de cardiopatía isquémica y enfermedad cerebrovascular en españa: revisión sistemática de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2600^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
