<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120633</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Feeding habits play a prominent role in carcinogenesis. The dietary patterns approach applied to the study of chronic diseases is of increasing interest in nutritional epidemiology. Nevertheless, it has been seldom used in Latin America. Objective: To identify dietary patterns in adult population in Cordoba (Argentina) and to estimate their effects on the risk of colon-rectal (CRC), urothelial (UC), breast (BC) and prostate(PC) cancers. Methods: Four case control studies were conducted, 2006-2012for CRC, PC, BC and UC. To identify the dietary patterns, a Principal Components Factor Analysis was conducted. A multilevel logistic regression was adjusted for the risk analyses. Results: Characteristic dietary patterns in the whole population, and in women and men independently, were identified. In the whole population South Cone and Sweet Beverages patterns behaved as promoters for CRC and UC while the Prudent Pattern had a protective effect. Female South Cone, Rural and Starchy patterns were associated to a higher BC risk. Prudent Pattern lowered BC risk. In men, South Cone, Sweet Beverages and Typical Measured patterns promoted PC. Conclusion: It is necessary to promote a regular intake of vegetables, fruits and diary products (although a moderate intake for men), and to reduce red meat (especially fat meat), processed meat, starchy vegetables, wine and sweet beverages intakes, to prevent the occurrence of cancer. In men, it is recommended a moderate intake of egg. In women, it is advised a moderate intake of refined grains, bakery products, oils and mayonnaise intake (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, María del Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aballay, Laura Rosana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tumas, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Niclis, Camila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Sonia Edith</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coquet, Julia Becaria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pou, Sonia Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La alimentación es un importante factor vinculado a la ocurrencia del cáncer. Su abordaje en términos de patrones alimentarios es de creciente interés en epidemiología nutricional, no obstante ha sido pocas veces empleado en Latinoamérica. Objetivos: Identificar patrones alimentarios en la población adulta de Córdoba (Argentina) y estimar sus efectos sobre el riesgo de ocurrencia de cáncer colorrectal (CCR), cáncer de mama (CM), cáncer de próstata (CP) y urotelial (CU).Métodos: Se condujeron estudios caso-control, 2006-2012, correspondientes a CCR, CM, CP y CU. Empleando un análisis factorial de componentes principales se identificaron patrones alimentarios. Se estimaron ORs mediante regresión logística multinivel. Resultados: Se identificaron patrones característicos en la población general, y en hombres y mujeres independientemente. En población total, los patrones Cono Sur y Bebidas Azucaradas evidenciaron un efecto promotor para CCR y CU, y el Patrón Prudente mostró efecto protector. En mujeres, el CM se asoció de manera directa con los patrones Cono Sur Femenino, Rural y Amiláceo, e inversa con el Patrón Prudente. En hombres, los Patrones Cono Sur Masculino, Bebidas Azucaradas y Típico Mesurado mostraron un efecto promotor para CP. Conclusión: Resulta necesario promover una ingesta habitual de vegetales, frutas y lácteos (éstos últimos de manera moderada en hombres), y disminuir el consumo de carnes rojas (fundamentalmente grasas), carnes procesadas, vegetales amiláceos, vino y bebidas azucaradas, a fin de prevenir la ocurrencia de cáncer. En hombres se sugiere moderar la ingesta de huevos, y en mujeres la de granos refinados, productos de pastelería, aceites y mayonesa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(3): 618-628, 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cancer and its association with dietary patterns in Cordoba (Argentina)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24455^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2316^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
