<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165534</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vitamin D deficiency and morbimortality in critically ill paediatric patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the prevalence and risks factors of vitamin D deficiency, as well as its relationship with morbidity and mortality in a PICU. Material and methods An observational prospective study in a tertiary children's University Hospital PICU conducted in two phases: i: cohorts study, and ii: prevalence study. The study included 340 critically ill children with ages comprising 6 months to 16 years old. Exclusion criteria: Chronic kidney disease, known parathyroid disorders, and vitamin D supplementation. Total 25-hydroxyvitamin D [25(OH)D] was measured in the first 48 hours of admission to a PICU. Parathormone, calcium, phosphate, blood gases, blood count, C-reactive protein, and procalcitonin were also analysed. A record was also made of demographic features, characteristics of the episode, and complications during the PICU stay. Results: The overall prevalence rate of vitamin D deficiency was 43.8%, with a mean of 22.28 (95% CI 21.15&#150;23.41) ng/ml. Patients with vitamin D deficiency were older (61 vs 47 months, P=.039), had parents with a higher level of academic studies (36.5% vs 20%, P=.016), were admitted more often in winter and spring, had a higher PRISM-III (6.8 vs 5.1, P=.037), a longer PICU stay (3 vs 2 days, P=.001), and higher morbidity (61.1% vs 30.4%, P&lt; 001) than the patients with sufficient levels of 25(OH)D. Patients who died had lower levels of 25(OH)D (14 ± 8.81ng/ml versus 22.53 ± 10.53ng/ml, P=.012). Adjusted OR for morbidity was 5.44 (95%CI; 2.5-11.6). Conclusions: Vitamin D deficiency is frequent in critically ill children, and it is related to both morbidity and mortality, although it remains unclear whether it is a causal relationship or it is simply a marker of severity in different clinical situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Soler, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Martínez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Camacho, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Milano-Manso, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lillo-Muñoz, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar la prevalencia y factores de riesgo del déficit de vitamina D (VDD) en una unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátricos (UCIP), así como su relación con la morbimortalidad durante el ingreso. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional prospectivo realizado en la UCIP de un hospital terciario en 2 fases: i: estudio de cohortes, y ii: estudio de prevalencia. Se incluyó a 340 niños &gt; 6 meses, excluyendo a aquellos con enfermedad renal crónica, trastornos paratiroideos y suplementación con vitamina D. Se realizó medición de 25-hidroxivitamina D total (25[OH]D) en las primeras 48 h del ingreso, parathormona (PTH), calcio, fósforo, gasometría venosa, hemograma, proteína C reactiva y procalcitonina. Se registraron datos sociodemográficos, características del episodio y complicaciones. Resultados: La prevalencia de VDD (&lt; 20ng/ml) fue del 43,8%, con media de 22,28 (IC del 95%, 21,15-23,41) ng/ml. Los pacientes con déficit fueron de mayor edad (61 vs. 47 meses, p = 0,039), sus padres tenían un mayor nivel académico (36,5% vs. 20%, p = 0,016), ingresaron más frecuentemente en invierno y primavera, obtuvieron mayor puntuación PRISM-III (6,8 vs. 5,1, p = 0,037), mayor estancia (3 vs. 2 días, p = 0,001) y morbilidad (61,1% vs. 30,4%, p&lt;0,001) que los pacientes con niveles suficientes (&amp;#8805; 20ng/ml). Los pacientes fallecidos tuvieron niveles inferiores de 25(OH)D (14 ± 8,81ng/ml vs. 22,53 ± 10,53ng/ml, p = 0,012). La OR ajustada para la morbilidad fue 5,44 (IC del 95%, 2,5-11,6). Conclusiones: El VDD es frecuente en pacientes críticos pediátricos y está relacionado con la morbimortalidad en UCIP, aunque queda por esclarecer si se trata de una relación causal o es simplemente un marcador de gravedad en diferentes situaciones clínicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);87(2): 95-103, ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165534</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Déficit de vitamina D y morbimortalidad en pacientes críticos pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24213^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32030^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
