<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168598</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of encephalopathy by means of valproic acid with carglumic acid: two case reports and a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Valproic acid (VPA) is a drug mainly used to treat epilepsy. Hyperammonaemic encephalopathy due to VPA is a rare but serious complication. The mechanism by which VPA influences the increase in ammonia consists in blocking the urea cycle, thereby inhibiting N-acetylglutamate synthase and diminishing acetyl coenzyme A. Generally, the treatment employed has been to withdraw VPA and to administer arginine, carnitine, antibiotics, glucose and protein restriction. Previous experience with carglumic acid is limited to reports of isolated cases of paediatric patients. Case reports. We report the cases of two adult patients with encephalopathy due to VPA who were treated with carglumic acid, in addition to the conventional measures. Following treatment with the drug, ammonia levels can be seen to return to normal values. In one of the two cases, owing to the existence of another cause of encephalopathy, no clinical improvementwas observed. Conclusions. From the biochemical point of view, treating encephalopathy due to VPA with carglumic acid is a logical step, as it reverses the blockage of the urea cycle conditioned by VPA. The mechanism proposed as being the one by which brain toxicity and, therefore, encephalopathy are produced is the passage of ammonia in the form of glutamine to the inside of the cell, which then returns to ammonia and glutamate in the mitochondria and leads to oxidative stress. Carglumic acid must be considered an important part of the treatment in adult patients with hyperammonaemic encephalopathy due to VPA, although a randomised clinical trial needs to be conducted with the drug in order to test its efficacy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roiz-Rey, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Álvarez-Mediavilla, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceberio-Hualde, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nava-Mateos, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrián-Novella, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Del Olmo, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El ácido valproico (VPA) es un fármaco principalmente usado en la epilepsia. La encefalopatía hiperamoniémica por VPA es una complicación grave e infrecuente. El mecanismo por el que el VPA influye en la elevación del amonio es bloqueando el ciclo de la urea, inhibiendo la N-acetilglutamato sintasa y disminuyendo la acetil coenzima A. De forma general, el tratamiento que se ha empleado ha sido la suspensión del VPA y la administración de arginina, carnitina, antibióticos, glucosa y restricción proteica. La experiencia con ácido carbaglúmico se limita a comunicaciones de casos aislados de pacientes pediátricos. Casos clínicos. Descripción de dos casos de pacientes adultos con encefalopatía por VPA tratados, además de las medidas convencionales, con ácido carbaglúmico. Tras el tratamiento con el fármaco se aprecia una normalización de los niveles de amonio. En uno de los casos, al existir otra causa de encefalopatía, no se apreció mejora clínica. Conclusiones. Desde el punto de vista bioquímico es lógico tratar la encefalopatía por VPA con ácido carbaglúmico, ya que revierte el bloqueo del ciclo de la urea condicionado por el VPA. El mecanismo propuesto por el que se produce la toxicidad cerebral y, por tanto, la encefalopatía, es el paso de amonio en forma de glutamina al interior celular, que retorna a amonio y glutamato en la mitocondria y genera estrés oxidativo. El ácido carbaglúmico ha de considerarse como parte importante del tratamiento en pacientes adultos con encefalopatía hiperamoniémica por VPA, aunque es necesario realizar un ensayo clínico aleatorizado con el fármaco para comprobar su eficacia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;65(9): 409-414, 1 nov., 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168598</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la encefalopatía por ácido valproico con ácido carbaglúmico: descripción de dos casos y revisión de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19127^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35317</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2372^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6114^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
