<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147250</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Delirium: etiology and pathophysiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The physiopathology of delirium has still not been characterized in depth, although this entity can be defined as a functional brain disorder provoked by one or multiple organic causes that display a common clinical syndrome. Certain specific brain regions that are involved in delirium have been identified, such as the prefrontal cortex, the thalamus and the basal ganglia, especially in the nondominant hemisphere. Functional changes occur in a large number of neurotransmitters: the most frequent and best characterized are a reduction of cholinergic function and an increase in dopaminergic and gabaergic function, although alterations in almost all neurotransmitter systems (serotoninergic, noradrenergic, glutaminergic, histaminergic) have been found. Inflammation also seems to play an important role, at least in some types of delirium. Delirium in the elderly typically has a multifactorial etiology, with several simultaneous or sequential causes. Numerous risk factors have been described, both predisposing individuals to delirium and triggering this syndrome. Knowledge of these factors and their interactions is of great clinical importance and consequently etiologic diagnosis should be based on a multifactorial model (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cruz Jentoft, Alfonso J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veiga Fernández, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fisiopatología del delirium no se conoce aún en profundidad, aunque puede definirse como un trastorno funcional cerebral causado por una o múltiples causas orgánicas que manifiestan un cuadro clínico común. Se han identificado algunas regiones cerebrales específicas que intervienen en el delirium, como el córtex prefrontal, el tálamo y los ganglios basales, sobre todo del hemisferio no dominante. Existen cambios funcionales en un gran número de neurotransmisores: los más frecuentes y mejor estudiados son la disminución de la función colinérgica y el aumento de la dopaminérgica y gabaérgica, pero se han encontrado alteraciones en casi todos los sistemas neurotransmisores (serotoninérgico, noradrenérgico, glutaminérgico, histaminérgico). La inflamación parece también desempeñar un papel relevante, al menos en algunos tipos de delirium. El delirium en los mayores es típicamente de etiología multifactorial, con varias causas simultáneas o secuenciales. Se han descrito numerosos factores de riesgo, tanto predisponentes a presentar un delirium como precipitantes de éste. El conocimiento de estos factores y sus interacciones es de gran relevancia clínica, por lo que el diagnóstico etiológico debe basarse en un modelo multifactorial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);43(supl.3): 4-12, dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147250</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiología y fisiopatología del delirium</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
