<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050098</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gycolytic metabolism in basketball players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The basketball from an energetic point of view, is classified in 15 % aerobic (Fox y Mathews 1984), Dalmonte (1987), reported the major role of lactic metabolism during competition in 20 %. But there is a few studies to evaluate glycolytic metabolism during competition, and a few scientific evidence with young players. Objetive: To measure the glycolitic metabolism during the matches by plasmatic lactate concentration and study differences between periods and positions. Metodology: 15 internacional male basketball players participated in this study. Blood lactate testing was performed pre, per and post competition. Results: Our data present (3.92 mMol/l), the highest value was (5.30 mMol/l). There are significant differences between periods and there is not relation between playing time and (LA). Conclusion: The glycolytic metabolism, aerobic and anaerobic can be useful information to know the metabolic responses during the games, nutritional strategies and fatigue/recovery relation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lekue, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terrados, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leibar, X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El baloncesto desde un punto de vista energético, es clasificado en un 15 % aeróbico (Fox y Mathews 1984). Dalmonte (1987), justifica la importancia del metabolismo láctico en competición en 20 %. Sin embargo hay pocos estudios que evalúen la intervención de la glucólisis durante los partidos, además, sólo algunos de ellos utilizan jugadores jóvenes. Objetivo: Valorar el metabolismo glucolítico, mediante análisis de lactato plasmático durante la competición y estudiar su cinética en función del tiempo y puesto. Metodología: A 15 jugadores internacionales junior se les realizó muestras antes, durante y después del partido. Resultados: Los datos de concentración de lactato (LA) final son cercanos a 4 mmol/ (3,92 mMol/l), siendo el más alto de (5,30 mMol/l). Existen diferencias significativas entre períodos de juego, así como del base con respecto a los demás. No hemos observado relación entre el tiempo de juego y la concentración de lactato. Conclusión: El uso del metabolismo glucolítico, tanto aeróbico como anaeróbico, parece tener una importancia, en el baloncesto de alto nivel, mayor de la que se pensaba hasta ahora. Su estudio puede aportar información práctica para ajustar cargas de entrenamiento, conocer la situación metabólica durante el juego y diseño de estrategias nutricionales y de recuperación de la fatiga</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(6): 308-316, nov. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050098</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio del metabolismo glucolítico en jugadores de baloncesto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32981^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6161^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
