<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105560</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Secondary effects of antipsychotic treatment in naive or quasi-naive children and adolescents: Design of a follow-up protocol and baseline results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The prescribing of anti-psychotic drugs has become a normal clinical practice. Methods. This article presents a longitudinal, multicentre 12-months-long study conducted on 266 children and adolescents who were prescribed a first or second generation antipsychotic drug for the first time, and the baseline results of the study. The follow-up protocol had its purpose to detect the possible appearance of metabolic, cardiological, and motor changes. Results. When the presence of side effects was evaluated using the UKU (clinical side-effects scale) statistically significant differences were found between naïve (patients who had never taken an anti-psychotic drug) and quasi-naïve patients (those who have taken anti-psychotic drugs for a period of less than 30 days), with a greater number of the latter showing symptoms of: anxiety/laxity/tiredness (P=0.0049), drowsiness/sedation (P&lt;0.001), increase in dream duration (P&lt;0.001), increase in dreams (P=0.0199), emotional indifference (P=0.0194), hypokinesia/akinesia (P=0.0224), paresthesias (P=0.0049), accommodation disorder (P=0.0254), increase in salivation (P&lt;0.001), polyuria/polydipsia (P=0.0076), increase in sweating (P=0.0076), increase in sexual desire (P=0.0117), decrease in sexual desire (P=0.0053), tension headaches (P=0.0405). When the presence of extrapyramidal symptoms was assessed using the MPRC-IMS (Maryland Psychiatry Research Center-Involuntary Movement Scale), it was observed that the quasi-naïve patients had a statistically higher number of dyskinesia (P=0.002), Parkinsonism (P=0.0004) and akathisia (P=0.0437) symptoms compared to the naïve patients. Conclusions. These results show that, in the childhood&#150;adolescent population, the presence of secondary effects begins to be observed from the first dose of the antipsychotic drug(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tapia, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alda, José Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bailón, Concha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Escalona, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arango, Celso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Cantarero, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merchán-Naranjo, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morer, Astrid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baeza, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nestares, Patricia Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La prescripción de fármacos antipsicóticos en niños y adolescentes se ha convertido en una práctica habitual. Métodos. Este artículo presenta el diseño de un estudio multicéntrico longitudinal a 12 meses con 266 niños y adolescentes a los que se les prescribió por primera vez un antipsicótico de primera o segunda generación y los resultados basales del estudio. El protocolo de seguimiento tuvo como finalidad detectar la posible aparición de cambios metabólicos, cardiológicos y motores. Resultados. Cuando se valoró la presencia de efectos secundarios a través de la UKU (Udvalg für Kliniske Undersogelser) se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre pacientes naïve (pacientes incluidos que nunca habían tomado antipsicótico) y quasi-naïve (aquellos que habían tomado antipsicóticos durante un periodo inferior a 30 días), mostrando un mayor número de estos últimos síntomas de: ansiedad/laxitud/fatigabilidad (p=0,0049), somnolencia/sedación (p&lt;0,001), aumento duración sueños (p&lt;0,001), aumento de sueños (p=0,0199), indiferencia emocional (p=0,0194), hipocinesia/acinesia (p=0,0224), parestesias (p=0,0049), trastorno de acomodación (p=0,0254), aumento de la salivación (p&lt;0,001), poliuria/polidipsia (p=0,0076), aumento de la sudoración (p=0,0076), aumento del deseo sexual (p=0,0117), disminución del deseo sexual (p=0,0053), cefaleas tensionales. (p=0,0405). Cuando se valoró la presencia de síntomas extrapiramidales con la MPRC-IMS (Maryland Psychiatry Research Center-Involuntary Movements Scale) se observó que los pacientes quasi-naïve presentaron un número estadísticamente superior de síntomas de discinesia (p=0,002), parkinsonismo (p=0,0004) y acatisia (p=0,0437) con respecto a los naïve. Conclusiones. Estos resultados ponen de manifiesto que en población infanto-juvenil, la presencia de efectos secundarios se comienza a observar ya desde el inicio de la toma de fármacos antipsicóticos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);5(4): 217-228, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105560</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos secundarios del tratamiento antipsicótico en niños y adolescentes naïve o quasi-naïve: diseño de un protocolo de seguimiento y resultados basales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16508^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7761^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7761^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55111^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2902^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34315^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
