<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037610</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biomolecular advances in hereditary epidermal disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years, the genes responsible for many    hereditary skin diseases have been discovered. These genes    encode different proteins that participate in the terminal differentiation    of the epidermis, so their alteration or absence    causes a keratinization disorder and/or an increase in skin    fragility. Thanks to genetic analyses, we have been able to understand    the physiopathology of numerous genodermatoses    and we have become closer to diagnosing many others. In    the not-too-distant future, biomolecular techniques may foreseeably    help us prevent and treat these processes, which include    skin diseases as serious as epidermolysis bullosa or    epidermolytic hyperkeratosis. In this article, we will study the    most recent biomolecular findings referring to keratinization    and epidermal disorders, mentioning the altered genes and/    or the defective proteins that cause them</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Martín, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>fr</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se han descubierto los genes    responsables de muchas enfermedades cutáneas hereditarias.    Estos genes codifican diversas proteínas que participan    en la diferenciación terminal de la epidermis, por lo que    su alteración o su ausencia provoca un trastorno de la queratinización    y/o un aumento de la fragilidad cutánea. Gracias a    los análisis genéticos ha sido posible comprender la fisiopatología    de numerosas genodermatosis, acercarse al diagnóstico    de otras muchas, y es previsible que, en un futuro no lejano,    las técnicas biomoleculares nos ayuden en la prevención y el    tratamiento de estos procesos, entre los que se encuentran    enfermedades cutáneas tan graves como las epidermolisis    ampollosas o la hiperqueratosis epidermolítica. En este artículo    se estudian los hallazgos biomoleculares más recientes    referidos a los trastornos de la queratinización y de la epidermis,    mencionando los genes alterados y/o las proteínas defectuosas    que los originan</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;96(4): 203-216, mayo 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances biomoleculares en los trastornos epidérmicos hereditarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7240^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28987^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7240^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2856^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22434^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29384^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29384^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30695^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7802^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24314^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30914^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4898^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4898^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4898^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28986^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29121^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9694^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
