<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154480</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body composition changes assessed by bioelectrical impedance and their associations with functional class deterioration in stable heart failure patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Heart failure (HF) patients develop important changes in body composition, but only a small number of studies have evaluated the associations between these changes and functional class deterioration in a prospective manner. Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate whether changes in bioimpedance parameters were associated with NYHA functional class deterioration over six months. Methods: A total of 275 chronic stable HF patients confirmed by echocardiography were recruited. Body composition measurements were obtained by whole body bioelectrical impedance with multiple frequency equipment (BodyStat QuadScan 4000). We evaluated functional class using the New York Heart Association (NYHA) classification at baseline and after six months. Results: According to our results, 66 (24%) subjects exhibited functional class deterioration, while 209 improved or exhibited no change. A greater proportion of patients exhibited higher extracellular water (&gt; 5%), and these patients developed hypervolemia, according to location on the resistance/reactance graph. A 5% decrease in resistance/height was associated with functional class deterioration with an OR of 1.42 (95% CI 1.01-2.0, p = 0.04). Conclusions: Body composition assessment through bioelectrical impedance exhibited a valuable performance as a marker of functional class deterioration in stable HF patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orea-Tejeda, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santillan-Díaz, Cira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Martínez, Manuel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Martínez, Lilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernal-Ceballos, Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozada-Mellado, Mariel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca (IC) desarrollan cambios importantes en la composición corporal; sin embargo, pocos estudios han evaluado prospectivamente la asociación entre estos cambios y el empeoramiento de la clase funcional en pacientes con IC crónica estable. Objetivo: el objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar si los cambios en los parámetros de la bioimpedancia estaban relacionados con el deterioro de la clase funcional de la clasificación de la New York Heart Association (NYHA) después de 6 meses. Métodos: se incluyeron 275 sujetos con IC crónica estable confirmada por ecocardiograma. Se les realizaron mediciones de composición corporal por impedancia bioeléctrica de cuerpo completo con un equipo de múltiples frecuencias BodyStat QuadScan 4000 y se determinó la clase funcional por la clasificación de la New York Heart Association (NYHA) después de seis meses. Resultados: sesenta y seis (24%) sujetos mostraron deterioro de su clase funcional y 209 la mejoraron o no cambiaron. Se encontró mayor proporción de pacientes que cuya clase funcional se deterioró, en los que aumentó &gt; 5% el agua extracelular y que desarrollaron hipervolemia de acuerdo a su localización en la gráfica resistencia/reactancia. La disminución de &gt; 5% de la resistencia/talla se asoció de forma independiente con el deterioro de la clase funcional con un OR = 1.42 (IC 95% 1.01-2.0, p = 0.04). Conclusiones: la evaluación de la composición corporal a través de bioimpedancia eléctrica en pacientes con IC es un marcador de deterioro funcional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(3): 623-628, mayo-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en la composición corporal por impedancia bioeléctrica y su asociación con el deterioro de la capacidad funcional en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca crónica estable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
