<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140902</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterization of tuberculosis cases in the foreign- and native-born population in Guipúzcoa (Spain) from 2003&#150;2007</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the sociodemographic and clinical characteristics of tuberculosis cases registered in Guipúzcoa and their management and to investigate possible differences depending on the country of origin of affected individuals. Material and methods: We performed a population-based descriptive analysis of cases diagnosed from 2003 to 2007. Cases were drawn from the surveillance system, which incorporates an active information search in distinct sources. Incidences were calculated with the populations obtained from the Basque Institute of Statistics and the Ikuspegi-Basque Immigration Observatory. Chi-squared and Fisher's exact tests were used to compare categorical variables and the Mann-Whitney U-test was used to compare means. Results: A total of 903 cases were registered, of which 94 corresponded to foreigners. During the study period, the mean incidence per 100,000 inhabitants was 86.3 for foreigners and 24.4 for native-born residents. No significant differences were found by gender, prior treatment, diagnostic delay, the microbiological tests performed or their results. Differences were found in age (foreigners were younger), contact tracing recommendation and its completion (less frequent in foreigners), treatment adherence (worse among foreigners), site of infection (more common in lymph nodes in foreigners) and risk factors (fewer chronic diseases in foreigners). Conclusions: Foreigners with tuberculosis were younger and had fewer chronic diseases than native-born individuals with tuberculosis. Study of contacts and treatment adherence were less successful among foreigners. Providing the most suitable care for each patients is essential (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Basterrechea, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Temprano, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Idígoras, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir los casos de tuberculosis registrados en Guipúzcoa en función de sus características sociodemográficas, clínicas y manejo, y estudiar si existen diferencias entre los casos según su origen. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo poblacional de casos diagnosticados entre 2003 y 2007. La fuente de datos fue el sistema de vigilancia que incorpora una búsqueda activa de información en distintas fuentes. Para el cálculo de la incidencia, las poblaciones se obtuvieron del Instituto Vasco de Estadística y el Ikuspegi-Observatorio Vasco de Inmigración. Se utilizaron las pruebas de &amp;#967;2 y exacta de Fisher para la comparación de proporciones y, la prueba U de Mann-Whitney para la comparación de medias. Resultados: Se registraron 903 casos, de los que 94 correspondían a extranjeros. La incidencia media por 100.000 habitantes fue 86,3 para los extranjeros y 24,4 para los autóctonos. No se observaron diferencias en sexo, tratamiento previo, demora diagnóstica, estudios microbiológicos realizados y resultados de éstos. Se observaron diferencias en edad (más jóvenes los extranjeros), indicación de estudio de contactos y finalización del estudio (menos en extranjeros), cumplimiento del tratamiento (peor en extranjeros), localización (más frecuente la linfática en extranjeros) y factores de riesgo (menos enfermedades crónicas en extranjeros). Conclusiones: Los casos de tuberculosis en población extranjera son más jóvenes y tienen menos patología crónica, y presentan un peor perfil en la realización del estudio de contactos y en el cumplimiento del tratamiento que los autóctonos. Es indispensable buscar los recursos asistenciales más adaptados a cada caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(supl.1): 74-79, dic. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de los casos de tuberculosis en población autóctona y extranjera de Guipúzcoa en el período 2003&#150;2007</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8022^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d354^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d999^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1215^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28442</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
