<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14009</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Problem gambling in Secondary school students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study we analized the problem gambling prevalence in a representative sample of 2,790 students of secondary education from Galicia (14-21 years).The SOGS-RA questionnaire (Winters et al., 1993) was used to assess problem and at risk gambling behavior. It was found that 86.1% were not gamblers, 8.2% at risk gamblers, and 5.6% problem gamblers. There were significant differences among problem gamblers group and the other two groups in the amount of money spent on gambling, perception of parental gambling, school drop-out, and the relation between young people and their parents. In the problem gamblers group, 10.4% were men and 1.6% were women. There was a decrease of gambling with age (6% for 14-17 years, and 4.6% for 18-21 years). These data showed the high prevalence of the problem gambling and the need to introduce preventive programs for gambling in order to diminish the number of problem gamblers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Míguez Varela, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez González, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becoña Iglesias, Elisardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analiza la prevalencia del juego problema en una muestra representativa de 2.970 estudiantes de enseñanza secundaria de Galia (14-21 años). Se utilizó el cuestionario SOGS-RA de winters et al. (1993) que evalúa las personas que son jugadores problema (los que tienen la mayor probabilidad de tener problemas de juego) y jugadores en riesgo. Se encontró que el 86.1 por ciento no tenía problemas de juego, un 8.2 por ciento eran jugadores en riesgo, y un 5.6 por ciento eran jugadores problema. Se hallaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los jugadores problemas y los otros grupos en gasto en juego, percepción de la conducta de juego en sus padres, fracaso en los estudios y relación con los padres. En los jugadores problema, el 10.4 por ciento eran hombres y el 1.6 por ciento mujeres. Hay una disminución del juego problema con la edad (6 por ciento de 14-17 años y 4.6 por ciento de 18-21 años). Estos datos indican la alta prevalencia de este problema, la necesidad de conocerlo más profundamente y de implantar programas de prevención para reducir el elevado número de jugadores problema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(4): 551-556, nov. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El juego problema en los estudiantes de Enseñanza Secundaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13323^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
