<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91010</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multicentric study of the care quality perceived by patients on haemodialysis programme in Tarragona</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">New technologies have optimized renal replacement therapy. However, our interest is focused on finding out the patient&#146;s opinion of the care received at Haemodialysis (HD) Units, in order to improve the healthcare. The aim of the study is to determine the care quality perceived by the user in the Haemodialysis Units in the province of Tarragona. It is sought to survey patients of the HD centres in the province of Tarragona with Chronic Renal Insufficiency who wish to participate in the study. The modified SERVQHOS survey and the Likert scale are used to determine the user Satisfaction Index. We have weighted the results using two different methods: correlation and Weighting of the patient to determine which is more reliable. The data were processed using the SPSS-15 programme for Windows. According to the results obtained, Overall Patient Satisfaction is 4.3 out of 5 (very satisfied) Cronbach&#146;s alpha 0.90. The items on the survey that are most important to patients are (p&lt;0.05) Staff&#146;s willingness to help, Staff&#146;s interest in solving problems, The confidence and assurance conveyed by staff, The friendliness of staff, How well-trained staff are, The personalized way patients are treated, and Nursing staff&#146;s interest. The Weighted Satisfaction Indices for the three centres are: Centre A: 8, Centre B: 8.6, Centre C: 8. The most satisfied users are found in centre B. We verified that patient weighting is a more reliable procedure than correlation weighting. Opportunities for improvement in care quality have been detected. Using the multivariate study we have confirmed that the Characteristics of the centre affect 8 of the Satisfaction items (2, 3, 5, 9, 13, 14, 19, 21) (p&lt;0.05). We have also found that 16 Patient Characteristics affect 18 of the Satisfaction items on the survey (p&lt;0.05) (all except 1, 10, 12). Finally, it would be interesting to carry out a qualitative study as we sense that user satisfaction may depend, to a significant extent, on the relationship of aid established with the nurse (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Bateman, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anguera Guinovart, Esperança</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las nuevas tecnologías han optimizado el trataminto renal sustitutivo, sin embargo, nuestro interés se centra en conocer la opinión del paciente sobre los cuidados que recibe en las Unidades de Hemodiálisis (HD), con el fin de mejorar la asistencia sanitaria. El objetivo del estudio es determinar la calidad asistencial percibida por el usuario en las Unidades de Hemodiálisis de la provincia de Tarragona. Se pretende encuestar a los pacientes de los centros de HD de la provincia de Tarragona con Insuficiencia Renal Crónica que deseen participar en el estudio. Se utiliza la encuesta SERVQHOS modificada y la escala Likert para determinar el Índice de Satisfacción del usuario. Hemos ponderado los resultados mediante dos métodos distintos: La correlación y la Ponderación del paciente para determinar cuál es más fiable. Se realiza el tratamiento informático de los datos con el programa informático SPSS-15 para Windows. Según los resultados obtenidos, la Satisfacción Global del Paciente es de 4.3 sobre 5 (muy satisfecho) Alpha de Cronbach de 0.90. Los ítems del cuestionario que mayor importancia tienen para el paciente son (p&lt;0.05). La disposición del personal para ayudar, el interés del personal para solucionar problemas, la confianza y seguridad que el personal transmite, la amabilidad del personal, la preparación del personal, el trato personalizado que se da a los pacientes y el interés del personal de enfermería. Los Índices de Satisfacción Ponderada de los tres centros son: Centro A: 8, Centro B: 8.6, Centro C: 8. Los usuarios más satisfechos se encuentran en el centro B. Verificamos que la ponderación de paciente es un procedimiento más fiable que la ponderación por correlación. Se han detectado oportunidades de mejora de la calidad asistencial. Mediante el estudio multivariante hemos comprobado que las Características de los centros influyen en 8 de los ítems de Satisfacción (2, 3, 5, 9, 13, 14, 19, 21) (p&lt;0.05). También hemos comprobado que 16 Características de los pacientes influyen en 18 de los ítems de Satisfacción de la encuesta (p&lt;0.05) (todos excepto 1, 10, 12). Por último, sería interesante hacer un estudio de tipo cualitativo ya que intuimos que la satisfacción del usuario puede depender, en gran medida, de la relación de ayuda que se establece con la enfermera (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;14(3): 172-180, jul.-sept. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91010</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio multicéntrico sobre la calidad asistencial percibida por los pacientes en programa de hemodiálisis de Tarragona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
