<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115594</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of cross-reactive host-pathogen antibodies in patients with different stages of chronic Chagas disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Trypanosoma cruzi infection has been shown to induce humoral autoimmune responses against host antigens tissues. Particularly, antibodies cross-reacting with myocardial antigens may play a role in the development of the severe forms of chronic Chagas disease. The aim of this study was to determine the association between clinical stage of the disease and the presence of autoantibodies in patients with chronic Chagasic disease. Methods. We performed a cross-sectional study in T. cruzi-seropositive patients divided into 3 groups according to the classic classification of chronic Chagas heart of Storino et al. All participants underwent complete clinical examination and their sera were used to measure autoantibody levels. Results. All patients had detectable levels of anti-p2Beta and anti-B13 autoantibodies but none had anti-Na-K-ATPase antibodies. No association was observed between electrocardiographic conduction disturbances and autoantibody levels. Patients with chronic Chagas disease stage III had the highest levels of anti-B13 antibodies and a high risk of mortality score, showing a clear association between disease stage and this score. Conclusions. Anti-B13 antibodies were significantly higher in chronic Chagas disease stage III patients, suggesting that these antibodies may be involved in disease progression and that they might be a useful marker of poor prognosis in terms of heart compromise. Our results also reveal an important correlation between the level of anti-B13 autoantibodies and symptomatic heart failure and/or dilated cardiomyopathy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beloscar, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcipar, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bottasso, Oscar A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nara, Takeshi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardona, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicco, Miguel H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferini, Franco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lioi, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodeles, Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bontempi, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La infección por Trypanosoma cruzi induce una respuesta autoinmunitaria humoral contra diferentes antígenos del huésped. En especial, los anticuerpos que presentan reactividad cruzada con antígenos del miocardio tienen un papel importante en el desarrollo de las formas graves de la cardiopatía chagásica crónica. En este trabajo se analiza la asociación del estadio clínico de la enfermedad con la presencia de autoanticuerpos en pacientes con cardiopatía chagásica crónica. Métodos. Estudio transversal con pacientes con serología positiva para enfermedad de Chagas, categorizados en tres grupos según la clasificación de cardiopatía chagásica de Storino et al. Se realizó a todas las personas incluidas un examen clínico completo y se usaron las muestras de suero para cuantificar los autoanticuerpos. Resultados. Todos los pacientes presentaron cantidades detectables de anti-p2Beta y anti B13; el anti-Na-K-ATPasa fue negativo en todos los casos. No se halló asociación significativa entre las alteraciones electrocardiográficas y los valores de autoanticuerpos. Los pacientes con cardiopatía chagásica en estadio III presentaron mayor concentración de anti-B13 y riesgo de mortalidad alto, lo que muestra una clara asociación entre el estadio de la enfermedad y la puntuación de mortalidad. Conclusiones. La concentración del autoanticuerpo anti-B13 fue significativamente mayor en los pacientes con cardiopatía chagásica en estadio  III , lo que indica que este anticuerpo puede estar involucrado en la progresión de la enfermedad y podría usarse como marcador de mal pronóstico respecto a la afección cardiaca. Los resultados revelan también una importante correlación entre el anti-B13 y la insuficiencia cardiaca sintomática y la cardiomiopatía dilatada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;66(10): 791-796, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115594</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de anticuerpos con reactividad cruzada patógeno-huésped en pacientes con diferentes estadios de cardiopatía chagásica crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3448^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14752^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3448^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52891^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52891^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
