<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155140</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of ventilator-associated pneumonia: a comparison of level of knowledge in three critical care units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the level of knowledge of the prevention of ventilator-associated pneumonia guidelines of nurses working in three intensive care units (ICU) in 3 university hospitals in a Spanish region, and evaluate the relationship between this level of knowledge and years worked in the ICU. Method. A descriptive, prospective, cross-sectional, multicentre study was conducted using a validated and reliable questionnaire, made up by 9 questions with closed answers drawn from the EVIDENCE study. A total of 98 questionnaires were collected from ICU nurses of the three university hospitals (A, B, and C) from January to April 2014. The sample from hospital A responded the most, in contrast with the sample from hospital B, which was the one with the less participation. The Pearson correlation was calculated in order to determine the relationship between nurse years worked in ICU and level of knowledge. Results. Hospital A obtained in the best mean score in the questionnaire, 6.33 (SD 1.4) points, followed by hospital C with 6.21 (SD 1.4), and finally, the hospital B with 6.06 (SD 1.5) points. A p=.08 was obtained on relating years worked with the level of knowledge. Conclusion. The results showed a high level of knowledge compared other studies. There was a tendency between the years worked in the unit and the level of knowledge in ventilator-associated pneumonia prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Mondéjar, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujante-Palazón, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armero-Barranco, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez-Paredes, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el grado de conocimientos de las guías de prevención de la neumonía asociada a ventilación de los profesionales de enfermería de la unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI) de tres hospitales españoles de nivel asistencial II y III y relacionar el grado de conocimiento con los años trabajados en UCI. Método. Estudio descriptivo, prospectivo, transversal, y multicéntrico. Para llevarlo a cabo, se facilitó un cuestionario validado y fiable que constaba de 9 preguntas con respuestas cerradas extraídas del estudio EVIDENCE, a los enfermeros de UCI de los tres hospitales universitarios, en el periodo comprendido entre enero y abril del 2014. Siendo la muestra del hospital A la más representativa, y por el contrario, la del B la de menor participación. Para determinar la relación entre los años trabajados en UCI de los enfermeros y el grado de conocimientos se calculó la correlación de Pearson. Resultados. Se recogieron un total de 98 cuestionarios. La mejor puntuación media de los test obtenida fue en el hospital A con una media de 6,33 puntos DE 1,4, seguida del C con 6,21 DE 1,4. Y por último, el hospital B con 6,06 DE 1,5. Al relacionar años trabajados y grado de conocimiento p=0,08. Conclusiones. Los resultados obtenidos indicaron un grado de conocimiento medio-alto comparándolo con otros estudios, y una tendencia entre los años trabajados en la unidad y el grado de conocimiento de prevención de la neumonía asociada a ventilación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;27(3): 120-128, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de neumonía asociada a ventilación mecánica, comparación de conocimientos entre tres unidades de críticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15097^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
