<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056616</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Concepts, confusions and contradictions on the impact factor in Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Latin American scientists are making tremendous efforts    to conduct good-quality research worthy of being published    internationally. However, Colciencias, an entity created to    support this research in Colombia, introduced scienciometric    evaluations which had been re-evaluated elsewhere some time    ago, based on measurements of aspects such as the ill-termed    &#147;impact factor&#148;. Even more serious is that the aforementioned    government office is unaware that measures are based on    debated mathematical principles, placing Colombian science    at imminent risk of suffering from an academic yatrogeny of    irreparable consequences. Therefore, an urgent restructuring    of the way in which Colombia&#146;s scientific production is to be    evaluated is thus mandatory before these measures have a    negative impact thereon</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leon-S, Martha E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leon-Sarmiento, Fidias E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayona-Prieto, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los esfuerzos que realizan los científicos latinoamericanos    para desarrollar investigaciones de calidad, dignas de ser    publicadas a nivel internacional son enormes. Sin embargo,    Colciencias, ente creado para apoyar dichas investigaciones    en Colombia, introdujo evaluaciones cienciométricas revaluadas    hace tiempo en otras latitudes, basándose entre otras    medidas en aspectos como el mal llamado factor de impacto.    Más grave aún es que dicha entidad gubernamental desconoce    que tales medidas se basan en principios matemáticos discutidos,    poniendo así a la ciencia colombiana en riesgo inminente    de padecer una iatrogenia académica de irreparables    consecuencias. Por tal razón, una reestructuración urgente de    la forma como se debe evaluar la producción científica colombiana    se hace mandatoria, antes de que estas medidas terminen    afectando aún más la apenas incipiente materialización    de las investigaciones científicas en Colombia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;81(2): 147-154, mar.-abr.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concepciones, confusiones y contradicciones del factor de impacto en Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
