<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155650</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The dialogue between medical doctors and bioethicists: rethinking experience to improve medical education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">More and more seems to be necessary to find new ways of communication between medical doctors and bioethicists in order to build a shared vocabulary and to prevent conflicts: many bioethical problems seem to be caused by the lack of dialogue between them, which both seem to speak two different languages. Improving this dialogue means searching new languages and innovative forms of communication: the narration could be a really effective tool to enhance the physicians&#146; and bioethicist&#146;s moral conscience, since it facilitates reasoning on someone&#146;s particular experience, and, ultimately, on our experience. Starting from the results of a questionnaire administered to a group of students of the Faculty of Medicine and Surgery of the University Campus Bio-Medico we present a theoretical discussion about the need for more dialogue and for a shared vocabulary in medical experiences. In this regard, we suggest as a possible solution to the conflicts among medical doctors and bioethicists, an educational strategy, i.e., humanities courses for medical students, which may help them to deeply describe their practical present (and future) experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valera, Luca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Russo, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Curcio, Giuseppe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cada vez más parece ser necesario encontrar nuevas formas de comunicación entre los médicos y los bioeticistas con el fin de construir un vocabulario común para evitar conflictos: muchos problemas bioéticos se deben a la falta de diálogo entre ellos, ya que ambos parecen hablar idiomas diferentes. Mejorar este diálogo significa buscar nuevos lenguajes y formas innovadoras de comunicación: la narración podría constituir un instrumento muy eficaz para mejorar la conciencia moral de los médicos y de los bioeticistas, dado que facilita el razonamiento sobre la experiencia de una persona en particular, y, en último término, sobre nuestra experiencia. A partir de los resultados de un cuestionario administrado a un grupo de estudiantes de la Facultad de Medicina y Cirugía de la Universidad Campus Bio-Médico presentamos una discusión teórica sobre la necesidad de un mayor diálogo y de un vocabulario común con referencia a las experiencias médicas. En este sentido, sugerimos como posible solución a los conflictos entre médicos y bioeticistas una estrategia educativa, es decir, cursos de humanidades para estudiantes de medicina, que pueden ayudarlos a describir profundamente sus experiencias prácticas presentes (y futuras) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;27(90): 163-173, mayo-ago. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155650</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El diálogo entre los médicos y los bioeticistas: repensar la experiencia para mejorar la educación médica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7564</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
