<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105203</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Needs of the family in the intensive care units: a review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AbstractAdmission to the Intensive Care Units (ICU) is perceived by both patients and their family as a stressful experience. This situation can cause shock, skepticism and anxiety in the patient's setting.ObjectiveTo analyze and present the needs of the family members of the critical patient.MethodologyA review was made of the literature in the following data bases: Pubmed, CINAHL, Cuiden and Cochrane Library. Furthermore, three journals specialized in Intensive Cares were reviewed.ResultsAfter including the articles that met the screening criteria, 30 articles were finally selected. Of these, 11 were reviews of the literature, 7 qualitative studies and 12 more were quantitative investigations. Four groups of needs in the families were identified after the analysis of these articles, these being cognitive, emotional, social and practical.DiscussionOne of the main needs of the family is to receive better information from the professionals followed by the need for closeness with the ill family member. This review proposes that, in order to cover these needs, the information should be protocolized and the visiting hours should be made flexible. Furthermore, incorporation of two familial evaluation tools, the genogram and ecomap, is proposed.ConclusionsThis work has revealed the importance of having the Intensive Care nurses identify the needs of the family during the admission of the patient in the ICU in order to be able to provide help, support and counseling care that relieves the suffering of the families (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardavila Belio, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivar, C. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ResumenEl ingreso en las Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI) es percibido, tanto por los pacientes como por los familiares, como una vivencia estresante. Esta situación puede provocar que el entorno del paciente experimente shock, incredulidad y ansiedad.ObjetivoAnalizar y presentar las necesidades de las familias del paciente crítico.MetodologíaSe realizó una revisión de la literatura en las bases de datos de Pubmed, CINAHL, Cuiden y la Cochrane Library. Asimismo, se revisaron tres revistas especializadas en Cuidados Intensivos.ResultadosTras incluir los artículos que cumplían los criterios de selección, se seleccionaron finalmente 30 artículos de los cuales 11 eran revisiones de la literatura, 7 eran estudios cualitativos y los otros 12 eran investigaciones cuantitativas. Del análisis de estos artículos se identificaron cuatro grupos de necesidades en las familias: cognitiva, emocional, social y práctica.DiscusiónUna de las principales necesidades de la familia es recibir mayor información por parte de los profesionales seguida de la necesidad de proximidad con su familiar enfermo. Esta revisión propone que para cubrir estas necesidades se protocolice la información y se flexibilice el horario de visitas. Además, se propone la incorporación de dos herramientas de valoración familiar: el genograma y el ecomapa.ConclusionesEste trabajo revela la importancia de que las enfermeras de Cuidados Intensivos identifiquen las necesidades que presenta la familia durante el ingreso del paciente en UCI para poder así prestar una atención de ayuda, apoyo y asesoramiento que alivie el sufrimiento de los familiares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;23(2): 51-67, abr. -jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105203</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidades de la familia en las unidades de cuidados intensivos. Revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
