<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146370</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peripherally inserted central venous catheter through drum system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It described a one lumen central venous catheter peripherally inserted drum system whose insertion into the vein is performed through a plastic splittable cannula by braunula technique. The braunula technique is particularly important in certain urgent or emergency situations, where speed and aseptic conditions of which the procedure is performed represent a further improvement over other insertion techniques. The catheter mantains the advantages, in terms of easy placement, that all devices equipped with a drum system have but at the same time eliminates the complications presented by other similar catheters whose insertion to the venous circulation used to be performed through a needle. These catheters allow quick, simple and safe access to the central venous circulation and reduce risks associated with the procedure, improving patient safety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salas Campos, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe un catéter venoso central de una luz de inserción periférica con sistema tambor cuya introducción en el interior de la vena se realiza a través de una cánula plástica pelable mediante técnica braunula. La técnica braunula adquiere una especial importancia en determinadas situaciones de urgencia o emergencia, en donde la rapidez y asepsia con las que se realiza el procedimiento suponen una mejora adicional frente a otras técnicas de inserción. El catéter mantiene todas las ventajas, en cuanto a facilidad de colocación, que poseen los dispositivos dotados de tambor, y elimina las complicaciones que presentan otros catéteres de características similares en los que el paso del catéter a la circulación venosa se realizaba a través de una aguja. Estos catéteres posibilitan el acceso rápido, sencillo y seguro a la circulación central y reducen riesgos relacionados con el procedimiento, lo que mejora la seguridad del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(11): 729-734, nov. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146370</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Catéter venoso central de inserción periférica con sistema de tambor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55073^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24885^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55073^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55073^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29751^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
