<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76386</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vibrato is one of the most frequent ornamentations of western classicalsong, and of certain types of instrumental music. Physically speaking,vocal vibrato is a periodic sinusoidal modulation of the fundamentalfrequency of phonation.Vibrato makes the voice sound pleasant, lively, exciting, warm and lessmechanical than when a flat pitch is used. It makes the voice soundnatural and expressive. Most singers regard it as desirable, but not allare capable of developing it. It would seem that vibrato can only bedeveloped at a certain technical level. Historical considerations arereviewed, and the physical, acoustic and aerodynamic properties ofvibrato are discussed. Hypotheses are advanced regarding its origin,and strategies are described which facilitate its acquisition anddevelopment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández González, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués Girbau, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Tapia Urrutia, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruba San Miguel, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uzcanga Lacabe, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El vibrato es uno de los ornamentos más comunes del canto clásicooccidental y de la música destinada a aquellos instrumentos que puedenproducirlo. El vibrato vocal corresponde físicamente a una modulaciónperiódica sinusoidal de frecuencia fundamental de la fonación.El vibrato hace que la voz suene agradable, viva, excitante, cálida, menosmecánica que aquella que se consigue al emitir un tono plano. Da naturalidady expresividad al sonido vocal. La mayoría de los cantantes loconsideran un elemento deseable pero no todos son capaces de desarrollarlo.Parece que la aparición del vibrato depende de un nivel técnicodeterminado. Se revisan las consideraciones históricas, las propiedadesfísicas, acústicas y aerodinámicas del vibrato. Se establecenhipótesis en lo referente a su origen y se plantean estrategias dirigidas afacilitar su desarrollo y aprendizaje(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Med Univ Navarra;50(3): 65-72, jul.-sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vibrato de la voz cantada. Caracterización acústica y bases fisiológicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15235^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10894^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15233^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
