<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60288</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A genetic-behavioral alternative to the personality disorders: the Livesley dimensional model</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the personality disorder section of the DSM-V research agenda, the authors stress the need for studies on the relevance of a change from diagnostic categorical models to dimensional ones. These studies should identify the underlying genetic and neurobiologic mechanisms and appropriate representation on the dimensions of clinical criteria as cognitive disturbances, identity conflicts and attachment. Livesley&#146;s behavioral-genetic model represents an interesting dimensional paradigm of personality pathology. It was elaborated deductively from the consensus and statistical refinement of data collected by a large number of clinicians from different psychopathological tendencies. The traits are made operative in the «Dimensional Assessment of Personality Pathology-Basic Questionnaire»(DAPP-BQ) tool with 18 dimensions (that became 30) and4 higher rank factors (adapted to Spanish by Gutiérrez-Zotes et al, 2008). The model has shown an appropriate relationship with important personality paradigms and good predictive power for personality disorders. The authors incorporate methods of variance breakdown for statistical processing of the genetic-environmental mechanism underlying each personality disorder dimension. Homologation of DSM-IV-TR criteria for personality disorders is proposed so that the model's dimensions capture and represent the clinical complexity of the symptoms in a convenient manner for the new location in DSM-V (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Zote, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labad, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gárriz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la agenda de investigación para el DSM-V, sección de los trastornos de la personalidad, se enfatiza la necesidad de estudios sobre la pertinencia de un cambio de modelo de categorías diagnósticas por uno dimensional. Estos trabajos deberían identificar los mecanismos genéticos y neurobiológicos subyacentes así como la adecuada representación, en las dimensiones, de criterios clínicos como las alteraciones cognitivas, los conflictos de la identidad y del vínculo. El modelo genético conductual de Livesley se constituye como un interesante paradigma dimensional de la patología de la personalidad. Ha sido elaborado de forma inductiva a partir del consenso y depuración estadística de un gran número de clínicos de diferentes corrientes psicopatológicas. Los rasgos se operativizan en el instrumento «Valoración Dimensional de la Personalidad Patológica-Cuestionario Básico» (DAPPBQ) con 18 dimensiones (posteriormente 30) y cuatro factores de rango superior (adaptado al español por Gutiérrez-Zotes et al., 2008). El modelo ha demostrado una adecuada relación con importantes paradigmas de personalidad y buena capacidad predictiva con los trastornos de la personalidad. Los autores incorporan métodos de descomposición de la varianza para depurar el mecanismo genético y ambiental que subyace a cada dimensión de la patología de la personalidad. Se propone una homologación de los criterios DSM-IV-TR para los trastornos de la personalidad, en donde las dimensiones del modelo capturan y representan la complejidad clínica de los síntomas de forma conveniente en la nueva ubicación para el DSM-V (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(3): 174-183, mayo-jun. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una alternativa genético-conductual a los trastornos de la personalidad: el modelo dimensional de Livesley</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33529^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28405^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
