<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133344</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reccomendations for the detection, study and referral of inflammatory low-back pain in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To design a strategy for the early detection and referral of patients with possible spondyloarthritis based on recommendations developed, agreed upon, and directed to primary care physicians. Methods. We used a modified RAND/UCLA methodology plus a systematic literature review. The information was presented to a discussion group formed by rheumatologists and primary care physicians. The group studied the process map and proposed recommendations and algorithms that were subsequently submitted in two Delphi rounds to a larger group of rheumatologists and primary care physicians. The final set of recommendations was derived from the analysis of the second Delphi round. Results. We present the recommendations, along with their mean level of agreement, on the early referral of patients with possible spondyloarthritis. The panel recommends that the study of chronic low back pain in patients under 45 years be performed in four phases 1) clinical: key questions, 2) clinical: extra questions, 3) physical examination, and 4) additional tests. Conclusions. The level of agreement with these simple recommendations is high. It is necessary to design strategies for the education and sensitization from rheumatology services to maintain an optimal collaboration with primary care and to facilitate referral to rheumatology departments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juanola Roura, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Vázquez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Criado, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Villamor, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collantes Estévez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona, Loreto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gratacós Masmitja, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Yébenes, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queiro Silva, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Diseñar una estrategia de detección y derivación precoz de pacientes con posible espondiloartritis mediante el desarrollo de recomendaciones consensuadas dirigidas a los médicos de Atención Primaria (AP). Métodos. Se utilizó una metodología modificada de RAND/UCLA y revisión sistemática de la literatura. Se seleccionó un grupo de discusión formado por reumatólogos y médicos de AP. Se estudió el mapa del proceso y se propusieron recomendaciones y algoritmos que fueron sometidos a 2 rondas Delphi para evaluar el grado de aceptación y preferencia de criterios en un grupo amplio de reumatólogos y médicos de AP. Del análisis de la segunda ronda Delphi se extrajeron las recomendaciones finales. Resultados. Se presentan recomendaciones, junto con su grado medio de acuerdo, para la derivación rápida de pacientes con sospecha de espondiloartritis. En concreto, se recomienda investigar el dolor lumbar crónico en menores de 45 años en 4 fases: 1) clínica: preguntas clave; 2) clínica: preguntas extra; 3) exploración física, y 4) pruebas complementarias. Se debe derivar a Reumatología si existen: 1) dolor lumbar inflamatorio; 2) signos indicativos de espondiloartritis, o 3) HLA B27 positivo, elevación de proteína C reactiva o signos radiológicos de sacroilitis. Se incluyen recomendaciones sobre el proceso de derivación y otras adicionales. Conclusiones. El grado de acuerdo con estas sencillas recomendaciones es amplio. Es necesario diseñar estrategias de formación y sensibilización desde los servicios de Reumatología para mantener una óptima colaboración de AP en la identificación de los casos y facilitar que los servicios de Reumatología estén preparados para asumir las derivaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);11(2): 90-98, mar.-abr. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones para la detección, investigación y derivación del dolor lumbar inflamatorio en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36004^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
