<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109406</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Renal biopsies for small renal masses. For whom, when and how</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective of this manuscript is to provide an evidence-based analysis of the current status and future perspectives in kidney biopsies in small renal masses (BSRM). A PubMed search has been performed for all relevant urological literature regarding BSRM. A literature research of English, French and Spanish languages was performed using the Pubmed database from 2000 to February 2012 using the terms renal mass biopsy and renal tumor biopsy. Manuscripts providing a highest level of evidence were selected for the review. Clinical experience from author´s Institutions is also reflected in the manuscript. Considerable technical advances have been made in imaging over the last decade. The latter allow for a comprehensive sharp diagnosis of small renal masses (SRM). Therapeutic decision for SRM&#146;s is supported by objective knowledge of histological features and renal biopsy represents an accurate and safe option to particularize treatment in renal incidentalomas. Furthermore, renal biopsies are incorporated in the application and follow-up of patients undergoing ablative therapies. An important number of clinical reports have been published in the subject but there is lack of technical standardization. The available experience is limited to referral centers and there are still up to 30% of biopsies that fail to provide clear diagnosis. Renal biopsies have significantly improved in its diagnostic accuracy and it is indicated when tissue diagnosis can change the therapeutic approach of SRM´s. Meantime, the role of renal biopsies keeps on growing and limitations of the procedure are less when compared to the benefits it provides(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Validire, Pierre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galiano, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Strauss, Christiane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yap, Stanley A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stakhovskyi, Oleksandr</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Finelli, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rozet, Francois</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barret, Eric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cathelineau, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez-Salas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lenoir, Stépahane</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente manuscrito es ofrecer un análisis basado en la evidencia del estado actual y perspectivas futuras de las biopsias renales en pequeñas masas renales. Se ha realizado una búsqueda en PubMed de toda la literatura relevante sobre pequeñas masas renales. Se realizó una búsqueda de la literatura en lengua inglesa, francesa y española en la base de datos PubMed entre el 2000 y febrero del 2012 utilizando los términos biopsia de masa renal y biopsia de tumor renal. Se seleccionaron para revisión los manuscritos que ofrecían el mayor nivel de evidencia. El manuscrito también recoge en la experiencia clínica de las Instituciones de los autores. Durante la última década se han realizado considerable avances técnicos en pruebas de imagen. Esto permite un diagnostico completo y preciso de las masas renales pequeñas. La decisión terapéutica se apoya en el conocimiento objetivo de las características histológicas, y la biopsia renal representa una opción precisa y segura para el tratamiento particularizado de los incidentalomas renales. Además, las biopsias renales están incorporadas en la aplicación y el seguimiento de los pacientes sometidos a terapias ablativas. Se ha publicado un número importante de artículos clínicos sobre el tema pero falta una estandarización técnica. La experiencia disponible está limitada a centros de referencia, y todavía hay hasta un 30% de biopsias que no consiguen dar un diagnostico claro. Las biopsias renales han mejorado significativamente en su precisión diagnóstica y está indicada cuando el diagnostico tisular pueda cambiar el abordaje terapéutico de las masas renales pequeñas. Mientras tanto, el papel de las biopsias renales sigue creciendo y las limitaciones del procedimiento son menores en comparación con los beneficios que aporta(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(1): 4-15, ene.-feb. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biopsia de las masas renales pequeñas. Quien debe realizarlas, cuándo y cómo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
