<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054861</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Follow-up of patients with Hunter syndrome: the Hunter Outcome Survey (HOS) registry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hunter syndrome, or mucopolysaccharidosis type II, is an inherited disease linked to the X chromosome    that is caused by a deficit of the enzyme iduronate-2-sulfatase and its main symptoms affect the bones, neurological system and the viscera. In order to further our knowledge of its natural history, a registry containing data about patients' clinical    histories was compiled. The purpose of this review is to describe how the registry works and to present the initial data concerning Spanish patients with Hunter syndrome included in it. Development. The Hunter Outcome Survey (HOS) registry  is a multicentre, world-wide, observational, long-term follow-up study that is open to all patients diagnosed with the disease.    The registry includes clinical data and information from the complementary examinations that are commonly performed as usual practice while attending these patients. Its main aims are to describe the population of patients with the disease, to  further our knowledge of its natural history, to keep a check on the safety and effectiveness of enzyme replacement therapy in    patients who are candidates for such treatment and to create a database that makes it possible to draw up a set of guidelines    for clinical practice. Conclusions. Specific registries of low-prevalence diseases, such as the HOS registry for patients with    Hunter syndrome, are important to improve the follow-up of patients and to determine the impact of new treatments. The Spanish HOS registry is an important step forward in furthering our knowledge of the current situation of the patients registered throughout the country (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toro Riera, M. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Hunter o mucopolisacaridosis tipo II es una enfermedad de herencia ligada al cromosoma    X, que se debe al déficit del enzima iduronato-2-sulfatasa y se presenta principalmente con semiología ósea, neurológica    y visceral. Para potenciar el conocimiento de su historia natural se ha elaborado un registro que recoge datos de la historia    clínica de los pacientes. En esta revisión se da a conocer el funcionamiento del registro y los primeros datos de pacientes    españoles con síndrome de Hunter incluidos en él. Desarrollo. El registro HOS (Hunter Outcome Survey) es un instrumento    de seguimiento observacional a largo plazo, multicéntrico e internacional, abierto a todos los pacientes con la enfermedad.    El registro incluye datos clínicos y de exploraciones complementarias que se realizan en la práctica habitual durante la atención    a estos pacientes. Tiene como objetivos principales: la descripción de la población de pacientes afectada por la enfermedad,    la mejoría del conocimiento de su evolución natural, la vigilancia de la seguridad y efectividad del tratamiento de sustitución    enzimática en los pacientes candidatos a éste y la creación de una base de datos que permita la elaboración de guías    de práctica clínica. Conclusión. Los registros específicos de enfermedades de baja prevalencia, como es el caso del registro    HOS para pacientes con síndrome de Hunter, son importantes para mejorar el seguimiento de los pacientes y determinar el    impacto de nuevos tratamientos. El registro HOS español ha supuesto un avance en el conocimiento de la situación actual de    los pacientes registrados en el país (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(supl.1): s13-s17, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054861</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de pacientes con síndrome de Hunter: el registro HOS (Hunter Outcome Survey)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29956^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
