<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76347</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Indication of bone scans in early breast cancer staging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveEvaluate the indication for bone scanning during staging of early breast cancer in the light of scientific evidence to assess the need to modify practices with scant effectiveness.Material and methodsThe bone scans carried out in our Nuclear Medicine Department in 2007 on patients with primary breast cancer were reviewed retrospectively. Results were analyzed in relation to the clinical and histopathologic findings for each tumor. Bone scan results of tumors &gt;2cm y &lt;=5cm (T2) were analyzed in two groups stratified by tumor size, &lt;=3cm or &gt;3cm, and pre-treatment clinical stage.ResultsOut of 245 bone scans of patients with breast cancer, 237 (97%) were negative for metastatic disease and 8 (3%) were positive. Lesions&lt;2cm (Tis and T1) were diagnosed in 131 patients (53.5%), none of which had bone metastasis at time of diagnosis. Lesions &gt;2cm and &lt;=5cm (T2) were diagnosed in 84 patients (34%), of which 3.6% had bone metastasis. There were no differences in the rate of bone metastases in patients with stage T2 disease and lesions &lt;=3cm vs. &gt;3cm. The bone scan findings did not modify staging in any of the 66 patients with T2 tumors stage IIA, but it did modify staging in 2 of 12 patients with stage IIB tumors. Twenty percent of 15 patients with T3 tumors and 13% of patients with T4 tumors had bone metastasis at time of diagnosis.ConclusionsIneffective practices should be modified and bone scanning should not be indicated in patients with early breast cancer Tis, T1 and T2 with tumor &lt;=2cm, clinical stage IIA. Pre-treatment bone scanning is still indicated in T2 IIB, T3 and T4 disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liévano, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abós, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baringo, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colmenarejo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueva, L. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Añaños, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuerte, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosRevisar nuestra experiencia y reflexionar a la luz de la evidencia científica sobre la indicación del rastreo óseo (RO) en la estadificación del cáncer de mama de inicio en estadios precoces, con el fin de contribuir en la modificación de rutinas de baja eficacia.Material y métodosRevisión retrospectiva de los RO hechos en nuestro Servicio de Medicina Nuclear durante 2007 en las pacientes con cáncer de mama de inicio, analizando su resultado en función del tamaño clínico o anatomopatológico tumoral. Los RO para tumores T2 se analizaron estratificando las lesiones en dos grupos, &lt;= o &gt; de 3cm y en función de su estadio clínico pretratamiento.ResultadosSe incluyeron 245 rastreos, 237 de éstos (97%) fueron negativos y 8 de éstos (3%) fueron positivos para metástasis óseas. En 131 pacientes (53,5%) se diagnosticaron lesiones&lt;2cm (Tis y T1) y ninguna tenía metástasis óseas. Se hallaron 84 lesiones (34%) que eran &gt;2cm y &lt;=5cm (T2) y entre éstas, el 3,6% de las pacientes presentó metástasis óseas, sin diferencias entre lesiones &lt;=3cm y &gt;3cm. El RO no modificó el estadio en ninguna de las 66 pacientes con tumores T2 en estadio IIA clínico, mientras que sí lo hizo en 2 de las 12 pacientes en estadio clínico IIB. El 20% de las 15 pacientes con lesiones T3 y el 13% de las 15 pacientes con T4 presentaron metástasis óseas en el diagnóstico.ConclusionesEs necesario modificar rutinas poco eficientes excluyendo de las indicaciones del RO la estadificación de las neoplasias de mama de inicio con lesiones &lt;=2cm y lesiones en estadio clínico IIA, siendo necesaria su realización previa al tratamiento en el resto de los casos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;28(6): 273-277, nov.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76347</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicación del rastreo óseo en la estadificación del cáncer de mama de inicio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13434^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31274^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
