<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85324</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of Anxiety and Depressive Disorders in University Students: Associated Academic and Socio-Family Factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The high frequency of anxiety and depression in university students is related to social and family factors, as well as academic stress. The goal of this paper is to analyze the prevalence of anxiety and depressive disorders and associated academic and social-family factors. A research was carried out on 700 students who were administered the Goldberg&#146;s Anxiety and Depression Scale. Variables assessing a myriad of stressful situations related to socio-family and academic factors were used. Results, 47.1% of the students suffered from  anxiety disorders and 55.6% suffered from depressive anxiety. In the multivariate analysis, females showed a higher level of anxiety (OR: 2.30 IC 955 1.65-3.19) and depression (OR: 1.98 IC 95% 1.43-2.76) &#150;they are students who commute on a daily basis and have other extra-academic duties, resulting in higher risk in law and business students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales Moreno, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balanza Galindo, Serafín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Muñoz, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La elevada frecuencia de ansiedad y depresión en estudiantes universitarios está relacionada con factores sociales, familiares y por el estrés académico. El objetivo es analizar la prevalencia de trastornos de ansiedad y depresión y factores académicos y sociofamiliares asociados. El estudio se realizó en una muestra de 700 alumnos, aplicando la Escala de Ansiedad y Depresión de Goldberg (EADG). Como factores de estudio se utilizaron variables que medían diversas situaciones estresantes relacionadas con factores sociofamiliares y académicos. El 47,1% de los estudiantes sufrían trastornos de ansiedad y el 55,6%  depresión. En el análisis multivariante, el sexo femenino son quienes presentan mayor riesgo de ansiedad (OR: 2,30 IC 955 1,65-3,19) y de depresión (OR.: 1,98 IC 95% 1,43 -2,76), son estudiantes que realizan largos desplazamientos diarios y tienen otras obligaciones extra académicas, suponiendo mayor riesgo en estudiantes de ciencias jurídicas y de la empresa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;20(2): 177-187, jul. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de Ansiedad y Depresión en una Población de Estudiantes Universitarios: Factores Académicos y Sociofamiliares Asociados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
