<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99976</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contribution of diffusion tensor magnetic resonance imaging to the diagnosis of focal cortical dysplasias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Focal cortical dysplasias (FCD) are cortical malformations and, although they display typical characteristicsin conventional magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), the precise determination of the epileptogenic zone remains a controversial issue. The less favourable progress during the post-operative period with respect to other symptomaticepilepsies could be explained by the existence of epileptogenic areas that do not show up in conventional MRI. Diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) is sensitive to subtle  icrostructural abnormalities, and fractional anisotropy, which is an indirectindicator, shows areas with reductions in the underlying white matter that go beyond the alterations detected withconventional MRI in isolated cases in previous works. Aim. In this study we analyse the characteristics of fractional anisotropy in a series of patients with FCD in order to evaluatethe contribution made to diagnosis by MRI by DTI. Subjects and methods. Twenty-one controls and eleven patients with FCD that was visible in MRI were scanned, andclinical and imaging variables were both recorded. A visual analysis of the fractional anisotropy maps was conducted to search for asymmetries between hemispheres and biases in the clinical or structural MRI data. Results. Two females and nine males, aged 30 ± 9.7 years took part in the study; time to progression of epilepsy: 22 ± 9.3 years; average frequency of the seizures: 3/month (range: 0.16-8/month). All of them showed inter-hemispheric asymmetries, which went beyond the structural limits of FCD in the case of 10 of the patients (90%). None of the controlsdisplayed asymmetries in the fractional anisotropy. No significant relation was found with the variables that were compared.Conclusions. Further studies need to be conducted with larger numbers of patients in order to evaluate the usefulness of DTI in defining the location and extension of the epileptogenic zone in this population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bienkmann, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kocher, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kauffman, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Consalvo, Damián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selfer, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Princich, Juan P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las displasias corticales focales (DCF) son malformaciones corticales y, aunque evidencian característicastípicas en la resonancia magnética (RM) convencional, la determinación precisa de la zona epileptógena es controvertida. La evolución postoperatoria menos favorable con respecto a otras epilepsias sintomáticas se explicaría mediante la existencia de áreas epileptógenas no visibles en la RM convencional. Las imágenes por tensor de difusión (DTI) son sensibles a anomalías microestructurales sutiles, y la anisotropía fraccional, un indicador indirecto, demuestra áreas de reducción en la sustancia blanca subyacente a las DCF, excediendo las alteraciones detectadas con la RM convencional en casosaislados de trabajos previos.Objetivo. Analizar las  características de la anisotropía fraccional en una serie de pacientes con DCF, para evaluar la contribución diagnóstica de la RM por DTI. Sujetos y métodos. Se escanearon 21 controles y 11 pacientes con DCF visible en la RM, con registro de variables clínicas eimaginológicas. Se realizó un análisis visual de los mapas de anisotropía fraccional en busca de asimetrías entre hemisferios,sesgado a los datos clínicos o de RM estructural. Resultados. Dos mujeres y nueve varones, de 30,0 ± 9,7 años de edad; tiempo de evolución de la epilepsia: 22,0 ± 9,3años; frecuencia promedio de las crisis: 3/mes (rango: 0,16-8/mes). Todos evidenciaron asimetrías interhemisféricas, en 10 pacientes (90%) excediendo los límites estructurales de la DCF. Ninguno de los controles demostró asimetrías en la anisotropía fraccional. No se encontró relación significativa con las variables confrontadas.Conclusiones. Se necesita estudiar un mayor número de pacientes para valorar la utilidad de las DTI para definir la localizacióny extensión de la zona epileptógena en esta población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(8): 453-460, abr. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99976</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribución de las imágenes de resonancia magnética por tensor de difusión al diagnóstico de displasias corticales focales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30264</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
