<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91983</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Child sexuality and sexuality in adolescence. Similarities and differences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author centers the paper in a re-thinking of child sexuality as the great discovery of Freud; (which is the ground of all repression, all displacement and all sublimation) and differentiates it from adolescent sexuality. The paper takes into consideration the postulates of J. Laplanche by which adolescence is not considered as the culmination of child sexuality but as a period in which there is a confluence of child sexuality, instinctive puberal sexuality and the elaboration of subjectivity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escrivá, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de la autora, en este artículo se centra en volver a pensar la sexualidad infantil como el gran descubrimiento de Freud &#150; condición de base de toda represión, de todo desplazamiento y de toda sublimación &#150; y  diferenciarla de la sexualidad en la adolescencia. Teniendo en cuenta los planteamientos de J. Laplanche, la adolescencia no se considera como un tiempo de culminación de la sexualidad infantil sino como un tiempo en el que confluyen: la sexualidad infantil, la sexualidad instintiva puberal y la elaboración de la subjetivación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(56): 139-149, jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La sexualidad infantil y la sexualidad en la adolescencia. Confluencias y diferencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
