<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139318</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The combined use of virtual reality exposure in the treatment of agoraphobia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. This study compares the differential efficacy of three groups of treatments for agoraphobia: paroxetine combined with cognitive-behavioral therapy, paroxetine combined with cognitive-behavioral therapy and virtual reality exposure, and a group with only paroxetine. Methodology. 99 patients with agoraphobia were finally selected. Both combined treatment groups received 11 sessions of cognitive-behavioral therapy, and one of the groups was also exposed to 4 sessions of virtual reality treatment. Treatments were applied in individual sessions once a week for 3 months. Results. The three treatment groups showed statistically significant improvements. In some measures, combined treatment groups showed greater improvements. The virtual reality exposure group showed greater improvement confronting phobic stimuli. Conclusions. Treatments combining psychopharmacological and psychological therapy showed greater efficacy. Although the use of new technologies led to greater improvement, treatment adherence problems still remain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pitti, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca-Sánchez, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bethencourt, Juan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde, María L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñate, Wenceslao</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuente, Juan de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta, Leopoldo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Este estudio compara la eficacia diferencia  de tres grupos de tratamiento para la agorafobia: paroxetina en combinación con terapia cognitivo-conductual, paroxetina en combinación con terapia cognitivo-conductual y exposición de realidad virtual, y un grupo sólo con paroxetina. Metodología. Fueron seleccionados 99 pacientes con agorafobia. Ambos grupos de tratamiento combinado recibieron 11 sesiones de terapia cognitivo-conductual y uno de los grupos también fue expuesto a 4 sesiones de tratamiento de realidad virtual. Los tratamientos se aplicaron en sesiones individuales una vez a la semana durante 3 meses. Resultados. Los tres grupos de tratamiento mostraron mejoras estadísticamente significativas. En algunas de las medidas, los grupos de tratamiento combinado mostraron mayores mejoras y el grupo tratado con la exposición de realidad virtual mostró una mayor capacidad de enfrentar los estímulos fóbicos. Conclusiones. Los tratamientos que combinaron terapia psicofarmacológica y psicológica mostraron una mayor eficacia. Aunque el uso de las nuevas tecnologías dio lugar a una mejoría mayor, siguen existiendo problemas relacionados con la adherencia al tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;43(4): 133-141, jul.-ago. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139318</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El uso combinado de la exposición a realidad virtual en el tratamiento de la agorafobia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d383^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55091^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30623^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
