<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037367</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical treatment of bronchiectasis: scientific evidence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bronchiectases are the final result of an entire series of different etiological conditions. Although they may be defined as abnormal and permanent dilatations of the bronchi, the magnitude of the dilations, extension in the bronchial tree and etiology give rise to enormous differences in the clinical and functional results and thus in the management of the patients. The scientific evidence of each one of the medical treatments used in this disease is reviewed. Problems in the design of the clinical trials may have caused differences of criterion in the analysis and compiling of the studies analyzed and consequently affect and distort the conclusions of the reviewers regarding the efficacy of the different therapeutic modal modalities, especially in the section of respiratory physiotherapy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calderón González, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las bronquiectasias son el resultado final de toda una serie de procesos etiológicos diferentes. Aunque pueden definirse como dilataciones anormales y permanentes de los bronquios, la magnitud de la dilatación, la extensión en el árbol bronquial y la etiología producen enormes diferenciasen el resultado clínico y funcional y, por lo tanto, en el tratamiento de los enfermos. Se revisa la evidencia científica de cada uno de los tratamientos médicos que se utilizan en esta enfermedad. Problemas en el diseño de los ensayos clínicos pueden haber ocasionado diferencias de criterio en el análisis y recopilación de los trabajos analizados y en consecuencia, incidir y distorsionar las conclusiones de los revisores con respecto a la eficacia de las diferentes modalidades terapéuticas, en especial en el apartado de la fisioterapia respiratoria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(2): 70-77, mar.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento médico de las bronquiectasias: evidencia científica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5198^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1970</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
