<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131465</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endobronchial Valves in the Treatment of Persistent Air Leak, an Alternative to Surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Persistent air leak is frustrating for both patients and physicians, above all leaks with a high risk of surgery. Insertion of endobronchial valves could be an alternative to surgery. The aim of this study is to describe our experience in these valves and analyse their efficacy in a series of patients with persistent air leaks. Material and methods: The valves are inserted by means of flexible bronchoscopy under conscious sedation and local anesthesia. A preliminary bronchoscopy identifies the air leak by bronchial occlusion using a balloon catheter. A successful outcome is defined as complete disappearance of the leak following removal of the chest drain, without the need for further surgery. Results: From November 2010 to December 2013, 8 patients with persistent air leaks were treated with endobronchial valves. The number of valves used ranged from 1 to 4 (median 2), with a median duration of air leak prior to placement of 15.5 days. There were no complications and the resolution of the leak was complete in 6 of 8 patients (75%). The median duration of drainage after insertion of the valves was 13 days and the median time to removal of 52.5 days. Conclusions: Insertion of endobronchial valves is a safe and effective method for treating persistent air leaks, and a valid alternative to surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrueco, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranda, Jose Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordobilla, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo Torracchi, Aldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novoa, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Marcelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La fuga aérea prolongada es motivo de frustración entre médicos y pacientes, sobre todo para aquellos con alto riesgo quirúrgico. El uso de válvulas endobronquiales podría ser una alternativa al tratamiento quirúrgico. El objetivo de este trabajo es mostrar nuestra experiencia con el uso de las mismas y analizar su eficacia en una serie de casos tratados por fuga aérea persistente. Material y métodos: La colocación de las válvulas se realiza mediante broncoscopia flexible, bajo sedación consciente y anestesia local. La fuga aérea se identifica, en un primer paso, mediante la oclusión del bronquio con un catéter-balón durante una broncoscopia. El éxito del procedimiento se define como la desaparición completa de la misma, con la retirada del drenaje torácico sin necesidad de otros procedimientos posteriores. Resultados: De noviembre de 2010 a diciembre de 2013 se han tratado 8 pacientes por fuga aérea persistente con válvulas endobronquiales. El número de válvulas utilizadas osciló entre 1 y 4 (mediana de 2), con una mediana de duración de la fuga aérea previa a su colocación de 15,5 días. No hubo complicaciones, y la resolución de la fuga fue completa en 6 de los 8 pacientes (75%). La mediana de duración del drenaje después de la inserción de las válvulas fue de 13 días y la mediana del tiempo transcurrido hasta su extracción, de 52,5 días. Conclusiones: El uso de válvulas endobronquiales es un método eficaz y seguro para el tratamiento endobronquial de la fuga aérea prolongada y una alternativa válida a la cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(1): 10-15, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131465</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Válvulas endobronquiales para el tratamiento de la fuga aérea persistente, una alternativa al tratamiento quirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2015^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
