<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125354</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What do the new anticoagulants contribute to the prevention of venous and arterial thromboembolism?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the last decades, the only available oral anticoagulants were antivitamin K(AVK). The efficacy of the AVKs has been demonstrated, although they entail many disadvantages which require periodic monitoring of their anticoagulation action to adjust the doses. The new oral anticoagulants (NOACs) have pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic advantages because they can be administered orally at fixed doses without requiring monitorization. In the prevention of venous thromboembolic disease (VTD) after orthopedic surgery, NOACs have been shown to have a superior or similar efficacy to enoxaparin and similar safety. However, in the treatment and prevention of recurrences of VTD and in the prevention of stroke and systemic arterial embolisms in patients with nonvalvular auricular fibrillation, the NOACs have shown similar or greater efficacy as AVK and a superior safety profile with a very significant reduction in the rate of intracranial hemorrhages (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Bragado Dalmau, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A lo largo de las últimas décadas los únicos anticoagulantes orales disponibles han sido los antivitaminas K (AVK). Estos han demostrado su eficacia pero tienen múltiples inconvenientes, lo cual obliga a monitorizar periódicamente su acción anticoagulante para ajustar las dosis. Los nuevos anticoagulantes orales (NACOS) presentan ventajas farmacocinéticas y farmacodinámicas que permiten su administración por vía oral a dosis fijas sin necesidad de monitorización. En la prevención de la enfermedad tromboembólica venosa (ETV) tras cirugía ortopédica, los NACOS han demostrado una eficacia superior o similar a la enoxaparina y una seguridad similar. Mientras que, en el tratamiento y prevención de recurrencias de la ETV y en la prevención de ictus y embolias arteriales sistémicas en pacientes con fibrilación auricular no valvular, los NACOS han mostrado una eficacia similar o superior a los AVK y un perfil de seguridad superior con una reducción muy significativa en la tasa de hemorragias intracraneales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;31(3): 102-109, jul.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué aportan los nuevos anticoagulantes en la prevención del tromboembolismo venoso y arterial?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34256^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52618^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11729^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
