<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94700</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Understanding the pathophysiology of epilepsy in an animal model: pentylenetetrazole induces activation but not death of neurons of the medial extended amygdala</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Since middle of the 20th century the importance of amygdala in epilepsy it has suggested, although the basic mechanisms of this participation are still unknown. This ignorance increases when the different subdivisions of amygdala are considered, especially the medial amygdala. In this work we assess the involvement of the medial extended amygdala in an animal model of epilepsy and the consequences of its application in this brain structure. Material and methods: Forty eight adult Wistar male rats were used, of which 24 of them received i.p. injections of pentylenetetrazole, and 24 (controls) were injected with saline. After 2, 6, 12 and 24 h survival, animals were fixed; the brains were sectioned serially and stained for fos (immunochemistry) and for neuronal death with the A-Cu-Ag technique. Data were analysed using two-way ANOVA followed by the Fisher post hoc test. Results: Very few or no fos-immunoreactive neurons were seen in control animals. In experimental animals, fos was rapidly induced in structures of medial extended amygdala with peak levels at 2 h. Marked fos immunoreactivity persisted up to 12 h followed by a gradual return to baseline at 24 h. However, status epilepticus did not induced neuronal death. Conclusions: These results show involvement of medial extended amygdala in epileptic mechanisms with an inhibitory component. However, neuronal death is not a consequence of status epilepticus-induced by pentylentetrazole (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pereno, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltramino, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Desde mitad del siglo XX se ha apuntado a la importancia de la amígdala en la epilepsia, aunque los mecanismos básicos de esta participación en su mayoría son aún desconocidos. Esta ignorancia es aún mayor cuando se tienen en cuenta las distintas subdivisiones de la amígdala, especialmente sus partes mediales. En este trabajo evaluamos la participación de la amígdala extendida medial en un modelo animal de epilepsia, así como las consecuencias que tiene el epileptógeno en esta estructura cerebral. Material y métodos: Se utilizaron ratas adultas Wistar machos (n = 48); 24 animales recibieron inyecciones intraperitoneales de pentilentetrazol y 24, de salina. Luego de 2, 6, 12 y 24 h de sobrevida, los animales se fijaron, y sus cerebros se cortaron seriadamente y se procesaron para fos (inmunoquímica) y muerte neuronal con la técnica A-Cu-Ag. Los datos se analizaron con un ANOVA de 2 vías seguido de un test post-hoc (LSD de Fisher). Resultados: Muy poca activación fos se halla en animales controles. En animales experimentales, fos fue rápidamente inducida en la amígdala extendida medial a las 2 h. Esta activación fue sostenida hasta las 12 h y retornó a valores basales a las 24 h. Sin embargo, el estado epiléptico no produjo muerte neuronal. Conclusiones: Se demuestra así una participación de la amígdala extendida medial en mecanismos epilépticos en los cuales subyace un componente inhibitorio. Sin embargo, el estado epiléptico inducido no produce muerte neuronal en esta estructura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;25(3): 148-155, abr. 2010. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94700</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descifrando la fisiopatología de la epilepsia en un modelo animal: el pentilentetrazol induce la activación pero no la muerte de las neuronas de la amígdala extendida medial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9624^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d693^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10627^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
