<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117341</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing and Anthropology in Brazil: Relations, Dilemmas and Challenges</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Taking as a starting point to finding the invisibility of nursing scientific production in anthropological perspective on the literature reviews on anthropology of health in Brazil, the aim of this essay is to make a brief critical discussion of nursing and anthropology punctuating the particularities of the Brazilian context compared with countries like United States, England and Spain, and especially discuss the dilemmas (problems and limits) in the relations existing between the two disciplines and indicate some challenges to its development and consolidation. Finally, the enrollment of the arguments and comparative analysis of building this relationship in different countries allowed viewing certain hypotheses that aim to contribute to future discussions and studies in Brazil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Melo, Lucas Pereira de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tomando como punto de partida la invisibilidad de la producción científica de enfermería, en la perspectiva antropológica, en las revisiones de la literatura sobre antropología de la salud en Brasil, el objetivo de este artículo es realizar un breve análisis crítico de la relación entre enfermería y antropología puntuando las particularidades del contexto brasileño en comparación con países como Estados Unidos, Gran Bretaña y España y, en especial, discutir los dilemas (problemas y límites) en las relaciones existentes entre las dos disciplinas y señalar algunos desafíos para su desarrollo y consolidación. Por último, los argumentos y análisis comparativo de la construcción de esta relación en los diferentes países permiten ver ciertas hipótesis que apuntan a contribuir a los futuros debates y estudios en Brasil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;17(36): 66-76, mayo-ago. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117341</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermería y Antropología en Brasil: Relaciones, Dilemas y Desafíos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d896^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29771^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
