<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162354</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">History of the compressive therapy: the &#145;Baynton Method&#146; for the treatment of ulcers of the leg</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Baynton method or &#145;Baynton cure&#146; was a therapeutic technique of the late eighteenth century that revolutionized the conservative treatment that until the date applied to the healing of ulcers of the leg. Through the application of a dressing of diachylon, a compressive bandage pad spiral and the early mobilization of the extremity, it managed to settle the empirical bases of what is known as compression therapy. It is evident as the compression improved the edema, favored the humid environment and achieved a bacteriostatic effect and healing on the chronic ulcers of the lower extremity, becoming one of medical advances and most important public health and innovative of his time. This research represents one of the few documents that describe us as was evolving knowledge of the compression therapy for the treatment of chronic ulcers of the lower extremity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arantón Areosa, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Fernández, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rumbo Prieto, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El método Baynton o &#145;cura Baynton&#146; fue una técnica terapéutica de finales siglo XVIII que revolucionó el tratamiento conservador que hasta la fecha se aplicaba a la curación de las úlceras de la pierna. A través de la aplicación de un emplaste, un vendaje compresivo elástico en espiral y la movilización temprana de la extremidad, se lograron asentar las bases empíricas de lo que se conoce como &#145;terapia de compresión&#146;. Se evidenció cómo la compresión mejoraba el edema, favorecía el ambiente húmedo logrando un efecto bacteriostático y cicatrizante sobre las úlceras tórpidas de la extremidad inferior, convirtiéndose en uno de avances médicos y de salud pública más importantes e innovadores de su época. Esta investigación representa uno de los escasos documentos que nos describen cómo fue evolucionando el conocimiento de la terapia de compresión para el tratamiento de úlceras crónicas de la extremidad inferior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(1): 49-54, mar. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antecedentes de la terapia compresiva: el &#145;método Baynton&#146; para el tratamiento de úlceras de la pierna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54277^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
