<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-25917</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional debt</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The human brain is capable of reacting with emotional responses to stimuli coming both from the external world and from internal representations produced by imagination. These virtual images can elicit perfectly real emotions with physiological effects in the organism. A typical result of these emotions is that the subject commits him/herself to obtain or avoid the object that evoked the emotion. Such commitment is described here as &#145;emotional debt&#146;. Emotional debt involves the overestimation of an illusory reality, bringing about maladjusted behaviors in the present and giving rise in the long term to moral suffering and chronic stress. Canceling an emotional debt is a real possibility that produces therapeutic effects (as is the case in forgiveness). It is even possible to avoid any emotional debt at all, which implies an important change (and a further developmental stage) in the functioning of the human mind (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cerebro humano es capaz de generar respuestas emocionales no sólo ante estímulos sensoriales del mundo externo, sino también ante imágenes producidas por la fantasía. Estas imágenes virtuales evocan emociones perfectamente reales y con efectos fisiológicos en el organismo que, además, incitan al sujeto a comprometerse consigo mismo en obtener (o en rehuir), en el futuro, aquel objeto que suscita la emoción. Este compromiso se denomina aquí "deuda emocional". La deuda emocional suele entrañar una sobrevaloración afectiva del objeto imaginado, susceptible de provocar comportamientos inadecuados en el presente y de convertirse, a largo plazo, en fuente de sufrimiento y de estrés crónico. Las deudas emocionales, sin embargo, también pueden ser saldadas definitivamente, proceso que conlleva importantes efectos terapéuticos, como sucede en el perdón. Incluso, es posible no asumir deuda emocional alguna, lo que implica un importante cambio cualitativo (y un estadio posiblemente más avanzado) en el funcionamiento de la mente humana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(2): 328-334, mayo 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-25917</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La deuda emocional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3729</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14382</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12481</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
