<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73508</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exposure of phytoestrogens intake through diet in a sample of females</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The phytoestrogens are naturally occurring compounds that are part of many foods of plant origin and could therefore modulate aspects related hormones, such as type of antioxidant reactions, learning about intakes of these compounds in different populations clarify important aspects on their responses on the human body. Objective: To evaluate the exposure of phytoestrogens through diet, in a sample of women of all ages belonging to the university community (teachers, students and administrative), residents in the province of Granada,Spain. Material and method: 52 adult females, aged between 20 and 63 years completed a questionnaire individually Frequency of Food Consumption (FFQ) composed of a total of 144 foods. It weighted the total daily consumption of phytoestrogens standardizing these values referring to the daidzein as substance pattern (mg/day). Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 15.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA), with a level of significance of p &lt; 0.05. Results: The results show that the total intake of phytoestrogens was (0.89 mg/day), and most of phytoestrogens was consumed in the form of lignanos. The total consumption of isoflavones, was 0.12 mg/day, of lignanos was 1.32 mg/day intake coumestrol was not significative. A linear regression analysis determined the equation to calculate intake phytoestrogens took into account 9 food groups (R: 0.918; p &lt; 0.001). Discussion: Average intake of phytoestrogens in Spain, is comparable to intakes reported by similar studies in Germany, England and the United States (&lt; 1 mg/ day). Conclusions: There were no significant differences in the intake of phytoestrogens, when comparing results by age, educational level, marital status or physical activity. The intake of phytoestrogens (mg/day) can be estimated from the intake (g/day) from 9 food groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velasco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feriche, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olea-Serrano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariscal-Arcas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Elizondo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los fitoestrógenos son compuestos naturales que forman parte de numerosos alimentos de origen vegetal y que podrían modular tanto aspectos relacionados con hormonas, como reacciones de tipo antioxidante, por lo que conocer las ingestas de estos compuestos en diferentes poblaciones aclararía aspectos importantes sobre sus respuestas en el organismo. Objetivo: Valorar la exposición de fitoestrógenos por medio de la dieta, en una muestra de mujeres de todas las edades pertenecientes a la comunidad universitaria (docentes, administrativas y estudiantes), residentes en la provincia de Granada, España. Material y método: 52 mujeres adultas, con edades entre 20 y 63 años completaron individualmente un cuestionario de frecuencia de consumo de alimentos (FFQ) compuesto por un total de 144 alimentos. Se ponderó el consumo diario de fitoestrógenos totales estandarizando los valores refiriendo estos a la daidzeína como sustancia patrón (mg/día). El análisis estadístico se realizó con SPSS 15.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA), con un nivel de significancia de p &lt; 0,05. Resultados: Muestran que la ingesta total de fitoestrógenos referidos a la daizdeína fue de 0,89 mg/día, y la mayor parte de fitoestrogenos fue consumido en forma de lignanos. El consumo total de isoflavonas, fue de 0,12 mg/día, el de lignanos fue de 1,32 mg/día y la ingesta de coumestrol no fue significativa. Un Análisis de Regresión Lineal, determinó la ecuación para calcular la ingesta de fitoestrógenos, tomando en cuenta 9 grupos de alimentos (R: 0,918; p &lt; 0,001). Discusión: La ingesta media de fitoestrógenos en España, es comparable con las ingestas descritas por estudios similares en Alemania, Inglaterra y Estados Unidos (&lt; 1 mg/d). Conclusiones: No existen diferencias significativas en la ingesta de fitoestrógenos, cuando se compara la muestra por edad, nivel educativo, actividad física o estado civil. La ingesta de fitoestrógenos (mg/día) puede ser estimada a partir de la ingesta (g/día) de 9 grupos de alimentos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;24(4): 445-451, jul.-ago. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73508</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación de la ingesta de fitoestrógenos en población femenina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38791^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
