<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049975</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Respiratory syncitial virus bronchiolitis: an update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bronchiolitis due to respiratory syncytial virus (RSV)is one of the leading causes of hospitalization of infants under 12 months of age in our patient population; the mortality associated with this infection ranges around 0.5%, although in risk groups, the rate can reach up to approximately 3%. For this reason, it is important to clearly define the groups at risk for this infection, as well as to design adequate prevention strategies for these patient subgroups. The importance of under standing this infection lies not only in its early diagnosis and proper therapeutic management, but in the in-depth knowledge of the virus and the immune response of the organism, as well. There is a large body of evidence supporting a causal relationship, between RSV infection and post-bronchiolitis asthma, although we still need to clarify key aspects that will enable us to determine which patients will present recurrent wheezing and which patients will not, and whether the virus actually triggers asthma or is simply a marker that selects individuals who are genetically predisposed to develop this disease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La bronquiolitis por virus respiratorio sincitial es una de las causas más frecuentes de hospitalización en los lactantes menores de 12 meses en nuestro medio; la mortalidad de esta infección se sitúa en torno al 0,5%, si bien en los grupos de riesgo puede alcanzar hasta un 3% aproximadamente. Por ello, es importante definir bien los grupos de riesgo para la infección, así como diseñar estrategias adecuadas de prevención en estos subgrupos de pacientes. La importancia de esta infección radica no solamente en su diagnóstico precoz y en su adecuado manejo terapéutico, sino también en el profundo conocimiento del virus y de la respuesta inmunológica del organismo. Numerosas evidencias científicas avalan la asociáción causal entre infección por VAS y asma posbronquiolitis, aunque aún permanecen sin dilucidar aspectos clave que permitan explicar qué pacientes van a tener sibilancias recurrentes y qué pacientes no, y si el virus en realidad desencadena asma o simplemente es un marcador que selecciona a pacientes genéticamente predispuestos a tener esta patología</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;64(7): 316-322, jul. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049975</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bronquiolitis por virus respiratorio sincitial. Actualización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23173^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31083^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23173^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31081^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
