<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047490</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Piogenic abscess in the psoas muscle after lumbar spondylodiskitis postartrodesis. A case report, comentary and revision</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a case of a immunocompromised patient withvertebral artrodesis that presented an infection by Staphylococcusaureus with torpid evolution and several local recidivain spite of antibiotic therapy and surgical drainage.After 3 months the artrodesis instrumental was extirpatedand the patient developed a chronic spondylodiskitisand cutaneous lumbar fistula. Appeared an abscess in thepsoas iliac musculature after 5 years.The differential diagnosis is established among the differententities responsible for the affectation of the retroperitonealcompartment.The evolutionary images are analyzed from the spondylodiskitisto psoas abscess and the progression until its resolution</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llamas Cascón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gala Sánchez, F. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Lacosta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Méndez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartolomé Villar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Barba, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asenjo Siguero, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de un paciente inmunocompetentesometido a artrodesis vertebral que sufre infección quirúrgicapor Staph. Aureus multisensible con evolución tórpiday múltiples recidivas locales pese antibioterapia e intervencionesquirúrgicas de drenaje.A los 3 meses de la artrodesis se retiró el material de fijación,y evoluciona a espondilodiscitis crónica con fístulacutánea lumbar. Aparece absceso del músculo psoas iliacoa los 5 años.Se establece el diagnóstico diferencial entre las entidadesresponsables de afectación del espacio retroperitoneal.Se analizan las imágenes evolutivas desde espondilodiscitisa absceso del psoas y la progresión hasta la resolución</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;3(4): 275-281, oct.-dic. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047490</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Absceso piógeno del psoas secundario a espondilodiscitis postartrodesis lumbar. Revisión y comentario, a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1182^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29859^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23612^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29859^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23612^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
