<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114068</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acceptance and commitment therapy for drug abuse in incarcerated women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Acceptance and Commitment Therapy is the third wave therapy with the greatest empirical evidence in the treatment of drug abuse. Method: Thirty-one women with substance use disorder (SUD) were randomly assigned to two conditions, an intervention based on Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT) and a control group on a waiting list. All participants were assessed three times (before treatment, at the end, and at a six-month follow-up) using urinalysis, the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI), the Addiction Severity Index (ASI-6), the Anxiety Sensitivity Index, and the Acceptance and Action Questionnaire (AAQ-II). Results: After 16 ACT intervention sessions, abstinence rates of 27.8% were observed, increasing to 43.8% after six months. The treatment also promoted improvements in other areas, such as reductions in the percentage of comorbid psychopathology and anxiety sensitivity, and the increase of psychological flexibility, which, in general, were not documented in the comparison group. Conclusions: Clinical gains were achieved, and we consider ACT to be an effective and appropriate treatment to be applied in the prison context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Menéndez, ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villagrá Lanza, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la Terapia de Aceptación y Compromiso (ACT) es una de las terapias de tercera generación que cuenta con mayor evidencia empírica en el tratamiento del abuso de sustancias (TUS). Método: treinta y un mujeres con TUS fueron asignadas al azar a dos condiciones: un tratamiento de 16 sesiones con base en ACT y un grupo de control en lista de espera. Todas fueron evaluadas en 3 momentos (pre, post y al cabo de seis meses de recibir el tratamiento) mediante analíticas de orina, la Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI), el Addiction Severity Index (ASI-6), el Índice de sensibilidad a la Ansiedad y el Cuestionario de Aceptación y Acción (AAQ-II). Resultados: tras la intervención, se observó un porcentaje de abstinencia del 27,8% y del 43,8% al cabo de seis meses. La intervención también provocó mejorías en otras áreas, como reducciones en los porcentajes de psicopatología asociada y de sensibilidad a la ansiedad, así como aumento de la flexibilidad psicológica, que, en general, no se documentaron en el grupo de comparación. Conclusiones: se discuten estas ganancias clínicas y se ofrece ACT como un tratamiento apropiado para ser dispensado en mujeres reclusas con trastorno por abuso de sustancias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);25(3): 307-312, jul.-sept. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114068</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia de Aceptación y Compromiso para el abuso de sustancias en mujeres encarceladas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23920^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54306^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
