<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145574</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of thyroid follicular carcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Differentiated thyroid carcinoma includes 2 different tumor types, papillary (PC) and follicular carcinoma (FC), and although similar, their prognosis is different. FC is uncommon, and this has led to it often being analyzed together with PC, and therefore the true reality of this tumor is difficult to know. As a result, the diagnostic and therapeutic management and the prognostic factors in differentiated carcinoma are more predictive of PC than FC. In this review we analyze the current state of many of the therapeutic aspects of this pathology. The best surgical technique and the usefulness of associated lymphadenectomy is also analyzed. Regarding post-surgical ablation with 131I, the indications, doses and usefulness are discussed. For the remaining therapies we analyze the few indications for radiotherapy and chemotherapy, and of new drugs such as tyrosine kinase inhibitors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parrilla, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El carcinoma diferenciado de tiroides incluye 2 tipos tumorales diferentes: el carcinoma papilar (CP) y el folicular (CF) y, aunque similares, su pronóstico es diferente. La infrecuencia del CF ha hecho que habitualmente se analice conjuntamente con el CP, lo cual dificulta conocer su verdadera realidad. En esta revisión se analiza la situación de los diferentes aspectos terapéuticos de esta dolencia. Se revisa cuál es la mejor técnica quirúrgica y la utilidad de realizar vaciamiento ganglionar asociado. Respecto a la ablación posquirúrgica con 131I se evalúan las indicaciones, las dosis y su utilidad. En el resto de terapias se analizan las pocas indicaciones que tiene la radioterapia y la quimioterapia, y la aparición de nuevos fármacos como los inhibidores de la tirosin-cinasa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(10): 611-618, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145574</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del carcinoma folicular de tiroides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31586^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
