<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167827</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of GATA-3 as a marker of seminal epithelium in prostate biopsies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The incidental presence of seminal vesicle epithelium in prostate needle biopsies is generally recognisable through routine microscopy. However, the biopsy can sometimes be erroneously interpreted as malignant due to its architectural and cytological characteristics, and immunohistochemistry can be useful for correctly identifying the biopsy. Our objective was to analyse the potential usefulness of GATA-3 as a marker of seminal epithelium. Material and methods: Through  immunohistochemistry with a monoclonal anti-GATA-3 antibody (clone L50-823), we studied seminal vesicle sections from 20 prostatectomy specimens, 12 prostate needle biopsies that contained seminal vesicle tissue and 68 prostate biopsies without seminal vesicle epithelium, 36 of which showed adenocarcinoma. Results: Staining for GATA-3 was intense in the 20 seminal vesicles of the prostatectomy specimens and in the 12 prostate needle biopsies that contained seminal epithelium. In the 60 biopsies without a seminal vesicle, GATA-3 was positive in the prostate basal cells and even in the secretory cells (57 cases), although with less intensity in 55 of the cases. One of the 36 prostatic adenocarcinomas tested positive for GATA-3. Conclusions: The intense immunohistochemical expression of GATA-3 in the seminal vesicle epithelium can help identify the epithelium in prostate biopsies. This marker is also positive in the basal cells of healthy prostates and, with less intensity, in the secretory cells. Positivity, weak or moderate, is observed on rare occasions in prostatic adenocarcinomas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>San Miguel-Fraile, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Rey, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chantada-de la Fuente, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peteiro-Cancelo, MÁ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-de María, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La presencia incidental de epitelio de la vesícula seminal en las biopsias por aguja de próstata es generalmente reconocible mediante el estudio microscópico de rutina. Sin embargo, en ocasiones, se puede interpretar erróneamente como maligno debido a sus características arquitecturales y citológicas, y la inmunohistoquímica puede ser útil para identificarlo correctamente. Nuestro objetivo ha sido analizar la posible utilidad de GATA-3 como marcador de epitelio seminal. Material y métodos_ Se han estudiado mediante inmunohistoquímica con un anticuerpo monoclonal anti-GATA-3 (clon L50-823) secciones de vesícula seminal procedentes de 20 piezas de prostatectomía, 12 biopsias por aguja de la próstata que contenían tejido de vesícula seminal y 68 biopsias de próstata sin epitelio de vesícula seminal, 36 de las cuales presentaban adenocarcinoma. Resultados: La tinción para GATA-3 fue intensa en las 20 vesículas seminales de las piezas de prostatectomía y en las 12 biopsias por aguja de próstata que contenían epitelio seminal. En las 60 biopsias sin vesícula seminal GATA-3 fue positiva en las células basales de la próstata, e incluso en las células secretoras (57 casos), aunque con menor intensidad en 55 de los casos. Uno de los 36 adenocarcinomas prostáticos fue GATA-3 positivo. Conclusiones: La expresión inmunohistoquímica intensa de GATA-3 en el epitelio de la vesícula seminal puede ayudar a identificarlo en las biopsias prostáticas. Este marcador también es positivo en las células basales de la próstata normal y, con menor intensidad, en las secretoras. Raramente se observa positividad, débil o moderada, en adenocarcinomas prostáticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;41(9): 577-583, nov. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167827</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de GATA-3 como marcador de epitelio seminal en las biopsias de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32875^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13052^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31599^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29574^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2338^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50988^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
