<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167730</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bringing back a forgotten classic: «Problems of technique» by Hellmuth Kaiser (1934). Part I</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Around 1934 the debate on therapeutic technique became the focus of psychoanalytic research. In this context Hellmuth Kaiser, a Wilhelm Reich's disciple, published Problems of technique. His technical proposal was based on the systematic analysis of resistance, the technique of  "Character analysis", taking it much further than Reich, to the extent of ending up without content interpretation and, through the recovery of the cathartic factor, encouraged the analyzand to produce his own interpretation. The text of Kaiser had an enormous impact and received criticism from some of the leading researchers of psychoanalytic technique (Reich, Fenichel and Alexander). The rejection of his proposals,  together with its interminable exile and his untimely death, made his work fell into almost total oblivion. Today his works are recognized from psychotherapeutic perspectives far removed from each other: on one hand, he claimed his role as precursor of the ego psychology's technique, and on the other hand, some framed authors in Gestalt Psychotherapy recognize him as one of their precursors. In this paper, we present for the first time in Spanish the translation of Problems of technique (1934 ), historically contextualized and accompanied by a brief biographical sketch of the autor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montejo Alonso, F Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Barrios, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cuando en 1934 el debate sobre la técnica terapéutica se convirtió en el eje de la investigación psicoanalítica, Hellmuth Kaiser publicó Problemas de técnica. Su propuesta técnica se basaba en el análisis sistemático de las resistencias, la técnica del «análisis del carácter», llevándolo mucho más lejos que su maestro Wilhelm Reich, hasta el extremo de prescindir de las interpretaciones de contenido y, a través de la recuperación del factor catártico, lograr que las interpretaciones fueran producidas por el analizando. El texto de Kaiser tuvo enorme impacto y recibió las críticas de algunos de los principales investigadores de la técnica psicoanalítica (Reich, Fenichel y Alexander). El rechazo a sus propuestas, unido a su interminable exilio y su prematura muerte, hicieron que su obra cayera en el olvido. Actualmente sus trabajos son reconocidos desde perspectivas psicoterapéuticas muy alejadas unas de otras: por un lado, se reivindica su papel de precursor de la técnica de la Psicología del Yo, y por otro algunos autores encuadrados en la Psicoterapia Gestalt le reconocen como uno de sus precursores. En este artículo presentamos por primera vez en español la traducción de Problemas de técnica (1934), contextualizado históricamente y acompañado de un breve esbozo biográfico del autor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(80): 251-278, 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167730</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recuperación de un clásico olvidado: «Problemas de técnica» de Hellmuth Kaiser (1934). Parte I</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6005^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6005^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2442</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6004^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
