<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104823</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of maternal glucose tolerance, pregnancy diet quality  and neonatal insulinemia upon insulin resistance/sensitivity biomarkers in normoweight neonates</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Differences in neonatal insulin sensitivity/resistance markers due to the maternal impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) have not been tested. The Healthy Eating Index (HEI) score has been employed for evaluating pregnancy diet quality. Aims: To study, the effect of neonatal insulinemia, maternal IGT and diet HEI score upon insulin sensitivity/resistance at birth. Methods: 176 singleton, normoweight, full-term, Caucasian Spanish neonates, delivered without fetal distress whose mothers were screened for gestational IGT were studied. Quantitative Insulin Sensitivity Check Index (QUICKI) and Homeostatic Model Assessment (HOMAIR) were calculated. Diet followed during the third month of pregnancy was recorded and the respective HEI score calculated in a sample of 29 mothers. Results: As quartile for cord blood insulin levels increased, glucose, the insulin/cortisol ratio and HOMA-IR(all p &lt; 0.001) and IGF-I (p &lt; 0.01) increased while QUICKI and the glucose/insulin ratio (both p &lt; 0.001) and GH (p &lt;0.05) decreased. Neonates from IGT mothers had higher insulin, HOMA-IR (both p &lt; 0.01) and insulin/cortisol ratio(p &lt; 0.05) and lower GH, QUICKI (both p &lt; 0.01) and glucose/insulin ratio (p &lt; 0.05) than their normal maternal glucose tolerance (NGT) counterparts. Neonatal insulinemia influences more than IGT on the insulin resistance/sensitivity markers at birth. Mothers of hyperinsulinemic neonates showed lower HEI scores (p &lt; 0.05).Conclusion: A large percentage of full-term normoweightinfants with hyperinsulinemia showed altered insulin resistance markers. Their mothers consumed low quality diets. Screening strategies focused on neonatal glycemia and insulinemia together with maternal nutritional assessment and advice during pregnancy should be considered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gesteiro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bastida, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Muniz, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los efectos de la disminución de la tolerancia a la glucosa (DTG) materna sobre la insulinorresistencia neonatal han sido poco estudiados. La puntuación del Índice de Alimentación Saludable (HEI) es útil para evaluar la calidad de la dieta en gestantes. Objetivos: Estudiar la asociación de insulinemia neonatal y DTG materna con la resistencia/sensibilidad a la insulina al nacimiento y con el HEI materno. Métodos: Se estudiaron 176 neonatos españoles, caucásicos, a término, normopeso, de embarazo único y sin distrés fetal, cuyas madres fueron cribadas para DTG en elembarazo. Se calcularon el Quantitative Insulin Sensitivity Check Index (QUICKI) y el Homeostatic  Model Assessment (HOMA-IR). En 29 madres se estudió la dieta consumida durante el tercer mes de gestación y se calculó su respectivo HEI. Resultados: Al aumentar el cuartil de insulina en sangre de cordón, aumentaron glucosa, cociente insulina/cortisol, HOMA-IR (p &lt; 0,001) e IGF-I (p &lt; 0,01), y disminuyeron QUICKI y cociente glucosa/insulina (p &lt; 0,001) y GH (p &lt; 0,05). Los neonatos de madres con DTG tuvieron mayores niveles de insulina, HOMA-IR (p &lt; 0,01) y cociente insulina/cortisol (p &lt; 0,05) y menores de GH,QUICKI (p &lt; 0,01) y el cociente glucosa/insulina (p &lt; 0,05)que los de madres con tolerancia a la glucosa normal. La insulinemia neonatal influye más en los marcadores de resistencia/sensibilidad a la insulina que la DTG. Las madres de los niños hiperinsulinémicos tuvieron HEI más bajos (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: Un gran porcentaje de neonatos con hiperinsulinemia muestran marcadores de insulinorresistencia alterados. Sus madres ingirieron dietas de baja calidad. Debe considerarse la necesidad del cribado de glucosa e insulina en estos neonatos y el asesoramiento y evaluación nutricional durante el embarazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(6): 1447-1455, nov.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la tolerancia a la glucosa y calidad de la dieta materna durante embarazo y de los niveles de insulina al nacimiento sobre biomarcadores de resistencia/sensibilidad a la insulina en neonatos normopeso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22231^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6862^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
