<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91396</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biohazard management and its integration into Labor Health at the Immunology and Bioproducts Centre in Cuba</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Risk assessments are useful to plan and improve biological safety, quality control and in general health and safety at work, taking into account the legal framework in Cuba. Supervision is an important part of these processes. Research was done in order to identify and to evaluate the biohazard in the Immunology and Bioproducts Centre (CIBHO). It included the identification and risk assessment in three areas, the biological safety supervisions and its evolution and the corrective measures recommended. The results allowed to design and to implement a Safety Regulation which includes measures for biological safety and health and safety at work  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Lima, Mayra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Cruz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pittaluga Rivero, Aiket</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Ponce, Zuleidis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobos Valdes, Dailín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de riesgos es útil para planificar y mejorar la Seguridad Biológica, el control de la calidad y la Seguridad y Salud en el Trabajo, considerando el marco legal vigente en Cuba y la inspección constituye una parte importante de estos procesos. Con el objetivo de identificar y evaluar el riesgo biológico en el Centro de Inmunología y Biopreparados se realizó esta investigación. La misma incluyó la identificación del riesgo biológico en tres áreas, la evolución de inspecciones de Seguridad Biológica y las medidas correctivas recomendadas. Los resultados permitieron diseñar e implementar el Reglamento de Seguridad en el se integraron las funciones de Seguridad Biológica y Seguridad y Salud en el Trabajo  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;57(223): 163-169, abr.-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91396</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión del riesgo biológico y su integración con la Seguridad y Salud del Trabajo en el Centro de Inmunología y Biopreparados de Cuba</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12720^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53400^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3482^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
