<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165331</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Work conditions, ergonomic risks and the presence of musculoskeletal disorders in coffee collectors in a municipality in Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The presence of musculoskeletal disorders are important public health problems among farmers. Few studies have examined the ergonomic risks and working conditions associated with the presence of these disorders. The objective of this study is to describe the socio-demographic characteristics, social security, working conditions, ergonomic risk and musculoskeletal disorders in a group of coffee collectors in the municipality of Andes. Materials and methods: a cross-sectional study was conducted in a group of 70 coffee collectors in the municipality of Andes, Antioquia, applying an assisted instrument and an assessment using the OWAS method for the identification of postural risk factors, and the Nordic questionnaire for the identification of musculoskeletal disorders that could be associated with the postural risks and other labour and socio-demographic factors. Results: The study showed a higher prevalence of low back pain and neck pain in female workers compared with male workers. There was a trend towards a higher rate of cervicalgia and low back pain in workers who reported having had work-related accidents and occupational diseases, but the association was not statistically significant. Conclusion:It was found that 64.3% of the municipal coffee collectors surveyed presented medium risk associated with inadequate and / or maintained postures, and when related to musculoskeletal disorders, 30% of the respondents reported low back pain. There was no statistically significant association between the presence of musculoskeletal disorders and working conditions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Osley Garzón, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Juliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giovana Muñoz, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez, Elsa María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la presencia de desórdenes músculo esqueléticos son problemas de salud pública importantes entre los agricultores. Pocos estudios han examinado los riesgos ergonómicos y las condiciones de trabajo asociadas con la presencia estos desórdenes. El objetivo de este estudio es describir las características sociodemográficas, de seguridad social, las condiciones laborales, el riesgo ergonómico y los desórdenes musculo esqueléticos en un grupo de recolectores de café del municipio de Andes. Materiales y métodos: Estudio descriptivo, transversal, en un grupo de 70 recolectores de café en el municipio de Andes Antioquia, aplicando un instrumento asistido y una valoración con el método OWAS para la identificación de factores de riesgo posturales y el cuestionario nórdico para la identificación de desórdenes musculo esqueléticos que pudieran estar asociados con los riesgos posturales y a otros factores laborales y sociodemográficos explorados. Resultados: Se observó mayor prevalencia de riesgo de presentar lumbalgia y cervicalgia en las mujeres recolectoras de café. Se observa una tendencia a un mayor reporte de cervicalgia y lumbalgia en aquellos trabajadores que refirieron haber presentado accidentes laborales y enfermedades laborales, sin embargo, la asociación no fue estadísticamente significativa. Conclusión: Se encontró que el 64.3% de los recolectores de café del municipio encuestados presentaron mediano riesgo ergonómico, asociado a posturas inadecuadas y/o mantenidas, y al relacionar lo anterior con los desórdenes musculo esqueléticos, el 30% de los encuestados refirió lumbalgia. No se encontró asociación estadísticamente significativa entre la presencia de desórdenes musculo esqueléticos y las condiciones de trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;26(2): 127-136, jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165331</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condiciones de trabajo, riesgos ergonómicos y presencia de desórdenes músculo-esqueléticos en recolectores de café de un municipio de Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6956</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56194^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
