<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103569</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of leadership styles and human resources management practices on innovation climate in organizations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An increasing number of organizations and countries are focusing in innovations as the lever for a new model of economic development, front proposals based in decreasing costs. Due to their marked social character, the present study analyses the relationship between organizational climate of innovation and the leadership styles and practices of human resources management addressed by organizations to their members. Regression analyses carried out explained near of 60% of the variance in innovation climate, outstanding HRM practices addressed to stimulate workers participation and inspirational leadership as main predictors(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos López, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons Verdú, Fernando J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Frente a propuestas de valor asociadas a un bajo coste productivo, numerosas naciones y organizaciones buscan convertir a la innovación en la palanca de un nuevo modelo de crecimiento económico. Por su marcado carácter social, este estudio analiza la relación entre el clima organizacional de innovación, los estilos de liderazgo y las prácticas de gestión de RRHH características en la organización. Los modelos de regresión obtenidos explican una varianza cercana al 60% del clima organizacional innovador y señalan a las prácticas dirigidas a estimular la participación de los miembros y el estilo de liderazgo inspiracional como sus principales predictores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);28(2): 81-98, 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103569</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de los estilos de liderazgo y las prácticas de gestión de RRHH sobre el clima organizacional de innovación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28433^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4535^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
