<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167571</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body shape as body image determinant in university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Body shape (BSP) and body image (BI) are part of the external physical structure, then modifications in body shape necessarily affect body image; however, both combined have not been studied. The purpose of the study was to evaluate the statistical relationship between BSP and BI in university students. Method: Two hundred and ninety-six participants (17-35 years) were included in this study. Different anthropometric measurements were used to define their somatotype (BSP), body mass index (BMI), waist to hip ratio (WHR) and waist circumference (WC). In addition, a questionnaire on body image perception was applied (McElhone et al.), regarding «how do I look?», «how do I think others see me?», «how do others see me?», and «how do I want to look like?». Results: On average, men perceived themselves in normal weight; in contrast, women perceived themselves as overweight. Men were meso-endomorphic, while women were endo-mesomorphic as an average. Conclusion: Body shape measured as somatotype as well as WC and WHR were excellent determinants of body image. Participants who presented a higher endomorphy, WC and WHR and a lower ectomorphy had a higher appreciation of being overweight or obese and wish to become thinner (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Wall Medrano, Abraham</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Jiménez, Arnulfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalobos Molina, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urquídez Romero, René</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barahona, Igor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Torres, Rosa P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: la forma corporal (FC) y la imagen corporal (IC) son parte de la estructura física externa, por lo tanto, las modificaciones en la forma del cuerpo afectan necesariamente a la imagen corporal; sin embargo, combinados ambos no han sido estudiados. El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar la relación estadística entre FC e IC en estudiantes universitarios. Método: doscientos noventa y seis participantes (17-35 años) fueron incluidos en este estudio. Se utilizaron diferentes medidas antropométricas para definir el somatotipo, índice de masa corporal (IMC), índice cintura/cadera (ICC) y circunferencia de cintura (CC). Además, se aplicó un cuestionario sobre la percepción de la imagen corporal (McElhone et al.), relacionado con: «¿cómo me veo?», «¿cómo pienso que los demás me ven?», «¿cómo me ven los demás?» y «¿cómo quiero parecer?». Resultados: en promedio, los hombres se perciben en peso normal; en cambio, las mujeres se perciben con sobrepeso. En promedio, los hombres fueron meso-endomórficos, mientras que las mujeres endo-mesomórficas. Conclusión: la forma corporal medida como somatotipo, ICC y CC fueron excelentes determinantes de la imagen corporal. Los participantes que presentaron mayor endomorfia, mayor ICC, mayor CC y menor ectomorfia tuvieron una mayor apreciación de sobrepeso u obesidad, y el deseo de verse más delgados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(5): 1112-1118, sept.-oct. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167571</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La forma corporal como determinante de la imagen corporal en estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38802^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
