<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131017</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personality disorders in adolescence: Clinical characteristics and therapeutic paths from infancy to adulthood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper studies the concept of personality disorders paying special attention to its use in childhood and adolescence. Personality disorders in childhood constitute a clinical reality that often becomes dramatically relevant in adolescence. However, from a nosological point of view, the World Health Organization&#146;s diagnostic classification (ICD-10) does not consider its usage until after 16 or 17 years of age. The paper presents a sample of patients with personality disorders attended in our Center and analyses their clinical and diagnostic development, their treatment history into adulthood and the weight of risk factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rigon, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancaruso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cassetti, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chiodo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamberini, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poggioli, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa,  S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno de la personalidad en la infancia representa una realidad clínica presente y, a menudo, dramáticamente relevante en la adolescencia, mientras que desde el punto de vista nosográfico la codificación de la OMS (ICD-10) no prevé su utilización hasta después de los 16-17 años. La primera parte del trabajo presenta el concepto de trastorno de la personalidad haciendo hincapié en su uso en la infancia. En la parte experimental se analiza una muestra de pacientes con trastornos de la personalidad (TP) ingresados en nuestro servicio. Se comenta, básicamente, la evolución clínico-nosográfica, el recorrido asistencial incluso después de su mayoría de edad, el peso de los factores de riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(16): 29-40, nov. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos de personalidad en la adolescencia: características clínicas y vías asistenciales desde la infancia a la adultez</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
