<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140676</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of argirophilic nucleolar organizer regions (AgNORs) in thyroid follicular neoplasias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The Nucleolar Organizer Regions (NOR) are segments of DNA that encode ribosomal RNA which is directly related to protein synthesis and cellular proliferation. Silver-staining methods allow detection of AgNOR proteins with the amount of silver-stained proteins proportional to cell proliferative activity. This seems to be important in distinguishing between benign and malignant tumors. The aim of this study is to determine the utility of the expresion of AgNORs in the differential diagnosis of follicular thyroid neoplasms. Material and Methods: 17 surgical specimens of follicular thyroid neoplasms (10 adenomas and 7 carcinomas) were studied. Ploton&#146;s original silver technique (1986) with gold toning, fixation with sodiumthiosulfate and counterstaining with nuclear red extra was carried out. One hundred cells per case were evaluated, taking into account the mean number of Agnor dots per nucleus, their location, distribution and the number of cells with five or more dots. Results: The total mean number of AgNOR dots per nucleus was significantly higher in carcinomas than in adenomas as was the number of nuclei with 5 or more AgNOR dots. Carcinomas were frequently found to present AgNOR dots grouped in a central cluster. Adenomas showed small, dispersed and peripheral dots which were often unique. The technique applied did not appear to have been adversely affected by the time elapsed in the older cases. Conclusions: The mean total number of AgNOR dots per nucleus, the number of nuclei with 5 or more AgNOR dots and the grouped distribution of them may be useful in the differential diagnosis of follicular adenoma and carcinoma of thyroid (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Requena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Nieto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo-González, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rego-González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañizares Benítez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las Regiones Organizadoras Nucleolares (NOR) son segmentos de DNA que codifican el RNA ribosómico, el cual está directamente relacionado con la síntesis proteica y la proliferación celular. Mediante técnicas de impregnación argéntica se pueden detectar las proteinas asociadas a los NORs (AgNORs), siendo su cantidad proporcional a la actividad proliferativa. Esto parece tener importancia para distinguir entre tumores benignos y malignos. El objetivo de este trabajo es determinar la utilidad de la expresión de AgNORs en el diagnóstico diferencial de neoplasias foliculares tiroideas. Material y métodos: La técnica se realizó sobre piezas quirúrgicas correspondientes a 10 adenomas y 7 carcinomas foliculares tiroideos. La técnica de plata fue la original de Ploton (1986) con viraje con cloruro de oro, fijación con tiosulfato sódico y contraste con rojo nuclear extra. Se evaluaron mediante microscopía óptica en 100 células tumorales por caso: número de puntos AgNOR por núcleo, localización, distribución y número de núcleos con 5 o más puntos AgNOR. Resultados: El número de puntos AgNOR por núcleo resultó significativamente mayor en los carcinomas que en los adenomas foliculares, así como el número de núcleos con 5 o más puntos AgNOR por cada 100 células. El número de núcleos con puntos AgNOR agrupados (versus dispersos) fue mayor en los carcinomas que en los adenomas, mostrando los carcinomas mayor cantidad de puntos localizados en el centro del núcleo y menor proporción de casos con un punto AgNOR único. La antigüedad de los casos de archivo no afectó negativamente los resultados de la técnica. Conclusiones: En las neoplasias foliculares tiroideas el número medio de puntos AgNOR por núcleo, el número de núcleos con 5 o más puntos AgNOR y la disposición agrupada de los mismos pueden ser útiles en la distinción entre adenomas y carcinomas tiroideos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;35(1): 95-100, ene.-mar. 2002. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140676</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de regiones organizadoras nucleolares argirófilas (AgNORs) en neoplasias foliculares tiroideas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55015^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4839^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31683^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9884^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
