<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155805</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eating practices of adolescents of Cantabria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive. To analyse some food practices, by age and sex, in primary and secondary schools adolescents in Cantabria, who are participating in the &#145;Adolescents Health Habits Promotion since Education field&#146; project. Methodology. A cross-sectional study was carried out, analysing a sample of 1101 adolescents: 568 (51.6%) were men and 533 (48.4%) were women, aged between 12 and 17, attending 16 different primary and secondary education centers in Cantabria, by means of questionnaire. Results. Adolescents usually eats between 4 and 5 times a day. They use between 10 to 15 minutes in having breakfast, between 30 to 35 minutes in having lunch and dinner on school days. A high percentage have breakfast alone on school days. The main eats were carried on at home. Soft drinks and sweet are the main purchase with their pocket money. Almost always, the mother is charged of buying the foods, preparing the meals and decide the morning and the afternoon snacks. Pizza and fried potatoes are considerated as most taste, whereas hot dog and hamburger are considerated as less healthy. The 58.6% of adolescents having dinner watching television. Conclusions. In the food behavior study, it is necessary to analyse the influence of other factors which, in many occasions, are behind of dietetic recommendations and the almost always are ignored. Food practices as we have analysed permit, when these are carry out in a right way, an important improve in the people nutritional health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Redondo Figuero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casuso Ruiz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobaler Castañeda, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rufino Rivas, PM de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Benito, LA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mico DÍaz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Pablos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amigo Lanza, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noriega Borge, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaen Canser, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcines Medrano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antolín Guerra, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hijano Bandera, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar determinadas prácticas alimentarias en adolescentes escolarizados en centros de educación pública de Cantabria, participantes en el Proyecto &#145;Promoción de Hábitos Saludables en Adolescentes desde el Ámbito Educativo&#146;. Sujetos. Se realizó un estudio transversal, analizando una muestra de 1.101 adolescentes: 568 (51,6%) varones y 533 (48,4%) mujeres, de edades comprendidas entre los 10 y los 17 años, escolarizados en dieciséis centros de enseñanza primaria y secundaria, mediante un cuestionario autocumplimentado. Resultados. Los adolescentes suelen realizar entre cuatro (41,5%) y cinco (31,6%) ingestas diarias. Durante los días de colegio, el 34% emplea entre diez y quince minutos en desayunar, y entre 30 y 35 minutos en comer (33,5%) y cenar (23%). Un elevado porcentaje (49,4%) de adolescentes desayunaba en soledad durante los días lectivos. Las principales ingestas alimenticias se realizan en el hogar. Las bebidas no alcohólicas (53,6%) y los dulces (42%) son los principales destinos de su dinero de bolsillo. En la casi totalidad de los hogares, es la madre la que se encarga de la compra de los alimentos, de la preparación de las comidas y de decidir tanto el almuerzo como la merienda. La pizza (72,6%) y las patatas fritas (70,8%) son los alimentos considerados más ricos entre los analizados, mientras que el perrito caliente (49,4%) y la hamburguesa (48,5%) son considerados como los menos sanos. El 58,6% de los encuestados cena viendo la televisión. Conclusión. En el estudio del comportamiento alimentario es necesario analizar la influencia de otros factores que, en muchas ocasiones, están detrás de las recomendaciones dietéticas y que casi siempre son ignorados. Prácticas alimentarias como las analizadas en el presente estudio, permiten, cuando estas se desarrollan de forma adecuada, una mejora sustancial en la salud alimentaria y nutricional de las personas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;56(236): 146-156, feb. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prácticas alimentarias de los adolescentes de Cantabria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
