<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158511</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Pacemaker Registry. Thirteenth Official Report of the Spanish Society of Cardiology Working Group on Cardiac Pacing (2015)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: We describe the results of the analysis of the devices implanted and conveyed to the Spanish Pacemaker Registry in 2015. Methods: The report is based on the processing of information provided by the European Pacemaker Patient Identification Card. Results: We received information from 111 hospitals, with a total of 12 555 cards, representing 32.1% of all the estimated activity. The use of conventional generators and resynchronization devices was 820 and 73 units per million population, respectively. The mean age of the patients receiving an implantation was 77.7 years, and more than 50% of the devices were implanted in patients over 80 years of age. Overall, 58.6% of the implants and 58.8% of the replacements were performed in men. All of the endocardial leads employed were bipolar, 81.5% had an active fixation system, and 16.5% were compatible with magnetic resonance. Although dual chamber sequential pacing continues to be more widespread, pacing with VVI/R mode is used because up to 23.8% of the patients with sinus node disease are in sinus rhythm, as are 24.1% of those with atrioventricular block. Conclusions: The total use of pacemaker generators in Spain has increased by about 5% with respect to 2014. The majority of the leads implanted are of active fixation, and less than 20% are protected from magnetic resonance. The factors directly related to the selection of pacing mode are age and sex. In around 20% of patients, the choice of the pacing mode could be improved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano Pérez, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pombo Jiménez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coma Samartín, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fidalgo Andrés, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente Carreño, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Se describe el resultado del análisis de los dispositivos implantados y remitidos al Registro Español de Marcapasos en 2015. Métodos: Se basa en el procesado de la información que aporta la Tarjeta Europea del Paciente Portador de Marcapasos. Resultados: Se recibió información de 111 centros hospitalarios, con un total de 12.555 tarjetas, el 32,1% de la actividad estimada. El consumo de generadores convencionales y dispositivos de resincronización fue de 820 y 73 unidades por millón de habitantes respectivamente. La media de edad de los pacientes que recibieron un implante fue 77,7 años y más del 50% de los dispositivos se implantaron en mayores de 80 años. El 58,6% de los implantes y el 58,8% de los recambios se realizaron en varones. Los cables endocavitarios utilizados fueron bipolares, el 81,5% con sistema de fijación activa y el 16,5%, compatibles con resonancia magnética. Aunque la estimulación secuencial bicameral sigue siendo mayoritaria, se estimula en modo VVI/R pese a estar en ritmo sinusal al 23,8% de los pacientes con enfermedad del nódulo sinusal y el 24,1% de aquellos con bloqueo auriculoventricular. Conclusiones: El consumo total de generadores de marcapasos en España ha aumentado en un 5% con respecto a 2014. La mayor parte de los cables implantados son de fijación activa y menos del 20% tienen protección para la resonancia magnética. Los factores directamente relacionados con la elección del modo de estimulación son la edad y el sexo. En alrededor del 20% de los casos podría mejorarse la elección del modo de estimulación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;69(12): 1190-1203, dic. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158511</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro Español de Marcapasos. XIII  Informe Oficial de la Sección de Estimulación Cardiaca de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología (2015)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10326</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54283</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27794^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
