<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036261</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hiperprolactinemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hyperprolactinemia is a frequent problem in daily clinical practice. There are several causes of hyperprolactinemia, the most common of which are medications. Consequently, a detailed history must be taken to guide diagnosis. In women the main symptoms are the association of oligomenorrhea/amenorrhea, galactorrhea and infertility while men usually present compression symptoms (vision loss, headache or neurological deficit). A thorough history and physical examination, routine laboratory investigations thyroid&#150;stimulatinghormone determination, and pregnancy test allow can rule out all causes of hyperprolactinemia except hypothalamus&#150;pituitary disease. When no evident cause of secondary hyperprolactinemia is found, hypothalamus-pituitary magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) should be performed and patients should be diagnosed with idiopathic hyperprolactinemia only when MRI is negative. Treatment of secondary hyperprolactinemia should be etiologic. Medical therapy with dopamine agonists is currently the treatment of choice for prolactinomas and idiopathic hyperprolactinemia. Transsphenoidal surgery is suitable only when there is resistance or intolerance to dopamine agonists and in some cases of pre-gestational microadenoma. Radiotherapy is suitable in highly invasive, resistant tumors that have not responded to medical or surgical treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-García, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiperprolactinemia es un motivo de consulta frecuente en la práctica diaria. Las causas de hiperprolactinemia son múltiples; la causa más frecuente es la toma de fármacos, por lo que es necesario realizar una historia clínica detallada a fin de orientar al diagnóstico. En la mujer, los síntomas más frecuentes son la oligomenorrea/amenorrea, la galactorrea y la infertilidad, mientras que en el varón predominan los síntomas compresivos (pérdida de visión, cefaleas, déficits neurológicos). Una historia clínica detallada, junto con la exploración clínica y la determinación de bioquímica básica, tirotropina y test de embarazo, permite excluir todas las causas de hiperprolactinemia excepto las secundarias a la enfermedad hipotálamo-hipofisaria. Cuando no se encuentra causa de la hiperprolactinemia debe realizarse una resonancia magnética nuclear del área hipotálamo-hipofisaria, y sólo en caso de que ésta sea negativa se diagnosticará al paciente de hiperprolactinemia idiopática. El tratamiento debe ser etiológico en las hiperprolactinemias secundarias. El tratamiento médico con agonistas dopaminérgicos es, hoy día, el tratamiento de elección en los prolactinomas y en la hiperprolactinemia idiopática. La cirugía transesfenoidal sólo está indicada en casos de resistencia o intolerancia a los agonistas dopaminérgicos y en algunos casos de microadenoma pregestación. La radioterapia sólo está indicada en tumores resistentes muy invasivos, que no responden a cirugía o tratamiento médico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(2): 59-64, feb. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036261</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperprolactinemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d20186^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20186^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23803^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23803^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5826^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
