<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92330</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bilateral primary renal lymphoma: case report and bibliographic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To review the presentation, diagnosis and treatment of primary renal lymphoma through a new case report.METHODS: We report the case of a 73-year-old man who presented at A&amp;E with constitutional symptoms and weight loss of 9 kilograms over 3 months.RESULTS: Laboratory analysis showed impaired renal function, anemia and hypercalcemia. Imaging tests showed a large solid mass in the right perirenal area with infiltration of the parenchyma and Gerota`s fascia surrounding the hilum of the kidney, as well as a solid mass in the inferior pole of the left kidney. Pathology showed the presence of lymphoid-like monomorphic cells. After establishing the diagnosis of bilateral primary renal lymphoma it was decided to start treatment with CHOP-Rituximab-type combination chemotherapy.                                          CONCLUSIONS: Primary renal lymphoma is a rare entity and the diagnostic technique of choice is CT. Definitive diagnosis is confirmed on histology. In view of its aggressive nature and poor prognosis, it is important to make an early diagnosis in order to start treatment promptly. The treatment of choice is systemic chemotherapy using a CHOP regimen(AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soto Delgado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Escudero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas Martínez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Romero, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Jiménez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Revisar la forma de presentación, diagnóstico y tratamiento del linfoma renal primario mediante la presentación de un nuevo caso.MÉTODOS: Presentamos el caso de un de 73 años que acudió a Urgencias por síndrome constitucional y pérdida de peso de 9 kilos de 3 meses de evolución.RESULTADOS: En la analítica sanguínea se evidencia deterioro de la función renal, anemia e hipercalcemia. Las pruebas de imagen realizadas evidencian una gran masa solida perirrenal derecha con infiltración del parénquima incluida en la fascia de Gerota que engloba el hilio renal, además de una masa solida en el polo inferior del riñon izquierdo. El estudio anatomopatologico revela la presencia de células monomorfas de naturaleza linfoide. Tras establecer el diagnostico de linfoma renal primario bilateral se decide iniciar tratamiento con poliquimioterapia tipo CHOP-Rituximab.CONCLUSIONES: El linfoma renal primario es una entidad poco frecuente cuya técnica diagnostica de elección es el TC. El diagnostico definitivo se establece mediante estudio histológico. Dado su carácter agresivo y su mal pronóstico es importante realizar un diagnostico temprano para iniciar de forma precoz el tratamiento. La terapia de elección es la quimioterapia sistémica basada en el régimen CHOP(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(9): 904-907, nov. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma renal primario bilateral: aportación de un nuevo caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7114^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32961^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
