<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157342</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of multiple myeloma following an osteolytic mandibular lesion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. Multiple myeloma is a neoplasic proliferation of plasma cells with systemic repercussion and osteolytic lesions. The initial diagnosis by a mandibular lesion is extremely rare. Therefore we present a clinical case of multiple myeloma diagnosed following pain and swelling from an ostelytic mandibular lesion, and we review the literature in order establish a clinical profile and a typical radiological image that would allow us to suspect the diagnosis with more certainty. Material and methods. A 46 year-old woman comes to the Emergency Department complaining about preauricular pain and swelling. The orthopantomography shows a radiolucid multilolocular image along the mandibulary ramus and condyle. The histology and extension follow up concludes with a multiple myeloma diagnosis. A systematic review of Pubmed database was made searching for mandibular lesion at initial diagnosis of multiple myeloma within the last 5 years. Results. We found 13 cases including ours The mean age was 61 years with a slight male predominance; the most common clinical presentation was a firm to hard mandibular swelling with or without mucosal ulceration; and the most characteristic radiological image was a uni or multilocular osteolysis, with periostic reaction in one case. Conclusions. A mandibular lesion as a first sign of multiple myeloma is infrequent. Nevertheless, a maxilofacial surgeon should suspect a plasma cell neoplasia in cases of mandibular osteolytic images and start further studying without delay (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bellotti Mustecic, Marco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Guerra, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zylberberg, Ian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marinescu, Bogdan Stavaru</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sastre Pérez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Diez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El mieloma múltiple es una neoplasia de células plasmáticas con repercusión sistémica y lesiones osteolíticas. Su diagnóstico a raíz de una lesión mandibular es bastante infrecuente. Por ello presentamos un caso de mieloma múltiple diagnosticado a partir de sintomatología dolorosa e inflamatoria por una lesión osteolítica en la rama mandibular y revisamos la literatura para establecer el perfil clínico e imagen radiológica típica que nos faciliten sospechar el diagnóstico con más certeza. Material y métodos. Mujer de 46 años acude al servicio de Urgencias por inflamación y dolor preauricular. La ortopantomografía muestra una imagen radiolúcida multilobulada a lo largo de la rama y cóndilo mandibulares. El estudio anatomopatológico y de extensión desenmascaran un mieloma múltiple. Se hace además una revisión de la base de datos Pubmed para casos de diagnóstico de mieloma múltiple a partir de una lesión mandibular en los últimos 5 años. Resultados. Se encontraron 13 casos incluyendo el presente. La edad media era de 61 años con ligero predominio del sexo masculino; la clínica más frecuenta era inflamación indurada de la región mandibular afectada con o sin ulceración mucosa, y la imagen radiológica característica osteólisis uni o multilocular, en un caso con reacción perióstica. Conclusiones. La presentación inicial del mieloma múltiple mediante una lesión mandibular es poco frecuente. Sin embargo, el cirujano maxilofacial debe sospechar una neoplasia de células plasmáticas ante imágenes radiolúcidas mandibulares y no demorar un estudio más exhaustivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;38(4): 213-217, oct.-dic. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157342</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico de mieloma múltiple a raíz de una lesión osteolítica mandibular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10194^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11388^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11388^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11388^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10194^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23440^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10194^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
