<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117537</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ophathalmological pathology in the work related environment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The ocular pathology of occupational cause is a major economic and social problem despite the protective measures which recommend the use of protective equipment. According to The Group for the Multicentric Study of Ocular Trauma in Spain, work related accidents are the first cause of ocular trauma , representing 23,2% of the total. Ocular injuries related to the work environment are demonstrated to be more frequent in the metal industry. The prevalence of the ophthalmological pathology in the work related environment is more frequent in men with the medium age of 35 years. The welders have a higher risk of developing cataracts comparing to other workers. The constant use of protective equipment could prevent 2/3 of the work related accidents. Therefore the protective measures have to be focused in the constant usage of ocular protection during the activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marin, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marin, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La patología ocular de causa ocupacional constituye un problema económico y social mayor a pesar de las medidas de prevención que obligan la utilización de equipos de protección. Según el Grupo para el Estudio Multicéntrico de los Traumatismos Oculares en España (GEMTO), los accidentes laborales suponen la primera causa de traumatismo ocular, representando el 23,2% del total. Las heridas oculares relacionadas con el medio laboral ocurren con mayor frecuencia en la industria de los metales. La prevalencia de la patología oftalmológica en el medio laboral es mayor en varones con una edad media de 35 años. Los soldadores tienen más riesgo de padecer cataratas que otros tipos de trabajadores. Los equipos de protección utilizados constantemente podrían prevenir 2/3 de los accidentes laborales. Por esto, las medidas preventivas tienen que ser enfocadas en utilizar la protección ocular adecuada constantemente durante el trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;3(3): 148-150, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología oftalmológica en el medio laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5237^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12581^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
