<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131155</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of alternatives therapies, current challenge in the management of pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pain, defined as an unpleasant sensory or emotional experience from actual or potential tissue damage, it has been the subject of multiple investigations seeking to explain its pathophysiology, from their genetic and molecular bases until their physical and biological principles, in order to develop different therapeutic options that reduce or eradicate his presentation among the population. During recent decades, the use of complementary and alternative therapies has taken strength and gained popularity, being particularly useful in some specific groups of patients, like those who have chronic pain. These therapies are constituted by a wide and varied group of therapeutic interventions such as ayurvedic medicine, homeopathy, herbal, aromatherapy, among others; it is important that health professional know it and consider it as an option in the integral management of the pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Valencia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Grisales, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopera Valle, J. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo Agudelo, E. O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego González, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sánchez, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Domínguez, G. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor, definido como una experiencia sensorial o emocional desagradable de daño tisular real o potencial, ha sido motivo de múltiples investigaciones que buscan explicar su fisiopatología, desde sus bases genéticas y moleculares, hasta sus principios físicos y biológicos, con el fin de desarrollar diferentes opciones terapéuticas que permitan disminuir o erradicar su presentación entre la población. Durante las últimas décadas, el uso de las terapias complementarias y alternativas ha tomado fuerza y ganado popularidad, siendo particularmente útiles en algunos grupos específicos de pacientes, como aquellos que presentan dolor crónico oncológico. Estas terapias están constituidas por un amplio y variado grupo de intervenciones terapéuticas tales como medicina herbal, ayurvédica, homeopatía, aromaterapia, entre otras; es importante entonces que el personal de salud las conozca y las considere como una opción en el manejo integral del dolor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;21(6): 338-344, nov.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de terapias alternativas, desafío actual en el manejo del dolor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36321^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36321^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8680</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
