<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93856</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patellar tendinopathy prevention in athletes with eccentric exercise</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: The aim of this study is to know the effect of different eccentric exercises programs in the morphology  of the patellar tendon. Methods: This is an experimental study. Eighty-five athletes were included: 25 college basketball players (GBC) and 60 college students (GCAFD) with regular sport activity (at least 3 times/week). A 12-weeks eccentric exercise program was performed. Morphology of patellar tendon was seen with ultrasound both at the beginning and at the end of the program. The difference between both groups was that in the GCAFD program, strength increased progressively, meanwhile in the GBC group it was the same during the whole 12 weeks. Results: Both tendon diameters increased with the program in the experimental GCAFD (p&lt;0.001) versus control group. The GBC showed no changes between both experimental and control group in APLONG and APTRANS, but these parameters were lower in post-test measurement in the control group (p&lt;0.05). LATMED increased in both experimental groups, GCAFD (p&lt;0.001) and GBC (p=0.042). Conclusion: In athletes without patellar tendinopathy, tendon hypertrophy is seen after a program of eccentric exercises, with increase in both anteroposterior and medial lateral diameter. An individualized program must be designed to achieve these results after the exercises (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abellán, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer el efecto de dos programas de entrenamiento excéntrico sobre la morfología del tendón rotuliano. Material y método: Estudio experimental con pre y pos-test y grupo control. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 85 sujetos deportistas; 25 jugadores de baloncesto (BC) y 60 estudiantes de educación física (CAFD) que practican ejercicio físico regulado, mínimo 3 veces por semana. El entrenamiento excéntrico llevado a cabo en ambos grupos tuvo una duración de 12 semanas entre una valoración ecográfica inicial y la final. En el grupo formado por los estudiantes de CAFD se incrementó la carga de forma progresiva que no varió en el grupo de BC. Resultados: Se encontraron diferencias significativas entre la interacción del momento de la medida y el grupo. Las mediciones ecográficas aumentaron de forma significativa (p&lt;0.001) en el grupo CAFD. El grupo experimental BC no mostró cambios, y en el grupo control obtuvo menores longitudes en el post test (p&lt;0.05). La anchura aumentó en el grupo experimental CAFD (p&lt;0.001) y en el grupo experimental BC (p=0.042). Conclusión: El entrenamiento excéntrico provoca una hipertrofia sobre el tendón en pacientes sin tendinopatía rotuliana. Estas mejoras deben basarse sobre una correcta progresión de la carga de trabajo y prestando atención de forma individualizada a cada sujeto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);22(4): 241-247, oct.-dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de la tendinopatía rotuliana con ejercicios excéntricos en deportistas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
