<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97044</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Soluble TWEAK, a new biomarker of cardiovascular risk</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective Assessment of vascular risk in asymptomatic patients and the response to medical therapy is a major challenge for prevention of cardiovascular events. Our aim was to investigate if a novel protein of TNF superfamliy, TWEAK, is differentially released by healthy versus atherosclerotic arterial walls. Moreover, we have analysed whether soluble TWEAK (sTWEAK), which could be found in plasma and serve as biomarker of atherosclerosis. Material and methods Supernatants obtained from cultured human carotid plaques and healthy arteries were analysed by ELISA. In addition, sTWEAK plasma levels were measured in subjects with carotid atherosclerosis (N=30), patients with endothelial dysfunction (N=200) and asymptomatic patients (N=106) and compared with healthy subjects (N=28). Results and conclusions TWEAK concentrations were decreased in supernatants from carotid atherosclerotic plaques compared with healthy arteries. Furthermore, measurement of sTWEAK in plasma showed a reduced concentration in subjects with carotid stenosis compared with healthy subjects. Moreover, sTWEAK concentrations were diminished in asymptomatic subjects in whom intima-media thickness was measured and in subjects with endothelial dysfunction.Results and conclusion These results suggest that sTWEAK could be a potential biomarker of atherosclerosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Egido, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Colio,  Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñóz-García, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Ventura,  José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo La valoración del riesgo vascular en pacientes asintomáticos y la respuesta a la intervención terapéutica es uno de los mayores objetivos para la prevención de eventos cardiovasculares. Nuestro objetivo fue evaluar si una nueva proteína descrita de la superfamilia del factor de necrosis tumoral, TWEAK, se secreta diferencialmente por la pared vascular sana en comparación con la lesión aterosclerótica humana, y si las concentraciones plasmáticas de esta proteína pueden servir como biomarcador de aterosclerosis. Material y métodos Mediante técnica de radioinmunoanálisis analizamos el sobrenadante procedente del cultivo de placas carotídeas y de arterias sanas humanas. Además, analizamos la concentración plasmática de TWEAK soluble (sTWEAK) en pacientes con aterosclerosis carotídea (n=30), pacientes que presentaban disfunción endotelial (n=200) y sujetos asintomáticos (n=106), y se compararon con sujetos sanos (n=83). Resultados y conclusión Los niveles de sTWEAK se encontraban disminuidos en el sobrenadante procedente de placas carotídeas comparadas con arterias sanas. Posteriormente, el análisis de la concentración plasmática de sTWEAK mostró que sujetos con estenosis carotídea tenían niveles reducidos en comparación con sujetos sanos. Además, los niveles plasmáticos de sTWEAK se encontraron disminuidos en sujetos asintomáticos en los cuales se midió el espesor íntima-media (un índice de aterosclerosis subclínica) y en sujetos en los cuales se había medido su función endotelial. Estos resultados sugieren que sTWEAK puede ser un nuevo marcador potencial de aterosclerosis subclínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);22(3): 99-104, mayo-jun. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97044</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">TWEAK soluble, un nuevo biomarcador de riesgo cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30211^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38737^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
