<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124456</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biochemical and nutritional markers and antioxidant activity in metabolic syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives1) Nutritional assessment of the diet followed by patients with metabolic syndrome, and 2) biochemical analysis of the oxidation-reduction level in patients with metabolic syndrome. Material and methods A cross-sectional study was conducted in patients with metabolic syndrome in Murcia. Fifty-three patients, 33 with and 20 without (control group) metabolic syndrome, were selected. The intervention consisted of completion of a recall survey and a test to nutritionally assess dietary intake. Anthropometric and laboratory variables, including those related to antioxidant activity, were also tested. Results Antioxidant activity was within normal limits in both groups (1.7 ± 0.2 mmol/L in the control group and 1.8 ± 0.1 mmol/L in the metabolic syndrome group) (NS). Superoxide dismutase levels were not significantly different between the groups. Mean glutathione reductase levels (U/L) were higher in the control group as compared to patients with metabolic syndrome (P &lt; .05). As regards oxidative stress biomarkers, mean isoprostane levels were higher in the control group (4.9 ± 6.2 ng/mL) than in metabolic syndrome patients (3.5 ± 3.9 ng/mL) (P &lt; .05). Oxidized LDL values tended to be higher in metabolic syndrome patients (96 ± 23.2 U/L) as compared to the control group (86.2 ± 17.3  U/L), but differences were not significant. Conclusions There is a trend to a poorer nutritional and biochemical profile in patients with metabolic syndrome, who also tend to have a greater degree of oxidative stress (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leal Hernández, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Jara, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abellán Alemán, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zafrilla Rentero, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mulero Cánovas, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabé García, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos 1) Valorar nutricionalmente la dieta seguida por los pacientes con síndrome metabólico, y 2) analizar bioquímicamente el nivel de oxidación-reducción en los pacientes con síndrome metabólico. Material y método Se trata de un estudio transversal realizado a pacientes con síndrome metabólico de la Región de Murcia. Se seleccionaron 53 individuos, 33 con síndrome metabólico y 20 sin él (grupo control). La intervención realizada consistió en la cumplimentación de una encuesta recordatorio y un test para valorar nutricionalmente la ingesta dietética, además de la determinación de variables antropométricas y analíticas que incluyen variables relacionas con la actividad antioxidante. Resultados La actividad antioxidante en ambos grupos analizados está dentro de los límites normales (1,7 ± 0,2 mmol/l en el grupo control y 1,8 ± 0,1 mmol/l en el grupo con síndrome metabólico; ns). La enzima superóxido dismutasa no presenta diferencias significativas entre ambos grupos. Los valores medios de glutatión reductasa (U/l) son superiores en el grupo control que en los pacientes con SM (p &lt; 0,05). Respecto a los biomarcadores de estrés oxidativo, los valores medios de isoprostanos son superiores en el grupo control (4,9 ± 6,2 ng/ml) que en los pacientes con SM (3,5 ± 3,9 ng/ml; p &lt; 0,05). Los valores de LDL oxidadas tienden a ser superiores en los enfermos con SM (96 ± 23,2 U/l) que en el grupo control (86,2 ± 17,3 U/l), no observándose diferencias significativas. Conclusiones Existe una tendencia a un peor perfil nutricional y bioquímico de los pacientes que presentan síndrome metabólico. También tienden a presentar un mayor grado de estrés oxidativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(6): 302-308, jun.-jul. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124456</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores bioquímicos, nutricionales y actividad antioxidante en el síndrome metabólico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55100</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36046^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
