<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149727</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Compliance with the guidelines of the European Society of Cardiology and morbidity and mortality from infectious endocarditis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The antibiotic treatment recommended for infectious endocarditis (IE) has a low level of evidence. Our objective was to determine whether compliance with the recommendations of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) was related to lower inhospital morbidity and mortality for this disease. Methods. A retrospective study was conducted on 162 cases of IE diagnosed between 2005 and 2014. A propensity score-matching analysis was performed to determine the effect of treatment on hospital mortality. Results. There were no differences in terms of disease complications between the treatment groups. Hospital mortality was 29.2% when the treatment was adjusted to the guidelines and 28.2% when the treatment was not adjusted (OR=1.048; 95%CI: 0.442-2.484; P=.916). Conclusion. The use of the ESC guidelines does not appear to translate into a reduction in hospital morbidity and mortality due to IE when compared with alternative antibiotic treatment regimens (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farrais Villalba, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ode Febles, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Montero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballo Arzola, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Esteban, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina García, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El tratamiento antibiótico recomendado para la endocarditis infecciosa (EI) tiene un nivel de evidencia bajo. Nuestro objetivo fue comprobar si la adherencia a las recomendaciones de la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología (ESC) se relaciona con una menor morbimortalidad intrahospitalaria de la enfermedad. Métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de 162 casos de EI diagnosticados entre 2005 y 2014. Se realizó un análisis de propensity score matching para determinar el efecto del tratamiento en la mortalidad intrahospitalaria. Resultados. No hubo diferencias en cuanto a complicaciones de la enfermedad entre los grupos de tratamiento. La mortalidad intrahospitalaria fue del 29,2% cuando el tratamiento fue ajustado a las guías, y del 28,2% cuando no lo fue (OR=1,048; IC95%: 0,442-2,484; p=0,916). Conclusión. El uso de las guías de la ESC no parece traducirse en una reducción de la morbimortalidad intrahospitalaria por EI cuando se compara con regímenes de tratamiento antibiótico alternativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;216(1): 15-18, ene.-feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento de las guías de la Sociedad Europea de Cardiología y morbimortalidad por endocarditis infecciosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54535^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54535^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2353^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34257^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
