<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152801</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nicotine acetylcholine receptors and neuropsychiatric disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. This review will be attempt to describe the current knowledge on the neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors (nAChRs) and their involvement in the pathogenesis of a number of neuropsychiatric disorders and the properties of recently synthesized subtype-selective nAChRs. The potential brain therapeutic targets for nAChRs are reviewed. Development. The nAChRs belong to a family of ligand-gated channels which are widely distributed in brain. Multiple subtypes of these receptors exist, each with diverse structures, individual pharmacological and functional properties. In contrast to the muscular nAChRs, the physiological functions of nAChRs are not well defined to date. In addition, the majority of evidence defining potential therapeutic targets involving nAChRs has resulted from studies on the effects of nicotine in a variety of preclinical and, to a lesser extent, clinical models. The preclinical research continues to focus on nicotine and a number of novel nAChRs agonists have been synthesized in the last few years that may have therapeutic potential in a number of neurological and psychiatric conditions. Conclusions. The structure of nAChRs and the considerable molecular diversity in subunits offers the possibility of a large number of nAChRs subtypes, which, based on pharmacological precedent, may serve a variety of discrete functions within the brain and thus represent novel targets for therapeutic agents. A promising trend for therapy is the synthesis of new agonists with high nAChRs subtype selectivity, which do not exhibit nicotine&#146;s side effects and do show clear beneficial actions in the neuropsychiatric disorders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Palacios, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonilla Jaime, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. En esta revisión se pretende describir los conocimientos actuales de los receptores neuronales nicotínicos de la acetilcolina (nAChR) y su implicación en la patogénesis de diversos trastornos neuropsiquiátricos, así como las propiedades de los recién sintetizados nAChR de subtipo selectivo. Se revisan también los posibles blancos terapéuticos cerebrales para los nAChR. Desarrollo. Existen múltiples tipos de estos receptores, cada uno con diversas estructuras y unas propiedades farmacológicas y funcionales individuales. En contraste con los nAChR musculares, las funciones fisiológicas de los nAChR aún no han sido bien definidas. Además, la mayor parte de los datos que definen los posibles blancos terapéuticos que implican los nAChR provienen de estudios sobre los efectos de la nicotina en varios modelos preclínicos y, aunque en menor grado, clínicos. Las investigaciones preclínicas siguen centrándose en la nicotina y en los últimos años se han sintetizado diversos agonistas nuevos de los nAChR que podrían tener un valor terapéutico potencial en diversas patologías neurológicas y psiquiátricas. Conclusiones. La estructura de los nAChR y la elevada diversidad molecular en las subunidades facilitan la posibilidad de que exista un gran número de subtipos de nAChR, que, en base a los precedentes farmacológicos, pueden desempeñar diversas funciones discretas en el cerebro y por lo tanto representar blancos nuevos para las sustancias terapéuticas. Una tendencia esperanzadora en la terapéutica es la síntesis de nuevos agonistas con un elevado grado de selectividad de subtipos de nAChR, los cuales no parecen tener los efectos adversos de la nicotina y sí que exhiben una actividad beneficiosa clara en los trastornos neuropsiquiátricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(12): 1146-1160, dic. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152801</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Receptores nicotínicos cerebrales y trastornos neuropsiquiátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33840^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32112^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29543^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23765</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35349^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33840^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35349^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32112^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29543^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
