<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117270</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">IgM nephropathy in children: clinicopathologic analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: IgM nephropathy (IgMN) is a glomerulonephritis characterized by diffuse mesangial deposits of immunoglobulin M (IgM), which usually presents with nephrotic range proteinuria and, according to some previous studies, occurs most often in patients who are resistant or dependent of steroid treatment. Aim: To perform a clinical, histological and inmunopathological description, and assess response to steroid treatment of pediatric patients diagnosed with nephrotic syndrome and diffuse mesangial deposits of IgM. Methods: This is a descriptive, retrospective study done in two hospitals. Clinical data were taken from medical records. All the slides with the histologic sections were re-evaluated. Results: thirteen children were included in this study. IgMN corresponded to 5.17% of all pediatric renal biopsies. The age of patients ranged from 1 year to 12 years (median: 2 years), 46,15% were women. The most common morphological finding was diffuse mesangial hypercellularity (46,1%), followed by focal segmental glomerulosclerosis (30,8%) and minimal glomerular changes (23,1%). All patients received steroids, in 4 cases (30,7%) as the only immunosuppressant  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Gayubo, Ana K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serna-Higuita, Lina M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vélez-Echeverri, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prada, M. Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanegas-Ruiz, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Luis F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa, Carolina L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La nefropatía IgM (NIgM) es una glomerulonefritis caracterizada por depósitos mesangiales difusos de inmunoglobulina M (IgM), que suele manifestarse con proteinuria en rango nefrótico y que, según algunos trabajos previos, se presenta más frecuentemente en pacientes que son resistentes o dependientes del tratamiento con esteroides. Objetivo: Realizar una descripción clínica, histológica e inmunopatológica, y evaluar la respuesta al tratamiento esteroideo de los pacientes pediátricos con diagnóstico de síndrome nefrótico y depósitos mesangiales y difusos de IgM. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo, retrospectivo, realizado en dos centros hospitalarios, donde se analizaron los registros clínicos de pacientes pediátricos con diagnóstico de NIgM y se revaluaron los cortes histológicos. Resultados: Trece niños fueron incluidos en el presente estudio. La NIgM correspondió al 5,17 % de todas las biopsias renales pediátricas. La edad de los pacientes estuvo entre 1 y 12 años (mediana: 2 años); el 46,7 % fueron mujeres. El hallazgo morfológico más frecuente fue hipercelularidad mesangial difusa (46,1 %), seguido de glomeruloesclerosis focal y segmentaria (30,8 %) y cambios glomerulares mínimos (23,1 %). Todos los pacientes recibieron esteroides, en 4 de ellos (30,7 %) como el único medicamento inmunosupresor; 3 (23,1 %) recibieron además ciclofosfamida, 5 (38,4 %) micofenolato y 1 (7,7 %) ciclosporina. Siete pacientes (53,8 %) presentaron recaídas frecuentes, 5 (38,5 %) fueron corticorresistentes y 1 (7,7 %) corticodependiente. Dos pacientes (15,38 %) presentaron alteración crónica  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;33(4): 532-538, jul.-ago. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117270</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nefropatía IgM en niños: análisis clinicopatológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6065^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23256^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9596^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
