<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102747</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebrovascular disease in childhood: a retrospective analysis of hospital admissions in a tertiary hospital in the community of Valencia in the last ten years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There has been increasing interest in stroke in children in the last few years. A literature review produced little information on risk factors and other clinical questions. The aim of this study is to describe the characteristics of stroke in children, mainly in order to identify the risk factors, clinical presentation and outcomes. Patients and methods: A retrospective study was conducted on patients admitted to the Hospital La Fe in Valencia between January 2000 to September 2010 with the diagnosis of ischaemic or haemorrhagic stroke. Results: A total of 76 patients were identified, of whom 44.7% had an ischaemic stroke and 55.3% had a haemorrhagic one. The average age of presentation was 6.8 years; 8.4 years for haemorrhagic strokes and 4.7 years for ischaemic strokes. Headache was the most frequent symptom of presentation. The most frequent risk factor was vascular malformations in haemorrhagic cerebral stroke, and vascular and cardiac disorders in ischaemic stroke. A study of prothrombotic factors was conducted on 34 patients, which was positive in 64.7% of them. As regards outcome, 17% of the patients died; only 3 patients had a secondary epilepsy, and 31% and 60% of the haemorrhagic and ischaemic stokes, respectively, had a hemiparesis. Conclusions: In this study we identified the principal risk factors as well as, the age of presentation, symptomatology and outcome. We would like to emphasise that the age of presentation was earlier in ischaemic strokes than in haemorrhagic ones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tellez De Meneses Lorenzo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vazquez Costa, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mulas Delgado, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Sebastiá, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Vila, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dasí Carpio, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En los últimos años ha aumentado el interés por el ictus en la infancia. La revisión de la literatura aporta poca información sobre factores de riesgo y otros aspectos de interés clínico. El objetivo es describir las características del ictus en niños con el objetivo de identificar factores de riesgo, presentación clínica y el pronóstico. Pacientes y métodos: Se llevó a cabo un estudio retrospectivo entre los pacientes ingresados en el hospital La Fe entre enero de 2000 y septiembre de 2010 con los diagnósticos de ictus, isquémicos o hemorrágicos. Resultados: Un total de 76 pacientes cumplían los criterios de inclusión, 44,7% presentaron un ictus isquémico y 55,3% fue hemorrágico. La edad media de presentación fue de 6,8 años, 8,4 años para los hemorrágicos y 4,7 años para los isquémicos. La cefalea fue el síntoma de presentación más frecuente. El principal factor de riesgo fue la malformación vascular en los ictus hemorrágicos y las vasculopatías y cardiopatías en los isquémicos. En 34 pacientes se llevó a cabo un estudio de trombofilia y en un 64,7%, de estos, el estudio fue positivo. Respecto al pronóstico, el 17% de los pacientes falleció, solamente tres pacientes presentaron una epilepsia secundaria y el 31 y 60% de los infartos hemorrágicos e isquémicos, respectivamente, desarrollaron una hemiparesia. Conclusiones: En este estudio hemos identificado los principales factores de riesgo, así como edad de presentación, sintomatología y pronóstico. Queremos destacar la edad de presentación más precoz en los ictus isquémicos frente a los hemorrágicos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);77(2): 75-82, ago. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102747</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad cerebrovascular en la infancia. Análisis retrospectivo de los ingresos hospitalarios en los últimos diez años en un hospital terciario de la Comunidad Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30834</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34218^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22316^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15059^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15059^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
