<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64197</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The retinoic acid (RA) signaling pathway regulates the transcription of target genes which control lipid metabolism mediated by the ligand of the nuclear receptors, retinoic X receptor and RA receptor, and the cofactor cellular RA binding protein-II. Interestingly, this signaling pathway has been associated with disorders of lipid metabolism such as familial combined hyperlipidemia (FCHL) and the hyperlipidemia secondary to antiretroviral HIV treatment with protease inhibitors (PI). We sought evidence for the hypothesis that the CRABP2 gene is involved in the regulation of lipid metabolism. Subjects and methods. We performed association studies using the promoter ­394T&gt;C polymorphism of the CRABP2 gene in 3 different cohorts (299 healthy males, 182 HIV-infected patients and 151 patients with familial hypercholesterolemia [FH]). All cholesterol measurements were in the absence of any lipid lowering agents. ANOVA was performed on the data adjusted for age, BMI, gender and PI use. Results. The frequency of the C allele was 0.03 in the 3 groups. Among healthy males, carriers of the C allele had 9% higher total plasma cholesterol (p = 0.027) and 13% higher LDLc concentrations (p = 0.020). In HIV-infected patients, a multivariate analysis of 4 measurements over a one year period showed that carriers of the C allele had significantly higher LDLc of between 10 and 31% (p = 0.001) compared with non-carriers of the allele. FH patients who were carriers of the C allele had a 16% increase in LDLc (p = 0.038). The C allele was significantly over-represented among hypercholesterolemic patients (p = 0.001). Conclusions. Our results show that the CRABP2 gene, a member of the retinoid signaling pathway, is associated with increased plasma LDLc concentrations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guardiola, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Winklhofer-Roob, Brigitte M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masana, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Villaverde, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blai Coll, Blai</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribalta, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Ballart, Joan D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar, Juliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Civeira, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferré, Raimon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Edmond Rock, Edmond</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pocoví, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La vía de señalización del ácido retinoico (AR) media la transcripción inducida por ligando de genes del metabolismo lipídico a través de los receptores nucleares, receptor X de retinoico y receptor de AR, y del coactivador proteína de unión al AR tipo II. Se ha establecido una asociación entre esta vía de señalización y las alteraciones lipídicas en trastornos como la hiperlipemia familar combinada y la hiperlipemia inducida por el tratamiento con inhibidores de la proteasa (IP) en pacientes con infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH). Nuestro objetivo ha sido comprobar la hipótesis según la cual el gen CRABP2 estaría involucrado en la modulación de la dislipemia. Sujetos y métodos. Se ha realizado un estudio de asociación del polimorfismo ­394T&gt;C del promotor de CRABP2 en 3 poblaciones independientes (299 individuos sanos, 182 pacientes con infección por el VIH y 151 pacientes con hipercolesterolemia familiar [HF]). Todas las analíticas se determinaron en ausencia de tratamiento hipolipemiante. Se realizó ANOVA ajustando por edad, índice de masa corporal, sexo, y uso de IP cuando fue necesario. Resultados. La frecuencia del alelo C fue del 0,03 en los 3 grupos estudiados. Entre los individuos sanos, los portadores del alelo C presentaban un aumento en la concentración de colesterol total del 9% (p = 0,027) y de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) del 13% (p = 0,020). En los pacientes infectados por el VIH, se realizó un análisis multivariante de 4 medidas tomadas durante 1 año, y se observó que los valores de cLDL eran significativamente más elevados en los portadores del alelo C (p = 0,001), y que éstos oscilaban entre el 10 y el 31%. Asimismo, los pacientes HF portadores del alelo C presentaban un aumento significativo en la concentración de cLDL del 16% (p = 0,038). El alelo C estaba sobrerrepresentado en individuos hipercolesterolémicos (p = 0,001). Conclusiones. Nuestros resultados muestran que el gen CRABP2, involucrado en la vía de señalización del ácido retinoico, está asociado con elevadas concentraciones de cLDL en plasma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);20(2): 48-54, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64197</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8251^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4659^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14860^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31097^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31097^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
