<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056415</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Group F chronic cholesteatomatous otomastoiditis with spontaneous fistulization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic cholesteatomatous otomastoiditis is a rare entity in childhood, and its spontaneous intra- or extracranial fistulization is even more uncommon. The otologic sequelae are always important, especially when the disease is long standing. The agents causing chronic otomastoiditis are the same as those that can cause otitis. When there is associated cholesteatoma, Gram-negative and anaerobic bacilli are often present, but not group F beta-hemolytic streptococcus. The case of an 8-year-old boy with chronic cholesteatomatous otomastoiditis and spontaneous fistulization caused by group F beta-hemolytic streptococcus is reported</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Berciano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maseda Álvarez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Caro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La otomastoiditis crónica colesteatomatosa es un proceso muy poco frecuente en la infancia y menos aún su fistulización espontánea intracraneal o extracraneal. Las secuelas óticas son siempre importantes, especialmente en los casos de larga evolución.         Los patógenos responsables de la otomastoiditis crónica son los mismos que originan la otitis. Cuando se asocia a colesteatoma, es frecuente la presencia de gramnegativos y anaerobios, pero no de estreptococo betahemolítico de grupo F.         Se presenta el caso de un niño de 8 años con otomastoiditis crónica colesteatomatosa de larga evolución originada por estreptococo betahemolítico de grupo F que cursó con fistulización espontánea intracraneal y extracraneal</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(4): 378-380, oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Otomastoiditis colesteatomatosa crónica por estreptococo de grupo F con fistulización espontánea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10209^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10209^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8587^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8587^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
