<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037156</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of post-infarction coronary perfusion using quantitative analysis of myocardial echocardiography with intravenous injection of contrast</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. After a myocardial infarction, damage to the microcirculation indicates a worse prognosis. We compared the usefulness of the quantitative analysis of myocardial contrast echocardiography with intravenous injection of contrast (MCE-iv) with intracoronary injection (MCE-ic) for analyzing coronary perfusion. Patients and method. We studied 42 patients with afirst ST-elevation myocardial infarction, single-vessel disease and a patent artery (TIMI 3, stenosis 0.75) and MCE-iv (perfusion of SonoVue, single image capture in 1 out of each 6 cycles with trigger set attend-systole, perfusion considered normal if &gt; 0.9). Perfusion was considered abnormal if 2 or more segments showed altered perfusion. Results. Quantification with MCE-iv took 5 ± 1 minutes. No side effects were observed. MCE-ic was normal in 141segments (80%) out of 176 segments included in the infarcted area, whereas 35 segments (20%) showed abnormal perfusion. MCE-ic was normal in 31 patients (74%)and was altered in 11 cases (26%). Normal perfusion with MCE-iv had a sensitivity of 91%, a specificity of 84% and a kappa index of 0.67 for predicting normal perfusion with MCE-ic (r = 0.86; P&lt;.0001 between the two techniques).Conclusions. In comparison with MCE-ic, quantitative analysis of single images captured during intravenous perfusion of contrast is an easy, rapid and valid method or analyzing post infarction coronary perfusion</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Millet, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchís, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bodí, Vicent</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Losada, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chorro, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellicer, Mauricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llácer, Àngel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Tras un infarto de miocardio el daño en la microcirculación indica un peor pronóstico. Investigamos la utilidad del estudio cuantitativo de la ecografía miocárdica con inyección de contraste por vía intravenosa(EMC-i.v.) para analizar la perfusión coronaria en comparación con la inyección intracoronaria (EMC-i.c.).Pacientes y método. Estudiamos a 42 pacientes con un primer infarto con elevación del segmento ST, enfermedad de un vaso y arteria abierta (TIMI 3, estenosis 0,75) y EMC-i.v. (perfusión de SonoVue, imágenes únicas capturando 1 de cada 6 ciclos con trigger en tele sístole, perfusión normal si &gt; 0,9). Se consideró que un paciente tenía perfusión alterada si 2 o más segmentos estaban afectados. Resultados. La cuantificación de EMC-i.v. se realizó en 5 ± 1 min. No se detectaron efectos secundarios. Delos 176 segmentos del área infartada, 141 (80%) presentaron una EMC-i.c. normal y 35 (20%), alterada. Por pacientes, la EMC-i.c. fue normal en 31 (74%) casos y estaba afectada en 11 (26%). Una perfusión normal con EMC-i.v. mostró una sensibilidad del 91%, una especificidad del 84% y un índice kappa del 0,67 para predecir una perfusión normal con EMC-i.c. (r = 0,86; p &lt; 0,0001 entre ambas técnicas).Conclusiones. Un análisis cuantitativo de imágenes únicas capturadas durante una perfusión intravenosa de contraste es un método sencillo, rápido y válido para el análisis de la perfusión coronaria postinfarto al compararlo con EMC-i.c</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;58(2): 137-144, feb. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037156</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la perfusión coronaria postinfarto mediante análisis cuantitativo de la ecocardiografía miocárdica con inyección de contraste por vía intravenosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3342^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3342^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23623^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30178</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
