<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058932</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New concepts in the treatment of lupic nephropathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The therapeutic goals for a patient with newly diagnosed lupus nephritis should be to achieve a prompt renal remission, to avoid renal flares, to avoid chronic renal impairment, and to fulfil these objectives with minimal toxicity. An advance in the therapy of LN has been the introduction of concepts of induction of remission (by a sort course of vigorous immunosupression such as monthly intravenous cyclophosphamide) and maintenance of remission (by long-term administration of the same cytotoxic drug given less frequently or a potentially safer immunosupressant such as azathioprine). Mycophenolate mofetil may be an alternative to cyclophosphamide for induction and maintenance therapy of patients with proliferative LN. Optimal care of lupus nephritis patients should include non immunosuppressive measures such as the vigorous management of cardiovascular risk factors and the treatment of proteinuria</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cervera Segura, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa Garriga, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos del tratamiento en los pacientes con nefropatía lúpica (NL) deben ser la remisión precoz del brote renal y evitar la aparición de rebrotes renales y la evolución a insuficiencia renal crónica. Además estos objetivos deben conseguirse con la mínima toxicidad posible. Un avance en el tratamiento de la NL ha sido la introducción de los conceptos de inducción de la remisión (con la administración de inmunodepresores potentes como la ciclofosfamida por vía intravenosa en bolos mensuales) y de mantenimiento de la remisión (con la administración a largo plazo, menos frecuente, de la ciclofosfamida o con otros inmunodepresores menos tóxicos como la azatioprina). El micofenolato de mofetilo puede ser una alternativa a la ciclofosfamida en el tratamiento de inducción y mantenimiento de la NL proliferativa. El tratamiento de la NL también debe incluir medidas no inmunodepresoras como el control estricto de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular y de la proteinuria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(11): 570-572, dic.2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058932</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos conceptos en el tratamiento de la nefropatía lúpica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3540^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9365^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1394^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19233^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19233^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
