<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154691</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Invasive yeast infections in severely burned patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Currently, there are few studies on candidaemia in the severely burned patient. These patients share the same risk factors for invasive fungal infections as other critically ill patients, but have certain characteristics that make them particularly susceptible. These include the loss of skin barrier due to extensive burns, fungal colonisation of the latter, and the use of hydrotherapy or other topical therapies (occasionally with antimicrobials). In addition, the increased survival rate achieved in recent decades in critically burned patients due to the advances in treatment has led to the increase of invasive Candida infections. This explains the growing interest in making an earlier and more accurate diagnosis, as well as more effective treatments to reduce morbidity and mortality of candidaemia in severe burned patients. A review is presented on all aspects of the burned patient, including the predisposition and risk factors for invasive candidiasis, pathogenesis of candidaemia, underlying immunodeficiency, local epidemiology and antifungal susceptibility, evolution and prognostic factors, as well as other non-Candida yeast infections. Finally, we include specific data on our local experience in the management of candidaemia in severe burned patients, which may serve to quantify the problem, place it in context, and offer a realistic perspective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Renau, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salavert, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Vidal, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente son escasos los estudios sobre candidemia en el enfermo gran quemado. Estos pacientes, sumamente graves, además de compartir los factores de riesgo para infecciones fúngicas presentes en los pacientes críticos, poseen ciertas características que los hacen especialmente susceptibles, como son la pérdida de la barrera cutánea por las quemaduras extensas, la colonización de las mismas y el uso de hidroterapia u otras terapias tópicas (ocasionalmente con antimicrobianos). Además, el aumento de la supervivencia en el quemado crítico conseguido en las últimas décadas debido a los avances terapéuticos ha favorecido el incremento de las infecciones invasivas por Candida, por lo que existe un interés cada vez mayor por implementar un diagnóstico más precoz y preciso, así como un tratamiento más eficaz que reduzca la morbimortalidad de la candidemia en los pacientes quemados graves. Todos los aspectos sobre predisposición y riesgos infecciosos en el enfermo quemado, patogenia de la candidemia, alteración inmunitaria subyacente, epidemiología local y sensibilidad a los antifúngicos, factores de riesgo de candidiasis invasiva, evolución y factores pronóstico, además de las infecciones por otras levaduras no-Candida son incluidos en la presente revisión. Finalmente se incorporan datos concretos sobre la experiencia local en el manejo de la candidemia del paciente quemado grave que pueden servir para dimensionar el problema y ponerlo en el marco de la perspectiva real (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;33(3): 160-169, jul.-sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154691</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades invasivas por hongos levaduriformes en pacientes quemados graves</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53932^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53932^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55600^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2088^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
