<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121927</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasound diagnosis of fetal ventriculomegaly. Postnatal follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives. To determine the prevalence of fetal ventriculomegaly and identify the neurological outcomes of newborns with a prenatal diagnosis. Method. Observational study of ventriculomegaly prenatally diagnosed by ultrasound in our department between 2004 and 2012. Results. We diagnosed 61 cases of ventriculomegaly. The prevalence rate was 2.25 per 1,000. Diagnosis was made during the second trimester in 54 patients and during the third trimester in 7. Bilateral ventriculomegaly was found in 91% of the fetuses. Ventriculomegaly was mild (10-12 mm) in 79.4% and moderate (12-15 mm) in 5.6%. Severe ventriculomegaly (&gt;15 mm) or hydrocephalus was diagnosed in 15% of the fetuses. The clinical course during pregnancy was unfavorable in 13%. Associated anomalies were diagnosed in 23 cases. Conclusions. Mild, isolated and non-progressive ventriculomegaly has the best neurological prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa Pueyo, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escofet Soteras, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pina Pérez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Marín, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Azuara, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corona Martínez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Conocer la prevalencia de la ventriculomegalia fetal (VM). Estudiar la evolución de los casos diagnosticados prenatalmente y realizar el seguimiento neurológico de los nacidos vivos. Método.  Estudio observacional de los casos de VM diagnosticados prenatalmente en nuestro servicio entre 2004 y 2012. Resultados. Diagnosticamos 61 casos de VM, siendo la prevalencia del 2,25 por 1.000. En 54 pacientes el diagnóstico se realizó en el segundo trimestre y en 7 pacientes durante el tercer trimestre. La bilateralidad se observó en el 91% de los casos. En el 79,4% de casos, la VM fue leve (10-12 mm) y en un 5,6% moderada (12-15 mm). Un 15% de los fetos mostraban una VM severa (&gt; 15 mm) o hidrocefalia y en un 13% de los casos la VM evolucionó desfavorablemente durante la gestación. En 23 casos se diagnosticaron otras anomalías asociadas. Conclusiones. El pronóstico más favorable lo observamos cuando la afectación es leve, aislada y no progresiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);57(5): 202-207, mayo 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121927</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico ecográfico de la ventriculomegalia fetal. Seguimiento posnatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7002^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5426^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2591^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2591^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7002^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11704^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11704^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11704^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
