<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85197</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of the clinical applications of proteomics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The practical usefulness of the results of Proteomics in relation to health is very important. The discovery of protein markers of diseases such as cardiovascular, neurological, oncologic, metabolic, among others, has an immediate clinical application in the diagnosis, monitoring and treatment of these diseases. The Human Proteome Organization (HUPO, www.hupo.org) was established in 2001 to promote greater awareness of the importance of proteomics and opportunities in the diagnosis, prognosis and treatment of diseases. It has subsequently formed several groups: HPPP (Human Plasma Proteome Project), HLPP (Human Liver Proteome Project), PSI (Proteome Standards Initiative), HBPP (Human Brain Proteome Project) and MRPP (Mouse and Rat Proteome Project). One of the main goals of proteomics is the identification of markers of disease. One approach has been to compare the expression of proteins in normal and diseased tissues to identify proteins that are expressed abnormally and may represent new markers. Another strategy is the analysis of proteins in segregated cell lines and primary cultures and finally, obtaining serum protein profiles. Proteomic studies are gaining a higher profile in recent years, mainly in its application to human pathology. To this end a large number of studies are being conducted in human plasma, tissues and various body fluids (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>San Miguel Hernández, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Miguel, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Gil, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilidad práctica de los resultados obtenidos con la Proteómica en relación con la salud está cobrando gran importancia. El descubrimiento de marcadores proteicos de enfermedades como las cardiovasculares, las neurológicas, las oncológicas, las metabólicas, entre otras, tiene una aplicación clínica en un futuro próximo en el diagnóstico, el seguimiento y el tratamiento de estas enfermedades. La HUPO (Human Proteome Organization) (disponible en: www.hupo.org) se creó en el año 2001 para impulsar un mayor conocimiento de la importancia de la Proteómica y las oportunidades que ofrece en el diagnóstico, el pronóstico y el tratamiento de las enfermedades. Se han constituido posteriormente varios grupos: HPPP (Human Plasma Proteome Project), HLPP (Human Liver Proteome Project), PSI (Proteome Standards Initiative), HBPP (Human Brain Proteome Project) y MRPP (Mouse and Rat Proteome Project). Uno de los principales objetivos de la Proteómica es la identificación de marcadores de enfermedad. Un planteamiento ha sido comparar la expresión proteica de los tejidos normales y enfermos para identificar proteínas que se expresen de forma aberrante y que puedan representar nuevos marcadores. Otra estrategia es el análisis de las proteínas segregadas en líneas celulares y cultivos primarios y, finalmente, la obtención de perfiles proteicos en suero. Los estudios proteómicos están adquiriendo en los últimos años una gran relevancia, fundamentalmente en lo que hace referencia a su aplicación a la enfermedad humana. Con este fin se está realizando un gran número de estudios en el plasma humano, los tejidos y diversos líquidos biológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;3(1): 40-48, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85197</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de las aplicaciones clínicas de la Proteómica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33149^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33149^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37630^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4649^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33149^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25169^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
