<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137192</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-9476</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Advanced Practice Nursing is an emerging model in Spain, with great experience in the Anglo-Saxon context, which is being developed in other European countries. These new profiles are based on an advanced further training of nurses in four areas: advanced clinical competencies, clinical management, teaching and research. The Advanced Practice Nursing has two main figures: Nurse Practitioner (also known as Advanced Practitioner) and Nurse Consultant, characterized by a specific training orientate to perform tasks of greater complexity based on autonomous decision making and defined catalogue of services which goes beyond traditional activities set in our context, and where the nurse Advanced Practice leads patient assessment and follow up. The Nurse Consultant also performs health policy design and consultancy functions. Within the urologic care field, different roles have emerged in the U.S., Canada and England known as Advanced Urology Nurse or Urology Nurse Practitioner with defined professional positions and specific professional accreditation systems. These new orientation is being proposed as the key to more traditional models in many European health systems, improving access to healthcare services through a shared management of the clinical demand based on the design of a new competency map for healthcare practitioners and, therefore, contributing to the cost-efficiency of health systems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camacho-Bejarano, Rafaela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-González, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Ruiz, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Enfermería de Práctica Avanzada es un modelo emergente en España, con gran trayectoria en el contexto anglosajón, y que está empezando a desarrollarse en otros países europeos. Estos nuevos perfiles avanzados toman como base una mayor capacitación de las enfermeras en cuatro vertientes: clínica avanzada, gestión, docencia e investigación, y se materializa en distintas figuras, entre las que cabe destacar la Nurse Practitioner (actualmente denominada Advanced Practitioner) y la Nurse Consultant, caracterizadas por una capacitación específica que les permite desarrollar tareas de mayor nivel de complejidad, basada en la toma de decisiones autónoma y una cartera de servicios propia que va más allá de las actividades tradicionales establecidas en nuestro contexto, y donde la enfermera de práctica avanzada lidérala valoración y el seguimiento de los pacientes e incluso, en el caso de la Nurse Consultant, con participación activa en el diseño de estrategias de salud y como asesora en materia de investigación, gestión y clínica avanzada. En el campo de los cuidados urológicos existen diferentes figuras, conocidas como Advanced Urology Nurse o Urology Nurse Practitioner, cuyo desarrollo ha tenido lugar en EEUU, Canadá e Inglaterra principalmente, con puestos específicos definidos y un sistema de acreditación profesional propio, y que se está planteando como la clave a los modelos más tradicionales en muchos sistemas sanitarios europeos, mejorando la accesibilidad a los servicios a través de una gestión compartida de la demanda asistencial partiendo de un nuevo diseño de los mapas competenciales de los distintos profesionales y, por ende, contribuyendo a la coste-eficiencia de los sistemas sanitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>ENFURO: Rev. Asoc. Esp. A.T.S. Urol;(126): 4-12, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137192</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas perspectivas profesionales: la enfermera de práctica avanzada en Urología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53395</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53787^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
