<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112891</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive dysfunction in fibromyalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. People with a fibromyalgia diagnosis complain of having very poor cognitive functioning. In recent years, there has been an increasing interest to investigate which cognitive impairment is present in this disease. Aim. To review the published research on fibromyalgia and cognitive dysfunction. Development. A literature search was performed with a time interval from 1995 to 2012. Search terms included the keywords &#145;fibromyalgia&#146; and &#145;cognition&#146;, &#145;attention&#146;, &#145;memory&#146;, &#145;language&#146;, &#145;perception&#146;, &#145;executive functions&#146; and &#145;disexecutive syndrome&#146;. 64 records were selected after applying inclusion criteria. Conclusions. Studies that have examined cognitive function in people diagnosed with fibromyalgia have been few and mostly with small samples. Deficits have been identified mainly in working memory and complex attentional functions, where the distraction factor has an important significance. Impairment has also been identified in long-term memory and executive functions. There is consensus among the studies in which the degree of pain is directly related to the level of cognitive dysfunction, while no full consensus to explain the  influence of depression and anxiety on cognitive functioning in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pifarré, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosselló, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garolera, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gelonch, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las personas diagnosticadas de fibromialgia refieren de manera muy frecuente quejas sobre su pobre funcionamiento cognitivo. En los últimos años ha aumentado el interés para investigar cuáles son las alteraciones cognitivas presentes en esta enfermedad. Objetivo. Realizar una revisión de las investigaciones publicadas sobre fibromialgia y funciones cognitivas. Desarrollo. Se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica con un intervalo temporal desde 1995 hasta 2012. Los términos de búsqueda incluyeron las palabras clave &#145;fibromyalgia&#146; y &#145;cognition&#146;, &#145;attention&#146;, &#145;memory&#146;, &#145;language&#146;, &#145;perception&#146;, &#145;executive functions&#146; y &#145;disexecutive syndrome&#146;. Se seleccionaron 64 registros tras aplicar criterios de inclusión. Conclusiones. Los estudios que han analizado las funciones cognitivas en las personas diagnosticadas de fibromialgia han sido escasos y mayoritariamente con muestras pequeñas. Se han identificado déficits principalmente en la memoria de trabajo y en las capacidades atencionales más complejas, donde el factor distracción tiene una relevancia importante. También se ha identificado deterioro en la memoria a largo plazo y en las funciones ejecutivas. Existe consenso entre los diversos estudios en que el grado de dolor tiene una relación directa con el nivel de disfunción cognitiva, mientras que no existe total consenso para explicar la influencia de la depresión y ansiedad sobre el funcionamiento cognitivo en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;56(11): 573-588, jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disfunción cognitiva en la fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
