<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157727</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radix Entomolaris in mandibular second molars and caucasian patients. Clinical Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The most important anatomical variant which the mandibular first molar presents is a third extra distolingual root called radix entomolaris or buccal root called radix paramolaris, this variant is practically non-existent in mandibular second molars and even more so in patients of Caucasian origin. To ensure successful endodontic treatment, it is necessary to locate all the root canals, clean them thoroughly and seal them completely with an inert material. The anatomy of the root canal is very complex and unpredictable and the understanding of the presence of an additional root is essential as it will determine the success of the endodontic treatment. The current clinical case describes a mandibular second molar with radix entomolaris subjected to such treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Neira Vizcarra, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Castellano, Erick</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La variante anatómica más importante que presenta el primer molar inferior es una tercera raíz adicional distolingual llamada radix entomolaris o bucal llamada radix paramolaris, esta variante es prácticamente nula en segundos molares inferiores y más aún en pacientes de raza caucásica. Para asegurar el éxito de un tratamiento endodóncico es necesario localizar todos los conductos radiculares, limpiarlos a fondo y sellarlos completamente con un material inerte. La anatomía del conducto radicular es muy compleja e impredecible y la comprensión de la presencia de una raíz adicional es esencial ya que determinará el éxito del tratamiento endodóncico. El presente caso clínico describe un segundo molar inferior con radix entomolaris sometido a dicho tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);34(3): 149-156, jul.-sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radix Entomolaris en segundo molar inferior y paciente de raza caucásica. A propósito de un caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d776^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d776^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
