<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98079</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glycaemic management in type 1 and 2 diabetes patients undergoing interventional cardiology procedures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite the growing number of therapeutic alternatives available as well as general reviews and treatment guidelines for the treatment of diabetes, physicians are often left without a clear pathway of therapy to follow in specific clinical contexts such as interventional cardiology. The present document proposes a consensus treatment algorithm, based both on a critical appraisal of evidence from recent clinical trials and on value judgements supported by the authors&#146; collective clinical knowledge and experience, in an attempt to guide practitioners when choosing the most appropriate alternatives in the context of glycemic management in type 1 and 2 diabetic patients scheduled to undergo interventional cardiology procedures in a haemodynamic laboratory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artola-Menéndez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Gómez, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lisbona-Gil, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Guardiola, Faustino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-García, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar del creciente número tanto de alternativas terapéuticas disponibles para el tratamiento de la diabetes como de revisiones y guías de práctica clínica generales, en el caso de contextos específicos como la cardiología intervencionista se encuentra una ausencia de pautas terapéuticas claras e inequívocas. En esta guía de actuación clínica se propone un algoritmo consensuado, basado tanto en la revisión crítica de la evidencia de ensayos clínicos recientes como en criterios subjetivos derivados de la experiencia clínica y conocimiento colectivos, para orientar en la elección de las alternativas más adecuadas en esta situación clínica del manejo del control glucémico de pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 y 2 que van a ser sometidos a procedimientos de cardiología intervencionista en el laboratorio de hemodinámica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);138(5): e1-e5, mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control glucémico de los pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 y 2 tratados mediante procedimientos de cardiología intervencionista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38060^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
