<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108696</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethic and bioethic dilemmas on palliative care for hospitalized elderly: nurses&#146; experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: analyzing ethic and bioethics dilemmas experienced by nurses who take palliative care for hospitalized elderly. Method: quality study, exploring, descriptive, using the interview as technical for collecting oral history from tem nurses. The context was a geriatric palliative care unit from the city of Salvador - Brazil, in the period between May and August 2005. Content was used for speech analyzing. Results: the speeches arose dilemmas like: artificially prolonging of life; feeding terminal condition patients; neglecting information; and obtaining an undesired effect - Double effect. Conclusion: the nurses experienced some ethic and bioethics dilemmas, values conflicts and contradictions, for it is impossible to dissociate the historical and cultural aspects inserted in the daily life of the Health Professionals. However, the theoretical study about this theme Will contribute to complete deployment of the basics of palliative care by enabling cultural point of view transformation concerning to the process of dying and death (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amaral, Juliana Bezerra do</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martorell-Poveda, Maria Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Passos, Simone Cardoso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menezes, Maria do Rosário de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar los dilemas éticos y bioéticos vivenciados por enfermeras que ofrecen cuidados paliativos a mayores hospitalizados en una unidad de cuidados paliativos geriátrica de la ciudad de Salvador - Brasil, de mayo a agosto de 2005. Metodología: Estudio cualitativo, exploratorio, descriptivo. Para la recogida de datos se utilizó la entrevista y la historia oral temática. Los datos fueron sometidos al análisis de contenido. Resultados: del discurso surgieron dilemas como: Prolongando artificialmente la vida; Alimentando pacientes en condiciones terminales; Negando informaciones; y obteniendo un efecto indeseado - doble efecto. Conclusión: Las enfermeras vivencian algunos dilemas éticos y bioéticos, conflictos de valores y contradicciones, pues es imposible disociar los aspectos históricos y culturales del cotidiano de los profesionales de salud. Sin embargo, la profundización teórica sobre la temática contribuirá para la plena implantación de los cuidados paliativos, promoviendo una transformación de la visión cultural sobre el proceso de muerte y morir (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;16(33): 14-21, mayo-ago. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108696</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dilemas éticos y bioéticos en los cuidados paliativos de mayores hospitalizados: vivencia de enfermeras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19340^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
