<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119950</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary pleural thymoma presenting as a malignant mesothelioma. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ectopic thymoma is rarely found in the pleura. We report a case of a 46 year old female who presented with chest pain, shortness of breath and weight loss and with the clinical and radiological signs of a malignant mesothelioma. After surgical resection, the tumour was diagnosed as a pleural thymoma WHO type B2 and Masaoka stage IVa. As there was no continuity with the normal thymus tissue, the thymoma was thought to have arisen from ectopic thymic tissue in the pleura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mendoza-Ramírez, Saulo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Salinas, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales-Bahena, Martin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arturo Martínez-Quiroga, Carlos Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murguía-Pérez, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los timomas ectópicos rara vez se presentan como tumores pleurales. Informamos el caso de un timoma ectópico que se manifiesta clínica y radiológicamente como mesotelioma maligno en una mujer de 46 años quien presentó dolor torácico, disnea y pérdida de peso. Se realizó resección del tumor con diagnóstico patológico definitivo de timoma pleural ectópico B2 de acuerdo con la OMS y Masaoka estadio IVa. No se observó continuidad con el tejido del timo normal, por lo que pensamos que el timoma se originó de tejido ectópico en pleura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;47(1): 37-40, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119950</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Timoma pleural primario con presentación clínica de mesotelioma maligno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14332^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31266^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2878^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
