<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124458</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of use of specific features of subcutaneous insulin infusion systems and their relationship to metabolic control in patients with type 1 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective Patients with type 1 diabetes (T1DM) treated with continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) have available several specific features of these devices. The aim of this study was to evaluate the relationship between real use of them and the degree of glycemic control in patients using this therapy. Patients and methods Forty-four T1DM patients on CSII therapy with or without real-time continuous glucose monitoring (CGM) were included. Data from 14 consecutive days were retrospectively collected using the therapy management software CareLink Personal/Pro® and HbA1c measurement performed at that period. The relationship between the frequency of usie of specific features of insulin pumps (non-sensor augmented or sensor-augmented) and glycemic control was analyzed. Results Mean HbA1c in the group was 7.5 ± .8%. Mean daily number of boluses administered was 5.1 ± 1.8, with 75.4% of them being bolus wizards (BW). Daily number of boluses was significantly greater in patients with HbA1c &lt; 7.5% than in those with HbA1c &gt; 7.5% (5.3 ± 1.6 vs. 4.3 ± 1.6, P = .056). There was a trend to greater use of BW in patients with better control (82.8 ± 21.4% vs. 69.9 ± 29.1%,P = .106). HbA1c was lower in patients using CGM (n = 8) as compared to those not using sensor-augmented pumps (7.6 ± .8 vs 7.1 ± .7, P = .067), but the difference was not statistically significant. Conclusions More frequent use of BW appears to be associated to better metabolic control in patients with T1DM using pump therapy. In standard clinical practice, augmentation of insulin pump with CGM may be associated to improved glycemic control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quirós, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jansà, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Patrascioiu, Ioana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vinagre, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conget, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, Marga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo Los pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 (DT1) en tratamiento con infusión subcutánea de insulina (ISCI) tienen a su alcance diversas prestaciones específicas para estos dispositivos. El objetivo del estudio fue valorar la relación entre la utilización real de las mismas y el grado de control glucémico en pacientes habituados a este tipo de terapia. Pacientes y métodos Incluimos 44 pacientes con DT1 en tratamiento con ISCI con o sin monitorización continua de glucosa (MCG). Recogimos retrospectivamente los datos de 14 días consecutivos mediante la plataforma Care Link Personal/Pro® y la determinación de HbA1c realizada en ese periodo. Posteriormente, analizamos las diferencias en el uso de las prestaciones del dispositivo en función del grado de control glucémico y las diferencias entre los grupos con o sin MCG. Resultados La HbA1c media del grupo fue de 7,5 ± 0,8%. El número de bolus/día administrados fue de 5,1 ± 1,8, siendo el 75,4% de ellos en forma de bolus ayuda (BA). Los pacientes con mejor control (HbA1c &lt; 7,5%) se administraban más bolus/día (5,3 ± 1,6 vs. 4,3 ± 1,6; p = 0,056) que aquellos con peor control. Existía una tendencia a una mayor utilización de BA en los pacientes con mejor control (82,8 ± 21,4% vs. 69,9 ± 29,1%; p = 0,106). Sin alcanzar la significación estadística, los pacientes portadores de MCG (n = 8) tenían una HbA1c inferior a aquellos sin esta prestación (7,6 ± 0,8 vs. 7,1 ± 0,7; p = 0,067).Conclusiones El mayor uso del BA en los pacientes con DT1 en tratamiento con terapia ISCI tiende a asociarse con un mejor grado de control metabólico. En la práctica clínica habitual la utilización de MCG combinada con ISCI podría asociarse a un mejor control glucémico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(6): 318-322, jun.-jul. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124458</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la utilización de las prestaciones específicas de los sistemas de infusión subcutánea de insulina y su relación con el control metabólico en pacientes con diabetes tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54559^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53227^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
