<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63746</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A clinical case of frontal meningioma is presented. It began with progressive alcohol addiction. The patient, a 53-year-old woman with no personal background of interest, had no known toxic habits and was not receiving any treatment. Three months after her diagnosis, she began to take increasing amounts of alcohol that occasionally led to states of drunkenness. Four months after, due to daytime drowsiness and absence episode that lasted five minutes, she consulted about this situation. The clinical examination with apparatuses was normal. Laboratory analysis showed increase of transaminases with mild megaloblastic anemia. The brain computed tomography (CT) and magnetic nuclear resonance (MRI) showed a mass in the frontal lobe consistent with meningioma that was treated with photon radiosurgery satisfactorily</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáez Pérez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso clínico de meningioma frontal que comenzó con una adicción al alcohol de carácter progresivo. La enferma, mujer de 53 años sin antecedentes personales de interés, no tenía hábitos tóxicos conocidos, ni llevaba ningún tratamiento, había comenzando tres meses antes de su diagnóstico a ingerir cantidades crecientes de etanol que le producían ocasionalmente estados de embriaguez. Cuatro meses después, a raíz de una somnolencia diurna y una crisis de ausencia que duró cinco minutos, consultó por todo lo sucedido. La exploración clínica por aparatos fue normal. La analítica puso de manifiesto un aumento de las transaminasas, con discreta anemia de tipo megaloblástico. La tomografía axial computarizada (TAC) y la resonancia magnética nuclear (RMN) cerebral pusieron de manifiesto una masa en el lóbulo frontal, compatible con meningioma, que se trató con radiocirugía fotónica de forma satisfactoria</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(6): 308-312, jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63746</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29853^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8750^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
