<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159013</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transforming the amorpbous eountertransference into a representalale form: another perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author considers the way in which countertransference may prove useful in the psychoanalytic work. He takes as a starting point the description of the patients &#145;acts of language&#146; inducing a wide range of reactions in the analyst which must then be painstakingly self-analysed. He argues the case for the cautious approach, always directed at the part of the material most accessible to the analysand´s consciousness. In this respect, he attaches high importance to &#145;clarification&#146;. When the analyst is able to show his patient how an &#145;act of language&#146; has been produced, and the patient is able to establish how this has in fact taken place in the here and now of the relationship with his analyst, this can aid representation and open up an associative pathway in the patient towards connections with his history and deeper levels of his psyche. He is critical of those who consider countertransference merely as a means of validation of the analyst's hypotheses and those who, from this, interpret outright the strata most profound and inaccessible to the analysand´s consciousness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Busch, Fred</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autor reflexiona sobre el modo en que la contratransferencia puede resultar de utilidad en el trabajo psicoanalítico. Parte de la descripción de los actos de lenguaje del paciente que inducen en el analista toda una serie de reacciones que han de ser cuidadosamente autoanalizadas. Y defiende la aproximación cautelosa, siempre a la parte más accesible del material para la conciencia del analizando. En este sentido, da mucha importancia a la aclaración. Cuando el analista puede mostrarle a su paciente cómo se ha producido un acto de lenguaje, y el paciente puede verificar cómo efectivamente se ha producido en el aquí y el ahora de la relación con su analista, puede ayudar a representarlo y abrir una vía asociativa en el paciente a conexiones con su historia y niveles más profundos de su psíquismo. Se muestra crítico con quienes consideran la contratransferencia como una validadora de las hipótesis del analista y con quienes interpretan desde ahí directamente los estratos más profundos e inaccesibles para la conciencia del analizando (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(78): 141-157, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159013</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transformar la contratransferencía amorfa en una forma representable: otra perspectiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3395</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33540</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
