<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047758</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to measure death anxiety levels and the presence orabsence of a burnout syndrome; to know what stressors impact on each profession directly dealing with end-stage patients at a Palliative Care Unit; to evaluate care provider level of communication regarding work related concerns with colleagues or relatives. Methodology: templer&#146;s DAS and Maslach&#146;s MBI were individually administered along with a survey on issues related to stressing factors, changes in ideas about death, search for family/labor support, etc. Results: results were processed between June and October 2004, and questionnaires were administered to both healthcare and non-healthcare staff, resulting in 24 surveyed people in all. Average death anxiety was 5.75, but this figure varies depending on the presence of spiritual beliefsor otherwise. No burnout syndrome was found in these professions, but doctors are the halth-caring group with higher emotional weariness. According to our data, nurses scored highest on depersonalization. Also, factors related to team relationships are most stressing. Physical therapists prefer colleague support when discussing work-related problems, while doctors prefer family support. Assistant nurses is a group that hardly ever searches family or colleague support to discuss work-related topics. Conclusions: death anxiety levels are similar to those seen in other studies. Even in the absence of burnout syndrome, differences in the various MBI variables may be seen in accordance with professional categories. Furthermore, we found some obvious differences in stressors and in need of colleague/family support depending on professional category. We describe potential future research in this regard</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mier, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santisteban Etxeburu, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: medir el nivel de ansiedad ante la muerte y la presencia ono del síndrome de burnout; conocer cuáles son los factores estresantesen cada uno de los colectivos de profesionales que directamente atienden a pacientes terminales en una Unidad de Cuidados Paliativos; valorar el nivel de comunicación que presentan dichos profesionales con sus compañeros de trabajo o familia respecto a problemas laborales. Metodología: se administra de manera individual la escala de ansiedad ante la muerte (DAS) de Templer, el MBI de Maslach y una encuesta con preguntas relacionadas con factores estresantes, cambios en las ideas de muerte, búsqueda de apoyo familiar o laboral, etc. Resultados: se realizaron encuestas entre junio y octubre de 2004 a personal tanto sanitario como no, con un total de 24 encuestados. El nivel medio de ansiedad ante la muerte es de 5,75. Este nivel varía en función de la presencia o no de creencias espirituales. No existe síndrome de burnout en ningún colectivo. Los médicos es el grupo sanitario que presenta mayor cansancio emocional y las DUEs las que puntúan más alto en despersonalización. Los factores señalados como más estresantes son los vinculados con las relaciones en equipo. Ante problemas laborales, el grupo de fisioterapeutas prefiere el apoyo entre compañeros, mientras que los médicos prefieren el apoyo familiar. Las AUXs es el grupo que menos apoyo busca tanto entre compañeros como en la familia ante problemas laborales. Conclusiones: el nivel de ansiedad ante la muerte es similar al de otros estudios. Aunque no existe síndrome de burnout, aparecen diferencias en las distintas variables del MBI según categoría profesional. Asimismo,se constatan diferencias en cuanto a factores estresantes y búsqueda de apoyo laboral o familiar en función de la categoría profesional. Enumeramos posibles futuras líneas de investigación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;13(1): 18-24, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047758</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo de la ansiedad ante la muerte y factores estresantes en los distintos profesionales de una Unidad de Cuidados Paliativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
