<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147215</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Portuguese version of the Physical Education State Anxiety Scale: Psychometric properties and its association with gender, age and extracurricular physical activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aims to provide the translation and the cultural adaptation of the Physical Education State Anxiety Scale (PESAS) in Portuguese, assess its psychometric properties, and investigate the effects of gender, age and extracurricular physical activity, on the different dimensions of PESAS (somatic anxiety, cognitive processes and worry). The sample comprised 496 students (221 male, 275 female) aged between 13 and 21 years (M =15.71, SD = 1.34). Confirmatory factor analysis confirmed the original factor structure of the scale. There was appropriate factorial validity of the 3-factor structure (somatic anxiety, cognitive processes and worry). Female students reported higher levels in the dimensions of anxiety, in comparison to boys. Students who practiced extracurricular physical activity revealed lower levels of cognitive processes and worries/fears. Age negatively correlated with cognitive processes and somatic anxiety. These findings support the use of the Portuguese version of PESAS and provide additional information about state anxiety in school physical education (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saavedra, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lazuras, Lambros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandes, Helder Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barkoukis, Vassilis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima, Flávia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue la traducción y adaptación cultural de la escala PESAS en portugués, evaluar sus propiedades psicométricas, e investigar los efectos del género, la edad y la actividad física extracurricular, en las diferentes dimensiones de PESAS (ansiedad somática, procesos cognitivos y preocupación). La muestra fue de 496 estudiantes (221 varones, 275 mujeres) con edades comprendidas entre 13 y 21 años (M = 15,71, SD = 1,34). El análisis factorial confirmatorio confirmó una adecuada validez factorial de la estructura multidimensional original de tres factores (procesos cognitivos, ansiedad somática y preocupaciones/miedos). Las estudiantes reportaron niveles más altos en las dimensiones de la ansiedad, en comparación con los varones. Los practicantes de actividad física extracurricular revelaron niveles más bajos de los procesos cognitivos y preocupaciones/ miedos. La edad correlacionó negativamente con los procesos cognitivos y la ansiedad somática. Estos resultados apoyan el uso de la versión portuguesa de la escala PESAS y proporcionan información adicional sobre el estado de ansiedad en la educación física escolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(3): 135-144, oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147215</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versión portuguesa de la Escala de Estado de Ansiedad en Educación Física: Propiedades psicométricas y su asociación con el sexo, edad y actividad física extracurricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14111^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
