<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96001</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What treatment can we use for the rehabilitation of patients with Combination Syndrom?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The term &#147;Combination Syndrome &#147;was defined by Ellsworth Kelly in 1962 when, after carrying out a study involving almost 500 patients wearing a removable prosthetis, it was observed that there were a serious of characteristics that repeated in some patients wearing a complete upper prosthesis occluding with a partial lower prosthesis, the endetulous mandible being Kenndyclass I. Specifically, the syndrom was defined by a grouping of five characteristics, the mainone being significant reabsorption of the upper maxillary anterior, hypertrophy of the maxillary tuberosity and extrusion of the mandibular dental section. Subsequently, Tolstunov suggested a much broader classification of the syndrome including more patients with the common characteristics of the anterior reabsorption of the maxillary and the extrusion of the anterior mandibular section. Patient and method: The case was presented of a patient with Combination System, wearing a removable partial upper prosthesis. To come up with the treatment plan indicated, a bibliographic search was carried out in the Pubmed and Compludoc search engines. Next a therapeutic plan to restore both function and aesthetics was designed to suit the characteristics of the type of syndrome. Conclusion: After consulting the bibliography and according to our clinical experience, among the restorative options for patients with Combinato in Syndrome, the first optionis considered to be a fixed supported implant treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Polo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celemín Viñuela, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramiro Guillén, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guevara García, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El término de &#147;Síndrome de Combinación&#148; fue definido por Ellswoth Kelly en 1972, cuando tras realizar un estudio con casi 500 pacientes portadores de prótesis removible, observó que había una serie de características que se repetían en algunos de los pacientes que portaban una prótesis completa superior ocluyendo con una prótesis parcial inferior, siendo la mandíbula edéntula tipo clase I de Kennedy. En concreto, agrupó cinco características para definir el síndrome, siendo lo esencial que presentaban, una gran reabsorción del maxilar anterior, una hipertrofia de las tuberosidades maxilares y una extrusión del sector dentario mandibular. Posteriormente, Tolstunov planteó una clasificación del síndrome mucho más abierta en la que incluían más pacientes con la característica común de la reabsorción anterior del maxilar y la extrusión del sector anterior mandibular. Paciente y método: Se presenta el caso de una paciente con Síndrome de Combinación, portadora de una prótesis parcial removible superior. Para plantear llevar a cabo el plan de tratamiento de la manera más indicada, se realiza una revisión bibliográfica en los buscadores Pubmed y Compludoc. Posteriormente se diseñará, atendiendo a las características del tipo de síndrome, un plan terapéutico que restaurara tanto la función como la estética de la paciente. Conclusión: Tras la bibliografía consultada y nuestra experiencia clínica, entre las diferentes alternativas restauradoras que se pueden plantearen pacientes con Síndrome de Combinación, se ha considerado como primera opción, un tratamiento fijo implanto- soportado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);8(3): 65-69, sept.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué tratamiento podemos elegir para rehabilitar pacientes con Síndrome de Combinación?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8510^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8605^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1887^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30762^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
