<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055998</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Critical comparative analysis between open, laparoscopic and robotic radical prostatectomy: perioperative morbidity and oncological results (part I)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: With regard to oncological outcomes and perioperative morbidity, surgical treatment of localized prostate cancer has proved to be an excellenttreatment option. At present, there are three different approaches, open, laparoscopic and robotic. Open radicalprostatectomy remains the &#147;gold Standard&#148; due to accumulated experience and long follow up of series. But, without a doubt, laparoscopic and robotic groups are contributing with a far from negligible experience. Looking carefully at outcomes we will have to elucidate amongst advantages and disadvantages of each one of them. In this study we have performed a review of the literaturetrying to compare the three techniques, focusing in available surgical morbidity and oncological outcomes.METHODS: We performed a systematic search in the following data bases: PubMed; EMBASE; Cochrane; SCOPUS; Science Citation Index, from January 1990 to January 2007 for terms: &#147;radical retropubic prostatectomy&#148;;&#147;open radical prostatectomy&#148;; &#147;laparoscopic prostatectomy&#148;; &#147;laparoscopic radical prostatectomy&#148;; &#148;robotic prostatectomy&#148;; &#147;robotic radical prostatectomy&#148;;&#147;treatment outcome&#148;; &#147;oncologic outcome&#148;; &#147;outcomesmorbidity&#148;; &#147;mortality&#148; and &#147;minimally invasive treatment&#148;. We analyzed the most representative series (finished learning curve) in each one of the three approachesregarding perioperative morbidity and oncologicaloutcomes.RESULTS: To be able to perform an objective and truthful comparison of the three techniques, there is an absence in randomized studies in the literature. In this scenario we have analyzed the most representative individual series.With respect to the analyzed perioperative results, it seems to be no clear differences regarding surgical time, intraoperative complications, and catheter and hospital stay days. Otherwise, the endoscopic approach(laparoscopy and robotics) show a more favorable results in respect of blood loss and less postoperatorive analgesic. The short-term oncological outcomes (surgicalmargins) seem to be comparable amongst the three approaches. We only have long-term data (more than 10 years) on open series biochemical recurrence.CONCLUSIONS: The open surgery has become a referencefor all comparisons. The laparoscopic surgery is being replaced (specially in North America) by robotic surgery which is constantly expanding. It is necessary the publication of randomized and prospective studies to be able to objectively compare the three techniques</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Otero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Salamanca, Juan I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: El tratamiento quirúrgico del cáncer de próstata clínicamente localizado ha demostradoser una opción excelente en lo que ha resultados oncológicos y morbilidad operatoria se refiere. Actualmentecoexisten tres abordajes; abierto, laparoscópico y robótico. Debido a la experiencia acumulada y al largo seguimiento de las series, la prostatectomía radicalabierta sigue siendo el &#147;patrón oro&#148;. Pero, sin duda, los grupos laparoscópicos y robóticos van aportando una experiencia nada despreciable. En los próximos años debemos dilucidar a la vista de los resultados las ventajas e inconvenientes de cada una de ellas. En este trabajo hemos realizado una revisión de la literatura para intentar comparar las tres técnicas, centrándonos en la morbilidad quirúrgica y los resultados oncológicos disponibles.MÉTODOS: Realizamos una búsqueda sistemática en las siguientes bases de datos: PubMed; EMBASE; Cochrane;SCOPUS; Science Citation Index durante el periodoenero de 1990 a enero de 2007 para los términos:&#147;radical retropubic prostatectomy&#148;; &#147;open radical prostatectomy&#148;; &#147;laparoscopic prostatectomy&#148;; &#147;laparoscopicradical prostatectomy&#148;; &#148;robotic prostatectomy&#148;; &#147;robotic radical prostatectomy&#148;; &#147;treatment outcome&#148;; &#147;oncologic outcome&#148;; &#147;outcomes morbidity&#148;; &#147;mortality&#148; y &#147;minimally invasive treatment&#148;. Analizamos las series más representativas (curva de aprendizaje finalizada) para cada uno de los tres abordajes en cuanto a morbilidadperioperatoria y resultados oncológicos.RESULTADOS: Existe una ausencia en la literatura de estudios aleatorizados para poder realizar una comparaciónobjetiva y veraz de las tres técnicas. En este escenario, hemos analizado las series individuales más representativas. En cuanto a los resultados perioperatoriosanalizados, parecen no existir diferencias claras en cuanto a tiempo quirúrgico, complicaciones intraoperatorias,días de sondaje y estancia hospitalaria. Por el contrario, los abordajes endoscópicos (laparoscopia y robótica) presentan unos resultados mas favorables en cuanto a menor pérdida sanguínea y menor necesidad de analgesia postoperatoria. Los resultados oncológicosa corto plazo (márgenes quirúrgicos) parecen ser comparables entre los tres abordajes. Sólo disponemos de datos a largo plazo (más de 10 años) sobre recurrenciabioquímica de las series abiertas.CONCLUSIONES: La cirugía abierta sigue siendo el referente para todas las comparaciones. La cirugía laparoscópicaesta siendo sustituida (sobre todo en Norteamérica)por la cirugía robótica, que se encuentra en plena expansión. Es necesario, la publicación de estudiosaleatorizados y prospectivos para poder comparar objetivamente las tres técnicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(7): 755-765, sept. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055998</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis crítico comparativo de prostatectomía radical abierta retropúbica, laparoscópica y robótica: resultados de morbilidad perioperatoria y control oncológico (I)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
