<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153475</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The gif of the application of Reiki therapy in cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pain is one of the most feared symptoms of cancer. Bad pain not properly relieved contributes to the suffering of the patient and family. This may encourage them to seek additional complementary and alternative therapies, such as the one in our literature review. Reiki is understood as a healing method that uses universal energy to achieve balance and harmony of body, mind and soul, through the laying on of hands. Reiki is a relatively new therapy in relation to the relief of the symptoms of cancer. In fact, there are still a few articles in this field. Currently, the authors explore the evidence on the effectiveness of Reiki in relation to cancer pain and symptom control. Due to the increased interest deposited in Reiki by the health professionals &#150;especially for oncology professionals&#150; to relieve the symptoms of cancer, there has been a synthesis of recent studies to provide the evidence so far. After our literature review, we can conclude that there is insufficient evidence on the effectiveness of Reiki in relieving the cancer&#146;s symptoms due to the small sample size used, the paucity of studies and the abandonment of the study participants and others (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Domínguez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor es una de las consecuencias más temidas del cáncer. Cuando este no se alivia bien contribuye al sufrimiento del paciente y su familia. Ello puede motivarlos a buscar terapias alternativas y complementarias adicionales, tal y como la que nos ocupa en esta revisión bibliográfica. El Reiki es un método de curación que utiliza la energía universal, a través de la imposición de las manos. Es una terapia relativamente nueva en relación con el alivio de los síntomas del cáncer. De hecho, aún existen pocos artículos en este campo. En la actualidad, los autores exploran la evidencia sobre la eficacia del Reiki en relación con el dolor del cáncer y el control de los síntomas. Debido al mayor interés depositado en el Reiki por los profesionales de la salud &#150;en especial por los profesionales de oncología&#150; para el alivio de los síntomas del cáncer, se ha realizado una síntesis de los últimos estudios para ofrecer la evidencia existente hasta el momento. Tras la revisión bibliográfica, se puede concluir que en este momento no existe suficiente evidencia sobre la eficacia del Reiki en el alivio de los síntomas del cáncer debido al reducido tamaño muestral utilizado, la escasez de estudios y el abandono de los participantes de los estudios, entre otras causas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;39(6): 430-441, jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153475</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El don de la aplicación de la terapia de Reiki en pacientes oncológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32591^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32591^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32591^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32591^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32725^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29189^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29189^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29189^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
