<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95928</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objectives of this study are to study the activity of our out-patient surgical unit during 2006 and the quality of the care given. Material and method: The Ambulatory Unit (UCMA), a type II integrated unit, was inaugurated in 2005, with the participation of different Departments practicing surgery, using protocols for admission, nursing care and anaesthesia. Results: 1.592 patients underwent surgery (an 80.91% increase over 2003) with: 53.52% males, 59.74% for ophthalmological surgery, 9.65 patients/day in the UCMA, 75.56% were ASA I,1.9% cancellations, 4.96% un expected admissions (74.69% females),0.3% re-admissions, 97% excellent satisfaction in UCMA and 0% mortality. Conclusions: Increase of surgical activity through CMA programs allows the hospital to operate on a large number as out-patients, which in turn allows hospital resources to be dedicated to other processes. Quality indexes lead us to affirm that this is a reliable and safe means of treatment, with an excellent degree of patient´s acceptance and satisfaction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vila-Blanco, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáiz-Jarabo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Los objetivos del estudio son conocer la actividad de la cirugía mayor ambulatoria (CMA) desarrollada en nuestro hospital en el año 2006 y su calidad. Material y método: La unidad de CMA (UCMA), unidad integrada tipo II, se inauguró en el año 2005. Participan diferentes servicios, que realizan técnicas quirúrgicas con protocolos de inclusión, de cuidados de enfermería y de anestesia. Resultados: Intervenidos 1.592 pacientes (incremento del 80,91% respecto al 2003); 53,52% varones; 59,74% de oftalmología,9,65 pacientes/día en la UCMA, 75,56% ASA I, 1,9% de suspensiones, 4,96% hospitalizaciones (74,69% mujeres), 0,3% de reingresos, 97% de satisfacción y 0% de mortalidad. Conclusiones: El incremento de la actividad quirúrgica con CMA ha permitido intervenir un gran número de pacientes sin ingreso hospitalario, lo que ha posibilitado destinar recursos hospitalariosa otros procesos. Los índices de calidad demuestran que se trata de una forma de asistencia segura y fiable, y excelente grado de satisfacción y aceptación por la población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;14(3): 99-102, jul.-sept. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95928</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implantación de la cirugía mayor ambulatoria en un hospital general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6925^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
