<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80944</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Health Care&#150;Associated Infections (HCAI) in long-term care facilities (LTCFs) is one of the main problems related to patient safety. In recent years, acute health conditions have increased amongst nursing home residents. LTCF residents have a risk of developing HCAI that approaches that seen inacute care hospital patients. A great deal of information has been published concerning infections inthe LTCF, and infection control programs are nearly universal in that setting. Recommendations are developed for long-term care infection control programs based on expert opinions. The lack of metaanalyses and clinical randomised controlled trials in this field is surprising. The development of surveillance systems with appropriate definitions of HCAI to enable the systematic collection, data analysis and use of information in order to improve care to patients, reduce the incidence HCAI that can be prevented and enables to compare data from other facilities with same patient mix (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miguel, Mariano de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gabernet, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaig, Neus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robledo, Asunció</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barcenilla, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barceló, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toribio, Paquita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nadal, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Blas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección relacionada con la asistencia sanitaria (IRA) en los centros sociosanitarios (CSS) es uno de los principales problemas relacionados con la seguridad del paciente. En los últimos años, ha aumentado el componente agudo en los centros sociosanitarios. Los residentes de los CSS tienen un riesgo similar de desarrollar una IRA a de los pacientes de los hospitales agudos. Se ha publicadoun gran número de información y trabajos sobre programas de control de la infección en CSS. Las recomendaciones desarrolladas por los programas de control de infección en CSS están basadas en opiniones de expertos. Llama la atención la falta de meta-análisis y estudios controlados en este campo. El desarrollo de sistemas de vigilancia, con definiciones adaptadas de IRA en los CSS, permitela recogida sistemática de información, análisis de datos y uso de información orientado a mejorar los cuidados de los pacientes, reducir la incidencia prevenible de IRAS y comparar resultados concentros con características parecidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;20(2): 75-80, abr.-jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención y control de la infección relacionada con la asistencia en el ámbito sociosanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29045^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
