<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153327</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family eating habits, family support and subjective well-being in university students in Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To characterize typologies of university students according to the perception of their families&#146; eating habits. Material and method: A questionnaire was applied to a non-probabilistic sample of 372 students of both genders at the Universidad de La Frontera, Temuco, Chile. The instrument included: the Family Eating Habits Questionnaire (FEHQ), the Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS), the Satisfaction with Food-related Life Scale (SWFL) and the Family Resources Scale (FRS). Estimated weight and height were asked about as well as sociodemographic variables. Results: Using an exploratory factor analysis (EFA) three factors were detected in the FEHQ: importance of eating to family members, cohesiveness of family eating, and pressure to eat. The EFA detected two factors on the FRS: intangible and tangible support. A confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) validated the structure of the FEHQ and the FRS with good goodness-of-fit indicators. A cluster analysis distinguished four typologies that differed significantly in the scores of the components on the FEHQ and FRS, scores on the SWLS and SWFL, body mass index, gender and socioeconomic level. Typologies with higher scores in &#147;cohesiveness of family eating&#148; report greater intangible support from their families and higher scores on the SWLS and SWFL. Conclusions: The results show that the frequency and importance assigned to family meals are associated positively with perceived family support, particularly in intangible resources, as well as with the overall satisfaction with life and in the food domain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grunert, Klaus G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schnettler, Berta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Höger, Yesly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobos, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sepúlveda, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orellana, Ligia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas-Oñate, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: caracterizar tipologías de estudiantes universitarios según la percepción de los hábitos alimentarios de sus familias. Material y método: se aplicó un cuestionario a una muestra no probabilística de 372 estudiantes de ambos géneros de la Universidad de La Frontera, Chile. El instrumento incluyó: Cuestionario de Hábitos Alimentarios Familiares (FEHQ), Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS), Satisfaction with Food-related Life (SWFL) y la Escala de Recursos Familiares (FRS). Se consultó peso y estatura aproximada, así como variables sociodemográficas. Resultados: mediante análisis factorial exploratorio (AFE) se detectaron tres factores en el FEHQ: importancia de la alimentación para los miembros de la familia, cohesión en las comidas familiares y presión por comer. Mediante AFE se detectaron dos factores en la FRS: apoyo intangible y tangible. Mediante análisis factorial confirmatorio se validó la estructura del FEHQ y de la FRS con aceptables niveles de bondad de ajuste. Mediante análisis clúster se distinguieron cuatro tipologías que difirieron significativamente en las puntuaciones de los componentes del FEHQ y de la FRS, puntajes de la SWLS y SWFL, índice de masa corporal, género y nivel socioeconómico. Las tipologías con mayores puntuaciones en &#147;cohesión en las comidas familiares&#148; reportan mayor apoyo intangible de sus familias y superiores puntuaciones en la SWLS y SWFL. Conclusiones: los resultados muestran que la frecuencia y la importancia asignada a las comidas en familia se asocian positivamente con el apoyo familiar percibido, especialmente en recursos intangibles, así como también con la satisfacción global con la vida y en el dominio de la alimentación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(2): 451-458, mar.-abr. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153327</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábitos de alimentación familiar, apoyo familiar y bienestar subjetivo en estudiantes universitarios en Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
