<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127997</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biomarkers for the screening of pediatric infectious diseases: a true diagnostic revolution for the developing world</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Health workers in rural facilities in Africa are confronted every day with the diagnosis and treatment of sick children with infectious diseases. Malaria, pneumonia and diarrhea are among the most important infectious diseases in developing countries in terms of morbidity and mortality burden in children. However, there is a scarcity of diagnostic tools to determine the etiologic origin of these infections in health facilities in rural Africa, and therefore guide clinical management including the prescription of anti-malarials and/or antibiotics. Clinical presentations of malaria, bacterial infections and viral infections often overlap, particularly in children. Misdiagnosis of malaria, bacterial infections and viral infections may increase the morbidity and mortality among children, as well as boost resistance levels to antimalarial drugs and antibiotics. As a result, there is a need to develop new diagnostic tools for infectious diseases that can be used for diagnosis of such highly prevalent conditions in the developing world. Malaria rapid diagnostic tests are a good example of these new diagnostic tools, affordable, accessible and with a high-impact on the diagnosis of one of the diseases causing more deaths in the developing world. Widespread implementation of tools similar to the RDTs for other infectious diseases, and particularly those of bacterial origin, will surely result in improvements in the recognition and management of life-threatening childhood infections, and in a reduction of their intolerable burden (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lanaspa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bassat Orellana, Q</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madrid, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El personal clínico que trabaja en países en desarrollose enfrenta cada día al diagnóstico ytratamiento de niños enfermos. Malaria, neumonía y diarreason lasenfermedades infecciosas másimportantes en los países con recursos limitados entérminos de morbilidad ymortalidadinfantil. La escasez deherramientas diagnósticaspara determinar su etiologíaen estos medios es un problema frecuente, y por lo tanto es difícil orientar el manejo clínico, incluyendola prescripción demedicamentos para estas patologías. Por otro lado, los síntomas demalaria, de algunas infecciones bacterianasy de infeccionesviralesson a menudo compartidos y difíciles de distinguir en ausencia de apoyo diagnóstico. El reconocimiento erróneode estas enfermedadespuede aumentarlamorbimortalidadpediátrica, así como los niveles de resistenciaa fármacos antimaláricosy antibióticos. Es importante, por tanto, desarrollarnuevasherramientas diagnósticas paraenfermedadesinfecciosasque se puedan utilizarincluso en las zonas más rurales de países con recursos limitados. Las pruebas de diagnóstico rápido demalaria son un buen ejemplo de estas herramientas de diagnóstico precoz, asequibles, accesibles, de resultado casi inmediato y con alto impacto en el diagnóstico de una de las enfermedades que más mortalidad causan en el mundo en desarrollo. La implementación de pruebas de diagnóstico rápido similares para otras enfermedades infecciosas, significaría sin duda un gran avance en el diagnóstico y manejo de las infecciones pediátricas, suponiendo un paso adelante en la disminución de la inaceptablemente alta mortalidad infantil que todavía afecta a estos países (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;16(63): 259-264, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127997</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biomarcadores para el despistaje de enfermedades infecciosas: una revolución diagnóstica para los países pobres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52870^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52841^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8462^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
