<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126669</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early loading of GMI implants with internal connection and sandblasted-acid-etched surface</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Today, oral implantology constitute a therapeutic modality in the prosthodontic treatment of patients with partial and total tooth loss. This study reports the evaluation of patients treated by early loading of titanium implants with internal connection and sandblasted-acid-etched surface. Methods: 39 patients with tooth loss were treated with Frontier GMI® sandblasted and acid-etched surface implants. Implants were loaded after a healing free-loading period of 6 weeks (mandible) and 8 weeks (maxilla). Clinical findings (implants and prosthodontics) were followed during 1 year. Results: 111 implants were inserted (50 maxillary, and 61 mandibular) for prosthodontic rehabilitation. 44 implants were inserted in anterior sites and 67 in posterior sites. After 1-year follow-up, clinical results indicate a survival and success rate of implants of 99.1%. One implant were lost during the healing period by mobility. A case of periimplantitis were reported as late complication after functional loading. Prosthodontic restorations included 30 single crowns, 15 fixed bridges, 5 ball-over dentures and 2 fixed totally rehabilitation. Conclusions: Clinical results of this study indicate that prosthodontic rehabilitation supported by internal connection and sandblasted and etched-titanium implants and loaded early can be a successful dental treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Guerra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matos Garrido, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Méndez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Ortega, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monsalve Guil, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medel Soteras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>España López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La implantología oral representa en la actualidad, una modalidad terapéutica odontológica en los pacientes con pérdida dental total y parcial. El estudio muestra la evaluación de los pacientes tratados mediante carga precoz de implantes de titanio con conexión interna y superficie arenada y grabada. Métodos: 39 pacientes con pérdidas dentales fueron tratados con implantes con conexión interna y superficie arenada y grabada Frontier GMI®. Los implantes fueron cargados funcionalmente tras un periodo de tiempo de 6 semanas en la mandíbula y 8 semanas en el maxilar superior. Los hallazgos clínicos (implantológicos y prostodóncicos) se han seguido durante 1 año. Resultados: 111 implantes fueron insertados en ambos maxilares (50 en el maxilar superior y 61 en la mandíbula) para su rehabilitación prostodóncica. 44 implantes fueron insertados en el sector anterior y 67 implantes en el sector posterior. Después de 1 año de seguimiento clínico, los resultados indican una supervivencia y éxito de los implantes del 99,1%. Durante el periodo de cicatrización libre de carga funcional, se perdió 1 implante por movilidad. Como complicaciones tardías hubo un caso de periimplantitis. Las restauraciones prostodóncicas incluyeron 30 coronas unitarias, 15 puentes fijos, 5 sobre dentaduras con bolas y 2 rehabilitaciones totales fijas. Conclusiones: Los hallazgos clínicos del presente estudio indican que la rehabilitación prostodóncica mediante la inserción de implantes de titanio con conexión interna y superficie arenada + grabada, y cargados precozmente, representa una terapéutica odontológica con éxito elevado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;26(2): 67-75, ago. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126669</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La carga precoz de los implantes GMI con conexión interna y superficie arenada y grabada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29076</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3808^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53959^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
