<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055897</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life of patients with BAHA</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study is to quantify changes in quality of life due to the use of BAHA.                 Patients and method: Twenty-eight patients were included. The instrument used to quantify the change in quality of life was the Glasgow Benefit Inventory and a questionnaire including 2 open questions, BAHA use, change in tinnitus, and postoperative pain.                 Results: The average total benefit score with the Glasgow Benefit Inventory was 38, and the general, social, and physical score were 54, 10, and 1, respectively. There was no significant association between preoperative hearing, aetiology or type of hearing loss, and quality of life. Tinnitus rate went from 37.5 % to 20.8 % following BAHA; this difference being significant.                 Conclusions: Our results show that the use of BAHA is associated with a great improvement in quality of life. Also, they show that its use has a positive effect upon tinnitus</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gavilán, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Camón, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lassaletta, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio es cuantificar los cambios en la calidad de vida en los pacientes con implantes osteointegrados (BAHA).                 Pacientes y método: Se incluyó a 28 pacientes. El instrumento empleado para medir la calidad de vida fue el Glasgow Benefit Inventory y un cuestionario con 2 preguntas abiertas, uso del BAHA, modificación de los acufenos y dolor postoperatorio.                 Resultados: La puntuación media del Glasgow Benefit Inventory total fue 38, y en las subescalas general, social y física, 54, 10 y 1, respectivamente. No se encontró relación significativa entre el grado de audición preoperatorio, la etiología o el tipo de hipoacusia y la calidad de vida. La tasa de acufenos disminuyó del 37,5 al 20,8 % tras la colocación del BAHA, con diferencias significativas.                 Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados muestran que el uso del BAHA se asocia a una gran mejoría en la calidad de vida. Asimismo, muestran que su uso tiene un efecto positivo en los acufenos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(7): 316-320, ago.-sept. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida de los pacientes con BAHA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14399^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14399^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29076</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13887</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33582</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
