<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039384</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Remifentanyl in neurosurgery. Impact on early extubation and implications for the early postoperative period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives:To determine whether the use of a new opioid such as remifentanyl modifies the standard care provided to patients undergoing elective neurosurgery in our hospital. To assess the time of extubation and the length of stay in the Intensive Care Unit (ICU). Material and method: Retrospective study of a cohort of neurosurgical patients free from complications undergoing elective supratentorial tumor surgery through craniotomy. All consecutivepatients between November 2003 and February 2004 were included in the study. Data were obtained from preanesthesia, anesthesia and intensive care medical records. Age, sex, ASA risk, anesthetic technique, length of the surgical procedure, intraoperative opiate use, time and place of extubation, as well as length of stay in the ICU, were recorded. In order to study the impact of intraoperative opiate use on the time of extubation and the postoperative stay, patients were divided in two groups: remifentanyl and fentanyl. The descriptive analysis of quantitative end points is shown with mean values, standard deviations and quartiles, and is graphically shown using box charts; for qualitativeendpoints, contingency tables were used. Intergroup comparisons were performed using the chi-square test for qualitative endpoints and the Student´s t or Mann Whitney test for quantitative endpoints. Results: Thirty two elective craniotomies were performed for resection of supratentorial tumors in patients free from complications, and data were obtained from 31 patients. The statistical analysis did not show differences regarding sex, age or ASA classification between patients receiving remifentanyl (18) and patients receiving fentanyl (13) intraoperatively. When remifentanyl was used in 67% of patients,total intravenous anesthesia (TIVA) was provided for anesthetic maintenance, while sevoflurane was used in 77% of patients with fentanyl. Length of surgical-anestheticprocedure was greater in the fentanyl group, with a mean difference of almost one hour. Extubation was performed in the operating room in 67% of patients in theremifentanyl group and in the ICU in 100% of patients in the fentanyl group; however, this did not result in an earlier discharge from the Intensive Care Unit. Conclusion:Data suggest that remifentanyl facilitates the extubation. New pharmacological options allow variations of the clinical practice that can benefit our patients. However, thesechanges do not lead to a shorter stay in the ICU, since that does not only depends on clinical factors, but also on organizational factorsObjectives:        To determine whether the use of a new opioid such as        remifentanyl modifies the standard care provided to patients        undergoing elective neurosurgery in our hospital. To        assess the time of extubation and the length of stay in the        Intensive Care Unit (ICU).        Material and method:        Retrospective study of a cohort of neurosurgical patients        free from complications undergoing elective supratentorial        tumor surgery through craniotomy. All consecutive        patients between November 2003 and February 2004        were included in the study. Data were obtained from preanesthesia,        anesthesia and intensive care medical records.        Age, sex, ASA risk, anesthetic technique, length of the surgical        procedure, intraoperative opiate use, time and place        of extubation, as well as length of stay in the ICU, were        recorded. In order to study the impact of intraoperative        opiate use on the time of extubation and the postoperative        stay, patients were divided in two groups: remifentanyl and        fentanyl. The descriptive analysis of quantitative endpoints        is shown with mean values, standard deviations and quartiles,        and is graphically shown using box charts; for qualitative        endpoints, contingency tables were used. Intergroup        comparisons were performed using the chi-square test for        qualitative endpoints and the Student´s t or Mann Whitney        test for quantitative endpoints.        Results:        Thirty two elective craniotomies were performed for resection        of supratentorial tumors in patients free from complications,        and data were obtained from 31 patients. The        statistical analysis did not show differences regarding sex,        age or ASA classification between patients receiving        remifentanyl (18) and patients receiving fentanyl (13) intraoperatively.        When remifentanyl was used in 67% of patients,        total intravenous anesthesia (TIVA) was provided for        anesthetic maintenance, while sevoflurane was used in        77% of patients with fentanyl. Length of surgical-anesthetic        procedure was greater in the fentanyl group, with a        mean difference of almost one hour. Extubation was performed        in the operating room in 67% of patients in the        remifentanyl group and in the ICU in 100% of patients in        the fentanyl group; however, this did not result in an earlier        discharge from the Intensive Care Unit.        Conclusion:        Data suggest that remifentanyl facilitates the extubation.        New pharmacological options allow variations of the clinical        practice that can benefit our patients. However, these        changes do not lead to a shorter stay in the ICU, since that        does not only depends on clinical factors, but also on organizational        factors</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuéllar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llácer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar si el uso de un nuevo opioide como remifentanilo modifica la actuación habitual en el manejo de los pacientes neuroquirúrgicos programados en nuestro centro. Valorar el momento de la extubación y la duración de la estancia en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI). Material y método: Estudio retrospectivo de una cohorte de pacientes neuroquirúrgicos no complicados sometidos a cirugía tumoral supratentorial programada mediante craneotomía. La muestra consistió en todos los casos consecutivos entre noviembre de 2003 y febrero de 2004. Los datos se obtuvieron de las historias clínicas de preanestesia, anestesia y de cuidados intensivos. Se recogió edad, sexo, riesgo ASA,técnica anestésica, duración quirúrgica, opioide intraoperatorio empleado, momento y lugar de la extubación, así como la duración de la estancia en UCI. Para estudiar la influenciadel opioide intraoperatorio empleado sobre los resultados de momento de la extubación y estancia postoperatoria se dividen los casos en dos grupos: remifentanilo y fentanilo. El análisis descriptivo de variables cuantitativas se presenta mediante media, desviación estándar y cuartiles y gráficamente con diagramas de cajas; cara las variables cualitativas mediante tablas de contingencia. Las comparaciones intergrupo se realizaron con test Chi cuadrado en el caso de variables cualitativas y con t de Student o Mann-Whitney en las cuantitativas. Resultados: Se realizaron 32 craneotomías para resección de tumoressupratentoriales programadas no complicadas, obteniéndose los datos de 31 casos. Tras el análisis estadístico no se objetivan diferencias respecto al sexo, edad ni clasificaciónASA entre los pacientes que recibieron remifentanilo (18) y aquellos a los que se les administró fentanilo (13) intraoperatorio. Cuando se utilizó remifentanilo, en el 67%de los casos, se optó por realizar anestesia total intravenosa (TIVA) para el mantenimiento anestésico, mientras que el sevoflurano fue utilizado en el 77% de los pacientes confentanilo. La duración quirúrgico-anestésica fue superior en el grupo de fentanilo, con una diferencia media aproximada de una hora. La extubación se realizó en quirófanoen el 67% de los casos en el grupo remifentanilo y en UCI en el 100% de los casos en el grupo fentanilo; sin embargo, esto no se reflejó en un alta más precoz de la Unidadde Cuidados Intensivos. Conclusión: Los datos señalan una facilitación de la extubación con remifentanilo. Las nuevas opciones farmacológicas permiten variaciones en la práctica clínica de las que se pueden beneficiar nuestros pacientes. Sin embargo, estos cambiosno se traducen en una menor estancia en UCI, ya que esta no está sólo condicionada por razones clínicas sino también organizativas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(3): 141-145, abr. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Remifentanilo en neurocirugía. Influencia en la extubación precoz e implicaciones en la estancia postoperatoria inmediata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23845^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9489^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
