<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144354</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Explicative factors of face-to-face harassment and cyberbullying in a sample of primary students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Research has shown that there is a co-occurrence between bullying and cyberbullying in relation to certain variables that describe and explain them. The present study aims to examine the differential influence of individual and contextual variables on perception of the role played in the involvement in both phenomena. Method: Participants were 1278 schoolchildren (47.7 % girls) of primary education, aged 10 to 14 years (M=11.11, SD= 0.75). Results: Logistic regression analysis indicated that social adjustment, normative adjustment, disruptiveness, gender, and self-esteem explain a substantial part of the involvement in both violent phenomena as victims, aggressors, and bully/victims. Conclusions: The results are discussed regarding the weight that must attributed to individual versus contextual factors, concluding that the explicative weight of the immediate social elements and educational context may make the difference (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, Cristina María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romera Félix, Eva M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Ruiz, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la investigación ha puesto de manifiesto cierta co-ocurrencia entre el bullying y el cyberbullying en determinadas variables que los describen y explican. El presente estudio tiene como objetivo examinar la influencia diferencial de variables individuales y de contexto en la percepción del rol jugado en la implicación en bullying y cyberbullying. Método: participaron 1278 escolares de Educación Primaria (47.7% chicas) con edades comprendidas entre los 10 y los 14 años (M = 11.11;DT=0.75). Resultados: los análisis de regresión logística señalaron que el ajuste social, el ajuste a las normas, la disruptividad, el género y la autoestima explican una parte sustancial de la implicación, en ambos fenómenos violentos, de víctimas, agresores y agresores victimizados. Conclusiones: se discuten los resultados en relación al peso que debe atribuirse a factores individuales frente a factores contextuales próximos, concluyéndose que el peso explicativo de los elementos sociales inmediatos y de contexto educativo pueden estar marcando las diferencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);27(4): 347-353, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144354</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores explicativos del acoso cara a cara y del ciberacoso en escolares de primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2699^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
