<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-28210</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diabetic neuropathy: vascular disease?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The major neurologic complications of diabetes are: 1) Neuropathy, both peripheral and autonomic, with principal manifestations in the lower limbs; 2) Microvascular disease, mainly affecting the retina, resulting in blindness; and 3) Macrovascular disease, presenting with atherosclerosis in the cerebral arteries causing ischemic cerebrovascular disease and stroke. Method. The definition of diabetic neuropathy has changed over the last 50 years. Over the last 20 years there have been three main pathogenetic theories to explain diabetic neuropathy: the polyol pathway theory, the microvascular theory, and the glycosylation end product theory. It is apparent that several pathophysiologic factors probably operate simultaneously, and it may be too simplistic to attempt to explain the many clinical and pathologic findings of diabetic neuropathy through a single theory. Diabetic peripheral neuropathy is not caused by large-vessel peripheral vascular disease, however, it does appear that small-vessel disease plays a role. Conclusion. It seems likely, that microangiopathy on the one hand and changes of various metabolic pathways due to hyperglycemia on the other hand are much more related to each other than it was suggested previously (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las principales complicaciones neurológicas de la diabetes son: 1) Neuropatía periférica y autonómica, cuyas manifestaciones principales ocurren en las extremidades inferiores; 2) Enfermedad microvascular, que afecta principalmente a la retina y desencadena ceguera, y 3) Enfermedad macrovascular, presente con aterosclerosis en las arterias cerebrales y que causa enfermedad isquémica cerebrovascular. Desarrollo. La definición de la neuropatía diabética (ND) ha cambiado en los últimos 50 años; en los últimos veinte se han propuesto tres teorías patogénicas principales para explicar la ND: la teoría de la vía poliol, la teoría microvascular y la teoría del producto final de la glucosilación. Probablemente, varios factores patofisiológicos actúan simultáneamente, y puede parecer muy simplista explicar que muchas manifestaciones clínicas y hallazgos patológicos en la ND pueden ser resultado de un solo mecanismo. La ND periférica no la ocasiona la enfermedad vascular periférica de grandes vasos; sin embargo, parece que la enfermedad de pequeños vasos desempeña un papel importante. Conclusión. Es probable que la microangiopatía, por un lado, y las alteraciones de varias vías metabólicas por la hiperglucemia, por otro, se relacionen más entre sí que como se había descrito anteriormente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(7): 658-661, oct. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuropatía diabética: ¿una enfermedad vascular?</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Otero Siliceo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruano-Calderón, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-28210</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d11545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30709</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1836</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
