<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100091</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Onabotulinumtoxin A in the treatment of chronic migraine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Chronic migraine is the most frequent complication of migraine. Its management is complex and difficult, and is based essentially on preventive measures. Aim. To analyse the development of the use of Onabotulinumtoxin A (OnabotA) in migraine, especially in its chronic form, the method of administration, its mechanism of action, its safety profile and its possible indications in clinical practice. Development. The study conducts a thorough review of all the clinical trials in the literature that have used OnabotA in the prevention of migraine, both in its episodic and its chronic forms, and the outcomes in the chronic form are analysed in detail.  Conclusions. In studies in phase III, OnabotA has proved to be effective in the treatment of patients with chronic migraine, with significant reductions in the mean frequency of days with headaches, the number of headache episodes, the days with migraine or the proportion of patients with severe disability, in addition to other parameters. It is also effective in the subgroup of patients with symptomatic headache due to medication abuse. OnabotA has proved to be safe and well tolerated in this indication, with foreseeable, usually mild or moderate, transitory side effects. In sum, OnabotA is a safe,   well-tolerated alternative in the preventive treatment of chronic migraine (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Láinez Andrés, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La migraña crónica constituye la complicación más frecuente de la migraña. Su manejo es complejo y difícil y se basa fundamentalmente en la profilaxis. Objetivo. Analizar el desarrollo de la utilización de Onabotulinumtoxin A (OnabotA) en la migraña, especialmente en su forma crónica, el modo de administración, su mecanismo de acción, el perfil de seguridad y sus posibles indicaciones en la práctica clínica. Desarrollo. Se realiza una revisión exhaustiva de todos los ensayos clínicos publicados que han utilizado OnabotA en la prevención de la migraña, tanto en su forma episódica como crónica, y se analizan detalladamente los resultados en la forma crónica.  Conclusiones. En los estudios en fase III, la OnabotA ha demostrado ser eficaz en el tratamiento de pacientes con migraña crónica al reducir significativamente la frecuencia media de días de dolor de cabeza, los episodios de dolor de cabeza, los días de migraña o la proporción de pacientes con discapacidad grave, además de otros parámetros. Es eficaz también en el subgrupo de pacientes con cefalea por abuso de medición sintomática. La OnabotA se ha mostrado segura y bien tolerada en esta indicación, con efectos adversos previsibles, habitualmente leves o moderados, y pasajeros. En definitiva, la  OnabotA constituye una alternativa eficaz y bien tolerada en el tratamiento preventivo de la migraña crónica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(supl.2): s39-s50, abr. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100091</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Onabotulinumtoxin A en el tratamiento de la migraña crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50485^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
