<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75316</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aspirin for the primary prevention of cardiovascular diseases in diabetic patients. A review of currently available tests</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The benefits of aspirin treatment in reducing the risk of myocardialinfarction, cerebrovascular accidents and vascular death iswell-documented among individuals having prior cardiovasculardisease, including the subgroup with diabetes mellitus. The role ofaspirin in primary prevention is less clear and debatable: the resultsof the clinical trials currently available are not consistent, althoughthe meta-analyses are favorable in some aspects. There seems to bea disparity between the type of benefit (when found to exist) andgender, the findings being particularly contradictory for diabeticsubjects, totalling a minor percentage of the population sampleincluded in the studies. Despite this fact, in 1997, the AmericanDiabetes Association and more recently other scientific societies(including several Spanish societies) have been recommending theuse of aspirin in low doses in primary prevention in all type 1 ortype 2 diabetic patients over 40 years of age and in all those withinthe 21-40 age range having any other cardiovascular risk factor inaddition to diabetes (family history of vascular disease, hypertension,smoking, dyslipidemia or albuminuria). This study reviewsthe findings of the randomized, controlled clinical trials on primarycardiovascular prevention with aspirin, on which the official AmericanDiabetes Association guidelines might be based, the conclusionbeing reached that there is not currently sufficient scientificevidence to uphold these guidelines(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ronzón Fernández, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández García, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maciá Bobes, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El beneficio del tratamiento con aspirina en la reducción del riesgode infarto de miocardio, accidente vascular cerebral y muerte deorigen vascular, está bien documentado en personas con enfermedadcardiovascular previa, incluido el subgrupo portador de una diabetesmellitus. Sin embargo el papel de la aspirina en prevención primariaes menos claro y objeto de discusión: los resultados de los ensayosclínicos disponibles no son consistentes, aunque los meta-análisisson favorables en algunos aspectos. Parece existir una disparidadentre el tipo de beneficio (cuando se observa) y el sexo. Y en particularlos resultados son contradictorios en personas diabéticas, lascuales representan un pequeño porcentaje de la muestra de poblaciónincluida en los estudios. A pesar de esto, la American Diabetes Associationdesde 1997, y otras sociedades científicas (incluidas variasespañolas) desde tiempos más recientes, recomiendan el uso de aspirinaa dosis bajas en prevención primaria en todo paciente diabéticomayor de 40 años, tipo 1 o tipo 2; y en todos los menores de 40 ymayores de 21 años que presenten otro factor de riesgo cardiovascular,además de la diabetes (antecedentes familiares de enfermedadvascular, hipertensión arterial, tabaquismo, dislipidemia o albuminuria).En este trabajo se revisan los resultados de los ensayos clínicosrandomizados y controlados sobre la prevención cardiovascular primariacon aspirina, en los que se podrían apoyar las directrices oficialesde la American Diabetes Association, y se llega a la conclusiónde que no existen actualmente pruebas científicas suficientes parasostenerlas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(6): 613-620, nov.-dic.2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75316</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La prevención primaria con aspirina de enfermedades cardiovasculares en personas diabéticas. Revisión de las pruebas disponibles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
