<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94222</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Identification and prioritization of interventions to improve efficiency in the National Health System</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To identify a significant number of interventions to improve efficiency and reduce waste in the Spanish National Health System (NHS), to prioritize these interventions according to their impact, and to assess the measures recently adopted by the Spanish government. Material and methods: A meeting was held with 13 healthcare experts, structured according to a mixed method adapted from brainstorming, nominal group and Rand consensus methods. Results: The panel proposed 101 possible actions to improve the efficiency of the Spanish NHS. The11 measures announced by the Government in the Royal Decrees-Laws 4 and 8 of 2010 increased the total number of measures assessed to 112. The panel&#146;s proposals centered on accountability and good governance, the concentration of hospital equipment and services, reduction of preventive services of little value, utilization management (including copayments, but not as a sole element), management of the incorporation of new medicines and technologies, strengthening the role of primary care, reforming workforce policies, and a series of regulatory and managerial interventions. Government measures received an intermediate overall score, but scores of their financial impact were high. Conclusions: There are several opportunities to improve the efficiency of the Spanish NHS beyond the &#147;anticrisis&#148; measures recently adopted by the Spanish Government. Most of these opportunities require feasible structural reforms, although their financial impact is less immediate than that of government measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meneu, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artells, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Identificar un número significativo de actuaciones orientadas a mejorar la eficiencia y reducir el despilfarro en el Sistema Nacional de Salud (SNS), y priorizarlas en función de su impacto. Valorar el impacto y la prioridad de las medidas implantadas o anunciadas por el gobierno. Material y métodos. Reunión de 13 expertos, estructurada siguiendo procedimientos adaptados de las técnicas de brainstorming, grupo nominal y método de consenso Rand. Resultados. El panel propuso 101 posibles medidas para mejorar la eficiencia del SNS, que junto a las 11 contenidas en los Reales Decretos-Ley 4 y 8 de 2010, suman un total de 112 propuestas valoradas. Las propuestas se centraron en el buen gobierno y la transparencia, la concentración de servicios y equipamientos de atención especializada, la reducción de actividades asistenciales y preventivas de escaso valor, la gestión de la demanda (que puede incluir copagos, pero no como único elemento), la gestión de la incorporación de nuevas tecnologías y medicamentos, el refuerzo del papel de la atención primaria, la reforma de las políticas de personal y una serie de actuaciones reguladoras y de gestión. Las medidas gubernamentales recibieron una puntuación global intermedia, pero alta en cuanto a su impacto presupuestario. Conclusiones. Además de las medidas «anticrisis» adoptadas por el gobierno, hay numerosas posibilidades de mejorar la eficiencia interna del SNS. En su mayor parte pasan por reformas estructurales factibles, pero con impacto presupuestario menos inmediato que las medidas gubernamentales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(2): 95-105, may. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Identificación y priorización de actuaciones de mejora de la eficiencia en el Sistema Nacional de Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2046^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31424^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
