<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117942</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medical support in terrorist attacks with chemical warfare agents: over ten years since the sarin terrorist attacks in Japan (Part 2)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After the September 11 (2001) terrorist attacks in the USA and the subsequent mailing of letters contaminated with B. anthracisspores, a high perception of risk has become noticeable regarding the possibility of attacks with weapons of mass destruction, particularly by groups associated to the Al Qaeda terror network. For this reason, the medical personnel &#150;both extra- and intrahospitalary&#150; has become concerned about how to act and perform in this type of events. In the case of chemical warfare agents, the guiding principles of medical support are based on the experiences and on the lessons learned by the personnel that dealt with the sarin terrorist attacks in Japan in1994 and 1995. The present paper aims at delving deeper into these lessons and findings of over ten years ago, bearing in mind that any and every medical service and organisation should adapt them to their particular environment, situation and characteristics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pita, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ishimatsu, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras los atentados del 11 de septiembre de 2001 en EE.UU. y, sobre todo, desde los envíos de sobres con esporas de carbunco, existe una alta percepción del riesgo sobre posibles atentados con armas de destrucción masiva por grupos asociados a la red terrorista Al Qaeda. Esto ha llevado a que el personal sanitario extrahospitalario y hospitalario se interese sobre cómo debería ser su actuación en este tipo de incidentes. En el caso particular de los agentes químicos de guerra la base de la actuación sanitaria son las lecciones aprendidas por el personal sanitario que participó en los atentados terroristas con sarín que tuvieron lugar en Japón en 1994 y 1995. El presente trabajo intenta profundizar en estas lecciones aprendidas hace ya más de diez años, teniendo en cuenta que será cada servicio y organización sanitaria el que deberá adaptarlas a su situación y características particulares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);19(6): 337-346, dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117942</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actuación sanitaria en atentados terroristas con agentes químicos de guerra: más de diez años después de los atentados con sarín en Japón (2ª parte)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52888^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2665^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2666^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27980^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35146</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
