<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057815</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nurses and the draft of the Bill of Promotion of Personal Autonomy and Attention to Individuals on a Situation of Dependency: challenges and opportunities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Next passing of the Law of Personal Autonomy and Dependency will cover a great amount of needs: as those of dependent people as those of their relatives. But at the same time it will permit to set a setting in which a great amount of professionals will combine their activities in order to give an answer to those people demands.     In this setting, nurses, whose main job is the caring, should be the key element in the diagnostic of the situation, planning, management, assessment of cares and coordination of the communal resources, to give the answer to the communal demands and the approach of the Law.     We are not demanding a place, as for that, it should be a space. We want to visualize what the nurses have always been doing: giving their cares -in this case to dependent people and their families- in the framework of a Law of such a great significance which means challenges and opportunities to nurses, mainly in the field of the Health Primary Care, in which strategies in this sense are being introduced</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Riera, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriaga Piñeiro, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La próxima aprobación de la Ley de Autonomía Personal y Dependencia dará cobertura a una gran cantidad de necesidades tanto de las personas dependientes como de sus familiares. Pero al mismo tiempo permitirá dibujar un escenario en el que una gran cantidad de profesionales deberán articular sus actividades con el fin de dar respuesta a las demandas de estas personas.     En este escenario las enfermeras, cuya esencia son los cuidados, deben configurarse como la pieza clave en el diagnóstico de la situación, la planificación, dirección, evaluación de los cuidados y la coordinación de los recursos comunitarios, que permitan dar respuesta a las demandas comunitarias y a los planteamientos de la Ley.     No se trata de reivindicar un espacio, pues para esto debería existir vacío. Se trata de visibilizar lo que desde siempre han venido haciendo las enfermeras, la prestación de cuidados -en este caso a personas dependientes y sus familias- en el marco de una Ley de tanta trascendencia social y que supone retos y oportunidades para las enfermeras en el ámbito fundamentalmente de la Atención Primaria de Salud en el que ya se están implantando estrategias en este sentido</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;15(54): 35-38, 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057815</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las enfermeras y el anteproyecto de Ley de Promoción de la  Autonomía Personal y Atención a las Personas en Situación de Dependencia. Retos y oportunidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37692</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
