<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048533</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Description of an outbreak of Campylobacter jejuni gastroenteritis and molecular characterization of the implicated strain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this study is to describe an outbreak of diarrhea caused by Campylobacter jejuni in a primary school. Methods. Stool samples from five patients were cultured. Molecular typing of the isolated strains was performed using PCR-RFLP-flaA, PFGE and MLST. Results. Campylobacter jejuni was isolated from all five patients. Two of the five strains were available for typing. The DNA patterns of the two isolates were indistinguishable. Conclusion. The results suggest that the causal strain had a common identity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Echeita, María Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos, Rosa de los</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Portolés, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taveira, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir el estudio de un brote de diarrea por Campylobacter jejuni en una escuela infantil. Métodos. Se obtuvieron coprocultivos en 5 pacientes. La tipificación molecular se realizó mediante (RFLP-PCR flaA), electroforesis en campo pulsante (PFGE) y secuenciación de genes metabólicos (MLST). Resultados. Se aisló Campylobacter jejuni en los 5 enfermos. Sólo pudieron recuperarse para la tipificación 2 cepas. La tipificación mediante los 3 métodos resultó indistinguible en ambos aislamientos. Conclusión. Estos resultados sugieren una identidad común de la cepa causal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;24(7): 437-439, ago. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048533</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de un brote de gastroenteritis por y caracterización molecular de la cepa implicada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22153^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22153^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2201^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28882^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28882^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33872</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2201^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
