<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-12962</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The structure of personality traits in adolescents: the Five-Factor Model and the Alternative Five</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last years, the Five-Factor Model has been object of an increasing interest as a structural description of personality. Nevertheless, the usefulness of the model in adolescence has not received enough attention. Particularly scarce are the studies examining its most representative questionnaire (the NEO-PI-R) in adolescent samples. Also scarce are the studies on the ZKPQ-III, which assesses the Zuckerman-Kuhlman «Alternative Five». In this study, the NEO-PI-R and the ZKPQ-III were administered to a sample of adolescents aged 15-19, together with measures of positive and negative affect, antisocial behavior and academic failure. These data allow examination of: 1) the structures of the NEO-PI-R and the ZKPQ-III in a young population ; 2) the relationships between both models and revelant correlates, in order to explore their nomological nets; 3) the convergence of the NEO-PI-R and the ZKPQ-III in an integrated model (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sobral, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Fraguela, J. Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años, el Modelo de Cinco Factores ha adquirido gran popularidad como descripción estructural de la personalidad. A pesar de ello, se ha analizado muy poco su aplicabilidad en la adolescencia. Son particularmente escasos los trabajos realizados con adolescentes sobre el NEO-PI-R, el instrumento más emblemático del modelo. Igualmente escasos son los trabajos con adolescentes sobre el ZKPQ, que evalúa los 'Cinco Alternativos' de Zuckerman-Kuhlman. En el presente trabajo, el NEO-Pl-R y el ZKPQ-111 fueron aplicados a una muestra de adolescentes (15-19 años), junto con medidas de afecto positivo y negativo, conducta antisocial y fracaso escolar. Con estos datos se examina 1) las estructuras del NEO-PI-R y del ZKPQ-111, con el fin de conocer en qué medida se replican, en los adolescentes, los modelos subyacentes a estos instrumentos; 2) la relación de ambos modelos con correlatos relevantes, con el fin de explorar su red nomológica y 3) cómo convergen el NEO-PI-R y en ZKPQ-111 en un modelo integrado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(1): 134-143, ene. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-12962</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La estructura de los rasgos de personalidad en adolescentes: el Modelo de Cinco Factores y los Cinco Alternativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
