<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83099</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Botulinum Toxin Type A for the Treatment of Primary Hyperhidrosis: A Prospective Study of 52 Patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Primary hyperhidrosis is characterized by excessive sweating in a defined region of the body. It should not be considered a purely cosmetic problem as it has a significant impact on the social and professional relationships of affected individuals. The aim of this study was to determine the clinical profile of patients with primary hyperhidrosis and assess the results obtained with the use of botulinum toxin type A (BTX-A) in clinical practice. Material and methods: The study included 52 patients (39 women and 13 men) with a diagnosis of primary hyperhidrosis treated for the first time with BTX-A. All patients completed a questionnaire that included the following information: age; sex; profession; age at onset, family history, and site of hyperhidrosis; accompanying signs and symptoms, and previous treatment; time to effect of BTX-A; local or systemic side effects; and severity of hyperhidrosis before and after BTX-A treatment. Results and conclusions: Primary hyperhidrosis began during puberty in 61.5% of the patients included in the study, 75% were women, and the mean age was 29.9 years. In 36.5% of patients, first-degree relatives also had primary hyperhidrosis. Hyperhidrosis was classified as palmar in 61.5% of cases, plantar in 53.8%, and axillary in 59.6%. Other sites were affected less frequently. The most common accompanying symptoms were facial erythema (32.7%), palpitations (30.7%), muscle tension (28.8%), shivering (23%), and headache (17.3%). Treatment with BTX-A was well tolerated and there was a highly significant reduction in the severity of hyperhidrosis 2 months after performing the treatment (P&lt;0.001) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gámez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pérez, MÁ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reig, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordá, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La hiperhidrosis primaria (HP) consiste en un exceso de sudación de una zona concreta del cuerpo que es clínicamente perceptible. La HP no debe considerarse un simple problema cosmético, pues supone una dificultad muy importante de relación social y laboral para las personas que lo experimentan. Los objetivos de este estudio han sido definir el perfil clínico de los pacientes con HP y evaluar en la práctica clínica los resultados que consigue el tratamiento con Toxina Botulínica A (TB-A). Material y métodos: La muestra acota un total de 52 pacientes, 39 mujeres y 13 hombres, con diagnóstico de HP tratada por primera vez con TB-A. Todos cumplimentaron una encuesta donde se registraron: edad, sexo, profesión, inicio, antecedentes familiares, localización, signos/síntomas acompañantes y tratamientos previos; inicio del efecto de la TB-A; efectos secundarios locales y/o sistémicos y el grado de severidad de su hiperhidrosis antes del tratamiento y después del mismo. Resultados y conclusiones: La HP se inicia en la pubertad en el 61,5% de los casos; el 75% son mujeres con una edad media de 29,9 años. El 36,5% de los pacientes tienen familiares de primer grado con HP. La localización de la hipersudación es palmar en el 61,5% casos, plantar en el 53,8% y axilar en el 59,6 %, siendo menor en otras localizaciones. La clínica acompañante más frecuente es: eritema facial (32,7%), palpitaciones (30,7%), tensión muscular (28,8%), temblor (23%) y cefalea (17,3%). El tratamiento con TB-A es bien tolerado y respecto a la escala de severidad de la hiperhidrosis, se produce una mejoría muy significativa (p&lt;1,0×10&amp;#8722;32; potencia estadística=1) a los dos meses del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;101(7): 614-621, sept. 2010. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83099</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Toxina Botulínica A en el tratamiento de la hiperhidrosis primaria: estudio prospectivo de 52 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7126^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
