<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165923</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Living conditions of malnourished women victims of domestic violence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Malnutrition is a multifactorial pathology, to which different authors have associated with violence. Both are present routinely in our settings, however, there are not enough studies to investigate the relationship between them. This paper describes the living conditions of Venezuelan malnourished women victims of violence. Methods: Nine women between 20 and 60 years of age with malnutrition and victims of intrafamily violence were interviewed in several states of Venezuela. Food and nutritional interviews and evaluation were carried out. Results: Monotonous diets, a reduced number of meals a day, and the intake of water to quench hunger were common aspects in the eating habits of the participants. Physical and psychological violence was present in most women, and half suffered sexual violence. Conclusions: A relationship between malnutrition and violence experienced by participants is difficult to establish because of the multifactorial nature of malnutrition. This research serves as a reference for future research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reveco Moreno, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ahumada, Mary Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintero Godoy, Marcos Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cravino Urbáez, Aldo Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Cerda, María Fernanda dos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La malnutrición es una patología multifactorial, a la que distintos autores han asociado con la violencia. Ambas están presentes de manera habitual en nuestros entornos, sin embargo, no existen estudios suficientes que investiguen la relación entre ellas. Este trabajo describe las condiciones de vida de mujeres venezolanas malnutridas víctimas de violencia. Métodos: Se entrevistaron 9 mujeres entre 20 y 60 años de edad con malnutrición y víctimas de violencia intrafamiliar, en varios estados de Venezuela. Se realizaron entrevistas y se realizó una evaluación alimentaria y nutricional. Resultados: Dietas monótonas, un número reducido de comidas al día y la ingesta de agua para calmar el hambre, fueron aspectos comunes en los hábitos alimentarios de las participantes. La violencia física y psicológica estuvo presente en la mayoría de las mujeres, y la mitad sufrió violencia sexual. Conclusiones: Una relación entre la malnutrición y la violencia experimentada por las participantes, es difícil de establecer, por el carácter multifactorial de la malnutrición. La presente investigación sirve como una referencia para futuras investigaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;23(2): 0-0, abr.-jun. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165923</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condiciones de vida de mujeres malnutridas víctimas de violencia doméstica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50334^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
