<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049041</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Well-differentiated lymphocytic lymphoma of the prostate. Case report and bibliographic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To report a case of prostate    lymphoma and a brief review of the literature.    METHODS/RESULTS: A 70 year-old mele patient was    referred to the Urology departament with a clinical picture of prostatism, with acute urinary retention (AUR). Surgery with retropubic prostatectomy was performed, and pathology revealed a primary prostate lymphoma. The patient was referred to the departament of Oncology where he received polychemotherapy and radiotherapy. The patient is currently followed by regular visits to Urology outpatients service.The case study is followed by a brief bibliographic review, where we analyse clinical menifestations of this entity,    complementary studies useful for diagnosis (laboratory test, trasrectal prostate biopsy, transuretral resection, ultrasound and computerised axial tomography), treatment options (surgery, polychemotherapy, radiotherapy) as well as survival in these patients.    CONCLUSIONS: Of the cases reviewed, mean age at diagnosis was 57 years. Clinical debut was with prostate symptoms, with or without AUR and sometimes manifestations of renal failure due to obstructive uropathy, as well as general symptoms (astenia, anorexia, weight loss). PSA values    remain unaltered in prostate lymphoma patients. Histologic diagnosis may be made by transrectal prostate biopsy, although transurethral resection (TUR) may be necessary for confirmation. Ultrasound and CT scan are of great utility for diagnosis of both local and distant tumors. From a therapeutic    point of view, surgery for the obstruction of the lower urinary tract (TURP or retropubic prostatectomy) may be necessary, as well as the cyclophosphamide based polychemotherapy with corticosteroids and other cytostatic agents, and    radiotherapy; intratecal chemotherapy has also been used adjuvant bone marrow transplantation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Félix León, Juan M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Undargarain, Otto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermida Pérez, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Montes de Oca, Johannes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar un caso portador de un linfoma de próstata, en un paciente de 70 años de edad y hacer una breve revisión de la literatura.    MÉTODO/RESULTADOS: Se trata de un paciente varón de 70 años de edad, que es visto en consulta de Urología por presentar un cuadro de prostatismo, llegando a la retención aguda de orina (RAO). Es intervenido quirúrgicamente realizándosele    una prostatectomía retropúbica, obteniéndose como resultado anatomopatológico un linfoma primario de próstata, el paciente fue remitido a Oncología, siendo tratado con radioterapia, llevando actualmente seguimiento    en consulta de Urología. Se hace una breve revisión bibliográfica, donde analizamos las manifestaciones clínicas    de esta entidad, las pruebas complementarias que nos ayudan a hacer el diagnóstico (exámenes de laboratorio, biopsia prostática transrectal, resección transuretral, ecografía,    tomografía axial computarizada), los tratamientos que se aplican (cirugía, radioterapia, poliquimioterapia) así como la supervivencia de estos pacientes.    CONCLUSIONES: La edad promedio de diagnóstico en la casuística revisada por nosotros fue de 57 años. La forma    clínica de debut son síntomas de prostatismo, pudiendo estar presente la RAO y en algunos casos manifestaciones de insuficiencia renal por uropatía obstructiva, así como manifestaciones generales (astenia, anorexia, pérdida de peso). Las cifras de antígeno específico prostático (PSA) no sufren alteraciones en los linfomas prostáticos. El diagnóstico    histológico se puede realizar a través de la biopsia    de próstata transrectal, aunque puede ser necesario la resección transuretral (RTU) de próstata para una mejor confirmación. La ultrasonografía y la tomografía axial computarizada    (TAC) son de gran utilidad para el diagnóstico tanto local como de extensión de estos tumores. Desde el punto de vista del tratamiento puede ser necesario la cirugía    desobstructiva (RTU, prostatectomía a cielo abierto), así como la poliquimioterapia a base de ciclofosfamida en asociación con corticoides y otros citostáticos, la radioterapia    y también se ha utilizado la quimioterapia intratecal, el transplante autólogo de médula ósea como complemento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;59(5): 538-541, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049041</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma linfocítico, bien diferenciado de la próstata. Presentación de un caso y breve revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
