<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137948</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of the utilization of antidepressant drugs in the Rioja and Zamora health districts throughout the 1997-2001 period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Due to the high increase in the utilization of anti- depressant drugs and the change in the prescription profile within this group, this study is aimed at discovering the evolution of the utilization of antidepressant drugs (NO6A subgroup) outside of the hospital setting in the Rioja and Zamora health districts throughout the 1997-2001 period and to evaluate the impact of the new drugs. Methods: A study was made of the utilization of drugs included in the NO6A treatment subgroup under the Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) classification. The data on the utilization of each specialty was taken from the pharmacy management (SIFAR) software applications and has been stated for each active ingredient in Daily Dose per Inhabitant (DDI). Results: In the period under study, there was an increase in the total utilization of antidepressants in the two areas (Zamora 55% and Rioja 93%) due mainly to the increase in selective serotinin reuptake inhibitors (SSRI) (Zamora 80% and Rioja 143%) and in the new heterocyclic antidepressants (Zamora 82% and Rioja 78%). Conclusions: There has been an increase in the utilization of antidepressants, all of which has taken place in conjunction with a change in the prescription profile. There is a clear shift toward the utilization of the SSRI's and some heterocyclic antidepressants (venlafaxine, trazodone, reboxetine), the utilization of tricyclic antidepressants and IMAO's having decreased (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sainz de Rozas Aparicio, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Madero, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Clavijo Díez, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Debido al gran aumento del consumo de antidepresivos, y al cambio del perfil de prescripción dentro del grupo, el objetivo del estudio es describir la evolución del consumo extrahospitalario de este subgrupo terapéutico (N06A) en las áreas de salud de La Rioja y Zamora durante el periodo 1997-2001 y valorar el impacto de los nuevos fármacos. Métodos: Se ha estudiado el consumo de fármacos incluidos en el subgrupo terapéutico N06A de la Clasificación Anatómica Terapéutica Química. Los datos de consumo de cada especialidad se han obtenido de los programas informáticos de gestión de farmacia (SIFAR) y se han expresado para cada principio activo en Dosis Habitante Día (DHD). Resultados: En el periodo de estudio se ha producido un incremento del consumo total de antidepresivos en las dos áreas (Zamora 55% y La Rioja 93%), debido fundamentalmente al incremento de los inhibidores selectivos de la recaptación de serotonina (ISRS) (Zamora 80% y La Rioja 143%) y de los nuevos antidepresivos heterocíclicos (Zamora 82% y La Rioja 78%). Conclusiones: El incremento en la utilización de antidepresivos va acompañado de un cambio en el perfil de prescripción: hay un claro desplazamiento hacia el consumo de los ISRS y algunos heterocíclicos (venlafaxina, trazodona, reboxetina), disminuyendo la utilización de los antidepresivos tricíclicos y de los inhibidores de la monoaminooxidasa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;78(5): 631-645, sept.-oct. 2004. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137948</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del consumo de fármacos antidepresivos en las áreas sanitarias de La Rioja y Zamora durante el periodo 1997-2001</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2435</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
