<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055866</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the situation of treatments for smoking cessation based on cognitive-behavioral therapy and nicotine patches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the last 10-15 years or so, there has been a stagnation of research in cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) for smoking cessation and an increase of research in pharmacological therapy, while part of scientific community seems biased towards pharmacological therapy and against CBT. The aim of the present study was to test whether that situation refl ects the efficacy of clinical treatments for smokers. After reviewing and re-analyzing two previous meta-analyses and new empirical studies, results pointed out that, according to abstinence rates at post-treatment and 6- and 12-month follow-ups, CBT, administered alone or in combination with nicotine patches, is more efficacious than nicotine patches administered alone. Therefore, nicotine patches should always be used in combination with CBT to maximize their efficacy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vera, María Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos 10-15 años se ha producido un estancamiento de la investigación sobre la terapia cognitivo-conductual (TCC) del tabaquismo y un auge de la investigación sobre la terapia farmacológica, mientras que parte de la comunidad científica parece sesgada en favor de esta última terapia y en detrimento de la TCC. Esta situación no refl eja los datos sobre la efi cacia de los tratamientos clínicos para el tabaquismo. Tras revisar y reanalizar dos meta-análisis previos y completarlos con nuevas investigaciones, los resultados indican que, en función de las tasas de abstinencia en el postratamiento y en los seguimientos a 6 y 12 meses, la TCC utilizada en solitario o en combinación con parches de nicotina es más eficaz que la administración aislada de los parches. Por tanto, los parches deberían utilizarse siempre en combinación con TCC para maximizar su eficacia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);3(2/3): 260-290, dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055866</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la situación de los tratamientos para dejar de fumar basados en terapia cognitivo-conductual y en parches de nicotina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
