<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148488</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Care and economic impact of thyroid ultrasound examination at single visits to endocrinology clinics (the ETIEN 1 study)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Routine thyroid ultrasound examination in a single medical appointment is rarely performed in Spain. The objective of this study was to evaluate the care and economic impact of thyroid US examination in a single endocrine appointment. Methods: A prospective, observational, descriptive study was conducted to analyze data from 2274 patients (mean age, 59 ± 16 years; 83% females) performed at least one thyroid US in a single visit to an endocrinology clinic during 2013 and 2014. The number of endocrine acts with thyroid US, single endocrine and US acts without review, and the change in the number of thyroid US requested by endocrinologists to the radiology department and total thyroid US examinations performed at the radiology department during the study period were assessed. Results: In 2013 and 2014, 2558 endocrine acts with thyroid US were performed, of which 42.2% were single endocrine and US appointments without a second endocrine act, with estimated savings of &#128;58,946.40. As compared to 2012, the number of thyroid US requested by endocrinologists to the radiology department decreased by 43.3% and 86.0% in 2013 and 2014 respectively, and total thyroid US performed by the radiology department decreased by 28.1% and 68.3% respectively, with estimated savings of &#128;94,441.36. Conclusions: Thyroid US examination in a single endocrine appointment allows for decreasing the number of both second endocrine acts and thyroid US examinations performed at the radiology department, thus reducing the number of unnecessary clinic visits and promoting considerable economic savings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayala, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carral, Florentino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La realización de ecografía tiroidea en consultas en acto único está escasamente implantada en nuestro país. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el impacto asistencial y económico de la utilización de la ecografía tiroidea en consultas de endocrinología en acto único. Métodos: Se trata de un estudio prospectivo, observacional y descriptivo en el que se analizaron los datos de 2.274 pacientes (edad media: 59 +/- 16 años; 83% mujeres) a los cuales se les realizó al menos una ecografía tiroidea en acto único en consultas de endocrinología durante 2013 y 2014. Se evaluaron el número de consultas de acto único, consultas con alta directa y la variación en el número de ecografías solicitadas y realizadas en radiodiagnóstico durante el período de estudio. Resultados: En 2013 y 2014 se realizaron 2.558 ecografías tiroideas en consultas de endocrinología en acto único, siendo el 42,2% consultas de alta directa sin revisión de resultados, con un ahorro estimado de 58.946,40 euros. En 2013 y 2014 se redujo el número de ecografías solicitadas a radiodiagnóstico en un 43,3% y 86,0%, respectivamente. De forma global se realizaron en radiodiagnóstico un 28,1% y un 68,3% menos ecografías tiroideas respecto al año 2012, estimándose un ahorro económico de 94.441,36 euros. Conclusiones: La realización de ecografías tiroideas en consultas de endocrinología en acto único permite reducir tanto el número de revisiones de recogida de resultados como las ecografías tiroideas realizadas en radiodiagnóstico, lo cual disminuye el número de desplazamientos innecesarios de pacientes y favorece un ahorro económico considerable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(2): 64-69, feb. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148488</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto asistencial y económico de la ecografía tiroidea en acto único en consultas de endocrinología (estudio ETIEN 1)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30176^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
