<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100702</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of systemic corticosteroid administration in the prognosis of patients with community-acquired pneumonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) is a common and potentially serious disease. In recent years, control of the inflammatory response has begun to be taken into account as a new therapeutic target. This study has aimed to analyze the influence of the administration of systemic corticosteroids on mortality of patients admitted with CAP in the common clinical practice. Patients and methods. A prospective observational study was carried out. The study included patients with CAP admitted to Internal Medicine and Pulmonology services of a tertiary hospital in 2007. Treatment given during admission was recorded and mortality during hospitalization and at 30 and 90 days after discharge was determined. Results. A total of 257 patients, 179 men (69.6%) and 78 women (30.4%) were analyzed. Mean age was 72±15 years. Both in-hospital mortality as well as at 30 days of discharge was 10.2%, while overall mortality at 90 days was 14.8%. No relation was found between the use of corticosteroids and mortality. Use of corticosteroids also did not modify the length of hospital stay or readmission rate. Conclusions. It was observed in this study that treatment with corticosteroids in CAP is not associated with lower mortality and does not affect the rate of readmissions. It also does not change the length of hospital stay(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellón-Cano, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel-Díez, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Rueda, A. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Sala-Walther, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Herranz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La neumonía adquirida en la comunidad (NAC) es una afección común y potencialmente grave. En los últimos años ha empezado a tenerse en cuenta el control de la respuesta inflamatoria como un nuevo objetivo terapéutico en esta enfermedad. El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar la influencia de la administración de corticoides sistémicos sobre la mortalidad de los pacientes ingresados con NAC en condiciones de práctica clínica habitual. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio prospectivo observacional en el que se recogieron casos de NAC en pacientes ingresados en los servicios de Medicina Interna y Neumología de un hospital terciario a lo largo del año 2007. Se registró el tratamiento administrado durante su ingreso y se determinó la mortalidad hospitalaria, así como a los 30 y 90 días del alta hospitalaria. Resultados. Se analizaron 257 pacientes, 179 varones (69,6%) y 78 mujeres (30,4%). La edad media fue de 72±15 años. Tanto la mortalidad hospitalaria como a los 30 días del alta fue del 10,2%, mientras que la mortalidad global a los 90 días fue del 14,8%. No se encontró relación entre el empleo de corticoides y la mortalidad. El uso de corticoides tampoco modificó los días de estancia hospitalaria ni la tasa de reingresos. Conclusiones. En este estudio se ha observado que el tratamiento con corticoides sistémicos en la NAC no se asocia con una menor mortalidad ni influye en la tasa de reingresos. Tampoco modifica la duración de la estancia hospitalaria(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;212(7): 337-343, jul.-ago.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100702</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la administración de corticoides sistémicos en el pronóstico de los pacientes con neumonía adquirida en la comunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2016^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
