<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82971</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of intravenous hyoscine butylbromide-oxytocin or oxytocin on the duration of labor in term pregnancies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To compare the effects of intravenous hyoscine butylbromide-oxytocin or oxytocin on the duration of labor in term pregnancies. Method. Ninety patients were selected and randomly assigned to receive intravenous hyoscine butylbromide-oxytocin (n=45) or intravenous oxytocin (n=45). We evaluated maternal adverse effects, effects on neonatal Apgar score, cervical dilatation 1 hour after drug administration and the interval between the onset of labor and delivery. Results. There were no significant differences between the two groups in maternal age, gestational age, or Bishop score at drug administration (p=ns). No significant differences were observed in the duration of the first, second or third phases of labor between the two groups (p=ns). No significant differences were found between the groups in Apgar scores at 1 and 5minutes (p=ns). No maternal adverse effects were observed or reported due to the use of hyoscine-butylbromide or oxytocin. Conclusion. The effect of hyoscine butylbromide-oxytocin on the duration of labour in term pregnancies is similar to that of oxytocin. The drug does not alter Apgar score or produce maternal adverse effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerra-Velásquez, MEry</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejia-Montilla, Jorly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nobrega-Correa, Helen de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Bolívar, Joel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Cepeda, Duly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Nadia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perozo-Romero, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Comparar los efectos del butil bromuro de hioscina-oxitocina u oxitocina intravenosos en la duración del parto de embarazos a término. Método. Se seleccionaron 90 pacientes y fueron asignadas al azar para recibir: butil bromuro de hioscina+oxitocina intravenosos (grupo A, n=45) u oxitocina intravenosa (grupo B, n=45). Se evaluaron efectos adversos maternos, efectos sobre el Apgar del recién nacido, dilatación cervical después de una hora de la administración y tiempo entre el inicio del trabajo del parto y la obtención del recién nacido. Resultados. No se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los grupos con relación a edad materna, edad gestacional y puntuación de Bishop en el momento de la administración de los fármacos (p=ns). No se observaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la duración de la primera, segunda y tercera fase del trabajo de parto entre las pacientes del grupo A y las pacientes del grupo B (p=ns). Tampoco se observaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los grupos en las mediciones de Apgar al minuto y a los 5 minutos (p=ns). No se reportaron u observaron afectos adversos maternos atribuibles al uso del butil bromuro de hioscina o de oxitocina. Conclusión. El butil bromuro de hioscina-oxitocina tiene un efecto similar a la oxitocina en la duración del parto en embarazos a término, sin alteraciones en el Apgar del recién nacido y sin efectos adversos maternos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(12): 502-506, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82971</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del butil bromuro de hioscina-oxitocina u oxitocina intravenosos en la duración del parto de embarazos a término</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22596^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31106^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38862^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2119^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
