<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73550</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Secondary prevention of alcohol and/or drug abuse in trauma patients: Results of a national survey in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo determine the degree of activity in the field of secondary prevention of alcohol and/or drug abuse in trauma patients in Spain.Material and methodsWe surveyed 76 hospitals located in all the autonomous regions of Spain. We collected information about the number of severe trauma patients admitted to the ICU per year, the detection of alcohol and drugs in these patients, and the activity for secondary prevention through motivational intervention among other approaches.ResultsOf the 76 hospitals surveyed, 66 responded and only one carried out any secondary prevention activity through motivational intervention. Most of the hospitals surveyed (64.5%, 40/62) did not know of the possibility of secondary prevention through motivational intervention and (29%, 18/62) did not have the resources to carry it out. Asked whether they screened trauma patients for drugs and/or alcohol, 15.6% of centers responded &#147;always&#148; 37.5% (24/64) &#147;usually&#148;, and 40.6% only &#147;sometimes&#148;.ConclusionMost centers surveyed are unaware of the usefulness of secondary prevention in trauma patients. This lack of awareness may be responsible for the lack of activity in this field in Spain. A plan to increase awareness, including educational interventions, is necessary to promote secondary prevention of alcohol and drug abuse among trauma patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Mondéjar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galdos Anuncyabay, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alted, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Gabiña, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miñambres, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoAveriguar cuál es el grado de actividad en el campo de la prevención secundaria en traumatizados relacionados con alcohol y drogas en el territorio español.Material y métodoEncuesta a 76 hospitales de todas las comunidades autónomas del país, solicitando información sobre número de pacientes traumatizados graves que requerían ingreso en UCI por año, la detección de alcohol y drogas en estos pacientes y la actividad en prevención secundaria mediante intervención motivacional, entre otras.ResultadosDe los 76 hospitales encuestados, 66 respondieron y tan sólo uno realizaba alguna actividad de prevención secundaria mediante intervención motivacional. La mayoría de los encuestados (64,5% [40/62]) desconocían esta posibilidad y el 29% no la realizaba por falta de medios (18/62). El 15,6% de los centros realiza siempre análisis de alcohol y drogas en traumatizados. El 37,5% (24/64) admite realizar estas pruebas en la &#147;mayoría&#148; de los pacientes, y un 40,6% sólo lo realiza &#147;a veces&#148;.ConclusiónLa mayoría de los encuestados desconoce la utilidad de la prevención secundaria en traumatizados. Este desconocimiento puede ser causante de la nula actividad que se detecta en España en este campo. Es necesario un plan de difusión con acciones educacionales para promocionar este tipo de actividades(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(7): 321-326, oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73550</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención secundaria en traumatizados relacionados con alcohol y drogas. Resultados de una encuesta nacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
