<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59620</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Isolated conjunctival involvement in langerhans cell histiocytosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 43-year-old woman referred for ahyperemic node in the inferior conjunctival fornix.No improvement was observed after 10 days ofantibiotic and anti-inflammatory topical treatment,so biopsy-extirpation was performed. Histopathologicaland immunohistochemical findings suggestedthe diagnosis of Langerhans cell histiocytosis(LCH). No findings of extraocular manifestationswere shown after an intensive clinical and analyticalinvestigation.Discussion: LCH is a disease with different organmanifestations whose diagnosis depends on histologicalfindings. We present a patient with isolatedconjunctival affectation, which to our knowledge isthe third case published in the literature(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Molina, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sotoca-Fernández, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez-Méndez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez-Llatas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escario-Travesedo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Marchite, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Mujer de 43 años que consulta por unnódulo hiperémico en fondo de saco conjuntivalinferior. Tras diez días de tratamiento antibiótico yantiinflamatorio tópico no se observa mejoría, porlo que se realiza una biopsia-extirpación. El resultadoanatomopatológico e inmunohistoquímico esinformado como histiocitosis de células de Langerhans(HCL), procediéndose a realizar un estudiosistémico con diferentes pruebas complementarias,sin hallar afectación a otro nivel.Discusión: La histiocitosis de células de Langerhanses una enfermedad de afectación muy variada,cuyo diagnóstico se establece mediante hallazgoshistológicos. Presentamos un caso de implicaciónexclusivamente conjuntival, habiéndose publicadosólo tres casos previamente en la literatura médica consultada(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;84(4): 217-220, abr. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59620</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histiocitosis de células de Langerhans con afectación conjuntival aislada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
