<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037392</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-4815</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vaccination in patients with systemic lupus erythematous</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vaccination has been perhaps the most important achievement in medicine of the last century. A hoard of infectious diseases that used to claim the lives of many, especially children, have been prevented or even eradicated. Concerns regarding the safety and effectiveness of immunization in patients with systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) have persisted for over 50 years. Prospective studies have shown that immunization with inactivated/killed vaccines is probable safe in patients with SLE. Individuals on immunosuppressive agents and/or high-dose steroids (more than 20 mg/day) should not receive live vaccines, as stated in the guidelines proposed by the British Society of Rheumatology (BSR). Until evidence becomes available, the advice of the BSR should be followed and patients with SLE who are at risk of exposure should be vaccinated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rial, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tavares, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La vacunación ha sido, quizá, el logro más importante de la medicina en el último siglo. Un gran número de enfermedades infecciosas que se cobraban las vidas de muchas personas, especialmente niños, se han prevenido y algunas, incluso, se han erradicado. Las preocupaciones con respecto a la seguridad y la eficacia de la inmunización de pacientes con lupus eritematoso sistémico han persistido durante más de 50 años. Estudios prospectivos han demostrado que la inmunización con vacunas inactivadas o de virus muertos es probablemente segura en pacientes con lupus eritematoso sistémico. Los individuos tratados con fármacos inmunodepresores y/o altas dosis de esteroides (más de 20 mg/día) no deberían recibir vacunas vivas, según se establece en las pautas propuestas por la British Society of Rheumatology (BSR). Sin embargo, hasta que tal evidencia llegue a estar disponible, deberíamos seguir los consejos de la BSR, y se debería vacunar a los pacientes con lupus eritematoso sistémico expuestos a factores de riesgo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. reumatol. (Ed. impr.);32(2): 60-63, feb. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037392</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vacunación en pacientes con lupus eritematoso sistémico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23853^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
