<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155515</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inequalities in mental health in the working population of Spain: a National Health Survey-based study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: In the working population, poor mental health is a significant problem whose prevalence rates and associated factors could differ by gender, especially in a period of socioeconomic changes. The aims of this study were: a) to determine the prevalence of poor mental health in the working population of Spain in 2011; b) to identify the association of this prevalence with socioeconomic and work-related variables for men and women separately; c) to determine if the patterns differ by gender. Methods: A cross-sectional study was conducted with data from the National Health Survey of Spain (2011). Of the 21,007 participants in the survey, we selected 7396 whose employment status was described as &#145;working&#146; The General Health Questionnaire (GHQ-12) was used as a screening tool to detect poor mental health. Prevalences were calculated and bivariate and multivariate logistic regression models were fitted to verify the association between variables. Results: The prevalence of poor mental health was higher among women (19.9%) than men (13.9%), the overall prevalence being 16.8%. The variables associated with a higher prevalence were type of contract and work-related variables in men, and age and socioeconomic variables in women. Conclusions: This study shows that, in the working population of Spain, the prevalence of poor mental health and its related factors differ by gender. Poor mental health is mainly related to socioeconomic variables in women but is mostly associated with work-related variables in men (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artazcoz, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias-de la Torre, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Antonio José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Villa, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín,  Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En población trabajadora, los problemas de salud mental son un problema significativo cuya prevalencia y factores asociados pueden diferir según el sexo, en especial durante un periodo de cambios socioeconómicos. Los objetivos de este estudio son: a) conocer la prevalencia de problemas de salud mental en población trabajadora de España en 2011; b) evaluar la asociación de esta prevalencia con variables socioeconómicas y laborales para hombres y mujeres por separado; c) determinar si los patrones difieren por sexos. Métodos: Estudio transversal con datos de la Encuesta Nacional de Salud de España (2011). De los 21.007 participantes en la encuesta, se seleccionaron 7396 cuya situación laboral era «trabajando». Se utilizó el General Health Questionnaire (GHQ-12) como herramienta de cribado para detectar problemas de salud mental. Se calcularon las prevalencias y se realizaron modelos bivariados y multivariados de regresión logística para comprobar la asociación entre variables. Resultados: La prevalencia de problemas de salud mental fue mayor entre las mujeres (19,9%) que entre los hombres (13,9%), con una prevalencia global del 16,8%. Las variables asociadas a una mayor prevalencia fueron el tipo de contrato y las relacionadas con el empleo remunerado entre hombres, y la edad y las variables socioeconómicas en las mujeres. Conclusiones: En población trabajadora de España, la prevalencia de problemas de salud mental y sus factores relacionados difieren en función del sexo. Mientras en las mujeres la prevalencia podría estar más relacionada con factores socioeconómicos, en los hombres podría estarlo más con variables relacionadas con el empleo remunerado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(5): 339-344, sept.-oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155515</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desigualdades en salud mental en población trabajadora de España: un estudio basado en la Encuesta Nacional de Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
