<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129467</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Manual tool grip span and grip force during flower cutting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the association between grip span of a manual flower cutting tool and maximum peak force exerted by each finger in the operating hand during apprehension. Methods: An experiment was conducted in which 11 women performed the stem cut of a flower. These women did not suffer from carpal tunnel syndrome. Grip span was calculated when they exerted the maximum peak force with each finger. Results: The main finding of the study reveals that fingers exert the maximum peak force when the grip span values are the same for everyone. However, due to the shape of the tool commonly used in the Colombian flower industry (first order level), each finger reaches its maximum peak force at different times, bypassing the full capacity of each finger&#146;s grip force. Conclusion: These findings could be used to improve the mechanical advantage of manual cutting tools to reduce risk factors for carpal tunnel syndrome due to overexertion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maradei García, María Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinel Correal, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo Estupiñán, Zuli Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la relación entre la apertura de la herramienta manual de corte de flores y la fuerza ejercida por cada dedo de la mano operante durante el gesto de aprehensión. Métodos: Se desarrolló un experimento con 11 mujeres que realizaron el corte del tallo de una flor. Las operarias no sufrían del síndrome del túnel carpiano. Se calculó el diámetro de apertura de la herramienta cuando la fuerza de aprehensión en cada dedo era máxima al realizar el corte. Resultados: El principal hallazgo del estudio revela que los dedos ejercen el pico máximo de su fuerza de aprehensión cuando el valor del diámetro de apertura de la herramienta es igual para todos los dedos. Sin embargo, debido a las características formales de la herramienta comúnmente usada en el sector floricultor colombiano (palanca de primer orden), cada dedo realiza el pico máximo de la fuerza de aprehensión en diferentes instantes en el tiempo, desaprovechando la capacidad total de la fuerza de aprehensión. Conclusiones: Este hallazgo podría ser utilizado para mejorar la ventaja mecánica de las herramientas manuales de corte y reducir los factores de riesgo del síndrome del túnel carpiano debidos al sobresfuerzo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);17(4): 190-195, oct.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apertura de la herramienta manual y fuerza de aprehensión durante el corte de flores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37253</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2392^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14503^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2392^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2392^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
