<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81100</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cystatin C and cardiovascular risk in the general population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Cystatin C has been proposed as a novel marker of renal function and as a predictor of cardiovascular risk in the elderly. The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence of an elevated cystatin C level in the general population and its relationship with cardiovascular risk factors and disease. Methods. This descriptive epidemiologic cross-sectional study involved a simple randomized sample of individuals aged &gt;49 years from the general population, and was based on personal health records. From the final selection of 415 individuals, 359 underwent cystatin C measurement using a immunonephelometric assay. The cut-point used was that recommended for the method in adults. Results. Of the 359 individuals (mean±standard deviation age, 64±10 years, 63.5% female) studied, 17.3% (95% confidence interval [CI] 13.4%-21.2%) had an elevated cystatin C level. The mean level was 0.81±0.21 mg/L, and increased with age. Elevation of the cystatin C level was associated with: older age (P &lt; .0001); high measures of systolic blood pressure (P &lt; .0001), hemoglobin A1c (P=.031), triglycerides (P=.019), homocysteine (P &lt; .0001), C-reactive protein (P=.015), fibrinogen (P=.006) and microalbuminuria (P=.001); and a low high-density lipoprotein cholesterol level (P=.021) and estimated glomerular filtration rate (P &lt; .0001). Associated cardiovascular diseases included coronary heart disease (P=.013) and heart failure (P=.038). The main factors independently associated with an elevated cystatin C level were diabetes (odds ratio [OR]=5.37), male sex (OR=4.91) and decreased glomerular filtration (OR=0.83). Conclusions. The prevalence of an elevated cystatin C level in the general population was found to be high and was associated with the presence of classical cardiovascular risk factors such as diabetes, hypertension and chronic renal disease, along with higher levels of C-reactive protein, homocysteine and fibrinogen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Rodríguez, Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cepeda, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tranche-Iparraguirre, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín-Iranzo, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hevia-Rodríguez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riesgo-García, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Casas, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Las determinaciones de cistatina C se han propuesto como nuevo marcador de la función renal y predictor del riesgo cardiovascular en ancianos. Nuestro objetivo fue conocer la prevalencia de individuos con cistatina C elevada en población general y su asociación con factores de riesgo y enfermedad cardiovascular. Métodos. Estudio epidemiológico descriptivo transversal por muestreo aleatorio simple en población general mayor de 49 años, obtenido de la base de tarjeta sanitaria individual. Fueron seleccionados 415 pacientes de los que se realizó la determinación de cistatina C a 359 de ellos utilizando un método inmunonefelométrico. Como punto de corte se aceptó el recomendado para el método en adultos. Resultados. Se estudió a 359 pacientes (media de edad ± desviación estándar, 64 ± 10 años; el 63,5%, mujeres); presentó cistatina C elevada el 17,3% (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 13,4%-21,2%), con concentraciones medias de 0,81 ± 0,21 mg/l, que aumentaban con la edad. Las elevaciones de cistatina C se asociaron con: mayor edad (p &lt; 0,0001), presión arterial sistólica (p &lt; 0,0001), hemoglobina A1c (p = 0,031), triglicéridos (p = 0,019), homocisteína (p &lt; 0,0001), proteína C reactiva (p = 0,015), fibrinógeno (p = 0,006), microalbuminuria (p = 0,001) y menor cifra de colesterol de las lipoproteínas de alta densidad (p = 0,021) y filtrado glomerular estimado (p &lt; 0,0001). Las enfermedades cardiovasculares concomitantes fueron la cardiopatía isquémica (p = 0,013) y la insuficiencia cardiaca (p = 0,038). Los principales factores asociados de manera independiente con elevaciones de cistatina C fueron la diabetes (odds ratio [OR] = 5,37), el sexo masculino (OR = 4,91) y el filtrado glomerular descendido (OR = 0,83). Conclusiones. Encontramos una alta prevalencia de individuos con cistatina C elevada en la población general, lo que conlleva factores de riesgo cardiovascular clásicos, como diabetes, hipertensión arterial y enfermedad renal crónica, junto con concentraciones más elevadas de proteína C reactiva, homocisteína y fibrinógeno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(4): 415-422, abr. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81100</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cistatina C y riesgo cardiovascular en población general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24594^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22179^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22124^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
