<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054811</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anesthetic management for elective cesarean section for a woman with beriberi</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Beriberi is a disease caused by thiamine (vitamin B1)    deficiency. Peripheral and central nerve involvement    causes psychosis and memory loss as well as    cardiocirculatory effects.    We report the case of a 35-year-old woman 8 weeks    pregnant who came to the emergency department after    bouts of nausea and vomiting over a period of 6 days,    with intolerance of both solids and liquids. The initial    diagnosis of gastroenteritis was later changed to    hyperemesis gravidarum. Episodes of vomiting and    nausea continued 48 hours after admission, accompanied    by vertical nystagmus, ataxia, and diminished    osteotendinous reflexes. Evaluation of the clinical picture    confirmed vitamin B1 deficiency, leading to a diagnosis    of Wernicke&#150;Korsakoff syndrome. Symptoms improved    with thiamine therapy but did not entirely disappear.    The patient was admitted for elective cesarean section    at 37 weeks&#146; gestation. Examination revealed    neurological involvement (horizontal and vertical    nystagmus) and general anesthesia was therefore chosen    to assure adequate hemodynamic control given the    possibility of cardiocirculatory alteration</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Raynard, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jamart, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borràs, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Beriberi es una patología ocasionada por el déficit    de vitamina B1 o tiamina y que causa alteraciones nerviosas    periféricas como neuropatías y centrales del tipo    psicosis y pérdida de memoria, además de alteraciones    del sistema cardiocirculatorio.    Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 35 años de edad    gestante de 8 semanas, que acudió a Urgencias por vómitos    de seis días de evolución con intolerancia a sólidos y    líquidos, diagnosticándose inicialmente de gastroenteritis    y posteriormente de hiperémesis gravídica. A las 48    horas continuaba con episodios emético-vertiginosos,    presentando nistagmo vertical, ataxia y reflejos osteotendinosos    disminuidos. Tras valoración del cuadro clínico    y confirmación analítica de déficit de vitamina B1,    fue diagnosticada de Síndrome Wernicke-Korsakoff y se    inició tratamiento con tiamina, con lo que se produjo    mejoría clínica aunque no desapareció la sintomatología    por completo.    A las 37 semanas de gestación la paciente ingresó para    cesárea electiva. A la exploración se observaba ataxia y    nistagmo horizontal-vertical, por lo que ante la afección    neurológica que presentaba se decidió realizar una anestesia    general que permitiera el adecuado manejo hemodinámico    dada la posible afectación del aparato cardiocirculatorio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;54(2): 125-127, feb. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054811</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo anestésico en cesárea electiva de una gestante con enfermedad de Beriberi</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d784</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
