<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048402</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of a virtual inmersion computer simulator as a model for basic training in laparoscopic urology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: to date, it has not been defined the best method for teaching urologic laparoscopy, however it is    well recognized that it involves a steep learning curve.    Methods: A course of Laparoscopic Urology was done in our Institute. The program included skill practices in    a virtual immersion simulator which evaluated, the score and time to complete each activity. This was done in a    group of residents with previous experience with this virtual simulator (group 1) and another group of residents    with no experience (group 2). Four different basic tasks were performed in the virtual simulator, which included:    coordination, cutting, clip application and performing a simple suture.    Results: When we compared the scores between both groups the mean scores for each task were superior in    group 1 compared to the group 2, with no statistically significant difference, however when we compared the time    to complete each task, it was shorter in group 1 compared to group 2 with a statistically significant difference.    Conclusions: The performance of residents without experience in a virtual simulator was similar to that of previously    trained residents, however it takes less time to complete each task as the resident gains experience in    these simulators. The use of virtual simulators for laparoscopy training are useful when learning basic techniques    allowing the surgeon to improve hand dexterity and coordination in laparoscopic surgery</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Covarrubias, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gabilondo Pliego, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Liévano, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gabilondo Navarro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atisha-Fregoso, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: En la actualidad aún no está definido el mejor método de enseñanza para laparoscopia aplicada    en urología, sin embargo se sabe que implica una larga curva de aprendizaje.    Métodos: Se llevó a cabo en nuestro Instituto un Curso de Laparoscopia Urológica que incluyó prácticas en un    simulador computarizado de inmersión virtual en el que se evaluó las aptitudes de residentes que utilizaron rutinariamente    el simulador como el grupo con experiencia (grupo 1) contra otro grupo sin experiencia (grupo 2). Se    utilizaron diferentes modalidades en el simulador calificando la destreza y el tiempo para completar 4 tareas:    coordinación, corte, colocación de clips y suturas endoscópicas.    Resultados: Las calificaciones promedio en las cuatro tareas fueron superiores en el grupo 1 comparado con    el grupo 2, sin embargo nunca existió una diferencia estadísticamente significativa. Por otra parte en lo que    corresponde al tiempo para realizar las prácticas fue menor en el grupo 1 comparado con el grupo 2, con diferencia    estadísticamente significativa.    Conclusiones: El desempeño de los alumnos sin experiencia en el uso de simuladores fue similar al de los    alumnos habituados a este tipo de entrenamiento, sin embargo, se observó una mayor velocidad en la realización    de las tareas conforme se aumenta el tiempo del uso de estos simuladores. El uso de simuladores permite el    aprendizaje de técnicas básicas permitiendo mejorar la destreza y coordinación para la práctica de laparoscopia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(8): 819-823, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048402</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Simulador computarizado de inmersión virtual como modelo de inicio de entrenamiento de laparoscopia urológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19244^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19244^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54404^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
