<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167658</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aetiology of renal failure in patients with infective endocarditis. The role of antibiotics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: The possible renal toxicity of certain antibiotics (AB) is well known. The objective of our work is to know the possible effect of AB treatments in the development of renal failure (RF) in patients with infective endocarditis (IE). Material and method: Collection from a national multi-centre registry of collection on renal function, both prior and its impairment, if any, during the treatment of IE and in relation to possible causative factors, including the use of AB. Results: Between 2008 and 2012, 1,853 episodes of IE reported from 26 Spanish centres were analysed. Of these, 21.6% had prior RF. They developed new RF or impairment of renal function in 38.7% of the cases. In patients with prior RF, impairment was more frequent (64 vs. 31.7%, P&lt;.001). Overall, patients with RF were older (70.6 vs. 67 years, P&lt;.01), had more comorbidities (Charlson index 5 vs. 4, P&lt;.01), and IE by Staphylococcus aureus (32.1 vs. 16.5%, P&lt;.01). Potentially nephrotoxic AB use was only associated with RF in patients without prior RF (aminoglycosides: OR=1.47 [95% CI 1.096-1.988], P=.010; aminoglycosides with vancomycin: OR=1.49 [95% CI 1.069-2.09], P=.019). Conclusions: In patients without prior RF, the use of nephrotoxic AB is associated with impairment of renal function. In patients with RF prior to the IE episode, impairment of renal function was more frequent but appears to be more related to the severity of infection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pericás Pulido, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goenaga Sánchez, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verde Moreno, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón González, Arístides de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iribarren Loyarte, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouza Santiago, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Morales, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antorrena Miranda, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sousa Regueiro, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Álvarez, Regino José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kortajarena Urkola, Xabier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fariñas Álvarez, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teira Cobo, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivos: La toxicidad renal de ciertos antibióticos (AB) es conocida. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo es conocer el posible efecto de los tratamientos AB en el desarrollo de insuficiencia renal (IR) en pacientes con endocarditis infecciosa (EI). Material y método: Recogida en un registro nacional multicéntrico de los datos referentes a la función renal, tanto previa como su deterioro si existiese, durante el tratamiento de las EI y relacionarlo con los posibles factores causantes, entre ellos los AB. Resultados: Entre 2008 y 2012 se han analizado 1.853 episodios de EI remitidos desde 26 centros españoles. De ellos, un 21,6% presentaban una alteración previa de la función renal. Desarrollaron IR de novo o un empeoramiento de la función renal previa un 38,7% de los casos. En aquellos pacientes que presentaban IR previa, el deterioro fue más frecuente (64 frente a 31,7%; p&lt;0,001). Globalmente los pacientes con IR tenían más edad (70,6 frente a 67 años; p&lt;0,01) y comorbilidades (índice de Charlson 5 frente a 4; p&lt;0,01), y la EI era por Staphylococcus aureus (32,1 frente a 16,5%; p&lt;0,01). El uso de AB potencialmente nefrotóxicos solo se asoció a IR en el grupo de pacientes sin IR previa (aminoglucósidos: OR=1,47 [IC 95% 1,096-1,988], p=0,010; aminoglucósidos-vancomicina: OR=1,49 [IC 95% 1,069-2,09], p=0,019]). Conclusiones: En pacientes sin IR previa, los AB nefrotóxicos se asocian a un deterioro de la función renal. En pacientes con IR previa al episodio de EI, el deterioro de renal fue más frecuente, pero parece estar más relacionado con la gravedad de la infección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);149(8): 331-338, oct. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167658</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiología de la insuficiencia renal en pacientes con endocarditis infecciosa. Papel de los antibióticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23504^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31999^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d626^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4778</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
