<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140387</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between work shift and the practice of physical activity among workers of a poultry processing plant in Southern Brazil</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The regular practice of physical activity (PA) has been associated with better health. In addition, job characteristics may determine the PA behaviours of employees, including the work shift. However, relatively few studies have examined the PA behaviour among shift workers. Objective: This study aimed to investigate the association between work shift and the practice of PA among workers of a poultry processing plant in Southern Brazil. Methods: A cross-sectional study was conducted with 1206 workers (786 females), ages 18 to 50, working in shifts on a production line that operates 24 hours/day. Workers who engaged in more than 150 minutes/week of PA were considered active. Multivariate analyses were conducted using Poisson regression and all analyses were stratified by gender. Results: Of the total participants studied, 36% (95%CI: 33-39) were considered active and the sociodemographic characteristics associated with PA differed among males and females. Regarding work shift, night shift workers had higher prevalence of PA. However, increased PA was significantly associated with work shift particularly among females. After controlling for potential confounders, women who worked during the night shift were approximately 30% more active than those who worked during the day (PR[prevalence ratio]=1.32;95%CI: 1.07-1.62;p=0.010). Conclusions: This study found a low prevalence of PA among the workers and indicated a significantly association between work shift and PA. Working at night was positively associated with regular PA, particularly among females. These results contribute for initiatives that aim to increase PA among the workers, take into account the job characteristics and gender differences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcez, Anderson da Silva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olinto, Maria Teresa Anselmo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macagnan, Jamile</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anselmo Olinto, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pattussi, Marcos Pascoal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paniz, Vera Maria Vieira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Henn, Ruth Liane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canuto, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La práctica regular de actividad física (AF) se ha asociado con una mejor salud. Además, las características del trabajo se pueden determinar las conductas de la AF de los trabajadores, incluyendo el turno de trabajo. Sin embargo, relativamente pocos estudios han examinado el comportamiento AF entre los trabajadores por turnos. Objetivo: Este estudio tuvo como objetivo investigar la asociación entre turno de trabajo y la práctica de la AF entre los trabajadores de una planta de procesamiento de aves en el sur de Brasil. Métodos: Un estudio transversal se llevó a cabo con 1.206 trabajadores (786 mujeres), con edades entre 18 a 50 años, trabajando en turnos de una línea de producción que funciona las 24 horas/día. Los trabajadores que han participado en más de 150 minutos/semana de AF se consideraron activos. Se realizó un análisis multivariante mediante regresión de Poisson y todos los análisis se estratificó por sexo. Resultados: De los participantes en el estudio, el 36% (IC del 95%: 33-39) se consideraron activas y las características sociodemográficas asociadas con AF difirieron entre machos y hembras. En cuanto a los turnos de trabajo, los trabajadores del turno de noche tenían mayor prevalencia de la AF. Sin embargo, el aumento de la AF se asoció significativamente con el trabajo por turnos sobre todo entre las mujeres. Después de ajustar por factores de confusión, las mujeres que trabajaban en el turno de la noche fueron aproximadamente un 30% más activos que los que han trabajado durante el día (PR[razón de prevalencia]=1,32;IC del 95%: 1,07-1,62;p=0,010). Conclusiones: Este estudio encontró una baja prevalencia de PA entre los trabajadores e indicó una asociación significativa entre el trabajo por turnos y AF. Trabajar de noche se asoció positivamente con la AF regular, especialmente entre las mujeres. Estos resultados contribuyen a las iniciativas para aumentar la AF entre los trabajadores, teniendo en cuenta las características de las diferencias laborales y de género (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(5): 2174-2181, mayo 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140387</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre turno de trabajo y la práctica de la actividad física entre los trabajadores de una planta de procesamiento de aves en el sur de Brasil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16370</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
