<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048284</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A proposal for a clinical registry of dementias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. We outline a proposal for the structural and functional features needed to develop a registry of dementiaswhich can be used to collect standardised information that is both reliable and valid concerning cases of dementia in thespecialised health care centres within a particular geographical area. Development. Due to the shortage of information aboutaspects concerning the impact of dementias on the health care system (in terms of the usage of resources and patterns ofdetection, referral, diagnosis and treatment in usual clinical practice in primary and secondary care), a sequentialimplementation of the registry is proposed so that it can be adapted to each health district or region. The first step is to identifythe cases and sources of information; second, a system for collecting data must be developed that allows information to begathered in a standardised manner while at the same time making it possible to work in close collaboration with thespecialists who diagnose dementia; and, third, it must be set up with the logistics and staff needed to centralise all thefunctions and activities of the registry. Conclusions. Epidemiological surveillance is an essential instrument for planning,managing and distributing community health resources, for following up the natural history of chronic diseases and forassessing the impact of programmes of prevention. In this respect, and from a functional point of view, the proposed registry ofdementias meets all the basic requirements of epidemiological surveillance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Barberá, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pousa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano-Fernández de Pinedo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo-Ferrer,  J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garre-Olmo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tárraga-Mestre, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monserrat-Vila, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boada-Rovira, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Se presenta una propuesta de las característicasestructurales y funcionales necesarias para desarrollar un registrode demencias que permita recoger con garantías de fiabilidady validez la información estandarizada de los casos diagnosticadosde demencia en los centros sanitarios de atención especializada deun área geográfica definida. Desarrollo. Debido a la falta de informaciónsobre los aspectos relativos al impacto de las demenciassobre el sistema sanitario, en términos de utilización de recursos yen patrones de detección, derivación, diagnóstico y tratamiento enla práctica clínica habitual por parte de atención primaria y secundaria,se propone una implementación secuencial del registro paraadaptarse a cada territorio o región sanitaria. En primer lugar, sedeberían identificar los casos y las fuentes de información; en segundolugar, desarrollar un sistema de recogida de datos que permitaadoptar de forma estandarizada la recogida de información yestablecer una estrecha colaboración con los especialistas que llevena cabo el diagnóstico de demencia; y, en tercer lugar, aportar alregistro una estructura logística y de personal que centralice todaslas funciones y actividades del registro. Conclusiones. La vigilanciaepidemiológica es un instrumento fundamental para la planificación,gestión y distribución de los recursos sociosanitarios, para elseguimiento de la evolución natural de enfermedades crónicas asícomo para evaluar el impacto de programas preventivos. En estesentido, y desde un punto de vista funcional, la propuesta de unregistro de demencias cumple todos los requisitos básicos de la vigilanciaepidemiológica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(1): 32-38, jul. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048284</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta para un registro clínico de demencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28442</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
