<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143785</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of two field methods for estimating body fat in different Spanish Dance disciplines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of the present study was to investigate percentage body fat (%BF) differences in three Spanish dance disciplines and to compare skinfold and bioelectrical impedance predictions of body fat percentage in the same sample. Seventy-six female dancers, divided into three groups, Classical (n=23), Spanish (n=29) and Flamenco (n=24), were measured using skinfold measurements at four sites: triceps, subscapular, biceps and iliac crest, and whole body multi-frequency bioelectrical impedance (BIA). The skinfold measures were used to predict body fat percentage via Durnin and Womersley&#146;s and Segal, Sun and Yannakoulia equations by BIA. Differences in percent fat mass between groups (Classical, Spanish and Flamenco) were tested by using repeated measures analysis (ANOVA). Also, Pearson&#146;s product-moment correlations were performed on the body fat percentage values obtained using both methods. In addition, Bland-Altman plots were used to assess agreement, between anthropometric and BIA methods. Repeated measures analysis of variance did not found differences in % BF between modalities (p&lt;0.05). Fat percentage correlations ranged from r= 0.57 to r=0.97 (all, p&lt;0.001). Bland-Altman analysis revealed differences between BIA Yannakoulia as a reference method with BIA Segal (-0.35 ± 2.32%, 95%CI: -0.89to 0.18, p=0.38), with BIA Sun (-0.73 ± 2.3%, 95%CI: -1.27 to -0.20, p=0.014) and Durnin-Womersley (-2.65 ± 2,48%, 95%CI: -3.22 to -2.07, p&lt;0.0001). It was concluded that body fat percentage estimates by BIA compared with skinfold method were systematically different in young adult female ballet dancers, having a tendency to produce underestimations as %BF increased with Segal and Durnin-Womersley equations compared to Yannakoulia, concluding that these methods are not interchangeable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alacid, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marfell-Jones, Mike</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santonja Medina, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artero Orta, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carnero, Elvis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correas-Gómez, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvero-Cruz, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio fue investigar el porcentaje de grasa corporal (% GC) y comparar las predicciones y las diferencias en tres disciplinas de danza española, así como las predicciones del porcentaje de grasa corporal mediante los pliegues de grasa y por impedancia bioeléctrica en la misma muestra. Setenta y seis bailarinas, divididos en tres grupos, Clásica (n = 23), Danza española (n = 29) y Flamenco (n = 24), fueron evaluados mediante mediciones de los pliegues cutáneos:  tríceps, subescapular , bíceps y la cresta ilíaca y por impedancia bioeléctrica de cuerpo entero (BIA) . Se utilizaron las medidas de pliegues cutáneos para predecir el porcentaje de grasa corporal a través de ecuaciones de Durnin y Womersley y Segal, Sun y Yannakoulia por BIA. Las diferencias en el porcentaje de grasa en masa entre los grupos Clásica, Española y Flamenco fueron evaluadas mediante un análisis de medidas repetidas (ANOVA). Además se realizaron correlaciones de Pearson entre los valores de porcentaje de grasa corporal obtenidos entre métodos. Así mismo se utilizó un análisis de Bland-Altman para evaluar la concordancia entre los métodos antropométricos y BIA. El análisis de medidas repetidas no encontró diferencias en el % de grasa corporal entre modalidades (P &lt;0,05). Las correlaciones entre los porcentaje de grasa oscilaron entre r = 0,57 y r = 0,97 (todos, P &lt; 0,001). El análisis de Bland y Altman reveló diferencias entre BIA Yannakoulia como método de referencia con BIA Segal (-0.35 ± 2.32 %, IC del 95 %: - 0.89to 0,18, P = 0,38), con BIA Sun (-0,73 ± 2,3 %, 95 % IC: -1,27 a -0,20, P = 0,014) y Durnin-Womersley (-2,65 ± 2,48 %, IC del 95 %: -3,22 a -2,07, P &lt; 0,0001). Se concluye que las estimaciones de porcentaje de grasa corporal por BIA en comparación con el método de los pliegues cutáneos fueron sistemáticamente diferentes en jóvenes bailarinas de ballet, además de existir una tendencia a la subestimación en el porcentaje de grasa corporal a medida que aumenta la magnitud de los valores de las ecuaciones de Segal y Durnin - Womersley en comparación con Yannakoulia, por lo cual no son métodos intercambiables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(3): 614-621, sept. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143785</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de dos métodos de campo para estimar la grasa corporal en diferentes disciplinas de la danza española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13266</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3634^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
