<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057401</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">MARS, albumin dialysis and other bioartificial systems</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Serum albumin is a transporter for bilirubin, aminoacids or biliary salts. Adding albumin    to a dialyser improves its capability for clearing these molecules (single pass albumin    dialysis). Two systems has been developed for reducing the cost of this technique:    the Molecular Adsorbent Recirculating System (MARS®) regenerates albumin reducing    the final amount used and the Prometheus system separates serum albumin and performs    direct adsorption on it. Results point to higher efficiency on clearance for Prometheus    but higher impact on hemodynamics for MARS.    These treatments are indicated for clearing bilirubin or biliary salts (recommendation    B) and improve hemodynamics (evidence C), hepatorenal syndrome (evidence B) and    hepatic encephalopathy (evidence B) in acute as well as acute on chronic patients, but    we can not recommend a specific technique (recommendation C). Adverse affects are    the same that in other extracorporeal techniques. Apart from clinically irrelevant lowering    of platelets the treatment is safe and well tolerated (evidence B).    Acute liver failure: It has been useful in cases of viral or toxic hepatitis, primary graph    dysfunction after liver transplant or extensive liver surgery when hyperbilirubinemia, hepatic    encephalopathy or high intracranial pressure are present. Two RCT show a possible    effect on outcome for MARS treatment (recommendation C).    Acute decompensation of chronic hepatopathy: It has been useful for liver cirrhosis,    primary biliary cirrhosis or agudization of viral or alcoholic hepatitis. The clinical effect    is more evident in the most severely ill patients (i.e. MELD &gt; 20). Two RCT show a positive    effect on survival but a third study did not show positive results. A meta-analysis of    these data did not reach statistical significance (recommendation B).    Pruritus: The effect of these treatments is intense but of limited duration. Subsequent treatments    lose efficacy. It has been used as an effective rescue therapy for refractory pruritus but    at this point a specific dosage or protocol has not jet been defined (recommendation C).    Bioartificial systems: Cell based systems (bioreactors) have been recently introduced    and a recent RCT with a low number of patients has been published but this study did    not show a clear effect on outcome even though a positive effect on acute failure has    been suggested (no recommendation). A preliminary study has been presented with the    use of a circuit based on human tubular cells but more studies are needed before this    system is introduced in the clinical practice (no recommendation)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrera Gutiérrez, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maynar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dado que la albúmina participa en el transporte de bilirrubina, aminoácidos aromáticos,    cobre o ácidos biliares, el añadir albúmina al dializador permite eliminar los compuestos adheridos a la albúmina del paciente (diálisis con albúmina de un    solo paso). Existen dos variantes de este tratamiento que aumentan su eficacia y disminuyen    su coste. Por una parte, el sistema «Molecular Adsorbent Recuirculating System    » (MARS®) realiza el reciclado de la albúmina y disminuye su consumo. Por otra,    el sistema Prometeus separa la albúmina del paciente y realiza la adsorción directamente    sobre esta. Los resultados publicados apuntan a una mayor eficacia en la eliminación    mediante el sistema Prometeus sobre el MARS pero con un posible menor    impacto sobre la hemodinámica del paciente.    Estos sistemas son útiles para eliminar bilirrubina y sales biliares (Recomendación    Grado B). Su uso produce una mejoría significativa sobre la hemodinámica (Evidencia    Grado C), el síndrome hepatorrenal (Evidencia Grado B) y la encefalopatía hepática    (Evidencia Grado B) tanto en pacientes con insuficiencia hepática aguda como    aguda sobre crónica. No se puede actualmente aconsejar un tratamiento de preferencia    sobre los demás (Recomendación Grado C).    Los efectos adversos esperables son los mismos que los descritos para las TDE y,    salvo por una trombopenia sin trascendencia clínica, el tratamiento es seguro y bien    tolerado (Evidencia Grado B). No existe suficiente evidencia para la generalización    de su uso en niños (Sin Recomendación)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;27(supl.3): 195-205, 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057401</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">MARS, diálisis con albúmina y otros sistemas bioartificiales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23606^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30667^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d421^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33137^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
