<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65436</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">FOXP2 is the first gene linked to a hereditary variant of specific language impairment and seems tocode for a transcriptional repressor that intervenes in the regulation of the development and the functioning of certain thalamic-cortical-striatal circuits. Development. In the last three years, significant progress has been made in the determination of the structural and functional properties of the gene. These advances essentially have to do with the precise analysis of the most important structural motifs of the protein that it codes for and the main parameters that determine its interaction with DNA. They also concern the determination of the functional and behavioural properties in vivo of the main isoforms of the FOXP2 protein, the exact determination of the pattern of expression of new orthologues of the gene, and the identification of the different target genes for factor FOXP2. Conclusions. This new evidence suggests that protein FOXP2 protein has a high degree of versatility in vivo when it comes to binding to DNA; that its different isoforms are biologically functional; and that the FOXP2 gene is functional during embryonic development and during the adult phase. It also suggests that it is involved in the development and/or functioning of the thalamic-cortical-striatal circuits associated to motor planning, sequential behaviour and procedural learning (a significant saving in developmental terms of the regulatory mechanism in which the gene is involved), as well as the accuracy of the models of linguistic processing that consider language to be, to a large extent, the result of an interaction between certain cortical and subcortical structures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Burraco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FOXP2 es el primer gen ligado a una variante hereditaria del trastorno específico del lenguaje y parececodificar un represor transcripcional que interviene en la regulación del desarrollo y del funcionamiento de determinados circuitos corticotalamoestriatales. Desarrollo. En los últimos tres años se han producido significativos avances en la determinación de las propiedades estructurales y funcionales del gen, que conciernen fundamentalmente al análisis preciso delos motivos estructurales más importantes de la proteína que codifica y de los parámetros más relevantes que determinan la interacción de ésta con el ADN; al esclarecimiento de las propiedades funcionales y del comportamiento in vivo de las principales isoformas de la misma; a la determinación exacta del patrón de expresión de nuevos ortólogos del gen; y a la identificación de diferentes genes diana para el factor FOXP2. Conclusiones. Estas nuevas evidencias sugieren una gran versatilidad in vivo por parte de la proteína FOXP2 a la hora de unirse al ADN; la funcionalidad biológica de sus diversas isoformas; la implicación del gen FOXP2 en el desarrollo y/o el funcionamiento de los circuitos corticotalamoestriatales asociados a la planificación motora, el comportamiento secuencial y el aprendizaje procedimental, tanto en la fase adulta como durante el desarrollo embrionario; una significativa conservación en términos evolutivos del mecanismo regulador en el que interviene el gen; y la idoneidad de los modelos de procesamiento lingüístico que consideran que el lenguaje es, en buena medida, el resultado de una interacción entre determinadas estructuras corticales y subcorticales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;46(6): 351-359, mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65436</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33840^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
