<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100904</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Design and validation of scales to measure adolescent attitude toward eating and toward physical activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Different authors suggest that attitude is amediator in behavior change, so it is a predictor of behavior practice. The main of this study was to design and to validate two scales for measure adolescent attitude toward healthy eating and adolescent attitude toward healthy physical activity. Methods: Scales were design based on a literature review. After, they were validated using an on-line Delphi Panel with eighteen experts, a pretest, and a pilot test with a sample of 188 high school students. Comprehensibility, content validity, adequacy, as well as the reliability (alpha of Cronbach test), and construct validity (exploratory factor analysis) of scales were tested. Results: Scales validated by experts were considered appropriate in the pretest. In the pilot test, the ten-item Attitude to Eating Scale obtained &amp;#945;=0.72. The eight-itemAttitude to PhysicalActivity Scale obtained &amp;#945;=0.86. They showed evidence of one-dimensional interpretation after factor analysis, a) all items got weights r&gt;0.30 in first factor before rotations, b) the first factor explained a significant proportion of variance before rotations, and c) the total variance explained by the main factors extracted was greater than 50%. Conclusions: The Scales showed their reliability and validity. They could be employed to assess attitude to these priority intervention areas in Spanish adolescents, and to evaluate this intermediate result of health interventions and health programs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáez-Bueno, África</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima-Rodríguez, Joaquín Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima-Serrano, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Diversos autores proponen la actitud como un mediador en el cambio de comportamiento, por lo que puede predecir la práctica de este. El objetivo del trabajo fue diseñar y validar dos escalas para medir la actitud de los adolescentes hacia la alimentación saludable, y la actitud hacia la actividad física. Métodos: Se realizó el diseño tras una revisión de la literatura. Se procedió a la validación mediante un panel Delphi on-line con 18 expertos/ as, un pretest, y una prueba piloto con una muestra de 188 alumnos/ as de educación secundaria. Se analizaron la comprensibilidad, la validez de contenido, la adecuación, la fiabilidad mediante la prueba alpha de Cronbach, y la validez de constructo, mediante el análisis factorial exploratorio. Resultados: Las escalas validadas por los expertos/as se consideraron adecuadas en el pretest. En la prueba piloto, la Escala deActitud hacia la Alimentación de diez ítems, obtuvo un &amp;#945;=0,72. La Escala de Actitud hacia la Actividad Física de ocho ítems, tuvo un &amp;#945;=0,86. En el análisis factorial mostraron datos a favor de su unidimensionalidad, a) todos los ítems obtuvieron pesos r&gt;0,30 en el primer factor sin rotar, b) este explicaba una proporción importante de varianza con respecto a los demás, c) la varianza total explicada por los factores principales era mayor al 50%. Conclusiones: Las escalas demostraron su validez y fiabilidad y pueden ser utilizadas para valorar la actitud hacia estas áreas de atención prioritarias en adolescentes españoles, y para evaluar este resultado intermedio de intervenciones y programas de salud(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;86(3): 253-268, may.-jun.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100904</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño y validación de dos escalas para medir la actitud hacia la alimentación y la actividad física durante la adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
