<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043621</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The vacuum chest wall lifter in the treatment of pectus excavatum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since 2002, the Eckart Klobe vacuum has been used in our    Service as an innovate and non-invasive procedure in patients with pectus    excavatum. This vacuum method contributes not only to hold promise  as a valuable adjunct in minimally invasive surgery, but also as  an effective method to lift and fix the funnel for repairing pectus excavatum  in some patients.  Our experience is limited to the use of this device in 10 patients, during  the Nuss technique. This procedure has been useful for safer passage  of the introducer, and as a definitive treatment in a 10 years old girl with    pectus excavatum and a Haller index of 5.1 with successful result after    one year of treatment. The aim of this study is to report the safety and efficacy of this procedure  in appropriate patients. Long-term results will be necessary to confirm  this method as an alternative to more invasive techniques (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chueca, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bento, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde hace 3 años, se ha comenzado a emplear la ventosa  de Eckart Klobe como un procedimiento novedoso, no invasivo, en  el tratamiento del pectus excavatum. La aportación ha sido, no sólo  como ayuda en el momento de la cirugía mínimamente invasiva, sino como tratamiento definitivo para el levantamiento y fijación del embudo    en algunos pacientes. Nuestra experiencia se limita al empleo del sistema en 10 pacientes en  el momento de la realización de la técnica de Nuss, donde se demostró   como una gran ayuda para minimizar el riesgo del paso de la férula,  y un tratamiento definitivo en una niña de 10 años afecta de un pectus  Excavatum con índice de Haller de 5,1 en donde se ha conseguido la corrección de la deformidad, con un aceptable resultado, después  de un año de tratamiento.  Pretendemos en este trabajo, dar a conocer la eficacia y benevolencia del sistema en pacientes seleccionados adecuadamente. Harán falta más  pacientes y años para confirmar el método como una alternativa a la  cirugía, algo que pensamos merece la pena intentar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;19(1): 46-48, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043621</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Empleo de la campana de succión en el tratamiento del pectus excavatum</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5796^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
