<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-29435</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical and neuroimaging findings in a family with cadasil associated to c475t mutation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The term CADASIL (cerebral autosomal dominant arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy) refers to an autosomal dominant hereditary arteriopathy of the brain that is characterised by headache, recurring strokes and progressive cognitive deterioration. We report the case of another family with CADASIL and emphasise the importance of a genetic study in its diagnosis. Case report. A 62-year-old female patient with repeating lacunar strokes, subcortical dementia and a family history of dementia and strokes. Neuroimaging studies conducted on the patient and her siblings showed signs of leukoencephalopathy and lacunar infarctions. The ultrastructural study of the biopsy performed on a sample of the patient&#146;s skin, which included five dermal vessels, did not show any electron-dense deposits. The genetic study revealed the presence of mutation C475T in exon 4 of NOTCH3. Conclusions. The possible presence of CADASIL must be suspected in patients with symptoms of cerebrovascular disease or dementia who present characteristic alterations in the magnetic resonance brain scan, especially when there is a compatible family history. The first choice diagnostic procedure must be a genetic study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El término CADASIL (cerebral autosomal dominant arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy) se refiere a una arteriopatía cerebral hereditaria autosómica dominante que se caracteriza por migraña, ictus recurrentes y deterioro cognitivo progresivo. Presentamos una nueva familia con CADASIL y destacamos la importancia del estudio genético en su diagnóstico. Caso clínico. Mujer de 62 años con ictus lacunares de repetición, demencia subcortical y antecedentes familiares de demencia e ictus. Los estudios de neuroimagen que se realizaron a la paciente y los hermanos mostraron signos de leucoencefalopatía e infartos lacunares. El estudio ultraestructural de la biopsia de la piel de la paciente, que incluyó cinco vasos dérmicos, no mostró depósitos electrodensos. El estudio genético demostró la presencia de la mutación C475T en el exón 4 del NOTCH3. Conclusiones. Debemos sospechar la posibilidad del CADASIL en pacientes con clínica de enfermedad cerebrascular o demencia que presenten alteraciones características en la resonancia magnética cerebral, especialmente cuando exista una historia familiar compatible. El procedimiento diagnóstico de elección debe ser el estudio genético (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(1): 37-41, ene. 2004. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hallazgos clínicos y de neuroimagen en una familia con CADASIL asociada a la mutación C475T</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Mola, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Tur, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Barragán, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medrano, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sempere, AP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-29435</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27832</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29309</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23597</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31906</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1267</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6470</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
