<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132813</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological habits associated with appetite: a preliminary approach to their comprehension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Appetite and impulse control deficit in obese population are the outcomes of a multidisciplinary perspective on obesity, completing the actual model and supplying scientific basis for a new explicative one. Methods: This research displays a preliminary study which evaluates ten psychological variables in both obese and non-obese samples. Results: The resultant data describes a psychological problems as the cause of excess weight called edorexia syndrome, which is characterized by four main components: emotional dimension, psychological welfare deficit, food dependency and obesity avoidance; and aims to increase the relevance of psychological aspects and the environment. In addition, an interactive model between these factors is proposed together with a comprehensive integrated model for obesity from a multidisciplinary perspective. Conclusions: In summary, the main cause of the elevated incidence rates of obesity is addressed, based on evidences from different disciplines, contributing to a multidisciplinary vision and developing a theoretical and empirical framework towards a better understanding of obese individuals&#146; behavior, and also of the population with pathological problems regarding to appetite control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcés De Los Fayos Ruiz, Enrique Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Morales, Jose Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El apetito y el déficit de control de impulsos en la población obesa es el resultado de la perspectiva multidisciplinar de la obesidad, completand o el modelo actual y proporcionando las bases científicas a un nuevo modelo explicativo más completo. Método: En este trabajo se presenta un estudio preliminar evaluando diez variables psicológicas a una muestra compuesta con población obesa y no obesa. Resultados: Los datos obtenidos describen un problema psicológico causante del exceso de peso denominado síndrome de edorexia y caracterizado por cuatro factores principales, la dimensión emocional, el déficit del bienestar psicológico, la dependencia a los alimentos y la evitación de la obesidad; incrementando la importancia de los aspectos psicológicos y el ambiente. Además, se plantea un modelo de interacción entre dichos factores y con el modelo integral comprensivo de la obesidad desde la perspectiva multidisciplinar.Conclusiones: En resumen, se describe brevemente la principal causa de las elevadas tasas de incidencia de obesidad, apoyándose en evidencias de diferentes disciplinas, aportando una visión multidisciplinar y desarrollando un marco teórico y empírico para una mejor compresión del comportamiento de la población obesa y también en la población con problemas en el control del apetito patológico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;19(3): 144-151, sept. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132813</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábitos psicológicos asociados al apetito: un acercamiento preliminar a su comprensiónn</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5014^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1072^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51232^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7352^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7352^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
