<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110762</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orthostatic hypotension in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Orthostatic hypotension (OH) is defined as a decrease in systolic blood pressure of 20 mmHg, or a decrease in diastolic blood pressure of 10 mmHg within three minutes of standing. It results from an inadequate response to postural changes in blood pressure. Common symptoms include dizziness, light-headedness, blurred vision, weakness, fatigue, nausea, palpitations, sweating, head and neck ache, slow cognitive performance and transient loss of conscientiousness.  OH is a common problem among elderly patients and its aetiology is diverse, including autonomic nervous system dysfunction, cardiac problems, medication side effects, ageing changes or transitory deregulation of blood volume. The instrumental diagnosis can be easily accomplished by the tilt-table test, with continuous monitoring of blood pressure and  ardiac parameters. It is a non-invasive technique and needs minimal collaboration from the patient. In our experience, when reviewing 327 patients, aged over 40 years and examined because of clinical suspicion of OH, the prevalence  thereof was 51% whereas if focused in subjects older than 70, OH was proven in 90% of the cases. The older the patients, the more frequently they presented general deterioration, neurological or cardiac problems as well as pharmacological side effects. Ruling out neurological or cardiac malfunction can drastically improve the prognosis with possible reversibility of symptoms. Some nonpharmacological and pharmacological approaches to improve management of OH and life quality are described for guidance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Gila, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rízea, Cristian</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se define hipotensión ortostática (HO) como el descenso de la tensión arterial al menos en 20 mmHg la sistólica y 10 mmHg la diastólica durante los tres primeros minutos de ortostatismo, y está causada por una respuesta inadecuada de la tensión arterial en el paso a la bipedestación. Los síntomas que la acompañan son: mareo, visión borrosa, debilidad, fatiga, náuseas, palpitaciones, sudoración, dolor de cabeza y cuello, lentificación de pensamiento y pérdida de  conciencia. La HO es frecuente en los mayores y su etiología puede variar entre patologías del sistema nervioso autónomo, problemas cardíacos, efectos secundarios indeseados de fármacos, deterioro fisiológico o modificaciones transitorias del volumen hemático. El diagnóstico instrumental es sencillo, mediante la utilización de la mesa basculante con monitorización cardiovascular continua. Es una técnica no invasiva y precisa mínima colaboración por parte del paciente. En  nuestra experiencia, cuando hemos revisado a 327 pacientes mayores de 40 años con sospecha clínica de HO, la prevalencia global fue del 51%, mientras que si consideramos sólo a los mayores de 70 años, la HO se demostró en el 90% de los casos. A medida que aumenta la edad, es más frecuente el deterioro, la patología neurológica o cardíaca, así como los efectos secundarios de los fármacos. Descartar patología neurológica o cardíaca puede mejorar drásticamente el pronóstico, así como hacer posible la reversibilidad de los síntomas. Se incluyen algunas medidas no farmacológicas y farmacológicas que pueden aminorar la HO y mejorar la calidad de vida del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;56(6): 337-343, mar. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipotensión ortostática en ancianos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7204^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1350^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13955^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
