<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79477</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urodynamic evaluation in prostate cancer patients with urinary incontinence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: Update on the urodynamic evaluation in patients with prostate cancer who have incontinence.METHODS: To review the urodynamic studies in prostate cancer patients who suffer from incontinence, irrespective of the treatment carried out.RESULTS: The largest amount of information on urodynamic studies in patients with prostate cancer and incontinence was found in those with post-prostatectomy incontinence. There is much more limited work on irradiated patients, and after medical treatment.CONCLUSION: The urodynamic study in these patients may help clarify the etiopathogenic mechanisms of incontinence, try to predict risk factors before treatment and help the therapeutic decision making. Further studies are needed, especially in patients undergoing radiotherapy, to further assess the mechanisms involved in lower urinary tract abnormalities that occur in these patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chiarelli, Leandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silmi Moyano, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Rubio, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Casado, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Virseda Chamorro, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Puesta al día sobre la valoración urodinámica en los pacientes con cáncer de próstata que presentan incontinencia.MÉTODOS: Revisión de los estudios urodinámicos en pacientes con cáncer de próstata que padecen incontinencia, sea cual sea el tratamiento efectuado.RESULTADOS: La información más numerosa sobre estudios urodinámicos en los pacientes con cáncer de próstata e incontinencia se refiere a la incontinencia post-prostatectomía. Son mucho más escasos los trabajos referidos a pacientes radiados y postratamiento farmacológico.CONCLUSIÓN: El estudio urodinámico en estos pacientes puede ayudar a aclarar los mecanismos etiopatogénicos de la incontinencia, a tratar de predecir factores de riesgo pre tratamiento y ayudar a la toma de decisión terapeútica. Son necesarios más estudios, sobre todo en pacientes sometidos a radioterapia, para evaluar con mayor profundidad los mecanismos implicados en las alteraciones del tracto urinario inferior que se producen en estos pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;62(10): 793-808, dic. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79477</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración urodinámica en el cáncer de próstata con incontinencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14955^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
