<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84312</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Burnout, hardy personality, and psychological distress in nursing personnel</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this research was to analyze the relevance of individual variables in the development of burnout, as well as the possible effects of &#132;hardiness&#148; or &#132;hardy personality&#148; as a protective factor against burnout and its consequences on workers&#148; health. The sample was com-posed of 97 nursing professionals belonging to the intensive care and emergency units in a hospital. Four assessment instruments were applied to the participants: an ad hoc questionnaire of sociodemographic and work variables, a Spanish version of the General Health Questionnaire (GHQ-28), a Spanish adaptation of the Maslach Burnout Inventory (MBI), and the Hardy Personality Scale (CPR) of the Nursing Burnout Questionnaire (CDPE). The results confirmed the relationship between hardy personality and burnout, as well as the health consequences of the latter. Finally, the clinical implications of the results are discussed, as well as some recommendations for future research in this field (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ríos Rísquez, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Meca, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy Fernández, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta investigación pretendía analizar la relevancia de las variables de tipo individual en el desarrollo del síndrome de quemarse por el trabajo, así como el potencial efecto de la &#147;dureza&#148; o &#147;personalidad resistente&#148; como factor de protección de dicho proceso y sus consecuencias sobre la salud de los trabajadores. La muestra estaba constituida por 97 profesionales de enfermería pertenecientes a las unidades de Intensivos y de Urgencias de un Hospital de tercer nivel. Se les aplicaron cuatro instrumentos: un cuestionario elaborado ad hoc de variables sociodemográficas y laborales, una versión española del Cuestionario de Salud General (GHQ-28), una adaptación española del Inventario de Burnout de Maslach (MBI) y la Escala de Personalidad Resistente (CPR) del Cuestionario de Desgaste Profesional del Personal de Enfermería (CDPE). Los resultados apoyan la relación entre la personalidad resistente, el síndrome de burnout y sus consecuencias sobre la salud. Finalmente, se discuten las implicaciones clínicas de los resultados, así como algunas recomendaciones para la investigación futura en este campo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(1): 71-79, ene.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84312</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de quemarse por el trabajo, personalidad resistente y malestar psicológico en personal de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31198</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
