<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140678</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Whipple&#146;s disease restricted to intestine. Case report and review of literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Whipple &amp;#769;s disease (WD) is a rare systemic disease with a tendency to involve the gastrointestinal tract, and is due to the infection by a bacteria named Tropheryma whippelii, recently cultured. Histological study is the standard method for diagnosis of WD, the characteristic feature is the presence of macrophages with intracellular inclusions, that react with the periodic acid-Schiff stain, in the lamina propria of the small intestine. We report a case of a 44 year-old female who displayed an intense diarrhea without systemic manifestations, making difficult the diagnosis, that was definitively achieved by the histopathological study of multiple endoscopic samples. A review of the recent epidemiologic and pathogenic theories is made (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yus, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azúa-Romeo, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfaro, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Whipple (EW) es una rara enfermedad sistémica que afecta preferente- mente al tracto gastrointestinal, causada por la infección de una bacteria, la Tropheryma whippelii, que ha podido ser cultivada recientemente. El estudio histológico es el método estandar para el diagnóstico de EW, siendo la característica principal la presencia de macrófagos con inclusiones intracelulares, PAS positivo, en la lámina propia del intestino delgado. Describimos el caso de una mujer de 44 años que presentaba un cuadro diarreico severo sin manifestaciones extraintestinales, lo que dificultó el diagnóstico que se alcanzó definitivamente tras el estudio histopatológico de biopsias endoscópicas múltiples. Asimismo, se revisan las últimas teorías epidemiológicas y patogénicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;35(1): 107-111, ene.-mar. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140678</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Whipple de manifestación exclusivamente intestinal. Presentación de un caso y actualización bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52553^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7584^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8236^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8436^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
