<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91139</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Responsibility versus informed consent nurse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years we have witnessed a quick development in concern and research about informed consent in the biomedical field. This development has taken place mainly due to the increased importance given within the medical field to the patient's autonomy, as well as law ratified legally recognized and regulated in our country in law 41/2002 of patient autonomy. However, in the field of nursing is not even clear what the role of professional nursing with regard to informed consent, or what its responsibilities in this regard. Therefore, the objective of this study is to clarify what is the responsibility of nursing in relation to the CI. In addition, we discuss the relevance or otherwise of the implementation of informed consent documents for nursing care, addressing both its advantages and disadvantages(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado Rodríguez, Janet</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años hemos asistido a un desarrollo vertiginoso de la preocupación y la investigación acerca del consentimiento informado dentro del ámbito biomédico. Éste ha tenido lugar, fundamentalmente, como consecuencia de la mayor importancia dentro del mundo sanitario de la autonomía del paciente, ratificado -además- como derecho legalmente reconocido y regulado en nuestro país en la Ley 41/2002 de autonomía del paciente. Sin embargo, en el ámbito de enfermería no queda aún claro cuál es el rol que desempeña dicho profesional con respecto al consentimiento informado, ni cuáles son sus responsabilidades al respecto. Por ello, el objetivo de este trabajo es clarificar cuál es la responsabilidad de enfermería en relación al consentimiento informado. Además, se pretende discutir sobre la pertinencia o no de la implementación de documentos de consentimiento informado de cuidados para enfermería, abordando tanto sus ventajas como sus inconvenientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;34(10): 656-661, oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Responsabilidad enfermera frente al consentimiento informado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13308^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
