<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82999</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidermoid cysts of the floor of the mouth: presentation of two cases and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Epidermoid cysts are a frequent pathology; nevertheless their location in the oral cavity is exceptional. Their size and anatomical location are determining factors in the surgical approach.. We present two cases diagnosed in our ENT Department between 1999 and 2007, which were referred to us due to slow growing masses on the floor of the mouth. A literature review was made on the diagnosis, surgical techniques and management of epidermoid cysts in an attempt to standardise their management(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamboa, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los quistes epidermoides son una patología frecuente, pero su localización en la cavidad oral es excepcional. Para el abordaje quirúrgico son factores determinantes su tamaño y las relaciones anatómicas. Presentamos dos casos clínicos diagnosticados en el servicio de ORL entre 1999 y 2007, que consultaron por tumoración de crecimiento progresivo en el suelo de boca. Se realiza una revisión acerca del diagnóstico y de los abordajes quirúrgicos de los quistes epidermoides para intentar estandarizar su tratamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;32(3): 115-118, jul.-sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82999</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quistes epidermoides del suelo de boca: presentación de dos casos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9254^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9254^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9247^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9247^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
