<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101962</identifier>
<setSpec>0558-6291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Splicing Mutations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Splicing or maturation of pre-mRNA is a mechanism that is becoming more relevant not only for its potential expansion of the proteome, but also for its involvement in the physiopathology of human diseases. Splicing mutations after the processing of mRNA by affecting pre-mRNA sequences (mutations in cis) or proteins involved in splicing (mutations in trans). The sequences that can be altered are: the limiting areas between exons and interns, the branch site, the polypirimidine tract and, finally, other regulatory elements that enhance or suppress the selection of an exon. The whole understanding of the effect of mutations on the splicing processes will help to design molecular therapy targets to correct these defects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, María Arnedo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pusiac Uriol, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribate Molina, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pié Juste, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pié Juste, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teresa Rodrigo, María Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Fuentes, Feliciano J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ridruejo Sáez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Rodríguez, María Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El splicing o maduración del pre-mRNA es un mecanismo que está adquiriendo gran relevancia no sólo por las posibilidades que ofrece de expansión del proteoma, sino también por su implicación en la patofisiología de las enfermedades humanas. Las mutaciones de splicing alteran el procesamiento del mRNA al afectar a las secuencias del pre-mRNA (mutaciones en cis) o a las proteínas que intervienen en el splicing (mutaciones en trans). Las secuencias que pueden verse alteradas son: las limitantes de exones e intrones, la zona de ramificación, la zona rica en pirimidinas y también otros elementos reguladores que incrementan o suprimen la selección de un exón. La comprensión en profundidad del efecto de las mutaciones sobre el splicing puede abrir la puerta a su tratamiento mediante terapia moléculas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. Fac. Med. Zaragoza;50(1): 16-21, mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101962</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mutaciones de Splicing</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6702^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27820^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53723^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
