<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113692</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of hospitalizations due to bacteraemia related to the haemodialysis catheter</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of central venous catheters for haemodialysis has increased to such an extent that in our country 30% of patients now have this vascular access. However their duration is limited and they frequently present complications, such as bacteraemia related to the haemodialysis catheter. This is a complication with high morbimortality in patients undergoing chronic renal replacement therapy. The aim of this analysis was to determine the incidence of hospitalizations, identify the germs most frequently found in our population and analyse the associated demographic and clinical factors. A prospective observational study was carried out in which all hospital admissions during 2011 for bacteraemia related to the haemodialysis catheter were analysed. Clinical, demographic and comborbility data of the patients were compiled. The total number of admissions for catheter-related bacteraemia was 45 in 35 patients, with a mean age of 69.9 years. The most frequently isolated germs were gram-positive cocci (Methicillin-Resistant Staphylococcus Aureus and Methicillin-Sensitive Staphylococcus Aureus). Mortality was 14% (5 patients). In light of our results, we may conclude that catheter- related bacteraemia is a serious complication in haemodialysis patients. It represents almost 50% of hospital admissions in 2011 of haemodialysis patients. It is associated to high morbility and consumption of resources(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez López, Victoria Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Ordóñez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Montero, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Andreu, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Salinas, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz García, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso de catéteres venosos centrales para hemodiálisis se ha incrementado de tal forma, que actualmente en nuestro país, el 30%, de los pacientes son portadores de este acceso vascular. No obstante su duración es limitada y presentan con frecuencia complicaciones, como por ejemplo bacteriemias relacionadas con el catéter de hemodiálisis. Esta, es una complicación con elevada morbimortalidad en los pacientes en tratamiento renal sustitutivo crónico. El objetivo de este análisis fue conocer la incidencia de hospitalizaciones, identificar los gérmenes más frecuentemente relacionados en nuestra población y analizar los factores demográficos y clínicos asociados. Se realizó un estudio observacional prospectivo en el que se analizaron todos los ingresos por bacteriemia relacionada con el catéter de hemodiálisis durante el año 2011. Se recogieron los datos clínicos de los pacientes, demográficos y comorbilidad. El número total de ingresos por bacteriemias relacionadas con el catéter fue de 45 en 35 pacientes, con una edad media de 69.9 años. Los gérmenes más frecuentemente aislados fueron cocos gram positivos (Staphilococcus aureus mecitilin resistente y Staphilococcus aureus meticilin sensible). La mortalidad fue de 14% (5 pacientes). A la vista de nuestros resultados, podemos concluir que la bacteriemia relacionada con el catéter es una complicación grave en los pacientes en hemodiálisis. Representa casi el 50% de los ingresos durante 2011 de los pacientes en hemodiálisis. Está asociada con una elevada morbilidad y consumo de recursos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;16(2): 88-92, abr.-jun.2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113692</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las hospitalizaciones por bacteriemia relacionada con el catéter de hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
