<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83164</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">COPD and alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alpha-1-antitrypsin deficiency (AATD) is the main genetic factor related to the development of emphysema.This protein has numerous variants, some of which are clinically relevant because their anomalousconformation implies that they fail to reach the target organs as they are polymerized in the hepatocyte. Themain abnormal variant is PiZ. In a small percentage of individuals, the accumulation of Z polymers in the liverleads to the development of liver disease. The lack of AATD in the lung favors the development of emphysema,since the proteolytic effect of elastases &#150; the main biological function of AATD &#150; is not counteracted. In Spain,approximately 400 persons are diagnosed with severe AATD deficiency, representing less than 10 % of thoseexpected by epidemiological studies. The principal prognostic factor in these patients is forced expiratoryvolume in one second (FEV1), which is affected mainly by exposure to tobacco smoke. Thus, life expectancy innonsmokers is similar to that in the general population while lung function decreases faster in smokers thanin other patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). The treatment of the lung disease is thesame, although exogenous AATD augmentation is indicated when lung function deteriorates(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lara, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El déficit de alfa-1-antitripsina (DAAT) es el primer factor genético relacionado con el desarrollo de enfisema.Esta proteína tiene numerosa variantes, algunas de las cuales tienen relevancia clínica porque su conformaciónanómala implica que no alcanzan los órganos diana por polimerizar en el hepatocito. La principal variantedeficitaria es la PiZ. La acumulación de polímeros Z en el hígado condiciona la aparición de hepatopatía enun pequeño porcentaje de individuos. La falta de AAT en el pulmón favorece el desarrollo de enfisema al nocontrarrestarse el efecto proteolítico de las elastasas, que es la principal función biológica de la AAT. En España,el número de casos diagnosticados de déficit grave de AAT es de aproximadamente 400 individuos, lo querepresenta menos del 10 % de los esperados por los estudios epidemiológicos. El principal factor pronóstico enestos pacientes es el volumen espiratorio máximo en el primer segundo, condicionado principalmente por laexposición al tabaco, de manera que los individuos no fumadores tienen una esperanza de vida similar a lapoblación general, mientras que los fumadores tienen una caída de la función pulmonar más acelerada que elresto de afectados por la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC). El tratamiento de la enfermedadpulmonar es el mismo, aunque está indicado el tratamiento sustitutivo con AAT exógena cuando la funciónpulmonar se deteriora(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;46(supl.4): 2-8, sept. 2010. tab, mapa, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83164</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">EPOC y déficit de alfa-1-antitripsina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12093^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27940^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33363^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
