<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80577</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience with a simplified format of decision making tool adjuvant Online in breast cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Adjuvant. Online estimates 10-year recurrence and mortality outcomes for breast cancer patients and predicts the effect of each type of treatment. Our purpose was to test the applicability by only analysing mortality estimations. Method. We present estimations of 66 women with definitive surgery and axillary staging for unilateral, unicentric, invasive adenocarcinoma, without metastatic or residual disease. Age, co-morbidity, estrogen receptor status, histological grade, tumor size, number of positive nodes, and hormone therapy or chemotherapy option, were the variables required. Results. Median of survival estimations was 77%, cancer mortality 18% and mortality for other reasons 5%. The average of absolute risk reduction (ARR) with hormone therapy was 4%, with chemotherapy 4.5% and with combined treatment 7%. Results. All the patients with some benefit decided to receive hormone therapy. Forty-three patients (65%) decided to receive chemotherapy and 23 (35%) did not. The average risk reduction with chemotherapy was 2% in those who decided not to receive chemotherapy and 8% in those who decided to receive it. There was an association between a chemotherapy decision and the estimation of the risk of breast cancer mortality (P=0.0001), risk of mortality for other reasons (P=0.038), and the ARR (P=0.0001). There were 6% of the patients with an ARR of 1%, 50% between 2&#150;5% and 61.8% between 6&#150;10%, who chose chemotherapy. Conclusions. All women opted for hormone therapy regardless of benefit. The reasons for choosing chemotherapy were the prognosis itself and the magnitude of benefit. Some patients decided to choose chemotherapy even when the benefit was minimal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Daffós, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Díaz, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriola Arellano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Reina, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda Ramos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Contreras Ibáñez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Calvo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estalella Mendoza, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baena Cañada, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Gómez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Adjuvant. Online calcula el riesgo de recidiva y muerte a 10 años y proporciona estimaciones del beneficio del tratamiento adyuvante en pacientes con cáncer de mama. Testamos su aplicabilidad y analizamos únicamente estimaciones de mortalidad. Método. Presentamos las estimaciones de 66 pacientes intervenidas de cáncer de mama unilateral y unicéntrico, sin enfermedad residual ni metástasis. Las variables analizadas fueron edad, comorbilidad, receptores de estrógenos, grado histológico, tamaño tumoral, ganglios metastásicos, tipo de tratamiento hormonal y de quimioterapia. Resultados. La estimación de la mediana de supervivencia fue del 77%, de mortalidad por cáncer fue del 18% y por otras causas fue del 5%. La media de reducción absoluta del riesgo (RAR) de mortalidad con tratamiento hormonal fue del 4%, con quimioterapia fue del 4,5% y con tratamiento combinado fue del 7%. Resultados. Todas las pacientes con algún beneficio decidieron recibir tratamiento hormonal. Cuarenta y tres pacientes (65%) decidieron recibir quimioterapia y 23 pacientes (35%) decidieron no recibirla. La media de reducción del riesgo con quimioterapia fue del 2% en quien decidió no recibir quimioterapia y fue del 8% en quien decidió recibirla. Existe asociación entre la decisión de quimioterapia y la estimación del riesgo de mortalidad por cáncer (p=0,0001), del riesgo de mortalidad por otras causas (p=0,038) y de la RAR (p=0,0001). El 6% de las pacientes con RAR del 1%, el 50% de las que tenían RAR entre el 2&#150;5%, y el 61,8% con RAR entre el 6&#150;10% eligieron la quimioterapia. Conclusiones. Todas las mujeres optan por el tratamiento hormonal independientemente del beneficio. Las razones para elegir la quimioterapia fueron el propio pronóstico vital y la magnitud del beneficio. Algunas pacientes deciden elegir quimioterapia con beneficios mínimos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(4): 228-231, jul.-ago. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia con un formato simplificado de la herramienta de ayuda en la toma de decisiones Adjuvant Online en pacientes con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29199</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11482</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
