<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139918</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The chair of births: a resource companion of verticality in childbirth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In primitive cultures, women chose to give birth in upright positions such as squatting or sitting, because these positions stimulate a physiological birth. In this way, in order to make easier the delivery support tools such as birthing chair (BC) are discovered. Later, with the medicalization of childbirth, the lithotomy position was introduced as standard practice, with the aim of promoting comfort to the birth attendant. Currently, this position is still prevalent in the hospital environment. The World Health Organization recommendations, stresses the importance of providing impartial information on birthing positions to women, so that she will decide how to give birth without professional influence as a limiting factor in maternal posture. The aim of this review is to make known the utility of the BC, the advantages and disadvantages associated with it, to make it an available resource in vertical childbirth. The BC is a low rise seat horseshoe shaped stable and sturdy structure, and sitting in the chair women acquire squatting position, considered the most natural. The BC is considered a useful tool for childbirth upright. Giving birth using the BC seems to be protective against episiotomies and Kristeller maneuver, provides comfort and empowerment of women and helps them to have a more positive birth experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Pan, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Onandia Garate, Maialen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luces Lago, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tizón Bouza, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde antiguo, en las culturas primitivas las mujeres elegían parir en posiciones verticales, como en cuclillas o sentadas, ya que favorecían la consecución de un parto y un nacimiento fisiológicos. Para facilitar la adquisición de estas posturas surgen instrumentos de apoyo como la silla de partos (SDP). Posteriormente, con la medicalización del parto, se introduce la posición de litotomía como una práctica habitual, con el único objetivo de favorecer la comodidad del asistente al parto. En la actualidad, esta posición sigue imperando en el entorno hospitalario. La Organización Mundial de la Salud subraya la importancia de ofrecer información imparcial sobre las posturas de parto a la mujer, para que sea ella misma la que decida cómo quiere dar a luz, sin que los profesionales actúen como factor limitante de la postura materna. El objetivo de esta revisión es dar a conocer la utilidad de la SDP, así como las ventajas e inconvenientes que se le asocian, para poder hacer de ella un recurso facilitador del parto en la posición vertical. La SDP es un asiento de poca altura con forma de herradura, de estructura estable y resistente. Cuando se sientan en ella, las mujeres adquieren la posición de cuclillas, considerada la más natural. La SDP se perfila como un instrumento útil para el parto en posición vertical. Dar a luz utilizando la SDP parece tener un efecto protector contra las episiotomías y la maniobra de Kristeller, proporciona una mayor comodidad y autonomía a la mujer, y contribuye a que tenga una experiencia de nacimiento más positiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(6): 426-432, jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139918</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La silla de partos. Un recurso acompañante de la verticalidad en el parto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53693^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9514^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
