<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93936</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cluster analysis of the physical activity and sedentary behaviour of spanish adolescents with respect to their biopsychosocial health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study is part of the 2006 edition of the Health Behaviour in School-Aged Children (HBSC) study. The data presented was drawn from a sample of 21,811 Spanish adolescents ranging from 11 to 18 years of age. Through a cluster analysis, General Lineal Model, significance and effect size tests, we obtained relevant information about the physical activity habits and sedentary behaviours of Spanish adolescents. It is evident that there is a risk situation in older adolescents, especially girls. These results have the advantage of relating to a global health score; clear indicators of the advantages of an active lifestyle for adolescents were obtained. Furthermore, these data provide information that is relevant to the displacement hypothesis, which is widely discussed in the scientific literature. In short, this paper provides interesting keys for theoretical debate and practical action in the field of physical activity during adolescence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Iglesias, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta investigación forma parte de la edición 2006 el estudio Health Behavior in School-aged Children (HBSC). Los datos que se presentan constituyen una muestra de 21811 adolescentes españoles de 11 a 18 años. Realizando análisis de clúster, Modelo Lineal General, pruebas de significación y tamaños de efecto, se obtiene información relevante acerca de los hábitos de actividad física y sedentarismo de los adolescentes españoles, evidenciando la situación de riesgo de los adolescentes mayores, especialmente en el caso de las chicas. Estos resultados tienen la fortaleza de relacionarse con una puntuación global de salud, obteniéndose indicadores claros de las ventajas que supone para los adolescentes un estilo de vida activo. Además, estos datos aportan información de interés en relación con la hipótesis de desplazamiento, muy discutid a en la literatura científica. En definitiva, este trabajo aporta claves interesantes para el debate teórico y para la intervención práctica en el campo de la actividad física durante la adolescencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;21(1): 99-106, ene.-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93936</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de clúster de la actividad física y las conductas sedentarias de los adolescentes españoles, correlación con la salud biopsicosocial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
