<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115544</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update of primary breast lymphomas: a case series and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Primary breast lymphomas (PBL) are a rare malignant disease of the breast that can be mistaken for breast carcinoma. Knowledge of PBL allows a correct diagnostic-therapeutic approach to this uncommon malignancy (0.04- 0.5% of breast cancers). Material and methods: This update is based on an analytic retrospective study of a series of cases recorded at the Hospital Prý´ncipe de Asturias and a comprehensive review of the oncologic and gynecologic literature available. Discussion: PBL are virtually indistinguishable from breast carcinomas because of their similar age distribution, clinical presentation and imaging features. Diagnosis can only be confirmed by histology. The most effective treatment is combined therapy based on chemotherapy (the most widely used being the CHOP-R regimen). Surgery and radiotherapy play a secondary role. The course of PBL varies widely, from early dissemination to complete remission. Prognostic factors play an important role in PBL. Prompt diagnosis is essential to improve outcome. Conclusion: Because of their low prevalence, PBL are a diagnostic-therapeutic challenge. There is no agreement on treatment regimens, and outcome is highly variable. New in-depth studies are required to unify criteria and knowledge of this entity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guzmán Muñoz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos González, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle Rubido, Cristina del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Cuetos, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras Sedano, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Suárez, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapico Goñi, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los linfomas primarios de mama (LPM) son un rarísimo proceso patológico maligno de la mama que se puede confundir fácilmente con un carcinoma de mama. El conocimiento de esta entidad nos permitirá un abordaje diagnóstico-terapéutico correcto de los pocos casos que encontramos (0,04-0,5% de cánceres de mama). Material y métodos. Esta actualización se basa en un estudio analítico retrospectivo sobre la serie de casos recogida en el Hospital Príncipe de Asturias y una exhaustiva revisión de la literatura ginecológica y oncológica. Discusión. Los LPM son una entidad cuyo diagnóstico es prácticamente indistinguible del carcinoma de mama, por su similar distribución por edad, clínica e imagen radiológica. Solo la histología permite diferenciarlos. El tratamiento más eficaz es el combinado, basándose en la quimioterapia (siendo el régimen CHOP-R el más utilizado). La cirugía y radioterapia tienen un papel secundario. La evolución de la enfermedad es muy variable, desde la diseminación precoz a la remisión completa, teniendo gran importancia los factores pronósticos de los linfomas. Un diagnóstico precoz es fundamental para mejorar el pronóstico de esta enfermedad. Conclusión. Los LPM suponen un reto diagnóstico-terapéutico por su baja prevalencia. Las pautas de tratamiento no están consensuadas y su evolución es muy variable. Es necesario un estudio más profundo para lograr unificar criterios y conocimientos sobre esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(8): 436-441, oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115544</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en linfomas primarios de mama: serie de casos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19237^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
