<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162669</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The discontent of the adolescent student, of their teachers and parents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The article aims to shed light on the links between problematic teenagers, the school and the family. Beginning with an analysis of the emotional experiences of each of these groups, their behaviours, thoughts and discontent are analysed. Functional communication between teachers and students, as well as between the school and the home, is a factor that all the parties involved can benefit from. In this regard, the authors highlight the importance of the psycho-pedagogical training of teachers to help to deal with the difficulties they may encounter in the relationship with students, especially with the most problematic ones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catta, Tiziana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Scappaticci, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo pretende arrojar luz sobre los vínculos que se establecen entre el adolescente problemático, la escuela y la familia. A partir del análisis de las experiencias emocionales de cada uno de ellos, se analizan sus comportamientos, pensamientos y malestar. La comunicación funcional entre profesores y alumnos, así como entre la escuela y el hogar, es un factor del que todas las partes implicadas pueden beneficiarse. Respecto esto, las autoras señalan la importancia de la formación psico-pedagógica de los profesores para ayudar a hacer frente a las dificultades que pueden encontrar en la relación con los estudiantes, especialmente con los más problemáticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(29): 93-100, abr. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162669</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El malestar del estudiante adolescente, de sus profesores y de sus padres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30184</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
