<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037780</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of recurrent secondary hyperparathyroidism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Secondary renal hyperparathyroidism (SHPT) affects nearly all patients on regular hemodialysis. Between 5% and 10% will need surgery to control the disease. Despite a meticulous technique, the rate of recurrent/persistent hyperparathyroidism after surgery remains between 2% and 12%.                 Patients and method. We reviewed the reoperations of 7 patients with recurrent or persistent SHPT from a series of 56 patients, 3 of which were referred from other units for treatment of recurrence. Subtotal parathyroidectomy (ST-PTX) was performed in 51 patients and total parathyroidectomy with autograft (TPTX-AT) was performed in the remaining 5 patients.                 Results. Seven patients underwent reoperation for recurrent SHPT, 1 of them twice (8 reinterventions in 56 patients). In 2 patients only 3 parathyroid glands were removed at the first intervention and recurrence was due to the presence of a fourth gland. In 4 patients, ST-PTX was performed and recurrence was due to a remnant hyperplasic area in 1 and to a fifth gland in 3. Recurrence in the patient with a TPTX-AT was to due to cervical parathyromatosis. All the patients with recurrence had a positive preoperative Tc-MIBI scintigraphy and the computed tomography/magnetic resonance examination was highly useful for anatomical localization of the lesion and for planning the surgical approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jimeno, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sitges-Serra, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El hiperparatiroidismo secundario (HPTS) renal afecta aproximadamente al 100% de los pacientes en programa de hemodiálisis periódica. Entre un 5 y un 10% de estos pacientes requerirá una intervención quirúrgica para el control de la enfermedad. A pesar de una técnica quirúrgica meticulosa, la tasa de persistencia/recidiva postoperatoria del HPTS se sitúa entre el 2 y el 12%.                 Pacientes y método. Se han revisado las reintervenciones de 7 enfermos por recidiva o persistencia de HPTS en una serie global de 56 pacientes, 3 de los cuales fueron remitidos por recidiva desde otros centros. La técnica quirúrgica que se realizó inicialmente fue la paratiroidectomía subtotal en 51 casos y la paratiroidectomía total con autoinjerto en 5 pacientes.                 Resultados. Siete pacientes fueron reintervenidos por recidiva del HPTS, 1 de ellos en 2 ocasiones (8 reintervenciones/56 pacientes). En la primera intervención quirúrgica, en 2 pacientes se había realizado la resección de sólo 3 glándulas paratiroides (GPT) y la recidiva era secundaria a la presencia de una cuarta glándula GPT. En 4 pacientes se había realizado previamente una paratiroidectomía subtotal; la recidiva de 1 de ellos se debió a la hiperplasia del remanente paratiroideo y en los otros 3 pacientes se evidenció, como causa de la recidiva, la presencia de una quinta GPT. En 1 paciente en el que se realizó una paratiroidectomía total con autoinjerto braquial la recidiva fue debida a una paratiromatosis cervical. En todos los pacientes que presentaron recidiva, la gammagrafía preoperatoria fue positiva y las pruebas radiológicas fueron de gran valor para la localización anatómica de la lesión y para la planificación del abordaje quirúrgico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);78(1): 34-38, jul. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037780</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico del hiperparatiroidismo secundario recidivado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7141^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7141^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7141^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
