<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94426</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical recommendations for acute peritoneal dialysis in the new born</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence of acute renal insufficiency is seen in as many as 23% of newborns admitted to intensive care units, being 70% of these caused by a prerenal condition. Peritoneal dialysis represents an effective technique in neonatal acuterenal insufficiency, mainly following extracorporeal cardiac surgery. The objective of this work was to elaborate updated clinical recommendations about peritoneal dialysis currently in place at the neonatal intensive care unit. The phases examined include a preliminary phase, execution or implementation, maintenance and removal. In the maintenance phase, the nursing interventions that need to be carried out to establish nursing diagnoses as well as the collaboration problems that nurses encounter when treating newborns in whom the technique is applied are examined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo Salinas, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada Vargas, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Álvarez, M. del Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriba Marcos, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La incidencia de Insuficiencia Renal Aguda se observa hasta en 23% de los recién nacidos ingresados en las unidad desde cuidos intensivos, siendo el 70% de causa prerrenal. La diálisis peritoneal representa una técnica eficaz en la insuficiencia renal aguda neonatal, sobre todo tras una cirugía cardiaca extracorpórea. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue elaborar unas recomendaciones clínicas actualizadas sobre la diálisis peritoneal dentro del protocolo asistencial existente en la unidad de cuidados intensivos neonatal. Se recorren la fase preliminar, de ejecución, mantenimiento y retirada. Dentro de la fase de mantenimiento se abordan las intervenciones enfermeras que deben realizarse para los diagnósticos enfermeros y los problemas de colaboración que más frecuentemente pueden presentarte en los recién nacidos a los que se les realiza esta técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;11(4): 12-17, mayo 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones clínicas para la realización de la diálisis peritoneal aguda en el recién nacido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5211^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
