<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054787</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Odontogenic tumors in children and adolescents. A 15-year retrospective study in Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are few studies on bucco-maxillary lesions in children and adolescents, and reports on odontogenic tumors (OT)are scanty. Comparison among the available data is difficult due to differences in the criteria used in each study. Theaim of the present work was to perform a retrospective study of OT in patients aged up to 20 years diagnosed at a cen-ter specialized in histopathologic diagnosis of oral diseases. All cases diagnosed with OT between 1990 and 2004 wereretrieved from the Service archives. The 153 retrieved cases accounted for 7% of total biopsies performed during thatperiod, and to 78.4% of tumors of the jaws. Mean age of the whole population was 12.7 years and the male to femaleratio was 2:1. The most frequent tumor types were Odontoma, (50.9%), Ameloblastoma (18.3%) and Myxoma (8.5%),and the most infrequent was Calcifying Epithelial Odontogenic Tumor (1.3%). According to our results, OT cannot beconsidered infrequent. They are the prevalent tumors of the jaws in the age group studied herein</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piloni, María Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrisi, Marcela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Keszler, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios sobre lesiones buco maxilares en niños y adolescentes son relativamente poco comunes y escasos los reportes sobre tumores odontogénicos (TO) en la literatura internacional actualizada. Los datos disponibles son difíciles decomparar debido a los diferentes criterios de análisis utilizados. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue realizar un estudio retrospectivo de TO en pacientes de hasta 20 años de edad diagnosticados en un centro especializado en diagnóstico anatomopatológico bucal. Se seleccionaron de los archivos del Servicio los casos con diagnósticos de TO correspondientes al período 1990-2004. Los 153 casos hallados representaron el 7% del total de biopsias realizadas y el 78.4 % de los tumores maxilares. La edad media general fue de 12.7 años y la relación hombre-mujer 2:1. Los tipos tumorales más frecuentes fueron el Odontoma (50.9%), Ameloblastoma (18.3%) y Mixoma (8.5%). El más infrecuente fue el TumorOdontogénico Epitelial Calcificante (1.3%). Según los datos obtenidos los TO no pueden ser considerados infrecuentes. En los maxilares son los prevalentes en el grupo etario estudiado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);12(3): E180-E185, mayo 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores odontogénicos en niños y adolescentes. Estudio retrospectivo de 15 años en Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24273^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24274^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24238^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
