<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100476</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">General considerations emergency care in the obstetric patient polytrauma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article's main objective is that the toilets are aware of the physiological changes that occur in pregnant women who require special considerations in prehospital emergency care for better maternal and fetal outcomes. Its production has made a systematic search of major databases: Cinahl, Pubmed, Take care, Cochrane, Google Scholar and Midwifery Profession Magazine with keywords: trauma and pregnancy. The search yielded a score of 55 articles of which 33 were eliminated for lack of validity in the methodology or may not be related to the subject matter. In conclusion we can say that the increase in female labor activity, persistence in his work until the end of gestation and greater car use have increased rates of obstetric trauma and morbidity and mortality of women in the industrialized countries (1) being the most important consequence of fetal death (2), it is necessary to understand the physiological changes of pregnancy and their own impact on the organic compensation to provide the best care possible and to improve maternal outcomes and ensure the greater good fetal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García González, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duarte González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejías Paneque, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo tiene como objetivo principal que los sanitarios conozcan las modificaciones fisiológicas que se producen en la mujer embarazada y que precisan consideraciones especiales en la atención de urgencias prehospitalaria para conseguir mejores resultados materno-fetales. Para su elaboración se ha procedido a una búsqueda sistemática de las principales bases de datos: Cinahl, Pubmed, Cuiden, Cochrane, Google académico y Revista Matronas Profesión con las palabras clave: Politraumatismo y Embarazo. La búsqueda obtuvo un resultado de 55 artículos de los cuales se eliminaron 33 por su falta de validez en la metodología o no estar relacionados con el objeto de estudio. Como conclusión podemos decir que el aumento de la actividad laboral de la mujer, la persistencia en su trabajo hasta el final de su gestación y el mayor uso del automóvil han incrementado las tasas de traumatismos obstétricos y de la morbi-mortalidad de la mujer en los países industrializados (1) siendo la consecuencia más importante la muerte fetal (2), es necesario conocer las modificaciones fisiológicas propias del embarazo y su repercusión en la compensación orgánica para proporcionar la mejor atención posible y mejorar los resultados maternos así como garantizar el mayor bienestar fetal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(25): 464-469, ene. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100476</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consideraciones generales en la atención de urgencia a la paciente obstétrica politraumatizada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9958^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13894^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13894^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34382^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
