<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152417</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extensive left-leg venous thrombosis in young patients: Should we perform extended tests?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report 3 cases of left iliac vein thrombosis whose underlying cause was right iliac artery compression syndrome, also known as May-Thurner syndrome. Endovascular treatment with anatomical correction (stent placement) was applied in 2 of the cases; anticoagulant therapy was maintained given the presence of associated hypercoagulability. A thorough understanding of this diagnosis is important so that an attempt at anatomical correction can be proposed to complement anticoagulant therapy in the interest of improving prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Carrillo, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Pedro, Ivan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo Herrera, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar de Troya, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan 3 casos de trombosis de la vena ilíaca izquierda que como causa subyacente presentaban una compresión por parte de la arteria ilíaca derecha, lo cual es conocido como síndrome de May-Thurner. Se procedió en 2 de ellos a tratamiento endovascular con corrección anatómica mediante colocación de un stent, manteniendo la anticoagulación por presentar trombofilia asociada. Es importante conocer esta entidad, para además de aplicar la anticoagulación, intentar realizar una corrección anatómica que mejore el pronóstico del enfermo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(2): 121-123, abr. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152417</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis venosa extensa de la extremidad inferior izquierda en sujetos jóvenes: ¿debemos realizar estudio de extensión?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54891^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
