<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81306</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Afebrile pneumonia syndrome of the unweaned baby</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Chlamydia trachomatis infection is one of the most frequent diseases of sexual transmission. The newborn can be infected through the birth canal, and develop a pneumonia or a conjunctivitis later. Pneumonia can appear between the first and third month of life, and is manifested with coughing fit and nasal congestion. Given its clinical similarity with the bronchiolitis, it should be considered in its differential diagnosis, especially during the first three months of age. The diagnosis can be performed either by culture of C. trachomatis or by the detection of antigens in nasopharyngeal aspirate samples or determination of antibodies in blood. A 14-day course of oral erythromycin is the best treatment option for its eradication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Río Camacho, G. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Moreno, T. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernácer Borja, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rado Peralta, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección por Chlamydia trachomatis es una de las enfermedades de transmisión sexual más frecuentes. El neonato puede infectarse en el canal del parto, y puede desarrollar una neumonía o una conjuntivitis posteriormente. La neumonía suele presentarse entre el primer y el tercer mes de vida, y cursa con accesos de tos y congestión nasal. Dada su similitud clínica con la bronquiolitis, debemos tenerla en cuenta en el diagnóstico diferencial, especialmente en los primeros 3 meses de vida. El diagnóstico puede hacerse tanto por cultivo de C. trachomatis como por la detección de antígeno en muestras de aspirado nasofaríngeo o mediante la determinación de anticuerpos en sangre. El tratamiento de elección para su erradicación es la eritromicina oral durante 14 días (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;67(9): 455-456, oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía afebril del lactante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28027^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23966^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2738^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
