<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163870</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of ultra-mini percutaneous nephrolithotomy and micro-percutaneous nephrolithotomy in moderate-size renal stones</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: We aimed to compare the success and complications of ultra-mini percutaneous nephrolithotomy and micro-percutaneous nephrolithotomy techniques. Methods: We retrospectively analyzed data from 74 patients. Moderate-size stones were included in the study. Results: Forty-two patients were included in MPNL, and 32 patients were included in UPNL groups. Among our patient cohort, 42 (56.7%) were males, and 32 (43.3%) were females. The mean age of the patients was 40±13.2 years in the MPNL group, and the mean age of the patients was 42±14.1 years in the UPNL group. The mean stone size was 17±3.2 mm in the MPNL group and 16.4±3.7 mm in the UPNL group. The stonefree rates were 88.1% (37/42) and 90.6% (29/32) in the MPNL and UPNL groups, respectively; there was no statically significant difference between the groups. The mean hospital stay was 1.4±0.23 days in the MPNL group and 1.1±0.12 day in the UPNL group. Conclusions: Two techniques have similar success and complication rates, and both may be preferred particularly in moderate-size stones. Our experience supports that our UPNL technique is safe and effective using with a standard ureteroscope (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Karakan, Tolga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fatih Kilinc, Muhammet</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gokhan Doluoglu, Omer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yildiz, Yildiray</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bagcioglu, Murat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bozkurt, Selen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Demirbas, Arif</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Resorlu, Berkan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar las tasas de éxito y las complicaciones de las técnicas ultra-mini nefrolitotomia percutánea (UNLP) y micro Nefrolitotomía percutánea (MNLP). Métodos: Analizamos retrospectivamente los datos de 74 pacientes. Se incluyeron en el estudio litiasis de tamaño moderado. Resultados: Cuarenta y dos pacientes se incluyeron en el grupo de MNLP y 32 pacientes en el de UNLP. En nuestra cohorte de pacientes, 42 (56,7%) eran varones y 32 (43,3%) mujeres. La edad media de los pacientes fue de 40±13,2 años en el grupo de MNLP y 42±14,1 años en el grupo de UNLP. El tamaño medio de la litiasis fue de 17±3,2 mm en el grupo de MNLP y 16,4±3,7 mm en el grupo de UNLP. Las tasas de pacientes libres de litiasis fueron del 88,1% (37/42) y 90,6% (29/32) en los grupos de MNLP y UNLP, respectivamente; no había diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los grupos. La estancia hospitalaria media fue de 1,4±0,23 días en el grupo de MNLP y 1,1±0,12 días en el de UNLP. Conclusiones: Las dos técnicas tienen tasas de éxito y de complicaciones similares, y ambas pueden ser las preferidas para litiasis de tamaño moderado. Nuestra experiencia apoya que nuestra técnica de UNLP es segura y efectiva utilizando un ureteroscopio estándar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;70(5): 550-555, jun. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de la nefrolitotomía percutánea ultra-mini y micro-nefrolitotomía percutánea en cálculos renales de tamaño moderado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19612^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24256^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
