<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109948</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electrosurgery in Patients With Implantable Electronic Cardiac Devices (Pacemakers and Defibrillators)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The electrosurgical unit is a very useful tool widely used in dermatology to treat benign and malignant skin lesions and to achieve hemostasis during surgery. However, precautions are required when this technique is used in patients with implantable electronic cardiac devices (IECD), such as pacemakers and defibrillators, because electromagnetic interference produced by the tool may cause such devices to malfunction. Before using electrosurgery in patients with IECDs, it is essential to ascertain the type of implanted device and the patient&#146;s level of dependence on it. The location of the skin lesion to be treated with respect to the device should also be assessed. Bipolar pacemakers are more resistant to interference. Appropriate monitoring and the use of bipolar forceps are recommended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanaclocha, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bracamonte, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El electrobisturí es una herramienta muy útil y ampliamente utilizada en dermatología para el tratamiento de lesiones benignas y malignas cutáneas, y para la hemostasia durante la cirugía dermatológica. Su uso en pacientes con dispositivos electrónicos cardiacos implantables (marcapasos y desfibriladores) requiere tomar ciertas precauciones ya que puede producir interferencias electromagnéticas capaces de provocar su malfuncionamiento. Ante un paciente con uno de estos dispositivos se debe conocer el tipo de dispositivo que presenta y la dependencia del paciente, y valorar la localización tanto del dispositivo como de la lesión cutánea a tratar. El marcapasos en configuración bipolar es el más resistente a la interferencia. Se aconseja la monitorización adecuada del paciente y el uso de la pinza bipolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;104(2): 128-132, mar. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109948</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Electrocirugía y dispositivos electrónicos cardiacos implantables (marcapasos y desfibriladores)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4671^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
