<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83208</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gene therapy for type 1 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 1 diabetes mellitus is a chronic disease characterized by autoimmunedestruction of insulin-producing beta-cells. Current insulin replacement therapiesoffer many patient benefits, but do not prevent secondary complicationswhen glycemic control is insufficient and are associated with the risk of hypoglycemia.Therefore, more efficient and safer therapies are still required.Gene therapy is considered a new approach/tool to treat diabetes. Importantadvances in the field of gene therapy have made vectors both more efficientand safer in delivering genes to most tissues and cell types. In this review, wefirst analyze the key issues that should be considered for designing a newgene therapy approach for diabetes and second, we discuss main approachescurrently under investigation for this disease. Finally, most relevant results inthe field are presented(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anguela, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mann, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes mellitus tipo 1 es una enfermedad crónica que resulta de la destrucciónautoinmune de las células beta pancreáticas. Aunque la terapia sustitutivacon insulina permite a los pacientes llevar una vida activa, no impide laaparición de complicaciones secundarias graves cuando el control de la glucemiaes insufi ciente, y está asociada al riesgo de padecer episodios de hipoglucemia.Por tanto, es necesario disponer de terapias más efectivas y seguras. Laterapia génica se puede considerar una nueva aproximación o herramienta prometedoraen la búsqueda de una curación para la diabetes. Los avances en elcampo de la terapia génica nos permiten disponer de vectores más seguros yefi caces para transferir los genes de interés a las diferentes células/tejidos delorganismo. En esta revisión se presentan, por un lado, los elementos que espreciso tener en cuenta a la hora de diseñar una estrategia de terapia génicapara la diabetes y, por otro, las diferentes aproximaciones actuales para la diabetestipo 1. Por último, se discuten los resultados más relevantes descritos eneste campo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(1): 6-12, ene.-feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83208</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximaciones de terapia génica para la diabetes tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23652^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29211^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5955^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
