<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93443</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of nutritional overweight and obesity and hypertension as well as their relationship with anthropometric indicators in a population of students in Granada and its provinces</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Several authors have found correlations between anthropometric parameters and blood pressure levels in overweight and obese subjects. This paper is an update on the potential of these parameters as a tool for predicting cardiovascular risk. Aims: to estimate the prevalence of overweight and obesity. Second verify the existence of a significant correlation between the main anthropometric indicators and the blood pressure levels. Sample: The population consisted of 977 children and adolescents between 9 and 17 years of age belonging to 13 schools in the province of Granada and city. Methodology: anthropometric evaluation in which they were assessed six skinfolds, waist circumference, hip and determination of blood pressure in three consecutive occasions. The anthropometric assessment phase began in March 2008 lasted until April 2009. Results: We found that the prevalence of overweight in girls varied between 18.3% and 32.2%. For its part, the prevalence among boys was between 10.9% and 26.1%. Regarding the prevalence of obesity, the girls had similar rates between 4.5% and 15.1%. Among boys the prevalence of obesity was similar, and found rates between 4.7% and 12.6%. Of all the parameters measured, body mass index and waist circumference were the anthropometric indicators that showed a better correlation to blood pressure. Conclusions: BMI and WC are useful anthropometric indicators to predict cardiovascular risk in non adults (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García López, PA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ferré, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Jiménez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla López, CA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, CJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Cordero, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Diversos autores han encontrado correlaciones entre parámetros antropométricos y los niveles de presión arterial en sujetos con sobrepeso y obesidad. El presente trabajo supone una puesta al día sobre las potencialidades de dichos parámetros como un instrumento más de predicción del riesgo cardiovascular. Objetivos: Realizar una estimación de la prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad. En segundo lugar verificar la existencia de una correlación significativa entre los principales indicadores antropométricos valorados y los niveles de presión arterial mostrados por los alumnos. Muestra: una población constituida por 977 niños y adolescentes de entre 9 y 17 años de edad pertenecientes a 13 centros educativos de la provincia de Granada y ciudad. Metodología: Se realizó una evaluación antropométrica en la que fueron valorados seis pliegues cutáneos, la circunferencia de la cintura, de la cadera y la determinación de la presión arterial en hasta tres ocasiones consecutivas. Esta fase de valoración antropométrica comenzó en marzo de 2008 prolongándose hasta mayo de 2009. Resultados: Se encontró una prevalencia de sobrepeso en chicas que oscilaba entre el 18,3% y el 32,2%. Por su parte, entre los chicos su prevalencia se situaba entre el 10,9% y el 26,1%. Respecto de la prevalencia de obesidad, las chicas mostraron tasas comprendidas entre el 4,5% y el 15,1%. Entre los chicos la prevalencia de obesidad resultó similar, encontrando tasas comprendidas entre el 4,7% y el 12,6%. De todos los parámetros valorados, el índice de masa corporal y la circunferencia fueron los indicadores antropométricos que mayor grado de correlación mostraron respecto de las cifras de presión arterial. Conclusiones: El índice de masa corporal, así como la circunferencia de la cintura constituyen indicadores antropométricos precisos para predecir el riesgo cardiovascular en sujetos no adultos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(5): 1004-1010, sept.-oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93443</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad nutricional e hipertensión arterial y su relación con indicadores antropométricos en una población de escolares de Granada y su provincia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51213^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
