<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045005</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional magnetic resonance imaging of the brain's response to pain in patients with a diagnosis of fibromyalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Pain is a subjective experience that is difficult to evaluate due to its varied expression. Currently, functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) can reveal the brain's response to painful stimuli. Objective: To evaluate the brain's response to pain in patients with chronic generalized essential pain diagnosed with fibromyalgia (FM). Subjects and Methods: Pain stimulus through mechanical pressure was administered to 15 patients with FM and to 22 control subjects while fMRI was carried out. Several attempts at activation were performed, varying the pressure exerted on a 2 cm2 surface of the thumb. Results: During acquisition of fRMI, none of the control subjects experienced significant discomfort when mechanical pressure of 4 kg was applied. However, all patients except one reported moderate-severe pain with the same stimulus. fMRI revealed that with slight pressure (4 and 5 kg), activation of areas other than the primary sensory-motor area contralateral to the stimulated thumb was exceptional in controls. However, 5 patients (p = 0.027) at 4 kg of pressure and seven (p = 0.030) at 5 kg of pressure showed activation of brain regions known to be mediators of pain response (primary sensory-motor area, parietal cortex, insula, and anterior cingulum). Conclusions: The results of this study suggest that in a significant proportion of patients diagnosed with FM and with a low pain threshold, there is a consistent brain response to low-intensity mechanical stimuli while in another proportion of patients, the response of the brain to painful stimuli is similar to that of control subjects</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soriano-Mas, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deus, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardoner, Narcís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Hector</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bofia, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cámara, Estela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El dolor es una experiencia subjetiva difícilmente evaluable por su variada expresión. Actualmente, la resonancia magnética funcional (RMf) permite objetivar la respuesta cerebral al estímulo doloroso. Objetivo: Evaluar la respuesta cerebral al dolor en pacientes con dolor crónico esencial generalizado diagnosticados de fibromialgia (FM). Sujetos y métodos: Se administró un estímulo doloroso por presión mecánica a 15 pacientes con FM y 11 controles durante la adquisición de RMf. Se realizaron diversos ensayos de activación variando la presión ejercida sobre una superficie de 1 cm2 del dedo pulgar. Resultados: Durante la adquisición de RMf, la aplicación de una presión mecánica de 4 kg no ocasionó molestias relevantes en ningún sujeto control. Contrariamente, todos los pacientes, excepto uno, refirieron dolor moderado-grave con este estímulo. La RMf puso de manifiesto que, con poca presión (4 y 5 kg), es excepcional la activación de regiones distintas al área sensitivomotora primaria contralateral al dedo estimulado en los sujetos control. Sin embargo, 5 pacientes (p = 0,027), a 4 kg de presión, y 7 (p = 0,030), a 5 kg, activaron las regiones cerebrales conocidas como mediadoras de la respuesta al dolor (área sensitivomotora primaria, corteza parietal, ínsula y región del cíngulo anterior). Conclusiones: Los resultados sugieren que una proporción significativa de pacientes diagnosticados de FM y con bajo umbral doloroso presentan una consistente respuesta cerebral al dolor con estímulos mecánicos de baja intensidad, mientras que en otra parte de los casos el cerebro responde de forma similar a los sujetos control</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);13(2): 39-46, mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045005</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resonancia magnética funcional de la respuesta cerebral al dolor en pacientes con diagnóstico de fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
