<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152678</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body weight- independent variations in HDL-cholesterol following gastric bypass</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Bariatric surgery has multiple beneficial effects on lipid profile in patients with morbid obesity. However, these changes can be attenuated by weight regain. This retrospective study was designed to assess the effects of gastric bypass (GBP) on different lipid fractions over a 6 year follow-up. Patients and Methods. We studied 177 patients (135 women) with morbid obesity (BMI 44.2+0.4 kg/m2) aged 42.4+0.9 years before and 3, 6, 9, 12, 24, 36, 48, 60 and 72 months after laparoscopic proximal GBP. Anthropometry, body composition measurement (Bod-Pod) and fasting blood samples were taken in all evaluations to measure total cholesterol (TC), LDL-cholesterol (LDL-C), HDL-cholesterol (HDL-C), triglycerides (TG), glucose and insulin. Results. GPB was followed by a significant BMI reduction (nadir BMI at 18 m 28.3+0.4 kg/m2 p&lt;0,001) and fat mass decrease (p&lt;0,001). Maximal percentage of excess BMI lost was 84.1% and that of body fat was 87% 18 months after GBP. These numbers decreased to 65.6% and 38.3% (p&lt;0,005 vs nadir) respectively 72 months after the operation, indicating both weight and fat mass regain. TG and LDL-C values decreased 30% with respect to preoperative levels, while HDL-C increased 97% over initial values. This HDL-C increase was progressive even over the weight regain phase. Both TC/HDL-C and TG/HDL-C ratios normalized after GBP and values were sustained over the weight regain period until the end of the study. Conclusions. These results confirm the beneficial effects of GBP on all lipid fractions, which are maintained over 6 years of follow-up. Globally, the rise in HDL-C seems to be independent of weight or fat mass changes, since it increases even over the weight regain phase, so contributing to a reduction in the prevalence of dyslipidaemia and to cardiovascular risk reduction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrada, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenti, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frühbeck, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rotellar, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Ambrosi, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La cirugía bariátrica posee efectos beneficiosos sobre el perfil lipídico en pacientes con obesidad mórbida que pueden atenuarse con la recuperación ponderal. El presente estudio se ha llevado a cabo para evaluar el perfil lipídico antes y a lo largo de los seis años consiguientes a la realización de bypass gástrico proximal (BPG). Material y métodos. Se han estudiado 177 pacientes (135 mujeres) con obesidad mórbida (IMC 44,2+0,4 kg/m2) de 42,4+0,9 años de edad antes, 3,6,9, 12,24,36,48,60 y 72 meses después de realizar BPG. En todas las revisiones se evaluó el tratamiento hipolipemiante, antropometría (IMC, cintura), composición corporal (Bod-Pod) y determinaciones de colesterol total (CT), colesterol-LDL (LDL-C), colesterol-HDL (HDL-C), triglicéridos (TG), glucosa e insulina. Resultados. El BPG indujo marcada reducción de IMC (nadir IMC a 18 meses 28,3+0,4 kg/m2 p&lt;0,001) y grasa corporal consiguiendo una pérdida de exceso IMC del 84,1% y del exceso de porcentaje de grasa del 87% que disminuyó al 65,6 y 38,3% (ambos p&lt;0,005 respecto a nadir) respectivamente a los 6 años del BPG, indicando recuperación de peso y grasa corporal. Los valores de TG alcanzaron el 70% a los 60 meses, los de LDL-C el 70,6% a los 18 meses y los de HDL-C el 197% del valor pre-intervención a los 48 meses. La elevación de HDL-C aumentó durante la fase de recuperación ponderal de forma continuada (p&lt;0,001). Tanto los cocientes CT/HDL-C como TG/HDL-C se normalizaron de forma mantenida durante los 6 años de seguimiento. Conclusiones. Estos resultados confirman la mejoría de todas las fracciones lipídicas 6 años después del BPG, con especial mención a HDL-C, que mantuvo progresión creciente incluso durante la recuperación ponderal, reduciendo la tasa de dislipemia a los 6 años del BPG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;39(1): 23-33, ene.-abr. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152678</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las variaciones en colesterol-HDL tras bypass gástrico proximal son independientes de la evolución ponderal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16508^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
