<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133053</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Something old, something new and&#133; something slow?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Atrial fibrillation (AT) is the most frequent type of arrhythmia in clinical practice. It causes a high rate of morbidity and mortality. A patient with known AF who follows adequate therapy and starts feeling dizzy, should alert his/her GP. An electrocardiogram is essential for correct diagnosis: the presence of bradycardia in a patient with AF. This clinical situation constitutes a non-delayable reason to refer the patient to the hospital in order to carry out an etiologic study and adequate therapy because of the seriousness of this clinical picture (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gabriela Tomoiu, Ileana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Casado, José Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez García, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hoyo Gómez, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrilación auricular (FA) es la arritmia más frecuente en la práctica clínica. Es responsable de una elevada morbilidad y mortalidad. Un paciente con FA conocida, que sigue tratamiento adecuadamente, y comienza con mareo, debe alertar al Médico de Familia. Un electrocardiograma es fundamental para un correcto diagnóstico: la presencia de una bradicardia en un paciente con FA. Esta situación clínica constituye una causa de derivación hospitalaria no demorable para realizar estudio etiológico y tratamiento adecuado ante la gravedad del cuadro clínico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;7(3): 220-222, oct. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133053</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Algo viejo, algo nuevo y ¿algo lento?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6480^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6480^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1945^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1945^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6480^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
