<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133983</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of EVAR anatomy in the surgical treatment of a ruptured abdominal aortic aneurysm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Several comparative studies have suggested that endovascular treatment (EVAR) of ruptured abdominal aortic aneurysms (AAAr) could reduce mortality compared to conventional open repair (OR). A confounding factor in these findings could be the aorto-iliac anatomy. EVAR is suitable if patients have an appropriate surgical anatomy. Objective: The purpose of this study was to analyze the results of surgical treatment of rAAA in the presence or not of an EVAR-friendly anatomy. Material and methods: A retrospective study was designed and conducted on consecutive patients with rAAA treated in our hospital between June 2005 and June 2010. Patients were categorized according to the anatomical suitability for EVAR, based on a blinded analysis of preoperative CT-angiography. Perioperative mortality and complications were determined in each group. Results: Of the 71 patients studied, 50 underwent preoperative CT. Of these, only 41 patients were operated on (30-OR, 11 EVAR). In the 30 patients who underwent OR, 14 were suitable for EVAR, and 16 showed a hostile anatomy. Both groups were homogeneous with a Glasgow-aneurysm-score of 90 ± 13.8 and 92.1 ± 14.6, respectively. A significant reduction in mortality at 30 days in the EVAR suitable group (21.4%) was observed in comparison to the EVAR unsuitable group (56.3%) (P=.05). A lower transfusion requirement, length of stay, and in hospital morbidity was shown in patients with a friendly anatomy. Conclusion: Anatomical suitability for EVAR significantly improves short-term prognosis of patients treated with rAAA. This suggests that the reduction in mortality from EVAR is probably biased by the selection of patients with a better anatomical configuration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Fajardo, J. Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla Calavia, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengíbar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Diversas series han indicado que el tratamiento endovascular (EVAR) del aneurisma de aorta roto (AAAr) podría disminuir la mortalidad respecto a la cirugía convencional abierta (OR). Sin embargo, un factor confusional en estos hallazgos puede ser la anatomía aortoilíaca del aneurisma. El EVAR solo es posible si los pacientes tienen una anatomía quirúrgica apropiada. Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio ha sido analizar los resultados del tratamiento quirúrgico de los AAAr en presencia o no de una anatomía EVAR-favorable. Material y métodos: Se diseñó un estudio retrospectivo de todos los AAAr atendidos en nuestro hospital entre junio de 2005 y junio de 2010. Los pacientes se agruparon de acuerdo con la idoneidad anatómica para EVAR basados en el análisis ciego de la angio-TAC preoperatoria. Se analizó la mortalidad perioperatoria y las complicaciones según la idoneidad anatómica de los pacientes intervenidos. Resultados: De 71 pacientes atendidos, 50 disponían de angio-TAC. Solo se intervino a 41 (30-OR, 11-EVAR). De los 30-OR, 14 fueron EVAR-favorable y 16 no lo fueron. Ambos grupos fueron homogéneos con un Glasgow-aneurysm-score de 90 ± 13,8 y 92,1 ± 14,6, respectivamente. Se observó una reducción significativa en la mortalidad a 30 días en el grupo EVAR-favorable (21,4%) en comparación con el grupo EVAR-no favorable (56,3%) (p = 0,05), lo que se tradujo en una menor tasa de transfusiones, complicaciones sistémicas y estancia hospitalaria. Conclusión: La idoneidad anatómica para EVAR mejora significativamente el pronóstico a corto plazo de los pacientes tratados de AAAr. Esto indica que la reducción de la mortalidad debida al EVAR probablemente esté sesgada por la selección de pacientes con mejor configuración anatómica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;67(2): 89-93, mar.-abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de la anatomía EVAR en el tratamiento quirúrgico del aneurisma de aorta abdominal roto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1024^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
