<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046946</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The right to a second opinion. Advantages, obstacles and recommendations for responsible use</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To identify the most important advantages of and obstacles against the right to a second opinion, as well as the most effective new proposals for establishing this right. Material and method: The following issues were analyzed through various qualitative methods: the advantages of a second opinion, ways to provide the right to a second opinion, obstacles against establishing this right, expected changes in the doctor-patient relationship, and ways to improve patient access to health information. Twenty-six experts from diverse second opinion-related fields took part in the working groups. Results: All the experts agreed that the main advantages of a second opinion were that this option increases the quality, reliability and credibility of the health system. The principal obstacle to a second opinion was loss of reputation and patient distrust when a medical mistake occurs. Conclusions: The right to a second opinion provides a positive response to patients and helps to improve the quality of healthcare. This right must be accompanied by an intense information campaign aimed at both patients and health professionals. Such a campaign should clearly explain the limits of this right and the procedures to be followed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Marín, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blaya, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira, José Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Jover, Virtudes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Identificar las principales ventajas, barreras y propuestas innovadoras y eficaces para implantar efectivamente el derecho a una segunda opinión. Material y método: Mediante técnicas cualitativas de búsqueda de consenso se analizaron los temas siguientes: ventajas de la segunda opinión, acciones para facilitar el derecho a la segunda opinión, dificultades derivadas del derecho a la segunda opinión, cambios previstos en el modelo de relación con el paciente y acciones para mejorar el acceso de los ciudadanos a la información sanitaria. En los grupos de trabajo participaron 26 expertos de diferentes ámbitos relacionados con la segunda opinión. Resultados: Respecto a las principales "ventajas de la segunda opinión", los expertos señalaron que aumentará la calidad, la confianza y la credibilidad del Sistema Sanitario. Respecto a la principal "dificultad derivada del derecho a la segunda opinión", se señaló la pérdida de imagen y desconfianza de los pacientes en el caso de evidenciar un error médico. Conclusiones: Además de responder positivamente a una demanda ciudadana, la segunda opinión contribuirá a mejorar la calidad de la asistencia sanitaria, siempre y cuando se acompañe de una intensa campaña de información, dirigida tanto al paciente como al profesional, que explique con claridad sus límites y el procedimiento que se debe seguir</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;21(3): 120-128, may.-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046946</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El derecho a una segunda opinión. Ventajas, barreras y recomendaciones para su ejercicio responsable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
