<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057218</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phobic orthostatic insecurity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: The authors attempt to expand knowledge about a subjective balance disorder they have called phobic orthostatic insecurity, a condition representing the second cause of medical visits (22.3 %) to their ENT &amp; neuro-otology clinic, and attempt to identify relationships with similar conditions described in psychiatry (agoraphobia, somatoform vertigo, and space-phobia) and in neurology (phobic postural vertigo). They also propose a simple diagnostic method and present their therapies and results. Patients and method: A total of 151 patients with an indefinite symptomatology of &#147;dizziness&#148; &#147;vertigo&#148; or &#147;insecurity&#148; were evaluated (from 1999 to 2005) by means of a full medical history and an appropriate neurological examination, pharmacological treatments with anxiolytics-antidepressives, a measurement of the degree of depression with the Beck test (a kind of psychiatric benchmark) and with a specific standardized test. Results: Three symptoms and one exploratory condition, among others, were found in all 151 patients studied; these constitute the four bases for a positive diagnosis. This is confirmed if the treatment achieves total remission (this occurred in 69.53 % of all patients) or a sub-total remission (24.49 %), according to valuation scale for insecurity in all situations. Conclusions: The statistical analysis showed a symptomatic concordance within the group analyzed, a syndromic equivalence between patients and satisfactory results with the antidepressive treatments (94 %), thus confirming the diagnostic and aetiopathogenic hypotheses for the disorder and, later, providing a logical method for diagnosis. The authors propose to assimilate this diagnostic protocol (and therapeutic when no specialist psychotherapy teams are available) to most of the psychogenic insecurity syndromes described</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Batuecas-Caletrío, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coscarón-Bernabé, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán-Mateos, Luis D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santa Cruz-Ruiz, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solana-Sorribas, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Melcón, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Los autores describen y tratan de extender el conocimiento de una frecuente afección a la que denominan inseguridad fóbica ortostática que, en su unidad de otorrinolaringología-neurootología, resulta ser la segunda causa (22,3 %) de consultas por vértigos reales o aparentes, así como de establecer analogías y diferencias de dicho trastorno con otras afecciones similares descritas en psiquiatría (agorafobia, vértigo somatomorfo y vértigo espacial) y en neurología (vértigo postural fóbico). Proponen para su diagnóstico un sencillo método, y exponen su tratamiento y resultados. Pacientes y método: Se analiza a 151 pacientes con síntomas indefinidos de &#147;mareo&#148;, &#147;vértigo&#148; o &#147;inseguridad&#148;, seleccionados entre 1999 y 2005, a los que, además de una anamnesis y una exploración neurootológica adecuadas, realizaron un interrogatorio estandarizado específico, un test de Beck (de referencia psiquiátrica) y un tratamiento farmacológico ansiolítico-antidepresivo. Resultados: Encontraron, entre otros, 3 síntomas y 1 condición exploratoria que se cumplen en todos los enfermos y constituyen los 4 pilares del diagnóstico positivo. Éste se convierte en seguro cuando el tratamiento consigue una remisión total (en el 69,53 % de todos los pacientes) o subtotal (en el 24,49 %), según su escala de valoración de la inseguridad para todas las situaciones. Conclusiones: El estudio estadístico permite extraer una concordancia sintomática dentro del grupo analizado, una equivalencia sindrómica entre los enfermos y unos resultados satisfactorios del tratamiento antidepresivo (en el 94 %), lo que permite verificar las hipótesis etiopatogénica y diagnóstica sospechadas ante el trastorno y obtener, consecuentemente, un método lógico de diagnóstico y tratamiento. Los autores proponen asimilar a este protocolo diagnóstico, incluso terapéutico &#151;cuando no se disponga de equipos psicoterapéuticos especializados&#151;, la mayor parte de los síndromes psicógenos de inseguridad descritos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(9): 393-400, nov. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inseguridad fóbica ortostática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7204^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
