<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038529</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Breakfast and snack of schooled adolescents in Santander</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the breakfast model and food intake at mid-morning (snack) in schooled adolescents at Santander city.  Subjects: A cross-sectional study was performed analyzing a sample of 403 adolescents: 232 girls (58%; 95%CI: 52%-62%) and 171 boys (42%; 95%CI: 38%-48%), with ages between 12 and 19 years, schooled at 12 second degree education centers of Santander, by means of a closed questionnaire and a recall 24 hours later.  Results: Five percent (95%CI: 3.1%-7.6%) of the adolescents referred neglecting breakfast. The most consumed foods were milk (47%; 95%CI: 42%-52%), chocolate milk (40%; 95%CI: 36%-45%), and cookies (45%; 95%CI: 36%-45%). On the other hand, 63% of adolescents consume whole milk (95%CI: 58%-70%), 21% semi-skimmed milk (95%CI: 17%-26%), and 11% skimmed milk (95%CI: 8%-15%). A decreasing lineal tendency in whole milk consumption is observed and a parallel increase in consumption of milks with a lower fat content as the academic year of adolescents advances (Armitage's r2 test for lineal tendency = 2.32; p = 0.02). Boys consume an average of 3.0 (SD = 1.35) different foods during breakfast and girls 2.4 (SD = 1.20). Forty-three percent (95%CI: 38%-48%) of adolescents have a snack, which means that 2% of adolescents do not have breakfast or a snack (95%CI: 1%-4%). Breakfast represents 18% (95%CI: 16%-19%) of the total daily energy intake, whereas for snack, this percentage is 16% (95%CI: 14%-17%).  Conclusion: it is necessary to promote consumption of a healthy breakfast and snack that provide an appropriate quantitative and qualitative intake (AU</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Redondo Figuero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amigo Lanza, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fuentes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Lamuño, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rufino Rivas, P de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar el modelo de desayuno e ingesta alimentaria de media mañana (almuerzo) de los adolescentes escolarizados de la ciudad de Santander.  Sujetos: Se realizó un estudio transversal, analizando una muestra de 403 adolescentes: 232 mujeres (58%; IC-95%:52%-62%) y 171 varones (42%; IC-95%: 38%-48%), de edades comprendidas entre los 12 y los 19 años, escolarizados en 12 centros de enseñanza secundaria de Santander, mediante un cuestionario cerrado y un recuerdo de 24 horas.  Resultados: El 5% (IC-95%: 3,1%-7,6%) de los jóvenes manifestó no desayunar. Los alimentos más consumidos son la leche (47%; IC-95%: 42%-52%), la leche chocolateada (40%: IC-95%: 36%-45%) y las galletas (45%; IC-95%: 36%-45%). Por otro lado, el 63% (IC-95%:58%-70%) de los jóvenes consume leche entera, el 21% (IC-95%:17%-26%) leche semidesnatada y el 11% (IC-95%:8%-15%) leche desnatada. Se aprecia una tendencia lineal decreciente en el consumo de leche entera, y un aumento paralelo en el consumo de leches con menos fracción grasa conforme aumenta el curso académico de los adolescentes (test r2 de tendencia lineal de Armitage = 2,32; p = 0,02). Los varones consumen una media de 3,0 (DE=1,35) alimentos diferentes en el desayuno y las mujeres 2,4 (DE=1,20). El 43% (IC-95%:38%-48%) de los adolescentes almuerza, lo que implica que un 2% (IC-95%: 1%-4%) de los jóvenes ni desayuna ni almuerza. El desayuno representa el 18% (IC-95%: 16%-19%) del total de la ingesta energética diaria, mientras que para el almuerzo este porcentaje es del 16% (IC-95%:14%-17%).  Conclusión: Es necesario fomentar el consumo de un desayuno y almuerzo saludables que proporcionen una ingesta cuantitativa y cualitativa adecuadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;20(3): 217-222, mayo-jun. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desayuno y almuerzo de los adolescentes escolarizados de Santander</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
