<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036238</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of burnout in primar y care nurses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Burnout syndrome refers to a kind of occupational stress that can have psychosomatic, behavioral, emotional, familial and social repercussions; it can also cause absenteeism and loss of efficiency at work. Objectives. The aim of this study was to determinate the prevalence of burnout among primary care nurses in Burgos, as well as the personal and occupational characteristics associated with this syndrome. Material and method. A crosssectional study was designed. Three selfadministered, anonymous questionnaires were sent out by internal mail: a questionnaire on social and demographic variables, the Maslach Burnout Inventory and the Goldberg&#146;s 28item General Health Questionnaire. Results. Participation was 84%. A high degree of burnout was found in the dimension of emotional exhaustion in 28.8% of the staff surveyed, in depersonalization in 32.2% and in personal achievement in 92.8%. Twentythree staff members had high scores on all three scales. Psychological impairment probably requiring psychiatric treatment was identified in 28.8%. The present study detected high levels of burnout, similar to those reported in other surveys in Spain</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soto Cámara, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Cuesta, M. Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de &#147;estar quemado&#148; o de burnout es un tipo de estrés laboral que puede tener repercusiones psicosomáticas, conductuales, emocionales, familiares y sociales y que puede ser motivo de absentismo laboral y de bajo rendimiento en el trabajo. Objetivos. El objetivo de este trabajo es conocer la prevalencia del síndrome del quemado entre los enfermeros de atención primaria de Burgos, así como las características personales y laborales que se asocian a dicho síndrome. Material y método. Estudio descriptivo, transversal, en el que como instrumentos de medida se utilizaron 3 cuestionarios autoadministrados y anónimos, enviados por correo interno: encuesta sobre variables sociodemográficas, cuestionario Maslach Burnout Inventory y Cuestionario de Salud General de Goldberg. Resultados. Se consiguió una participación del 84%. El 28,8% de los entrevistados presentó un grado elevado de burnout en la dimensión agotamiento emocional, el 32,2% en la dimensión despersonalización y el 92,8% en realización personal. Veintitrés personas presentaron valores elevados en las 3 escalas. El 28,8% se manifestó como probable caso psiquiátrico. Se detectaron niveles elevados de este síndrome, similares a los encontrados en otras encuestas nacionales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);15(3): 123-130, mayo 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036238</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del burnout en la enfermería de atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
