<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116794</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peritoneal carcinomatosis due to metastatic spread of lobular carcinoma of the breast</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Invasive lobular breast cancer has a special tropism for the peritoneal cavity and gastrointestinal and genitourinary systems. We describe 2 cases of peritoneal carcinomatosis secondary to metastatic spread of lobular carcinoma of the breast. The diagnosis was made several years after detection of the primary tumor. The peritoneal carcinomatosis (with genitourinary or gastrointestinal metastases) in breast cancer is rare and is most frequent in invasive lobular carcinoma. Diagnosis is difficult because the symptoms are often nonspecific and there is often a long interval between the initial diagnosis of breast cancer and peritoneal involvement. Clinical suspicion and histological-immunohistochemical study help to differentiate between a primary tumor of the peritoneal cavity and the presence of metastatic breast carcinoma. Treatment should be individualized in each patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrido Esteban, Rosa Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hipólito, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Hernández, María Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Dávila, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alpuente Torres, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González López, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hidalgo, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de mama lobulillar infiltrante presenta un especial tropismo sobre la cavidad peritoneal, aparato genitourinario y gastrointestinal. Describimos 2 casos de carcinomatosis peritoneal secundaria a la diseminación metastásica de un carcinoma lobulillar infiltrante de mama. El diagnóstico se hizo años después de la aparición del tumor primario. La carcinomatosis peritoneal (asociada a metástasis genitourinarias y/o gastrointestinales) en cáncer de mama es rara, siendo más frecuente en el tipo lobulillar infiltrante. Su diagnóstico es difícil dada la inespecificidad de la sintomatología y el largo periodo que, con frecuencia, ocurre desde el diagnóstico inicial del tumor mamario hasta la afectación peritoneal. La sospecha clínica y el estudio histológico-inmunohistoquímico ayudan a diferenciar entre un tumor primario de cavidad peritoneal y metástasis de carcinoma de mama. Debe individualizarse el tratamiento en cada caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(9): 467-472, nov. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116794</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis peritoneales en cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10724^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10724^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4371^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31996^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
