<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043935</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk and management of burnout syndrome in mental health Nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this article is to analyse the importance of mental healthcare of those professionals who render their services in mentalhealth, mainly the mental health nurse. This professionalgroup runs the risk of developing the so called &#147;burn out syndrome&#148;a type of work-related stress. This article defines first themeaning of the term b u rn out and predisposing factors, togetherwith the consequences for the person and his/her environment.Secondly, the relationship between burn out and nursing practiceis analysed and then the relationship between burn out and themental health nurse. Lastly, management strategies to cope withburnout are presented, both from an organisational as well asfrom a personal perspective</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pedreño Aznar, María Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este artículo es analizar la importancia del cuidadode la salud mental de los profesionales que trabajan en esteárea, centrándose principalmente en la enfermera especialista deSalud Mental. Este colectivo tiene riesgo de padecer el llamadosíndrome de burnout o &#147;estar quemado&#148;, un tipo específico deestrés laboral. En el desarrollo de este artículo se define, en primerlugar, el significado del término burnout y los factores predisponentes, junto con las consecuencias para la persona y suentorno. En segundo lugar, se analiza la relación entre burnout yla práctica de Enfermería y, a continuación, entre burnout y laenfermera de Salud Mental. Finalmente, se proponen estrategiasde afrontamiento tanto de tipo organizacional como personal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;8(9): 14-17, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043935</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo y afrontamiento del burnout de la enfermera de Salud Mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12005^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12005^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
