<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73800</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phytopharmaceuticals in the treatment of chronic venous insufficiency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic venous insufficiency (CVI) is one of the most commonvascular disorders. The main risk factors are the gravitationaleffect on the venous circulation, elderly, a familyhistory of venous disease, obesity and pregnancy. Also, theworking conditions and lifestyles favouring orthostatismcan have a role in CVI.The preparations most commonly used for the treatment ofIVC come from Aesculus hippocastanum, Ruscus aculeatus,Pinus pinaster and Hamamelis virginiana, among others,and contain bioactive compounds such as saponins,proanthocyanidins and flavonoids. The use of phytopharmaceuticalsin the treatment of IVC is associated with reliefof pain and heaviness in the legs, fatigue, cramps andparaesthesia, symptoms that constitute the pre-varicosesyndrome. Although there is evidence of its safety and efficacyat short term use, it is considered necessary to carryout further clinical studies(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bustamante Delgado, Sandro E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Castro, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Segura, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia venosa crónica (IVC) es uno de los desórdenes vascularesmás comunes. Los principales factores de riesgo son el efectogravitacional sobre la circulación venosa, la edad avanzada, una historiafamiliar de enfermedades venosas, la obesidad y el embarazo.También inciden las condiciones de trabajo y el estilo de vida que favorezcanel ortostatismo.Las preparados mas utilizados para el tratamiento de la IVC derivan deAesculus hippocastanum, Ruscus aculeatus, Pinus pinaster y Hamamelisvirginiana, entre otras, y contienen compuestos bioactivos talescomo saponósidos, proantocianidinas y flavonoides. El uso de fitofármacosen el tratamiento de la IVC se asocia al alivio tanto del dolorcomo de la pesadez de piernas, cansancio, calambres y parestesia,síntomas que constituyen el síndrome prevaricoso. Aunque existe unaamplia evidencia de su efecacia y seguridad a corto plazo, se consideranecesaria la realización de más estudios clínicos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;9(1): 35-51, 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73800</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fitofármacos en el tratamiento de la insuficiencia venosa crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35668^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35668^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9311</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25909^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1701^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36927^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36927^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1701^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1701^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25909^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
