<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59397</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors related to non-participation in a breast cancer early detection program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the causes of non-participation in a breast cancer early detection program for women in the northern area of Almería (Spain). Methods: We performed a case-control study. A sample of women included in a breast cancer early detection program between October 2002 and February 2004 was chosen. Participants were interviewed about family, sociodemographic and program-related variables (knowledge, accessibility, attitudes), family and personal history, and health status. Possible differences among women who attended the program and those who did not were analyzed through bivariate analysis and multivariate logistic regression. Odds ratio (OR) and 95% confidence interval (95%CI) were calculated. Results: A total of 720 questionnaires were completed (350 cases and 370 controls) and 291 women (40.4% of the sample) were replaced. The variables found to be independently associated with non-participation in the program were as follows: not receiving a letter (OR=11.2; 95%CI: 4.6¿26.9), undergoing mammography outside the program (OR=4.4; 95%CI: 2.8¿6.9), not having illnesses requiring medical examinations (OR=2; 95%CI: 1.3¿3), and expressing fear of the result of mammography (OR=1.8; 95%CI: 1.2¿2.6). Conclusions: Women who did not receive a letter or who underwent mammography outside the program had a greater risk of not attending the program, hence the need to improve the quality of the database. Awareness of the program should be increased among women and health education should be provided to women fearing the outcome(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Pérez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puertas de Rojas, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barroso García, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corpas Nogales, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrón Carreño, Tesifón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las causas de no participación en el Programa de Detección Precoz de Cáncer de Mama (PDPCM) en mujeres del Área de Gestión Sanitaria Norte de Almería. Métodos: Estudio de casos y controles. Se eligió una muestra de mujeres invitadas a participar en el PDPCM, entre octubre de 2002 y febrero de 2004. Se recogieron las variables sociodemográficas y las cargas familiares, las variables relacionadas con el programa (conocimiento, accesibilidad, actitudes), los antecedentes familiares y personales, y el estado de salud. Se analizó si había diferencias entre las mujeres que acudieron al programa y las que no, mediante análisis bivariado, y multivariado mediante regresión logística. Se calculó la odds ratio (OR) y su intervalo de confianza del 95% (IC95%). Resultados: Se realizaron 720 encuestas 350 casos y 370 controles. Se sustituyó a 291 mujeres (un 40,4% de la muestra). Las variables que de forma independiente se encontraron asociadas a no acudir al programa fueron no recibir carta (OR=11,2; IC95%: 4,6¿26,9), haberse realizado mamografía fuera del programa (OR=4,4; IC95%: 2,8¿6,9), no tener enfermedades que requieren revisiones médicas (OR=2; IC95%: 1,3¿3) y manifestar miedo al resultado de la mamografía (OR=1,8; IC95%: 1,2¿2,6). Conclusiones: Se ha encontrado un mayor riesgo de no acudir al programa en las mujeres que no han recibido carta o que tienen una mamografía realizada fuera del programa, y de ahí la necesidad de mejorar la depuración de la base de datos. Hay que seguir divulgando el programa y realizando educación sanitaria en las mujeres con miedo al resultado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(1): 44-48, ene.-feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59397</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores relacionados con la no participación en el programa de detección precoz de cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
