<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132187</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The darker side of coaching: influence of sport context on the negativ experience of basketball coaches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Grounded in self-determination theory, the aim of the present study was to analyze the negative experiences of development coaches. To do so, we tested a theoretical model where negative environmental factors (i.e., club pressures regarding how to run practices, work-life conflict, and perception of players&#146; amotivation) were hypothesized to positively predict coaches&#146; basic psychological need thwarting, and in turn coaches&#146; need thwarting was expected to positively predict their amotivation for coaching. One hundred and seventy-seven basketball coaches (Mage = 21.74, 27.1% women) participated in the study. Before the inclusion of the scales in the structural equation model, we obtained evidence supporting their reliability and internal structure (i.e., using confirmatory factor analyses). It was noted that for coaches&#146; psychological need thwarting, the results supported the choice of a single factor structure, instead of the hypothesized 3-factor structure. The results of the structural equation model provided evidence supporting the validity of the theoretical model, showing that club pressures, work-life conflict, and players&#146; amotivation led coaches to suffer more negative sport experiences (i.e., psychological need thwarting and amotivation for coaching) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torregrosa, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz, Saül</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viladrich, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Enmarcado dentro de la Teoría de la Autodeterminación, el objetivo del presente estudio fue analizar la experiencia negativa de los entrenadores de formación, comprobando el ajuste de un modelo teórico en el que factores negativos del ambiente (e.g., presión del club para entrenar de una determinada manera, conflicto laboral-personal y percepción de la amotivación en los jugadores) predecían positivamente la frustración de las necesidades psicológicas de los entrenadores, y a su vez esta frustración influía positivamente en su amotivación para entrenar. Un total de 177 entrenadores de baloncesto (Medad = 21.74, 27.1% mujeres) participaron en el estudio. Como paso previo a su inclusión en el modelo estructural, se obtuvieron evidencias que apoyaron la fiabilidad y la estructura interna de las escalas, mediante análisis factoriales confirmatorios. Cabe destacar que  para la frustración de las necesidades psicológicas básicas se optó por una estructura unifactorial, en lugar de la estructura de tres factores esperada según la teoría. Los resultados del modelo estructural apoyaron la validez del modelo hipotetizado, mostrando que la presión del club, el conflicto laboral-personal y la amotivación de los jugadores llevaban a los entrenadores a sufrir una experiencia deportiva más negativa (e.g., frustración de sus necesidades psicológicas y amotivación para entrenar) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(1): 71-78, 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132187</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El lado oscuro de entrenar: Influencia del contexto deportivo sobre la experiencia negativa de entrenadores de baloncesto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
