<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87483</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ambulatory surgery for cervical tumours</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">KIND OF STUDY: Descriptive. SETTING: A Public General Hospital. MATERIAL AND METHODS: We present 10cases of Cervical Tumours: 3 thyroid nodules, 2thyroglossal cysts, 2 parotid adenomas, 1 submaxillary tumour, 1 submaxillary lithiasis/abscess and 1 branchial cyst. All these tumours were treated in a Day Surgery Unit (DSU). Both the selection criteria and the surgical treatment hardly differed from that used in conventional procedures except in hemithyroidectomies where we tried to avoid extension of the neck. Postoperative observation during hospital stay was the same as that applied to any other pathology. Personalized postoperative monitoring was carried out allowing the patient to have direct access to his surgical team during the 24 hours following the operation. RESULTS: The results are good as there have been no complications. We evaluated the attitude towards possible complications which mayarise. CONCLUSION: We concluded that this group of nodular thyroid pathology may be included among Ambulatory procedures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Barreda, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín García, R. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aracil Kessler, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorens Salvador, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicent Dols, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boldó Roda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">TIPO DE ESTUDIO: Descriptivo PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: Se presentan 10casos de Tumoraciones Cervicales: 3 nódulos tiroideos, 2 quistes tiroglosos,2 adenomas parotídeos,1 Tumor submaxilar, 1 litiasis/abceso submaxilary 1 quiste branquial tratadas en régimen de Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria. Los criterios de selección varían poco con respecto a los convencionales, así como el tratamiento quirúrgico, ya que solo en las hemitiroidectomías se trataba de evitar la extensión del cuello; y la vigilancia postoperatoria en el Hospital era igual a la que se aplica a cualquier otra patología. Se ha realizado un seguimiento postoperatorio personalizado, en el que el paciente tenía acceso directo a su equipo quirúrgico durante las primeras 24horas postoperatorias. RESULTADOS: Los resultados han sido buenos, ya que no se han producido complicaciones. Se hace una valoración de la actitud con respecto a las complicaciones mas graves que se podían haber producido. Conclusiones: Se concluye que este grupo de patología nodular tiroidea se puede incluir entre las entidades de CMA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;9(1): 14-17, ene.-abr. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87483</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía ambulatoria en tumores cervicales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29779^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1961^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22683^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10470^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14343^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
