<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99242</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neonatal gastroesophageal reflux: debut with persistent hiccups crisis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hiccups are defined as a sudden, involuntary and intermittent twitching of the diaphragm, associated with early and abrupt closure of the glottis by the end of the inspiration, and it create a distinctive sound. It is classified as transitional hiccups if it last less than 48 hours, persistent hiccups if it last more than 48 hours, and intractable hipccus if it last longer than 1 month. The acute form is a benign and transient problem, often without known precipitating cause. However, when it is persistent, it is often related to organic causes (digestive, respiratory, cardiac...), sometimes of serious etiology, especially in children with a manifestation of neurological dysfunction. In this cases, their admission to been study is indicated. We present a newborn with a crisis of prolonged and continuous hiccups accompanied by respiratory dysfunction, associated with moderate gastro-esophageal reflux, condition is not mentioned so far associated with neonatal persistent hiccups. We establish the differential diagnosis of neonatal persistent hiccups, little reported in the medical literature(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa Romero, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hoyos Vázquez, M. P. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Serrano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balmaseda Serrano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Monzón, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hipo se define como contracciones espasmódicas, súbitas, involuntarias e intermitentes del diafragma. Se asocia al cierre anticipado y abrupto de la glotis, haciendo terminar la inspiración, y origina un sonido distintivo. Se clasifica en hipo transitorio si dura menos de 48 horas, hipo persistente si dura más de 48 horas, e hipo intratable si dura más de un mes. La forma aguda es un problema benigno y transitorio, la mayoría de las veces sin causa desencadenante conocida. Sin embargo, cuando es persistente suele relacionarse con causas orgánicas (digestivas, respiratorias, cardiacas...), en ocasiones de etiología grave, sobre todo en niños como una manifestación de una disfunción neurológica, por lo que está indicado el ingreso del paciente para su estudio. Presentamos el caso de un recién nacido con una crisis de hipo prolongada y continua, acompañada de disfunción respiratoria, asociada a un reflujo gastroesofágico moderado, patología no relacionada hasta ahora con el hipo persistente neonatal. Establecemos el diagnóstico diferencial del hipo persistente neonatal, poco referido en la literatura médica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;70(3): 115-119, mar. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflujo gastroesofágico neonatal: presentación como crisis de hipo persistente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6765^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12548^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
