<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049675</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malignant fibrous histiocytoma (undifferentiated high grade pleomorphic sarcoma) arising in a gouty tophus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gout is a uric acid metabolism disorder that is able toproduce severe joint injuries. We describe a case of a 76year old man with a history of acute gout attacks during 30years and tophaceous deposits in hands and feet. After aquick growth of a tophus located in his left hand dorsal 2ndand 3rd metacarpophalangical joint, radiological studieswere done. An image compatible with destructive uric aciddeposit illness was shown. Resection was made, findingtendons affected which made necessary 2nd finger amputation.Surgical specimen showed two differentiated areas: ayellowish and granular corresponding to the typical tophaceousdeposit and other fleshy and white corresponding to ahigh grade malignant fusocellular proliferation. Immunohistochemicalstudies showed only positivity for CD68 andlysozime in tumoral cells. The diagnosis of malignantfibrous histiocytoma associated to gouty tophus was made.Residual tumor was found after reintervention, and thepatient was sent to the Oncology Service for adjuvant radioand chemotherapy. Five months later, the patient was reoperatedfor recurrence of the tumor in the left arm, staying freeof disease at these moments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Higuera, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Mies, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de la Parte, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terán Saavedra, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarría Iturbe, Celina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Osés, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La gota es una enfermedad por alteración del metabolismodel ácido úrico que puede producir graves lesiones articulares.Presentamos un caso clínico correspondiente a unvarón de 76 años con episodios de gota aguda desde hace 30años y presencia de tofos gotosos en manos y pies. Debidoal crecimiento rápido del tofo situado en la región dorsal dela articulación metacarpofalángica del 2.º y 3.er dedo de lamano izquierda, se hicieron estudios de imagen, observándoseuna imagen radiológica compatible con enfermedad dedepósito. Se procede a resecar la lesión, siendo necesaria laamputación del 2.º dedo por afectación de sus tendones. Enel examen de la pieza, se observaron dos zonas diferenciadas,una amarillenta y granular que microscópicamentecorrespondía a un típico tofo gotoso y otra zona blanquecinay carnosa que correspondía a una proliferación fusocelularmaligna de alto grado que inmunohistoquímicamentesólo expresaba CD68 y lisozima. Con estos hallazgos sehizo el diagnóstico de fibrohistiocitoma maligno sobre tofogotoso. El paciente fue reintervenido, encontrándose tumorresidual, remitiéndose al servicio de Oncología donde fuetratado con radioterapia y quimioterapia adyuvante. A los 5meses fue reintervenido por una recidiva en el antebrazoizquierdo, encontrándose actualmente libre de enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;39(2): 113-116, abr.-jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049675</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fibrohistiocitoma maligno (sarcoma pleomórfico indiferenciado de alto grado) sobre tofo gotoso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5520^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6223^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31407^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8254^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
