<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048364</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunohistochemical profile and clinical features of mucinous tubular and spindle renal cell carcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: We present the immunohistochemical (IHC) analyses of a series of four kidney tumors currently        classified as mucinous tubular and spindle renal cell carcinoma (WHO), a tumor with uncertain histogenesis and        differentiation. Our aims were to determine an immunoprofile and to add clinical and morphological information        about this rare renal carcinoma.        Material and methods: The four tumors were found between 415 renal carcinomas at our center (0.89%). IHC        was carried out with a panel of antibodies in these four cases. Morphogical and clinical information was collected        and analyzed.        Results: All tumors were well circumscribed and confined to the kidney. Immunoreactivity for cytokeratin        (CK)7 was intense and diffuse. Immunostaining was variable for EMA, vimentin, S-100, Ulex europaeus antigen,        high-molecular-weight CK, CK 8, CK18, and CK 19. The tumors were homogeneously negative for CEA, CD15,        CD10, CD34, desmin, actin, CK10, CK20, and HMB45. Proliferative index (Ki67) was &lt;1% en all cases. The immunoreactivity        was similar in cuboidal and spindle cells.        Conclusions: The present tumor shows a variable immunophenotype and there is not a precise cell type differentiation.        The immunostaining in cuboidal and spindle cells suggests a similar differentiation and histogenesis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bocardo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El carcinoma renal mucinoso y tubular de células fusiformes es una neoplasia recientemente        incluida en la clasificación de tumores renales. Aún desconocemos aspectos moleculares y de su evolución.        Nuestros objetivos son describir características inmunofenotípicas del tumor y aportar casos adicionales para un        mejor conocimiento de la neoplasia.        Material y métodos: Realizamos inmunohistoquímica con un amplio panel de anticuerpos a 4 tumores (0,89%        de carcinomas renales en nuestro centro). Correlacionamos con hallazgos clínicos y tratamos de determinar patrones        de inmunotinción.        Resultados: Todos los casos marcaron intensa y difusamente para citoqueratina (CK)7. La inmunotinción fue        variable para antígeno de membrana epitelial, vimentina, S-100, antígeno Ulex europaeus, CK de alto peso molecular,        CK8, CK18 y CK19. Los tumores fueron homogéneamente negativos para antígeno carcinoembriónico,        CD15, CD10, CD34, desmina, actina, CK10, CK20 y HMB45. El índice proliferativo (Ki67) fue menor del 1% en        todos los casos. La marcación fue similar en células cúbicas y fusiformes.        Conclusiones: Este tumor presenta un inmunofenotipo variable de acuerdo con diferentes trabajos y no se        conoce con precisión su histogénesis o la célula hacia la cual se diferencian. La similitud en la expresión de marcadores        en células cúbicas y fusiformes confirma un mismo origen y diferenciación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(7): 649-654, jul.-ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048364</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características inmunofenotípicas y clínicas del carcinoma renal mucinoso tubular y de células fusiformes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31806^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31806^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23422^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31529^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31529^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
