<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137555</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of a relational frame theory account of psychological flexibility in young children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Acceptance and commitment therapy (ACT) is a contextual behavior therapy based on relational frame theory (RFT), a functional contextual approach to human language and cognition. The main aim of ACT is to promote psychological flexibility, which has been defined in middle-level terms. The current study proposes that a recently developed RFT account of psychological flexibility might facilitate the adaptation of ACT to the work with young children. Method: A case study with a 5-year-old boy presenting problematic anger is presented to illustrate the previous suggestion. The intervention consisted of a brief ACT protocol applied in four, 20-min sessions and a token economy at the service of promoting psychological flexibility. The ACT protocol involved a multipleexemplar training in framing own ongoing experiences through deictic and hierarchical relations and transforming the discriminative functions of those experiences by relating them to rules that progressively specified longer term and symbolic, positive consequences. Results: The intervention was shown to be highly effective in reducing the anger episodes, and the results were maintained during the one year of follow-up. Conclusions: This study supports the feasibility of the RFT account of psychological flexibility to adapt ACT to the work with young children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Francisco J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perete, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la terapia de aceptación y compromiso (ACT) es una terapia contextual basada en la teoría del marco relacional (RFT), una aproximación funcional-contextual al lenguaje y la cognición. El objetivo de ACT es incrementar la flexibilidad psicológica, que ha sido definida en términos de nivel medio. Este estudio propone que una aproximación a la flexibilidad psicológica basada en la RFT podría facilitar la adaptación de ACT en el trabajo con niños. Método: se presenta un estudio de caso con un niño de 5 años con ira problemática tratado con un protocolo de ACT aplicado en cuatro sesiones de 20 minutos y una economía de fichas al servicio de promover flexibilidad psicológica. El protocolo consistió en un entrenamiento en múltiples ejemplos en enmarcar la propia experiencia en curso a través de relaciones deícticas y jerárquicas y transformar sus funciones discriminativas al relacionarla con reglas que progresivamente especificaban consecuencias positivas, simbólicas y a más largo plazo. Resultados: la intervención mostró ser altamente eficaz en reducir los episodios de ira, manteniéndose los resultados durante el año de seguimiento. Conclusiones: este estudio apoya la viabilidad de la aproximación a la flexibilidad psicológica basada en la RFT para adaptar ACT en el trabajo con niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);27(2): 114-119, mayo 2015. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137555</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de una aproximación a la flexibilidad psicológica basada en la teoría del marco relacional en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
