<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91692</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hemodynamic monitoring. An essential examination in severely ill children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular system monitoring is essential for the diagnosis, treatment and evolutive control of different path physiological conditions in critically ill pediatric patients. This monitoring includes the evaluation of cardiac output through the variables that measure it, and peripheral perfusion and tissue oxygenation. Thus, the clinical interpretation of the hemodynamic variables of the patient is complemented with different and more or less complex techniques, chosen according to the pathophysiology and severity of the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Bouzas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Flores, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La monitorización del sistema cardiovascular es fundamental para el diagnóstico, tratamiento y control evolutivo de diferentes situaciones fisiopatológicas en los pacientes pediátricos críticos. Esta monitorización comprende la evaluación del gasto cardíaco a través de las variables que lo determinan, así como de la perfusión periférica y de la oxigenación tisular, para ello la interpretación clínica de las variables hemodinámicas del paciente se complementa con diversas técnicas más o menos complejas, elegidas en función de la fisiopatología y gravedad del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;66(1): 10-17, ene.-feb. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91692</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización hemodinámica. Una exploración imprescindible en los niños graves</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2346^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
