<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147029</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in allergies registration done by healthcare professionals in a third level hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The purpose of the study is to quantify the degree of coincidence in the allergies registered in the different computer applications available to each healthcare professional (doctors, nursing staff and pharmacists). Methods: It was conducted a three- month retrospective descriptive and observational study which included the participation of all Clinical Units with Medication Dispensing System in Single Doses. All in-patients with, at least, one allergy registered in any of the three computer applications used by the different healthcare professionals were included in the study. The percentage of allergies registered in one, two or three of the available applications was quantified. Results: 767 patients were included, among whom 1,257 allergies were recorded. The average age was 59 years and 60.76% were women. 70.09% of the recorded allergies were drug-related. The majority of allergies were just registered through the nursing application (36.67%). The percentage of allergies recorded by the three kinds of healthcare professionals was 7.88%. Differentiating the type of allergy, only 0.80% of non drug-related allergies were registered simultaneously by all three healthcare professionals in comparison with 10.90% of drug-related allergies. Medical staff recorded 59.29% of drug-related allergies and 10.65% of non drug-related allergies. Discussion: There is a high variability in the recording of allergies by the healthcare professionals and also a lack of concordance in those recorded by each type of professional. Medical staff only recorded 10% of non drug-related allergies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrari, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo del estudio es cuantificar el grado de coincidencia en las alergias registradas en las distintas aplicaciones informáticas disponibles para cada profesional sanitario (médicos, personal de enfermería y farmacéuticos). Métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo retrospectivo de 3 meses de duración en el que participaron todas las Unidades Clínicas con Sistema de Distribución de Medicamentos en Dosis Unitarias. Se incluyeron a todos los pacientes ingresados con al menos una alergia registrada en cualquiera de las tres aplicaciones informáticas utilizadas por los distintos profesionales sanitarios. Se cuantificaron el porcentaje de alergias registradas en una, dos o tres aplicaciones disponibles. Resultados: Se incluyeron 767 pacientes en los que se registraron 1.257 alergias. La mediana de edad fue 59 años y el 60,76% eran mujeres. El 70,09% de las alergias registradas fueron farmacológicas. El registro de alergias únicamente a través de la aplicación de enfermería fue el más frecuente (36,67%). El porcentaje de alergias registradas por los tres profesionales sanitarios fue el 7,88%. Haciendo distinción en el tipo de alergia, solamente el 0,80% de las alergias no farmacológicas fueron registradas simultáneamente por los tres profesionales sanitarios frente al 10,90% de las farmacológicas. El personal médico contribuyó al registro del 59,29% de las alergias farmacológicas y del 10,65% de las no farmacológicas. Discusión: Existe una gran variabilidad en el registro de alergias por parte del personal sanitario y escasa concordancia en las registradas por cada tipo de profesionales. El personal médico únicamente registró una décima parte de las alergias no farmacológicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;17(6): 732-744, 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147029</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad en el registro de alergias por profesionales sanitarios en un hospital de tercer nivel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29564^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29564^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53713^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53713^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53713^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53392^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53392^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53392^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53713^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4404^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53392^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
