<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140798</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of biofilm eradication in endodontics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Biofilms are complex systems where bacteria are able to organize, becoming more resistant to the attack of antimicrobials, being very difficult their elimination. Bacteria in nature are found in a 99% forming biofilms, so we have to understand that knowing how to eradicate them will be the key, not only in endodontics, otherwise in all other disciplines. The best way and what are the best endodontic irrigants have been investigated to get the biofilms eradication. The sodium hypochlorite, because of its capability of tissue dissolution, it is able to disorganize the internal structure of biofilms and all the checked studies confirms it as the best endodontic irrigant; passive ultrasonic irrigation, laser and photodynamic therapy, are big allies acting as adjuvants in biofilms eradication. This bibliographic revision helps us to understand how we must get biofilms elimination instead of isolated bacteria; E. faecalis is the most common bacteria found in endodontic failure, having a lot of virulence factors and a high resistance mediated by biofilm creation. Adequate irrigation with sodium hypochlorite and the use of calcium chelants like EDTA will improve the bacterial eradication inside the root canals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mena Álvarez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Álvarez, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Martín, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los biofilms bacterianos son sistemas complejos en los que las bacterias son capaces de organizarse, logrando así una mayor resistencia a los ataques antimicrobianos siendo mucho más difícil su erradicación. Las bacterias se encuentran en un 99% de las ocasiones formando biopelículas o biofilms, por tanto el conocimiento de cómo poder eliminarlos será la clave, no sólo en endodoncia, sino en cualquier disciplina. Se ha investigado cómo es la mejor manera y cuáles son los mejores irrigantes en endodoncia para conseguir eliminar los biofilms intrarradiculares. El hipoclorito sódico, debido a su capacidad inherente de disolución del tejido, es capaz de desorganizar la estructura de los biofilms y los estudios revisados lo colocan como el mejor irrigante en endodoncia; la irrigación ultrasónica pasiva, el uso del láser y la terapia fotodinámica, son grandes aliados que actúan como coadyuvantes en la erradicación del biofilm. Esta revisión bibliográfica nos ayuda a comprender cómo debemos centrarnos en la eliminación de los biofilms y no de bacterias aisladas; el E. faecalis es la bacteria principalmente relacionada con el fracaso endodóntico, poseyendo muchos factores de virulencia y una resistencia mediada por la formación de biofilms. una adecuada irrigación con hipoclorito sódico (NaOCl) y el uso de quelantes del calcio como el ácido etilendiamino-tetracético (EDTA) mejorará sobremanera la erradicación bacteriana dentro de los conductos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);12(1): 39-44, ene.-abr. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La importancia del biofilm y su eliminación en endodoncia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12763^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3788^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30421^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
