<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97702</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pansinusitis and intracranial impact of a dental implant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Odontogenic sinusitis is a relatively common disease caused by dental infections, periapical cysts and oral procedures such as root canal, sinus lift or implant placement. We report an extreme case of a right pansinusitis with an epidural space fistula caused by osseointegrated implants. When maxillary sinusitis of odontogenic origin is suspected, we should quickly start effective antibiotic treatment and monitor the patient closely because odontogenic sinusitis can have serious consequences, such as the loss of an eye, brain abscess or death(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Santamaría, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrés-Padró, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio-Palau, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chávez-Gatty, Mitchel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Linares, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueto-Madrid, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las sinusitis odontógenas son una patología relativamente frecuente causada por infecciones dentales, quistes periapicales así como tras procedimientos bucodentales como una endodoncia, una elevación sinusal o la colocación de un implante. A continuación se presenta un caso extremo de una pansinusitis derecha con fistulización a espacio epidural causada por un implante osteointegrado. Ante la sospecha de una sinusitis maxilar de origen odontogénico se debe iniciar rápidamente un tratamiento antibiótico correcto y un seguimiento estrecho ya que pueden tener consecuencias fatales como la pérdida de un ojo, abscesos cerebrales o incluso la muerte(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;34(1): 35-37, ene.-mar.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97702</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pansinusitis y afectación intracraneal por implante dental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1948^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1948^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31240^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31240^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31240^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31240^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13233^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
