<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137445</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9218</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Omeprazole safety: is the duration of the treatments suitable?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Omeprazole is one of the most prescribed drugs in the Spanish National Health System. Its safety profile is considered to be good, nevertheless there are different adverse reactions described in the summary of product characteristics, some of them, although somewhat rare or very rare, are considered serious. Clinical evidence and recent studies have shown a relationship between continued use of omeprazole and other adverse events. Objectives: To find out how much of the treated population exceeds the duration of treatment, as stated in the Summary of Product Characteristics, for the treatment of reflux esophagitis and what proportion of this population may present potential risk of suffering any adverse reaction in circumstances that they were detected Patients and methods: Multicenter observational study whose data collection was performed in 27 community pharmacies located in 24 towns in the province of Badajoz using a structured questionnaire with five questions related to the use of omeprazole. Results: 60% of the patients studied amply exceed the treatment time to treat gastroesophageal reflux according to the summary of product characteristics. The 39% was in elderly population. The 4.5% of elderly patients who taking omeprazole on high doses for a long period of time (over one year), circumstances that make them more vulnerable to suffer any adverse reactions described (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carranza Caricol, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Omeprazol es uno de los fármacos más prescritos dentro del Sistema Nacional de Salud español. Su perfil de seguridad se considera alto, aunque aparecen descritas en la ficha técnica diferentes reacciones adversas, algunas de ellas, aunque poco o muy poco frecuentes, de carácter grave. Evidencias clínicas y estudios recientes han puesto de manifiesto una relación del uso continuado de omeprazol con otras manifestaciones adversas. Objetivos: Conocer qué parte de la población tratada sobrepasa la duración del tratamiento según lo consignado en la ficha técnica para el tratamiento de la esofagitis por reflujo y qué proporción puede presentar un riesgo potencial de sufrir alguna reacción adversa en las circunstancias en las que se han detectado. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional multicéntrico cuya recogida de datos se efectuó en 27 farmacias comunitarias ubicadas en 24 localidades de la provincia de Badajoz mediante un cuestionario estructurado con cinco preguntas relacionadas con el uso de omeprazol. Resultados: El 60% de los pacientes estudiados sobrepasan ampliamente el tiempo de tratamiento para tratar el reflujo gastroesofágico según la ficha técnica. El porcentaje era del 39% en pacientes de más de 70 años. Un 4,5% de pacientes de edad avanzada llevaba tomando omeprazol a dosis altas durante un tiempo prolongado (más de un año), circunstancia que los hace más vulnerables a sufrir alguna de las reacciones adversas descritas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. comunitarios (Internet);7(1): 5-9, mar. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137445</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad del omeprazol: ¿es adecuada la duración de los tratamientos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52844^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10785^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
