<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132671</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical practice guideline: monosymptomatic primary enuresis in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to elaborate a clinical guide that analyze the evidences and help in the decision making process of prevention, risk factors, diagnosis and treatment of primary monosymptomatic nocturnal enuresis (PMNE). Costs and medical burden was not taken into consideration. Materials and methods: Evidences: a systemathic review answer the key clinical questions about each PMNE point of view. The best evidence described for each of the analysis was  discussed,  and  degrees  of  recommendation  were  stated.  Measurements:  OR  for  risk factors  and  RR  for  treatment  results.  We  only  considered  the  treatment  results  of:  initial success  (14  dry  nights),  complete  dryness  (100%  dry  nights),  complete  response  (&gt;  90% wet nights reduction) and cure (initial success or complete response without relapsing). Results: Prevention: we don&#146;t find evidence. Risk factors: chronic headache, attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), constipation/encopresis and sleep apnoea are associated with an increase frequency of nocturnal enuresis. PMNE has not been associated with either  urinary  tract  infection  or  psychological  problems,  although  persistence  of  enuresis drives  to  low  self-esteem.  Diagnosis:  clinical  presentation,  a  normal  physical  exam  and  a micturitional diary are the basis of diagnosis. Urinary culture or urine strip lack any utility. Treatment:  simple  and  complex  conductual  treatment,  alarm  and  treatment  with  desmopresin were analyzed, as well as the way of weaning the treatment. Prognostic factors of success or treatment failure were analyzed and taken into account when recommending different treatments. Diurnal maximum voided volume, attitude of the child and family to collaboration and their stress, number of wet nights and ADHD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Úbeda Sansano, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Domingo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: elaborar una guía de práctica clínica basada en la evidencia para ayudar a tomar decisiones en la prevención, factores asociados, diagnóstico y tratamiento de la enuresis nocturna primaria monosintomática (ENPM). Los costes y el impacto sobre la asistencia sanitaria de las diferentes alternativas no se han considerado. Material y métodos: evidencias: una revisión sistemática de la bibliografía responde a preguntas clínicas sobre distintos aspectos de la ENPM; medida de los resultados: OR para los factores asociados, RR para los resultados de tratamiento. En éste se valora éxito inicial (14 noches secas), sequedad completa (100% noches secas), respuesta completa (&lt; 90% reducción de noches mojadas) y curación (éxito inicial o respuesta completa sin recaída). Resultados: prevención: no se ha encontrado evidencia; Factores asociados: cefalea crónica, trastorno de déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH), estreñimiento/encopresis y apnea del sueño se asocian con la enuresis nocturna. La ENPM no se asocia con la infección urinaria ni con trastornos psicológicos, aunque la persistencia del problema provoca baja autoestima. Diagnóstico: son básicos la historia clínica, una exploración normal y el diario miccional. El urinocultivo y la tira reactiva de orina no tienen utilidad clínica. Tratamiento: conductual simple y complejo, alarma y tratamiento farmacológico con desmopresina. Se describen los objetivos, asociaciones, dosificación, duración, forma de retirada, actitud ante el fracaso y ventajas e inconvenientes de cada opción terapéutica. Factores de buen o mal pronóstico: son útiles para recomendar los distintos tratamientos: volumen miccional máximo diurno, predisposición a colaborar, existencia de situaciones estresantes, número de noches mojadas/semana y TDAH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;7(supl.3): s7-s151, jul. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía de práctica clínica: enuresis nocturna primaria monosintomática en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52131</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
