<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100551</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to investigate the use of female condom (PF) by sex workers registered with the Municipal Health Department of the municipality of Rio Grande / RS. It is a descriptive and quantitative study, conducted in 2009 with 19 women, through the application of an individual questionnaire containing questions about sexual habits and use of FP. The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the FURG in opinion No. 53/2009. The results found that 47.30% reported that they check their health status regularly, 58% already had contact with this type of condom in the health service and 73.55% claim never to have acquired an STI. Regarding sexual practices 68.45% reported using condoms only to prevent STDs, women who are already using PF practised vaginal sex and 47.30% do not see the advantages and 52.65% do not see the disadvantages of using the PF. It is important then that the health facilities, professionals including nurses, should be prepared to deal with health issues and counsel these women about the importance of condom use for health maintenance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kerber, NP da C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barros, AM de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa, CFS da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wachholz, VA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lemos, DB de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliveira, FS</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tuvo como objetivo investigar el uso del condón femenino (PF) de trabajadoras sexuales registradas en el Departamento Municipal de Salud de la municipalidad de Rio Grande / RS. Es un estudio descriptivo y cuantitativo, realizado en 2009 con 19 mujeres, a través de la aplicación de un cuestionario individual que contiene preguntas sobre los hábitos sexuales y el uso del PF. El estudio fue aprobado por el Comité de Ética de la FURG en opinión N º 53/2009. Los resultados indicaron que 47,30% informó que acompañan a su estado de salud regularmente, el 58% había tenido contacto con este tipo de condones en los servicios de salud y 73,55% no afirman haber adquirido nunca una Infección de Transmisión Sexual (ETS). En cuanto a las prácticas sexuales 68,45% informó del uso de preservativos sólo para prevenir las ETS, las mujeres que ya están utilizando el PF practicaron sexo vaginal y el 47,30% no ve las ventajas y el 52,65% no ve las desventajas en el uso del PF. Es importante entonces que los establecimientos de salud, incluyendo enfermeras profesionales, estén preparados para afrontar los problemas de salud de estas mujeres y asesorarlas sobre la importancia del uso del condón para el mantenimiento de la salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(26): 390-398, abr. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100551</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El uso del preservativo femenino por las profesionales del sexo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3290^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3290^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30772^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30772^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6418^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30772^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30772^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11920^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54390^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
