<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146243</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-031X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testicular fibrous pseudotumour as a rare intrascrotal mass</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Paratesticular fibrous pseudotumor (PFP) is a rare benign tumor that is not a neoplasm but a reactive fibrous inflammatory hyperplasia. Paratesticular fibrous pseudotumor occurs from intrascrotal tissues, such as tunica vaginalis, epididymis, or spermatic cord. Definitive diagnosis requires pathological examination. Radical orchiectomy should be avoided when possible, and local excision should be performed due to the lack of obvious evidence of potential malignancy. Case report. A 61 years old patient was referred to our clinic with complaints of right scrotal mass. Doppler ultrasonography is observed for the right epididymis in the neighborhood of 30 × 26 × 21 mm hypoechoic mass. Tumor markers were negative. Frozen came as negative. Testicular mass was excised with testis preventive approach. Pathology report revealed that paratesticular fibrous pseudotumor. Conclusion. According to this article frozen section should be done in paratesticular masses to avoid unnecessary radical orchiectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serkan Akan, Serkan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haki Yuksel, Ozgur</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ozbay, Nurver</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verit, Ayhan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El seudotumor fibroso paratesticular es un tumor benigno raro que no es una neoplasia sino una hiperplasia o proceso reactivo inflamatorio no tumoral. El seudotumor fibroso paratesticular aparece en el tejido intraescrotal, como la túnica vaginal, epidídimo, o el cordón espermático. El diagnóstico definitivo requiere un examen patológico. Debe evitarse la orquiectomía radical en la medida de lo posible. Asimismo, deberían realizarse escisiones locales en caso de no encontrar una evidencia clara de su potencial malignidad. Informe del caso. Un paciente de 61 años dirigido a nuestra clínica con quejas de una masa en el escroto derecho. Se observa una masa hipoecoica de 30 × 26 × 21 mm en las proximidades del epidídimo derecho durante el examen con ecografía doppler. Los marcadores tumorales fueron negativos. Se realizó biopsia de la masa como procedimiento preventivo testicular. El informe patológico confirmó que se trataba de un seudotumor fibroso paratesticular. Conclusión. De acuerdo con este artículo, la biopsia del tejido congelado debería realizarse en masas paratesticulares para evitar orquiectomías radicales innecesarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. androl. (Ed. impr.);13(4): 138-141, oct.-dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146243</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El seudotumor fibroso testicular como masa rara interescrotal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13468^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12992^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31268^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32953^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13468^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12992^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12992^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6255^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31268^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
