<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114127</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results from the 2012 Paediatric National Survey on Empirical Use of Antibiotics in Children in Spain (ABES Study)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There are currently several national guidelines on the appropriate empirical use of antibiotics in Spanish children. But, do the Spanish paediatricians use these guidelines when prescribing antimicrobials. Material and methods: A national study from was conducted from April to June 2012 using an on-line questionnaire on the empirical selection of antibiotics in children. An e-mail was sent to paediatrician members of the Spanish Association of Paediatrics (AEP) or its Regional or Paediatric Specialties Societies. Current guidelines and consensus documents were used to determine the appropriateness of the responses. Results: A total of 1214 responses were received. Eighty five per cent of the treatments selected by Spanish paediatricians were adjusted to guidelines. The least appropriate responses were obtained in those infectious diseases with no national consensus document at the time of the survey (73% in this case). Conclusions: Spanish paediatricians mainly select empirical antibiotics in accordance with current guidelines. However, there are features that could be improved in our country. The preparing and implementation of national consensus documents on the management of paediatric infectious diseases should be continued. We propose to regularly perform these kinds of surveys, including real prescription studies, and to also extend it to other paediatric specialities, in order to promote appropriateness of use of all the paediatric drugs in our country (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Rey, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Llamazares, C. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mellado Peña, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo Acuña, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Claros, A. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Actualmente existen diversas guías nacionales sobre el uso empírico adecuado de antibióticos en niños. Desconocemos si los pediatras españoles emplean dichas guías al seleccionar antimicrobianos. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal de ámbito nacional, mediante encuesta on-line sobre la selección empírica de antibióticos en niños, enviada por correo electrónico a pediatras socios de la Asociación Española de Pediatría o de sus sociedades de especialidades y regionales, entre abril y junio del 2012. Para considerar la adecuación de las respuestas se tuvieron en cuenta las guías, los documentos de consenso y los protocolos recientes. Resultados: Se recibieron 1.214 respuestas. Los tratamientos seleccionados se ajustan en un 85% a las recomendaciones. Los resultados menos adecuados se obtienen en enfermedades infecciosas en las que no existe un documento de consenso nacional en el momento de realizar la encuesta (73% de adecuación en este caso). Conclusiones: La elección empírica de antibióticos por parte de los pediatras españoles es bastante adecuada a las guías recientes. Sin embargo, la interpretación de los datos debe ser crítica, ya que existen aspectos del manejo racional de antibióticos en niños que podrían mejorar en nuestro país. Se plantea como necesidad continuar con la realización e implementación de documentos de consenso nacionales para el manejo de enfermedades infecciosas pediátricas. Proponemos que este tipo de encuestas se realicen periódicamente, así como análisis similares en otras áreas de capacitación específicas, incluyendo estudios de prescripción real, para promover el uso racional de todos los fármacos pediátricos en nuestro país (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);79(1): 32-41, jul. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114127</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso empírico de antibióticos en niños en España. Resultados de una Encuesta Pediátrica Nacional 2012 (Estudio ABES)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
