<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042035</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benzodiazepine use in Santiago, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. To describe benzodiazepine use in the adult population from Santiago, Chile and attempt to establish associations with different sociodemographic and medical variables.Methods. This is a cross-sectional study whose sampling frame was the adult population, aged 16 to 64 years (n = 3,237,286). The sampling strategy was probabilistic, poly-stage and stratified.Results. A total of 3,870 persons were interviewed. Prevalence of benzodiazepine use was 3.84 %. Statistically significant associations were found between benzodiazepine use and gender, age, marital status, income, presence of a common mental disorder and health perception.Discussion. Training of the general practitioner to regulate the use of benzodiazepine is necessary</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fritsch Montero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaete Olivares, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araya Baltra, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rubio, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas astillo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se quiere describir el consumo de benzodiazepinas en la población adulta del Gran Santiago e intentar establecer asociaciones con diferentes variables sociodemográficas y médicas.Métodos. Se trata de un estudio transversal que utilizó como marco muestral la población adulta entre 16 y 64 años del Gran Santiago (n = 3.237.286) y un diseño muestral probabilístico, polietápico y estratificado.Resultados. Se entrevistaron a 3.870 personas que tuvieron una prevalencia de consumo de benzodiazepinas de un 3,84 %. Se encontraron asociaciones estadísticamente significativas entre consumo de benzodiazepinas y sexo, edad, estado civil, ingresos, presencia de un trastorno mental común y percepción de enfermedad.Discusión. Se hace necesaria una capacitación de los médicos generales para regular el consumo de benzodiazepinas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(5): 286-291, sept.-oct. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de benzodiazepinas en la población general del Gran Santiago de Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
