<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045803</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intra-alveolar Chlorhexidine gel for the prevention of dry socket in mandibular third molar surgery. A pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: Chlorhexidine is a good prophylactic agent for post-extraction dry socket alveolitis. The bio-adhesive 0.2% chlorhexidine        gel could improve this action since its intra-alveolar positioning would allow a more direct action on the alveolus and more prolonged action of the medication.        Materials and Method: We present a single blind, randomised study on 30 patients to evaluate the efficacy of the bio-adhesive 0.2% chlorhexidine gel, placed only once within the alveolus, on the reduction of the incidence of impacted third molar post-extraction dry socket alveolitis and its post-operative effects on patients. Results. A reduction of 42.65% in the occurrence of alveolitis and a more favourable post-operative period in the experimental group was observed. In the control group, the appearance of alveolitis was 30.76% opposite to 17.64 % in the experimental group. Conclusions: The bio-adhesive 0.2% chlorhexidine gel, applied only once after the extraction of impacted third molars, seems to be an appropriate option for the reduction of alveolitis. It improves the buccal aperture and oedema in the post-operative period, although further double blind studies with larger samples are necessary</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Infante Cossio, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Lagares, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutierrez Perez, Jose Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Ruiz, Manuel Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Calderon, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrera Figallo, Maria Angeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La clorhexidina es un buen agente profiláctico de la alveolitis post-extracción. La aparición del gel bioadhesivo        conteniendo clorhexidina al 0,2% podría mejorar esta acción. Su colocación intraalveolar permitiría una actuación más directa sobre el alveolo y una actuación más prolongada del fármaco.        Pacientes y método: Presentamos un estudio a simple ciego, randomizado, sobre 30 pacientes, valorando la influencia de la colocación en una sola vez y de forma intraalveolar gel bioadhesivo conteniendo clorhexidina al 0,2% tras la extracción de terceros molares incluidos, en la aparición de alveolitis y en el postoperatorio de los pacientes. Resultados: Encontramos una reducción del 42,65% en la tasa de alveolitis y un postoperatorio más favorable en el grupo experimental. En el grupo control, la alveolitis apareció en un 30,76% frente a un 17,64 % en el grupo experimental. Discusión y conclusiones: Tras comparar nuestros datos con otros estudio, pensamos que el gel bioadhesivo de clorhexidina al 0,2%, aplicado en una sola vez de forma intraalveolar parece ser una opción adecuada para la prevención de la alveolitis. Esta actuación mejora la apertura bucal y el edema en el postoperatorio, aunque son necesarios nuevos estudios realizados a doble ciego y con muestras más amplias para confirmar nuestros datos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(2): E179-E184, mar.-abr. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045803</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gel de Clorhexidina intra-alveolar en la prevención de la alveolitis tras la extracción de terceros molares inferiores. Estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4426^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14476^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2755^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4426^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d540</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9154</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
