<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044854</identifier>
<setSpec>0378-4835</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebellum glioblastoma. Clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Glioblastoma is the mostfrequent and malignant of the brain tumours.However, it is exceptionally observed in thecerebellum.Clinical case: A case of a 42 year old womanwith a short history of gait disturbance andheadache is reported. A MRI brain scan showed a 4cm diameter, solid and cystic tumour with edema inthe right cerebellum.Surgery removed a glioblastoma multiforme witha positive p53.Conclusions: Age and positive p53 indicatethat it is a secondary form. Bibliography certifiesthat it is an infrequent location. Initial treatment issurgery, but survival is short in spite of radiotherapyand chemotherapy with temozolamide</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pallarés Quixal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguas Valiente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogués Bara, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El glioblastoma multiforme(GBM) es el más frecuente y maligno de los tumorescerebrales. Su presentación en cerebelo es excepcional.Caso clínico: Paciente de 42 años con historiabreve de trastorno de la marcha y cefalea.La resonancia magnética cerebral mostró una lesiónde unos 4 cm de diámetro sólida y quística, conedema, en hemisferio cerebeloso dcho. Se extirpóun Glioblastoma multiforme con p53 positiva.Conclusiones: La edad y la p53 hacen pensarque se trate de una forma secundaria de GBM.La bibliografía revisada constata que se trata deuna localización infrecuente.El tratamiento inicial es quirúrgico pero las supervivenciasson cortas a pesar de la radioterapia ydel uso de nuevos quimioterápicos como la Temozolomida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Oncologia;29(3): 129-133, mar. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Glioblastoma cerebeloso. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3404^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29089^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2565^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31846^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
