<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79227</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personalizing nursing care. An action research approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To evaluate the nursing care personalization process in hospitalization units. Methods: An action research was performed at hospitalization units selected by a convenience sample which guaranteed to carry it out. This process took five phases: approach and awareness, induction, interaction, implementation, and systematization.  Results: 18 units started the personalization process but 2 did not finish it. A synthesis of the most relevant results from each phase is presented, including the arguments to make professionals participate in this action research, qualities needed to provide a humanized care, difficulties and facilities, targets, strategies and evaluation of this nursing care personalization process.  Conclusion: Action research let professionals improved the personalization of the nursing care they provide at their hospitalization units, from strategies adapted to their particular contexts so as to advance to the targets they expected(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Alonso, Sergio R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueso Montoro, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gala Fernández, Bienvenida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Hernández, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Gómez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amezcua, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar el proceso de personalización de cuidados en unidades hospitalarias. Material y método: se llevó a cabo una investigación acción participativa en unidades de hospitalización seleccionadas mediante muestreo por conveniencia conforme a unos criterios que garantizaban llevarla a cabo. El proceso constó de cinco etapas: acercamiento y sensibilización, inducción, interacción, implementación, y sistematización. Resultados: 18 unidades iniciaron el proceso de personalización aunque dos no terminaron. Se presenta una síntesis de los resultados más destacados en cada etapa, tales como los argumentos usados en la sensibilización de los profesionales para su participación, las cualidades para proporcionar un cuidado humanizado, así como las dificultades y facilitadores, los objetivos, y las estrategias para personalizar el cuidado, además de su evaluación.  Conclusiones: la investigación acción participativa ha permitido a los profesionales mejorar la personalización de los cuidados en sus unidades hospitalarias, partiendo de estrategias adaptadas a sus contextos particulares para acercarse a los objetivos que se marcaron(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(3): 178-185, mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79227</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La investigación acción participativa. Un enfoque para personalizar los cuidados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31707^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13247^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11757^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11750^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16871</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11757^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13247^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
