<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040079</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antibacterial activity of cerein 8A, a bacteriocin-like peptide produced by Bacillus cereus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mode of action of cerein 8A, a bacteriocin produced by the soil bacterium Bacillus cereus 8A, was investigated. The effect of cerein 8A was tested against Listeria monocytogenes and a bactericidal effect at 400 arbitrary units (AU)/ml was observed. In addition, cerein 8A was bactericidal against Bacillus cereus at 200 AU/ml, and inhibited the growth of Escherichia coli and Salmonella Enteritidis. Stronger inhibition of these gram-negative bacteria was achieved when the chelating agent EDTA was added together with bacteriocin. The effect of cerein 8A on B. cereus and L. monocytogenes was also investigated by Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR). Treated cells had an important frequency increase at 2920 cm-1 and a decrease at 1400 cm-1, corresponding to assignments of fatty acids. Transmission electron microscopy showed damaged cell walls and loss of protoplasmic material. These results suggest that the mode of action of cerein 8A is to interfere with cell membranes and the cell wall (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morrissy, Juliana AC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brandelli, Adriano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bizani, Delmar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terra, Renata MS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto, André A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Motta, Amanda S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se investigó el modo de acción de la cereína 8A, una bacteriocina producida por la bacteria del suelo Bacillus cereus 8A. El efecto de la cereína 8A fue probado contra Listeria monocytogenes, obteniendo un efecto bactericida a concentraciones de 400 unidades arbitrarias (AU)/ml. La cereína 8A también tuvo un efecto bactericida contra Bacillus cereus a una concentración de 200 AU/ml. La bacteriocina inhibió el crecimiento de Escherichia coli y Salmonella Enteritidis. Mayor inhibición contra estas bacterias gram-negativas se consiguió cuando a la bacteriocina se le añadió el agente quelante EDTA. El efecto de la cereína 8A sobre B. cereus y L. monocytogenes también fue investigado por espectroscopía de infrarrojos de transformación de Fourier (FTIR). Las células tratadas mostraron un importante crecimiento en frecuencia de 2920 cm-1 y un decrecimiento de 1400 cm-1 de banda, correspondiéndose con la asignación de los ácidos grasos. La microscopía electrónica de transmisión mostró que las células habían padecido daños en la pared celular, con pérdida de material protoplásmico. Los resultados sugieren que el modo de acción de la cereína 8A se produce mediante su intervención en las membranas celulares y en la pared celular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;8(2): 125-131, jun. 2005. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040079</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad antibacteriana de la cereína 8A, un péptido de tipo bacteriocina producido por Bacillus cereus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33096^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8262^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8262^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1433^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1453^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10648^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
