<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85149</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vascular risk factors in HIV-infected patients in a penitentiary center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. There is little data regarding vascular risk factors (VRF) in HIV-infected inmates. In this study, we have studied the prevalence of VRF in HIV-infected patients, analyzing the differences with a non-infected population. Patients and method. HIV-infected inmates (n=80) and two non-HIV controls selected for each patient and matched for age and sex (n=160) were included in a descriptive cross-sectional study. We analyzed the VRF, and risk was assessed according to the SCORE, Framingham and REGICOR functions. Results. In the studied population (mean age: 38.1 years; 92.5% men), HIV-infected patients had a significantly higher prevalence of cigarette smoking (97.5 vs 78.8%), diabetes (8.8 vs 1.3%), serum triglycerides&gt;150mg/dl (43.8 vs 26.3%), low HDL-cholesterol levels (61.3 vs 40.6%), HCV infection (87.5 vs 22.5%), and cocaine consumption (77.5 vs 39.4%). The non-infected group had significantly higher prevalence of total cholesterol&gt;200mg/dl and/or LDL-cholesterol &gt;130mg/dl (45.6 vs 28.8%), obesity (14.4 vs 2.5%), sedentary lifestyle (67.5 vs 42.5%) and increased waist circumference (14.4 vs 3.8%). All the evaluated inmates were considered to be at a low risk by SCORE and REGICOR, and 1.3% to be at a high risk by Framingham in both groups. Conclusion. The prevalence of VRF in HIV-infected patients of the studied prison was much higher to that of the HIV-negative subjects. However, the estimation of the cardiovascular risk was low(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vera-Remartínez, E. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mínguez Gallego, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ródenas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Guerrero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rincón, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Los factores de riesgo vascular (FRV) en pacientes penitenciarios infectados por el VIH (VIH+) no se conocen en toda su extensión. Hemos estudiado la prevalencia de estos factores en pacientes VIH+, en comparación con una población no infectada (VIH&#150;). Pacientes y método. Estudio descriptivo transversal en el que se incluyeron pacientes VIH+ (n=80) de un centro penitenciario. Por cada paciente se analizaron dos internos VIH&amp;#8722;, emparejados por edad y sexo (n=160). Se analizaron los FRV, y se estimó el riesgo vascular según las funciones de SCORE, Framingham y REGICOR. Resultados. Los 80 pacientes seleccionados (92,5% varones) tenían una edad media de 38,1 años. Los enfermos VIH+ presentaron una prevalencia significativamente mayor de tabaquismo (97,5 frente al 78,8%), infección por el VHC (87,5 frente al 22,5%), consumo de cocaína (77,5 frente al 39,4%), niveles bajos de colesterol-HDL (61,3 frente al 40,6%), triglicéridos elevados (43,8 frente al 26,3%), y diabetes mellitus (8,8 frente al 1,3%) que los internos VIH&amp;#8722;. Entre los VIH&amp;#8722; hubo significativamente más pacientes con niveles de colesterol total &gt;200 mg/dl y/o colesterol-LDL &gt;130 mg/dl (45,6 vs. 28,8%), con obesidad (14,4 vs. 2,5%), sedentarismo (67,5 vs. 42,5%) y con un perímetro abdominal de riesgo (14,4 vs. 3,8%). Todos los internos tuvieron una estimación de riesgo bajo según las ecuaciones SCORE y REGICOR, tan solo un 1,3%, según la ecuación de Framingham, mostraron un riesgo elevado. Conclusiones. La prevalencia de los FRV en los pacientes VIH+ del centro penitenciario estudiado fue muy superior a la de los sujetos VIH&amp;#8722;. Sin embargo, la estimación del riesgo vascular fue reducida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;211(1): 9-16, ene.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85149</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo vascular en pacientes infectados por el VIH en un centro penitenciario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
