<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138875</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-0771</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Common controversies in total knee replacement Surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Total knee replacement (TKR) is an operation that has radically improved the quality of life of millions of people during the last decades. However, some technical details, concerning the surgical  procedure, are still a matter of a strong debate. In  this review of the literature, we have included the  best evidence available of the last decade, related to  TKR surgery like the use of tourniquet during operation,  patellar resufacing, all-polyethilene tibial component, cemented or cementless fixation, mobile bearings, or posterior-stabilized versus  cruciateretaining prosthesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent Peris, V. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensio Pascual, A. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domecq Fernández de Bobadilla, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artroplastia total de rodilla (ATR) es una operación que ha mejorado radicalmente la calidad de vida de millones de personas en las últimas décadas. Sin embargo, algunos detalles técnicos, relativos al procedimiento quirúrgico, son todavía un tema de fuerte debate. En esta revisión de  la literatura se ha incluido la mejor evidencia al respecto de la última década, sobre algunos de los temas más controvertidos de este procedimiento como  el uso de torniquete,  gestos  quirúrgicos sobre la rótula, bandeja tibial toda de polietileno (all-poly) o con respaldo metálico, la fijación cementada o sin cementar, el uso de platillos móviles, ó la conservación / sustitución del ligamento cruzado posterior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Andal. Traumatol. Ortop. (Ed. impr.);32(1): 9-24, ene.-jun. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Controversias en artroplastia total de rodilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1868^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14504^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32333^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33578^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29086^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
