<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151372</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Robot-assisted partial nephrectomy in 95 consecutive patients: Oncological and functional outcomes at 3 years of follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: We present the oncological and functional results from a series of 43 patients with renal tumours, treated consecutively with robot-assisted partial nephrectomy (RPN). Materials and method: Between 2010 and 2014, we performed 95 RPNs. To assess the results, we included only those patients (n = 43) who had a minimum follow-up of 2 years. A descriptive analysis was conducted of the demographic characteristics and perioperative variables. We employed Kaplan-Meier curves to assess overall survival, cancer-specific survival and recurrence-free survival. Results: The patients&#146; mean age was 53.1 ± 13.5 years. The mean preoperative tumour size was 3.7 ± 2.3 cm. The mean surgical time was 102.2 ± 37.1 min. The mean ischemia time was 21.27 ± 7.74 minutes, with a median intraoperative bleeding volume of 150 mL (IQR, 87.5-425). There was a 7% rate of postoperative complications (Clavien &amp;#8805; III). There was no mortality. The average Fürhman grade was 2.5 ± 0.56. There were no positive surgical margins or local recurrences. The median follow-up was 38 ± 8 months, with an overal survival, recurrence-free survival and cancer-specific survival of 100% at 3 years of follow-up. The recurrence-free survival was 92,3% at 48 months of follow-up. The mean preoperative glomerular filtration rate was 91.04 ± 28.17 mL/min/1.73 m2, and the postoperative rate was 89.9 ± 27.69 mL/min/1.73 m2, with a nonsignificant reduction (P = .74). Conclusions: The functional and oncological results of our series confirm the safety and efficacy of RPN. RPN offers optimal preservation of renal function and oncological control in the medium term (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, OA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borgna, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Carlin, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Presentamos los resultados oncológicos y funcionales de una serie de 43 pacientes afectos de un tumor renal, tratados en forma consecutiva mediante nefrectomía parcial robótica (NPR). Material y método: Entre los años 2010 y 2014 efectuamos 95 NPR. Para la evaluación de los resultados se incluyeron solo a los pacientes (n = 43) que tuvieran un seguimiento mínimo de 2 años. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo de las características demográficas y variables perioperatorias. Se utilizaron curvas de Kaplan-Meier para evaluar la supervivencia global, supervivencia cáncer-específica y supervivencia libre de recurrencia. Resultados: La edad media fue 53,1 ± 13,5 años. El tamaño tumoral preoperatorio fue 3,7 ± 2,3 cm. El tiempo quirúrgico fue 102,2 ± 37,1 min. El tiempo de isquemia fue de 21,27 ± 7,74 min con una mediana de sangrado intraoperatorio de 150 ml (RIC = 87,5-425). Hubo un 7% de complicaciones postoperatorias Clavien &amp;#8805; III. No hubo mortalidad. El grado de Fürhman promedio fue 2,5 ± 0,56. No hubo márgenes quirúrgicos positivos ni recurrencia local. La mediana de seguimiento fue 38 ± 8 meses, con una supervivencia global, una supervivencia libre de recurrencia y una supervivencia cáncer específica del 100% a 3 años de seguimiento. La supervivencia libre de recurrencia fue del 92,3% a 48 meses de seguimiento. La media de filtración glomerular preoperatoria fue 91,04 ± 28,17 y la postoperatoria 89,9 ± 27,69 ml/min por 1,73 m2, con una disminución no significativa (p = 0,74). Conclusiones: Los resultados funcionales y oncológicos de nuestra serie de NPR, confirman su seguridad y eficacia. La NPR ofrece una óptima preservación de la función renal y control oncológico a mediano plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;40(4): 217-223, mayo 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nefrectomía parcial robótica en 95 pacientes consecutivos: resultados oncológicos y funcionales a 3 años de seguimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9592^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9592^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9592^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
