<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124326</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Young people dating violence surveillance in Madrid, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Dating violence in young adults is an important public health issue because of itsmagnitude and impact on health. The goal of this study is to determine the prevalence 12 months before the survey by sex and its association with socio-demographic and health risk behavior. Methods: Data were drawn from the Non-communicable Disease Risk-Factor Surveillance Systemin young people (Spanish acronym, SIVFRENT- J), on a representative sample of students of the fourth-year of secondary education (15 to 16 years) inMadrid Region. The students were asked whether they had ever suffered any physical violence (PV) and/or sexual violence (SV) dating episodes. Prevalence with 95% confidence intervals (CI95%) of the occurrence of such episodes were estimated; generalized linear models with binomial family and logarithmic link were used to estimate the association between physical and/or sexual violence (PSV) and health risk behavior through prevalence ratios (PR, CI95%). Results: In 1713 dating girls and 1664 dating boys, the prevalence of PV was 2.9% (CI95%:2.0-3.9) and 4.0% (CI95%:2.9-5.0) (p&gt;0.05), SV 5.3% (CI95%:4.1-6.5) and 2.4% (CI95%:1.6-3.2) (p&lt; 0.001) and PSV 7.1% (CI95%:5.6-8.6) and 5.1% (CI95%:4.0-6.3) (p&lt;0.05) in that order. In the girls explanatory model, PSV was associated with eating disorders PR:1.74 (CI95%:1.14-2.66), sexual risk behavior (SRB), PR:1.67 (CI95%:1.11-2.50), excessive alcohol consumption, PR:1.57 (CI95%:1.06-2.34) and worse perceived health, PR:1.67 (CI95%:1.08-2.57). In boys, PSV was associated with having been born in a country other than Spain, PR:2.05 (CI95%:1.32-3.18), eating disorders, PR:2.79 (CI95%:1.58-4.92), SRB, PR:2.22 (CI95%:1.34- 3.66) and drug consumption, PR:2.14 (CI95%:1.39-3.28). Conclusion: VFS was higher in girls and was associated to others health risk factors with similar characteristics according to sex (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pichiule Castañeda, Myriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordobás Gavín, María Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-Gañán, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sonego, Michela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gandarillas Grande, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La violencia de pareja en jóvenes es un importante problema de salud pública por su magnitud y repercusiones. El objetivo fue estimar su prevalencia según sexo y su asociación con factores sociodemográficos y conductas de riesgo para la salud. Métodos: Se utilizó el Sistema de Vigilancia de Factores de Riesgo de Enfermedades No Transmisibles en población juvenil (SIVFRENT-J) 2011-2012 en una muestra representativa de estudiantes de 4º curso de la Enseñanza Secundaria Obligatoria (15 a 16 años) de la Comunidad deMadrid. Se preguntó por violencia física (VF) y violencia sexual (VS). Se calculó la prevalencia con intervalos de confianza al 95%(IC95%). La asociación entre violencia física y/o sexual (VFS) y conductas de riesgo para la salud se analizó con la razón de prevalencia (RP IC95%) mediante modelos lineales generalizados con vínculo logarítmico y familia binomial. Resultados: En 1.713 chicas y 1.664 chicos con pareja la prevalencia de VF fue respectivamente del 2,9% (IC95%:2,0-3,9) y del 4,0% (IC95%:2,9- 5,0) (p&gt;0,05), la de VS fue del 5,3% (IC95%:4,1-6,5) y 2,4% (IC95%:1,6- 3,2) (p&lt;0,001) y la de VFS 7,1% (IC95%:5,6-8,6) y 5,1%(IC95%:4,0-6,3) (p&lt;0,05). En chicas, en los modelos explicativos, la VFS se asoció con desorden alimentario: RP:1,74 (IC95%:1,14-2,66), conducta sexual de riesgo (CSR): RP:1,67 (IC95%:1,11-2,50), consumo excesivo de alcohol, RP:1,57 (IC95%:1,06-2,34) y mala salud percibida, RP:1,67 (IC95%:1,08-2,57). En chicos, la VFS se asoció con ser extranjero: RP:2,05 (IC95%:1,32-3,18), desorden alimentario: RP:2,79 (IC95%:1,58-4,92), CSR: RP:2,22 (IC95%:1,34- 3,66) y consumo de drogas: RP:2,14 (IC95%:1,39-3,28). Conclusiones: La VFS predomina en chicas y se asocia a diferentesconductas de riesgo según el sexo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;88(5): 639-652, sept.-oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124326</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Violencia de pareja en jóvenes de 15 a 16 años de la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
