<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17689</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary assessment and biochemical parameters for minerals in a group of elderly subjects in the province of LEÓN (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The population of the elderly people is increasing in our society, and it is very frequently affected by undernutrition problems. It is mainly due to an inadequate intake of micronutrients, as wsell as to a higher incidence of chronic diseases, which negatively affect the nutritional status. The aim of this study is to assess the levels, in terms of minerals (Ca, Fe, I, Zn, Mg, Na and K), of a population of 124 elderly persons (60 males and 64 females), aged between 65 and 98 years, who are institutionalized in five institutions for elderly people in the province of León (Spain). The dietetics study was carried out recording the food intake throughout 7 days by the precise weighting method. Blood concentration in Mg, Fe, Ca and ferritin was determined for the biochemical study. Calcium intake was 813 ± 182 mg in males and 792 ± 173 mg in females, which are lower values than those of reference that are being discussed at present. Regarding the values of serum calcium, no significant differences were found between males and females (9.2 ± 0.4 mg/dL vs 9.1 ± 0.6 mg/dl, respectively), but all these individuals are situated at the lower limit of range of normality. Iron intake was high, and there were 98% of males and 89% of females whose iron intakes were higher than the recommendations. Iron serum concentration was 89.6 ± 37.9 µg/dl vs 79.3 ± 24.2 µg/dl, and blood ferritin concentration was 107 ± 64 ng/ml vs 64 ± 48 ng/ml, in males and females respectively. Despite the fact that there is a very high percentage of elderly people whose iodine intake is lower than the 80% of the recommended intake (96% in males and 75% in females), no old person participating in this study was diagnosed of hypothyroidism. In relation to zinc intake, no significant differences are found between sexes, recording in both cases very low mean intake values compared to the dietetic recommendation (61 ± 10% I/RD) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La población anciana, cada vez más abundante en nuestra sociedad, se ve afectada con bastante frecuencia por problemas de desnutrición, debido fundamentalmente a la inadecuada ingesta de micronutrientes, y a la elevada incidencia de enfermedades crónicas, que afectan negativamente al estado nutricional. El objetivo del presente trabajo ha sido evaluar la situación en minerales (Ca, Fe, I, Zn, Mg, Na y K) de un colectivo de 124 ancianos (60 hombres y 64 mujeres) con edades comprendidas entre los 65 y los 98 años, procedentes de cinco instituciones para ancianos de la provincia de León. El estudio dietético se llevó a cabo mediante un control de la ingesta de alimentos durante siete días por el método de pesada precisa. Para el estudio bioquímico se determinó la concentración de Mg, Fe, Ca y ferritina en sangre. La ingesta de calcio fue 813 ñ 182 mg en los hombres y 792 ñ 173 mg en las mujeres, valores más bajos que los de referencia que se están discutiendo actualmente. En cuanto a los valores de calcio sérico, no se apreciaron diferencias significativas entre hombres y mujeres (9,2 ñ 0,4 mg/dl frente a 9,1 ñ 0,6 mg/dl, respectivamente), pero todos los individuos se sitúan en el límite inferior del rango de normalidad. La ingesta de hierro fue elevada, existiendo un 98 per cent de los hombres y el 89 per cent de las mujeres presentaban ingestas superiores a las recomendaciones. La concentración de hierro sérico fue de 89,6 ñ 37,9 µg/dl frente a 79,3 ñ 24,2 µg/dl, y la concentración de ferritina en sangre fue de 107 ñ 64 ng/ml frente a 64 ñ 48 ng/ml, para hombres y mujeres, respectivamente. Existe un altísimo porcentaje de ancianos con unas ingestas de yodo por debajo del 80 per cent de la ingesta recomendada (96 per cent en hombres y 75 per cent en mujeres), a pesar de los cual, a ningún anciano participante en este estudio se le diagnosticó hipotiroidismo. No se aprecian diferencias significativas entre géneros con respecto a la ingesta de cinc, observándose en ambos casos unos valores medios muy bajos de ingesta con respecto a la recomendación dietética, (71+/-10 per cent I/RD) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;18(1): 39-45, ene. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación dietética y parámetros bioquímicos de minerales en un colectivo de ancianos de la provincia de León (España)</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarino Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Arias, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Linares, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17689</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7619</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14523</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15427</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9091</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
