<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109897</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of troponin in patients with acute heart failure attended in Spanish Emergency Departments: TROPICA study (TROPonin in acute heart failure)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: To determine whether positive or negative troponin values determined in the Emergency Department (ED) in patients with acute heart failure (AHF) can predict short-term evolution(30-day intrahospitalary mortality and reconsultation at 30 days).Patients and methods: A retrospective, analytical, multicenter study with a follow-up of cohorts including patients diagnosed with AHF using the Framingham clinical criteria. Patients with acutecoronary syndrome concomitant with AHF were excluded. Data were collected at baseline and during the acute episode in each case. Troponin was considered as a dependent variable and variables of outcome results included intrahospitalary mortality and mortality and reconsultation to the ED within the following 30 days. Hazard ratios (HR) adjusted for differences in the basal state and during the acuteepisode, were calculated with their 95% con&amp;#64257;dence intervals (CI 95%) for troponin positive patients. Results: We included 806 patients from 17 Spanish EDs, 250 of whom (31%) were troponin-positive. The global intrahospitalary mortality was 9.2%, being 10.4% at 30 days and 21.3% reconsulted to the ED within 30 days. The troponin positive patients had a greater intrahospitalary (HR: 3.85; CI (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>miembros del grupo ICA-SEMES</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Determinar si el valor de la troponina (positiva o negativa) tomada en Urgencias a pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca aguda (ICA) permite predecir la evolución a corto plazo (mortalidad intrahospitalaria y a 30 días, y reconsulta a 30 días). Pacientes y método: Estudio de carácter analítico, multicéntrico, retrospectivo y con seguimiento de cohortes que incluyó pacientes diagnosticados de ICA por criterios clínicos de Framingham. Se excluyeron los pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo concomitante a la ICA. Para cada caso se consignaron datos del estado basal y del episodio agudo. Como variable dependiente se consideró la troponina. Como variables de resultado evolutivas se recogieron la mortalidad intrahospitalaria, y la mortalidad y la reconsulta a Urgencias durante los 30 días. Se calcularon las hazard ratio (HR) con su intervalo de confianza del 95% (IC 95%) para los pacientes con troponina positiva, tanto brutas como ajustadas por las diferencias en el estado basal y en el episodio agudo. Resultados: Se incluyeron 806 pacientes procedentes de 17 Servicios de Urgencias españoles, 250 de ellos (31,0%) con troponina positiva. La mortalidad global intrahospitalaria fue del 9,2%, a 30 días del 10,4%, y la reconsulta a 30 días del 21,3%. Los pacientes con troponina positiva tuvieron mayor mortalidad intrahospitalaria (HR 3,85; IC 95% 2,33-6,34) y a 30 días (HR 3,07; IC 95% 1,98-4,78), pero no una mayor reconsulta a 30 días (HR 0,88; IC 95% 0,62-1,26). Todos estos hallazgos se (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);140(4): 145-151, feb. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de la troponina en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca aguda atendidos en los Servicios de Urgencias hospitalarios españoles: estudio TROPICA (TROPonina en Insuficiencia Cardiaca Aguda)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14739^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
