<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147650</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Introduction to quality in community pharmacy (II): the separate consultation room</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The separate consultation room (SCR) is a parameter of quality in the community pharmacy, and its presence is compulsory according to the prevailing norms in Spain. Nevertheless, few pharmacies have an operative SCR, and the same occurs in other European countries. We propose some phased actions to introduce a SCR in the pharmacy, beginning with its justification and the identification of the possible difficulties that may arise during this process. We address the basic aspects of an ideal SCR as regards to visibility, accessibility, confidentiality and structural characteristics. We also classify the different types of SCR, with their description, application, advantages and disadvantages and how to overcome them. The best location is considered to be as close as possible to the dispensing site, in contrast to the usual custom of using the pharmacist&#146;s office. The need to carry out a proper filter on receiving the patient is also mentioned (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguiló Juanola, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La zona de atención personalizada (ZAP) es un parámetro de calidad en farmacia comunitaria, y su presencia es obligatoria, según establecen las normativas vigentes en las diferentes comunidades autónomas españolas. Sin embargo, son escasas las farmacias que disponen de una ZAP operativa, y lo mismo ocurre en el entorno europeo. En el presente artículo se plantean unas fases de actuación para implantar una ZAP en la farmacia, y se empieza exponiendo su justificación y las dificultades que pueden surgir en este proceso. Se proponen los aspectos básicos que debe cumplir una ZAP ideal en cuanto a visibilidad, accesibilidad, confidencialidad o características estructurales, y se realiza una clasificación de los diferentes tipos de ZAP, con su descripción, aplicación, ventajas, inconvenientes y forma de superarlos. Se considera que la mejor ubicación de la ZAP es cerca de la zona de dispensación, frente a la costumbre frecuente de utilizar el despacho del farmacéutico. Se describe la necesidad de realizar un filtro adecuado en la recepción del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;9(2): 91-96, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147650</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Introducción a la calidad en farmacia comunitaria (II): la zona de atención personalizada (ZAP)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7381</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
