<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048670</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Viral hepatitis among illegal drug users</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Among illegal drug users, the hepatitis C virus        (HCV) is the most prevalent, and illegal inyection        drug use is the predominat mode of transmision. In        Western and Southern Europe, the transmission of        hepatitis B virus (HBV) account by sexual activity        (heterosexual and MSM). In Northern Europe and UK,        inyecting drug use accounts for most cases.        The diagnosis of HBV infection is based on the        evaluation of serological, virological, biochemical        (AST/ALT) and histological markers. The most sensible        marker for HBV viral replication is the determination of        HBV DNA by PCR.        The laboratory test nowadays for HCV are a third        generation EIAs reach 99% sensivity, therefore the        clinical application of RIBA has been reduce to very        specific cases. HCV RNA qualitative detection is use        to diagnose active infection and evaluate treatment        effectiveness.        To date, several drugs have been approved for        the treatment of chronic hepatitis B virus: interferon        (INF), pegylated IFN alpha 2 (PEG-IFN), lamivudine        and adefovir. The choice of treatment should be        individualized according to the characteristics of the        virus and of the hepatic lesion and in agreement with        desires of the patient well.        Since the introduction of pegylated interferon and        ribavirin, the rate of cure or of sustained virological        response (SVR) in chronic hepatitis C have improved        markedly, surpassing 50% (40-50% for genotype        1 and nearly 80% for genotypes 2 and 3). A good        selection of candidates and adherence of treatment        are very important to get SVR</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pedreira Andrade, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Calvo, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Iglesias, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los pacientes usuarios a drogas, la hepatitis más        frecuente es la producida por el virus de la hepatitis        C (VHC), especialmente en los usuarios de drogas        intravenosas. La transmisión del virus de la hepatitis        B (VHB) en Europa Occidental, es fundamentalmente        por vía sexual (hetero y homosexual). En el Norte de        Europa y UK, la drogadicción intravenosa sigue siendo        la principal forma de transmisión del VHB.        El diagnóstico de la infección por el VHB se basa        en una evaluación serológica, virológica, bioquímica        (AST/ALT) e histológica. El marcador más sensible de        la replicación del VHB es el DNA-VHB por PCR. En        cuanto a los tests diagnósticos para el VHC, los EIAs        de tercera generación tienen actualmente, una sensibilidad        y especificidad del 99%. La determinación        cualitativa del RNA-VHC por PCR es útil en el diagnóstico        de la infección activa y en la monitorización.        Actualmente están aprobados varios fármacos        para la infección crónica por el VHB: interferon, interferon        pegilado (PEG-IFN), lamivudina y adefovir. La        elección del tratamiento ha de ser individualizado de        acuerdo a las características del virus, la lesión hepática        y las preferencias del paciente.        En cuanto a la hepatitis crónica C, el tratamiento        con interferon pegilado y ribavirina, consigue una        respuesta viral sostenida (RVS) que sobrepasa el        50% (40-50% para genotipo 1 y cerca del 80% para        genotipos 2 y 3). La selección adecuada de los candidatos        al tratamiento, y la buena adherencia al mismo,        son factores de gran importancia para alcanzar una        mayor RVS</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);18(supl.1): 115-136, 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatitis víricas en usuarios de drogas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24888^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
