<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141727</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A practice-based observational study on the use of micafungin in Surgical Critical Care Units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Echinocandins are first-line therapy in critically ill patients with invasive Candida infection (ICI). This study describes our experience with micafungin at Surgical Critical Care Units (SCCUs). Methods. A multicenter, observational, retrospective study was performed (12 SCCUs) by reviewing all adult patients receiving 100 mg/24h micafungin for &amp;#8805;72h during admission (April 2011-July 2013). Patients were divided by ICI category (possible, probable + proven), 24h-SOFA (&lt;7, &amp;#8805;7) and outcome. Results. 72 patients were included (29 possible, 13 probable, 30 proven ICI). Forty patients (55.6%) presented SOFA &amp;#8805;7. Up to 78.0% patients were admitted after urgent surgery (64.3% with SOFA &lt;7 vs. 90.3% with SOFA &amp;#8805;7, p=0.016), and 84.7% presented septic shock. In 66.7% the site of infection was intraabdominal. Forty-nine isolates were recovered (51.0% C. albicans). Treatment was empirical (59.7%), microbiologically directed (19.4%), rescue therapy (15.3%), or anticipated therapy and prophylaxis (2.8% each). Empirical treatment was more frequent (p&lt;0.001) in possible versus probable + proven ICI (86.2% vs. 41.9%). Treatment (median) was longer (p=0.002) in probable + proven versus possible ICI (13.0 vs.  8.0 days). Favorable response was 86.1%, without differences by group. Age, blood Candida isolation, rescue therapy, final MELD value and %MELD variation were significantly higher in patients with non-favorable response. In the multivariate analysis (R2 =0.246, p&lt;0.001) non-favorable response was associated with positive %MELD variations (OR=15.445, 95%CI= 2.529-94.308, p=0.003) and blood Candida isolation (OR=11.409, 95%CI=1.843-70.634, p=0.009) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Frías, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Bernedo, Carlos A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granizo, Juan-José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rico, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maseda, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, José-Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iranzo, Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samsó, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villagrán, María-José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las equinocandinas son tratamiento de primera línea en pacientes críticos con infección invasiva por Candida (IIC). Este estudio describe nuestra experiencia con micafungina en Unidades de Cuidados Críticos Quirúrgicos (UCCQs). Métodos. Se realizó un estudio multicéntrico, observacional y retrospectivo (12 UCCQs) revisando todos los pacientes adultos que recibieron 100 mg/24h micafungina durante &amp;#8805;72h tras su admisión en la UCCQ (Abril 2011-Julio 2013). Los pacientes se dividieron según la categoría de IIC (posible, probable + probada), valor de SOFA  (&lt;7, &gt;=7) y evolución. Resultados. Se incluyeron 72 pacientes (29 posible, 13 probable y 30 IIC probadas). Cuarenta pacientes (55,6%) presentaron SOFA &amp;#8805;7. Un total de 78,0% pacientes fueron ingresados tras cirugía urgente (64,3% con SOFA &lt;7 vs. 90,3% con SOFA &amp;#8805;7, p=0,016) y un 84,7% presentó shock séptico. El 66,7% de pacientes presentaban infección intraabdominal. Se recuperaron 49 aislados (51,0% C. albicans). El tratamiento fue empírico (59,7%), dirigido microbiológicamente (19,4%), terapia de rescate (15,3%), o anticipado y profilaxis (2,8% cada uno). El tratamiento empírico fue más frecuente (p&lt;0,001) en IIC posible versus probable + probada (86,2% vs. 41,9%). La duración del tratamiento (mediana) fue mayor (p=0,002) en IIC probable + probada que en IIC posible (13,0% vs. 8,0%). La respuesta clínica fue favorable en el 86,1% sin diferencias por grupo. La edad, el aislamiento de sangre, la terapia de rescate, el valor de MELD final y la variación de MELD fueron significativamente superiores en pacientes con respuesta clínica no favorable. En el análisis multivariado (R2 =0,246, p&lt;0,001) la respuesta no favorable se asoció con variación positiva del MELD (OR=15,445, 95%IC= 2,529-94,308, p=0,003) y aislamiento de Candida en sangre (OR=11,409, 95%IC=1,843-70,634, p=0,009). Conclusión: Se obtuvo una alta tasa de respuesta favorable, con el aislamiento de Candida en sangre asociado con respuesta no favorable en esta serie de pacientes con alto porcentaje de IIC intraabdominal, shock séptico e IIC con criterios microbiológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;28(3): 132-138, jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio observacional basado en la práctica clínica sobre la utilización de micafungina en Unidades de Cuidados Críticos Quirúrgicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53933^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
