<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043297</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary child antiphospholipid syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The antiphospholipid syndrome is an autoimmune disorder whose etiology is unknown. It is characterized by arterial and venous thrombosis, recurrent pregnancy loss and thrombocytopenia, among other symptoms, together with antiphospholipid antibodies. The syndrome is classified as primary when it occurs in the absence of systemic lupus erythematosus or other connective tissue diseases. The two most frequent antibodies are the lupus anticoagulant and the anticardiolipin antibody. We present a case of a sagittal sinus venous thrombosis associated with primary antiphospholipid syndrome in a girl, describing its symptomatology, course and treatment applied. We made a bibliographical review on this syndrome, stressing the clinical significance and prognosis of the presence of antiphospholipid antibodies in children</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burgos Checa, M. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elena Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrón Vázquez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romera Pérez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sampedro Santos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome antifosfolípido es una patología autoinmune de origen desconocido que se caracteriza por la aparición de trombosis tanto arteriales como venosas, abortos de repetición y trombocitopenia, entre otras manifestaciones, junto a la presencia de anticuerpos antifosfolípidos. El síndrome es definido como primario cuando aparece en pacientes que no padecen lupus eritematoso sistémico u otras conectivopatías. Los anticuerpos hallados más frecuentemente son el anticoagulante lúpico y los anticuerpos anticardiolipina. Presentamos el caso de una niña que sufrió una trombosis venosa del seno longitudinal superior como consecuencia de un síndrome antifosfolípido primario describiendo su sintomatología, evolución y el tratamiento realizado. Hacemos una revisión bibliográfica sobre este síndrome resaltando el significado clínico y pronóstico de la presencia de anticuerpos antifosfolípidos en niños</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(1): 43-46, ene.-feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome antifosfolípido primario infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30834^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13232^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30833^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30002^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30257^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
