<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158185</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing Process as tool in care practice. Application to the Nursing team in the Hospital Pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In a professional non-assistential healthcare subjected to intense workloads, the nursing team in the pharmacy of a second-level hospital begins a thoughtful process with nursing's own methodological resources. Object: Propose the Nursing Process as a capable tool of increasing professional motivation and reduce the moral suffering of nurses performing work without welfare functions. Method: Descriptive Study of Nursing Process applied to the job performance of a nursing team in risk of burnout, from april 14, 2010 to december 31, 2013, by establishing a Nursing Diagnosis, Care Plan, Interventions and Evaluations. Main results: Application of the Nursing Process to the Nursing team itself proved to be effective in order to face a difficult situation successfully, turning it into a dynamic and positive process. Identify the Nursing Diagnosis at risk of discouragement and burnout allows for the implementation of a Care Plan and scheduled interventions with effective measures to increase resilience and decrease burnout. Main conclusion: Nurse Process can be a powerful tool in care practice as well as in facing adverse situations by the nursing team. So is assessed the patient care, may be valued the nursing environment at professional risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López del Pino, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Villegas, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruíz Pérez, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García España,  Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En un entorno profesional sin pacientes y sometido a intensas cargas de trabajo, el equipo de enfermeras en la Farmacia en un Hospital de segundo nivel inicia un proceso reflexivo con herramientas metodológicas propias de su profesión. Objetivo: Proponer el Proceso Enfermero como herramienta capaz de incrementar la motivación profesional, y reducir el sufrimiento moral de enfermeras realizando trabajos desprovistos de funciones asistenciales. Método: Estudio descriptivo del Proceso Enfermero aplicado al desempeño laboral de un equipo de enfermeras en riesgo de burnout, desde el 14 de abril de 2010 al 31 de diciembre de 2013, estableciendo Diagnóstico de Enfermería, Plan de Cuidados, Intervenciones y Evaluaciones. Principales resultados: La aplicación del Proceso Enfermero al propio equipo de Enfermería transformó una situación difícil en un proceso dinámico y positivo, al identificar el diagnóstico de riesgo de desmotivación, e implementar un Plan de Cuidados e Intervenciones que resultaron ser efectivas para reforzar la resiliencia y reducir el riesgo de burnout. Conclusión principal: El Proceso Enfermero puede ser una herramienta potente para afrontar situaciones adversas del equipo de Enfermería. Al igual que se evalúan los pacientes, puede ser valorada la función laboral del equipo de enfermeras en situación de riesgo de deterioro profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;25(3): 175-179, jul.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158185</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Proceso Enfermero como herramienta de cuidados. Su aplicación en un equipo de Enfermería de Farmacia Hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
