<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165497</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">18F-FDG PET/CT in the clinical management of patients with lymphoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work was to review the current recommendations for staging and response assessment of patients with Hodgkin lymphoma (HL) and non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL) in routine clinical practice after chemotherapy and/or stem cell transplantation. A five-point scale (5-PS) from the First International Workshop on PET in Lymphoma in Deauville, France, in 2009, was recommended as the standard tool to score imaging to assess treatment response in patients with lymphoma using 18F-Fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) PET/CT. Following the recommendations of the 11th and 12th International Conferences on Malignant Lymphoma held in Lugano (Switzerland), in 2011 and 2013, respectively, a consensus (the so-called Lugano Classification) was reached regarding the use of PET/CT for staging and response assessment in FDG-avid lymphomas. As a result, 18F-FDG PET/CT was formally incorporated into standard staging for FDG-avid lymphomas. A bone marrow biopsy is no longer indicated for the routine staging of HL and most diffuse large B-cell lymphomas. PET/CT will be used to assess response in FDG-avid histologies using the 5-point scale. The recent introduction of biological agents with immune mechanisms requires flexibility in interpretations of the Lugano criteria due to tumour flare or a pseudo-progression effect produced by these agents. Provisional criteria have been proposed (Lymphoma Response to Immunomodulatory Therapy Criteria) with the introduction of the term &#145;Indeterminate Response&#146; in order to identify this phenomenon until confirmed as flare/pseudoprogression or true progression. All these recommendations will improve evaluations of patients with lymphoma, and allow comparison of results from clinical practice and trials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Talavera, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamayo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de la presente revisión es actualizar las recomendaciones sobre el papel de la tomografía por emisión de positrones (PET)/tomografía computarizada (TC) en la estadificación y valoración de la respuesta tras quimioterapia y/o trasplante de progenitores hematopoyéticos en pacientes con linfoma de Hodgkin (LH) y linfoma no-Hodgkin (LNH) en la práctica clínica habitual. En la primera reunión internacional sobre PET en linfoma, celebrada en 2009 en Deauville (Francia), se estableció una escala de 5 puntos para la valoración de la respuesta en pacientes con linfoma mediante la 18F-Fluordeoxiglucosa (FDG) PET/TC. Posteriormente, tras celebrarse la 11.a y 12.a Conferencia Internacional sobre Linfomas en Lugano (Suiza) en 2011 y 2013, respectivamente, se alcanzó un acuerdo en cuanto al uso de la PET/TC para la estadificación y se revisaron los criterios de respuesta en linfoma ávidos por la FDG en la práctica clínica y en ensayos clínicos; son los denominados criterios de valoración de respuesta de Lugano. Los principales consensos alcanzados fueron: i) la PET/TC con 18F-FDG fue formalmente incorporada en la estadificación de los linfomas con avidez por la FDG; ii) la biopsia de médula ósea ya no está indicada en la estadificación rutinaria de pacientes con LH y en la mayoría de los pacientes con linfoma B difuso de células grandes (LBDCG), y iii) la valoración de respuesta al tratamiento se hará mediante la PET/TC usando la escala de 5 puntos y la clasificación de Lugano. Actualmente, con la introducción de terapias basadas en agentes biológicos con mecanismos inmunes, los criterios de Lugano para valoración de la respuesta requieren una flexibilización y modificación, debido a que estos agentes pueden producir cambios en las técnicas de imagen que sugieren progresión de la enfermedad, a pesar de una respuesta clínica evidente (pseudoprogresión o tumor flare). Ello ha llevado a la adopción provisional de los criterios LYRIC (LYmphoma Response to Inmunomodulatory Therapy Criteria), con la introducción del término «respuesta indeterminada» para definir estos cambios hasta que sean confirmados o descartados como progresión de la enfermedad. El uso generalizado de todas estas recomendaciones mejorará la evaluación de pacientes con linfoma y hará posible la comparación de resultados procedentes de ensayos clínicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);36(5): 312-321, sept.-oct. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165497</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">18F-FDG PET/TC en el manejo clínico de los linfomas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53686</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
