<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163100</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cystic lymphangioma of the chest wall in Pediatrics and sclerotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Most lymphangiomas are diagnosed in the three first years of age. They are benign congenital malformations. They can grow and spread to sorrounding organs and tissues. A well performed anamnesis and physical examination must lead us to think that the best diagnostic tool is ultrasound with needle aspiration of the liquid contained in any cyst. Ultrasound characteristics and the aspect of the liquid must be sufficient to reach proper diagnosis. Surgical excision or sclerotherapy are both appropriate procedures. Two sclerosant agents are widly used, OK-432 and tetracyclines (doxycycline), being both safe and effective. We report a case of cystic lymphangioma of the thoracic wall. Sclerotherapy with OK-432 was performed. We review the literature and assess some critical aspects about diagnosis and treatment of lymphangiomas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Iglesias, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraña Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flor García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Yunta, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rius Peris, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osa Langreo, A de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayoría de los linfangiomas se diagnostican en la edad pediátrica. Se trata de lesiones de carácter benigno, y sólo su crecimiento y expansión local pueden originar problemas al comprimir estructuras vecinas. En los casos accesibles, como el que presentamos, una anamnesis y una exploración física adecuada debe llevarnos a la solicitud de la prueba diagnóstica más eficiente, la ecografía con punción de alguno de los quistes para el estudio directo del líquido intraquístico. El aspecto ecográfico de estas lesiones, junto con unas características típicas del líquido, bastará para efectuar un diagnóstico correcto en la mayoría de las ocasiones. La resección quirúrgica y la escleroterapia son opciones válidas de tratamiento, y entre ellas el OK-432 (Picibanil®) y las tetraciclinas son los agentes esclerosantes de los que se dispone de mayor experiencia, habiendo demostrado ser efectivos y seguros. Presentamos un caso de linfangioma quístico en la pared torácica tratado con el agente esclerosante OK-432, haciendo una revisión no sistemática de los aspectos diagnósticos y terapéuticos más relevantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;75(3/4): e48-e51, mar.-abr. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163100</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfangioma quístico de la pared torácica en pediatría y tratamiento esclerosante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12978^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31330^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14286^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31330^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36507^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
