<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118973</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of capnography for monitoring sedoanalgesia: Influence of oxygen on the parameters monitored</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To evaluate the usefulness of capnography for early detection of respiratory depression during sedoanalgesia procedures in the pediatric emergency department. To assess whether the administration of oxygen during the procedure can modify monitored parameters, thus delaying detection of respiratory depression. Material and methods: A prospective randomized study was performed on children between 1year and 16 years who underwent sedoanalgesia to perform diagnostic or therapeutic procedures. They were randomized into two groups (with or without supplemental oxygen). All patients were monitored by visual inspection, pulse-oximetry and non-invasive capnography. Monitoring was initiated prior to drug administration and continued until complete recovery of baseline. The main study variable was respiratory depression defined as apnea, hypoventilation or oxygen desaturation. Results: Twenty patients were included. Eleven patients were randomized in the supplemental oxygen group. This study showed a statistically significant elevation of EtCO2 levels at 5, 10and 15 min, compared with baseline. No significant change in the SatO2 mean was detected. No statistically significant differences were identified when comparing etCO2 mean and SatO2 mean in both groups. Two cases of respiratory depression were detected early by capnography. There was a statistically significant correlation between etCO2 at 5 and 10 min, and the degree of sedation achieved. Conclusions: The inclusion of capnography to routine monitoring for adequate sedation procedures could improve safety. Oxygen administration does not appear to modify the parameters monitored (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López López, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Míguez Navarro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Capín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marañón Pardillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Evaluar la utilidad de la capnografía para la detección precoz de depresión respiratoria durante los procedimientos de sedoanalgesia. Determinar si la administración de oxígeno durante el procedimiento puede modificar los parámetros monitorizados, retrasando la detección de depresión respiratoria. Material y métodos: Se diseña un estudio prospectivo aleatorizado. Se incluyeron pacientes de 1 a 16 años que precisaron sedoanalgesia para la realización de técnicas diagnósticas y/o terapéuticas, aleatorizando la administración o no de oxígeno suplementario. Todos fueron monitorizados mediante inspección visual, pulsioximetría y capnografía no invasiva, iniciando la monitorización antes de la administración del fármaco y manteniéndola hasta la recuperación completa del estado basal. La variable principal fue la detección de depresión respiratoria definida como apnea, hipoventilación o desaturación. Resultados: Se incluyeron 20 pacientes, de los cuales 11 recibieron oxígeno suplementario. Se objetivó una elevación estadísticamente significativa de los niveles de etCO2 a los 5, 10 y 15 min, comparados con su valor basal. No se detectaron cambios significativos en la media de SatO2. Comparando la evolución de las medias de etCO2 y SatO2 en ambos grupos no se identificaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Se registraron 2 casos de depresión respiratoria, detectados precozmente por la capnografía. Existe una correlación estadísticamente significativa entre el nivel de etCO2 a los 5 y 10 min y el grado de sedación alcanzado. Conclusiones: La incorporación de la capnografía a la monitorización rutinaria durante los procedimientos de sedoanalgesia podría mejorar su seguridad. La administración de oxígeno no parece modificar los parámetros monitorizados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);80(1): 41-46, ene. 2014. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la capnografía en la monitorización durante procedimientos de sedoanalgesia. Influencia de la administración de oxígeno en los parámetros monitorizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33095^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
