<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-24617</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of allocation of positions for specialist medical training</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Currently there is a large imbalance between supply and demand for medical specialists in the Spanish Health System. The aim of this study was to demonstrate the possible effects of current policies of allocating vacancies for interns and residents as well as to describe several measures and alternative policies. Methods: Using the methodology of System Dynamics, we designed a simulation model of the allocation process. Based on the validated model, possible changes in the system through time in response to diverse allocation policies were simulated. Specifically, changes in the accumulated number of graduates who over the years have remained without specialty, the number of unemployed specialists, and the imbalance between supply and demand in the period under consideration were observed. Results: The results obtained from the simulation indicate that allocation policies such as the current one tends to reduce the accumulated number of graduates without specialty, due to the philosophy characterizing this policy, but that it considerably increases the number of unemployed specialists and aggravates the supply-demand imbalance. In the simulation, this tendency remained over time even though more restrictive measures in numerus clausus and retirement age were adopted. Equally, a policy based on social needs and aware of delays in training would substantially contribute to eliminating unemployment among specialists and supply-demand imbalance over time. If such a policy were combined with the above-mentioned measures the results would be even better, more rapidly eliminating graduates without specialty, unemployed specialists, and supply-demand imbalances. Conclusions: If the Health Administration continues with the current system of allocation of places, the present imbalance in supply and demand will become even worse. Therefore, new and far-sighted measures and policies are required, as well as greater coordination between undergraduate and postgraduate training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Dado el actual desajuste existente entre oferta y demanda de médicos especialistas en el sistema sanitario español, el objetivo de este trabajo es mostrar el impacto que puede tener sobre el sistema las actuales políticas de convocatoria de plazas de formación médica especializada -plazas MIR-, así como diversas medidas y políticas alternativas de control. Métodos: Con esta finalidad se procedió a elaborar un modelo de simulación del proceso de convocatoria de plazas empleando como metodología la dinámica de sistemas. A partir del modelo elaborado y validado, se procede a simular la posible evolución del sistema a lo largo del tiempo ante diversas políticas de convocatoria. En concreto, se observa la evolución de la bolsa histórica de licenciados sin especialidad, la bolsa de médicos especialistas y el gap, o desajuste, entre oferta y demanda, existente en el período de simulación considerado. Resultados: De los resultados obtenidos de la simulación se observa que una política de convocatoria como la actual tiende a reducir la bolsa histórica de licenciados sin especialidad, debido a la propia filosofía que caracteriza a la actual convocatoria, pero incrementa considerablemente la bolsa de médicos especialistas y agudiza el desequilibrio existente. Esta tendencia se mantiene a pesar de que se adopten en la simulación medidas más restrictivas en numerus clausus y edad de jubilación forzosa. Se observa igualmente cómo una política consciente de las necesidades sociales y de los retrasos formativos existentes en el proceso mejora de modo sustancial la evolución, eliminando con el tiempo la bolsa de médicos especialistas y el desequilibrio. Si a su vez se combina dicha política con las medidas anteriormente citadas, los resultados obtenidos son aún superiores, eliminando ambas bolsas y el desajuste existente con mayor rapidez. Conclusiones: Si la Administración Sanitaria continúa convocando plazas de especialización como hasta el presente se agudizarán los problemas de desequilibrio existentes. Por lo tanto, es preciso adoptar medidas y políticas más previsoras con visión a largo plazo, así como una mayor coordinación entre la formación pre y posgraduada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;17(4): 289-295, jul. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La gestión del proceso de convocatoria de plazas de formaciónmédica especializada</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Alonso, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-24617</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10752</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
