<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165156</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A real life study of Helicobacter pylori eradication with bismuth quadruple therapy in naïve and previously treated patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the efficacy and safety of a quadruple regimen (BMTO) of the '3-in-1 capsule' (containing bismuth subcitrate potassium, metronidazole and tetracycline) plus omeprazole in naïve and previously treated patients diagnosed with Helicobacter pylori (H. pylori) infection in the clinical setting in Seville (Spain). Methods: This is a prospective study carried out on consecutive patients with a confirmed H. pylori infection and upper gastrointestinal symptoms. After providing their informed consent, the patients were treated for ten days with a 3-in-1 capsule containing bismuth subcitrate potassium (140 mg), metronidazole (125 mg) and tetracycline (125 mg: Pylera(R)), three capsules four times daily, plus omeprazole (20 or 40 mg) twice daily. Eradication of infection was determined by a negative urea breath test at least 28 days after the end of treatment. Results: A total of 58 consecutive patients were enrolled into this study, two of whom withdrew early due to vomiting on days three and five, respectively. In this cohort, 17 patients (29.3%) had a prior history of medication to treat H. pylori. In the intent-to-treat population, eradication was achieved in 97.6% (40/41) and 82.4% (14/17) of cases in patients treated with BMTO as a first-line or rescue therapy, respectively. At least one adverse event was reported by 28 (48%) patients, mostly mild effects (86%). Conclusion: A ten day treatment with BMTO is an effective and safe strategy to combat confirmed H. pylori infection in patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro Márquez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caunedo Álvarez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Rodríguez, Blas José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüelles Arias, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Laria, Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Gómez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar la eficacia y seguridad de la terapia cuádruple con omeprazol más 'una cápsula tres-en-uno' que contiene subcitrato de bismuto, metronidazol y tetraciclina (BMTO) en pacientes, naïve y fracasos previos, diagnosticados de infección con Helicobacter pylori, en el área de Sevilla, en condiciones de práctica clínica habitual. Métodos: estudio prospectivo realizado en pacientes consecutivos con infección confirmada por Helicobacter pylori y síntomas gastrointestinales del tracto superior. Los pacientes fueron tratados, tras firmar el consentimiento, con Pylera(R) (cápsula tres-en-uno que contiene 140 mg de subcitrato de bismuto, 125 mg de metronidazol y 125 mg de tetraciclina) cuatro veces al día, más omeprazol (20 o 40 mg) dos veces al día, durante diez días. La erradicación fue establecida mediante un test de urea en aliento negativo realizado, al menos, 28 días después de finalizar el tratamiento. Resultados: un total de 58 pacientes fueron incluidos consecutivamente, dos de ellos fueron retirados del estudio por vómitos al tercer y quinto día, respectivamente. Diecisiete (29,3%) pacientes tenían historia previa de tratamiento de su infección por Helicobacter pylori. En la población por intención de tratar las tasas de erradicación fueron del 97,6% (40/41) y del 82,4% (14/17) en los pacientes tratados con Pylera(R) como primera línea o como terapia de rescate, respectivamente. Veintiocho pacientes (48%) presentaron, al menos, un acontecimiento adverso, la mayoría (86%) leves. Conclusión: diez días de tratamiento con BMTO es una estrategia eficaz y segura en pacientes con infección confirmada por Helicobacter pylori (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;109(8): 552-558, ago. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165156</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Erradicación de Helicobacter pylori con terapia cuádruple con bismuto en pacientes naïve y fracasos previos: experiencia en la práctica clínica real</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14132^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1753^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
