<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148181</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How to live with COPD: patient´s perception</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to determine the mental model that patients with COPD (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease) have about their illness analyzed by the Leventhal´s Common Sense of Self-Regulation Model. An exploratory-descriptive study using qualitative methodology was performed. We included COPD-diagnosed patients attending three urban and a rural primary care centres. We used video-taped group interviews and transcribed them using Atlas.Ti 5.2 program. 22 group interviews (2009 - 2011) and 58 patients were included. There were 3 additional sessions to final inform validation. The results show that patients did not have a defined mental model about COPD: this disease was insufficiently recognized; diagnosis was made in exacerbations and it was confused with other diseases; the cause of illness was related to tobacco consumption and to &#147;something else&#148;: fumes, colds and hard work. Patients tended to minimize their symptoms and limitations. Participants had wrong beliefs about colds, smoking only a few cigarettes effects and damage of inhaled treatment. Emotions as despair, resignation and fear were reported. We conclude that COPD patients showed confusion about many aspects of the disease (causes, symptoms, treatments). It was difficult to identify a mental model of the disease among COPD patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Acero-Guasch, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca-del-Moral, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leiva Fernández, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ruiz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barnestein-Fonseca, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Cobos, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio pretende conocer la representación mental sobre la Enfermedad Pulmonar Obstructiva Crónica (EPOC) que tienen los pacientes que la presentan, siguiendo el Modelo de Autorregulación de Sentido Común de Leventhal. Para ello llevamos a cabo un estudio exploratorio descriptivo mediante metodología cualitativa. Incluimos pacientes diagnosticados de EPOC atendidos en 3 centros de salud urbanos y 1 rural. Utilizamos la entrevista grupal video-grabada y analizamos el contenido utilizando el programa Atlas.Ti. 5.2. Realizamos 22 entrevistas grupales (2009- 2011) incluyendo 58 pacientes y 3 sesiones de validación del informe por los participantes. Los resultados muestran que no existe un modelo mental compartido de la EPOC: la enfermedad tiene poco reconocimiento como tal; se diagnostica en descompensaciones y se confunde con otras enfermedades; la causa se atribuye no sólo al tabaco sino a &#147;algo más&#148; (humos, resfriados, trabajos duros); se minimizan los síntomas, incluyendo también los no respiratorios (dolor, cansancio) y se confunden con los de otras enfermedades. Existen creencias erróneas sobre los &#147;resfriados&#148;, efecto del &#147;fumar poco&#148; y efecto &#147;nocivo&#148; de los inhaladores. Aparecen sentimientos de desesperanza, resignación y miedo. Concluimos que los pacientes con EPOC manifiestan confusión en muchos aspectos de la enfermedad mostrando dificultades para identificar un modelo mental sobre ella (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;32(1): 18-31, ene. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148181</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cómo vivir con EPOC: percepción de los pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
