<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152218</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patterns of Play in the Fast attack of FC Barcelona, Manchester United and FC Internazionale Milano- A Mixed</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to detect and analyse regular patterns of play in fast attack of football teams, through the combination of the sequential analysis technique and semi-structured interviews to experienced first League Portuguese coaches. The sample included 36 games (12 games of the respective national leagues per team) of the F.C. Barcelona, Inter Milan, and Manchester United teams that were coded with the observational instrument tool developed by Sarmento et al. (2010) and the data analysed through sequential analysis with the software SDIS-GSEQ 5.0. Based on the detected patterns, semistructured interviews were carried out to 8 expert high-performance football coaches and data were analysed through the content analysis technique using the software NVivo 10. The detected patterns of play revealed specific characteristics of the teams under study. The combination of the results of sequential analysis with the qualitative interviews to the professional coaches proved to be very fruitful in this game the analysis of scope, allowing reconcile scientific knowledge with practical interpretation of coaches who develop their tasks in the field (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Anguera, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarmento, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campaniço, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira, Antonino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leitão, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tuvo como objetivo detectar y analizar los patrones regulares de juego en ataque rápido de los equipos de fútbol, a través de la combinación de la técnica de análisis secuencial y entrevistas semi-estructuradas a entrenadores con experiencia en la primera Liga Portuguesa. La muestra incluyó 36 partidos (12 juegos de las respetivas Ligas de Fútbol para cada equipo) del FC Barcelona, Inter de Milán y Manchester United, que han sido codificados con el instrumento observacional validado por Sarmento et al. (2010). Posteriormente los datos se analizaron a través del análisis secuencial con el programa SDIS-GSEQ 5.0. Tomando como referencia los patrones de juego detectados, se llevaron a cabo entrevistas semi-estructuradas a 8 entrenadores de fútbol de alto rendimiento y los datos se analizaron mediante la técnica de análisis de contenido utilizando el programa Nvivo 10. Los patrones de juego detectados revelaron características específicas de los equipos de estudio. La combinación de los resultados del análisis secuencial con las entrevistas cualitativas a los entrenadores profesionales demostró ser muy fructífera en este ámbito de análisis del juego, lo que permite conciliar el conocimiento científico con la interpretación práctica de los entrenadores que desarrollan su actividad en el campo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;16(1): 31-42, ene. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrones de juego en el ataque rápido de FC Barcelona, Manchester United y FC Internazionale Milano -Un enfoque de Mixed</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
