<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94118</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of paediatric parenteral nutrition over the last 15 years in a tertiary hospital in Madrid (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze the use of paediatric parenteral nutrition (PN) in a tertiary level hospital in Spain (1994-2008). Materials and methods: The charts from infants and children receiving NP in 2008 were reviewed. Data were compared with those in 1994 and 2002. Results: 120 patients received PN, 78 and 71 corresponding to 1.6%, 1.3% and 1.0% of total admissions in 2008, 2002 and 1994 respectively. When composition of PN was compared in the first day we found significant differences in energy and lipids; but not in volume, carbohydrate, or amino acid composition. Gastrointestinal surgery was the most common indication. Mean length was 11.0 ± 9.8 days (2008) to 15.2 ± 14.8 (1994) (p &lt; 0.05). Complications were present in 24.8 patients (2008), 10.8% (2002) and 16.9 (1994). Conclusions: PN use increased along the study period, although mean length decreased. There were more complications in 2008 than in previous years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ferreiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Villares, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomis Muñoz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros de Tejada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar el empleo de la nutrición parenteral (NP) pediátrica en un hospital terciario en Madrid (1994-2008). Material y métodos: Se revisaron las historias clínicas de pacientes pediátricos hospitalizados con NP en 2008, comparándose con 2002 y 1994. Resultados: Recibieron NP 120, 78 y 71 niños, siendo el 1,6%, 1,3% y 1,0% respectivamente del total de ingresados (2008, 2002 y 1994). Hubo diferencias significativas en la composición en el primer día en kilocalorías y lípidos; pero no en volumen, carbohidratos ni aminoácidos. La cirugía gastrointestinal fue la indicación más frecuente. La duración media de la NP varió de 15,2 ± 14,8 (1994) a 11 ± 9,8 días (2008) (p &lt; 0,05). Presentaron complicaciones el 24,8% (2008), 10,8% (2002) y 16,9% (1994) de los pacientes. Conclusiones: En número absoluto y relativo de NP ha aumentado durante los años evaluados, aunque la duración media se ha reducido significativamente. Las complicaciones, sin embargo, han aumentado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(6): 1057-1060, nov.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94118</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variación en el uso de nutrición parenteral en un hospital infantilen Madrid (España) a lo largo de 15 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13379^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24449^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
