<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141382</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A simple and reliable tool for detection of nutritional risk in hospitalized patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: malnutrition in hospital associates with complications such a high rates of infections, increased length of stay, and increased economic costs. Hospitals require applying a simple and reliable tool for detection of nutritional risk. Objective: to evaluate the agreement between a screening tool used in a hospital and both MUST and SGA tools to determine the prevalence of nutritional risk. Methods: patients &#150;with a hospitalization period less than 36 hours&#150; were assessed with three nutritional screening tools. Kappa value was used to assess agreement between the tests; SGA was the gold standard. Results: the study included 100 patients (F=49, M=51) with a mean age of 49 years. MUST presented a good agreement with the SGA (kappa = 0.55). Conclusions: MUST presents the highest agreement with the gold standard; therefore, it must be used to screen nutritional status of hospitalized patients due to its simplicity, reliability, and reproducibility (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Padilla-Romo, Martha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez-Cordero, Erika</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez-Cordero, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la desnutrición hospitalaria se asocia con retraso en la curación, mayor tiempo de hospitalización y gasto económico. Los hospitales requieren un instrumento sencillo para detectar un posible riesgo nutricional. Objetivo: evaluar la concordancia entre un formato de tamizaje utilizado en un hospital de tercer nivel y los instrumentos validados MUST y SGA para diagnosticar el riesgo nutricional. Métodos: pacientes con periodo de hospitalización menor a 36 horas fueron valorados con los tres tamizajes nutricionales. Utilizamos valor kappa para medir la concordancia entre las herramientas de tamizaje; el instrumento SGA fue el estándar de oro. Resultados: el estudio incluyó 100 pacientes (F = 49, M = 51) con una edad media de 49 años. MUST presentó buena concordancia con el SGA (kappa= 0,55). Conclusiones: MUST presentó mayor concordancia con el estándar de oro; por lo tanto, el MUST debería utilizarse para el tamizaje nutricional de los pacientes que ingresan en hospitales debido a su sencillez, fiabilidad y reproducibilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(1): 379-382, jul. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141382</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un instrumento sencillo y fiable para detectar riesgo nutricional en pacientes hospitalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
