<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143825</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in body composition of high competition rugby players during the phases of a regular season; influence of diet and exercise load</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Top athletes are subjected to intense training to achieve high performance. There are factors such as diet and strenuous exercise that affects body composition and can modify the performance. The aim of the study was to evaluate the effect of a personalized plan of diet and training on body composition. Methods: We studied the body composition of 18 professional rugby players using Kinanthropometry parameters. The study was conducted from the preseason to the end of the season taking into account the position of the player for measuring exercise intensity, and developing a personalized nutritional and training plan to each player. Results: At baseline the players were away from the internationally recommended body composition, with high percentages of body fat. Appropriate and personalized diet plans and training custom achieved fat percentages close to those recommended. Conclusions: The personalized program of diet and training directed has adequate leverage to improve all parameters studied them bringing them as close to the ideal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garcíacaballero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suarez Moreno-Arrones, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García A,  A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes-Ortiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Moreno, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los atletas de alto rendimiento están sometidos a grandes esfuerzos para lograr un alto nivel. Hay factores como la alimentación y el ejercicio extenuante que afectan la composición corporal modificando el rendimiento. Sin embargo con un plan personalizado de dieta y entrenamiento se puede modificar la composición corporal y lograr un máximo rendimiento. Métodos: Estudiamos la composición corporal de 18 jugadores profesionales de rugby por medio de bioimpedancia y kineantropometría. El estudio se llevó a cabo desde la pretemporada hasta el final de la temporada tomándose en cuenta la posición de juego para medir la intensidad del ejercicio, y desarrollando un plan personalizado de alimentación y entrenamiento a cada jugador. Resultados: Los jugadores estaban lejos de la composición corporal recomendada internacionalmente, con altos porcentajes de grasa corporal. Con planes personalizados de dieta y entrenamiento se logró porcentajes de grasa cercanos a los recomendados. Conclusiones: El programa personalizado de dieta y el entrenamiento dirigido, tiene una adecuada influencia para mejorar todos los parámetros de composición corporal estudiados acercándolos al ideal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(4): 913-921, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en la composición corporal de jugadores de rugby de alta competición durante las fases de una temporada habitual: influencia de la dieta y la carga de ejercicio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
