<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142206</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inflammation and obesity (lipoinflammation)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity is a chronic disease with multiple origins. It is a widespread global phenomenon carrying potentially serious complications which requires a multidisciplinary approach due to the significant clinical repercussions and elevated health costs associated with the disease. The most recent evidence indicates that it shares a common characteristic with other prevalent, difficult-to-treat pathologies: chronic, low-grade inflammation which perpetuates the disease and is associated with multiple complications. The current interest in lipoinflammation or chronic inflammation associated with obesity derives from an understanding of the alterations and remodelling that occurs in the adipose tissue, with the participation of multiple factors and elements throughout the process. Recent research highlights the importance of some of these molecules, called pro-resolving mediators, as possible therapeutic targets in the treatment of obesity. This article reviews the evidence published on the mechanisms that regulate the adipose tissue remodelling process and lipoinflammation both in obesity and in the mediators that are directly involved in the appearance and resolution of the inflammatory process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luis, Daniel de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo, Joan Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sajoux, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izaola, Olatz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad es una enfermedad crónica de origen multifactorial con una elevada prevalencia a nivel mundial que se asocia a complicaciones potencialmente graves y que precisa de un enfoque multidisciplinar por su gran repercusión clínica y elevado coste sanitario. La evidencia más reciente apunta que comparte con otras patologías comunes y de complejo abordaje terapéutico la existencia de un estado de inflamación crónica de bajo grado que perpetúa la enfermedad y se asocia a múltiples complicaciones. El interés actual de la lipoinflamación o inflamación crónica asociada a la obesidad deriva del conocimiento de las alteraciones y remodelado que se produce en el tejido adiposo, con la participación de múltiples factores y elementos implicados en todo el proceso. Investigaciones recientes subrayan la importancia de algunas de estas moléculas, denominadas mediadores especializados en la resolución, como posible dianas terapéuticas para el tratamiento de la obesidad. En este artículo se revisa la evidencia publicada acerca de los mecanismos que regulan el proceso de remodelado del tejido adiposo y el estado de lipoinflamación en la obesidad así como en los mediadores implicados directamente en la aparición y resolución del proceso inflamatorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(6): 2352-2358, jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142206</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inflamación y obesidad (lipoinflamación)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8436^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31672^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
