<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114363</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral reading fluency analysis in patients with Alzheimer disease and asymptomatic control subjects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Many studies highlight that an impaired ability to communicate is one of the key clinical features of Alzheimer disease (AD). Objective: To study temporal organisation of speech in an oral reading task in patients with AD and in matched healthy controls using a semi-automatic method, and evaluate that method's ability to discriminate between the 2 groups. Subjects and methods: A test with an oral reading task was administered to 70 subjects, comprising 35 AD patients and 35 controls. Before speech samples were recorded, participants completed a battery of neuropsychological tests. There were no differences between groups with regard to age, sex, or educational level. Results: All of the study variables showed impairment in the AD group. According to the results, AD patients&#146; oral reading was marked by reduced speech and articulation rates, low effectiveness of phonation time, and increases in the number and proportion of pauses. Signal processing algorithms applied to reading fluency recordings were shown to be capable of differentiating between AD patients and controls with an accuracy of 80% (specificity 74.2%, sensitivity 77.1%) based on speech rate. Conclusion: Analysis of oral reading fluency may be useful as a tool for the objective study and quantification of speech deficits in AD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meilán, J. J. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sevilla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Numerosos estudios han puesto de manifiesto que la alteración en la capacidad comunicativa es uno de los síntomas característicos de la enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA). Objetivo: Estudiar la organización temporal del habla en una tarea de lectura en un grupo de pacientes con EA y otro de controles sanos, utilizando un procedimiento semiautomático, así como valorar su capacidad para discriminar entre ambos grupos. Sujetos y método: Se aplicó una prueba de lectura a 70 sujetos: 35 con EA y otros tantos controles. Antes del registro del habla, los sujetos fueron sometidos a una batería de pruebas neuropsicológicas. Los grupos no diferían en edad, sexo o nivel de estudios. Resultados: Todas las variables analizadas se mostraron alteradas en el grupo con EA. Los resultados señalan que la lectura de los pacientes con EA se caracteriza por una reducida velocidad de elocución y articulación, una baja efectividad del tiempo de fonación, así como en un incremento del número y la proporción de las pausas. Los algoritmos de procesamiento de la señal aplicados a las grabaciones de fluidez lectora demostraron su capacidad para discriminar entre ambos grupos con una precisión del 80% (especificidad 74,2%; sensibilidad 77,1%) mediante la velocidad de elocución. Conclusión: El análisis de la fluidez de lectura oral puede representar una herramienta potencial para el análisis objetivo y la cuantificación de los déficits del lenguaje en la EA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;28(6): 325-331, jul.-ago. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114363</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la fluencia lectora en pacientes con la enfermedad de Alzheimer y controles asintomáticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
