<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149001</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The child&#146;s brain: normal (unaltered) development and development altered by perinatal injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study we analyse some of the morphological and functional aspects of normal and altered development (the latter due to perinatal injury) in the child&#146;s brain. Both normal and altered development are developmental processes that progressively interconnect the different regions. The neuropathological development of subpial and periventricular haemorrhages, as well as that of white matter infarct, are analysed in detail. Any kind of brain damage causes a local lesion with possible remote repercussions. All the components (neurons, fibres, blood capillaries and neuroglias) of the affected region undergo alterations. Those that are destroyed are eliminated by the inflammatory process and those that survive are transformed. The pyramidal neurons with amputated apical dendrites are transformed and become stellate cells, the axonal terminals and those of the radial glial cells are regenerated and the region involved is reinnervated and revascularised with an altered morphology and function (altered local corticogenesis). The specific microvascular system of the grey matter protects its neurons from infarction of the white matter. Although it survives, the grey matter is left disconnected from the afferent and efferent fibres, amputated by the infarct with alterations affecting its morphology and possibly its functioning (altered local corticogenesis). Any local lesion can modify the morphological and functional development of remote regions that are functionally interconnected with it (altered remote corticogenesis). We suggest that any local brain injury can alter the morphology and functioning of the regions that are morphologically and functionally interconnected with it and thus end up affecting the child&#146;s neurological and psychological development. These changes can cross different regions of the brain (epileptic auras) and, if they eventually reach the motor region, will give rise to the motor storm that characterises epilepsy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín Padilla, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Analizamos algunos aspectos morfológicos y funcionales del desarrollo normal y alterado (por daño perinatal) del cerebro del niño. Tanto el desarrollo normal como el alterado son procesos evolutivos que de manera progresiva interconectan sus distintas regiones. Se analiza en detalle la evolución neuropatológica de hemorragias subpiales y periventriculares y la del infarto de la sustancia blanca. Cualquier tipo de daño cerebral causa una lesión local con posibles repercusiones a distancia. Todos los componentes (neuronas, fibras, capilares sanguíneos y neuroglía) de la región afectada sufren alteraciones. Los destruidos quedan eliminados por el proceso inflamatorio y los que sobreviven se transforman. Las neuronas piramidales con dendritas apicales amputadas se transforman en células estrelladas, las terminales axónicas y de la glía radial se regeneran y la región afectada se reinerva y revasculariza con morfología y función alteradas (corticogénesis local alterada). El sistema microvascular específico de la sustancia gris protege sus neuronas del infarto de la sustancia blanca. Pese a sobrevivir, la sustancia gris queda desconectada de las fibras aferentes y eferentes amputadas por el infarto con una morfología y posible función alteradas (corticogénesis local alterada). Cualquier lesión local puede modificar el desarrollo morfológico y funcional de regiones distantes interconectadas funcionalmente con ella (corticogé- nesis distante alterada). Proponemos que cualquier lesión cerebral local puede alterar la morfología y función de las regiones interconectadas de manera morfológica y funcional con ella para acabar afectando al desarrollo neurológico y psicológico del niño. Estos cambios pueden marchar a través de distintas regiones del cerebro (auras epilépticas) y, si acabaran alcanzando la región motora, resolverse en la tormenta motora que caracteriza la epilepsia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;57(supl.1): s3-s15, 6 sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cerebro del niño: desarrollo normal (no alterado) y alterado por daño perinatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1947^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34262^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1947^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1947^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1947^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8495^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29179</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8495^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8749^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13581</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
