<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160734</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multiplex PCR designed to differentiate species within the Candida glabrata complex</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. No phenotypic methods are available to unequivocally differentiate species within the Candida glabrata complex. Aims. To develop a new multiplex PCR method to differentiate between the three species of the C. glabrata species complex, as well as using it to study a C. glabrata collection to discover strains of the newly described species. Methods. The method was developed based on the Internal Transcribed Spacer (ITS) sequence differences between the species. It was validated by using a blinded collection of strains and, finally, the new molecular method was used to study a collection of 192 C. glabrata species complex strains. The obtained results were compared with ITS sequencing. Results. The proposed method showed 100% concordance with ITS sequencing and proved to be effective for clinical and epidemiological applications. Two Candida bracarensis and three Candida nivariensis were found out of the 192 studied strains (0.93% and 1.40% prevalence, respectively). Conclusions. A fast, inexpensive, robust and highly reproducible multiplex PCR method is presented. Its usefulness is demonstrated by studying a large collection of C. glabrata sensu lato strains (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morales-López, Soraya E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabeza, Matías S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamarra, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Podesta, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tosello, María E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia-Effron, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macedo, Daiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitale, Roxana G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dudiuk, Catiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leonardelli, Florencia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Biasoli, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. No hay métodos fenotípicos disponibles para diferenciar las especies del complejo Candida glabrata. Objetivos. Diseñar un método de PCR multiplex para diferenciar las tres especies del complejo C. glabrata y usarlo para estudiar una colección de cepas identificadas anteriormente como C. glabrata. Métodos. El método fue desarrollado con base en las diferencias de la secuencia internal transcribed spacer (ITS) entre las especies. El método se validó mediante el uso de una colección de cepas incógnitas y se utilizó posteriormente para estudiar una colección de 192 cepas. Los resultados se compararon con las secuencias ITS. Resultados. El método propuesto mostró 100% de concordancia con la secuenciación de las regiones ITS y demostró ser eficaz clínica y epidemiológicamente. Se identificaron dos aislamientos de Candida bracarensis y tres de Candida nivariensis dentro de las 192 cepas identificadas fenotípicamente como C. glabrata (prevalencia de 0,93% y 1,40%, respectivamente). Conclusiones. Presentamos un método de PCR múltiplex rápido, económico y fiable. La utilidad de la metodología queda demostrada con el estudio de una gran colección de cepas de C. glabrata sensu lato (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;34(1): 43-45, ene.-mar. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160734</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">PCR multiplex diseñada para diferenciar las especies del complejo Candida glabrata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4659^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36630^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36630^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36630^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4659^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4659^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
