<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137364</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Statements about home care in world stage: narrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It was aimed to know the definitions and implications of home care approached in scientific articles. It is a bibliographic research, a narrative review. The search was performed in the database National Library of Medicine National Institutes of Health (PUBMED), in December of 2012. The descriptors Mesh Database used were: care services; patient care team; homebound persons and caregiver. It was found 2244 titles of publications. The process of inclusion and exclusion divided itself in two steps: the reading of the titles and abstracts to verify the approached theme, &#147;home care&#148;, being selected 253 titles and abstracts. The second one was the filling of the frame of information, performed in the Microsoft Excel 2007 program, being concluded with 209 abstracts. In the analysis in a full form, 72 articles were selected to analysis of content and identification of statements. It was performed three enunciative categories: home care: what is it? For what is it used?; Home care: Fragilities and Potentialities; Familiar Caregiver: fatigue and isolation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Griebeler Oliveira, Stefanie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sartor, Silvia Francine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarría-Guanilo, Maria Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luce Kruse, Maria Henriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se objetivó conocer las definiciones e implicaciones de la atención domiciliaria abordadas en artículos científicos. Se trata de una investigación bibliográfica, revisión narrativa. La búsqueda fue realizada en la base de datos National Library of Medicine National Institutes of Health (PUBMED), en diciembre de 2012. Los descriptores Mesh Database utilizados fueron: home care services; patient care team; homebound persons y caregiver. Fueron encontrados 2244 publicaciones. El proceso de inclusión y exclusión se dividió en dos etapas: la primera fue la lectura de los títulos y resúmenes para verificación del tema abordado &#147;atención domiciliaria&#148;, siendo seleccionados 253 títulos y resúmenes. La segunda fue el llenado del cuadro de informaciones elaborado en el programa Microsoft Excel 2007, siendo concluida con 209 resúmenes. Para el análisis en la integra, 72 artículos fueron seleccionados para análisis de contenido e identificación de los enunciados. Fueron elaboradas tres categorías enunciativas: Atención domiciliaria: ¿Qué es? ¿Para qué sirve?; Atención Domiciliaria: Fragilidades y potencialidades; Cuidador Familiar: fatiga y aislamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;14(39): 360-374, jul. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137364</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enunciados sobre la atención domiciliaria en el panorama mundial: revisión narrativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32195^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55416^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55416^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
