<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146944</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of power training in mechanical stiffness of the lower limbs in soccer players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The aim of this study was evaluate whether leg stiffness (Kleg) changes after power training. Methods. Forty professional soccer players were divided into 2 groups (20 were assigned to the trained group and 20 to the control group). A quasi-experimental study with pre&#150;post intervention was conducted to estimate Kleg before (period 1) and after a six-week period of power training (period 2). Leg stiffness was measured using a three-dimensional filming method while soccer players ran on a treadmill at 13 km/h. The heights of squat jumps (SJ) and countermovement jumps (CMJ) were measured and the pre-stretch augmentation (PSA) was calculated before and after the training period in both groups. Results. We found a significant increase in Kleg after the power training program. Significant positive linear relationships between Kleg and SJ height were found in both periods and groups, while CMJ height was not correlated with Kleg in the trained group during period 2. No significant relationships were found between Kleg and PSA in either case. Conclusions. We concluded that Kleg can change significantly after a short power training program. Based on our results and previous studies, we suggest that these changes could be mainly associated with adaptions at muscle control level (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fábrica, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar si la rigidez de la pierna (Kleg) cambia después de un período de entrenamiento de potencia. Métodos. Cuarenta jugadores profesionales de fútbol se dividieron en 2 grupos (20 se asignaron al grupo entrenado y 20 al grupo control). Se realizó un estudio cuasi-experimental con pre-post intervención para estimar Kleg antes (periodo 1) y después de 6 semanas de entrenamiento de potencia (período 2). Se cuantificó Kleg mediante la reconstrucción de imágenes en 3 dimensiones mientras los sujetos corrían en una cinta a 13 km/h. Se midieron las alturas de squat jumps (SJ) y countermovment jumps (CMJ) y se calculó el pre-stretch augmentation (PSA) antes y después del período de entrenamiento para ambos grupos. Resultados. Se encontró un aumento significativo en Kleg después del programa de entrenamiento. Se encontraron correlaciones lineales positivas entre Kleg y la altura de los SJ en ambos períodos para los 2 grupos, mientras que la altura CMJ no se correlacionó con Kleg únicamente en el grupo entrenado durante el periodo 2. No se encontraron relaciones significativas entre Kleg y PSA. Conclusiones. Llegamos a la conclusión de que Kleg puede cambiar significativamente como producto del entrenamiento de potencia. Basados en nuestros resultados y considerando estudios previos sugerimos que estos cambios podrían estar asociados principalmente con adaptaciones a nivel del control muscular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;8(4): 145-149, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/ Efectos del entrenamiento de potencia sobre la rigidez mecánica de miembros inferiores en jugadores de fútbol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9318^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
