<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135546</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Geographic patterns of mortality and socioeconomic inequalities in mortality in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Estimates of socioeconomic inequalities in mortality coming from individual data sources were only available from Madrid, the Basque Country and the city of Barcelona. The aim of this study was to show the geographical pattern of mortality in different socio-economic groups, as well as that of inequalities in mortality in the whole Spanish territory. Methods: All people aged 25 and older in the 2001 census were followed for seven years and two months to determine their vital status (196 470 401 person-years at risk and 2,379,558 deaths). The socioeconomic variable was educational level. Age-adjusted mortality rate was estimated for women and men in every province and in each category of educational level. Inequalities in mortality in each province have been estimated by the ratio of mortality in subjects with primary or lower level of education compared to subjects with university education. Results: In women, the lowest rate ratios &#150;between 1.06 and 1.16- are observed in Palencia, Segovia, Guadalajara, Avila and Castellon and the highest -between 1.53 and 1,75- in Malaga, Las Palmas, Ceuta, Melilla and Toledo. In men, the lowest rate ratios -between 1.00 and 1.12 &#150; are observed in Guadalajara, Teruel, Cuenca, La Rioja and Ávila and the highest -between 1.47 and 1,73- in Las Palmas, Cantabria, Murcia, Melilla and Ceuta. Conclusions: The geographical pattern of mortality rates in Spain varies by educational level. Inequalities in mortality by education have the lowest magnitude in central peninsular provinces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miqueleiz, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regidor, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reques, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giráldez-García, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Juana M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Las estimaciones sobre desigualdades socioeconómicas en mortalidad a partir de registros individuales de defunciones y población son escasas y proceden únicamente de la la ciudad de Barcelona, la Comunidad de Madrid y el País Vasco. El objetivo del presente estudio fue mostrar el patrón geográfico de mortalidad en diferentes grupos socioeconómicos, así como el de las desigualdades en mortalidad en el conjunto del territorio español. Métodos: Se realizó el seguimiento de todos los individuos mayores de 25 años del censo de población 2001 durante siete años y dos meses para conocer su estado vital (196.470.401 personas-año a riesgo y 2.379.558 defunciones). Se calculó la tasa de mortalidad ajustada por edad en hombres y mujeres por provincia y nivel de estudios. Las desigualdades en mortalidad provinciales se estimaron mediante la razón de tasas de mortalidad en los sujetos con nivel de estudios primarios o inferiores respecto a los sujetos con estudios universitarios. Resultados: En mujeres, las razones de tasas más bajas &#150;entre 1,06 y 1,16- se observaron Palencia, Segovia, Guadalajara y Ávila. Las más altas &#150;entre 1,53 y 1,75- en Málaga, Las Palmas, Ceuta, Toledo y Melilla. En hombres, las razones de tasas más bajas &#150;entre 1,00 y 1,12- se observan en Guadalajara, Teruel, Cuenca, La Rioja y Ávila y las más altas &#150;entre 1,47 y 1,73- en Las Palmas, Cantabria, Murcia, Melilla y Ceuta. Conclusiones: El patrón geográfico de las tasas de mortalidad en España varía según el nivel educativo. Las desigualdades en mortalidad muestran menor magnitud en las provincias del centro peninsular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(2): 137-147, mar.-abr. 2015. tab, mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrones geográficos de la mortalidad y de las desigualdades socioeconómicas en mortalidad en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50334^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37724^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
