<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166697</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Increasing incidence of community-acquired pneumonia caused by atypical microorganisms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Knowing the most common microorganisms in our environment can help us to make proper empirical treatment decisions. The aim is to identify those microorganisms causing community-acquired pneumonia. Patients and methods. An observational, descriptive and prospective study was conducted, including patients over 14 years with a clinical and radiographic diagnosis of community-acquired pneumonia during a 383 consecutive day period. A record was made of sociodemographic variables, personal history, prognostic severity scales, progress, and pathogenic agents. The aetiological diagnosis was made using blood cultures, detection of Streptococcus pneumoniae and Legionella pneumophila urinary antigens, sputum culture, influenza virus and Streptococcus pyogenes detection. Categorical variables are presented as absolute values and percentages, and continuous variables as their means and standard deviations. Results. Of the 287 patients included in the study (42% women, mean age 66±22 years), 10.45% died and 70% required hospital admission. An aetiological diagnosis was achieved in 43 patients (14.98%), with 16 microorganisms found in 59 positive samples. The most frequently isolated pathogen was Streptococcus pneumonia (24/59, 41%), followed by gram-negative enteric bacilli, Klebsiella pneumonia, Escherichia coli, Serratia marcescens and Enterobacter cloacae isolated in 20% of the samples (12/59), influenza virus (5/59, 9%), methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (3/59, 5%), Pseudomonas aeruginosa (2/59, 3%), Moraxella catarrhalis (2/59, 3%), Legionella pneumophila (2/59, 3%), and Haemophilus influenza (2/59, 3%). Polymicrobial infections accounted for 14% (8/59). Conclusion. A high percentage of atypical microorganisms causing community-acquired pneumonia were found (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Valle, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piris-García, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Cacho, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tazón-Varela, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallo-Terán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Mier, LA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Conocer los microorganismos más frecuentes en nuestro medio nos puede ayudar a tomar decisiones terapéuticas empíricas. El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar la etiología microbiológica de las neumonías adquiridas en la comunidad. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio observacional descriptivo prospectivo. Se incluyeron sujetos&amp;#8805;14 años con diagnóstico clínico-radiográfico de neumonía adquirida en la comunidad durante 383 días consecutivos. Se recogieron variables sociodemográficas, antecedentes personales, escalas pronósticas de gravedad, evolución y agentes patógenos. Para obtener un diagnóstico etiológico se realizaron hemocultivos, detección de antígenos urinarios de Streptococcus pneumoniae y Legionella pneumophila, cultivo de esputo, virus influenza y detección de Streptococcus pyogenes. Se describieron las variables categóricas como valor absoluto y porcentaje y las variables continuas por sus medias y desviaciones estándar. Resultados. Fueron incluidos en el estudio 287 pacientes (42% mujeres; edad media 66±22 años). Falleció el 10,45%, ingresando el 70%. Se consiguió un diagnóstico etiológico en 43 pacientes (14,98%), determinándose 16 microorganismos en 59 muestras positivas. El patógeno más frecuentemente aislado fue Streptococcus pneumoniae (24/59, 41%), seguido de bacilos entéricos gramnegativos, Klebsiella pneumoniae, Escherichia coli, Serratia marcescens y Enterobacter cloacae, aislados en un 20% de las muestras (12/59), virus influenza (5/59, 9%), Staphylococcus aureus, todos resistentes a meticilina (3/59, 5%), Pseudomonas aeruginosa (2/59, 3%), Moraxella catarrhalis (2/59, 3%), Legionella pneumophila (2/59, 3%) y Haemophilus influenzae (2/59, 3%). Las infecciones polimicrobianas supusieron el 14% (8/59). Conclusión. Encontramos un alto porcentaje de microorganismos no habituales en neumonías adquiridas en la comunidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);43(6): 437-444, sept. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166697</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aumento de microorganismos no habituales en la neumonía adquirida en la comunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4835^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4835^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
