<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107817</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug treatment in surgical patients with electrolyte imbalances</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To qualitatively and quantitatively determine electrolyte imbalances (potassium, phosphorus, magnesium and calcium) in patients admitted for general and gastrointestinal surgery, the degree of these imbalances in percentage detected by medical staff, and the acceptance of the recommendations made by the Hospital Pharmacy Department. Method Seven-month prospective study. Any alteration detected was recorded on a data collection form (personal data, hospital ward, type of alteration, detection by medical staff, type of pharmaceutical intervention, form of notification, acceptance of the intervention, date of imbalance correction, patient receiving parenteral nutrition).Results100 imbalances were detected in 66 patients (231 analytical tests revised). A total of 78 interventions were carried out. Most changes were due to hypokalaemia and hypomagnesaemia, hypophosphataemia being the most frequent abnormality in patients receiving parenteral nutrition. The acceptance of pharmaceutical intervention was higher if the information was oral (100% vs. 35% written). Twice the number of analytical tests were performed after interventions (RR: 2.1, 95% CI: 1.11 to 3.94, P=.006). When pharmaceutical intervention was accepted there was a greater number of imbalance resolutions in comparison with those cases which did not accept (RR: 1.5, 95% CI: 1.01 to 2.24, P=.04).Conclusions This study shows that electrolyte imbalances are common in surgical patients and the level of detection and monitoring by medical staff is low. Therefore, the pharmacist could help in improving this aspect (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miana-Mena, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Suñé, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribas-Sala, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diego-Del Río, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solà-Bonada, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carcelero-San Martín, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Determinar cuali y cuantitativamente las alteraciones electrolíticas (relacionadas con potasio, fósforo, magnesio y calcio) en pacientes ingresados en áreas de cirugía general y gastrointestinal, el porcentaje de dichas alteraciones detectado por el equipo médico y el grado de aceptación de las recomendaciones realizadas desde el Servicio de Farmacia Hospitalaria. Método Estudio prospectivo de 7 meses. Toda alteración detectada se registró en una hoja de recogida de datos (datos personales, sala de hospitalización, tipo de alteración, detección por equipo médico, tipo de intervención farmacéutica, modo de notificación, aceptación de la intervención, fecha de corrección de la alteración, paciente en tratamiento con nutrición parenteral).Resultados Se detectaron 100 alteraciones en 66 pacientes (231 analíticas revisadas). Se realizaron un total de 78 intervenciones. La mayoría de alteraciones se debieron a hipokalemias e hipomagnesemias, siendo la hipofosfatemia la alteración más frecuente en pacientes portadores de nutrición parenteral. El grado de aceptación de la intervención farmacéutica por parte del equipo médico fue superior cuando la información fue oral (100 vs 35% escrita). Se consiguió el doble de analíticas de comprobación tras las intervenciones (RR 2,1; IC 95% 1,11-3,94, p=0,006). La aceptación de la intervención comportó una mayor proporción de resoluciones de la alteración respecto a los casos en los que no se aceptó (RR 1,5; IC 95% 1,01-2,24, p=0,04).Conclusiones Este estudio pone de manifiesto que las alteraciones electrolíticas en pacientes quirúrgicos son frecuentes y su grado de detección y seguimiento por parte del equipo médico es bajo. Por ello, el farmacéutico podría contribuir en la mejora de dichos aspectos participando en la atención a estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;36(2): 84-91, Mar. -Abr. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención farmacéutica en pacientes quirúrgicos con alteraciones electrolíticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4645^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7186^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8449^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
