<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130950</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: The inversion of medicinal products marketing and distribution network circuits is an emergent illegal activity that results in serious threat to public health. Wholesale distributors obtain medicinal products from high street pharmacies instead of supplying them; and pharmacies become involved in wholesale distribution instead of focusing strictly on their legitimate function of dispensing the medicines to individual patients. This practice has expanded in the country due to price differentials between Spain and other European states. This activity is known as &#147;reverse pharmaceutical traffic&#148;. The aims were to explain the operation of the agents involved and provide an effective inspection methodology. Materials and Methods: Based on proving the inversion of the supply channel among the agents involved, hindered by a systematic and deliberate impediment to the inspection tasks. Such methodology includes activities like studies of purchasing data against sales, deliveries against sales, and analysis of the billing information systems to the Health Service. Not (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Costa, Elia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pose Reino, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvaro Esteban, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Martín, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cadórniga Valiño, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Mourelle, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La inversión de los circuitos de comercialización de medicamentos en la red de distribución es una actividad ilícita emergente en España y compromete seriamente la salud pública. Los almacenes farmacéuticos pasan a abastecerse de medicamentos a través de oficinas de farmacias, en lugar deponerlos a su disposición, y las oficinas de farmacia pasan a hacer actividades de suministro a éstos en lugar de dispensarlos a los pacientes. Se ha extendido en el territorio nacional debido a la diferencia de precios entre España y el resto de países de la Unión Europea. El objetivo fue explicar la operativa de estos agentes y dar a conocer una metodología de trabajo inspector efectiva. Material y Métodos: Probar la inversión del canal de suministro de medicamentos entre los agentes: estudio de datos de compras frente a ventas, de entregas y trazabilidad de los pedidos, y de los sistemas de información de facturación al Servicio de Salud. No necesita la colaboración del establecimiento inspeccionado. Resultados: Cuando no se tenía un tipo (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;55(4): 1-7, oct.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130950</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tráfico inverso: una actividad ilícita emergente en la cadena de suministro de medicamentos en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4398^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51461</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
