<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102284</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychopathological disorders and quality of life in patients with brain infarction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To study the influence of various factors on the health related quality of life (HRQOL) of patients who have suffered a brain infarction (BI), with special attention to psychopathological disorders (PD). Patients and methods: Prospective observational study on 45 patients admitted due to a BI, evaluated at 4, 12 and 26 weeks of the acute event. Social and demographic data, and medical history were collected; the SF-36 scale was used for the assessment of HRQOL, and the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI), MMSE, Canadian Neurological Scale, Modified Rankin Scale and other instruments for assessing psychopathological, cognitive, neurological and functional status. A linear regression analysis was performed to identify potential predictors of the SF-36 scores at 26 weeks, introducing, as independent variables, medical and psychiatric history, demographic characteristics and the functional, neuropsychological and psychopathological assessments at 4 weeks. Results: Valid predictive models for all the SF-36 domains were obtained, in which a history of pre-morbid depression, higher scores in the NPI and Rankin Scale, and lowest in the Canadian Neurological Scale were the main predictors of a worse HRQOL in the long term. Psychopathology related caregiver's distress (assessed with the NPI) was associated with a lower score in the social function index. Conclusions: PDs and functional status were the main determinants of HRQOL in patients with BI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castellanos Pinedo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fúnez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Manchón, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Pérez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zurdo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueli Rincón, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bejarano Parra, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Bayo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Estudiar la influencia de diversos factores en la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) de los pacientes tras un infarto cerebral (IC), con especial atención a los trastornos psicopatológicos (TP). Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional prospectivo sobre 45 pacientes ingresados por IC, evaluados a las 4, 12 y 26 semanas del evento agudo. Se recogieron antecedentes y datos sociodemográficos previos, se utilizó la escala SF-36 para la valoración de la CVRS, para la valoración psicopatológica, cognitiva, neurológica y funcional se utilizó el inventario neuropsiquiátrico (NPI), MMSE, escala de Canadá, escala de Rankin modificada y otras escalas. Para determinar los posibles factores predictivos de las puntuaciones del SF-36 a las 26 semanas se realizó un estudio de regresión lineal, introduciendo como variables independientes los antecedentes médicos y psiquiátricos, las características sociodemográficas y la evaluación funcional, neuropsicológica y psicopatológica a las 4 semanas. Resultados: Se obtuvieron modelos predictivos válidos para todos los índices del SF-36, en los que el antecedente de depresión, las puntuaciones más altas en el NPI y la escala de Rankin, y más baja en la escala canadiense fueron los principales indicadores predictivos de una peor CVRS a largo plazo. El distrés del cuidador asociado a la psicopatología del paciente (medido a través del NPI) tuvo una influencia negativa sobre el índice de función social. Conclusiones: Los TP y la situación funcional fueron los principales determinantes de la CVRS de los pacientes tras un IC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;27(2): 76-82, mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102284</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos psicopatológicos y calidad de vida en el infarto cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
