<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148981</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infections in nursing homes: the most frequent microorganisms, antimicrobial use and bacterial resistance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The elderly have an increased susceptibility to infection due to factors such as the physiological changes of ageing, deterioration of the immune system and malnutrition. The EPINGER study reported that the prevalence of healthcare-related infections in nursing homes in Spain ranged from 5.8 to 38.5% while the RISS-Lérida study reported an incidence of between 3.2 and 10.6 infections per 1000 patients days. In both studies, the highest rates occurred in palliative and convalescent units, which have the shortest average length of stay. Most transfers to acute care hospitals are due to respiratory and urinary infections. Atypical symptoms of infection in the elderly and the difficulties of access to laboratory and diagnostic imaging tests encourage the frequent use of empirical treatments. Antimicrobial use is greater in palliative care units. Geriatric centers are considered to be reservoirs of antimicrobial-resistant bacteria. In Spain, as in the rest of Europe, infections caused by methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus and extended-spectrum beta-lactamase-producing Escherichia coli are becoming increasingly common in geriatric homes. In these cases, infection should be prevented and, when prevention is not feasible, transmission between residents must be limited. Hand-washing and contact precautions in wound care are essential measures for minimizing infection risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canut Blasco, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los ancianos tienen una mayor susceptibilidad a las infecciones debido a los cambios fisiológicos del envejecimiento, del deterioro del sistema inmunitario y de la malnutrición. En España la prevalencia de infección relacionada con los cuidados sanitarios en geriátricos oscila en el 5,8 y el 38,5% en el estudio EPINGER y la incidencia varía entre 3,2-10,6 infecciones/1.000 estancias según el estudio RISS-Lérida. En ambos casos, las tasas más altas se obtuvieron en las unidades de paliativos y convalecencia, que presentan menor estancia media. La mayoría de los traslados a los hospitales de agudos se debe a infecciones respiratorias y urinarias. La sintomatología atípica en el anciano infectado y la dificultad de acceso a pruebas diagnósticas de laboratorio e imagen inducen a la instauración de frecuentes tratamientos empíricos. El consumo de antimicrobianos es mayor en las unidades de cuidados paliativos. Los geriátricos están considerados como reservorios de bacterias resistentes a los antimicrobianos. En España, como en el resto de Europa, destacan por su importancia creciente en los geriátricos las infecciones producidas por Staphylococcus aureus resistente a meticilina (SARM) y Escherichia coliproductor de betalactamasa de espectro extendido. En estos casos se debe prevenir la infección, y cuando no es posible, limitar la transmisión entre residentes. El lavado de manos y las precauciones de contacto para la cura de heridas son medidas indispensables para minimizar el riesgo de infección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);42(supl.1): 27-38, sept. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148981</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones en residencias de ancianos: microorganismos más frecuentes, uso de antimicrobianos y resistencias bacterianas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
