<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040053</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9744</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Burden in caregivers of Alzheimer disease person: psychological distress and regulating factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The informal caregivers play a key role in thecare of Alzheimer disease people. The target ofthis study has been the analyse of the existingrelationship between several demographical variables,the anxiety and the social support in theperception of the burden suffered by caregivers.The study has been made in 9 men and 37 womenbetween 25 and 75 years old, with an averageage of 51,5 and a standard deviation of13,56, from different school levels and labour situations.The elements used have been the Katzindex, the STAI, the poll from social support receivedand the personal interview with the caregiver.The results indicate that the caregiverswho suffered much more burden were youngmen, with a high school level, who work outsidehome, bachelors, with no children, and a veryhigh levels of state anxiety and trait anxiety andwith not very much social support. The 77% fromthe burden from the varianza is explained by theset of variables</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Linde, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iañez Velasco, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribe Rodríguez, A. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cuidadores informales juegan un papelfundamental en el cuidado de las personas afectadasde Alzheimer. El objetivo de este estudioha sido analizar la relación que existe entre determinadasvariables sociodemográficas, la ansiedady el apoyo social en la percepción de sobrecargaque experimentan los cuidadores. Lamuestra está formada por 9 hombres y 37 mujeres,de edades comprendidas entre los 25 y 75años, con una edad media de 51,5 años y desviacióntípica de 13,56, de diferentes niveleseducativos y situación laboral. Los instrumentosutilizados han sido el índice de Katz, el STAI, elcuestionario de apoyo social percibido y la entrevistade carga del cuidador. Los resultados indicanque experimentaron mayor sobrecarga loscuidadores que son hombres, jóvenes, con estudiossuperiores, trabajan fuera del hogar, sincónyuge, sin hijos, sin hijos a su cargo, con altosvalores en ansiedad estado y ansiedad rasgo ycon menor apoyo social. El 77% de la varianzade la sobrecarga se explica por el conjunto devariables estudiadas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Geriátrika (Madr.);21(3): 103-112, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040053</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sobrecarga en cuidadores de enfermos de Alzheimer: distrés psicológico y factores moduladores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
