<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128554</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The physipathology of cerebral ischemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Knowledge of physiopathological mechanisms permits understanding of neuro-imaging changes during the various phases of cerebral ischaemia and the mechanisms of action on which many aspects of treatment are based. Development. The physiopathology of cerebral ischemia is different in the white and grey matter of the brain. In the grey matter, obstruction of a blood vessel causes an ischemic gradient. In the more peripheral zones, known as the ischemic penumbra, functional alterations occur in the neurons and the glia, although the structural integrity is maintained for some time. Liberation of glutamate and the entrance of calcium into the cells leads to a series of biochemical processes which end in neurone death. In the white matter, loss of energy alters the direction of the ion exchange pumps, resulting in calcium entering the axon. Liberation of GABA activates specific receptors which protect the nerve fibres from the consequences of anoxia. Conclusions. The cerebral oedema which accompanies ischemia has a double mechanism: initially it is cytotoxic and then vasogenic. Both contribute to increase the neurological damage caused by cerebral ischaemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El conocimiento de los mecanismos fisiopatológicos permite comprender las modificaciones de la neuroimagen durante las diversas fases de la isquemia cerebral y los mecanismos de acción en los que se basan muchos aspectos terapéuticos. Desarrollo. La fisiopatología de la isquemia cerebral es diferente en la sustancia gris y blanca del cerebro. En la sustancia gris, la obstrucción de un vaso sanguíneo ocasiona un gradiente isquémico; en  la zona más periférica, denominada la penumbra isquémica, se originan alteraciones funcionales de las neuronas y de la glía, pero con preservación de su integridad estructural durante algún tiempo. La liberación de glutamato y la entrada de calcio en las células origina la puesta en marcha de una serie de procesos bioquímicos que terminan con la muerte neuronal. En la sustancia blanca, la pérdida de la capacidad energética altera la dirección de las bombas de intercambio iónico, produciéndose la entrada de calcio en el axón. La liberación del GABA activa receptores específicos que protegen a las fibras nerviosas de las consecuencias de la anoxia. Conclusiones. El edema cerebral que acompaña a la isquemia tiene un doble mecanismo: inicialmente es citotóxico y posteriormente vasogénico. Ambos contribuyen al aumento del daño neurológico ocasionado por la isquemia cerebral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;30(5): 459-464, mar. 2000. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128554</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fisiopatología de la isquemia cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32219^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30204^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5819^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23571^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1955^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
