<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110322</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Saw palmetto Berry improves BHP symptoms and sexual dysfunctions. Results from a pilot trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The benign prostate hiperplasia (BPH) is a major risk factor for sexual dysfunctions. Additionally, the standard treatments for BPH symptoms, alpha-blockers and 5alpha-reductase inhibitors, cause sexual dysfunction themselves. Preparations from saw palmetto (Serenoa repens (W. Bartram) Small) fruit have shown efficacy and good tolerability been used to treat sexual dysfunctions. We conducted an open, multicentric, clinical pilot trial to investigate wheter Prostasan (marketed in Spian as Sabalsan), a preparation of saw palmetto fruit, influenced BPH symptoms and sexual dysfunctions. Eighty two patients participated in a 8-week trial, taking one capsule (320mg) of the saw palmetto lipophilic extract daily. At the end of the treatment, the International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) was reduced from 14.4 to 6.9 (p&lt;0.0001). Sexual dysfunctions measured with the brief Sexual Function Inventory improved from 22.4 to 31.4 (p&lt;0.0001), and the score of the component regarding sexual life of the life quality questionnaire for benign prostatic syperplasia (Urolife BPH QoL-9 sex) improved from 13.7 to 195 (p&lt;0.0001). Investigators´and patients´assessments confirmed the efficacy, tolerability and acceptance by the patients. Correlation analyses confirmed the relationship between improved BPH symptoms and reduced sexual dysfunction. This is the first trial with Sabal serrulata showing improvement in BPH symptoms and in sexual dysfunction as well(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saller, Reinhard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heinrich, Michael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suter, Andreas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riedi, Eugen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hyperplasia prostática benigna (HPB) es un importante factor de riesgo para la disfunción sexual. Además, el tratamiento estándar, los bloqueadores alpha-adrenérgicos y  los inhibidores de la 5alpha-reductasa pueden causar a su vez disfunción sexual. Los preparados del fruto de sabal (Serenoa repens (W. Bartram) Samall son un tratamiento eficaz y bien tolerado para la HPB leve o moderada y se han utilizado tradicionalmente para tratar disfunciones sexuales. Se ha llevado a cabo un estudio clínico piloto, abierto, multicéntrico para investigar si el preparado de fruto de sabal Prostasan (comercializado en España como  Sabalsan) influye en los síntomas de la HPB y las disfunciones sexuales. Ochenta y dos pacientes participaron en el estudio, de 8 semanas de duración, tomando una cápsula diaria (320mg) de un extracto lipofílico de fruto de sabal. Al final del tratamiento, la puntuación en la escala internacional de síntomas prostáticos (IPSS) se redujo de 14,4 a 6,9 (p&lt;0,0001); las disfunciones sexuales, medidas con el inventario breve de la función sexual mejoraron de 22,4 a 31,4 (p&lt;0,0001); la puntuación del componente de la vida sexual del cuestionario de calidad de vida para la HPB (Urolife BHP QoL-9 sex), mejoró de 137,3 a 195 (p&lt;0,0001). Las evaluaciones de los investigadores y pacientes confirmaron la eficacia, tolerabilidad y aceptación por los pacientes. Los análisis de correlación confirmaron la vinculación entre la mejoría de los síntomas de la HPB y la reducción de la disfunción sexual. Este es el primer estudio que demuestra una mejoría simultánea en los síntomas de la HPB y las disfunciones sexuales con extracto de fruto de sabal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;12(2): 119-133, dic.2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110322</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El fruto de sabal mejora los síntomas de la hiperplasia benigna de próstata y la disfunción sexual. Resultados de un estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35701^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35701^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27338^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
