<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115790</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prenatal diagnosis of congenital intracranial tumors: Immature teratoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fetal intracranial tumors are uncommon and are mostly located in the supratentorialregion. The most frequent forms are teratomas. These neoplasms are usually suspected on the basis of obstetric ultrasound examination, the most frequent signs being macrocephaly, hydrocephalus, ventriculomegaly, polyhydramnios and intracranial mass. Prognosis is generally poor, depending on tumoral size and histological type. We report the case of a 32-week fetus with an ultrasonographic diagnosis of intracranial tumor. The histological analysis confirmed the presence of a congenital immature teratoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Polo-García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Laencina, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huelbes-Ros, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva-Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad-Martínez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera-Giménez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla-Paricio, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores fetales intracraneales son poco frecuentes. La mayoría se localizan a nivel supratentorial. Los tipos más frecuentes encontrados son los teratomas. Suelen sospecharse por ecografía obstétrica, siendo los signos más frecuentes macrocefalia, hidrocefalia, ventriculomegalia, polihidramnios y masa intracraneal. De forma global, su pronóstico es infausto, dependiendo del tamaño y del tipo histológico del tumor. Presentamos el caso de un feto de 32 semanas de edad gestacional con diagnóstico ecográfico de tumoración intracraneal, cuyo resultado histológico confirmó teratoma inmaduro congénito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);38(6): 240-243, nov.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115790</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico prenatal de tumores congénitos intracraneales: teratoma inmaduro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
