<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107505</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paradoxical embolism associated with hysterosalpingography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hysterosalpingography is a procedure used in the study of infertility. Embolism of contrast dye is a rare complication and is facilitated by certain factors. Persistence of permeable foramen ovale (PFO) complicates the prognosis and may produce paradoxical embolisms. We present the case of a 32-year-old woman who was referred from a district hospital due to an ischemic stroke following a hysterosalpingography reported as difficult, requiring a higher dose of contrast medium (diatrizoic acid) than usual. A cranial computed tomography scan was performed, which showed a right hemispheric stroke. Post-event echocardiography revealed a PFO. Eight days after the event, the patient showed progressive improvement and was able to walk without assistance. Consequently, she was discharged from hospital with antiplatelet therapy. The symptomology in this patient, as well as the findings of the diagnostic tests, are highly suggestive of ischemic stroke of the middle cerebral artery secondary to paradoxical embolism of the contrast medium through the PFO. A review of the topic is provided (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pérez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trabalón Pastor, Martina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Alonso, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fiol Ruiz, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdera Simbron, Carlos Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galvez Contreras, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La histerosalpingografía (HSG) es un procedimiento utilizado en el estudio de la infertilidad. La embolia del medio de contraste es una complicación infrecuente y está favorecida por ciertos factores. La persistencia del foramen oval permeable (FOP) complica el pronóstico, ya que puede producir embolias paradójicas. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 32 años, derivada de un hospital comarcal por accidente cerebrovascular isquémico tras realizarse una HSG informada como dificultosa, precisando una dosis mayor de contraste (ácido diazitroico) que la habitual. Se realizó una tomografía computarizada craneal que mostró infarto cerebral hemisférico derecho. La ecocardiografía posterior al acontecimiento reveló la existencia de un FOP. Tras 8 días de evolución, la paciente presentó mejoría progresiva del déficit, con capacidad para deambular autónomamente, por lo que se procedió al alta hospitalaria con tratamiento antiagregante domiciliario. La clínica acontecida en esta paciente y los hallazgos encontrados en las pruebas diagnósticas son altamente sugestivos de ictus isquémico de la arteria cerebral media secundario a embolismo paradójico del medio de contraste a través del FOP, por lo que resulta interesante realizar una revisión del tema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);55(10): 514-517, dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107505</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ictus paradójico asociado a histersalpingografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23287^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52605^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32952^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23287^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32952^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32952^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52605^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52605^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23287^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23287^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
