<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106180</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: a study was designed to assess the role of proteomics in the identi&amp;#64257;cation of differential proteins in patient with obstructive sleep apnea-hypopnea syndrome (OSAH). Patients and methods: Thirty seven patients with symptoms suggestive of OSAH and a apnea-hypopnea index (AHI) &amp;#8805; 5 were included in the study, and a control group was made up of 18 snorers, matched for BMI, gender and age with the OSAH group in which one OSAH was discarded (AHI &lt; 5). Subjects diagnosed with advanced chronic disease were excluded from both groups.  First, two-dimensional electrophoresis was performed, which compared the gels of both groups and established the differential spots (over-expression &gt; 2.5 times the control group and under-expression &lt; 0.5 times below the control group). Subsequently, a mass spectrometry was performed by means of MALDI / TOF-TOF (matrix laser assisted desorption - time of &amp;#64258;ight). Results: Regarding the control group, mean AHI = was 3.5 (3-4.1), and in those affected with OSAH it was, AHI = 53 (27-74). , Aan over-expressed protein, haptoglobin, was identi&amp;#64257;ed by means of  MALDI/TOF-TOF, which has been related with a greater vascular risk in patient with OSAH.  Likewise, two under-expressed proteins, albumin and serotransferrin, were identi&amp;#64257;ed, proteins that can facilitate a decrease of the anti-oxidant defences in OSAH. Conclusions: An initial differential proteomic pro&amp;#64257;le in mature patients with OSAH was found. The legitimacy of proteomics to identify a group of differential proteins that could be useful to diagnosis or establish a pro&amp;#64257;le of vascular risk has been demonstrated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arenas Delarriva, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jurado Gámez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bujalance Cabrera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Cabrera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Chaparro, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feu Collado, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Ballesteros, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz  Calero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Se diseña un estudio con el objetivo de valorar el papel de la  proteómica en la identi&amp;#64257;cación de proteínas diferenciales en pacientes con SAHS. Pacientes y métodos: Fueron incluidos 37 enfermos con sintomatología sugestiva de SAHS y un IAH &amp;#8805; 5 y  un grupo control compuesto por 18 sujetos roncadores, emparejados por IMC, género  y edad con el grupo con SAHS en los que se descartó un SAHS (IAH &lt; 5). En ambos grupos se excluyeron a los sujetos que estaban diagnosticados de enfermedad crónica avanzada. En primer lugar se efectuó electroforesis bidimensional que comparó los geles de ambos grupos y estableció los spots diferenciales (sobreexpresión &gt; 2,5 veces el grupo control y subexpresión &lt; 0,5 veces por debajo del grupo control). Posteriormente se realizó espectrometría de masas mediante MALDI /TOF-TOF (matrix laser assisted desorption- time of   &amp;#64258;ight).Resultados: Respecto al grupo control, IAH = 3,5 (3-4,1), en los enfermos con SAHS, IAH = 53 (27-74), mediante MALDI/TOF-TOF se identi&amp;#64257;có una proteína sobreexpresada, la haptoglobina que se ha relacionado con mayor riesgo vascular en pacientes con SAHS. Igualmente se identi&amp;#64257;caron dos proteínas subexpresadas, la albúmina y serotransferrina, proteínas que pueden facilitar una disminución de las defensas antioxidantes en el SAHS. Conclusiones: Se aporta el primer per&amp;#64257;l proteómico diferencial en pacientes adultos con SAHS. Se demuestra la validez de la proteómica para identi&amp;#64257;car un conjunto de proteínas diferenciales que puedan ser útiles para el diagnóstico o para establecer un per&amp;#64257;l de riesgo vascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;24(3): 272-278, jul.-sept. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106180</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la proteómica en la identificación de proteínas diferenciales en pacientes con SAHS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54252^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13441^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24016^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201207</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
