<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130806</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyponatremic encephalopathy resulting from the use of hyponatremic fluids. Could it have been avoided in this case?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The dilutional and iatrogenic hyponatremia is an underdiagnosed and avoidable situation, that can result in a life threatening condition, such as cerebral edema. The intravenous administration of hyponatremic fluids, as a maintenance fluid therapy according to Holliday &amp; Segar, has been related with this entity or the worsening of mild hyponatremia in acute ill pediatric patients and also postoperative pediatric patients. These patient's kidneys are unable of excrete free water because of an excess of antidiuretic hormone (ADH) effect. Best evidence at the present time says that isonatremic maintenance fluids can prevent hyponatremia and its health threatening consequences. We report a case of successful development and deeply insist on the necessary changes that paediatricians must do on using intravenous isotonic saline solutions instead of hyponatremic fluids (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torrecilla Caña, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rius Peris, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Muela, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Modesto i Alapont, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cueto Calvo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiponatremia dilucional yatrogénica es una entidad clínica infradiagnosticada y evitable, que puede tener consecuencias mortales, como el edema cerebral agudo. La administración de fluidos intravenosos hiposódicos de mantenimiento, según la pauta clásica de Holliday y Segar, es un factor determinante para la aparición de dicha entidad o para el agravamiento de las formas leves de hiponatremia, sobre todo en los pacientes pediátricos tras cirugía o ingresados por patologías agudas, cuyo riñón es incapaz de excretar agua libre por un exceso de hormona antidiurética (ADH). Los fluidos isonatrémicos pueden prevenir la aparición de la citada hiponatremia y sus temibles complicaciones. Presentamos un caso de evolución satisfactoria, con objeto de concienciar al personal sanitario de la necesidad de abandonar los fluidos hiposódicos y utilizar como fluidos de mantenimiento aquellos con un contenido de sodio más próximo al del plasma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;72(10): e356-e363, nov. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130806</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encefalopatía hiponatrémica como consecuencia de la utilización de fluidos hiposódicos. ¿Pudo haberse evitado en este caso?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7189^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1953^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4072^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7721^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
