<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128652</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ischemic optic neuropathy following a dural arteriovenous fistula. Vascular steal phenomenon</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report. We report the case of a 46-year-old patient, with a dural arteriovenous fistula in the left cavernous sinus fed by dural branches of both carotid siphons, by recurrent branches of the left ophthalmic artery (LOA) and by dural branches of the left external carotid artery. Twenty-four hours after arterial embolization with polyvinyl alcohol particles, the patient suffered visual loss in the left eye. All feeders were embolized except the recurrent branches of the LOA, which became hypertrophied. Fluorescein angiography of the retina was normal. Transocular Doppler ultrasound showed a turbulent, inverted, low resistance flow in the LOA distal part, and a high resistance anterograde flow in the left central artery of the retina, which accounted for an ischemic optic neuropathy. Conclusions. The ischemic optic neuropathy resulted from a vascular steal phenomenon. Hypertrophy of recurrent branches of the LOA, after embolization of the remaining feeders, contributed to a low resistance shunt between the LOA proximal part and the left cavernous sinus. This shunt caused the inversion of flow in the distal part of the artery and the subsequent decrease of retrobulbar blood supply (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Batista, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tuna, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xavier, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morals Silva, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bastos Lelte, AJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico. Paciente de 46 años, con una fístula arteriovenosa dural del seno cavernoso izquierdo, alimentada por ramificaciones durales de los dos sifones carotídeos, por ramificaciones recurrentes de la región proximal de la arteria oftálmica izquierda (AOI) y por ramificaciones de la arteria carótida externa homolateral. Después de 24 horas desde la embolización arterial con partículas de polivinil alcohol, sufrió un déficit visual del ojo izquierdo. Todos los pedículos alimentadores de la fístula se embolizaron, excepto las ramificaciones de la AOI, que se hipertrofiaron tras la embolización de las restantes. A pesar de la normalidad de la angiografía fluoresceínica retiniana, la ecografía Doppler transocular mostró un flujo turbulento, invertido y de baja resistencia en la región distal de la AOI, y un flujo anterógrado de alta resistencia en la arteria central de la retina homolateral, lo cual justifica una neuropatía óptica isquémica. Conclusiones. La neuropatía óptica isquémica se produjo como consecuencia de un fenómeno de robo vascular. La hipertrofia de las ramificaciones de la región proximal de la AOI, tras la embolización de los restantes pedículos alimentadores de la fístula, contribuyó en una comunicación de baja resistencia entre la región proximal de la arteria oftálmica y el seno cavernoso izquierdo, y causó la inversión del flujo en el tramo distal de la mencionada arteria y la consecuente disminución de la irrigación sanguínea retrobulbar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(11): 1032-1034, dic. 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128652</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuropatía óptica isquémica tras la embolización arterial de una fístula arteriovenosa dural. Fenómeno del robo vascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10061^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2464^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32660^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
