<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14610</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between visuospatial impairment and oculomotor parameters in Parkinson's disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Visuospatial functions and oculomotor parameters were studied in a sample of 96 patients with Parkinson&#146;s Disease (PD). Visuospatial deficits correlated with both motor impairment and severity of illness, as well as with oculomotor abnormalities. Partial correlations were performed to determine whether visuospatial impairment was secondary to oculomotor disorders. After controlling for gaze pursuit variables and saccades, Block Design (WAIS) and Line Orientation Test maintained their correlations with motor impairment and severity of illness. In conclusion, the results of the present study show that visuospatial deficits cannot be explained through oculomotor abnormalities in PD patients, pointing to a simultaneous expression of striatum dysfunction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roig, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Junqué, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vendrell, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau Veciana, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bruna, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se han estudiado las funciones visoespaciales y los parámetros oculomotores en una muestra de 96 pacientes afectados por Enfermedad de Parkinson 8EP). Los déficit visoespaciales han correlacionado con el deterioro a nivel motor y la gravedad de la enfermedad, así como con las anormalidades oculomotoras. Se realizaron correlaciones parciales con la finalidad de determinar si las alteraciones visoespaciales podían considerarse secundarias a los trastornos oculomotores. Las pruebas de Cubos de las Escala WAIS y el Test de Orientación de Líneas mantenían su correlación con la alteración motora y la gravedad de la enfermedad, tras haber controlado las variables de persecución y los movimientos sacádicos. En síntesis, los resultados del presente estudio muestran que los déficits visoespaciales no pueden ser explicados por anormalidades oculomotoras en los pacientes con EP, pudiendo considerarse ambos expresión del defecto estriatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(2): 187-191, mayo 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre las alteraciones visoespaciales y los parámetros oculomotores en la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10660^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24810^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34222^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
