<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124541</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Overdose prevention in injecting opioid users: The role of substance abuse treatment and training programs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Opioid overdose is still the first cause of preventable death among young men in Barcelona. Sound knowledge of opioid overdose prevention is important to avoid complications and deaths. This study aimed to identify the factors associated with limited knowledge of overdose prevention and to assess the possible effect of treatment and overdose prevention training programs on this variable. Methods From October 2008 to March 2009, current injecting opioid users attending harm reduction centers in Catalonia (Spain) were interviewed. Crude and adjusted prevalence ratios of limited knowledge about overdose prevention were calculated by adjusting Poisson regression models with a robust variance. Results In this sample, 28.7% of clients had limited knowledge of overdose prevention. Factors associated with limited knowledge were country of origin, never having received treatment for drug dependency, having a low educational level, and never having experienced an overdose. In contrast, treatment at the time of the interview was not associated with a lower prevalence of limited knowledge about overdose prevention. Conclusions These findings suggest that preventive programs would benefit from accounting for linguistic and educational limitations and from participation in every treatment episode. Comprehensiveness and broad coverage of such programs could help to maximize their impact (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Folch, Cinta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Majó, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espelt, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vecino, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugal, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casabona, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarasa-Renedo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La sobredosis por opioides sigue siendo la primera causa de muerte prevenible entre hombres jóvenes en Barcelona. El conocimiento profundo acerca de la prevención de sobredosis es importante a fin de evitar complicaciones y muertes. Los objetivos de este estudio fueron la identificación de aquellos factores asociados a un conocimiento limitado acerca de la prevención de sobredosis, y la evaluación del posible efecto sobre dicha variable del tratamiento y de la asistencia a talleres de prevención de sobredosis. Métodos Estudio transversal, mediante encuesta a usuarios de opioides por vía parenteral que acudieron a centros de reducción de daños de Cataluña entre octubre de 2008 y marzo de 2009. Se obtuvieron ratios de prevalencia crudas y ajustadas de Conocimiento limitado sobre prevención de sobredosis mediante la realización de modelos de regresión de Poisson con varianza robusta. Resultados El 28,7% de los usuarios entrevistados presentaba Conocimiento limitado sobre prevención de sobredosis. Los factores asociados a dicho Conocimiento limitado fueron el país de origen, no haber recibido tratamiento por el consumo de drogas, tener un menor nivel educativo, y nunca haber sufrido una sobredosis. El hecho de estar en tratamiento en el momento de la entrevista no se asoció a una menor prevalencia de conocimiento limitado sobre prevención de sobredosis. Conclusiones Estos hallazgos sugieren que los programas de prevención de sobredosis se verían beneficiados por tener en cuenta posibles limitaciones lingüísticas y educacionales, así como por estar integrados en todos los episodios de tratamiento. La exhaustividad y una cobertura elevada pueden ayudar a maximizar el impacto de dichos programas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(2): 146-154, mar.-abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124541</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d54899</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6715^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24888^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31825^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
