<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139729</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional problems in spanish women; results from the ANIBES study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: women may be nutritionally vulnerable across life stage and due to different physiological situations. Therefore, availability of updated data on several determinants (e.g. dietary energy intake and food sources) are urgently needed. The very recent ANIBES (&#147;Anthropometry, Intake, and Energy Balance in Spain&#148;) Study is an unique tool to evaluate nutritional status in spanish women. Goal: to describe and analyze energy intake, its determinants and food sources in the spanish women: findings from the ANIBES Study. Methods: the data were derived from The ANIBES (&#147;Anthropometry, Intake, and Energy Balance in Spain&#148;) Study, a cross-sectional study on a national representative sample of the Spanish population (9-75 years old). A 3-day dietary record by means of a tablet device was used to collect food and beverage consumption and discards. The final sample was comprised of 2009 (1013 men and 996 women) individuals. New emerging tools (i.e. tablet devices for food and beverages recording, and accelerometers for physical activity level have been used. Anthropometry measurements and socioeconomic determinants were also evaluated. Results: the observed mean dietary energy intake in the Spanish women was 1660 ± 426.7 kcal/day. Highest intakes were observed among adolescents aged 13 to 17 years and children, both age groups were the only ones to reach the EFSA average requirements. Of concern is the low energy intake for the elderly women (65-75 years), 1476 ± 359.9 kcal/d, which may compromise an adequate nutrient density. Contributions to caloric profile añadir: were inadequate: 17.0%E from proteins; 41.2%E from carbohydrates, and 38.7%E from lipids. Cereals/grains (27.0%), meats and derivatives (14.1%), oils and fats (13.1%) and milk and dairy products (12.4%) contributed most to daily energy intake. Discussion: results are discussed based on how may be affect the quality of the diet for the Spanish women, and compared to other recent dietary surveys in Spain, as well as within the European context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varela Moreiras, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la mujer presenta una situación de vulnerabilidad en su estado nutricional a lo largo de las diferentes etapas de la vida y las diversas situaciones fisiológicas. La necesidad de información lo más actualizada y precisa sobre los determinantes del estado nutricional, y de manera específica la cuantificación de la dieta, ha dado lugar al Estudio ANIBES (&#147;Antropometría, Ingesta y Balance Energético en España&#148;), en una población española representativa de entre 9 y 75 años. Objetivo: describir y evaluar algunos de los resultados disponibles de ingesta energética y fuentes alimentarias en la población femenina española, derivados del Estudio ANIBES. Métodos: en una muestra representativa (n = 2009, 996 mujeres/1013 hombres) de la población española (9-75 años), se ha determinado antropometría, estudio de la dieta mediante nuevas tecnologías (&#147;tablets&#148;), actividad física mediante acelerometría y cuestionario validado, así como un estudio de percepción sobre diferentes aspectos de la alimentación, la nutrición, la actividad física y, en definitiva, del balance energético. Resultados: la ingesta energética ha sido de 1660 ± 426.7 kcal/d, significativamente inferior a la de la población masculina. Cuando se analiza por grupos de edad, solo las niñas (9-12 años) y adolescentes (13-17 años) alcanzan las recientes recomendaciones establecidas por EFSA. De manera especial, la ingesta media observada de energía en las mujeres más mayores (65-75 años), 1476 ± 359.9 kcal/d refleja dificultades para una adecuada densidad nutricional. El perfil calórico es desequilibrado (17%E a partir de proteína; 41,2% de hidratos de carbono; 38,7% para los lípidos), y lo es para todos los grupos de edad. La principal fuente energética la constituyen los cereales y derivados (27%), los productos cárnicos y derivados (14,1%), los aceites y grasas (13,1%), y la leche y derivados (12,4%). Discusión: los resultados se discuten de manera esquemática de acuerdo a su potencial repercusión en la calidad nutricional de la dieta de la mujer española actual, la comparación con otros estudios en nuestro país, así como el entorno europeo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(supl.1): 14-19, jul. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139729</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Problemática nutricional en la población femenina española; resultados del Estudio ANIBES</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55398^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51826^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
