<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147152</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results of competency based teaching innovation program in pre-graduate Pediatrics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of our study was to analyse the effects of a competency-based teaching innovation program in undergraduate pediatric students and to evaluate its results performing an objective structured clinical examination (OSCE) which evaluated knowledge, history taking, communication, physical examination, technical skills and management of clinical situations. Methods. 145 students enrolled in the Pediatrics Clinical Practice Course participated. New methods of acquiring clinical competences were designed, using a virtual learning platform, a structured clinical rotations and medical simulation training. OSCE was performed to evaluate all the process. Results. All students achieved the level of competence for the structured clinical rotations. The use of virtual platform was adequate to achieve the planned educational objectives. All students accomplished the techniques scheduled for the medical simulation training. Cronbach&#146;s alpha of the OSCE was 0.75. In competence based assessment significant statistical changes were considered in negative results of history taking (confidence interval 95% -1.751 -2.123) and in the management of clinical situations (confidence interval 95% -0.930 -1.174) with respect to the other competences. Conclusions. The introduction using distance coaching methods is effective in undergraduate studies. Simulation techniques and the structured clinical rotation are applicable and suitable for competence training. New actions to improve the history taking competence and management of clinical situations in undergraduate medical students are needed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Guisasola, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coco Martín, MB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado Asensio, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrote Molpeceres, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbaneja Rodríguez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino Vázquez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayo Iscar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de nuestro estudio fue analizar los efectos de un programa de innovación docente basado en competencias en el pregrado de pediatría e investigar los resultados de una evaluación por competencias de conocimientos, anamnesis, comunicación, exploración física, habilidades técnicas y manejo de situaciones clínicas, mediante un examen clínico objetivo estructurado (ECOE). Material y Métodos. En 2013, en la asignatura Práctica Clínica de Pediatría se implantaron nuevas metodologías de adquisición de competencias mediante un aula virtual, un rotatorio estructurado con tutor y un aula de habilidades y se efectuó una evaluación ECOE, completando el proceso 145 alumnos. Resultados. Todos los alumnos alcanzaron el nivel exigido de las competencias programadas en el rotatorio estructurado con tutor. La utilización del aula virtual fue adecuada a los objetivos educativos. Todos los alumnos aplicaron las técnicas programadas en el aula de habilidades. El alfa de Cronbach de la prueba ECOE fue de 0,75. En la evaluación por competencias se aprecian como relevantes las diferencias en los resultados negativos en anamnesis (intervalo de confianza al 95%: -1,751 -2,123) y manejo de situaciones clínicas (intervalo de confianza al 95%: -0,930 -1,174) con respecto al resto de competencias. Conclusiones. La introducción del nuevo programa de innovación docente basado en competencias es efectivo en los estudios pregrado. Las técnicas de simulación y la estructuración de los rotatorios clínicos son aplicables y adecuados para la formación por competencias. Son necesarias acciones de mejora en el pregrado de medicina para las competencias de anamnesis y manejo de situaciones clínicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;55(234): 232-242, abr. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados de un programa de innovación docente basado en competencias en el Pregrado de Pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10114</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11241^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
