<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139756</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bisphosphonate-associated maxillary osteonecrosis in osteoporosis patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bisphosphonates are a potent family of bone resorption inhibitors, and are used in the treatment of osteoporosis and other diseases that cause bone mass loss, such as Paget's disease, and bone metastases mainly in multiple myeloma. Since 2003, avascular osteonecrosis of the jaw has been associated with the, mainly intravenous, use of bisphosphonates. According to the literature, the occurrence of osteonecrosis of the jaw has ranged from 0,8% to 12% of the patients on bisphosphonates, most of them on prolonged use. Physicians and odontologists should be aware of this potential complication in dental treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Picardo, Silvana Noemí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez Genta, Sergio Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los bifosfonatos constituyen una familia potente de inhibidores de la reabsorción ósea. Son utilizados para el tratamiento de la osteoporosis y otras enfermedades causadas por la pérdida de masa ósea como la enfermedad de Paget, metástasis óseas en patologías oncológicas principalmente en mieloma múltiple. Desde el año 2003, se han asociado necrosis avasculares en los maxilares con el uso de dichas drogas. De acuerdo a la literatura, la ocurrencia de dicha necrosis tiene un rango entre 0,8-12% de los pacientes que son prescriptos con ellas en forma prolongada. Médicos y odontólogos deben tomar conciencia con respecto a las potenciales complicaciones relacionadas con los tratamientos dentales cruentos a emprender en dichos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;37(2): 103-107, abr.-jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139756</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteonecrosis maxilar asociada a bifosfonatos en pacientes osteoporóticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54489^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1887^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
