<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053273</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ruptured femoral mycotic aneurysm: a case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Mycotic aneurysms are infectious processes that often result in rupture and death if they are not    treated properly. We report one clinical case and review different aspects of this pathology. Case report. This study    involves the case of a 73-year-old female who was attended in the Emergency Department because of a pulsating tumour    in the right inguinal region, with fever, signs of local inflammation, palpable distal pulses and a tendency towards    hypotension. Lab findings showed leukocytosis with left shift. An emergency computerised axial tomography scan was    performed and results showed an aneurysm in the common femoral artery surrounded by a haematoma with uncertain    gas production. The patient underwent emergency surgery involving resection and placement of a prosthetic (PTFE) graft.    Intraoperative and blood cultures were positive for Salmonella enteritidis. Intravenous treatment with antibiotics was    established and maintained until the patient was discharged from hospital. The fever disappeared and blood cultures    became negative but a small amount of purulent material continued drain from the inguinal wound, with positive cultures    for the same microorganism. A computerised axial tomography scan showed an inguinal periprosthetic collection and    the scintigraphy findings revealed local pathological uptake. No other structures were involved and no evidence of    endocarditis was observed. The decision was taken to replace the graft by the contralateral greater saphenous vein, after    which the drained material disappeared and the wound progressed favourably. After 30 months&#146; follow-up, the patient    does not present any complications or signs of recurrence. Conclusions. The preferred surgical treatment for mycotic    aneurysms is still a controversial issue. Anatomical revascularisation with a venous graft is the preferred treatment when    peripheral arteries are involved and, if necessary, a prosthetic graft can be used, preferably situated extra-anatomically.    In all cases selective therapy with antibiotics should be associated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Martínez, María Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Casas, José Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Meijide, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Noya, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde Rodríguez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los aneurismas micóticos son procesos infecciosos, con resultado frecuente de ruptura y muerte si    no se tratan adecuadamente. Aportamos un caso clínico y revisamos diversos aspectos de esta patología. Caso clínico.    Mujer de 73 años, atendida en Urgencias por presentar tumoración inguinal derecha pulsátil, así como fiebre, signos inflamatorios    locales, pulsos distales conservados y tendencia a la hipotensión. La analítica demuestra leucocitosis con desviación    izquierda. Se realiza tomografía axial computarizada urgente, con hallazgo de aneurisma de arteria femoral común    rodeado de hematoma con dudoso gas. Es intervenida de urgencia, realizándose resección e interposición de injerto protésico    (PTFE). Los cultivos intraoperatorios y hemocultivos son positivos para Salmonella enteritidis. Se inicia tratamiento    con antibióticos endovenosos, que se mantienen hasta el alta. Desaparece la fiebre, se negativizan los hemocultivos, pero    persiste drenado purulento escaso a través de la herida inguinal, con cultivo positivo para el mismo microorganismo.    En la tomografía axial computarizada se objetiva colección periprotésica inguinal, así como captación patológica local en    la gammagrafía. No se afectan otras estructuras ni se evidencia endocarditis. Se decide sustituir el injerto por vena safena    mayor contralateral, con lo que desaparece el drenado y la herida evoluciona favorablemente. Tras 30 meses de seguimiento,    no presenta complicaciones o signos de recidiva. Conclusión. El tratamiento quirúrgico de elección de los aneurismas    micóticos continua siendo controvertido. La revascularización anatómica con injerto venoso resulta de elección cuando    afectan a arterias periféricas, pudiendo emplearse en caso necesario el injerto protésico, preferentemente en localización    extraanatómica. En todos los casos debe asociarse antibioterapia selectiva</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;59(2): 179-184, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053273</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aneurisma micótico femoral roto: aportación de un caso y revisión de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5367^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22360^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19385^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30855^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33283^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
