<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166430</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Introduction to genetics and its value in cardiovascular disease diagnosis: basic concepts and the example of familial hypercholesterolemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main aim of this article is to provide clinicians with the basic knowledge needed to interpret data on genetic disorders that may be relevant to clinical decision-making. The human genome is likened to an encyclopedia, «The encyclopedia of life», which is used to explain how genetic information is transmitted and to describe the causes and consequences of mutations, along with the main rules used for naming them. There follows a discussion of which mutations can contribute to the development of cardiovascular disease and how they do so. Finally, there is a description of how genetics has contributed to improvements in the diagnosis and treatment of familial hypercholesterolemia, one of the conditions in which lipid-lowering therapy is efficacious and cost-effective. In addition, there is an explanation of how large-scale genetic assays, such as biochips, are used for detecting the principle mutations found in the genes responsible for familial hypercholesterolemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Civeira, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Rey, José C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pocoví, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nuestro objetivo es proporcionar al clínico los conocimientos básicos para la interpretación de datos referidos a enfermedades genéticas que le sirvan de ayuda a la hora de tomar decisiones clínicas. Se hace un símil del genoma humano con una enciclopedia, la «enciclopedia de la vida», analizando como se transmite la información genética, las causas, las consecuencias y las principales reglas de nomenclatura de las mutaciones. Se discute a continuación qué mutaciones y cómo pueden contribuir a la aparición de la enfermedad cardiovascular. Por último, se describe la contribución de la genética a la mejora del diagnóstico y el tratamiento de la hipercolesterolemia familiar (HF), una de las entidades en que el tratamiento hipolipemiante es eficaz y coste-efectivo. Se justifica el empleo de técnicas de detección genética a gran escala como son los biochips que analizan las principales mutaciones de los genes que originan el HF (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);9(supl.B): 14b-23b, 2009. graf, ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166430</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Introducción a la genética y su utilidad en el diagnóstico de las enfermedades cardiovasculares: conceptos básicos y el ejemplo de la hipercolesterolemia familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29056^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29056^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14550^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200900</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
