<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139476</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of a school-based program to prevent obesity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Intervention for childhood obesity is a public health priority. The purpose of this study was to evaluatethe effectiveness of an elementary school-based intervention against obesity in children. Material and methods: Non-randomised controlled trial was conducted on children from first to fifth grade from two public schools of Avilés (Spain). The intervention lasted for 2 school years comprising healthy diet workshops, educational chats, educational meetings, informative written material, and promotion of physical activities. Primary outcome measure was body mass index z-score. Secondary outcomes included: obesity and overweight prevalence, waist circumference, dietary habits, and physical activity. Results: A total of 382 (177 girls, 205 boys) out of 526 pupils of both schools were included in the study. Complete anthropometric data were obtained in 340 of the 382 individuals. Compared to children in control group, those in intervention group decreased body mass index z-score from 1.14 to 1.02 (P=.017), and improved KIDMED score from 7.33 to 7.71 points (P=.045). The percentage of students who carried on an optimal diet increased from 42.6% to 52.3% (P=.021). There were no statistical differences in the prevalence of obesity and overweight, or in waist circumference between the intervention and control groups. Conclusions: This school-based program resulted in modest beneficial changes in body mass index and diet quality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suárez Tomás, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riaño Galán, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Solís, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Martín, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Caro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Menéndez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las intervenciones sobre la obesidad infantil son una prioridad para la salud pública. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la efectividad de un programa de intervención contra la obesidad en un colegio de Educación Primaria. Material y métodos: Estudio de intervención controlado no aleatorizado en alumnos de primero a quinto cursos de Educación Primaria en 2 colegios públicos de Avilés (España). La intervención se desarrolló durante 2 cursos escolares, incluyendo talleres sobre alimentación saludable, charlas educativas, material informativo escrito y promoción de la actividad física. La variable de resultado principal fue la puntuación z del índice de masa corporal (IMC). Como variables de resultado secundarias se consideraron: prevalencia de obesidad y sobrepeso, perímetro abdominal, hábitos de dieta y actividad física. Resultados: Fueron incluidos en el estudio 382 (177 niñas, 205 niños) de 526 alumnos de ambos colegios. En 340 individuos se obtuvieron datos antropométricos completos. A diferencia del grupo control, los pertenecientes al grupo de intervención disminuyeron la puntuación z del IMC desde 1,14 a 1,02 (p=0,017), mejoraron el índice KIDMED de adhesión a la dieta mediterránea de 7,33 a 7,71 puntos (p=0,045) y aumentaron la proporción de estudiantes con una dieta óptima del 42,6% al 52,3% (p=0,021). No se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la prevalencia de obesidad y sobrepeso, ni en el perímetro abdominal, entre los grupos de intervención y control. Conclusiones: Este programa escolar consiguió pequeñas mejoras en el IMC y la calidad de la dieta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);83(1): 19-25, jul. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139476</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de una intervención escolar contra la obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
