<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149768</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mortality due to traffic injuries and its impact on life expectancy: a comparison between Mexico and Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the impact of mortality due to motor vehicle traffic injuries (MVTI) compared with other causes of death on life expectancy in Mexico and Spain during the three-year periods 2000-2002 and 2010-2012 and the weight of the different age groups in years of life expectancy lost (YLEL) due to this cause. Methods: Based on official death and population data, abridged life tables in Mexico and Spain were constructed for the three-year periods studied. Temporary life expectancy and YLEL for persons aged 15 to 75 years were calculated by selected causes (MVTI, diabetes mellitus, malignant neoplasms and ischemic heart diseases) and age groups in each three-year period. Results: In Spain, YLEL decreased in both sexes from all the causes studied, especially MVTI; this reduction was greater in the younger ages. In addition, temporary life expectancy increased. In Mexico, YLEL due to MVTI increased in men, mainly in young people, and remained unchanged among women. Temporary life expectancy declined in men but increased slightly among women. Conclusions: The reduction in YLEL due to MVTI in Spain has contributed to increased life expectancy. By contrast, the increase in YLEL due to MVTI among Mexican men has contributed to the decline in male life expectancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega-López, María Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera-Pivaral, Carlos Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Pérez, Guillermo Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar el impacto de la mortalidad por lesiones por tráfico de vehículo de motor (LTVM), comparándolo con el de otras causas de muerte, en la esperanza de vida de México y España en los trienios 2000-2002 y 2010-2012, así como el grado de participación de los diferentes grupos de edad en la pérdida de años de esperanza de vida por esta causa. Métodos: A partir de datos oficiales sobre defunciones y población se construyeron tablas de vida abreviadas para México y España en los trienios estudiados. Se calculó la esperanza de vida temporaria y los años de esperanza de vida perdidos (AEVP) en el grupo de 15 a 75 años de edad, por causas seleccionadas (LTVM, diabetes mellitus, tumores malignos y enfermedades isquémicas del corazón) y por grupos de edad en cada trienio. Resultados: En España disminuyeron los AEVP en ambos sexos por todas las causas estudiadas, especialmente por LTVM; esta reducción fue mayor en las edades más jóvenes. Además, se incrementó la esperanza de vida temporaria. En México se incrementaron los AEVP por LTVM en los hombres, principalmente en los jóvenes, y permanecieron igual en las mujeres. La esperanza de vida temporaria masculina se redujo y aumentó ligeramente la femenina. Conclusiones: La reducción de los AEVP por LTVM en España ha contribuido al aumento de la esperanza de vida. Por el contrario, el incremento de los AEVP por LTVM entre los hombres mexicanos ha coadyuvado al descenso de la esperanza de vida masculina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;29(supl.1): 70-75, sept. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149768</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad por lesiones de tráfico y su impacto en la esperanza de vida: comparativa entre México y España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54724^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
