<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166789</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of stable angina: myocardial revascularization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with stable angina normally have a good prognosis, with an annual mortality below 2%. Consequently, coronary angiography and myocardial revascularization are, in general, indicated only when symptoms continue to limit activity despite optimal medical treatment. In addition, patients whose noninvasive test results indicate a poor prognosis are also regarded as candidates for invasive treatment. Because drugeluting stents lead to a dramatic reduction in the risk of restenosis and in the need for repeat revascularization, they result in a greater reduction in angina after percutaneous coronary intervention than bare-metal stents. Other recent developments that have helped improve invasive treatment for patients with stable angina are high-resolution computed tomography and intracoronary diagnostic techniques, such as intravascular ultrasound and the use of pressure guidewires (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes con angina estable tienen un pronóstico generalmente favorable, con una mortalidad anual inferior al 2%. Por ello, en general, la coronariografía y la revascularización miocárdica están indicadas cuando persisten síntomas limitantes a pesar de tratamiento médico óptimo. Además, los pacientes con datos de mal pronóstico en pruebas no invasivas son considerados candidatos a manejo invasivo. Los stents farmacoactivos, debido a la reducción drástica de la reestenosis y de la necesidad de nuevas revascularizaciones, reducen la angina en comparación con los stents convencionales después de la realización de procedimientos de intervencionismo coronario percutáneo. Otros avances recientes que han ayudado en el manejo invasivo de los pacientes con angina estable son la tomografía computarizada de alta resolución y técnicas de diagnóstico intravascular como la ecografía intracoronaria y la guía de presión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.B): 31b-40b, 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166789</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la angina estable: revascularización miocárdica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24519^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54536^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30178^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
