<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039032</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Child rearing in the family and self-steem</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper, we relate the different childrearing practices in the families, with the young children self-esteem. In the study 283 families of middle or high-middle socio-cultural level participated, with children of 3, 4 and 5 years old and their respective teachers. The exploration of the childrearing in the families was made with the PEF (Alonso and Román, 2003a), the self-concept evaluation (auto-perception), with the PAI (Villa and Auzmendi, 1990) and with the Behavioural Rating Scale of self-esteem in young children (Haltiwanger and Harter, 1988) (hetero-perception). We founded disagreements between the adult and child perceptions -not only in the more used global valuation of the family educative style, but also in the specific valuations of the situations or conflicts. What is more, the statistical analysis confirms, among other things, the correlations between the family&#146;s educative styles and their young children self-esteem</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso García, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Sánchez, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se relacionan las diferentes prácticas educativas familiares con la autoestima de los hijos pequeños. En el estudio participaron 283 familias de nivel sociocultural medio y medio alto, con hijos de 3, 4 y 5 años y sus maestras. La exploración de las prácticas educativas familiares se hizo con las PEF (Alonso y Román, 2003a), la evaluación del autoconcepto (autopercepción) con el PAI (Villa y Auzmendi, 1990) y con la Escala de Referentes Conductuales de la Autoestima en niños pequeños (Haltiwanger y Harter, 1988) (heteropercepción). Hemos encontrado discrepancias entre las percepciones adultas e infantiles -tanto en la valoración global del estilo educativo familiar más utilizado, como en las valoraciones específicas de situaciones o conflictos-. Además, los análisis estadísticos confirman, entre otras cosas, la correlación entre el estilo educativo familiar y la autoestima de los hijos pequeños</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);17(1): 76-82, feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039032</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prácticas educativas familiares y autoestima</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
