<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163360</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Point-of-care ultrasound in Spanish paediatric intensive care units</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Point-of-care (bedside) ultrasound is being increasingly used by paediatricians who treat critically ill children. The aim of this study is to describe its availability, use, and specific training in Paediatric Intensive Care Units in Spain. Material and methods: A descriptive, cross-sectional, multicentre study was performed using an online survey. Results: Of a total of 51 PICUs identified in our country, 64.7% responded to the survey. Just over half (53.1%) have their own ultrasound machine, 25% share it, with other units with the usual location in the PICU, and 21.9% share it, but it is usually located outside the PICU. Ultrasound machine availability was not related to size, care complexity, or number PICU admissions. The ultrasound was used daily in 35% of the units, and was associated with location of the machine in the PICU (P = .026), the existence of a transplant program (P = .009), availability of ECMO (P = .006), and number of admissions (P = .015). 45.5% of PICUs has less than 50% of the medical staff specifically trained in bedside ultrasound, and 18.2% have all their medical staff trained. The presence of more than 50% of medical staff trained was associated with a higher rate of daily use (P = .033), and with specific use to evaluate cardiac function (P = .033), intravascular volume estimation (P = .004), or the presence of intra-abdominal collections (P = .021). Conclusions: Bedside ultrasound is frequently available in Spanish PICUs. Specific training is still variable, but it should serve to enhance its implementation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Martínez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Renter Valdovinos, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coca Pérez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Cortés, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La ecografía a pie de cama es cada vez más utilizada por los pediatras que tratan a niños críticos. El objetivo del estudio es describir la disponibilidad, el uso y la formación específica existente para esta técnica en las UCIP de nuestro entorno. Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo transversal multicéntrico mediante una encuesta en línea. Resultados: Se identificaron 51 UCIP en nuestro país, el 64,7% respondió a la encuesta. El 53,1% dispone de ecógrafo propio, el 25% lo comparte con otras unidades ubicándose en la unidad y el 21,9% dispone de él pero está ubicado en otra unidad. La disponibilidad de ecógrafo no se relacionó con el tamaño, la complejidad asistencial o el número de ingresos anuales. El 35% emplea la ecografía diariamente; esto se relacionó con la ubicación del ecógrafo en la unidad (p = 0,026), con la realización de trasplantes (p = 0,009), la disponibilidad de ECMO (p = 0,006) y con el número de ingresos anuales (p = 0,015). El 45,5% tiene menos del 50% de sus médicos con formación específica; el 18,2% ha formado a todos sus médicos. La presencia de más del 50% de médicos formados se asoció con mayor utilización a diario (p = 0,033) y con su uso para evaluar la función cardiaca (p = 0,033), la volemia (p = 0,004) o la presencia de líquido intraabdominal (p = 0,021). Conclusiones: La ecografía a pie de cama es una técnica frecuentemente disponible en las UCIP españolas. La formación específica para su uso es hasta el momento heterogénea pero debe servir para potenciar su implantación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(6): 344-349, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ecografía en el punto de cuidado en las unidades de cuidados intensivos pediátricos españolas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56221^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23699^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
