<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130699</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive-behavioral intervention in menopausal symptomatology: Short-term effects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For a high percentage of women, menopause is associated with an important variety of physical, psychological, and social symptoms, susceptible to treatment by means of cognitive-behavioral techniques. In the present work, 28 women followed a group intervention (eight weekly sessions, two hours each, including relaxation, cognitive techniques, exercise, and diet). Results show a significant reduction of most of the associated symptoms (physical and psychological), and an increase in quality of life in the treatment group, compared to baseline and to the control group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Larroy García, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Gómez-Calcerrada, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para un porcentaje elevado de mujeres, la menopausia se asocia a una importante variedad de síntomas físicos, psicológicos y sociales, susceptibles de ser tratados mediante técnicas cognitivo-conductuales. En el presente trabajo, 28 mujeres siguieron una intervención grupal de ocho sesiones semanales, de dos horas por sesión, que incluía psicoeducación, técnicas de desactivación, técnicas cognitivas, ejercicio y dieta. Los resultados muestran una reducción significativa de síntomas vasomotores, mialgias, ansiedad y depresión y un incremento en la calidad de vida en el grupo tratado, respecto al período de línea base como al grupo control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);21(2): 255-261, abr.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130699</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención cognitivo-conductual en sintomatología menopáusica: efectos a corto plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55208^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
