<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81856</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hysteroscopy and cancer: response to questions arising after two decades of experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. We retrospectively studied both the diagnostic hysteroscopies carried out by our group in the last two decades and the cancers diagnosed by this procedure. We describe our morphological-hysteroscopic classification and discuss several issues related to this procedure, namely: the reliability of the method, prediction of stage, prediction of histological grade, value of blind biopsy in focal lesions, value in stage II lesions, risk of dissemination, and risk of tamoxifen. Subjects and methods. We studied 329 endometrial cancers diagnosed in 8927 hysteroscopies performed by our group between 1991 and 2007. We determined the sensitivity, specificity and positive and negative predictive values of hysteroscopy in endometrial cancer. Subjects and methods. A morphological-hysteroscopic classification was formulated. The hysteroscopic pattern was compared with both the definitive stage (304 patients) and the histological grade (318 patients). Hysteroscopic findings in 734 asymptomatic women with advanced menopause and ultrasound endometrial lines larger than 4mm were assessed. The value of blind endometrial biopsy in the 329 endometrial cancers studied and in a subgroup of 94 focal cancers was determined. In 283 of the patients, the concordance of hysteroscopy in the diagnosis of invasion of the endocervical channel was calculated. A descriptive analysis was performed on 278 post-hysteroscopy peritoneal lavages and on eight cases of cancer treated with tamoxifen. Results. Our results indicate the value of hysteroscopy as the gold standard in the diagnosis of endometrial cancer, as well as the validity of our classification in predicting stage and histological grade. The sensitivity and specificity of hysteroscopy in the diagnosis of endocervical channel invasion are significantly superior to those of magnetic resonance imaging. Hysteroscopy is a suitable procedure in focal cancers, while blind biopsy shows deficiencies. Lastly, we found that the risks of both tubal dissemination and tamoxifen have been overstated. Conclusions. Hysteroscopy with directed biopsy is the gold standard in the diagnosis of endometrial cancer and provides statistically significant data on both staging and histological grade. This method offers advantages over other methods in the diagnosis of stage II cancers and is practically the only method that detects focal lesions. Under normal conditions, dissemination of cancer cells is null. In women treated with tamoxifen, hysteroscopic follow-up is only required in those presenting symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reynal, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coloma, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aliaga, Regina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Payá, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodenas, José Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilabert Aguilar, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas, Boris</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Estudiamos, retrospectivamente, tanto las histeroscopias diagnósticas realizadas por nuestro grupo, en las últimas dos décadas, como los cánceres diagnosticados por ellas. Exponemos nuestra clasificación morfológico-histeroscópica y damos respuesta a diversas cuestiones relacionadas con el tema: fiabilidad del método, predicción de estadio, predicción de grado histológico, valor de la biopsia ciega en las lesiones focales, valor de la histeroscopia en el estadio II, riesgo de diseminación tras estudio histeroscópico y riesgo del tamoxifeno. Sujetos y métodos. Estudiamos 329 cánceres endometriales diagnosticados en las 8.927 histeroscopias realizadas por nuestro grupo entre los años 1991 y 2007. Hallamos sensibilidad, especificidad y valores predictivos positivo y negativo de la histeroscopia frente al cáncer. Sujetos y métodos. Presentamos nuestra clasificación morfológico-histeroscópica. Comparamos el patrón histeroscópico tanto con el estadio definitivo (304 pacientes) como con el grado histológico (318 pacientes). Mostramos los hallazgos histeroscópicos de 734 pacientes asintomáticas, menopáusicas avanzadas y con líneas endometriales ecográficas &gt; 4mm. Calculamos el valor de la biopsia ciega endometrial, tanto en los 329 cánceres endometriales estudiados como en el subgrupo de 94 cánceres focales. Deducimos, en 283 pacientes, la concordancia de la histeroscopia en el diagnóstico de la invasión del canal endocervical. Expresamos nuestros resultados de 278 lavados peritoneales posthisteroscopia. Por último, analizamos las condiciones de 8 casos de cáncer con tamoxifeno. Resultados. Demostramos el valor de la histeroscopia como patrón oro en el diagnóstico del cáncer endometrial, así como la validez de nuestra clasificación para prever estadio y grado histológico. Comprobamos que la sensibilidad y la especificidad de la histeroscopia en el diagnóstico de la invasión de canal son significativamente superiores a las de la resonancia magnética. Demostramos la idoneidad de la histeroscopia en los cánceres focales y las carencias de la biopsia ciega en éstos. Por último, desdramatizamos tanto el riesgo de la diseminación tubárica como el del uso de tamoxifeno. Conclusiones. La histeroscopia con biopsia dirigida es el patrón de oro en el diagnóstico del cáncer endometrial. Proporciona datos estadísticamente significativos, tanto sobre la estadificación como del grado histológico. Supera al resto de métodos en el diagnóstico del estadio II y, sin ella, es prácticamente imposible detectar las lesiones focales. Afirmamos que la diseminación de células cancerosas es nula en condiciones normales. Finalmente, ratificamos el protocolo actual de realizar un control histeroscópico únicamente a las pacientes sintomáticas tratadas con tamoxifeno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(9): 341-346, sept. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histeroscopia y cáncer: respuesta a las cuestiones planteadas tras dos décadas de experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30131^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30131^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30131^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
