<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103916</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arteriovenous hemangioma of the right-hand genial region. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Arteriovenous hemangioma, also known as arteriovenous malformation, is the least common of the benign congenital vascular anomalies among vascular malformations, representing 1&#149;5% of reported cases. Its principal location is facial, followed by theintraoral region, the vulvar region and the extremities, but it can occur in any part of the body. It mainly affects middle-aged adults of both sexes. The case is that of a male patient with an arteriovenous hemangioma located in the right-hand genial region at the level of the yugal mucous, with no painful symptoms and closely related to the right-hand parotidduct. After x-ray it was surgically removed by intraoral approach following tutoring of the parotid duct with a lacrimal probe. The presumed diagnosis was later confirmed by anatomic pathology analysis. The review of professional literature for this article confirms that complete removal of the arteriovenous hemangioma is the treatment of choice for most authors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Corral, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribas Martín, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Domínguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loughney González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pezzi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hemangioma arteriovenoso, también denominado malformación arteriovenosa, esla anomalía vascular congénita benigna menos común dentro de las malformaciones vasculares, con una incidencia del 1,5% del total de casos reportados. Su principal localización es facial, seguida de la región intraoral, la vulvar y las extremidades, pero se puede localizar en cualquier parte del cuerpo. Afecta con mayor frecuencia a adultos de edad media, sin predominio de género. Se presenta un caso clínico de un paciente varón, con un hemangioma arteriovenoso localizado en la región geniana derecha a nivel de la mucosa yugal, sin sintomatología dolorosa y en íntima relación con el conducto de Stenon derecho. Tras el estudio radiológico pertinente, se procede a su extirpación quirúrgica mediante un abordaje intraoral y previa tutorización del conducto de Stenon con sonda lacrimal. Posteriormente el análisis anatomopatológico confirmó el diagnóstico de presunción. La revisión bibliográfica realizada en este artículo confirma que la exéresis completa del hemangioma arterio venoso es el tratamiento de elección para la mayoría de los autores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);9(2): 71-74, mayo-ago. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103916</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemangioma arteriovenoso en región geniana derecha. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32581^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1170^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
