<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142672</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of Confocal Microscopy in Distinguishing Between Basal Cell Carcinoma and Intradermal Melanocytic Nevus on the Face</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The clinical distinction between basal cell carcinoma (BCC) and intradermal melanocytic nevus lesions on the face can be difficult, particularly in young patients or patients with multiple nevi. Dermoscopy is a useful tool for analyzing characteristic dermoscopic features of BCC, such as cartwheel structures, maple leaf&#150;like areas, blue-gray nests and dots, and ulceration. It also reveals arborizing telangiectatic vessels and prominent curved vessels, which are typical of BCC, and comma vessels, which are typical of intradermal melanocytic nevi. It is, however, not always easy to distinguish between these 2 conditions, even when dermoscopy is used. We describe 2 facial lesions that posed a clinical and dermoscopic challenge in two 38-year-old patients; confocal microscopy showed separation between tumor nests and stroma and polarized nuclei, which are confocal microscopy features of basal cell carcinoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Floristan, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Estebaranz, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pampín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinedo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico clínico diferencial entre el epitelioma basocelular y el nevus melanocítico intradérmico facial puede ser a veces complicado, sobre todo en pacientes jóvenes o con múltiples nevus. La dermatoscopia es una herramienta útil que permite observar signos dermatoscópicos asociados a epitelioma como las ruedas de carro, las hojas de arce, los nidos y puntos azul grisáceos y la ulceración, además permite distinguir los vasos telangiéctasicos arboriformes y los vasos cortos curvados bien enfocados característicos de los epiteliomas basocelulares de los vasos en coma presentes en los nevus melanocíticos intradérmicos. Sin embargo, el diagnóstico diferencial clínico y dermatoscópico entre estas 2 afecciones dermatológicas puede ser complejo. Presentamos 2 lesiones faciales en 2 pacientes de 38 años de difícil diagnóstico clínico y dermatoscópico en los que la microscopia confocal mostró nidos celulares con separación entre los nidos y el estroma, y polarización de los núcleos de las células tumorales, que son signos confocales asociados a epitelioma basocelular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;106(8): e41-e44, oct. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142672</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la microscopia confocal en el diagnóstico diferencial de epiteliomas basocelulares y nevus melanocíticos intradérmicos de localización facial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9694^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22525^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23952^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32146^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32146^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9694^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32146^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23952^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9694^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9694^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9694^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
