<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83688</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body mass index in the prognosis of first myocardial infarction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: The value of body mass index in the prognosis of patients with ischemic heart disease is not well defined. The objective of our study was to determine the association of body mass index with classic and emergent cardiovascular risk factors and with intra-hospital and 6-months mortality. Patients and methods: We conducted a prospective, multicenter study with a 6-months follow-up. We included 1063 patients between the ages of 25&#150;75 years old who were consecutively admitted to the hospital within the first 24 hours of the onset of symptoms between years 2001 and 2003. We determined demographic and anthropometric variables, as well as classic and emergent factors of risk, clinical variables and the treatment administered. We carried out a univariate and multivariate analysis.Results: The percentage of patients with overweight or obesity in this population was 73.56%. Overweight and obesity were associated with classical risk factors, except for smoking, and emergent risk factors. Body mass index was not associated with short-or mid-term prognosis. Conclusions: Body mass index is not a useful anthropometric measure to determine the prognosis of patients after a first myocardial infarction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valle, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arós, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schröder, Helmut</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amézaga, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fiol, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugurera, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Covas, María Isable</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elosua, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burguera, Bartolome</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Gines</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fitó, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrugat, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sala, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivos: El valor del índice de masa corporal en el pronóstico de pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica no está bien definido. El objetivo de nuestro estudio fue determinar la asociación del índice de masa corporal con otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular tanto clásicos como emergentes, con la mortalidad intrahospitalaria y a los 6 meses en pacientes con un primer infarto de miocardio. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio prospectivo, multicéntrico, con seguimiento a los 6 meses. Se incluyeron 1.063 pacientes entre 25 y 75 años con un primer infarto de miocardio que ingresaron de forma consecutiva dentro de las primeras 24h del inicio de los síntomas entre los años 2001 y 2003. Se determinaron las características demográficas, antropométricas, de factores de riesgo clásicos y emergentes, clínicas y tratamiento recibido. Resultados: El porcentaje de pacientes con sobrepeso u obesidad fue del 73,6 % y presentaban mayor prevalencia de factores de riesgo clásicos -salvo tabaquismo- y emergentes. Tanto en el análisis univariado como en el multivariado el índice de masa corporal no se asoció al pronóstico a 6 meses. Conclusiones: En nuestra población el índice de masa corporal no parece predecir el pronóstico de los pacientes tras un primer infarto de miocardio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);135(14): 631-636, nov. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83688</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Índice de masa corporal como factor pronóstico en pacientes tras un primer infarto de miocardio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
