<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110912</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of overweight and obesity in children and adolescents aged 2-16 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To estimate the prevalence of obesity and overweight in children and adolescents in our city and to investigate the associated factors. Subjects and methods A cross-sectional study of 1317 children and adolescents aged 2-16 years. Multistage probability sampling was used to select three groups of subjects: 411 aged 12 to 16 years, 504 aged 6 to 12 years, and 402 aged 2 to 6 years. Body mass index was calculated, and obesity and overweight were diagnosed using the threshold levels of the International Obesity Task Force for children and adolescents. Parents were asked about eating habits, health, social, and demographic aspects. Results are given as percentages (95% confidence interval). The relationship between obesity and overweight and the different variables was studied using multiple logistic regression. The adjusted odds ratio (OR) was calculated. Results Among children and adolescentes aged 2-16 years, 9.5% (8.0%-11.0%) were obese and 22.4% (23.3%-24.6%) were overweight. Of subjects aged 12-16 years, 8.5% (5.9%-11.2%) were obese and 20.5% (16.7%-24.3%) were overweight. In the groups aged 6-12 years and 2-6 years, rates of obesity and overweight were 11.6% (8.9% -14.3%) and 31.0% (27.0-35.0) and 8.0% (5.4%-10.6%) and 13.6% (10.3%-16.9%) respectively. Obesity or overweight was associated to age (OR 1.21; P &lt;0.001), maternal obesity (OR 10.99; P= 0.008), a birthweight higher than 4kg (OR 2.91; p 0.002), and formula feeding (OR 1.82; P= 0.005).Conclusion Obesity and overweight in children and adolescents are highly prevalent problems in our city (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poveda González, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrico, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Sevilla, José Eugenio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Sánchez, Firma-Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Bueno, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Vico, Francisco-Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Pérez, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Escobar, Icíar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Tudela, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Sánchez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ruzafa, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín González, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Pérez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Lucenilla, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galera Martínez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonillo Perales, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez López, María-Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alias, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez, María I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Calcular la prevalencia de obesidad y sobrepeso en niños y adolescentes de nuestra ciudad e investigar los factores asociados. Sujetos y métodos Estudio transversal de 1.317 niños y adolescentes de 2 a 16 años. Mediante muestreo probabilístico polietápico se seleccionaron 3 grupos: 411 de 12 a 16, 504 de 6 a 12 y 402 de 2 a 6 años. Se les calculó el índice de masa corporal y se definió obesidad y sobrepeso según la International Obesity Task Force. Se realizó un cuestionario de consumo de alimentos y de características clínicas y sociodemográficas. Los resultados se expresan como porcentajes (intervalos de confianza al 95%). Mediante regresión logística múltiple se estudió la asociación entre exceso de peso (obesidad y sobrepeso) y las distintas variables, calculando la odds ratio (OR) ajustada. Resultados El 9,5% (8,0-11,0) de los niños y adolescentes de 2 a 16 años son obesos y 22,4% (23,3-24,6) tienen sobrepeso. En el grupo de 12 a 16 años, el 8,5% (5,9-11,2) son obesos y el 20,5% (16,7-24,3) tienen sobrepeso, en el grupo de 6 a 12 años el 11,6% (8,9-14,3) y el 31,0% (27,0-35,0) y en el de 2 a 6 años el 8,0% (5,4-10,6) y el 13,6% (10,3-16,9), respectivamente. Se asocian con el exceso de peso la edad (OR 1,21; p&lt;0,001), la obesidad materna (OR 10,99; p = 0,008), el peso al nacer mayor de 4kg (OR 2,91; p = 0,002) y la lactancia artificial exclusiva (OR 1,82; p = 0,005).Conclusión La obesidad y el sobrepeso infantil y juvenil son problemas extraordinariamente prevalentes en nuestra ciudad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;60(3): 121-126, mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110912</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad en niños y adolescentes de 2 a 16 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
