<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121544</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Estimation of the economic and health impact of complications of type 2 diabetes mellitus in the autonomous community of Madrid (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To estimate the economic and health impact of chronic complications (macrovascular and microvascular) of type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) in the autonomous community of Madrid (Spain) (ACM). Methods The number of expected complications was obtained from a descriptive, cross-sectional study on a cohort of 3,268 patients with T2DM from the ACM. Cost of complications (&#128;, 2012) was assessed both at hospitals and in primary care. The number of medical visits in primary care and drug treatment for complications were collected by a panel of 21 physicians experienced in treatment of T2DM. Population and epidemiological data and healthcare costs were obtained from Spanish sources. Univariate sensitivity analyses were performed. Results It is estimated that there are 390,944 patients with T2DM in the ACM, and that they experience 172,406 and 212,283 macrovascular and microvascular complications respectively during their lifetimes. Mean cost of T2DM complications per patient is estimated at &#128; 4,121.54 (66% due to macrovascular complications). The economic impact of T2DM complications in the ACM would be &#128; 1,611 million (1,065 and 545 millions from macrovascular and microvascular complications respectively). The economic impact would range from &#128; 1,249 and 2.509 million euro depending on T2DM prevalence. Conclusions Complications of T2DM have a great health and economic impact in ACM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de Estudio de Diabetes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Estimar el impacto económico y sanitario de las complicaciones crónicas macro y microvasculares de la diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2) en la Comunidad de Madrid (CM).Métodos El número de complicaciones esperadas se obtuvo de un estudio descriptivo transversal que incluyó una cohorte de 3.268 pacientes con DM2 de la CM. El coste de las complicaciones (&#128; de 2012) se valoró tanto a nivel hospitalario como en la atención primaria. El número de consultas médicas en atención primaria y el tratamiento farmacológico de las complicaciones se obtuvo mediante un panel de 21 médicos con experiencia en el tratamiento de la DM2. Los datos poblacionales, epidemiológicos y los costes sanitarios se consiguieron de fuentes españolas. Se hicieron análisis de sensibilidad univariantes. Resultados Se estima que la población con DM2 en la CM asciende a 390.944 pacientes y que estos sufren a lo largo de su vida 172.406 y 212.283 complicaciones macro y microvasculares, respectivamente. El coste promedio de las complicaciones de la DM2 por paciente se calcula en 4.121,54 &#128; (el 66% debido a las complicaciones macrovasculares). El impacto económico de las complicaciones de la DM2 en la CM sería de 1.611 millones de euros (1.065 en las complicaciones crónicas de tipo macrovascular y 545 en las complicaciones de tipo microvascular). El impacto económico oscilaría entre los 1.249 y los 2.509 millones de euros, según la prevalencia de DM2.ConclusionesLas complicaciones de la DM2 tienen un gran impacto, tanto sanitario como económico en la CM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(4): 193-201, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121544</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación del impacto económico y sanitario de las complicaciones de la diabetes mellitus tipo 2 en la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52971^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
