<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102136</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze how perceived risk and emotional distress were affected by the first visit to a Genetic Counseling Unit in patients with a family history of hereditarian breast cancer, ovarian cancer, or colorectal cancer. Methods: Risk perception of suffering cancer at 1 year, at 10 years, and across the life span, as well as emotional distress (assessed as sadness, anxiety and worries during the last week) was assessed in three moments: before the first visit to the Genetic Counseling Unit, immediately after finishing the visit, and 2-3 weeks after the first visit. Results: Emotional distress prior the first visit was observed in 30% of patients, with higher levels in patients without job. The first visit decreased emotional distress in most cases. However, 34% of patients stated that they were more anxious after the visit, 32% of patients become sadder, and 23% of patients were more worried. Patients who expressed increased levels of emotional distress after the visit were worried about their sons (or sons they wanted to have in the future). In spite of that, this emotional distress decreased at 2-3 weeks. The first visit to a Genetic Counseling Unit decreased risk perception of having cancer across the life span (p&lt;.01), and there were not differences between the three types of cancer. Conclusions: First visit to a Genetic  Counseling Unit decreases overestimation of risk perception of having cancer. Approximately one third of patients increased their emotional distress after the visit. Most studies are needed in order to clarify whether this increase in emotional distress is unavoidable for some  patients at the beginning of the genetic counseling process, or it can be reduced if some features of the protocol applied during the visit are changed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, Melinda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los efectos que provoca la primera visita de consejo genético para cáncer hereditario sobre la percepción de riesgo, y el malestar emocional en pacientes que acuden por primera vez a la Unidad de Consejo Genético (UCG) por historia familiar de cáncer de mama, ovario o colon hereditario. Método: Se evaluó la percepción de riesgo de padecer cáncer (al año, a 10 años, y a lo largo de toda la vida), y la intensidad del malestar emocional (evaluada como la ansiedad, tristeza y preocupación por la salud experimentadas durante la última semana) en tres ocasiones: inmediatamente antes de la primera visita de consejo genético (CG), inmediatamente después de la misma, y al cabo de 2-3 semanas. Resultados: El malestar emocional previo a la visita se producía en aproximadamente un 30% de los pacientes, siendo mayor en las personas que no realizaban actividad laboral. Si bien la visita de CG reducía el malestar emocional en muchos casos, ocurría lo contrario en algunos pacientes inmediatamente después de la misma (un 34% se sentía más ansioso, un 32% se sentía más triste, y un 23% se sentía más preocupado), y ello guardaba relación con la preocupación por los hijos (tanto si se tenían como si se pretendía tenerlos en el futuro). No obstante, este malestar se reducía en las 2-3 semanas posteriores. La visita de CG reducía la percepción de riesgo de padecer cáncer a lo largo de toda la vida (p&lt; .01), no existiendo  diferencias en función del tipo de cáncer. Conclusiones: Esta primera visita reduce la sobreestimación del riesgo de padecer cáncer que los pacientes tienen antes de la misma, pero, en aproximadamente un tercio de los  mismos, no reduce los niveles de malestar emocional, observándose, incluso, un incremento de éste que va disminuyendo durante las semanas posteriores a la visita. Son necesarios  más estudios que permitan determinar si este incremento es una consecuencia inevitable del inicio del proceso de CG, o si puede reducirse modificando algún aspecto del protocolo que  se aplica en la primera visita (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);8(2/3): 441-451, dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102136</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la primera visita de consejo genético sobre la percepción de riesgo y el malestar emocional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3142^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
