<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129107</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectivity of the iron supplementation pattern recommended in Spain for pregnant women without anemia at the beginning of pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Health authorities in Spain recommended supplementing the initially non-anemic pregnant women with 30 mg of iron per day from early gestation. The aim of the study was to analyze the rate of success in preventing iron deficiency in late pregnancy with the supplementation pattern recommended by the Spanish Ministery of Health. Methods: Longitudinal study conducted in 120 pregnant women without initial anemia and taking iron supplementation (20-40 mg/day). Clinical and obstetric histories were collected. Blood haemoglobin, serum ferritin and transferrin saturation were measured in each trimester and at delivery. Results: Iron status decreases during pregnancy and recovers slightly in late  pregnancy. A 17.9% of pregnant women start pregnancy without iron stores. At the time of delivery, 53.4% had exhausted iron stores and 16.2% presented iron deficiency anemia. Conclusions: The iron supplementation pattern recommended in Spain to pregnant  women without initial anemia does not prevent iron-deficiency states at the end of gestation in a high percentage of women in our population. More evidence is needed to help to define the more effective pattern of iron supplementation in order to prevent anemia in pregnant women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arija, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranda, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribot, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Las autoridades sanitarias españolas aconsejan  suplementar con 30 mg/día de hierro de forma temprana a las   embarazadas no anémicas. Nuestro objetivo es analizar el porcentaje de éxito en la prevención del déficit de hierro al final del embarazo con la pauta de suplementación recomendada por el Ministerio de Sanidad y Consumo. Métodos: Estudio longitudinal realizado en 120 embarazadas sin anemia inicial, suplementadas con hierro (20-40 mg/día). Se valora: historia  clínica y obstétrica. Durante los tres trimestres y parto se determinan: Hemoglobina, Ferritina sérica, Saturación de transferrina. Resultados: El estado en hierro evoluciona negativamente durante la gestación, recuperándose ligeramente al final del embarazo. El 17,9%  de las embarazadas inicia la gestación sin reservas de hierro. En el momento del parto, un 53,4% presentó las reservas de hierro exhaustas y un 16,2%, anemia ferropénica. Conclusiones: La pauta de suplementación con hierro aconsejada en  España a las mujeres embarazadas sin anemia inicial, no previene los estados carenciales en hierro al final de la gestación en un porcentaje elevado de mujeres de nuestra población. Son necesarias más  evidencias que contribuyan a definir la pauta de suplementación con hierro más efectiva para prevenir la anemia en la mujer embarazada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;18(2): 70-76, abr.-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129107</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la pauta de suplementación con hierro recomendada en España a embarazadas sin anemia al inicio de la gestación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32369^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31381^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11697^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
