<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040672</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The value of the internal capsule signs in the stimulation of the subthalamic nucleus in Parkinson&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The effectiveness of stimulating the subthalamic nucleus (DBS-STN) in advanced Parkinson&#146;s disease(PD) largely depends on the correct placement of the electrodes. Since the sensory-motor region of the STN lies beside the internalcapsule (IC), we believe that the motor effectiveness of DBS-STN could be related to the stimulation threshold in which IC signsappear (IC threshold). Patients and methods. An examination of 17 consecutive patients with advanced PD who had beensubmitted to bilateral DBS-STN (one case was unilateral) was carried out to determine the motor improvement on each side of thebody (n = 33) and the energy consumption one year after surgery according to the IC threshold obtained during the programming.Results. A 45% improvement was observed in the UPDRS III in off and there was a 24% reduction in the equivalent dose oflevodopa with bilateral DBS-STN. When the electrodes were considered, there was a statistically significant improvement thatdepended on the IC threshold. Energy consumption differed significantly between electrodes with an IC threshold of 3-7 V (1.5 ±1.2 µW) and those with an IC threshold &gt; 7 V (8.3 ± 9.4 µW). Conclusions. During the stimulation phase and following the correctlocation of the STN, which was achieved by neurophysiological recording, the IC threshold has prognostic implications in mediumlongterm motor effectiveness and in the consumption of the battery in the generator</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arjona-Morón, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escamilla, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Linares, J. M </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnáiz-Urrutia, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mínguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jouma-Katati, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meersmans Sánchez-Jofré, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La eficacia de la estimulación del núcleosubtalámico (ECP-NST) en la enfermedad de Parkinson (EP) avanzadadepende en gran medida de la correcta implantación de loselectrodos. Como la región sensitivomotora del NST está junto a lacápsula interna (CI), pensamos que la eficacia motora de ECPNSTpodría relacionarse con el umbral de estimulación en el queaparecen signos de CI (umbral de CI). Pacientes y métodos. En 17pacientes consecutivos con EP avanzada intervenidos medianteECP-NST bilateral (uno unilateral) determinamos la mejoría motoraen cada lado del cuerpo (n = 33) y el consumo de energía unaño después de la cirugía en función del umbral de CI obtenidodurante la programación. Resultados. Hubo una mejoría de un45% en la UPDRS III en off y un 24% de descenso en la dosisequivalente de levodopa con la ECP-NST bilateral. Cuando consideramoslos electrodos hubo una mejoría estadísticamente significativaque era dependiente del umbral de CI. El consumo energéticodifirió significativamente entre los electrodos con un umbral deCI de 3-7 V (1,5 ± 1,2 &amp;#956;W) y aquellos con un umbral de CI &gt; 7 V(8,3 ± 9,4 &amp;#956;W). Conclusión. Durante la fase de estimulación y trasuna correcta localización del NST, mediante registro neurofisiológico,el umbral de CI tiene implicaciones pronósticas en la eficaciamotora a medio-largo plazo y en el consumo de la batería del generador</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(4): 193-197, abr. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040672</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor de los signos de cápsula interna en la estimulación del núcleo subtalámico de la enfermedad de Parkinson</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34068^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28247^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4638</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
