<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120062</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of parenteral fish oil lipid emulsions on colon morphologyand cytokine expression after experimental colitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM: To study the effects of different protocols of fish oil lipid emulsion (FOLE) infusion on acute inflammation in a rat model of colitis. METHODS: Adult male Wistar rats (n = 51) were randomized into 5 groups to receive parenteral infusion of saline (SS) or soybean oil lipid emulsion (SO), as controls, and FOLE composed of: fish oil alone (FO); a mixture (9:1 v/v) of SO with FO (SO/FO); or 30% soybean oil, 30% medium-chain triglycerides, 25% olive oil, and 15%fish oil (SMOF). After 72 h of intravenous infusion, experimental colitis was induced with acetic acid. After 24 h, colonic samples were analyzed for histological and cytokine changes. RESULTS: In relation SS group, macroscopic necrosis was less frequent in the FO group and histological necrosis was more frequent in the SMOF group. There was a direct and inverse relation of colon interleukin (IL)-1 and IL-4 respectively, with histological necrosis. In comparison to the SS group, FO increased IL-4 and IFN-gamma and decreased TNF-alpha, SO/FO decreased TNF-alpha, and SMOF increased IL-1 and decreased IL- 4.CONCLUSION:In acetic acid-induced colitis, the isolate infusion of FOLE composed of fish oil alone was more advantageous in mitigating inflammation than the infusion of FOLE containing other oils, and this difference may be due the influences of their different fatty acid contents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bertevello, Pedro L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garib, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Logullo, Angela F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrinhas, Raquel S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Waitzberg, Dan L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garla, Priscila</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar los efectos de los diferentes protocolos de infusión de la emulsion de lípidos de aceite de pescado (Fole) sobre la inflamación aguda en el modelo de colitis en la rata. Material y métodos: Ratas Wistar macho adultas (n = 51) fueron asignados al azar en 5 grupos para recibir infusión parenteral de solución salina (SS) o emulsión de lípidos de aceite de soja (SO), como controles, y Fole compone de: aceite de pescado solo (FO), una mezcla (9:1 v/v) de SO con FO (SO/FO), o 30% de aceite de soja, 30% triglicéridos de cadena media, 25% de aceite de oliva, y 15% de aceite de pescado (SMOF). Después de 72 h de infusión intravenosa, colitis experimental fue inducida con ácido acético. Después de 24 h, las muestras de colon se analizaron para determinar cambios histológicos y citoquinas. Resultados: En relación en el SS grupo, necrosis macroscópica fue menos frecuente en el grupo FO y necrosis histológica fue más frecuente en el grupo de SMOF. Existe una relación directa e inversa de colon interleuquina (IL) -1 e IL-4, respectivamente, con necrosis histológica. En comparación con el grupo SS, en el FO hubo aumento de IL-4 e IFN-gamma y disminución de TNF-alfa, SO/FO disminuyó TNF-alfa, y en el SMOF hubo aumento de IL-1 y la disminución de IL-4. Conclusión: En la colitis inducida por ácido acético, la infusion aislada de Fole compuesto de aceite de pescado por sí solo fue más ventajosa en la atenuacion de la inflamación que la infusión de Fole contiendo otros aceites, y esta diferencia puede ser debida las influencias de su diferente contenido de ácido graso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(3): 849-856, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120062</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de las emulsiones parenterales de lípidos de peces sobre la morfología del colon y de la expresion de citoquinas después de colitis experimental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7438^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3123^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3138^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22453^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
