<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166311</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-0852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Population-based norms of the Life Orientation Test&#150;Revised (LOT-R)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/Objective: The most common used instrument to measure optimism, both in psychological and medical research, is the Life Orientation Test- Revised (LOT-R). A multi-countries study using the future item from the LOT-R, found that level of optimism varied between countries. The provision of population-based norms is necessary, since norms enable the application of the LOT-R in individual diagnosis to compare individuals or special patient groups&#146; scores with reference data. Method: A representative population based survey was conducted in 2014-2015. Norwegian aged 18-94 years (N=1,792) completed questionnaires assessing sociodemographic, optimism and health and quality of life. Results: The mean age was 53.2 (SD=16.6) and 53% were women. Mean LOT-R score was 17.2 (SD 3.0). There were marginal age and no gender differences. Although optimism was associated with sociodemographic variables, these were considered negligible due to small effect size. Norm data are given for the entire population. Optimism was associated with better health and quality of life. Conclusions: This study provides age and gender specific norm values from a representative sample of the Norwegian population. The normative data may be used in comparisons of optimism between individuals or between different samples of patients or sub-groups of people (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Skogstad, Laila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grimholt, Tine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonsaksen, Tore</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ekeberg, Oivind</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heir, Trond</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lerdal, Anners</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schou-Bredal, Inger</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes/Objetivo: El instrumento más comúnmente utilizado para medir el optimismo, tanto en la investigación psicológica como en la médica, es el Test de Orientación Vital Revisado (LOT-R). Disponer de normas poblacionales es necesario, ya que permiten comparar los puntajes de individuos o grupos con los datos de referencia. Método: En 2014-2015 se llevó a cabo un estudio poblacional. Noruegos de entre 18 y 94 años (N=1.792) cumplimentaron cuestionarios que evaluaban variables sociodemográficas, optimismo disposicional, salud y calidad de vida. Resultados: La edad media fue de 53,2 (DT=16,6) y el 53% fueron mujeres. La puntuación media del LOT-R fue de 17,2 (DT=3). Se encontraron diferencias marginales en la edad y no hubo diferencias de género. Aunque el optimismo se asoció con variables sociodemográficas, esta asociación no se consideró significativa debido a los pequeños tamaños del efecto, por lo que los datos normativos se refieren a la población general. El optimismo se asoció con mejor salud y calidad de vida. Conclusión: Este estudio proporciona valores normativos específicos en función de edad y sexo a partir de una muestra representativa de la población noruega(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. clin. health psychol. (Internet);17(3): 216-224, sept.-dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Datos normativos del Test de Orientación Vital Revisado (LOT-R) basados en la población</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27892^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56069^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56070^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9851^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28618</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
