<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84657</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe acute hepatitis associated with intake of aloe vera tea</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a 26-year-old man who developed severe acutehepatitis after consumption of an Aloe vera tea. On admission,the patient showed characteristic biochemical and clinicalfeatures of acute hepatitis and liver failure. The patientreported that he had been drinking an Aloe vera tea 2-4 weeksbefore symptom onset. Other causes of acute hepatitiswere excluded and the patient improved after withdrawal ofthe Aloe vera tea. Aloe vera should be considered as a possiblecause in cases of acute hepatitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Curciarello, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borzip, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosia, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Ortúzar, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de hepatitis aguda grave en un varónde 26 años, probablemente debida al consumo de té de Aloevera. El paciente se presentó con manifestaciones clínicas ybioquímicas de hepatitis aguda e insuficiencia hepática y refirióque había tomado té de Aloe vera, elaborado en formaartesanal, 2-4 semanas antes de comenzar con los síntomasde la enfermedad. Mediante el uso de escalas de causalidadse pudo considerar como causa probable de la enfermedadhepática el Aloe vera y como improbable los fármacos que elpaciente había consumido de forma simultánea. Recomendamostener en cuenta el Aloe vera como una causa posiblede hepatitis aguda (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;31(7): 436-438, agost. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84657</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatitis aguda grave asociada al consumo de té de Aloe vera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53500^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d507^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30667^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38622^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
