<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17924</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body composition in 10 to 14-year-old handball players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyses the body composition of male school children with an age range of 10-14: players from 11 league teams. The sample corresponds to 29.32% of the total population (854) and enabled us to find highly reliable conclusions. Besides the 5 specific data, we measured eight skinfolds, six lengths, eight heights, thirteen girths or perimeters, and nine diameters. The study of body composition was done following Matiegka's method. The percentage of fat mass was estimated using the equation of Slaughter et al; muscle mass by the Drinkwater and Ross formula; bone mass by Rocha's formula and residual mass by Würch's equation. The results show that these athletes are taller, weigh more and have a larger span than the athletes of other papers. From ages 10 to 14, the percentage of fat mass decreases, and a change in the distribution of subcutaneous fat is observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se estudia la composición corporal de escolares, sexo masculino, de 10 a 14 años de edad, jugadores de once equipos federados. La muestra corresponde al 29.32 per cent del total de la población (854) que permite dictaminar unas conclusiones de gran fiabilidad. Además de los 5 datos específicos se han hecho ocho pliegues, 6 longitudes; 8 alturas; 13 perímetros y 9 diámetros. El estudio de composición corporal se ha hecho por el método tetracompartimental de Matiegka. El porcentaje de masa grasa se ha obtenido usando la fórmula de Slaughter y col., la masa muscular por la fórmula de Drinkwater y Ross, la masa ósea por la fórmula de Rocha y la masa residual por la fórmula de Würch. Los resultados describen que estos deportistas son más altos, tienen más peso y más envergadura que los atletas de otros artículos semejantes. Desde los 10 hasta los 14 años, disminuye el porcentaje de masa grasa y cambia la distribución de la grasa subcutánea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;6(3): 153-160, dic. 2002. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Composición corporal en jugadores de balonmano de 10 a 14 años</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Ibnziaten, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leiva, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogueras, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poblador, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viana, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lancho, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17924</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
