<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117813</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Left ventricular hypertrophy and circadian variation in blood pressure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Multiple studies support the prognostic role of both ambulatory blood pressure (BP) monitoring and left ventricular hypertrophy (LVH) in patients with hypertension. Consequently, we evaluated the correlation between certain ambulatory BP monitoring parameters and left ventricular mass (LVM) measured by echocardiography in a sample of hypertensive patients. Material and methods: A cross sectional, retrospective study was performed in 405 patients(53.8% women; mean age, 55.5 years), diagnosed with essential hypertension and referred to the Hypertension and Vascular Risk Unit by their primary care centers between 1 January,1998 and 31 August, 1999. All patients underwent clinical and biological evaluation (using a standardized protocol), echocardiography, and 24-hour ambulatory BP monitoring (SaceLabs90207).Results: Ambulatory BP monitoring revealed poor BP control in 320 patients (79%); the meandip in systolic BP was 10.6 ± 0.9%. The dipper pattern was observed in 43.8%, the extreme dipper pattern in 13.4%, the non-dipper pattern in 30.2%, and the riser pattern in 12.6%. Left ventricular hypertrophy was identi&amp;#64257;ed in 248 patients (61.23%). An increase in ambulatory nocturnal BP was associated with an increase in LVM (p &lt; 0.0001) and a statistically significant negative correlation was observed between the drop in BP and the increase in LVM (P&lt;.0001).Conclusion: An increase in LVM was associated with nocturnal hypertension and a decrease in the nocturnal drop in BP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Paz, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Juanatey, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cinza Sanjurjo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Gómez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermida Ameijeiras, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: Son múltiples los estudios que avalan el papel pronóstico que han mostrado tanto la presión arterial (PA) ambulatoria como la hipertrofia ventricular izquierda (HVI) en el paciente hipertenso. Por ello, nos planteamos evaluar la correlación existente entre determinados parámetros de la PA ambulatoria y la masa ventricular izquierda (MVI) medida por ecocardiografía, en una muestra de pacientes hipertensos. Material y métodos Se diseñó un estudio transversal retrospectivo, que incluyó a 405 pacientes (53,8% mujeres), con una edad media de 55,5 años, diagnosticados de HTA esencial, remitidos a la Unidad de HTA y Riesgo Vascular, desde atención primaria, entre el 1 de enero de 1998 y el 31 de agosto de 1999. En todos los casos se realizó una evaluación clínica y biológica (según protocolo estandarizado), estudio ecocardiográfico y MAPA de 24 h (monitor Space Labs 90207).Resultados La MAPA demostró un mal control de la HTA en 320 pacientes (79%); la profundidad de la PA sistólica fue del 10,6 ± 0,9%. La prevalencia de perfil dipper fue del 43,8%, del dipper-extremo 13,4%, del no dipper 30,2% y del riser 12,6%. Se identificó a 248 pacientes (61,23%) con HVI. El aumento de la PA ambulatoria nocturna se asoció con un incremento de la MVI (p &lt; 0,0001) y se objetivó una correlación estadísticamente significativa y negativa entre la disminución de la profundidad de la PA y el incremento del índice de MVI (p &lt; 0,0001).Conclusión El incremento de la MVI se asocia con HTA nocturna y disminución de la profundidad nocturna de la PA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;30(4): 135-142, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117813</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipertrofia ventricular izquierda y variación circadiana de la presión arterial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25631^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55111^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34360^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
