<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056209</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Depressive disorders in childhood and adolescence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Major depression (MD) is defi ned as a depressed or irritable mood almost every day for most of        the day for more than two weeks. This disorder effects the normal development of a child to an        adolescent, causing social, educational and emotional disabilities.        This has been a very controversial issue, viewpoints ranging from not being accepted as occurring        before late adolescence to being a recognised entity in younger children. It is similar to        that in adults and the clinical picture varies enormously depending on the different stages of the        child&#146;s development.        Its prevalence is 2% in children and 4-8% in adolescents, increasing with age, and there is a        clear difference as regards gender after puberty.        There is very little evidence of treatment in children and adolescents, most treatments are based        on clinical experience or extrapolations of studies in adults.        Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRI) is the pharmacological treatment of choice, fl uoxetine        being the only antidepressant drug authorised in the USA for children and adolescents.        Recently, in Spain, the use of fl uoxetine has been extended to children over 8 years and adolescents        with severe to moderate depression who do not respond to psychotherapy. All published        studies base their therapeutic approach on psychopharmacological treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Granada Jiménez, Olvido</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de Cossío, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La depresión Mayor (DM) se defi ne como el estado de ánimo depresivo o irritable casi todos los        días y durante la mayor parte del día, durante más de dos semanas. Este trastorno altera el desarrollo        normal del niño a adolescente, generando una discapacidad de sus funciones sociales,        escolares y emocionales.        Ha sido un tema muy controvertido no aceptándose su existencia antes de la adolescencia tardía        hasta ser reconocida como entidad propia en edades tempranas. Es similar a la del adulto        variando enormemente la clínica en función de las diferentes etapas del desarrollo de niño.        Su prevalencia es de un 2% en niños y un 4-8% en adolescentes, aumentando con la edad, y        con claras diferencias por sexos después de la pubertad.        Existe escasa evidencia en niños y adolescentes en lo que se refi ere al tratamiento, la mayoría        basados en la experiencia clínica o en extrapolaciones de estudios en adultos.        En el tratamiento farmacológico son de elección los inhibidores selectivos de recaptación de        la serotonina (ISRS), siendo la fl uoxetina el único antidepresivo autorizado en EEUU en niños        y adolescentes. Recientemente, en España, se ha ampliado la indicación de fl uoxetina a niños        mayores de 8 años y adolescentes con depresión severa-moderada que no responden a        psicoterapia. Todos los estudios publicados basan su abordaje terapéutico en un tratamiento        psicofarmacológico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;1(6): 270-276, feb.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056209</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos Depresivos en la infancia y adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28248^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30515^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28248^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
