<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152411</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Peripheral venous catheter use in the emergency department: reducing adverse events in patients and biosafety problems for staff</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To test a strategy to reduce the rate of adverse events in patients and safety problems for emergency department staff who insert peripheral venous catheters (PVCs). The strategy consisted of training, implementing a protocol, and introducing safety-engineered PVCs. Methods. Prospective, multicenter, observational, preauthorization study in patients requiring PVC placement in an emergency department. The study had 2 phases. The first consisted of training, implementing a protocol for using conventional PVCs, and monitoring practice. The second phase introduced safety-engineered PVC sets. The number of adverse events in patients and threats to safety for staff were compared between the 2 phases. Results. A total of 520 patients were included, 180 in the first phase and 340 in the second. We detected breaches in aseptic technique, failure to maintain a sterile field, and improper management of safety equipment and devices. Some practices improved significantly during the second phase. Eighty-six adverse events occurred in the first phase and 52 (15.4%) in the second; the between-phase difference was not statistically significant. The incidence of postinfusion phlebitis was 50% lower in the second phase. Seven splash injuries and 1 accidental puncture occurred with conventional PVCs in the first phase; 2 splash injuries occurred with the safety-engineered PVCs in the second phase (36% decrease, P = .04). Differences were particularly noticeable for short-term PVC placements (P = .02). Conclusion. Combining training, a protocol, and the use of safety-engineered PVC sets offers an effective strategy for improving patient and staff safety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roqueta Egea, Fermin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mozota Duarte, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Juan Gago, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Marcos, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás Vecina, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Navarro, María Gracia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borillo, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chanovas Borrás, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Reducir la tasa de eventos adversos (EA) derivados de catéteres vasculares periféricos (CVP) en pacientes atendidos en servicios de urgencias (SU), así como accidentes de bioseguridad en profesionales, mediante una estrategia que combine formación, protocolización de la indicación y catéteres de bioseguridad. Método. Estudio prospectivo, multicéntrico, observacional no postautorización en pacientes atendidos en el SU que precisen de CVP. El estudio tiene dos fases: en la primera se procede a formación, protocolización y monitorización mediante ua lista de comprobación, utilizando CVP convencionales. En la segunda fase se introducen CVP de bioseguridad. Se comparan ambas fases y sus resultados en la reducción de EA y bioseguridad. Resultados. Se incluyeron un total de 520 pacientes: 180 en fase I y 340 en fase II. Se evidencian deficiencias en la técnica relacionadas con la desinfección, mantenimiento del campo estéril y manejo de equipo y apósitos; algunos mejoran significativamente con la progresión del estudio en fase II. Se observaron 86 EA, 34 en Fase I (18,8%) y 52 en fase II (15,4%) (p = ns). Destaca una reducción del 50% de flebitis en fase II. Sobre bioseguridad se detectaron 8 casos (7 salpicaduras, 1 pinchazo accidental) con CVP convencionales (fase I) y 2 salpicaduras con CVP de bioseguridad (fase II), equivalente a una reducción del 36% de accidentes (p = 0,04), especialmente con catéteres de corta duración (p = 0,02). Conclusiones. La combinación de formación, protocolización de la indicación y empleo de CVP de bioseguridad se muestra como una intervención más efectiva para mejorar la seguridad del paciente y del profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(2): 89-96, abr. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio sobre la reducción de eventos adversos en pacientes y problemas de bioseguridad de los profesionales derivados de la aplicación de catéteres vasculares en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55059^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
