<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165473</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prospective study of filtering blebs after XEN45 surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To qualitatively analyse the evolution of filtering blebs after XEN surgery, by using anterior segment optical coherence tomography (AS-OCT). Methods: A prospective study was performed on filtering blebs of 30 eyes with cataracts and glaucoma, surgically operated on using phacoemulsification and XEN45 implantation (PHACO-XEN). AS-OCT was used to analyse bleb morphology and reflectivity at 3, 6, and 12 months after surgery. Functionality was studied considering an intraocular pressure (IOP) &amp;#8804; 18 mm Hg without antihypertensive medication. Results: The IOP enabled the blebs to be classified into non-functional: flat (6.67%) and encapsulated (3.33%); and functional (90%), which were then divide by their morphology into cystic (5/27), diffuse (2/27), and layered (20/27). Cystic types had a mean IOP of 12.8, 12.6, and 14.0 mm Hg at 3, 6 and 12 months, respectively. In the diffuse type, the mean IOP was 13.0, 11.5 and 13.0 mm Hg at 3, 6 and 12 months, respectively. In the layers pattern the mean IOP was 14.45, 14.55 and 14.8 mm Hg at 3, 6 and 12 months respectively. The percentage of blebs with high reflectivity was 48.15%, 62.96%, and 77.78%, at 3, 6 and 12 months, with a mean IOP of 14.23, 14.59, and 15.14mmHg in each time period, respectively. Conclusion: AS-OCT could be a good predictor of bleb functionality in PHACO-XEN surgery. Those with a cystic pattern or low reflectivity seem to have better post-operative success. Nevertheless, more long-term studies are required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cerdà-Ibáñez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duch-Samper, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olate-Pérez, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gargallo-Benedicto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osorio-Alayo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Torregrosa, VT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro-Rego, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neira-Ibáñez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar cualitativamente la evolución de las ampollas de filtración mediante tomografía de coherencia óptica de segmento anterior (OCT-SA) en pacientes con implante XEN45. Métodos: Estudio prospectivo de las ampollas de filtración de 30 ojos operados de catarata y glaucoma mediante facoemulsificación e implantación XEN45 (FACO-XEN). Se realizó OCT-SA analizando la morfología y la reflectividad de la ampolla al mes 3, 6 y 12 postoperatorio. La funcionalidad se estudió considerando una presión intraocular (PIO) &amp;#8804; 18mm Hg sin medicación hipotensora. Resultados: La PIO permitió clasificar las ampollas en no funcionales: planas (6,67%) y encapsuladas (3,33%) y funcionales (90%), las cuales dividimos según su morfología en quísticas (5/27), difusas (2/27) y laminar o en capas (20/27). Las quísticas presentaron una PIO media de 12,8, 12,6 y 14,0 mm Hg a los 3, 6 y 12 meses respectivamente. En las difusas la PIO media fue 13,0, 11,5 y 13,0 mm Hg a los 3, 6 y 12 meses respectivamente. En las de patrón en capas la PIO media fue 14,45, 14,55 y 14,8 mm Hg a los 3, 6 y 12 meses respectivamente. El porcentaje de ampollas con alta reflectividad fue de 48,15%, 62,96% y 77,78% a los 3, 6 y 12 meses, con una PIO media de 14,23, 14,59 y 15,14mmHg en cada período, respectivamente. Conclusión: El análisis de OCT-SA podría ser un buen predictor de la funcionalidad de la ampollas en la cirugía FACO-XEN. Aquellas quísticas o con menor reflectividad parecen tener mejor éxito postoperatorio. Pese a ello, se requieren estudios a mayor largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(8): 366-371, ago. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165473</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio prospectivo de las ampollas de filtración poscirugía de implante XEN45</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23041^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1089^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3252^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32250^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32652^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33880^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
