<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043555</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Photodynamic therapy in dermatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Photodynamic therapy (PDT) is a therapeutic modality based on the photooxidation of biological materials induced by a photosensitizer, which selectively locates itself in certain tumorous cells or tissues, so that when illuminated by a light of the right length and at a sufficient dose, these cells are destroyed.         In dermatology, PDT with topical 5-aminolevulinic acid or 5-methyl aminolevulinate is very effective in the treatment of actinic keratoses, basal cell carcinomas and Bowen's disease. In addition, very promising results have been obtained in inflammatory pathologies like morphea or sarcoidosis, infections like warts, and cosmetic processes such as photoaging, among others.         This article reviews the most significant aspects of PDT in dermatology. First of all, we will review the basic fundamentals of photodynamic treatment. Next, we will outline its clinical applications in dermatology, both in oncological applications and all those dermatological processes in which PDT may play a role in their management. We will also discuss its promising cosmetic application in the treatment of photoaging. We will complete the review with photodiagnosis and the different non-invasive ways to monitor the effectiveness of PDT</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Heras, M. Elena de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Lorente, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra-Guillén, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén-Barona, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Rodríguez, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilaberte, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Rodríguez, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benvenuto-Andrade, Cristiane</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia fotodinámica (TF) es una modalidad terapéutica basada en la fotooxidación de materiales biológicos inducida por un fotosensibilizante, el cual se localiza selectivamente en determinadas células o tejidos tumorales, de forma que al ser iluminadas con una luz de adecuada longitud y en dosis suficiente, dichas células resultan destruidas.         En dermatología, la TF con ácido 5-aminolevulínico o 5-metilo aminolevulinato tópicos es muy efectiva en el tratamiento de queratosis actínicas, carcinomas basocelulares y enfermedad de Bowen. Además, se han obtenido resultados muy prometedores en patología inflamatoria como la morfea o la sarcoidosis, infecciones como las verrugas y procesos cosméticos, como el fotoenvejecimiento, entre otras.         El presente artículo revisa los aspectos más relevantes de la TF en dermatología. En primer lugar se hará una revisión de los fundamentos básicos del tratamiento fotodinámico; posteriormente se expondrán sus aplicaciones clínicas en dermatología, tanto las oncológicas como todos aquellos procesos dermatológicos en los que la TF puede desempeñar un papel en su manejo, sin olvidar su prometedora aplicación cosmética en el tratamiento del fotoenvejecimiento. Finalizaremos la revisión con el fotodiagnóstico y las diferentes formas de monitorización no invasiva de la efectividad de la TF</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;97(2): 83-102, mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043555</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia fotodinámica en dermatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24879^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d632^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32403^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d634^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9041^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5403^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
