<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78145</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">RESPONDIA. Iberoamerican spondyloarthritis Registry: Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the principal characteristics of spondyloarthritis in the Argentina population. Material and methods: A descriptive transversal study was carried out with information obtained between March and December 2007 and stored online at the Spondyloarthropathy Records website of the Spanish Society for Rheumatology (REGISPONSER). Eleven Argentine Centers participated and they all adopted similar criteria to assess patients and data were collected in the same database. Results: A total of 405 patients with spondyloarthritis (SpA) were included: 238 were males (59%) with an average age standard deviation 48.1 15.7 years and an average disease progress of 10.9 9.5 years. The majority was diagnosed with psoriatic arthritis (PsA) (46.7%), followed by ankylosing spondylitis (AS) (30.3%) and undifferentiated spondyloarthritis (U-SpA) (12.4%). Average age at onset was 38.4 16.6 years and time until diagnosis was 7.5 8.6 years. The most common initial symptoms were peripheral arthritis (66%), lumbago (54%) and sacroiliitis (39%). 43% of these patients presented dactylitis and 10% uveitis during the disease Obj progress. TNF inhibitor treatment was administered in 10.4% of the patients. Average BASDAI score was 4 2.5 and BASFI 3.3 2.9. Patients with ankylosing spondylitis were younger, showed a higher incapacity for work, felt more pain and presented more axial disorders and more evidence of radiologic damage than psoriatic arthritis patients. Conclusion. Argentina spondyloarthritis patients presented classical characteristics of axial and peripheral disorders and extraarticular symptoms were common (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zunino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreira, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aroca Briones, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellomio, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sueldo Ra, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Spindler, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Citera, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albiero, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sandoval, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rillo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chaparro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paira, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarellos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermana, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wong, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berman, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado, CG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romeo, CB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graf, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nitsche, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asnal, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado Cocco, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las principales características de las espondiloartritis (SpA) en la población argentina. Material y métodos: Se realizó un análisis descriptivo y transversal de la información recogida entre marzo y diciembre de 2007 y almacenada en línea, en la página electrónica del grupo Registro de Espondiloartritis de la Sociedad Española de Reumatología (REGISPONSER). Participaron 11 centros de Argentina, siguiendo todos similares pautas de evaluación del paciente y de registro de datos. Resultados: Se incluyó a 405 pacientes con SpA, 238 varones (59%), con una edad media desviación estándar de 48,1 15,7 años y un tiempo de evolución medio de la enfermedad de 10,9 9,5 años. La artritis psoriásica (APs) fue el diagnóstico prevalente (46,7%), y siguiendo en orden de frecuencia estaban la espondilitis anquilosante (EA) (30,3%) y la SpA indiferenciada (12,4%). La edad al inicio fue de 38,4 16,6 años y el tiempo de evolución hasta el diagnóstico fue de 7,5 8,6 años. Los síntomas de inicio más frecuentes fueron artritis periférica (66%), lumbalgia (54%) y sacroileítis (39%). El 43% presentó dactilitis y el 10%, uveítis durante la evolución de la enfermedad. El tratamiento incluyó inhibidores del factor de necrosis tumoral en un 10,4% de los pacientes. El BASDAI promedio fue de 4 2,5 puntos y el BASFI, de 3,3 2,9 puntos. Los pacientes con EA presentaron una edad menor, más discapacidad laboral, más dolor, una afectación axial mayor y más daño radiológico que los pacientes con APs. Regis Conclusión: Los pacientes de Argentina con SpA presentan las clásicas características de afectación axial y periférica, y con frecuencia presentan manifestaciones extraarticulares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);4(extr.4): 23-29, nov. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registro Iberoamericano de Espondiloartritis (RESPONDIA): Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36004^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
