<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130893</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of depression, anxiety, stress and adherence to treatment in dialysis patients&#146; health-related quality of life: a systematic review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Health-related quality of life (HRQOL) has been widely studied in the field of dialysis patients. However, there are few studies that include relationships of psychosocial variables and adherence to treatment with HRQOL. The aim of this review is to systematically synthesise available information on the role that psychological variables (depression, anxiety and stress) and adherence to treatment have on HRQOL of dialysis patients through a systematic narrative review. We selected studies that included and related, in their results psychological variables (at least one of the following: depression, anxiety or perceived stress), adherence to treatment and HRQOL in adults on dialysis due to advanced chronic kidney disease (ACKD). The studies included had to incorporate standardised instruments into their assessment protocol. We searched the MEDLINE and PsycINFO databases from January 2002 to August 2012. Thirty-eight studies were included in this review and we assessed their methodological quality. The review revealed that 100% of the studies identified a negative association between indicators of anxiety, depression and stress and HRQL, indicating that these variables are risk factors for quality of life. Adherence to treatment was associated with psychological factors and HRQOL in 8% (N=3) of the studies included and has been demonstrated to be a protective factor for quality of life in 66% of studies (2 of 3) that included this variable. Considering the effect of these variables on HRQOL, it is important to screen for early indicators of anxiety, stress and depression or difficulties in complying with treatment in the ACKD population on dialysis. This will allow preventive interventions to be carried out before HRQOL deteriorates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Selgas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Remor, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peso , Gloria del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Llana, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) ha sido ampliamente estudiada en el ámbito de los pacientes en diálisis. Sin embargo, son pocos los trabajos que incluyen las relaciones de variables psicosociales y de adhesión al tratamiento con la CVRS. El objetivo de esta revisión es sintetizar sistemáticamente la información disponible sobre el rol que las variables psicológicas (depresión, ansiedad y estrés) y la adhesión al tratamiento tienen sobre la CVRS de los pacientes en diálisis a través de una revisión narrativa sistemática. Se seleccionaron los estudios que incluyeron y relacionaron en sus resultados variables psicológicas (al menos una de ellas: depresión, ansiedad o estrés percibido), adhesión al tratamiento y CVRS en población adulta en tratamiento con diálisis debido a su enfermedad renal crónica avanzada (ERCA). Los estudios incluidos debían incorporar en su protocolo de evaluación instrumentos estandarizados. Se efectuaron búsquedas en las bases de datos MedLINE y PsycINFO de enero de 2002 a agosto de 2012. Se incluyeron 38 estudios en esta revisión y fueron sometidos a una evaluación de la calidad metodológica. La revisión ha permitido observar que un 100 % de los trabajos identifica una asociación negativa entre indicadores de ansiedad, depresión y estrés con la CVRS, reflejando que dichas variables son factores de riesgo para la calidad de vida. La adhesión al tratamiento ha sido asociada con factores psicológicos y con la CVRS en un 8 % (N = 3) de los estudios incluidos, mostrándose un factor de protección para la calidad de vida en el 66 % de los estudios (2 de 3) que incluyeron la variable adhesión. Considerando el efecto de dichas variables sobre la CVRS, es importante detectar precozmente indicadores de ansiedad, estrés y depresión o dificultades para cumplir con el tratamiento en la población ERCA en diálisis. Esto permitirá intervenir a tiempo antes de que la CVRS se vea mermada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;34(5): 637-657, sept.-oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130893</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel de la depresión, la ansiedad, el estrés y la adhesión al tratamiento en la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en pacientes en diálisis: revisión sistemática de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
