<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051252</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Accumulation of mast cells in the interstitium of eosinophilic colitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The mechanism of eosinophilic colitis remains unclear, and no case has been reported in which the number of mast cells was examined.         Case report: A 35-year-old man presented to our hospital with chief complaints of chills and consistent watery diarrhea after eating raw fresh-water fish. In blood examination, peripheral blood eosinophilia was found. Histological examination from biopsy specimens of both the ascending colon and rectum showed a prominent eosinophilic infiltration in the intestinal mucosa. Although a provocation test could not be performed due to lack of informed consent, a diagnosis of eosinophilic colitis was made on the basis of other findings. Immunohistochemical staining for human mast cell tryptase using monoclonal antibody against human mast cell tryptase showed an accumulation of mast cells in the colonic interstitium.         Conclusions: We report a case of eosinophilic colitis in which an accumulation of mast cells in the colonic interstitium was demonstrated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suzuki, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kashiwase, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kurosawa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Igarashi, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morioka, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Inamura, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el mecanismo de la colitis eosinofílica es aún incierto y no hay publicado ningún caso en que se haya examinado el contenido en mastocitos.         Caso clínico: varón de 35 años visitado en el hospital aquejado de escalofríos y diarrea acuosa después de haber comidado pescado de agua dulce crudo. El hemograma mostró eosinofilia. En las biópsias de la mucosa del colon ascendente y del recto se encontró un intenso infiltrado eosinofílico. Aunque no se realizó prueba de provocación por no haberse conseguido el cosentimiento informado del paciente, el diagnóstico de colitis eosinofílica se hizo por los hallazgos obtenidos. La tinción inmunohistoquímica de la triptasa de los mastocitos se realizó con anticuerpo monoclonal frente a triptasa de mastocitos humanos, mostrandose un acúmulo de estas células en el intesticio del colon.         Conclusiones: se presenta un caso de colitis eosinofílica en la que se demostró un acúmulo de mastocitos en el intersticio del cólon</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);34(5): 228-230, sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051252</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acumulación de mastocitos en el intersticio en la colitis eosinofílica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3123^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8579^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3123^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4881^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5908^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
