<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97854</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How is an instrument for measuring health to be validated?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is increasingly necessary to have a measuring instrument available in the health field that can be used in clinical practice and research. In order to guarantee the quality of their measurements it is essential that the instruments should be subjected to a process of validation. This process consists in adapting the instrument culturally to the setting where its psychometric characteristics are to be administered and checked, such as: reliability, validity, sensitivity and feasibility. There are measuring instruments from the health field available in other languages but that have not been validated into Spanish. Besides, the methodology for validating an instrument is little understood by the health professionals, which explains the indiscriminate use of instruments that have only been adapted or validated in a way that is not very consistent. The aim of this review is to bring up to date the process of validating an instrument for measuring health, and what it involves, in a practical way. The accessibility of evaluation instruments that have been culturally adapted and validated in different languages will facilitate the comparison of results obtained with the same instrument and the development international studies in different cultures(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Watson, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Centeno, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Rubiales, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carvajal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cada vez es más necesario disponer de instrumentos de medida en el ámbito de la salud que se puedan utilizar en la práctica clínica e investigación. Para garantizar la calidad de su medición es imprescindible que los instrumentos sean sometidos a un proceso de validación. Este proceso consiste en adaptar culturalmente un instrumento al medio donde se quiere administrar y comprobar sus características psicométricas como: fiabilidad, validez, sensibilidad y factibilidad. Hay instrumentos de medida del ámbito de la salud, disponibles en otros idiomas pero sin validar al español. Además la metodología para validar un instrumento es poco conocida por profesionales sanitarios, lo que explica el uso indiscriminado de instrumentos sólo adaptados o validados de manera poco consistente. El objetivo de esta revisión es realizar una puesta al día del proceso de validación de un instrumento de medida de la salud y en qué consiste de manera práctica. La accesibilidad de instrumentos de evaluación adaptados culturalmente y validados en distintos idiomas facilitará comparar resultados obtenidos con el mismo instrumento y desarrollar estudios internacionales en distintas culturas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;34(1): 63-72, ene.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo validar un instrumento de medida de la salud?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52871</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
