<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136507</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Latest advances in chronic pancreatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article summarizes some of the recent and clinically relevant advances in chronic pancreatitis. These advances mainly concern knowledge of the etiopathogenesis of the disease, the pharmacological treatment of pain, and knowledge of the natural history of autoimmune pancreatitis. New evidence supports the relatively low prevalence of chronic alcoholic pancreatitis, and the role of tobacco in triggering the etiopathogenic mechanisms of chronic pancreatitis is better understood. Some studies have identified certain factors that are associated with having a positive genetic test in adults with chronic idiopathic pancreatitis, which should help to select those patients who should undergo genetic studies. Antioxidant therapy has been shown to be effective in reducing pain secondary to chronic pancreatitis, although the type and optimal dose of antioxidants remains to be elucidated. Finally, the development of exocrine and endocrine pancreatic insufficiency is a very common finding during the long-term follow-up of patients with autoimmune pancreatitis. Smoking also seems to play a role in this type of pancreatitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez-Muñoz, J. Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los avances más recientes con impacto en la práctica clínica de los pacientes con pancreatitis crónica se centran en el conocimiento etiopatogénico de la enfermedad, en el tratamiento farmacológico del dolor y en el conocimiento de la historia natural de la pancreatitis autoinmune. Mientras que se confirma el papel relativamente menos relevante del consumo de alcohol en la etiopatogenia de la pancreatitis crónica, se han descrito los mecanismos a través de los cuales el tabaco es capaz de desencadenar los procesos que conllevan el desarrollo de la enfermedad. Además se han propuesto factores que se asocian a un resultado genético positivo en pacientes con pancreatitis crónica idiopática, lo cual ayuda a la selección de los pacientes para este tipo de estudios. En el tratamiento del dolor, la administración oral de antioxidantes es eficaz, aunque queda por demostrar la combinación y dosis óptima de antioxidantes. Por último, el desarrollo de insuficiencia pancreática exocrina y endocrina es muy frecuente en la historia natural de la pancreatitis autoinmune, en cuyo desarrollo juega igualmente un papel significativo el hábito tabáquico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;36(supl.2): 86-89, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Últimos avances en pancreatitis crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50479^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50479^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50479^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
