<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040677</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital insensitivity to pain with anhidrosis associated with congenital myasthenic syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Congenital insensitivity to pain with anhidrosis (CIPA) or hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathytype IV (HSAN IV) is a rare autosomal recessive disorder featuring recurrent fever episodes, inability to sweat, absent responseto noxious stimuli, self mutilating behavior and mental retardation. It has been associated with mutations in the NTRK1 gene,located in 1q21-22 and encoding a high-affinity NGF receptor. Case report. An 8-year-old boy, the first son of consanguineousparents, presented with hypotonia, episodic hyperpyrexia and global developmental delay since the neonatal period. In additionto these signs, typical of CIPA, he displayed some other not previously described in this disease, such as facial dysmorphism, asevere swallowing disorder and a myogenic EMG pattern, that led to the initial suspicion of a muscle disorder. Moleculargenetics studies uncovered a mutation c.C2011T in exon 15 of the NTRK1 gene. Genetic counselling was possible in thefollowing pregnancy of the couple, where the female fetus was found to harbour the mutation in heterozygosity. The subsequentdiagnosis of a congenital myasthenic syndrome in this sister led to neurophysiological re-evaluation of the probandus, in whom amyasthenic pattern of muscle activation was also found. Conclusions. A patient with CIPA and congenital myasthenic syndromeis described. CIPA must be the first diagnostic hypothesis when assessing a patient with insensitivity to pain, anhidrosis and selfmutilation.Given the rather homogeneous presentation of CIPA, the occurrence of atypical myopathic manifestations shouldraise the suspicion of a concurrent disorder. The present consanguineous kindred illustrates a rare instance of transmission of twomutated alleles giving rise to two unrelated, infrequent neurological syndromes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gratacós, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca-León, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macaya-Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Indo, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raspall-Chaure, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toro-Riera, M. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig-Quilis, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La insensibilidad congénita al dolor con anhidrosis(CIPA) o neuropatía hereditaria sensitivoautonómica detipo IV (HSAN IV) es un raro trastorno autosómico recesivo caracterizadopor episodios recurrentes de fiebre, anhidrosis, ausencia desensibilidad al dolor y retraso mental de gravedad variable. Se asociaa mutaciones en el gen NTRK1, localizado en el cromosoma1q21-22, que codifica uno de los receptores del factor de crecimientonervioso. Caso clínico. Describimos el caso de un niño de 8 añosde edad, primer hijo de padres consanguíneos, que presenta hipotonía,episodios de hiperpirexia y retraso global desde el período neonatal,manifestaciones típicas de la CIPA, además de signos previamenteno descritos en esta enfermedad como son anomalías fenotípicas,un grave trastorno de deglución durante los primeros mesesde vida y un patrón miógeno en el estudio neurofisiológico, que condujerona la sospecha inicial de proceso miopático. El estudio genéticomolecular detectó una mutación c.C2011T en el exón 15 del genNTRK1. El hallazgo de dicha mutación en heterocigosidad en lahermana menor del paciente permitió efectuar consejo genético. Sinembargo, el diagnóstico de un síndrome miasténico congénito enesta hermana y la posterior observación de hallazgos neurofisiológicosmiasteniformes también en nuestro paciente permiten explicarla existencia de estas manifestaciones atípicas de la CIPA. Conclusiones.Presentamos un paciente afecto de CIPA y síndrome miasténicocongénito. Debe considerarse la posibilidad de CIPA como primerahipótesis diagnóstica en la valoración de un paciente coninsensibilidad al dolor, anhidrosis y automutilación. Dada la considerablehomogeneidad clínica de la CIPA, la aparición de signosatípicos miopáticos debe despertar la sospecha de algún otro trastornoasociado. La familia consanguínea que presentamos ilustra lasituación muy poco frecuente de transmisión de dos alelos mutados,causantes de dos enfermedades neurológicas supuestamente monogénicas,a un mismo individuo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(4): 218-222, abr. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040677</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insensibilidad congénita al dolor con anhidrosis asociada a síndrome miasténico congénito</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9020^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34336^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23938^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23938^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23938^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23938^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
