<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042671</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Generic drugs in the treatment of epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. We discuss some controversial aspects with prescription of generic drugs (GD) and the problems concerningbioequivalence, mainly in the case of drugs with non-linear pharmacokinetics and/or narrow therapeutic rank, like the antiepilepticdrugs (AED). Development. There is considerable debate about GD in the treatment of epilepsy, with clearlyadvantages (cost saving) and disadvantages (loos of seizure control or drug toxicity) in prescribing generics anticonvulsivants.We make a systematic review of the literature in primary (PubMed) and secondary (Tripdatabase and Cochrane Library)bibliographic databases in relation to GD and AED. The main information is about classical AED (phenytoin, carbamazepine,valproic acid and primidone) and we don&#146;t found studies in this area about the new AED. The level of evidence is, generally,weak, based on case-series and expert opinion without explicit critical appraisal (except in phenytoin with level of evidencemoderate, based on some analytical studies). In Spain, at this moment, there are only two generic AED, one-classical(carbamazepine) and one-new (gabapentin). Conclusion. The American Academy of Neurology and Epilepsy Foundationmaintains that the individual and physician should be notified and give their consent before a switch in antiepilepticmedications is made, whether it involves generic substitution for brand name products, or generic to generic substitutions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sempere, A. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa-Sangrador, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Se plantean algunos aspectos controvertidosen la prescripción de una especialidad farmacéutica genérica(EFG), así como los problemas en relación con la bioequivalencia,principalmente en el caso de medicamentos con cinética no linealy/o rango terapéutico estrecho, como los fármacos antiepilépticos(FAE). Desarrollo. Existe un considerable debate en relación conlas EFG en el tratamiento de la epilepsia, con claras ventajas(ahorro de costes) e inconvenientes (pérdida en el control de lascrisis y toxicidad) al prescribir antiepilépticos genéricos. Realizamosuna revisión sistemática de la bibliografía, tanto en fuentes deinformación primaria (PubMed) como en fuentes de informaciónsecundaria (Tripdatabase y Cochrane Library), en relación conEFG y FAE. La principal información se obtiene de los FAE clásicos(fenitoína, carbamacepina, ácido valproico y primidona) y nodetectamos ningún estudio en esta área de estudio relativo a nuevosFAE. El nivel de evidencia es, generalmente, débil, basado enseries de casos y en la opinión de expertos sin una valoración críticaexplícita (excepto en el caso de la fenitoína, con un nivel de evidenciamoderado con base en algunos estudios analíticos). En España,en el momento actual, hay disponibles sólo dos FAE genéricos,uno clásico (carbamacepina) y otro nuevo (gabapentina). Conclusión.La American Academy of Neurology y la Epilepsy Foundationmantienen que el paciente y médico deben estar informados ydar su consentimiento antes de realizar un cambio de medicaciónantiepiléptica, bien sea la sustitución de un genérico por un fármacode marca, o la sustitución de un genérico por otro genérico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(11): 676-683, dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fármacos genéricos en el tratamiento de la epilepsia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30149^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30149^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
