<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140102</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Features healthcare of patients in temporary disability in the area of health of Albacete</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fundamentals: The temporary disability (TD) constitutes a major health, economic and social problem. The objective of the study is to describe the reasons for IT, job satisfaction, and features social and health care of subjects that remain in IT for a long time.  Methods: Descriptive study cross, about 404 patients in IT. Data were collected on: diagnosis of IT, job satisfaction, self-perceived health, features sociodemographic, health status and profile of locus of control.   Results: Among the people in IT dominate males (53.2%), with average age of 48.1, married (64.1%), with low level of education (36.1%) and lower social classes (27.2%). Predominant diseases are diseases of the locomotor system (46.5%), followed by psychological problems (18.6%) and cardiovascular diseases (6.2%). Patients show an acceptable level of job satisfaction, which is higher in men (76.5 ± 12, US), in belonging to higher social categories (80.9 ± 14.9 of in categories I-II) and workers with high level of instruction (80.5 ± 14.5 of in people with University studies). Most qualifies as good health (57.9%), and without a predominant profile of locus (37.6%). Most have previous episodes of IT, generally less than 6 months (74.5%).  Conclusions: Men of middle age, with diseases of the musculoskeletal, low level of instruction, good health self-perceived, satisfied with his work and belonging to the lower social classes comprise the most common profile of the patient who stays in IT for an extended period, not observed including a profile of locus of control predominantly (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Torres Hidalgo, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Verdejo, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Morote, M Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La incapacidad temporal (IT) constituye un importante problema sanitario, económico y social. El objetivo del estudio es describir los motivos de IT, satisfacción laboral y características sociosanitarias de los sujetos que permanecen en IT durante un periodo prolongado.  Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal, sobre 404 pacientes en IT. Se recogieron datos sobre: diagnóstico de IT, satisfacción laboral, salud autopercibida, características sociodemográficas, estado de salud y perfil de locus de control.  Resultados: Entre las personas en IT predominan los varones (53,2%), con edad media de 48,1 años, casados (64,1%), con bajo nivel de instrucción (36,1%) y pertenecientes a clases sociales inferiores (27,2%). Las enfermedades predominantes son las enfermedades del aparato locomotor (46,5%), seguidas de problemas psicológicos (18,6%) y enfermedades cardiovasculares (6,2%). Los pacientes muestran un nivel aceptable de satisfacción laboral, siendo ésta superior en hombres (76,5 ± 12,9DE), en pertenecientes a categorías sociales superiores (80,9 ± 14,9 DE en categorías I-II) y en trabajadores con nivel de instrucción elevado (80,5 ± 14,5 DE en personas con estudios universitarios). La mayoría califica su salud como buena (57,9%), y sin un perfil predominante de locus (37,6%). La mayoría tienen episodios previos de IT, generalmente inferiores a 6 meses (74,5%).  Conclusiones: Varones de mediana edad, con enfermedades del aparato locomotor, bajo nivel de instrucción, buena salud autopercibida, satisfechos con su trabajo y pertenecientes a clases sociales inferiores conforman el perfil más común del paciente que permanece en IT durante un periodo prolongado, no observándose entre ellos un perfil de locus de control predominante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;61(238): 45-46, ene.-mar. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140102</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características sociosanitarias de los pacientes en incapacidad temporal en el área sanitaria de Albacete</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
