<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118325</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Music in the teaching of pharmacology and psychiatry: the case of The Beautiful Brains</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Music, in its different modalities, is a prominent cultural element of modern societies. The use of songs and rhymes in the teaching of biomedical subjects is, however, a recent fact, even when they had been used in other educational levels during many years. At the college level, songs have been used in the teaching of basic biomedical disciplines, such as Biochemistry or Cellular biology, but also in clinical subjects, such as Psychiatry or Clinical Psychology. The present paper reviews the use of music in several subjects related with biomedical field. It also reviews the works of The Beautiful Brains, a musical group formed by psychiatrists, to find which songs can be useful in the teaching of pharmacology and psychiatry. In spite of the lack of known experiences in our context, we suggest that music, as well as songs, may be useful as a teaching aid in the training of students of biomedical disciplines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torrens, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baños, Josep E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La música, en sus diferentes posibilidades, constituye un elemento cultural básico de las sociedades modernas. La utilización de canciones en la docencia de las disciplinas científicas es un hecho relativamente reciente, aun cuando se han empleado en otros niveles educativos desde siempre. En el ámbito universitario se han utilizado tanto en las disciplinas básicas (bioquímica, biología celular, farmacología) como clínicas (psiquiatría, psicología clínica). En el presente artículo se revisa el empleo de la música en la docencia de las ciencias biomédicas. En este contexto se describe la obra musical de The Beautiful Brains, un grupo formado por psiquiatras, con una atención especial a las canciones que pueden emplearse en la docencia de la farmacología y de la psiquiatría. A pesar de la inexistencia de experiencias conocidas en nuestro ámbito, se sugiere que la utilización de los recursos musicales como adyuvante pedagógico puede tener gran interés en la docencia de las disciplinas sanitarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);16(4): 197-202, dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118325</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Música en la docencia de la farmacología y la psiquiatría: el caso de The Beautiful Brains</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10790^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
