<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158655</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Limits in medical care and social relief during the Spanish Civil War in a rear-guard city: the Inclusa of the Provincial Hospital of Valencia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to its geostrategic condition during the Spanish Civil War, Valencia became one of the Republican cities welcoming more refugees, including many children. In this scenario of demographic and health crisis, the town had to restructure the assistance network in order to accommodate thousands of displaced children, who often had their relatives in faraway places. The paper focuses in the progressive rehabilitation undertaken by the Inclusa of Valencia, which was the provincial foundling hospital. This included deep changes both in its operation and in the admission criteria, particularly following the transfer of the Inclusa of Madrid to Valencia. The resulting overcrowding encouraged the degradation of healthcare and the spread of infectious diseases among the welcomed children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Ferrandis, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Vidal, Álvar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Debido a su condición geoestratégica durante la Guerra Civil española, Valencia se convirtió en una de las ciudades republicanas que acogieron mayor número de refugiados, entre ellos muchos niños. En este escenario de crisis demográfica y sanitaria, la ciudad tuvo que reestructurar la red de asistencia con el fin de acoger miles de niños desplazados que, a menudo, tenían a sus familiares en lugares muy lejanos. El artículo analiza la readaptación progresiva que acometió la Inclusa del Hospital Provincial de Valencia. Esta sufrió profundos cambios tanto en su funcionamiento como en su demografía sanitaria, sobre todo como consecuencia del traslado a Valencia de la Inclusa de Madrid. El consiguiente hacinamiento favoreció la degradación de la asistencia sanitaria que allí se dispensaba y la propagación de enfermedades infecciosas entre los niños acogidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;68(2): 0-0, jul.-dic. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Límites de la asistencia médica y social durante la Guerra Civil Española en una ciudad de retaguardia: la Inclusa del Hospital Provincial de Valencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8653^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28462^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8653^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8653^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28462^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28462^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
