<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60282</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment with venlafaxine extended release for climacteric women with depression or anxiety diagnosis. An open-label study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The objective of this observational study was to assess under real clinical practice conditions the effectiveness and safety of venlafaxine extended release in anxiety-depressed and hormone-related symptoms in climacteric women with anxiety or depressive disorders. Methodology. Observational, prospective, open-label, multicenter, 24-week study, carried out in Spain. A sample of 45 outpatients, adult women between 45 and 55 years of age, diagnosed of depressive disorder, generalized anxiety disorder or social anxiety disorder were analyzed. Venlafaxine extended release was administered for 24 weeks at doses according to the investigator&#146;s clinical criteria. Results. Of the total of 45 patients who were included in the study, 43 (95.6%) completed it. The patients&#146; age range was of 47 to 55 years old, median of 50 and mean of 50.82. The clinical condition evolution was assessed with the evaluation scales scores: Blatt-Kuppermann Menopausal Index, Hamilton Depression Rating Scale, Hamilton Anxiety Scale and Clinical Global Impression. During the 24-week period, a significant decrease in the different scales scores showed a clinical improvement. Conclusions. The results achieved show that treatment with venlafaxine extended release significantly improved the clinical condition of climacteric patients with anxiety or depressive disorder. If these results are confirmed with placebo-controlled clinical trials, they will support the utility of Venlafaxine extended release in this kind of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocio, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortigosa, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pato, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamarina, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de este estudio observacional fue evaluar, bajo condiciones reales de práctica clínica, la efectividad y seguridad de venlafaxina clorhidrato en síntomas de ansiedad-depresión y síntomas hormonales en mujeres climatéricas con trastorno de ansiedad o depresivo. Metodología. Estudio observacional, prospectivo, abierto y multicéntrico, de 24 semanas de duración, llevado a cabo en España. Se analizó una muestra de 45 pacientes ambulatorios mujeres de entre 45 y 55 años con diagnóstico de episodio depresivo, trastorno de ansiedad generalizada o trastorno de ansiedad social. Se administró venlafaxina clorhidrato durante 24 semanas a dosis según criterio clínico del investigador. Resultados. De las 45 pacientes que iniciaron el estudio, 43 (95,6%) finalizaron el mismo. El rango de edad fue de 47 a 55 años, una mediana de 50 años y una media 50,82 años. La evolución de la situación clínica fue mesurada por la puntuación de las escalas de evaluación: Índice Menopáusico de Blatt-Kuppermann; Escala de Hamilton para la Depresión; Escala de Hamilton de Ansiedad e Impresión Clínica Global. Durante las 24 semanas se observó una mejoría clínica demostrada por una disminución significativa de las puntuaciones de las distintas escalas. Conclusiones. Los resultados obtenidos indican que el tratamiento con venlafaxina clorhidrato mejoró significativamente la situación clínica de las pacientes climatéricas con trastorno de ansiedad o trastorno depresivo. En el caso de confirmarse mediante ensayos controlados con placebo, estos resultados avalarían la utilidad de la venlafaxina clorhidrato en este tipo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(3): 137-142, mayo-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con venlafaxina clorhidrato de mujeres climatéricas con diagnóstico de ansiedad o depresión. Estudio abierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22129^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
