<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89244</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influenza A, pregnancy and neuraminidase inhibitors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Following the explosion of the influenza A pandemic (H1N1) during the first semester of 2009, oseltamivir and zanamivir were used as the treatment of choice in the absence of rigorous clinical studies demonstrating their efficacy in the treatment and prophylaxis of this disease. Knowledge of seasonal influenza, flu pandemics and particularly the H1N1, which produces more severe infection and a higher mortality rate during pregnancy, led to the use of antiviral treatment despite the scarcity of clinical studies on their efficacy and effectiveness, mainly due to the influence of the media. This study reviewed the experimental and clinical studies performed on the safety of oseltamivir and zanamivir in pregnancy. Likewise, the recommendations made by the different health care and governmental authorities as well as other institutions and scientific and health care organizations on the therapeutic management and prophylaxis of influenza A 2009 in pregnant women were reviewed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montané, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecumberri, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedro Botet, Marí­a Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras la eclosión de la pandemia de la gripe A (H1N1) durante el primer semestre de 2009, el oseltamivir y el zanamivir emergieron como tratamiento de elección en ausencia de estudios clínicos rigurosos que demostraran su eficacia en el tratamiento y la profilaxis de esta entidad. El conocimiento de que la gripe estacional, las pandemias de gripe y ésta en particular causan una infección más grave y una mayor tasa de mortalidad durante el embarazo obligó por razones mediáticas a considerar un tratamiento antivírico a pesar de la escasez de estudios clínicos de eficacia y de efectividad de que disponemos. En este trabajo se han revisado los estudios experimentales y clínicos sobre la seguridad de oseltamivir y zanamivir en el embarazo. Asimismo, se han recogido las recomendaciones realizadas por las distintas autoridades sanitarias y reguladoras, así como de otras instituciones y organismos científicos y sanitarios sobre el tratamiento terapéutico y la profilaxis de la gripe A (H1N1) 2009 en la mujer embarazada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);136(15): 688-693, mayo 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89244</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gripe A, embarazo y antiví­ricos inhibidores de la neuraminidasa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9632^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11691^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
