<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106618</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of the smoke-free legislation on the prevalence and referred time exposure to the environmental tobacco smoke in Zaragoza</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To assess the impact of the Law 42/2010, on the health measures on smoking, on the prevalence of the exposure to environmental tobacco smoke (ETS), the repercussions in frequently visited places, and support of the new legislation. Design: A before-after evaluation by comparing two cross-sectional studies the comparison of two transverse surveys. Place: Primary Care, Delicias district (115,446 inhabitants) of Zaragoza city, including the Delicias Sur, Delicias Norte, Bombarda and Univérsitas basic health districts. Participants: A total of 387 users in 2009, and 400 in 2011 with ages between 20 and 79 years old assigned to the participating Primary Care Centres. Main measurements: Prevalences and mean exposure times, with their confidence intervals (CI). The differences were then calculated using the Chi-squared test and Analysis of Variance (ANOVA). Results: The exposure prevalence to the ETS in 2011 was shown to be lower and statistically significant than that found before the implementation of the new legislative measure, falling from the 61.9% to the 40.5% (CI 95%=35.8-45.4%), with 61.5% of those polled being in favour of the new law (CI 95%=59.2-68.75), and 80.5% (79,08-86.44) mentioned still going to the same places with the same frequency. Conclusions: The impact has been favourable, decreasing the exposure by more than 20%, with this fall being more marked in the population that currently define themselves as non-smokers. There is population support for the new legislation. Finally, there has been no observed fall in the frequency of visits to the same places(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Requeno Jarabo, María Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde Royo, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Izaguerri, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Val Esco, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba-García, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coronas Mateos, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el impacto de la Ley 42/2010 de medidas sanitarias frente al tabaquismo en la prevalencia de exposición referida al humo ambiental del tabaco (HAT), la repercusión en frecuentación de lugares y el apoyo a la nueva legislación. Diseño: Estudio de evaluación antes-después mediante comparación de 2 encuestas transversales. Emplazamiento: Atención Primaria, distrito de Delicias (115.446 habitantes) de la ciudad de Zaragoza, incluye a las zonas básicas de salud de Delicias Sur, Delicias Norte, Bombarda y Univérsitas. Participantes: Se incluyeron 387 usuarios en 2009 y 400 en 2011 de edades entre 20 y 79 años usuarios de los centros participantes. Mediciones principales: Prevalencias y medias de tiempos de exposición, así como sus intervalos de confianza. Posteriormente se calcularon sus diferencias mediante test de chi cuadrado y análisis de la varianza (ANOVA). Resultados: La prevalencia de exposición referida al HAT en el 2011 se muestra inferior y estadísticamente significativa a la hallada antes de la aplicación de la nueva medida legislativa, pasando del 61,9 al 40,5% (IC al 95%=35,8-45,4%). El 61,5% de los encuestados se situaban a favor de la nueva ley (IC al 95%=59,2-68,75). El 80,5% (79,08-86,44) referían seguir acudiendo a los mismos con la misma frecuencia. Conclusiones: El impacto ha sido favorable, disminuyéndose las exposiciones en más de un 20%, siendo más marcado este descenso en la población que actualmente se define como no fumadora. Existe apoyo poblacional a la nueva legislación. Y no se objetiva descenso en la frecuentación de locales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;44(10): 603-610, oct. 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106618</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la regulación de espacios sin humo en la exposición referida al humo ambiental de tabaco en Zaragoza</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
