<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044081</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital coronary artery anomalies with origin in the contralateral sinus of Valsalva: which approach should we take?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent years have witnessed a change in our perception of congenital coronary artery anomalies. From being regarded as simple coronary angiographic observations of little clinical significance, they have come to be seen as potential causes of sudden death in young people and of myocardial ischemia in adults. Diagnostic difficulties, a lack of knowledge about the mechanisms through which they produce myocardial ischemia, and their highly variable incidence have made congenital coronary artery anomalies of great interest to cardiologists. This article focuses on the group of coronary artery anomalies that is responsible for most clinical events: anomalies that have their origin in the contralateral sinus of Valsalva. Coronary artery anomalies are defined, their incidence is discussed, diagnostic criteria are given, and finally a treatment algorithm based on current knowledge is proposed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morís de la Tassa, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriales-Villa, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años se está produciendo un cambio en la actitud hacia las anomalías congénitas de las arterias coronarias. De simples hallazgos de las coronariografías, sin mayor trascendencia clínica, han pasado a considerarse como causa de muerte súbita en jóvenes y posible causa de isquemia en la población adulta. La dificultad en su diagnóstico, el desconocimiento de los mecanismos implicados en la producción de isquemia y la gran variabilidad en su incidencia hacen de las anomalías congénitas de las arterias coronarias un tema de gran interés para el cardiólogo. En este artículo nos centraremos en el grupo de anomalías coronarias causante de la mayor parte de eventos clínicos, que son las que tienen su origen en el seno de Valsalva contralateral. Definiremos qué se considera una anomalía coronaria y analizaremos cuál es su incidencia, cómo se diagnostican y, finalmente, propondremos un algoritmo para su tratamiento basado en los conocimientos actuales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(4): 360-370, abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044081</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anomalías congénitas de las arterias coronarias con origen en el seno de Valsalva contralateral: ¿qué actitud se debe seguir?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3345^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13231^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
