<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161439</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health-related quality of life in patients with spinocerebellar ataxia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The progressive deterioration of patients with spinocerebellar ataxia (SCA) has a major impact on their health-related quality of life (HRQOL). This study evaluates HRQOL in a sample of patients diagnosed with SCA and aims to estimate the predictive ability of a set of sociodemographic variables for the different dimensions of the General Health Questionnaire. Methods. A total of 80 patients diagnosed with SCA were assessed using a sociodemographic questionnaire and the SF-36 General Health Questionnaire. The sociodemographic variables studied were sex, age, presence of a carer, employment status, and time elapsed from diagnosis of the disease. Results. The 8 subscales of the SF-36 show positive and significant correlations to one another. Mean scores obtained on each SF-36 subscale differ between women and men, although this difference is significant only on the general health subscale, with men scoring higher than women. We found significant age differences on the vitality and social function subscales, with higher scores among younger patients (&lt; 34 years). The variable &#145;presence of a carer&#146; accounts for most of the total variance of the questionnaire. Conclusions. The SF-36 is a valid and useful instrument for evaluating HRQOL in patients diagnosed with SCA. Presence of a carer seems to be a determinant of self-perceived quality of life in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escobar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perestelo-Pérez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Bastida, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-López, CR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Aguilar, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El deterioro progresivo de los pacientes con ataxias espinocerebelosas (AEC) genera un gran impacto sobre su calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS). En este estudio se evalúa la CVRS en una muestra de pacientes diagnosticados de AEC y se pretende estimar la capacidad predictiva de un conjunto de variables sociodemográficas en las distintas dimensiones que conforman el cuestionario. Métodos. Se evaluó a un total de 80 pacientes diagnosticados de AEC, a través de un cuestionario sociodemográfico y del cuestionario genérico de salud SF-36. Se estudiaron variables sociodemográficas como sexo, edad, existencia de cuidador, situación laboral y tiempo desde el diagnóstico de la enfermedad. Resultados. Las dimensiones que componen el SF-36 muestran correlaciones positivas y significativas entre ellas. Las puntuaciones medias obtenidas en cada una de las dimensiones difieren según el sexo, siendo significativa la diferencia solo en la dimensión salud general, con media más alta en los hombres. En relación con la edad, se encuentran diferencias significativas en las dimensiones vitalidad y función social, con puntuaciones mayores en el rango de menor edad (menores de 34 años). La variable que explica la mayor parte de la varianza del cuestionario es la existencia de cuidador. Conclusiones. El Cuestionario de Salud SF-36 es un instrumento válido y fiable para medir la CVRS en pacientes con diagnóstico de AEC. Asimismo, la variable existencia de cuidador parece determinar la calidad de vida autopercibida por estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(3): 143-151, abr. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161439</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en pacientes con ataxias espinocerebelosas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34243^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34243^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
