<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164283</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">ULPGC-UniZambeze project. Undergraduate medical education in developing countries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Every nation &#150;rich or poor and developed or developing&#150; strives hard to deliver optimal healthcare to its citizens. Good health is the necessary condition for development and human security, but inequities in health persist. Medical educators have a key role to play in reducing inequities in global health by addressing the underlying doctor shortages that have reached crisis levels in some regions. The region in which these health inequities and doctor deficiencies are starkest is sub-Saharan Africa. In poor countries, a major constraint to approach this issue is the scarcity of qualified teachers. One of the options is the short-term placement of graduates from rich countries seeking opportunities to contribute in other countries that are severely deficient in faculty. But the world of medical education is not a level playing field and working in developing countries, and in remote areas in particular, can be challenging. In this article we show a recent experience carried out at the University of Las Palmas de Gran Canaria designing and supporting a project on undergraduate medical education at the University of Zambeze, in Tete, Mozambique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berriel Martínez, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Azpeitia, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de Castro, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Rivero, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Hernández, José Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Todos los países, cualquiera que sea su grado de desarrollo, se esfuerzan por proporcionar unos cuidados sanitarios adecuados a sus ciudadanos. Gozar de buena salud es una condición básica para el desarrollo y la seguridad de las personas, a pesar de lo cual persisten enormes desigualdades en salud entre los países. Los educadores médicos tienen un papel clave en la reducción de estas desigualdades al abordar uno de los aspectos esenciales del problema: la acusada escasez de médicos que sufren algunas regiones, especialmente en el África subsahariana. Una de las mayores dificultades para afrontar esta cuestión es la falta de profesores cualificados, lo que podría solventarse mediante estancias cortas de graduados procedentes de países desarrollados que voluntariamente quisieran participar en este tipo de iniciativas. Pero el mundo de la educación médica tampoco es un terreno justo, equilibrado y equitativo, y trabajar en países pobres y alejados supone un reto importante. En este artículo, presentamos la experiencia en el diseño y desarrollo de un proyecto de formación de médicos en la Universidad de Zambeze, en Tete (Mozambique), llevada a cabo desde la Universidad de Las Palmas de Gran Canaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);20(3): 111-116, mayo-jun. 2017. ilus, tab, mapas, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164283</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proyecto ULPGC-UniZambeze. Formación médica universitaria en países en desarrollo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3926</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12958^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9266</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35176</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
