<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142178</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Breastfeeding at Pla d´Urgell, Catalonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The introduction of formula feeding resulted in a significant decrease in the use of breastfeeding, which has been partially corrected recently as a result of public health campaigns. In order to improve the prevalence and duration of breastfeeding, it is necessary to evaluate the current feeding practices and the determining factors in our population. Objective. To describe the trends in the prevalence of breastfeeding, and to evaluate the factors that influence its practice and maintenance in our population. Method. In this retrospective study, we reviewed the charts of all infants born in two periods, 1998-1999, and 2000-2001. The following variables were analyzed: maternal age, parity, feeding practice, duration, cause for discontinuation, cause for not using breastfeeding, and maternal work. Results. We reviewed 517 charts (first period, 236 infants; second period, 281 infants). Breastfeeding was started in 68.6% and 71.9% of the infants, respectively. The mean duration of breastfeeding was 90.9 and 104.7 days, respectively. The most common reasons for not starting breastfeeding were medical indications and maternal preference. The factors that conditioned the duration of breastfeeding were medical indications at the beginning, maternal work between 2 and 4 months, and maternal choice thereafter. Conclusions. We have documented an increase in the practice and duration of breastfeeding in our area. The factors that determine its use and duration are maternal preferences, medical indications, and maternal work (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juanós, Meritxell</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Arbonés, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarasa, M. Angels</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bringué, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carulla, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañete, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esquerda, Montse</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revuelta, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Con la aparición de las leches artificiales se produjo una disminución de la lactancia materna que se ha ido corrigiendo gracias a las campañas de promoción. Para mejorar la prevalencia y duración de la lactancia materna es fundamental conocer la situación actual y los factores que la condicionan. Estos datos varían según los estudios.  Objetivo. Conocer la evolución de la prevalencia y los factores que influyen en la instauración y el mantenimiento de la lactancia materna en nuestra área. Método. Estudio retrospectivo revisando las historias clínicas de los recién nacidos de los periodos 1998-1999 y 2000-2001. Se analizaron las variables: edad materna, paridad, duración, motivo de abandono, motivo de no inicio y tipo de trabajo materno. Resultados. Se registraron 517 historias, 236 del primer periodo y 281 del segundo. Iniciaron lactancia materna el 68.6% y el 71.9% respectivamente. La duración media de la lactancia materna fue de 90.9 y 104.7 días. Las causas más frecuentes de no instauración de lactancia materna fueron las indicaciones médicas y la voluntad materna. Los factores que condicionan de manera más importante la duración fueron las indicaciones médicas al inicio, el trabajo entre los 2 y los 4 meses y la voluntad materna después. Conclusiones. Hemos apreciado que en nuestra área la prevalencia de lactancia materna presenta una discreta tendencia a aumentar tanto en porcentage de inicio como en duración, y que los factores que más influyen en la decisión de iniciar o mantener la lactancia materna son la voluntad materna, las indicaciones médicas y el trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;63(6): 319-323, nov.-dic. 2003. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142178</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lactancia maternal en el Pla d´Urgell</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10487^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
