<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17597</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of symmetry and curvilinearity on the processing of closed stimuli</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Processing of features as color or line orientation can be carried out with speed and accuracy, and apparently without focused attention. There is controversy about whether closure can be processed with similar efficiency. In this study, we investigated processing of closed stimuli and the influence on that processing, of features of symmetry and curvilinearity. In an experiment of texture segregation and two experiments of visual search, participants had to discriminate the closed from the open shapes, while the form of stimuli varied during the experiments. Performance was quite efficient when closed stimuli were also symmetrical and curvilinear, but it got worse when they lacked those properties. These results suggest that closure is not processed by itself, in an efficient way, but some closed shapes can be discriminated with speed and accuracy, while other closed shapes can not (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leirós, Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El procesamiento de características como el color o la orientación de línea puede realizarse con rapidez y precisión, y sin que parezca intervenir la atención focalizada. Existe controversia sobre si el cierre puede procesarse con una eficiencia similar. En este estudio, investigamos el procesamiento de estímulos cerrados y la influencia sobre ese procesamiento, de las características de simetría y curvilinealidad. En un experimento de segregación de textura y dos experimentos de búsqueda visual, los participantes deberán discriminar figuras cerradas de figuras abiertas, mientras la forma de los estímulos variaba a lo largo de los experimentos. La realización fue bastante eficiente cuando los estímulos cerrados eran también simétricos y curvilíneos, pero empeoraba cuando carecían de esas propiedades. Estos resultados sugieren que el cierre no se procesa por sí mismo de modo eficiente, sino que algunas formas cerradas pueden discriminarse con rapidez y precisión, mientras otras formas cerradas no (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(3): 597-604, ago. 2002. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17597</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la simetría y la curvilinealidad en el procesamiento de estímulos cerrados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5690</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
