<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037456</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Temperament and character profile of persons with suicide attempt</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this study was to establish the association between temperament and character personality traits with attempted suicide patients.         Method. Consecutive male and female adults subjects, between 18-65 years old, presenting a suicide attempt and hospitalized in the Psychiatric Service of Civil Hospital of Guadalajara, Jalisco (Mexico), were evaluated based on Cloninger's Temperament and Character Inventory (TCI) and compared with the Mexican normative data.                 Results. A total 63 subjects, with a mean age of 28.25 +/- 9.28 years old, 54 % of whom were women, were enrolled. Personality traits associated with suicide attempt in comparison with general population included: temperament: elevation in "novelty seeking" (22.9 +/- 6.0 vs 20.2 +/- 5.1; t = 3.30, df = 83, p = 0.01), "harm avoidance" (19.0 +/- 4.8 vs 12.6 +/- 7.1; t = 8.54, df = 132, p &lt; 0.001), and "self-transcendence" (19.1 +/- 5.6 vs 16.4 +/- 6.2; t = 3.41, df = 100, p = 0.0009); and character: decrease in «self-directedness » (26.8 +/- 6.2 vs 29.9 +/- 10.8; t = -3.02, df = 161, p=0.002), and "cooperativeness" (26.0 +/- 4.5 vs 28.2 +/- 9.9; t = -2.59, df = 214, p = 0.01). Finally, males with suicide attempt showed higher "harm avoidance" than females (20.37 +/- 5.3 vs 17.82 +/- 4.1; t = -2.14, df = 61, p = 0.036).                 Conclusions. Temperament traits associated with suicide attempt in the present study are related with serotoninergic and noradrenergic deregulation previously involved in the phenomena, and the sum of the character personality dimensions explains the complex relationship between biological and learned factors of suicide behavior</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Páez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela, G. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerra, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles-García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue determinar el perfil de temperamento y carácter relacionado con el intento suicida.         Método. Los pacientes consecutivos (hombres y mujeres), entre 18 y 65 años de edad, con intento suicida, hospitalizados en el Servicio de Psiquiatría del Antiguo Hospital Civil de Guadalajara, Jalisco (México), fueron evaluados con base en el Inventario de Temperamento y Carácter (ITC) de Cloninger y comparados con los datos normativos mexicanos.                 Resultados. Del total de 63 pacientes con edad promedio de 28,25 +/- 9,28 años, el 54 % son mujeres. El perfil de personalidad de las personas con intento suicida, a diferencia de la población normal, se caracterizó por: a) elevación de "búsqueda de la novedad" (22,9 +/- 6,0 frente a 20,2 +/- 5,1; t = 3,30, gl = 83, p = 0,01), "evitación del daño" (19,0 +/- 4,8 frente a 12,6 + 7,1; t = 8,54, gl = 132, p (0,0001) y "autotrascendencia" (19,1 +/- 5,6 frente a 16,4 +/- 6,2; t = 3,41, gl = 100, p= 0,0009), y b) disminución de "autodirección" (26,8 +/- 6,2 frente a 29,9 +/- 10,8; t = -3,02, gl = 161, p = 0,002) y "cooperatividad" (26,0 +/- 4,5 frente a 28,2 +/- 9,9; t = -2,59, gl = 214, p = 0,01). Finalmente, los hombres con intento suicida mostraron un mayor índice de evitación del daño en comparación con las mujeres (20,37 +/- 5,3 frente a 17,82 +/- 4,1; t = -2,14, gl = 61, p = 0,036).                 Conclusiones. Los factores temperamentales relacionados con el intento suicida están vinculados con la desregulación serotoninérgica y noradrenérgica relacionada previamente con este fenómeno, y la suma de rasgos de carácter dan cuenta de la compleja interacción entre pautas heredadas y aprendidas del comportamiento suicida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;33(2): 117-122, mar.-abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037456</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil de temperamento y carácter de pesonas con intento suicida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14072</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2648</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
