<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135400</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and Treatment of Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are three major challenges in the diagnosis of malignant pleural mesothelioma: mesothelioma must be distinguished from benign mesothelial hyperplasia; malignant mesothelioma (and its subtypes) must be distinguished from metastatic carcinoma; and invasion of structures adjacent to the pleura must be demonstrated. The basis for clarifying the first two aspects is determination of a panel of monoclonal antibodies with appropriate immunohistochemical evaluation performed by highly qualified experts. Clarification of the third aspect requires sufficiently abundant, deep biopsy material, for which thoracoscopy is the technique of choice. Video-assisted needle biopsy with real-time imaging can be of great assistance when there is diffuse nodal thickening and scant or absent effusion. Given the difficulties of reaching an early diagnosis, cure is not generally achieved with radical surgery (pleuropneumonectomy), so liberation of the tumor mass with pleurectomy/decortication combined with chemo- or radiation therapy  (multimodal treatment) has been gaining followers in recent years. In cases in which surgery is not feasible, chemotherapy (a combination of pemetrexed and platinum-derived compounds, in most cases) with pleurodesis or a tunneled pleural drainage catheter, if control of pleural effusion is required, can be considered. Radiation therapy is reserved for treatment of pain associated with infiltration of the chest wall or any other neighboring structure. In any case, comprehensive support treatment for pain control in specialist units is essential: this acquires particular significance in this type of malignancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Panadero, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico del mesotelioma pleural maligno presenta 3 importantes retos: es necesario distinguir entre hiperplasia mesotelial benigna y mesotelioma, entre mesotelioma maligno (con subtipos) y carcinoma metastásico, y también se requiere demostrar la invasión de estructuras vecinas a la pleura. Para aclarar los 2 primeros aspectos hay que basarse en un panel de anticuerpos monoclonales con adecuado estudio inmunohistoquímico &#151;realizado por manos muy expertas&#151; y para el tercero hay que apoyarse en biopsias suficientemente amplias y profundas, y la toracoscopia es la técnica de elección. La biopsia con aguja guiada con técnicas de imagen en tiempo real puede ser de gran ayuda cuando existe marcado engrosamiento nodular difuso y derrame pequeño o ausente. Dadas las dificultades de un diagnóstico precoz, es infrecuente que se consiga un tratamiento curativo mediante cirugía radical (pleuroneumonectomía), por lo que en los últimos años está ganando adeptos la liberación de masa tumoral mediante pleurectomía/decorticación, con asociación de quimio y radioterapia a las técnicas quirúrgicas (terapia multimodal). En los casos en que la cirugía no es factible se plantea la quimioterapia (combinando pemetrexed y compuestos de platino en la mayoría de los casos), con pleurodesis o colocación de un catéter pleural tunelizado si se requiere el control del derrame pleural, y se reserva la radioterapia para el tratamiento del dolor asociado a infiltración de la pared torácica o cualquier otra estructura vecina. En todo caso, es esencial un completo tratamiento de soporte para el control del dolor (que adquiere particular protagonismo en esta neoplasia) en unidades especializadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(4): 177-184, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135400</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y tratamiento del mesotelioma pleural maligno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11426^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8830^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8830^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8830^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14293^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32076^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14293^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14293^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
