<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109682</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between serum uric acid levels and the prevalence of metabolic syndrome in airline pilots</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The increase in the uric acid serum levels and the metabolic syndrome are conditions independently related to cardiovascular disease. Objective: To assess the prevalence of metabolic syndrome and the levels of serum uric acid in a population of airline pilots and to establish possible relationships between levels of uric acid and the presence or absence of metabolic syndrome. Methods: We studied a population of 402 male airline pilots. The diagnosis of metabolic syndrome was established according the definition of National Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) Adult Treatment Panel III. The serum uric acid was considered elevated when higher than 7 mg/dl. Results: We found that 18.7 % of pilots presented elevated levels of serum uric acid and 7.2 % had metabolic syndrome. The pilots with increased levels of serum uric acid had 5.4 higher risk (prevalence&#146;s ratio) of having metabolic syndrome than those pilots with normal uric acid, (95% confidence interval between 2.7 and 10.7 with a statistical significance of p&lt;0.001). Subjects with metabolic syndrome presented a mean levels of serum uric acid 1.1 mg/dl (IC95%: 0,7 a 1,5 mg/dl) higher than those pilots without the syndrome (p&lt;0.001). Conclusions: Our results show that pilots with uric acid level elevated have a prevalence of metabolic syndrome 5.4 times higher than those with normal level of uric acid, and that there is a positive lineal correlation between the increasing concentrations of serum uric acid and the number of metabolic syndrome diagnostic criteria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina Font, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Rodríguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La elevación del ácido úrico sérico (AUS) y el síndrome metabólico (SM), son condiciones que se relacionan con la aparición de enfermedades cardiovasculares. Objetivo: Evaluar la prevalencia de SM así como la concentración de AUS en una población de pilotos de líneas aéreas, varones y determinar la relación entre las concentraciones de AUS con respecto a la presencia o ausencia de SM. Métodos: Población de 402 pilotos de líneas aéreas, todos varones. Para diagnóstico de SM se utilizó la definición establecida por la National Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) Adult Treatment Panel III. Las concentraciones de AUS se consideraron elevadas por encima de 7 mg/dl. Resultados: El 18,7% de los pilotos tuvieron concentraciones elevadas de AUS y el 7,2% de los pilotos presentó SM. El riesgo de presentar SM por tener el AUS elevado frente al riesgo que presentaron los pilotos con AUS normal (razón de prevalencias) fue de 5,4 superior (intervalo de confianza al 95% entre 2,7 y 10,7 y con una significación de p&lt;0,001). La concentración sérica de AU se encuentra incrementada en 1,1 mg/dl (IC95%: 0,7 a 1,5 mg/dl) en los individuos con SM (p&lt;0,001) con respecto a los que no lo presentan. Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados demuestran que los pilotos con niveles de ácido úrico elevado presentan una prevalencia de SM 5,4 veces superior a aquellos con niveles de ácido úrico normal y que existe una correlación lineal positiva entre el aumento de la concentración de AUS y el número de criterios diagnósticos de SM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;68(4): 211-215, oct.-dic. 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109682</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre los niveles de ácido úrico sérico y la prevalencia de síndrome metabólico en pilotos de líneas aéreas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d341</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14926^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
