<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041792</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cochrane Library plus: free access to systematic reviews in spanish from the Cochrane Library</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cochrane Library, created in 1996, is one of the most interesting scientificinformation resources presently available, especially because it provides documentsin synthesis derived from rigorous research. Even though access tothis database is not free, since 2003 there is a free of charge access called:Cochrane Library plus, subject of this paper. This web page contains thetranslation into Spanish of several complete systematic reviews and otherrelevant documents. This article will help you find basic tools for the searchand recovery of material</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mireia Subirana Casacuberta, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Gallardo, M. Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Cochrane Library, creada en 1996 desde la Colaboración Cochrane, esuno de los recursos de información científica más interesantes en la actualidad,especialmente porque proporciona documentos de síntesis del conocimientoderivados de investigaciones rigurosas. Si bien el acceso a esta basede datos no es gratuito, desde 2003 se crea uno gratuito: la Cochrane LibraryPlus, en el cual se centra este artículo, que contiene la traducción alespañol de revisiones sistemáticas completas y otros documentos relevantes.A lo largo del artículo se facilitan herramientas básicas para la búsqueday recuperación de documentos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;8(7): 22-25, sept. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041792</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cochrane Library Plus: acceso gratuito a las revisiones sistemáticas en español de la Cochrane Library</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
