<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157531</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Responsibility for the loss of opportunity in malignant cancer care in the Spanish public healthcare system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The loss of chance in healthcare has been forcibly introduced in the adjudications pronounced in recent years. Our objective was to analyse the verdicts of guilt resulting from the loss of chance ordered by the Contentious-Administrative Court (i.e., in the public healthcare system), in which both the origin of the disease to be treated and the sequelae were oncological processes. Method: We analysed 137 cancer-related court judgments from the Contentious-Administrative Court, which referred to the concept of loss of chance, issued in Spain up to May 2014. Results: Of the 137 sentences, 119 (86.9%), were pronounced due to diagnostic error and 14 (10.2%) due to inadequate treatment. Since 2010, 100 sentences have been passed (73.0%), representing an increase of more than 170% with respect to the 37 (27.0%) ordered in the first six years of the study (from 2004 to 2009). Most of the patients (68.6%) died, predominantly from breast cancer and gynaecological cancer (24.1%), and gastrointestinal cancers (21.1%). These malignancies were the ones most often involved in the sentences. Conclusions: The litigant activity due to loss of chance in oncological processes in the public health care has significantly increased in the last years. The judgments were mainly given because of diagnostic error or inadequate treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albarrán Juan, M Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, M. del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago Sáez, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labajo González, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito León,  Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea Pérez, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sardinero García, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La pérdida de oportunidad asistencial se ha introducido con mucha fuerza en las resoluciones judiciales dictadas en los últimos años. Nuestro objetivo fue analizar las sentencias condenatorias por responsabilidad derivada de pérdida de oportunidad asistencial, dictadas por la Jurisdicción Contencioso Administrativa (es decir, en la medicina pública), en las que tanto el origen de la patología a tratar como las secuelas fueron procesos oncológicos. Método: Se han analizado las 137 sentencias judiciales, relacionadas con patologías oncológicas, en el ámbito de la Jurisdicción Contencioso Administrativa, que hacían referencia al concepto de pérdida de oportunidad asistencial y que fueron dictadas en España hasta mayo de 2014. Resultados: De las 137 sentencias, 119 (86,9%) fueron dictadas por error diagnóstico y 14 (10,2%) por un tratamiento inadecuado. Desde el año 2010 se han producido 100 (73,0%) sentencias, lo que supone más de un 170% de aumento con respecto a las 37 (27,0%) dictadas en los primeros 6 años del estudio (2004 a 2009). La mayoría de los pacientes (68,6%) fallecieron, siendo las de mama y de órganos genitales femeninos (24,1%), así como las digestivas (21,1%), las neoplasias malignas que con más frecuencia originaron la condena. Conclusiones: La actividad litigante por pérdida de oportunidad asistencial en patologías oncológicas en la medicina pública española ha aumentado de manera significativa estos últimos años. Las sentencias fueron dictadas fundamentalmente por error diagnóstico o tratamiento inadecuado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;30(6): 421-425, nov.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157531</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Responsabilidad por pérdida de oportunidad asistencial en patología oncológica maligna en la medicina pública española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29106^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8491^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37686^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8062^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3979^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
