<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116923</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk and protective factors in suicide. A case-control study using the psychological autopsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rates, methods and some of the risk factors of suicide seem to depend on geographical and cultural differences, which involve conducting research in specific high-risk areas facing the implementation of preventive strategies. This study seeks to determine the risk and protective factors of suicide in the region of Antequera-Málaga (Spain). Is performed on a case-control study using the psychological autopsy of 40 cases of suicide and 80 population controls matched on gender, age and area of residence. The multivariate model found is composed of the following factors: the antecedents of suicide and mental disorders aggregate in families, a diagnosis of personality disorder and family conflict in the month prior to suicide. These factors discriminate risk populations facing the implementation of preventive programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Labajos-Manzanares, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comino-Ballesteros, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Calvo, Amalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perea-Milla, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diego-Otero, Yolanda de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Guerrero, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Medina, Valentín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Costilla, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón-San-Martín, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Parejo, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las tasas, los métodos y algunos de los factores de riesgo en el suicidio parecen depender de las diferencias geográficas y culturales, lo que implica la elaboración de estudios en zonas específicas de alto riesgo cara a la implementación de estrategias preventivas. Este estudio busca determinar los factores de riesgo y protectores en el suicidio en la Comarca de Antequera-Málaga (España). Se realiza en un estudio de caso y controles mediante la autopsia psicológica con 40 casos de suicidio y 80 controles poblacionales emparejados en género, edad y zona de residencia. El modelo multivariante hallado está compuesto por los siguientes factores: el presentar antecedentes familiares de suicidio y agregación de desordenes mentales en la familia, un diagnóstico de trastorno de la personalidad y conflictos familiares en el mes previo al suicidio. Estos factores permiten discriminar poblaciones de riesgo cara a la implementación de programas preventivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;29(3): 810-815, sept.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116923</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo y protectores en el suicidio. Un estudio de casos y controles mediante la autopsia psicológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
