<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132225</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of bariatric surgery patients at the emergency department of a tertiary referral hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the profile of the bariatric surgery patients that were admitted to the Emergency Department (ED). Method: A retrospective review of the reasons why bariatric surgery patients go to our ED. We analyzed the first 30 days after the surgery. We evaluated the number and indications of admissions, the examinations ordered, and final diagnosis and destination of the patients. Results: From January 2010 to July 2012, 320 patients underwent bariatric surgery at our Institution. Fifty three patients (16.6 %) were admitted to the ED at leas t once. We found 58 admissions (1.1 admissions by patient). Patients who had duodenal switch and Roux-en-Y gastric bypass were the most representative (74 %). The main indications for admission were abdominal pain (50 %), and problems related to the surgical wounds (22.4 %). Blood test was the most performed examination (75.9 %). The most frequent final diagnosis was unspecific abdominal pain in 27 cases (46.6 %), and complications of the surgical wound in 10 patients (17.2 %). Nineteen patients (35.84 %) were admitted to the surgical ward from the ED, and 5 of them required surgical revision (9.4 %). Multivariate analyses showed that the type of surgery was the only predictor variable for the ED admission. Conclusions: Attending ED after bariatric surgery is not common, and less than a third of the patients required hospital admission. Just a small percentage of the examinations showed any pathological value. Readmission rate is very low. Surgical procedure is the only predictor for ED admission (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amador García Ruiz de Gordejuela, Amador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta González, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol Gebelli, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casajoana Badia, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madrazo González, Zoilo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Campaña, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: describir el perfil de consulta en el servicio de Urgencias de pacientes intervenidos de cirugía bariátrica (CB). Método: análisis retrospectivo de las consultas al servicio de Urgencias de pacientes intervenidos de CB. Se analizan las visitas realizadas en los primeros 30 días tras el alta. Se evalúan número y motivos de consulta/reconsulta, exploraciones complementarias realizadas, diagnóstico clínico establecido y destino de los pacientes. Resultados: entre enero de 2010 y julio de 2012 se intervinieron de 320 pacientes de CB, 53 enfermos (16,6 %) consultaron al menos una vez en Urgencias. Se registraron 58 consultas (1,1 visitas/paciente). Los pacientes intervenidos de cruce duodenal y bypass gástrico representaron el 74 %. Los motivos de consulta más frecuentes fueron dolor abdominal (50 %) y problemas relacionados con la herida quirúrgica (22,4 %). La analítica sanguínea fue la exploración complementaria más solicitada (75,9 %). El diagnóstico más frecuente fue dolor abdominal inespecífico en 27 casos (46,6 %), y problemas de herida quirúrgica en 10 casos (17,2 %). Diecinueve pacientes (35,84 %) requirieron ingreso hospitalario desde Urgencias y 5 de ellos precisaron reintervención quirúrgica (9,4 %). El análisis multivariante muestra que la única variable en relación a las visitas a Urgencias es el tipo de cirugía. Conclusiones: las visitas a Urgencias de pacientes intervenidos de cirugía bariátrica son poco frecuentes, menos de un tercio de ellos precisan ingreso hospitalario. Las exploraciones complementarias sólo mostraron resultados patológicos en un pequeño porcentaje de los casos. La tasa de reconsultas es baja. La técnica quirúrgica es el único predictor de consulta en Urgencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;107(1): 23-28, ene. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132225</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de la asistencia en urgencias de pacientes intervenidos de cirugía bariátrica en un centro de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7432^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
