<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046596</identifier>
<setSpec>0303-8874</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic and treatment of necrotizing cervical fascitis. Evolution after a ludwig angina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Ludwig angina is an infection of the base of the mouth and submandibular region, frecuently after a dental extraction or a piece in bad state. When it surpassees the milohioid muscle it extends dissecting the superficial aponeurotic planes, and can evolve to a necrotisant fascitis. We present the case oía 67 years old man with a painful tumefaction of the mouth base and submandibular region. The CT reflected an heterogenous submaxilar lesion that extended by the deep cervical fascia introducing itself in the thorax. Under antibiotic treatment the pus was drained by cervicotomy, with daily cures during 3 weeks</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Manzano, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cegarra Navarro, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Meseguer, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Banegas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La «angina de Ludwig» es una infección del suelo de la    boca y región submandibular, frecuentemente tras una extracción dental o por una pieza en mal estado. Cuando sobrepasa el músculo milohiodeo se extiende disecando los planos aponeuróticos superficiales, pudiendo evolucionar hacia una fascitis necrotizante. Presentamos el caso de un hombre de 67 años con tumefacción dolorosa del suelo de la boca y región submandibular. La TC reflejaba una lesión heterogénea submaxilar que se extendía por la fascia profunda cervical hasta introducirse en el tórax. Bajo tratamiento antibiótico se drenó el pus mediante cervicotomía, con curas diarias durante 3 semanas</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Otorrinolaringol Ibero Am;33(3): 317-322, mayo-jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046596</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y tratamiento de la fascitis necrotizante cervical. Evolución tras una angida de Ludwig</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11311^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36618^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
