<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102395</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anticoagulation therapy in patients with heart failure due to systolic dysfunction and sinus rhythm: analysis of REDINSCOR Registry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. In patients with heart failure, left ventricular ejection fraction &amp;#8804;35% and sinus rhythm without conditions such as atrial fibrillation, thrombus or history of thromboembolic events, the use of anticoagulation is controversial. Our objective was to evaluate the anticoagulation strategy in these patients, variables associated with its use, and its effects on various cardiovascular events. Methods. Of the patients included in the REDINSCOR registry with left ventricular ejection fraction &amp;#8804;35% and sinus rhythm without other anticoagulation indications (including patients with heart failure from 19 Spanish centres), we compared those who received this treatment with the remaining patients. Results. Between 2007 and 2010, 2263 patients were included, of whom 902 had left ventricular ejection fraction &amp;#8804;35% and sinus rhythm. Of these, 237 (26%) were receiving anticoagulation therapy. Variables associated with this treatment were a lower left ventricular ejection fraction, ischemic etiology, advanced functional class, wider QRS, larger left atrial diameter, and hospitalization. After 21(11-32) months of median follow-up, there were no significant differences in total mortality (14% versus 12.5%) or stroke (0.8% versus 0.9%). A propensity score adjusted multivariate analysis showed a reduction in a combined end-point including cardiac death, heart transplantation, coronary revascularization, and cardiovascular hospitalization (hazard ratio=0.74; 95% confidence interval, 0.56-0.97; P=.03) in patients receiving anticoagulation therapy. No information regarding bleeding was collected in the follow-up. Conclusions. In a large and contemporary series of patients with heart failure, left ventricular ejection fraction &amp;#8804;35% and sinus rhythm, 26% received anticoagulation therapy. This was not associated with lower mortality or stroke incidence, although there was a reduction in major cardiac events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avellana, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero, Andreu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrás, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulpón, Luis Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segovia, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugada, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cinca, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. En pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca, fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo &amp;#8804;35% y ritmo sinusal, en ausencia de fibrilación auricular, trombos intracavitarios o tromboembolia previa, la indicación de anticoagulación es controvertida. Nuestro objetivo es evaluar la actitud actual respecto de la anticoagulación en estos pacientes, variables asociadas a su utilización y su efecto en diversos eventos cardiovasculares. Métodos. De los pacientes con fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo &amp;#8804; 35% y ritmo sinusal sin otra indicación de anticoagulación incluidos en el registro REDINSCOR (pertenecientes a 18 centros españoles), se comparó a los que recibían este tratamiento frente al resto. Resultados. Entre 2007 y 2010 se incluyeron 2.263 pacientes; 902 tenían fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo &amp;#8804;35% y ritmo sinusal. De ellos, 237 (26%) recibían anticoagulación. Las variables asociadas a su utilización fueron menor fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo, etiología no isquémica, clase funcional avanzada, mayor anchura del QRS, mayor diámetro auricular izquierdo y hospital prescriptor del tratamiento anticoagulante. Tras una mediana de seguimiento de 21 (11-32) meses, no se observaron diferencias significativas en mortalidad (14 frente a 12,5%) ni ictus (0,8 frente a 0,9%). El análisis multivariado ajustado por propensity score mostró una reducción en la combinación de mortalidad cardiaca, trasplante cardiaco, revascularización coronaria e ingresos cardiovasculares (hazard ratio = 0,74; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,56-0,97; p=0,03) en el grupo anticoagulado. No se recogió información sobre episodios hemorrágicos en el seguimiento. Conclusiones. En una serie amplia y contemporánea de pacientes de nuestro medio con insuficiencia cardiaca, fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo &amp;#8804;35% y ritmo sinusal, un 26% recibían anticoagulación. Ello no se asoció a menor mortalidad ni incidencia de ictus aunque se observó una reducción de una combinación de eventos cardiacos mayores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;65(8): 705-712, ago. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102395</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento anticoagulante en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca por disfunción sistólica y ritmo sinusal: análisis del registro REDINSCOR</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52612^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52612^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52618^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
