<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105440</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adenosine and homeostatic control of sleep. Actions in target structures of the sleep-wake circuits</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sleep homeostasis occurs during prolonged wakefulness. Drowsiness and sleep pressure are its behavioral manifestations and, when sleep is allowed, there is a sleep rebound of sufficient duration and intensity to compensate for the previous deprivation. Adenosine is one of the molecules involved in sleep homeostasic regulation. Caffeine and  theophylline, stimulants widely consumed by the humans, are antagonists. It is an endogenous factor, resulting from ATP metabolism in neurons and glia. Adenosine accumulates in the extracellular space, where it can exert regulatory actions on the sleep-wakefulness cycle circuits. Adenosine acts through the purinergic receptors A1 and A2. This paper reviews: 1) the metabolic pathways of cerebral adenosine, and the mechanisms of its release by neurons and glia to the extracellular space; 2) the actions of adenosine and its antagonists in regions of the central nervous system related to wakefulness, non-REM sleep, and REM sleep, and 3) the synaptic mechanisms involved in these actions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andrés, Isabel de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carús CAdavieco, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La homeostasis del sueño se manifiesta ante situaciones de vigilia prolongada de forma natural o experimentalmente. En estos casos, se presenta somnolencia (o presión de sueño) y, cuando se permite dormir, hay un rebote del sueño en duración e intensidad que compensa la pérdida del mismo. Entre las moléculas que pueden intervenir en la regulación homeostática del sueño, se encuentra la adenosina, cuyos antagonistas, la cafeína y la teofilina, consume la población humana ampliamente como estimulantes. La adenosina es un factor endógeno resultante del metabolismo del  ATP en neuronas y glía que se acumula en el medio extracelular y que es capaz de ejercer acciones reguladoras sobre circuitos del ciclo vigilia sueño. Actúa a través de los receptores purinérgicos A1 y A2. En este trabajo se presenta una revisión de las vías metabólicas de la adenosina cerebral y de su liberación por neuronas y glía, y se exponen las acciones de la adenosina y de sus antagonistas en regiones del sistema nervioso central de naturaleza hipnogénica y relacionadas con la vigilia. Se exponen, además, los mecanismos sinápticos involucrados en estas acciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(7): 413-420, oct. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105440</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adenosina y control homeostático del sueño. Acciones en estructuras diana de los circuitos de vigilia y sueño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13272^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29868^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7211^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d249^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28186^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23939^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29533^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
