<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058153</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improved accessibility in total knee arthroplasty: experience of a specialized unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In May 2004 a specific program for knee prosthesis surgery was established, due to the high demand for this type of surgery. The aim of this study was to assess the outcomes of clinical and quality indicators obtained in a monographic hospitalization unit specialized in knee prosthesis surgery compared with the outcomes previously obtained in a standard orthopedic surgery hospitalization unit. Material and method: The sample of this non-controlled community trial (before-after) consisted of the first 124 patients treated in the specialized unit and the last 124 patients treated in the standard unit for the same type of surgery. Age, gender, pain, length of hospital stay in days, movement at discharge, knee bending, comorbidity and complications were analyzed. Results: Patients admitted to the specialized unit spent less time in the hospital (p &lt; 0.0001) and showed better knee bending at discharge (p &lt; 0.0001). In general the specialized unit attended patients with a greater number of comorbidities than the standard unit. Conclusions: Creating a monographic unit specialized in the care of surgical patients with high prevalence could be a possible solution to this chronic problem in public hospitals. These units should follow a specific clinical pathway and should assess quality according to a group of indicators and objectives that allow continuous improvement</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prat, Andreu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiñá, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bori, Guillem</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segur, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baños, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En mayo de 2004 se implantó un programa específico para la cirugía protésica de rodilla, dada la alta demanda para este tipo de cirugía. El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar los resultados de los indicadores asistenciales y de calidad obtenidos en una unidad monográfica de prótesis de rodilla (UEPR), y compararlos con los obtenidos previamente en una unidad asistencial convencional de cirugía ortopédica y traumatología (UCOT). Material y metodo: La población objeto de este ensayo comunitario no controlado (antes-después) han sido los primeros 124 pacientes atendidos en la UEPR y los últimos 124 pacientes a quienes se había realizado este mismo tipo de intervención en la UCOT. Edad, sexo, días de estancia, dolor, deambulación al alta, flexión de la rodilla, comorbilidades y complicaciones han sido las variables analizadas. Resultados: Los pacientes atendidos en la UEPR estaban menos tiempo ingresados (p &lt; 0,0001) y presentaban una mayor flexión de la rodilla intervenida al alta (p &lt; 0,0001). En general la UEPR atendió a enfermos con un mayor número de comorbilidades que la UCOT. Conclusiones: El diseño y la puesta en funcionamiento de unidades monográficas y especializadas en la atención de pacientes quirúrgicos de alta prevalencia puede ser una alternativa satisfactoria en la resolución de este problema endémico de la sanidad pública. Estas unidades deben desarrollar su actividad según una guía clínica específica y evaluar la calidad asistencial conforme a una serie de indicadores y objetivos que posibiliten su mejora continua</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;22(4): 180-183, jul.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058153</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora del acceso a la artroplastia total de rodilla: experiencia de una unidad monográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33578^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6448^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
