<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164339</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Catatonia - an unusual presenting clinical manifestation of systemic lupus erythematosus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 24-year-old female presented with catatonia and symptoms suggestive of Depressive Disorder. She also gave history of undocumented low grade irregular fever. The patient was worked up to rule out any organic cause or psychiatric illness. However, further investigations revealed immunological profile diagnostic of Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) with CNS involvement (CNS lupus). The diagnosis of SLE in this patient presenting with catatonia was of practical importance because catatonia as one of the manifestations of SLE or as a standalone presenting symptom is extremely rare. Hence, clinicians should be aware of this rarity so that diagnosis of Neuropsychiatric SLE (NPSLE) or catatonia as a presenting feature of SLE is never missed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prasad, Shiv</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sharma, Simran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kumar Meena, Ravi Kumar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Qureshi, Arshna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chaudhury, Debasish</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Mujer de 24 años que se presentó con catatonía y síntomas indicativos de trastorno depresivo. También presentó historia de febrícula discontinua no registrada. Se llevó a cabo evaluación diagnóstica para descartar cualquier causa orgánica o enfermedad psiquiátrica. Sin embargo, exploraciones complementarias posteriores revelaron un perfil inmunológico diagnóstico de lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES) con implicación del SNC (lupus del SNC). El diagnóstico de LES en esta paciente que se presenta con catatonía era de significado práctico ya que la catatonía, como una de las manifestaciones del LES o como un síntoma que se presenta de forma independiente, es extremadamente rara. Por ello, los médicos deben ser conscientes de esta rareza y no deben olvidar nunca el diagnóstico de LES neuropsiquiátrico (LESNP) o catatonía como rasgo presente en el LES (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);13(4): 224-226, jul.-ago. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164339</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Catatonía - manifestación clínica de presentación infrecuente del lupus eritematoso sistémico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2433^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2433^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33077^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
