<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69981</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Levothyroxine requirements in patients with hypothyroidism are usually stable. Consequently, thyroid function is usually monitored once or twice yearly. Occasionally, the dose of levothyroxine can be changed by pharmacologicalreactions. We report the case of a 59-year-old woman who was under levothyroxine therapy for hypothyroidism secondary to subtotal thyroidectomy, with clinical and biochemical euthyroidism, who required an increased dose of levothyroxine after starting imatinib therapy. The patient was diagnosed with chronic myeloid leukemia and imatinib therapy was started. Subsequently, we observed clinical and biochemical hypothyroidism, requiring an increase in levothyroxine dose. Some cases of hypothyroidism after initiation of imatinib therapy in patients with levothyroxine replacement therapy have recently been published. Our case provides further evidence of a reaction between the two drugs. Therefore, wediscuss the most likely physiopathological mechanisms contributing to imatinibinduced hypothyroidism in patients underlevothyroxine replacement therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Diego García, Patricia de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Playáb Usón, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trincado Aznas, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albero Gamboa, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los requerimientos de levotiroxina de los pacientes con hipotiroidismo suelen ser estables y por ello se recomienda control de la función tiroidea1 o 2 veces al año. Las dosis de levotiroxina ocasionalmente pueden variar por interacciones farmacológicas. Presentamos el caso de una paciente que requirió ajuste de la dosis del evotiroxina al iniciar el tratamiento con imatinib. Mujer de 59 años en tratamiento con levotiroxina por hipotiroidismo secundario atiroidectomía subtotal con buen control clínico y analítico. Tras ser diagnosticada de leucemia mieloide crónica y ser tratada con imatinib,presentó clínica y bioquímica compatible con hipotiroidismo, que precisó un aumento de la dosis de levotiroxina para mantener la función tiroideanormal. Recientemente se ha descrito algún caso de hipotiroidismo al añadir imatinib a pacientes en tratamiento sustitutivo con levotiroxina. Este nuevo caso avala la interacción de ambos fármacos. Por lo tanto, c omentamos los posible mecanismos fisiopatológicos que contribuyen a que el imatinib induzca el hipotiroidismo en pacientes en tratamiento sustitutivo con hormona tiroidea (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;55(7): 304-307, ago. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69981</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d19589^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23724^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23724^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14360^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
