<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160112</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychopathological profile and prevalence of dual pathology on patients with alcoholic dependence undergoing outpatient treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. Assess the prevalence of dual pathology in patients with alcohol dependence and describe the psychopathological profile of mental disorders, impulsiveness, ADHD presence and craving. Method. It is a cross-sectional study about dual pathology, carried out on 102 patients undergoing outpatient treatment. The presence of dual pathology is established by means of the MINI-5 interview and the MCMI-III test; DSM-IV being used as the alcohol abuse criteria. Impulsiveness, ADHD presence, craving and quality of life were measured through SIS, ASRSv1, MACS and SF-36. Results. The prevalence of dual pathology ranges from 45.1% to 80.4% according to MCMI-III and MINI-5, respectively. The most frequent pathologies are current major depressive episodes, followed by current generalized anxiety disorders, suicide risk and current dysthymia disorders; 73.2% of dual patients present a moderate and intense global score according to MACS, 56.1% got a meaningful score in impulsiveness according to SIS and 41.5% has highly consistent symptoms with ADHD. As regards quality of life, 53.7% of the sample had bad mental health. In the case of dual patients consuming other substances, 30% had a history of bipolar disorders and 10% had a high suicide risk. Conclusions. The prevalence of psychiatric comorbidity in patients with alcohol dependence undergoing outpatient treatment varies depending on the detection method, MINI being the one identifying a greater number of cases. More than half of dual patients present impulsive behavior, a bad mental health state and high craving levels. Special attention should be paid to dual patients consuming other substances (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robles-Martínez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novalbos-Ruiz, José P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordán-Quintero, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Carretero, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>O&#146;Ferrall-González, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estimar la prevalencia de patología dual (PD) en pacientes con dependencia alcohólica y describir el perfil psicopatológico de los trastornos mentales, su impulsividad, hiperactividad y craving. Metodología. Estudio transversal sobre PD de 102 pacientes en tratamiento ambulatorio. Se determina la presencia de PD mediante la entrevista MINI-5 y el test MCMI-III, utilizando como criterio de abuso o dependencia de alcohol el DSM-IV. Se emplearon además la EIE (impulsividad), ASRSv1 (hiperactividad), EMCA (craving) y SF-36 (calidad de vida). Resultados. La prevalencia de PD varía del 45,1% (MCMI-III) al 80,4% (MINI-5) dependiendo del instrumento utilizado. Predominan el episodio depresivo mayor actual y recidivante, seguido por el trastorno de ansiedad generalizada actual, el riesgo de suicidio y el trastorno distímico actual; el 73,2% de los pacientes duales presenta una puntuación global moderada-intensa en EMCA, un 56,1% tiene conducta impulsiva y un 41,5% síntomas altamente consistentes con el TDAH. Respecto a la calidad de vida, el 53,7% tenía un mal estado de salud mental. Un 30% de los pacientes con PD y consumo añadido de drogas tenía antecedentes de trastorno bipolar y un 10% riesgo de suicidio alto. Conclusiones. La prevalencia de comorbilidad psiquiátrica en pacientes con dependencia alcohólica en tratamiento ambulatorio varía dependiendo del método de detección, siendo la MINI la que identifica un mayor número de casos. Más de la mitad de los pacientes con PD tiene conducta impulsiva, mala calidad de salud mental y altos niveles de craving. Requieren especial atención los PD con consumo de otras sustancias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;45(1): 1-11, ene.-feb. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160112</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil psicopatológico y prevalencia de patología dual de los pacientes con dependencia alcohólica en tratamiento ambulatorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
