<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148256</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dislipidaemia and cardiovascular risk in type 2 diabetes mellitus patients with associated diabetic nephropathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Diabetes patients with concomitant diabetic nephropathy are especially destined to cardiovascular complications due to the presence of microalbuminuria or proteinuria, that are potent inductors of dyslipidaemia. Methods: We have studied 98 type 2 diabetes mellitus patients, 61 male and 37 female, mean age 63+13 year old, all of them with overt proteinuria (above 500 mg/day), divided into 4 groups: G-I (n = 13): patients with t. cholesterol &gt; 6,25 mmol/l treated with fibric-acid derivatives; G-II (n = 52): hypercholesterolemic patients treated with statins; G-III (n = 20): hypercholesterolemic patients with no lipid-lowering intervention; G-IV (n = 13): normocholesterolemic patients (control group). Lipidic profile, proteinuria and renal function have being compared after 1, 3 and 5 years. Results: Base-line characteristics of the patients were similar when regarding age, onset of diabetes or nephropathy. Only proteinuria was higher in statinstreated group (p &lt; 0.05). Fibric-acid derivatives were more effective on hypertriglyceridaemia while statins were more effective lowering LDL cholesterol. A gemfibrocyl-treated patient presented a rhabdomyolysis episode. Statins were safe and well tolerated. Nine patients (19%) in G-II, 2 patients (10%) in G-III and 1 patient (7%) in G-IV achieved end-stage renal failure. Five-year cardiovascular mortality and all-cause mortality rate were 23%/23% in G-I, 13%/19% in G-II, 20%/25% in G-III and 31%/31% in G-IV. The difference was statistically significant when comparing normocolesterolemic versus statin-treated patients (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusion: Lipid-lowering therapy could probably delay but not avoid the progression of diabetic nephropathy. Since dyslipidaemia is closely related to the progression of cardiovascular disease and mortality, an aggressive lipid-lowering therapy is recommended, irrespectively of its potential effect on diabetic nephropathy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Castelao, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castiñeiras, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes diabéticos con nefropatía diabética asociada presentan un elevado riesgo cardiovascular, debido al desarrollo de proteinuria, potente inductor de dislipemia. Pacientes y Método. Hemos realizado un estudio observacional en 98 diabéticos tipo 2, 61 hombres y 37 mujeres, con edad media de 63 ± 13 años, y todos ellos con proteinuria superior a 500 mg/día, divididos en 4 grupos: G-I (n = 13): pacientes con colesterol total &gt; o = 6,25 mmol/l tratados con derivados del ácido fíbrico; G-II (n = 52): pacientes hipercolesterolémicos tratados con estatinas; G-III (n = 20), pacientes hipercolesterolémicos no tratados farmacológicamente por su dislipemia; G-IV (n = 13): pacientes normocolesterolémicos (grupo control). Se han comparado función renal, proteinuria y perfil lipídico 1, 3 y 5 años después del inicio de la observación. Resultados. Las característivas basales de los pacientes son similares en cuanto a edad, sexo, inicio de la diabetes e inicio de la nefropatía diabética. La proteinuria al inicio era más elevada en el grupo tratado con estatinas (p &lt; 0,05). Los fibratos se mostraron más eficaces para reducir la hipertrigliceridemia, mientras que las estatinas fueron más efectivas en la reducción de colesterol total y lipoproteínas de baja densidad. Un paciente tratado con gemfibrocilo presentó un episodio de rabdomiolisis. Las estatinas fueron muy bien toleradas. Nueve pacientes (19%) en G-II, 2 pacientes (10%) en G-III y 1 paciente (7%) en G-IV progresaron hacia la insuficiencia renal terminal durante el período del estudio. La mortalidad de causa cardiovascular y la mortalidad por todas las causas fueron 23%/23% en G-I, 13%/19% en G-II, 20%/25% en G-III y 31%/31% en G-IV, siendo la diferencia estadísticamente significativa cuando se comparó la mortalidad de causa cardiovascular entre el grupo normocolesterolémico y el grupo tratado con estatinas (p &lt; 0,05) Conclusiones. La intervención farmacológica hipolipemiante contribuye a disminuir la mortalidad cardiovascular en el diabético tipo 2 con nefropatía diabética asociada. Por ello creemos necesario instaurar tratamiento hipolipemiante agresivo precoz, antes de que las complicaciones micro y macroangiopáticas hagan hecho su aparición en el paciente diabético, independientemente del posible efecto para frenar la evolución de la nefropatía, que aún no ha sido suficientemente probado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;22(supl.1): 51-58, feb. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dislipemia y riesgo cardiovascular en el paciente diabético tipo 2 con nefropatía diabética asociada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d963^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
