<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106474</identifier>
<setSpec>2172-3761</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Accreditation of individualized interviews for Primary Care professional</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the activities carried out by Primary Care pharmacists aimed at improving prescription quality is a face-to-face interview with the medical professionals. Accreditation of these interviews as a training activity provides added value for the professional interviewed and for the pharmacist, in regards to incorporation of a structured methodology, establishment of the objectives agreed on, commitment for mutual collaboration and periodic follow-up of the prescription pro&amp;#64257;le. This methodology motivates the professional to improve the prescription pro&amp;#64257;le since it puts it into a clinical context frame and not a purely management one (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Urrusuno, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Balosa, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una de las actividades realizadas por los farmacéuticos de Atención Primaria dirigidas a mejorar la calidad de la prescripción consiste en la entrevista cara a cara con los facultativos. La acreditación de estas entrevistas como actividad formativa aporta un valor añadido para el profesional entrevistado y para el farmacéutico, en cuanto a la incorporación de una metodología estructurada, el establecimiento de objetivos consensuados, el compromiso de colaboración mutua y el seguimiento periódico del per&amp;#64257;l de prescripción. Esta metodología motiva al profesional a mejorar el per&amp;#64257;l de prescripción ya que se enmarca en un contexto clínico y no puramente de gestión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. aten. prim;9(2): 54-57, mayo-ago. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106474</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acreditación de entrevistas individualizadas con los facultativos de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7564</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
