<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115061</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Handbook for the preparation of evidence-based documents. Tools derived from scientific knowledge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. This handbook is intended to be an accessible, easy-to-consult guide to help professionals produce or adapt Evidence-Based Documents. Such documents will help standardize both clinical practice and decision-making, the quality always being monitored in such a way that established references are complied with. Materials and methods. Evidence-Based Health Care Committee, a member of &#147;Virgen del Rocío&#148; University Hospital quality structure, proposed the preparation of a handbook to produce Evidence-Based Documents including: a description of products, characteristics, qualities, uses, methodology of production, and application scope of every one of them. Results. The handbook consists of seven Evidence-Based tools, one chapter on critical analysis methodology of scientific literature, one chapter with internet resources, and some appendices with different assessment tools. Conclusions. This Handbook provides general practitioners with a great opportunity to improve quality and as a guideline to standardize clinical healthcare, and managers with a strategy to promote and encourage the development of documents in an effort to reduce clinical practice variability, as well as giving patients the opportunity of taking part in planning their own care(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Quero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega-Ruiz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobrino-Márquez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tamayo-López, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos-Pareja, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Brocca, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paneque-Sánchez-Toscano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Eiris-Delgado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero-Candelera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia-Martín, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Durán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-García-Bóveda, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrión-Camacho, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomino-García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El manual pretende ser una guía, accesible y fácil de consultar, que oriente a los profesionales en la elaboración o adaptación de documentos basados en la evidencia que ayuden a la estandarización de la práctica clínica y a la toma de decisiones velando siempre por la calidad de la misma de forma que siga unos referentes establecidos. Material y métodos. La Comisión de Atención Sanitaria Basada en la Evidencia (CASBE), perteneciente a la estructura de calidad del Hospital Universitario Virgen del Rocío, propuso elaborar un manual para la elaboración de documentos basados en la evidencia que incorpore la relación de productos, la descripción de sus características, atributos, utilidad, metodología de elaboración y ámbito de aplicación de cada uno de ellos. Resultados. El manual contiene 7 herramientas basadas en la evidencia, un capítulo sobre metodología de análisis crítico de la literatura científica, un capítulo con recursos en Internet y anexos con herramientas de evaluación. Conclusiones. Este manual ofrece grandes oportunidades para la mejora de la calidad a los clínicos como guía de estandarización de la práctica asistencial, a los gestores como estrategia para promover y fomentar la elaboración de documentos que ayuden a reducir la variabilidad de la práctica clínica y a los pacientes la oportunidad de participar en la planificación de sus cuidados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;28(4): 254-258, jul.-ago. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115061</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manual para la elaboración de documentos basados en la evidencia. Herramientas derivadas del conocimiento científico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54394^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
