<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152638</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elucidation of the mTOR Pathway and Therapeutic Applications in Dermatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The member of the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase family, mammalian target of rapamycin, is involved in modulating inflammatory response and regulating cellular processes associated with growth, differentiation, and angiogenesis. Recent years have seen major advances in our understanding of the mammalian target of rapamycin signaling pathway and the implication of this pathway in multiple genetic and inflammatory diseases and tumors. The development of the mammalian target of rapamycin inhibitors has given rise to new treatment approaches that have led to substantially improved outcomes in many diseases. In this article, we review the role of the mammalian target of rapamycin signaling pathway in the different skin diseases with which it has been associated, examine the therapeutic applications of drugs targeting this pathway, and provide an overview of current trends and future directions in research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salido Vallejo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garnacho Saucedo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vélez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La molécula diana de la rapamicina en mamíferos es una cinasa perteneciente a la familia de fosfatidil-3-inositol que está involucrada en la regulación de diferentes procesos relacionados con el crecimiento y diferenciación celular, la angiogénesis y la modulación de la respuesta inflamatoria. En los últimos años hemos presenciado un profundo avance en el conocimiento de las bases moleculares de la vía de señalización de la molécula diana de la rapamicina en mamíferos y su implicación en multitud de enfermedades genéticas, inflamatorias o tumorales. El desarrollo de moléculas inhibidoras de esta vía ha propiciado una nueva posibilidad de abordaje terapéutico que ha permitido una mejora sustancial en muchas de estas enfermedades. En este artículo revisamos las implicaciones de la vía de la molécula diana de la rapamicina en mamíferos en las diferentes dermatosis con las que se ha relacionado, sus aplicaciones farmacológicas y las futuras direcciones que están tomando las diferentes líneas de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;107(5): 379-390, jun. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152638</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases moleculares y aplicaciones farmacológicas de la vía de mTOR en dermatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55896^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33809^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55896^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55896^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3899^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3899^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3899^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54051^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54051^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54051^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33809^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33809^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13254^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13254^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13254^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
