<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10784</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato prevalence and diversity in ticks and small mammals in a Lyme borreliosis endemic Nature Reserve in North-Western Spain. Incidence in surrounding human populations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To determine the prevalence and diversity of Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato (s.l.) in an endemic Nature Reserve (Sierra del Sueve) in North-Western Spain, and the risk of human exposure to infected ticks in Asturias, 1013 questing ticks and 70 small mammals were collected between 2012 and 2014. A retrospective descriptive analysis was also carried out on human Lyme borreliosis (LB) cases reported to the local hospital (Cabueñes). Samples were screened for B. burgdorferi s.l. presence by a nested PCR assay, and genospecies were confirmed by sequencing. B. burgdorferi s.l. was detected in 1.4% (12/845) of I. ricinus questing nymphs, 9.1% (2/33) of questing adults, and 12.9% (9/70) of small mammals, as well as in the other tick species. PCR positive samples of 17 questing tick and 6 small mammals were sequenced. Four genospecies were identified: B. afzelii, B. garinii, B. lusitaniae, and B. valaisiana. Phylogenetic analyses based on the flaB gene showed the heterogeneity of B. afzelii in this area. The detection of B. burgdorferi s.l. among questing ticks and small mammals in the study area, as well as the abundance of ticks and of large wild and domestic mammals, indicate a high risk of infection by B. burgdorferi s.l. in the area. Reporting of LB cases to the local hospital support this, and shows the need of thorough monitoring of B. burgdorferi infection in ticks and hosts in the area. More investigations are needed to assess the role of different wildlife species and the risk of transmission to humans (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Somoano, Aitor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barandika, José F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pérez, Ana L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espí, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerro, Ana del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre 2012 y 2014 se recogieron 1.013 garrapatas de la vegetación y 70 pequeños mamíferos en la Reserva Natural de la Sierra del Sueve (Asturias) y zonas colindantes, con el fin de determinar la prevalencia de Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato (s.l.) y el riesgo de exposición humana a garrapatas infectadas en Asturias, área endémica de borreliosis de Lyme. También se incluye un estudio descriptivo y retrospectivo de pacientes diagnosticados de borreliosis en un hospital local (Hospital de Cabueñes, Gijón). B. burgdorferi s.l. se detectó, mediante una PCR anidada, en el 1,4% (12/845) de las ninfas y en el 9,1% (2/33) de los adultos de la garrapata I. ricinus, en porcentajes variables de las restantes especies y en el 12,9% (9/70) de los pequeños mamíferos. Se secuenciaron un total de 17 muestras de garrapatas de la vegetación y 6 de pequeños mamíferos detectándose 4 genoespecies causantes de la borreliosis de Lyme: B. afzelii, B. garinii, B. lusitaniae, y B. valaisiana. Los análisis filogenéticos basados en el gen flaB mostraron la heterogeneidad de B. afzelii en el área de estudio. La detección de B. burgdorferi s.l. en garrapatas de la vegetación y pequeños mamíferos de la zona de estudio, así como la gran abundancia de garrapatas y la presencia de grandes poblaciones de animales silvestres y domésticos, son indicativos de que el riesgo de infección en esta área es relevante. Este hecho está en consonancia con los casos de borreliosis de Lyme descritos en este estudio, mostrando la necesidad de establecer un seguimiento continuado de la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;35(9): 563-568, nov. 2017. tab, mapas, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y diversidad de Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato en garrapatas y pequeños mamíferos de una Reserva Natural del noroeste de España donde la borreliosis de Lyme es endémica. Incidencia en las poblaciones humanas circundantes</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
