<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167043</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of parental knowledge and care in childhood fever</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the parental knowledge and care of fever in children under 2years. Relate this data with socio-demographic with characteristics. Design: Cross-sectional and correlation multicenter study. Location: Five teams of Primary Care in Barcelona. Participants: Parents of children under 2 years attended to administer a vaccine included in the pediatric systematic calendar. A total of 311 subjects participated. Main measurements: The main variables are 9 items of knowledge and 8 of care or management of fever obtained with the adaptation of the questionnaire by Chiappini et al. (2012). Results: 69.8% had a correct care/management of fever. 3.9% matched all items of knowledge. The knowledge score is lower in people with no education (p=0.03); higher in Europe and South America and lowest in Asia and Africa (P&lt;.001). 100% of patients that had chronic problems answered correctly all items of fever care (P=.03). It is important to note that the correlation between the scores of knowledge and management is positive (rho=0.15, P=.008). Conclusions: A correct care of fever is observed despite the low knowledge. A good strategy to promote a correct care of febrile child is to do sanitary education with update information and adapted it to parents, focusing on the differences between ethnic groups because they seem to have inaccurate beliefs about fever (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Conesa, Maria-Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ridao Manonellas, Saida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fernández, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Hernando, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Pina, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tormo Esparza, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir los conocimientos y los cuidados parentales de la fiebre en niños menores de 2 años y relacionarlos con características sociodemográficas. Diseño: Estudio descriptivo transversal de correlación multicéntrico. Emplazamiento: Realizado en 5 equipos de atención primaria de Barcelona. Participantes: Padres, madres o tutores legales de niños menores de 2 años que acuden para la administración de una vacuna incluida en el calendario sistemático. Participaron un total de 311 sujetos. Mediciones principales: Las variables principales son 9 ítems de conocimientos y 8 de cuidados o manejo de la fiebre obtenidos con la adaptación del cuestionario de Chiappini et al. (2012). Resultados: El 69,8% tienen un manejo/cuidado correcto de la fiebre. Un 3,9% acertaron todos los ítems de conocimientos. La puntuación de conocimientos es menor en personas sin estudios (p=0,03), mayor en europeos y sudamericanos y menor en Asia y África (p&lt;0,001). El 100% de los pacientes crónicos tuvieron todos los ítems de cuidado/manejo correctos (p=0,03). Se observa que la correlación entre las puntuaciones de conocimiento y manejo es positiva (rho=0,15, p=0,008). Conclusiones: Se observan unos cuidados correctos de la fiebre a pesar de la falta de conocimientos. Una buena estrategia para fomentar el adecuado manejo del niño febril es dar información actualizada y adaptada a los padres, incidiendo en los grupos étnicos que parecen tener creencias inexactas sobre la fiebre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;49(8): 484-491, oct. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167043</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los cuidados y los conocimientos parentales sobre la fiebre en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54179^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2700^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
