<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120145</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The genetics and the dignity of the human being</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The biological elements of man are not sufficient to confront the bioethical questions around the person concept, but are necessary to accurately define the properties of the human beings and the theological, philosophical and legal aspects that are attributable to each person. The human being is a singular being. Indeed, the coexistence of two dimensions of different nature, material and spiritual, is the most important difference between the man and the rest of living beings. Moreover, in man appears a new characteristic, unique between the living beings, the ethical component. The values and guidelines of the moral and ethical behavior of the human being must be considered of natural origin since they have contributed to the success and survival of the species. The man is not only Homo sapiens but also Homo moralis. The recognition of fault, self-control, solidarity, love, generosity, altruism and honesty, among others, are innate qualities in the human beings. The unit of the human species demands the respect and the consideration of the same dignity for all its members, but only for its members. The philosophical anthropology emphasizes the singularity of each human being, each person. This agrees totally with the data of the science, which emphasize the individual and singular genetic identity of each human being (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jouve de Barreda, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los elementos biológicos del hombre no son suficientes para afrontar las cuestiones bioéticas que se plantean en torno al concepto de persona, pero son necesarios para definir con precisión las propiedades de los seres humanos y los aspectos teológicos, filosóficos y jurídicos que son atribuibles a cada persona. El ser humano es un ser singular. En él que conviven dos dimensiones de distinta naturaleza, una material y otra espiritual, y precisamente esta es la principal de las diferencias entre el hombre y el resto de seres vivos. Pero además en el hombre aparece una nueva característica, única entre los seres vivos, la componente ética. Los valores y pautas del comportamiento moral y ético del ser humano deben considerarse de origen natural ya que han contribuido al éxito y supervivencia de la especie. El hombre no es solo Homo sapiens sino también Homo moralis. El reconocimiento de culpa, autodominio, solidaridad, amor, generosidad, altruismo y honestidad, entre otras, son cualidades innatas en los seres humanos. La antropología filosófica destaca el carácter único e irrepetible propio de cada ser humano, cada persona. Esto coincide plenamente con los datos de la ciencia, que destaca la identidad genética individual y singular de cada ser humano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;24(80): 91-100, ene.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La genética y la dignidad del ser humano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5962^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36317</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35417^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
