<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10817</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical management of braquial plexus injuries at Plastic Surgery Unit Dr Salvador B Gautier Hospital, Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic: a 5 year retrospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objective. Treatment of braquial plexus injuries is highly demand and difficult, not only because of its complexity and anatomical variability, but because it needs of special abilities for diagnosis and management. Many surgical techniques and its modifications are described looking for recovering of functional capacity of a palsy extremity.  In this paper we review the experience of our Unit in management and treatment of these patients, looking for, in a second phase, to get an evaluation of results in order to archive rules for future attention to these patients.  Methods. A5 years and 49 patients series about management of brachial plexus injuries is presented. Cases were treated at Dr. Salvador B. Gautier Hospital in the Dominican Republic and evaluated retrospectively.  Results. Most of the patients were young adults between 21 and 29 years old (53%).Male patients predominance of 93%.Motorcycle accidents caused 86% of injuries. Closed lesion was present in 86%.Most of the patients were referred late to the hospital.  The most common affected roots were C5, C6. Avulsion was the most common injury and 48 out of 49 patients had a direct braquial plexus surgery with a 100% of neurolisis; 41% nerve grafts and nerve transfers; and 7 cases with out of the plexus nerve transfers.  Conclusions. With all our recovered data and once determined the most frequent type of patient with braquial plexus injury in our area, we may conduct a follow-up study of the patients in order to know their recover level, their autonomy and their back to a productive job (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrand-Perdomo, Héctor A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belén, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercedes-Acosta, Severo A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela, Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrand-Geraldino, María C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y Objetivo. El tratamiento de las lesiones de plexo braquial es demandante y dificultoso, no solo por su complejidad y variabilidad anatómica sino también por las habilidades requeridas para el diagnóstico y abordaje de las mismas. Están descritas gran cantidad de técnicas y modificaciones en busca de readquirir la capacidad funcional de un miembro paralizado.  En el presente trabajo revisamos la experiencia de nuestro servicio en el abordaje y tratamiento de estos pacientes, para, en una segunda fase, poder evaluar los resultados de estas intervenciones y establecer políticas de atención para el futuro.  Material y Método. Presentamos un estudio de revisión retrospectiva de la experiencia de 5 años y 49 pacientes con tratamiento de lesiones del plexo braquial en el Hospital Dr. Salvador B. Gautier de la República Dominicana.  Resultados. La mayoría de los afectados fueron adultos jóvenes (53%), sexo masculino (93%). La causa más frecuente de la lesión fue accidente relacionado con motocicleta (86%). La lesión fue cerrada en el 86%. Por lo general, los pacientes llegaron tardíamente al centro para recibir atención. Las raíces más afectadas fueron las superiores C5, C6, y la avulsión fue la lesión más frecuente. De los 49 pacientes intervenidos, 48 lo fueron directamente en el plexo braquial realizándose neurolisis en el 100%; transferencias e injertos nerviosos en el 41%; y transferencia extraplexual en 7 casos.  Conclusiones. Tras los datos recogidos y una vez determinado el perfil del paciente más frecuentemente afectado en nuestro entorno, procede realizar un estudio de seguimiento de los pacientes para determinar el grado de recuperación alcanzado, su autonomía y retorno al trabajo productivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;43(supl.1): s71-s75, sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje quirúrgico de las lesiones de plexo braquial en el departamento de Cirugía Plástica del Hospital Dr Salvador B Gautier, Santo Domingo, República Dominicana: estudio retrospectivo de 5 años</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
