<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98624</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Short-term effects of neuromuscular tape on knee extension force</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To study the short term effects of neuromuscular taping (NMT) on maximum force and explosive strength in knee extension. Material and methods21 subjects participated in this quasi-experimental study. Inclusion criteria healthy subjects who practiced 3 to 12hours of sports per week. Exclusion criteria Subjects with history of or who had an on-going cardiovascular and/or respiratory disease incompatible with the muscle strength tests applied, backgrounds of surgical intervention in lower limbs (LL) in the 6 previous months, muscle-tendon, joint lesion or severe traumatism in the LL in the last month, and subjects allergic to adhesive material of the NMT. Each subject underwent an isometric strength test of the explosive strength (depth jump) with and without applied NMT. Statistical analysis A descriptive statistical study and differences of means were performed with the Student's T test for paired samples. Results No significant differences were found in any variable except for the maximum strength peak, where the subject suffered a 20% decrease when the NMT was used. Conclusions The NMT has a short term effect on maximum isometric strength in knee extension, although it has no effect on the explosive strength (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta-Vargas, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez-Moya, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Estudiar los efectos a corto plazo del vendaje neuromuscular (VNM) en la fuerza máxima y explosiva en la extensión de rodilla. Material y métodos Veintiún sujetos participaron en este estudio cuasi experimental. Criterios de inclusión Sujetos sanos que practicaban entre 3 y 12 h de actividad deportiva a la semana. Criterios de exclusión Sujetos con antecedentes o que cursasen alguna enfermedad cardiovascular y/o respiratoria incompatible con los test de fuerza muscular aplicados, antecedentes de intervención quirúrgica en miembros inferiores (MMII) en los 6 meses previos, lesión músculo-tendinosa, articular o traumatismo severo en los MMII en el último mes, y sujetos alérgicos al material adhesivo del VNM. Cada sujeto realizó un test de fuerza isométrica de extensión de rodilla y un test de fuerza explosiva (salto en profundidad) con y sin VNM aplicado. Análisis estadístico Se realizó un análisis estadístico descriptivo y la diferencia de medias con la prueba de la t de Student para muestras relacionadas. Resultados No se encontraron diferencias significativas en ninguna variable, salvo en el pico máximo de fuerza, donde el sujeto sufría un descenso del 20% cuando llevaba aplicado el VNM. Conclusiones El VNM posee efectos a corto plazo sobre la fuerza isométrica máxima en la extensión de rodilla, aunque no provoca efecto en la fuerza explosiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(6): 256-261, Nov. - Dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98624</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del vendaje neuromuscular a corto plazo en la fuerza en la extensión de rodilla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7704^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9964^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9661^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7894^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
