<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043486</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety on sanitary professionals regarding death: review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: fearing death is one of the most deep-seated emotionsin human psyche. This death anxiety and everything related to it determineon the therapeutic relationship between sanitary professionals andthe patient or the family.Objectives: to analyze several existing articles on death anxiety and itsinfluence on sanitary professionals&#146; duties, attitude and behaviour at PalliativeCare. To know those factors which vary this level of death anxiety.We also review some articles, which suggest modifying the above-mentionedattitudes towards death by means of formative programmes.Method: searching and selection of articles in PubMed about deathanxiety and formative programmes in sanitary professionals.Conclusion: age, occupational stress, more profesional experience andpercentage of time in contact with terminally ill are factors, beside others,which determinate the level of death anxiety. This anxiety influences thecommunication between professionals (both physicians and DUEs) andpatients and families. Although the application of formative programmesor communication skill trainings in both professional categories notalways modify the level of death anxiety, it is considered that this cursesimprove the communication with the patient and the family</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mier Zárraga, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santisteban Etxeburu, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el miedo a la muerte es una de las emociones másenraizadas en la psique humana. Esta ansiedad ante la muerte y todo loque la rodea influye en la relación terapéutica entre el profesional sanitarioy el paciente o su familia.Objetivos: analizar diferentes artículos existentes sobre la ansiedad ala muerte y su influencia en la labor, actitud y comportamiento del personalsanitario que trabaja en Cuidados Paliativos. Conocer los factoresdeterminantes que varían esta ansiedad ante la muerte. Valorar si estenivel de ansiedad y actitudes ante la muerte se modifican mediante programasformativos.Método: búsqueda y selección de artículos en PubMed sobre la ansiedadante la muerte y cursos formativos en personal sanitarioConclusión: la edad, carga ocupacional, mayor experiencia profesionaly porcentaje de tiempo en contacto con enfermos terminales son factores,entre otros, que influyen en el nivel de ansiedad ante al muerte. Estaansiedad influye en la comunicación entre los profesionales y el paciente osu familia. Aunque el empleo de programas formativos o entrenamientoen habilidades de comunicación no siempre modifica el nivel de ansiedadante la muerte, estos cursos resultan beneficiosos a la hora de mejorar lacomunicación con el paciente y la familia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;12(3): 169-174, jul.-sept. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043486</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad ante la muerte en el personal sanitario: revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
