<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74292</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to study the association of nuclear grade (NG)with specific clinical and biological parameters which may influencethe clinical behaviour of infiltrating ductal carcinomasof the breast (IDC)Material and methods: we analyzed in 236 tissue samplesthe cytosolic concentrations of estrogen receptor (ER), progesteronereceptor (PR), pS2, cathepsin D and hyaluronic acid(HA), as well as those of the epidermal growth factor receptor(EGFR) and HA in the cell membrane fraction. Likewise, weconsidered size, ploidy, S-phase fraction and axillary node involvementand distant metastasis as variables of the study.Results: the transition from NG1 to NG3 was accompaniedby greater cellular S-Phase &gt; 7% (p = 0.001), higher cathepsinD levels (p = 0.021) and lower ER concentrations (p =0.033). When we considered the positivity for ER (&gt; 10fmol/mg prot.), we can observe that, in the IDC-ER+ tumors,NG3 was accompanied by greater SF+ (p = 0.002), whereasin the IDC-ER- cases it was associated with higher cathepsinDlevels (p = 0.026). Similar features were observed when axillarynodal involvemente was taken accountConclusions: these results led us to consider that NG is associatedwith some clinical-biological changes (greater proliferation,higher cathepsin D levels) that may help to explain itsvalue as a prognostic factor in breast carcinomas. Nevertheless,these biological associations depends on the hormonodependeceor axillary nodal invasion of the tumors. In ER-positiveor N-negative, NG3 was associated preferently with agreater cellular proliferation, whereas in ER-negative or N-positiveit was associated with higher cathepsin D levels(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruibal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: estudiar cómo el grado nuclear (GN) influye enlas características clínico-biológicas de los carcinomas ductalesinfiltrantes de mama.Material y métodos: se incluyeron 236 pacientes, de loscuales 87 eran GN1, 93 GN2 y 56 GN3. Hemos analizado lasconcentraciones citosólicas de receptor de estrógenos (RE), deprogesterona (RP), pS2, catepsina D y ácido hialurónico, asícomo las de este y el receptor del factor de crecimiento epidérmicoen las membranas celulares. Hemos considerado,además, el tamaño, afectación axilar, metástasis a distancia,ploidía y fase de síntesis celular.Resultados: los tumores grado 3 mostraron, en relación alos 1, mayores concentraciones de catepsina D (p = 0,021) ymenores de receptor de estrógenos (p = 0,033), siendo, asimismo,más frecuentemente proliferativos (Fase S &gt; 7%; p =0,001). Al considerar los carcinomas mamarios en función dela hormonodependencia, pudimos ver, en los tumores RE+,que los GN3 fueron más frecuentemente proliferativos (p =0,052), mientras que en los casos RE- cursaron con mayoresconcentraciones de catepsina D (p = 0,026). Similares hallazgosobtuvimos al tener presente la afectación ganglionar axilar.Conclusiones: a) el paso de GN 1 a 3 se asocia con menorhormonodependencia, mayor proliferación y superiores concentracionesde catepsina D; b) estas diferencias biológicas difierencuando los tumores se clasifican en función de la hormonodependenciay afectación ganglionar axilar: en los casosRE+ o N- la transición del GN se asocia preferentemente a laproliferación celular, mientras que en los casos RE- o N+ lohace con la catepsina D(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);20(4): 162-165, 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos biológicos del grado nuclear en los carcinomas mamarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9157^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
