<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94956</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tics and gilles de la tourette syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. Tourette syndrome is a neurologic disorder characterized by involuntary vocal and motor tics. It affects around 1 to 2% of school-age children and is the most common movement disorder in paediatric age. Tics are involuntary or semivoluntary, sudden, brief, intermittent, repetitive movements (motor tics) or sounds (phonic tics). It is often associated with psychiatric comorbidities, mainly attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder and obsessive-compulsive disorder.  Given its diverse presentation, Tourette&#146;s syndrome can almost mimic many hyperkinetic disorders, making the diagnosis challenging at times. Development. The etiology of this syndrome is thought to be related to basal ganglia dysfunction and many clues have been pursued, both genetic and environmental factors, but no compelling major contribution to the pathogenesis of the disease has yet emerged. Treatment can be behavioural, pharmacologic, or surgical, and is dictated by the  most incapacitating symptoms. Alpha-2-adrenergic agonists are the first line of pharmacologic therapy, but dopamine-receptorblocking drugs are required for multiple, complex tics. Dopamine-receptor-blocking drugs are associated with potential side effects. Conclusion. Appropriate diagnosis and treatment can substantially improve quality of life and psychosocial functioning in affected patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Esteba, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarranz, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tijero Merino, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. El síndrome de Tourette es un trastorno neurológico caracterizado por múltiples tics motores y vocales. Afecta al 1-2% de los niños en edad escolar y es el trastorno de movimiento más frecuente en edad pediátrica. Los tics son movimientos intermitentes, repetitivos, rápidos y estereotipados, precedidos de una sensación premonitoria que impulsa al realizar  el movimiento, se suprimen a voluntad y pueden persistir durante todas las fases del sueño. Frecuentemente se asocian a trastornos neuropsiquiátricos como los trastornos por déficit de atención/hiperactividad y los trastornos obsesivo-compulsivos. Pueden simular casi cualquier trastorno del movimiento. Desarrollo. Se piensa que el origen de la enfermedad está en una disfunción de los ganglios basales, pero a día de hoy no se conocen las causas genéticas o ambientales que la producen. El tratamiento se basa en terapias educacionales, farmacológicas e incluso quirúrgicas en función del síntoma más incapacitante. Los agonistas alfa2-adrenérgicos y los neurolépticos son los fármacos de primera elección. Los neurolépticos deben administrarse con precaución y en dosis bajas debido a sus potenciales efectos adversos. Conclusión. Es importante un tratamiento  adecuado de cara a mejorar la calidad de vida y la función psicosocial de los pacientes afectados por esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(supl.1): 17-20, ene. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94956</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tics y síndrome de Gilles de la Tourette</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9956^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24387^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34317^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
