<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-8097</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tonsillectomy as a major outpatient procedure. Prospective 8-year study: indications and complications. Comparison with inpatients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tonsillectomy is a classic procedure in othorinolaryngology and the most frequent performed in some industrialized countries. In the US more than 390,000 procedures were performed per year. The indications for tonsillectomy and the advisability of outpatients surgery are often debated in the current literature. A prospective 8 years study was made to collect the complications in a total of 348 inpatients and 148 outpatients tonsillectomy. The mean age of inpatients was 6.68 years and 6.14 years in the outpatients group; the 57.18% and 56.52% respectively were men. The mean duration of the surgery in all patients was 23 minutes and the mean time for discharge in the outpatients 173 minutes. The complications occurred in the 1.89% of the inpatients (3 reinterventions, 1 delayed bleeding and 3 delayed discharge) and in the 2.17% of the outpatients (2 reinterventions and 1 anaesthetic complication). Pain was present in the 30% of the patients, vomiting in the 1.57% and fever under 38 degrees C in the 5.52%. We conclude that tonsillectomy has a low rate of complications, the patients can be discharged 4 hours after the surgery, the age under 4 years and SAS were unrelated with the risk of complications, and the poor fluid intake is not a criterion for admission (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La amigdalectomía es un procedimiento clásico en otorrinolaringología y el más frecuente en muchos países industrializados, superando en USA las 390. 000 intervenciones/año. Es un procedimiento controvertido tanto en sus indicaciones como en si debe o no realizarse de forma ambulatoria. Presentamos un estudio prospectivo de 8 años de duración comparando las complicaciones de dos grupos homogéneos de 348 amigdalectomías ingresadas y 148 ambulatorias. La edad media para los pacientes ingresados fue de 6.68 años, siendo el 57,18 por ciento varones, y de 6,14 años y un 56,52 por ciento de varones para los pacientes ambulatorios. El tiempo medio de la cirugía fue de 23 minutos y el tiempo medio para el alta en el paciente ambulatorio fue de 173 minutos. Las complicaciones en los pacientes ingresados supusieron el 1,89 por ciento (3 reintervenciones, 1 hemorragia tardía, y 3 altas diferidas), y en el paciente ambulatorio el 2,17 por ciento (2 reintervenciones y una complicación anestésica). El 30 por ciento de los pacientes consideró el dolor 'importante', en el 1,57 por ciento aparecieron vómitos y en el 5,52 por ciento fiebre menor de 38ºC. Concluimos que la amigdalectomía es una intervención con un bajo índice de complicaciones, que el alta es posible a las 4 horas, que la edad (más de 4 años) y el SAS no aumentan el riesgo de complicaciones, y que el retraso en la ingesta líquida no es un criterio de ingreso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;51(3): 221-227, abr. 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Amigdalectomía por Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria. Estudio prospectivo de 8 años: Indicaciones y complicaciones. Comparación con el paciente ingresado</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rivas Lacarte, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-8097</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d14458^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15241^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24356</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
