<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050493</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Professional ethic and institutional ethic: convergency or conflict</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During the last decades, an important debate about professionsin general, and particularly about the medical profession, has takenplace. The classic idea that professionals do have a «special morality», different from the common morality, which among otherthings give them legal impunity, came to a head. This cause a greatdeal of confusion among the professionals, incapable of reactingand redefining precisely their own identity. Some new concepts,like that of «internal morality» of professional activities, made thedebate more difficult and confusing. On the other hand, the everydaymore powerful influence of free market forces in the health careeconomy, has made that some decisions taken by health care managerswould be considered by physicians as opposed to their professionalduties and incompatible with them. This has been the originof a debate about what is called in North America «New Professionalism». This debate deals with basic questions about the healthcare professional's identity at the beginning of this new Century</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gracia, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante las últimas décadas ha tenido lugar un amplio debatesobre las profesiones en general, y sobre la profesión médica en particular.La idea clásica de que los profesionales se rigen por una«moralidad especial» distinta de la moralidad común, que entre otrascosas les dota de impunidad jurídica, ha entrado en crisis. Esto haproducido un gran desconcierto en los cuerpos profesionales, que nohan sabido bien cómo redefinir su identidad. Algunos conceptos,como el de «fines internos» de la actividad profesional, no han hechomás que complicar la situación. Por otra parte, la presencia cada vezmás activa de las fuerzas del mercado en la economía sanitaria, hahecho que los profesionales de la medicina vieran ciertas decisionesde los gestores sanitarios como incompatibles con la moralidad de suprofesión. Esto ha dado lugar a un debate que en el ámbito anglosajón,se conoce con el nombre de New Professionalism. En él se estánventilando cuestiones fundamentales sobre la identidad de los profesionalessanitarios de cara al siglo XXI</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(5): 457-467, sept.-oct. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050493</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ética profesional y ética institucional: ¿convergencia o conflicto?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32497</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16672^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5086</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11251</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
