<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99386</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Urachal adenocarcinoma. Case report and bibliographic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Literature review of adenocarcinoma of the urachus in connection with two cases recently diagnosed and treated in our center. METHODS/RESULTS: We report 2 cases of urachus Adenocarcinoma treated in our institution, both underwent extended partial cystectomy including excision of the urachus up to the umbilicus. CONCLUSION: Urachal adenocarcinoma is an exceptional tumor, of poor prognosis, the treatment of which is surgical (partial cystectomy), and the main predictors of disease-free survival are the degree of tumor differentiation and the free margins of the surgical specimen(Au)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Fernández, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ogaya Piniés, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Husillos Alonso, Adrián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Amo, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Escudero, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lledó García, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano Patiño, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Revisión de la literatura del Adenocarcinoma de uraco a propósito de 2 casos diagnosticados y tratados recientemente en nuestro centro. MÉTODOS/RESULTADOS: Describimos 2 casos de adenocarcinoma de uraco tratados en nuestro, ambos sometidos con cistectomía parcial extensa incluyendo resección de el uraco hasta el ombligo. CONCLUSIONES: El adenocarcinoma de uraco es un tumor excepcional, de mal pronóstico, cuyo tratamiento recae fundamentalmente en la cirugía (cistectomía parcial), y donde los principales factores pronóstico de supervivencia libre de enfermedad son el grado de diferenciación tumoral y los márgenes libres de la pieza quirúrgica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(4): 498-501, mayo 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99386</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adenocarcinoma de uraco. Presentación de 2 casos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14896^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14896^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
