<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89236</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intima-media thickness and its relation with the SCORE function in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Measurement of carotid intima-media thickness (IMT) has been proposed for the evaluation of subclinical atherosclerosis as part of the cardiovascular prevention strategy. The objectives are to describe the association between IMT and the presence of other cardiovascular risk (CVR) factors and with CVR estimated by the SCORE function. Subjects and methods: Descriptive study in general population through non-probability sampling. There were 1,118 participants to whom we estimated their cardiovascular risk according to the SCORE function. We selected 467 participants who underwent carotid echo-doppler in which IMT was determined and carotid plaque was evaluated.Results: Of the 467 individuals, 24, 49 and 27% belonged to the CVR, medium and high respectively. The population mean IMT was 0.63745mm. The mean IMT for the cardiovascular risk groups low, medium and high was 0.5629, 0.66269 and 0.66016mm respectively. IMT increased with age and was associated with other cardiovascular risk factors. In 13% of carotid ultrasound performed, atherosclerotic plaques were found. The highest percentage of individuals with atherosclerotic plaques were seen in the intermediate and high CVR groups.Conclusions: The results of this study show similar values of carotid IMT and presence of carotid plaque in subjects of intermediate and high CVR. We also found an association between increased carotid IMT and age, weight and diabetes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Shea, Antonio Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Manuel, Elpidio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamorano, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La estimación del grosor íntimo-medial carotídeo (GIM) es un método que se ha propuesto para la detección de la aterosclerosis subclínica dentro de la estrategia de prevención cardiovascular. Los objetivos del estudio son describir la asociación entre el GIM y la presencia de otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular (RCV), así como describir la asociación entre el GIM y el RCV según SCORE.Sujetos y método: Estudio descriptivo realizado sobre la población general. Participaron 1.118 individuos a los que se les calculó el RCV según la función SCORE. Se escogió a 467 participantes a quienes se les realizó un eco-doppler carotídeo estimando el GIM y la presencia de placas ateroscleróticas. Resultados:De los 467 individuos, el 24, 49 y 27% pertenecieron a los grupos de RCV bajo, medio y alto, respectivamente. El GIM promedio fue de 0,63745mm. La media del GIM en los grupos de RCV bajo, medio y alto fue de 0,5629, 0,66269 y 0,66016mm, respectivamente. El GIM aumenta con la edad y está asociado a otros factores de RCV. En el 13% de las ecografías carotídeas realizadas se encontraron placas de aterosclerosis. El mayor porcentaje de individuos con placas de aterosclerosis se encontró en los grupos de RCV medio y alto.Conclusiones: Los resultados de este estudio muestran valores similares del GIM y de presencia de placas ateroscleróticas entre los grupos de RCV medio y alto. Existe una asociación directa entre un GIM aumentado y la edad, el peso y la diabetes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);136(15): 653-658, mayo 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89236</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grosor íntimo-medial carotídeo y su relación con la función SCORE en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30469^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2380^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30468^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
