<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111896</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between autoimmune disease and type 1 diabetes in the DIACAM1 Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the characteristics of autoimmune diseases (AD) in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM). Patients and methods: A cross-sectional, multicentre study on adult patients with T1DM seen in outpatient endocrinology clinics over a 12 month period. Sociodemographic and clinical variables and the presence of AD [autoimmune thyroid disease (ATD), chronic gastritis, coeliac disease (CD), vitiligo, primary adrenal insufficiency, and other AD in this cohort] were investigated. Results: The study included a total of 1,465 patients (51.5% male) with a median age of 38.2 years (interquartile range 28,5-48,3) and a median diabetes duration of 17.3 years (11.1-25.6). Just under one-third (29.2%) had AD, with ATD being the most frequent (22% with normal thyroid function or hypothyroidism, and 3.4% with hyperthyroidism). ATD was most frequent in females [70.5% (P&lt;0.001)] and the prevalence increased with age [41.7±14.5 vs 38.6±13.1 years in patients with and without ATD respectively (P&lt;.001)]. ATD with normal thyroid function or hypothyroidism increased also with longer duration of T1DM [17.1% with &lt;10years, 21% with 10-20 years, 24.6% with 20-30 years and 26.3 with &gt;30years (P&lt;.05)]. Other AD were chronic gastritis (3.6%), vitiligo (1.6%), CD (1.1%), primary adrenal insufficiency (0.3%) and others (3.4%). Conclusions: ATD was the most prevalent AD. CD and chronic gastritis were probably underdiagnosed in our study as there is no consensus for screening. Screening for AD may be necessary in patients with T1DM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado-del Rey, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiroga-López, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz-Antolín, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-López, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lamas-Oliveira, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sastre-Marcos, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar las características de las enfermedades autoinmunes (EA) asociadas a la diabetes mellitus tipo 1 (DM1). Pacientes y métodos: Estudio transversal, multicéntrico, que incluyó a pacientes adultos con DM1 valorados en consultas externas de endocrinología durante 12 meses. Se analizaron variables sociodemográficas, clínicas y la presencia de EA (enfermedad tiroidea autoinmune [ETA], gastritis crónica, enfermedad celiaca [EC], vitíligo, insuficiencia suprarrenal primaria [ISR] y otras EA registradas en esta cohorte). Resultados: De un total de 1.465 pacientes, el 51,5% varones, con una mediana de edad de 38,2 años (rango intercuartílico, 28,5-48,3) y una mediana de tiempo de evolución de la DM1 de 17,3 años (11,1-25,6), el 29,2% presentaron alguna EA, siendo la más frecuente la ETA (22% con normofunción o hipofunción y 3,4% con hiperfunción tiroidea). La ETA fue más frecuente en el sexo femenino (70,5% [p&lt;0,001]) y aumentó con la edad (41,7±14,5 vs 38,6±13,1 años en sujetos con y sin ETA, respectivamente [p&lt;0,001]). La ETA con normofunción o hipofunción tiroidea aumentó también con el tiempo de evolución de la DM1 (17,1% en &lt;10 años de evolución, 21% en 10-20 años, 24,6% en 20-30 años y 26,3% en &gt;30años [p&lt;0,05]). Otras EA que se asociaron fueron la gastritis crónica (3,6%), el vitíligo (1,6%), la EC (1,1%), la ISR (0,3%) y otras (3,4%). Conclusiones: La ETA es la EA más prevalente. La EC y la gastritis crónica probablemente se encuentren infradiagnosticadas en este estudio por la falta de consenso en cuanto a su cribado. Parece necesario realizar un cribado sistemático de EA en pacientes con DM1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;29(2): 50-56, mar.-abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111896</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades autoinmunes asociadas a la diabetes mellitus tipo 1 en el estudio DIACAM1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d306^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5897^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
