<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79808</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glycation of mitochondrial proteins, oxidative stress and aging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mitochondrial proteins can be modified by glycation reactions from endogenous dicarbonyl compounds such as physiologically generated methylglyoxal and glyoxal. This modification could cause structural and functional changes in the proteins Consequently, dicarbonyl attack of the mitochondrial proteome may be an event leading to mitochondrial dysfunction and thus, to oxidative stress. These protein chemical modifications can play an important role in the physiological aging process and age-associated diseases, where both mitochondrial deffects and increased dicarbonyl concentrations have been found. Future research should address the functional changes in mitochondrial proteins that are the targets for dicarbonyl glycation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayala, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portero-Otín, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pamplona, Reinald</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naudí, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jové, MAriona</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las proteínas mitocondriales pueden ser modificadas por reacciones de glicación inducidas por compuestos dicarbonilo procedentes del metabolismo tales como el glioxal y el metilglioxal. Estas modificaciones provocan cambios estructurales y funcionales en las proteínas implicadas. La modificación del proteoma mitocondrial por estos compuestos dicarbonilo puede inducir disfunción mitocondrial y acentuar un estado de estrés oxidativo. Así, estas modificaciones químicas podrían jugar un papel clave en el proceso fisiológico de envejecimiento y patologías asociadas a la edad, donde se han evidenciado tanto defectos de la actividad mitocondrial como incrementos de compuestos dicarbonilo. Identificar las proteínas mitocondriales especificamente modificadas, aseverar los cambios funcionales derivados y sus implicaciones constituyen lineas de investigación que tendrán su desarrollo en los próximos años(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);45(3): 156-166, abr.-jun.2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79808</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alicación de proteínas mitocondriales, estrés oxidativo y envejecimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51245^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34510</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36225^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30709^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
