<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054504</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuropsychological impairment in human immunodeficiency virus-positive children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. From human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)/AIDS epidemic onset in 1981 through 2003, 580,000 infants,        children and adolescents died worldwide. Currently, between 2.1 and 2.9 million are estimated to live with HIV/AIDS. Here we        review the main features of HIV/AIDS in infants, children and adolescents from a neuropsychological stance. Also, we review        current neuropsychological tests for assessment of HIV/AIDS-associated neuropsychological impairment in infants, children and        adolescents. Development. Most HIV-positive infants and children will die before adolescence. These children present both        neurological and neuropsychological derangements with a variety of cognitive and motor deficits and important differences in        their course. The main neurological condition related to HIV infection in childhood is HIV-associated progressive encephalopathy,        which may be the initial presenting condition for AIDS in 18% of cases, affecting 30-60% of seropositive infants, children        and adolescents at any time point of their disease. HIV-associated progressive encephalopathy causes neuropsychological        deficits involving a wide variety of domains, such as speed and language, memory, learning, information processing and motor        functioning. They may affect negatively children&#146;s normal development and school achievement. Conclusions. It is crucial to        determine how infection affects HIV-positive children and adolescents&#146; development and to establish which interventions are        more efficient to help them to be successful at school. Also, it is necessary to determine confounding variable role in HIV-positive        infants, children and adolescents&#146;cognitive development to determine direct and indirect HIV-infection effects on neuropsychological        development</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portellano, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Arias, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millana-Cuevas, L. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Desde el comienzo de la epidemia del virus de inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH)/sida en 1981 hasta        finales de 2003, han muerto 580.000 niños por esta enfermedad. Se calcula que entre 2,1 y 2,9 millones sufren el VIH/sida. En        este artículo revisamos las características de la infección por el VIH en lactantes, niños y adolescentes desde una perspectiva        neuropsicológica. Asimismo, revisamos las pruebas neuropsicológicas que se utilizan para evaluar las alteraciones cognitivas        y psicomotrices asociadas con la infección en lactantes, niños y adolescentes. Desarrollo. La mayoría de los niños infectados        morirá antes de llegar a la adolescencia. Los niños seropositivos sufren alteraciones tanto neurológicas como neuropsicológicas,        pero la evolución y los déficit concretos varían mucho de un niño a otro. La principal enfermedad neurológica        asociada con el VIH en niños es la encefalopatía progresiva de la infancia asociada con el VIH, que puede ser la presentación        clínica inicial del sida hasta en el 18% de los casos y afecta al 30-60% de los niños y adolescentes seropositivos en algún        momento de la enfermedad. Produce déficit neuropsicológicos en áreas cognitivas y motoras muy variadas, y puede afectar        muy negativamente al desarrollo evolutivo normal del niño y a su rendimiento escolar y social. Conclusiones. Es importante        determinar cómo el VIH afecta al desarrollo de estos niños y qué tipo de intervenciones les ayudarán a mejorar. Además, es        necesario determinar la influencia de las variables de confusión que pueden afectar al desarrollo neuropsicológico para determinar        así los efectos evolutivos directos e indirectos de la infección</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(6): 366-374, mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones neuropsicológicas en niños infectados por el virus de inmunodeficiencia humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33075^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29422</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
