<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94891</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Melatonin, synthetic analogs, and the sleep/wake rhythm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. Melatonin, a widespread hormone in the animal kingdom, is produced by several organs and tissues besides the pineal gland. Whilst extrapineal melatonin behaves as a cytoprotective molecule, the pineal produces the hormone in a rhythmic manner. The discovery of melatonin in 1958, and the characterization of its synthesis somewhat later, let to the description of its photoperiodic regulation and its relationship with the biological rhythms such as the sleep/wake rhythm. Development. The suprachiasmatic nuclei are the anatomical seat of the biological clock, represented by the clock genes, which code for the period and frequency of the rhythms. The photoperiod synchronizes the activity of the auprachiasmatic  biological clock, which in turn induces the melatonin&#146;s rhythm. The rhythm of melatonin, peaking at 2-3 am, acts as an endogenous synchronizer that translates the environmental photoperiodic signal in chemical information for the cells. The sleep/wake cycle is a typical biological rhythm synchronized by melatonin, and the sleep/wake cycle alterations of chronobiological origin, are very sensitive to melatonin treatment. Taking advantage of the chronobiotic and antidepressive properties of melatonin, a series of synthetic analogs of this hormone, with high interest in insomnia, are now available. Conclusions. Melatonin is a highly effective chronobiotic in the treatment of chronobiological alterations of the sleep/wake cycle. From a pharmacokinetic point of view, the synthetic drugs derived from melatonin are interesting tools in the therapy of  these alterations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escames, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acuña Castroviejo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. La melatonina, una hormona ampliamente distribuida en el reino animal, se produce en numerosos órganos y tejidos además de la glándula pineal. Mientras que la melatonina extrapineal tiene funciones de protección celular, la pineal se encarga de su producción rítmica. La caracterización de la melatonina en 1958 y la identificación de su síntesis permitieron describir su regulación fotoperiódica y su relación con los ritmos biológicos, entre otros, el ritmo sueño/vigilia. Desarrollo. Los núcleos supraquiasmáticos son la sede anatómica del reloj biológico, representado por los genes reloj, que codifican para el período y la frecuencia de los ritmos. El fotoperíodo sincroniza la actividad del reloj biológico en los núcleos  supraquiasmáticos, que a su vez inducen el ritmo de melatonina. Este ritmo, con un pico máximo hacia las dos o tres de la madrugada, actúa como un sincronizador endógeno que permite traducir la señal fotoperiódica ambiental en información química que las células del organismo pueden leer. El ciclo sueño/vigilia es un caso típico de ritmo biológico sincronizado por la melatonina, y las alteraciones del ciclo sueño/vigilia de origen cronobiológico responden muy bien a esta sustancia. Aprovechando las propiedades cronobióticas y antidepresivas de la melatonina, han aparecido recientemente diversos análogos sintéticos de ésta, de gran interés en la clínica del insomnio. Conclusiones. La melatonina es un cronobiótico de gran eficacia en el tratamiento de las alteraciones cronobiológicas del ciclo sueño/vigilia. Los fármacos sintéticos derivados de la melatonina representan una herramienta terapéutica muy interesante desde el punto de vista farmacocinético para el tratamiento de  dichas alteraciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(5): 245-254, mar. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Melatonina, análogos sintéticos y el ritmo sueño/vigilia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35313^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1708^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34359^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
