<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78961</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Poverty groups and tobacco consumption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The tobacco represents a serious problem of public health that affectsin way different to the diverse socioeconomic groups, being bigger inthe estamentos with smaller economic resources. It has been impelledas high-priority, the study of the relationship between groups of povertyand consumption of tobacco, with base to elaborate preventive andpolitical measures of public health that allow an effective interventionin the marginal groups of the developed countries and in the generalpopulation of the developing countries. He/she has intended this revisionto describe the studies and investigation lines developed until the presenttime, being based on the available evidence, like base for futureinvestigations in this topic(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Trullén, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tabaquismo representa un grave problema de salud pública que afectade forma diferente a los diversos grupos socioeconómicos, siendo mayoren los estamentos con menores recursos económicos. Se ha impulsadocomo prioritario el estudio de la relación entre grupos de pobreza yconsumo de tabaco, con base a elaborar medidas preventivas y políticas desalud pública, que permitan una intervención eficaz en los grupos marginalesde los países desarrollados y en la población general de los países envías de desarrollo. Se ha propuesto esta revisión para describir los estudiosy líneas de investigación desarrolladas hasta la actualidad, basándose en laevidencia disponible, como base para investigaciones futuras en este tema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;10(2): 63-72, abr.-jun. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78961</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grupos de pobreza y consumo de tabaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24471</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3926^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24487^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11641^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11641^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
