<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88710</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fibromyalgia and psychiatric comorbidity: their effect on the quality of life patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with fibromyalgia (FM) often have associated mental disorders. As well as being very prevalent, the two conditions also have sociodemographic and clinical similarities. If both of these clinical conditions lead independently to a limitation of the health-related quality of life (HRQL) of the patients, it may be thought that their conjunction could have a greater adverse effect on this parameter. Equally, it could be assumed that the factors that worsen the HRQL of patients with FM or with mental illness could have a more serious effect on the HRQL of those in whom the two clinical conditions coexist. Although this conclusion seems evident, as far as we know there have been no studies to assess how much or in what way psychiatric comorbidity affects the HRQL of patients with FM, or any studies to analyze the particular factors that may affect their HRQL. This study approaches the importance of psychiatric comorbidity inpatients with fibromyalgia and analyzes the combined effect that these two conditions have on the overall HRQL of these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elorza, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Failde, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes con Fibromialgia (FM) con frecuencia presentan trastornos mentales asociados. Tanto la FM como los trastornos mentales, además de tener elevada prevalencia, presentan similitudes tanto sociodemográficas como clínicas. Si ambos cuadros conducen de forma independiente a una limitación de la Calidad de Vida Relacionada con la Salud (CVRS) de los pacientes, cabe pensar que la conjunción de ambos podría tener una mayor consecuencia sobre este parámetro. Así mismo, podría suponerse que los factores que empeoran la CVRS de los pacientes con FM o con enfermedad mental podrían afectar más intensamente la CVRS de aquellos en los que ambos cuadros coexiste. A pesar de que esta circunstancia parece evidente, no existen a nuestro conocimiento estudios que valoren cuánto o cómo afecta la comorbilidad psiquiatrica a la CVRS de los pacientes con FM, ni estudios que analicen los factores que pueden condicionarla. En este trabajo se aborda la importancia de la comorbilidad psiquiátrica en los pacientes con fibromialgia y se analiza el efecto conjunto de ambos procesos sobre la CVRS de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;38(5): 295-300, sept.-oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88710</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comorbilidad psiquiátrica y fibromialgia. Su efecto sobre la calidad de vida de los pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
