<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123991</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of a test to evaluate kinematic wheelchair propulsion in wheelchair users</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Wheelchair users have a high prevalence of shoulder pain due to wheelchair propulsion. The aim of this study was to develop a test to analyze wheelchair propulsion and  validate it to determine whether wheelchair propulsion is related to strength and pain in the shoulder joint. Material and methods: A total of 36 wheelchair users performed the Wheelchair Users Shoulder Pain Index, the kinematic wheelchair propulsion test (T-CIDIF) and a maximum isokinetic  strength test of the internal and external rotators of the shoulder. The T-CIDIF consisted of a 30-second maximum test performed on rollers in which two linear transducers recorded the movements of each arm, registering the number of propulsions and maximum and mean velocity and power. Results: No differences between propulsion variables were observed between the two arms. Most T-CIDIF variables were negatively correlated with the shoulder pain questionnaire (from  r=&amp;#8722;0.347 to r=&amp;#8722;0.469, from P&lt;.05 to P&lt;01). All T-CIDIF variables were correlated with the peak torque, total work, mean power, and mean of the peak torques of the internal and external shoulder rotators (from r=0.390 to r=849, P&lt;.001). Conclusion: The T-CIDIF appears to be a valid tool that is related to pain and strength in the  shoulder joints of wheelchair users and could be used in the clinical setting to assess the efficacy of various therapies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero, C. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndes, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los usuarios en silla de ruedas tienen una alta prevalencia de dolor de hombro debido al gesto continuo de la propulsión. El objetivo de este estudio fue desarrollar un test para analizar la propulsión en silla de ruedas y validarlo para saber si se relacionaba con la fuerza y dolor en la articulación del hombro. Material y métodos: A 36 usuarios se les aplicó el Wheelchair Users Shoulder Pain Index, el test de propulsión en silla de ruedas «T-CIDIF» y un test de fuerza máxima isocinética de los rotadores internos y externos del hombro. El T-CIDIF consistió en una prueba máxima de 30 s realizada sobre unos rodillos en la que se registraba por 2 transductores lineales de posición el movimiento de cada brazo, registrándose número de propulsiones, velocidades y potencias media y máxima. Resultados: No se observaron diferencias entre las variables de propulsión entre ambos brazos. La mayoría de las variables del T-CIDIF se correlacionaron negativamente con el cuestionario de dolor de hombro (desde r = &amp;#8722;0,347 hasta r =  &amp;#8722;0,469, desde p &lt; 0,05 hasta p &lt; 0,01). Todas las variables del T-CIDIF se correlacionaron con el pico par, trabajo total, potencia media y media de los picos par máximos de los rotadores internos y externos del hombro (desde r = 0,390 hasta r = 849, p &lt; 0,001). Conclusión: El T-CIDIF parece ser un test válido que se relaciona con el dolor y la fuerza de la articulación del hombro en usuarios en silla de ruedas y podría utilizarse en el ámbito clínico  para evaluar la eficacia de diferentes tratamientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);48(3): 160-167, jul.-sept. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123991</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de un test para valorar la cinemática de propulsión en usuarios en silla de ruedas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
