<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83139</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ability of Heidelberg Retina Tomograph III to predict progression in patients with early glaucoma or suspected primary open-angle glaucoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To study the ability of Heidelberg Retina Tomography III (HRT 3) measurements topredict perimetry changes in patients with early glaucoma or suspected primary openangleglaucoma.Material and methods: One hundred and thirty two eyes with early glaucoma or suspectedglaucoma with no changes in basal perimetry were prospectively selected and periodicallyevaluated over five years. The eyes were divided in two groups depending on the presenceor absence of progression (changes in glaucoma perimetry).The association between morphometric parameters and baseline HRT 3 indices, glaucomaprobability score (GPS) and Moorefield&#146;s Regression Analysis (MRA), and perimetryprogression were studied using Cox multivariate regression analyses. Kaplan-Meier curveswere used to illustrate the results.Results: Forty-eight eyes (36.36%) showed perimetry progression. Perimetry progressionshowed higher correlations with the disc area (p = 0.001), the cup area (p = 0.002) and thevertical cup disc area (p = 0.001). Multivariate regression analyses showed that eyes withbaseline MRA or baseline GPA changes were at a higher risk of having perimetryabnormalities and a faster progression.Conclusions: MRA and GPA indices are useful to predict perimetry progression in patientswith early primary open-angle glaucoma or suspected glaucoma. These indices can beused as risk markers of functional progression in glaucoma(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Martín, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pueyo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreras, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Idoipe, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si las mediciones de la papila obtenidas con el Heidelberg Retina TomographIII (HRT 3) tienen valor predictivo respecto a las alteraciones del campo visual enpacientes sospechosos de desarrollar glaucoma o con glaucoma incipiente.Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo de cohortes en el que 132 ojos sospechosos de glaucomao con glaucoma incipiente y una campimetría basal normal o con cambios incipientes,fueron evaluados periódicamente durante 5 años y se dividieron en pacientes conprogresión (cambios glaucomatosos perimétricos) o sin ella.La asociación entre los parámetros morfométricos y los índices glaucoma probability score(GPS) y Moorfield&#146;s regression analysis (MRA) obtenidos de forma basal con el HRT 3 y la progresióncampimétrica se estudió mediante el modelo de regresión multivariante de Cox. Seutilizaron curvas de Kaplan-Meier para ilustrar los resultados.Resultados: Cuarenta y ocho ojos (36,36%) mostraron progresión. Los parámetros morfométricosque mejor se correlacionaron con la progresión fueron el área de disco (p = 0,001), elárea de excavación (p = 0,002) y el área excavación/disco vertical (p = 0,001). En el modelode regresión multivariante, los ojos con MRA inicial fuera de los límites normales o GPAinicial patológico o borderline, mostraron mayor tendencia a la progresión y ésta tuvo lugaren menos tiempo.Conclusiones: Los índices GPA y MRA son predictivos de aparición de alteraciones en elcampo visual en pacientes con glaucoma incipiente o sospechosos de desarrollarlo, y puedenser útiles para estimar el riesgo de progresión funcional en el glaucoma(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;85(4): 138-143, abr. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor predictivo del Heidelberg Retina Tomograph III en pacientes con glaucoma incipiente o sospecha de glaucoma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54195^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28054^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32146^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
