<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131546</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-0771</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Compression of the ulnar nerve in Guyon&#146;s canal: retrospective study of 12 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess causes and areas of ulnar nerve compression in Guyon&#146;s canal Methods: A retrospective study of 12 patients undergoing cubital tunnel syndrome with a mean of 9 months was performed. All we performed an electrophysiological study and found the correlation with the presence of carpal tunnel syndrome. Results: In only 3 cases we found a clear etiology of nerve compression. There is an increased presence of carpal tunnel syndrome in those with idiopathic ulnar compression but without statistical significance. Conclusions: Most of the ulnar compression at the wrist, in our experience, are idiopathic. With surgery there is clinical improvement of symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Liñán-Padilla, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrionuevo-Sánchez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro-Gonzálvez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: : valorar causas y zonas de compresión del nervio cubital en el canal de Guyon. Material y método: se realizó un estudio retrospectivo de 12 pacientes intervenidos de síndrome del túnel cubital con un seguimiento medio de 9 meses. A todos se les practicó un estudio electrofi - siológico y se observó si existe relación con la presencia de síndrome de túnel del carpo. Resultados: En solo 3 casos encontramos una etiología clara de la compresión nerviosa. Existe  mayor presencia de síndrome de túnel del carpo en aquellos con compresión cubital idiopática pero sin significación estadística. Conclusiones: La mayoría de las compresiones cubitales en la muñeca, bajo nuestra experiencia, son de origen idiopático. Con la cirugía existe mejoría clínica de la sintomatología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Andal. Traumatol. Ortop. (Ed. impr.);31(2): 41-44, jul.-dic. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Compresión nervio cubital en el canal de Guyón: estudio retrospectivo de 12 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30993^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34347^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34347^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4667^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34347^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34347^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34347^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54703^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2392^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30993^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
