<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115584</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Engagement and academics results of the grade students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The academic engagement is a three-feature psychological welfare (determination, knowledge absorptive capability and dedication) as an intrinsic commitment towards the studies. The main aim of this study is to know the motivational status in students and to compare this with their academic performance.  For the purpose of this paper, it was carried out an observational, correlational, cross-sectional study. The target population is the students carrying out the clinical training in the University of Malaga as part of the Nursing Degree. According to the data achieved, the mean score are the followings: determination 3.46 out of 6 (ST 1.05), dedication 5.16 out of 6 (ST 0.97) and knowledge absorptive capability 3.59 out of 6 (ST 1.18). The engagement global mean score of the nursing students enrolled in this University School of Nursing is 4.1 out of 6. It is worthy to mention the levels for dedication, ranging from almost always and always, which involves a remarkable vocation towards their profession. The marks on Practicum II-III have evidenced an association with the engagement determination (p&lt;0.008), and knowledge absorption capability (p&lt;0.036). Marks on Practicum I have not evidenced any association (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Luque, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labajos Manzanares, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodríguez, José Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El engagement académico es un estado de bienestar psicológico tridimensional (vigor, absorción y dedicación) de compromiso intrínseco hacia los estudios. El conocimiento de ese estado motivacional en los alumnos y poder compararlo con el rendimiento académico fue el principal objetivo a alcanzar. Para ello se ha realizado un estudio observacional, correlacional y transversal. La población objeto comprende los estudiantes de Grado en Enfermería que están cursando prácticas clínicas en la Universidad de Málaga. Nuestros datos arrojan las siguientes puntuaciones medias: vigor 3,46 sobre 6 (DT 1,05), dedicación 5,16, igualmente sobre 6 (DT 0,97). Y absorción, 3,59, también sobre 6 (DT 1,18). El nivel global de engagement de nuestros estudiantes de enfermería se sitúa en 4,1 sobre 6. Destacan los niveles en la dimensión dedicación, con valores medios que los sitúan entre las categorías casi siempre y siempre, lo que implica una altísima vocación hacia sus estudios. Las calificaciones del Practicum II-III han mostrado asociación con las dimensiones vigor (p&lt;0,008) y absorción (p&lt;0,036) del engagement. No lo han hecho las calificaciones del Practicum I (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;36(9): 570-577, sept. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Engagement y resultados académicos de los estudiantes de grado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9920^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
