<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102641</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychopathology and executive functions in cocaine addicts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to assess the presence of psycho-pathological symptoms in a sample of cocaine addicts and to examine the relationship between these symptoms and neuropsychological performance on executive functioning tasks. Fifty treatment-seeking outpatients for cocaine addiction participated. The EuropASI, the SCL-90-R, the BDI and a neuropsychological protocol, comprising different tasks sensitive to the detection of alterations in different components of the executive functions, were collected for each subject at the beginning of treatment. Results showed that at least 26% of the sample scored above the psycho-pathological risk cutoff of the dimensions of the SCL-90-R and 81.6% showed depressive symptoms at treatment entry assessment. Only a higher level of depression and phobic anxiety were associated with attentional difficulties and information processing speed. There were no significant associations between other psychopathological dimensions and neuropsychological test performance scores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramón Fernández-Hermida, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Rodríguez, Olaya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Secades-Villa, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Hervás, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la presencia de alteraciones psicopatológicas en una muestra de adictos a la cocaína y examinar la relación existente entre estas alteraciones y el rendimiento neuropsicológico en tareas de funcionamiento ejecutivo. La muestra se compuso por 50 participantes que habían solicitado tratamiento por su adicción a la cocaína. En el inicio del tratamiento, se aplicó a cada sujeto el EuropASI, el SCL-90-R, el BDI y una batería neuropsicológica compuesta por varias tareas sensibles a la detección de alteraciones en diferentes componentes de las funciones ejecutivas. Los resultados mostraron que al menos un 26% de la muestra puntuaba por encima del punto de corte de riesgo psicopatológico establecido en cada una de las escalas del SCL-90-R y que el 81,6% presentaba síntomas depresivos. Un mayor nivel de depresión y de ansiedad fóbica se relacionaron con la presencia de dificultades atencionales y de velocidad de procesamiento de información. No se encontraron relaciones estadísticamente significativas entre el resto las dimensiones psicopatológicas evaluadas y la ejecución en las distintas tareas neuropsicológicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(3): 720-727, oct.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102641</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicopatología y funciones ejecutivas en adictos a la cocaína</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
