<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163858</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A case report of giant cystic leiomyoma mimicking an ovarian tumour</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 73-year-old woman was referred to our service due to incidental discovery of a large abdominal mass. Abdominal ultrasound showed a mixed tumour, predominantly cystic, occupying the whole abdomen from the pelvis to the xyphoid process. Abdominal and pelvic computed tomography revealed a cystic mass that filled the abdomen. The preoperative diagnosis was ovarian mucinous cystadenoma/cystadenocarcinoma. Surgical treatment was indicated. The definitive diagnosis was leiomyoma with cystic degeneration. Leiomyomas are common tumours in women but if they have degenerative changes they may cause confusion in the initial diagnosis, as they can simulate a cystic adnexal mass (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vela Lete, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Campo, Leyre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalobos Salguero, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Rubio, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Cubillos, Mario Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón y Cajal, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Aragón, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente de 73 años remitida por hallazgo casual de una gran masa abdominal. En la ecografía abdominal se observó una tumoración mixta de predominio quístico que ocupaba todo el abdomen, desde la pelvis hasta el apéndice xifoides. La TC abdómino-pélvico informó de una masa quística que ocupaba todo el abdomen en relación con cistoadenoma/cistoadenocarcinoma mucinoso ovárico, por lo que se indicó tratamiento quirúrgico y el diagnóstico definitivo fue un leiomioma dependiente del útero con degeneración hidrópica. Los miomas uterinos son tumoraciones frecuentes en la mujer, sin embargo si presentan cambios degenerativos, puede ser difícil su diagnóstico inicial, al simular patología anexial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);59(3): 166-169, mayo-jun. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163858</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de un caso de un leiomioma quístico gigante que simula una tumoración ovárica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30131^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4796^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3556^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31529^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31529^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3556^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
