<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141808</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Activities to catch up and vaccinate the susceptible population in Valencian Community, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Eliminating measles and rubella and preventing congenital rubella infection plan of WHO highlighted the need to assess vaccination coverage and develop strategies to improve it and eliminate pockets of low immunization coverage. It exists evidence about the potential role of immunization information systems to improve coverage. The aim of this article is to describe the actions taken from the Vaccine Information System of Valencian Community addressed to improve the vaccination coverage. The Vaccine Information System is a comprehensive information system that allows the management of vaccination programs. It is connected to other systems so that decisions related to vaccinations as clinical and epidemiological management is facilitated. Regarding the role in improving vaccination coverage, the Vaccine Information System facilitates the implementation of all alternatives that have been proven effective: calculate coverage and feedback of results, active recruitment, cooperate with the epidemiological surveillance and logistics management of vaccines. We can conclude, therefore, that the Vaccine Information System is a useful tool to improve vaccination coverage and thus contribute to the elimination of measles and rubella (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pastor-Villalba, Eliseo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portero-Alonso, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alguacil-Ramos, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Ivorra, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lluch-Rodrigo, Jose A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Organización Mundial de la Salud en su revisión del Plan de eliminación del sarampión y la rubéola remarcó la necesidad de evaluar las coberturas vacunales y desarrollar estrategias para mejorarlas y eliminar las bolsas de baja cobertura vacunal. Existe evidencia del papel que pueden jugar los sistemas de información vacunal para mejorar estas coberturas. El objetivo del presente artículo es describir las acciones realizadas a partir del Sistema de Información Vacunal de la Comunidad Valenciana en la mejora de las coberturas vacunales. Se trata de un sistema integral que permite le gestión de los programas de vacunación. Está conectado con otros sistemas de manera que se facilita la toma de decisiones relacionadas con las vacunaciones, tanto clínicas como epidemiológicas o de gestión. Respecto al papel que juega en la mejora de las coberturas vacunales, el Sistema de Información Vacunal facilita la realización de todas las alternativas que se han demostrado efectivas: cálculo de coberturas y difusión de resultados, actividades de captación activa, colaboración con los servicios de vigilancia epidemiológica, gestión de la logística de las vacunas. Se puede concluir, por tanto, que el Sistema de Información Vacunal es una herramienta útil para mejorar las coberturas vacunales y contribuir así a la eliminación del sarampión y la rubéola (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(4): 419-426, jul.-sept. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141808</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividades para captar y vacunar a la población susceptible en la Comunidad Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6459^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15342^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29429</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23114^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23114^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
