<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79421</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement in the management of demand in a primary care team</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Demand management and particularly demand with no previous appointment is a challenge that concerns managers and professionals. Although the reasons have been extensively studied, the solution is not simple. Introduction: Since perception of excessive demand was the main reason of dissatisfaction of our professional team, we planned and implemented an organizational change with interventions on professional organization and structure to improve overall management of demand and particularly that generated with no previous appointment, to reduce excessive use and also increase the quality of the care to all the patients of the Primary Care Team (PCT). Material and methods: Detection of the processes to improve. Some of the most important interventions are summarized: multidisciplinary planning; creation of two separate care systems for the scheduled visit and the visit without an appointment; elimination of the bureaucratic aspects of the consultations; development of standards and standardization of performance criteria on visits with and without appointment; enhancing the role of nurses and administrative attention to the population in both the scheduled visit and in the spontaneous visit; changes of location to enhance the doctor-nurse collaboration. Material and methods: A statistical analysis and evaluation of results were performed. Results: A significant reduction was achieved in the total number of visits to the center of those with or without an appointment and in those patients with a high number of visits (both p&lt;0.001). The roles of nurse and administrative were strengthened. The satisfaction surveys of the users and professionals regarding the new system have been positive. Conclusion: A multidisciplinary strategy, developed and agreed on by the whole team, has a positive influence on demand and improves quality of care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallego-Álvarez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oriach-Alonso, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martos-Molines, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada-Couceiro, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berenguer-Gascón, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gili-Ribes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque-Mellado, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La gestión de la demanda y en particular de la demanda sin cita constituye un reto que preocupa a gestores y profesionales. Aunque los motivos han sido ampliamente estudiados, la solución al problema no es sencilla. Introducción: Dado que la excesiva demanda percibida era el principal motivo de insatisfacción de los profesionales de nuestro equipo, planificamos e implantamos un cambio organizativo con intervenciones sobre profesionales, organización y estructura con el objetivo de mejorar la gestión global de la demanda (en especial la generada sin citación previa), disminuir la hiperfrecuentación e incrementar además la calidad de la atención a todos los pacientes del equipo de Atención Primaria. Material y métodos: Detección de los procesos a mejorar. Material y métodos: Planificación multidisciplinar. Material y métodos: Creación de dos sistemas independientes de atención a la visita programada y a la visita sin cita. Eliminación de los aspectos burocráticos de las consultas. Elaboración de pautas y unificación de criterios de actuación sobre las visitas con y sin cita. Potenciación del rol de los profesionales de enfermería y administrativos en la atención a la población, tanto en la visita programada como en la visita sin cita. Cambios de ubicación para mejorar la colaboración médico-enfermera. Análisis estadístico y evaluación de resultados. Se ha conseguido una disminución significativa del número de visitas totales con o sin cita previa del centro así como las de los pacientes hiperfrecuentadores (ambas con p&lt;0,001). Los roles de los profesionales no facultativos se han reforzado. Las encuestas de satisfacción de usuarios y profesionales con el nuevo sistema son positivas. Conclusión: Una estrategia multidisciplinar, trabajada y consensuada por todo el equipo, consigue incidir de manera positiva sobre la demanda y mejorar la calidad asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(4): 243-252, abr. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79421</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora de la gestión de la demanda en un equipo de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23662^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1077</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
