<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88485</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of Airway Complications Following Lung Transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo describe our experience in airway complications following lung transplant and to suggest a management algorithm, using different tools from the Interventional Pulmonology armamentarium.MethodRetrospective chart review of all airway complications following lung transplant from January 1999 to July 2007.ResultsDuring that period 223 patients underwent lung transplantation, with a total of 345 anastomoses in the airway. Seventy anastomoses (20.23%) had complications requiring endoscopic treatment. The total number of endoscopic interventions were 631 in 52 patients. Thirty three patients had a combination of bronchial stenosis and bronchomalacia. Eighteen patients had bronchial stenosis only and 1 patient had dehiscence of the anastomosis. Balloon dilation was most commonly transiently effective and ultimately 47 patients required stent placement. The most common complication associated with the use of stent was granulation tissue formation, seen in 57.3% of patients. After stent placement, the forced expiratory volume in 1st second (FEV1) improved significantly.ConclusionAirway complications after lung transplant are frequent. Balloon dilation was effective only in a few patients with bronchial stenosis, although the majority ultimately needed a stent. Airway repermeabilization after stent placement improved FEV1. Based on our experience, we propose a management algorithm for airway complications after lung transplant(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Majid, Adnan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baz, Maher</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jantz, Michael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caviedes, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Bussy, Sebastián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Akindipe, Olufemi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">PropósitoDescribir nuestra experiencia en las complicaciones de la vía aérea después del trasplante pulmonar y sugerir un esquema de tratamiento, utilizando diferentes técnicas de broncoscopia intervencionista.MétodoAnálisis retrospectivo de todas las complicaciones en la vía aérea postrasplante pulmonar desde enero de 1999 hasta julio de 2007.ResultadosDurante este periodo, en 223 pacientes se realizó trasplante pulmonar, un total de 345 anastomosis en la vía aérea. En 70 de ellas (20,23%) hubo complicaciones, requiriendo de intervención endoscópica. Se realizó un total de 631 procedimientos en 52 pacientes. Treinta y tres pacientes presentaron la combinación de estenosis bronquial con broncomalacia, 18 pacientes presentaron solo estenosis bronquial y 1 paciente presentó dehiscencia de la anastomosis. En la mayoría de los casos, la dilatación neumática por balón tuvo efectividad transitoria, 47 pacientes requirieron de la instalación de un stent endobronquial. La complicación más común asociada con la utilización de stents fue el tejido de granulación en el 57,3% de los pacientes. Luego de la colocación de stents, el volumen espiratorio forzado en el primer segundo (FEV1) mejoró significativamente.ConclusionesLas complicaciones de la vía aérea después del trasplante pulmonar son frecuentes. En pocos pacientes con estenosis de la vía aérea hubo resolución definitiva con dilatación bronquial neumática, requiriendo la mayoría de la colocación de stents endobronquiales. La permeabilización de la vía aérea por stents endobronquiales demostró mejorar el FEV1 en estos pacientes. Sobre nuestra experiencia, proponemos un esquema de manejo de las complicaciones de la vía aérea postrasplante pulmonar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(3): 128-133, mar. 2011. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88485</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de complicaciones en la vía aérea postrasplante pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1131^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4149^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
