<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89313</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The shadows of evidence based medicien. A narrrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evidence-based-Medicine is the new medical systemic power model. The medical industrial complex is spending heavily todevelop and promote their drugs; "scientific" trials are the weapon used in this war of conquest and the ghost management  allows the pharmaceutical industry to shape the literature in ways that serve its interests. But, in the market for health care: where is the patient? While evidence-based medicine is a noble ideal, marketing-based medicine is the current reality, failing to provide an adequate account of optimal medical practice. Conflicts of interest, ubiquitous in medicine, occur when the interests of clinicians do not align with the interests of their patients. The fundamental ethos of medical practice contrasts sharply with that of ordinary commerce (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Sanos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Medicina Basada en la Evidencia, que es el modelo hegemónico biomédico actual, está sesgado a favor del superintervencionismo polifarmacológico y tecnológico, que olvida muchas veces la complejidad de la vida humana, con sus elementos imprecisos, subjetivos e intangibles, de tal forma que la subjetividad del enfermo se diluye en la pretendida objetividad de signos y cuadros clínicos. El gran emporio económico que sustenta el Complejo Médico-Industrial ejerce una influencia decisiva en la práctica médica, mercantilizando las evidencias científicas, con el consiguiente deterioro de la confianza, la credibilidad e integridad de nuestra profesión. ¿Se practica hoy día una medicina legítima, éticamente sin fisuras, diagnóstica y  terapéuticamente eficaz, productora de conocimientos y formalizadora de nuevas prácticas, socialmente racional y justa, viable económicamente y científicamente correcta? (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;14(1): 45-54, ene.-mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89313</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las sombras d ela medicina basada en la evidencia. Una revisión narrativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33125^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28895</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
