<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102637</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social deviance among immigrant adolescents from the former Soviet Union in Israel: Data and risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper describes the adjustment problems of immigrant adolescents from the former Soviet Union (FSU) in Israel and discussed risk factors for these problems. Adolescents from FSU immigrant families, native- and foreign-born, comprised in the last decade between 11% and 10% of their age-group in Israel. Presented are recent public data on education-related problems, substance abuse and delinquency among these adolescents. The data indicate that: a) FSU immigrants are highly over-represented among maladjusted students in schools and among those who drop out of school; b) the use of alcohol and cigarettes is more common among FSU immigrant youth than among Israeli non-immigrant adolescents as is the use of ecstasy; c) the rate of involvement of FSU immigrant adolescents in criminal activity is considerable and surpasses their relative weight in the population. Economic hardships and difficulties to integrate into the new society combine as risk factors for maladjustment and delinquency among FSU immigrant adolescents. However, the decisive factor that determines the extent of their maladjustment is the quality of family functioning &#150; family cohesion and relationships, parental functioning and the support extended to immigrant youths by their parents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mirsky, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desviación social entre adolescentes inmigrantes procedentes de la antigua Unión Soviética en Israel: Datos y factores de riesgo. Resumen: Este trabajo describe los problemas de adaptación de los inmigrantes adolescentes de la antigua Unión Soviética (AUS) en Israel y comenta los factores de riesgo relacionados con estos problemas. En la pasada década, los adolescentes de familias inmigrantes de la AUS, nacidos en su país y en el extranjero, constituían entre el 11 y 10% de su grupo de edad en Israel. Se presentan datos recientes sobre los problemas relacionados con la educación, el abuso de sustancias y la delincuencia entre estos adolescentes. Los datos indican que: a) los inmigrantes de la AUS están sobrerepresentados entre los estudiantes inadaptados en las escuelas y entre los que la abandonan; b) el uso de alcohol y cigarrillos es más común entre los jóvenes inmigrantes de la AUS que entre los adolescentes israelíes no inmigrantes, así como el uso de éxtasis; c) la implicación de los adolescentes inmigrantes de la AUS en actividades criminales es considerable y supera su peso relativo en la población. Las dificultades económicas y de integración en la nueva sociedad se combinan como factores de riesgo para la inadaptación y la delincuencia entre los adolescentes inmigrantes de la AUS. Sin embargo, el factor decisivo que determina el alcance de su inadaptación es la calidad del funcionamiento familiar - cohesión y relaciones familiares, es-tilo parental y apoyo que los jóvenes inmigrantes reciben de sus padres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(3): 675-682, oct.-dic. 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102637</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desviación social entre adolescentes inmigrantes procedentes de la antigua Unión Soviética en Israel: Datos y factores de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7726</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d282^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d73</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14987</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
