<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124823</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pathogenesis of halitosis. Review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Halitosis, or bad breath is a major problem because it can compromise the people relationship life. Often origin is attributed to stomach or nasal or lung problems. However, we know that up to 90 % of cases, the source is in the oral cavity, and so dominant due to the accumulation of plaque on the dorsum of the tongue "cover tongue". Periodontal disease is also directly related to bad breath, so that the accumulation of plaque, periodontal pockets and/or bleeding are aspects directly related to the problem. From the pathogenic point of view, the dietary and bacteria proteins, and the own oral tissues proteins, are degraded by the action of bacterial proteases to amino acids. Rich in sulfur amino acids are the maximum responsible of bad breath. In fact the three most closely related products are hydrogen sulfide, methyl mercaptan and dimethyl sulphide. In this update, we review all these aspects and causes more directly related to the problem, also reviewing the pseudohalitosis and halitophobia concepts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estrugo Devesa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jané Salas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero Rey, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La halitosis o mal aliento es un problema importante dado que puede comprometer la vida de relación de las personas. Es frecuente que se atribuya el origen al estómago o a problemas nasales o pulmonares. No obstante, sabemos que hasta en el 90% de los casos, el origen se encuentra en la cavidad oral, y de forma preponderante debido al acúmulo de placa en el dorso lingual "cubierta lingual". La enfermedad periodontal también está directamente relacionada con el mal aliento, de manera que el acumulo de placa, bolsas y/o sangrado son aspectos directamente relacionados con el problema. Desde el punto de vista patogénico, las proteínas de la dieta, las de las bacterias y las de los propios tejidos de la boca, son degradadas por la acción de las proteasas bacterianas hasta aminoácidos. Los aminoácidos ricos en azufre son los máximos responsables del mal aliento. De hecho los tres productos más directamente relacionados son el sulfuro de hidrógeno, el metil mercaptano y el dimetil sulfuro. En la presente revisión repasamos todos estos aspectos y las causas más directamente relacionadas con el problema, revisando igualmente el concepto de halitofobia y pseudohalitosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;30(3): 145-153, mayo-jun. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiopatogenia de la halitosis. Revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10090</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6362^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
