<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128742</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bladder endometriosis: report of 7 new cases and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To describe our experience with bladder endometriosis at the Department of Urology of Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Santiago de Compostela. METHODS: We performed a retrospective analysis of the cases of bladder endometriosis diagnosed during the last 11 years in our hospital, from January 2000 to December 2011. RESULTS: A total of 7 women, with a mean age of 32-year-old have been diagnosed by biopsy of bladder endometriosis. The most common symptoms were dysuria, suprapubic pain, urinary urgency and hematuria. All patients have undergone surgery (5 transurethral resection, 2 partial cystectomy), 6 of them were also treated with post-operative LHRH analogues. CONCLUSIONS: Endometriosis is a common disease in young women, but the involvement of the urinary tract is unusual. There are multiple therapeutic options; despite this there exists a high probability of recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lema Grille, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Gómez, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordeiro González, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puñal Pereira, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Describir nuestra experiencia en el Departamento de Urología del Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Santiago de Compostela en endometriosis vesical. MÉTODOS: Se realiza un análisis retrospectivo de los casos de endometriosis de vejiga diagnosticados durante los últimos 11 años en nuestro hospital, desde enero de 2000 a diciembre de 2011. RESULTADOS: Un total de 7 mujeres, con un promedio de 32 años de edad, ha sido diagnosticadas por biopsia de endometriosis vesical. Los síntomas más frecuentes han sido disuria, dolor suprapúbico, urgencia urinaria y hematuria. Todas ellas han sido tratadas con cirugía (5 con resección transuretral, 2 con cistectomía parcial), en 6 de ellas se asociaron análogos de LHRH en el post-operatorio. CONCLUSIONES: La endometriosis es una enfermedad común en mujeres jóvenes, pero la afectación de las vías urinarias es inhabitual. Existen múltiples posibilidades terapéuticas, pero a pesar de ello es alta la probabilidad de recurrencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(7): 646-649, sept. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128742</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endometriosis vesical: aportación de 7 nuevos casos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52157^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1770^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1770^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4794^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6566^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6566^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
