<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97204</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New dimensions, new addictions: the internet sex adicction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The network is endless: going anywhere, finding anything, being anyone. Typing the word sex on Google gives a figure of 96 million results. The network is changing our way of communication and relation; we can construct space-time coordinates before incompatible. Internet addiction is not recognized as a disorder in DSM-IV-TR or ICD-10. Both types of Internet addiction with sexual content are cybersex and pornography. Cybersex consists in experiencing sexual stimulation while maintaining sexual contact with other person. There is no user profile, it is a widespread behaviour and might have a positive aspect(in some communities, persons with fewer social skills, to spice sex life) and a negative aspect (addiction, loss of control, marital and family problems). Sex is safe, anonymous and without complications. Internet pornography voyeurism allows the visualization of all types of practices, the use of real models not professional and to spy our behaviour through the IP code. These sexual activities on the network seems to be powered by the "Triple A" engine: accessibility, anonymity, affordability. We must assess the individual, the couples and the Internet activities. There is no proven pharmacological or psychological treatment but cognitive behavioural programs and techniques used in other addictions are helpful. There is large comorbidity. The goal of treatment refers to the adaptive use of Internet. Health professionals should be in advance and learn about this kind of behaviours, as well as to disseminate the information appropriately not launching simplistic messages, providing markers and developing studies, research and prevention programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Zaldívar, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iruarrizaga Díez, Itziar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La red es interminable: se puede ir a cualquier sitio, encontrar cualquier cosa, ser cualquier persona. Teclear la palabra sexo en google arroja 96 millones de resultados. La redestá cambiando nuestra forma de comunicarnos y relacionarnos, nos permite construir coordenadas espacio-temporales antes incompatibles. La adicción a Internet no está reconocida en la actualidad como un trastorno en el DSM-IV-TR ni en la CIE-10. Las dos modalidades de adicción a internet con contenido sexual serían el cibersexo y la pornografía. En el cibersexo se experimenta estimulación sexual mientras se mantiene contacto sexual con otra persona. No existe un perfil de usuario, es una conducta extendida y puede tener su aspecto positivo (para determinadas comunidades, para personas con menos habilidades sociales, para condimentar la vida sexual) y su aspecto negativo (adicción, pérdida de control, problemas de pareja y familiares). Es un sexo seguro, anónimo, sin complicaciones. La pornografía en Internet permite el voyeurismo, la visualización de cualquier tipo de prácticas, el uso de modelos reales no profesionales y el espionaje de nuestras conductas a través de los códigos IP. Estas actividades sexuales en la red parecen estar alimentadas por el motor "Triple A": accesibilidad, anonimato, asequibilidad. Hay que evaluar al individuo, a la pareja y las actividades en Internet. No hay tratamiento psicológico ni farmacológico probado pero los programas cognitivos conductuales y técnicas usadas en otras adicciones son provechosas. Existe una gran comorbilidad. El objetivo del tratamiento es el uso adaptativo de Internet. Los profesionales de la salud debemos anticiparnos y aprender sobre estas conductas, diseminar adecuadamente la información para no lanzar mensajes simplistas, proporcionando marcadores y desarrollar estudios, investigaciones y programas de prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;18(3): 255-268, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97204</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas dimensiones, nuevas adicciones: la adiccional al sexo en internet</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33534^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
