<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163532</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Granular parakeratosis: a rare entity. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Granular parakeratosis is a rare entity that results from a disorder of keratinization, producing an epidermal thickening of the stratum corneum. The etiology is unknown although some factors, such as irritating agents, have been implicated. We present a case of granular parakeratosis associated with an irritating agent (a deodorant) in both axillae of a 31-year-old woman. She did not respond to therapy with corticosteroid and antifungal agents but the GP resolved spontaneously when use of the deodorant was stopped (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, Norberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Cuadra, Juan Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La paraqueratosis granular axilar es una entidad poco frecuente debida a una alteración del proceso de queratinización, lo que produce un engrosamiento de la epidermis a expensas de la capa córnea. La etiología es desconocida, implicándose, entre otros, a agentes irritantes. Presentamos un caso de paraqueratosis granular axilar en una mujer de 31 años, asociada a un posible factor irritante, el desodorante, localizada en ambas axilas, sin mejoría ante el tratamiento farmacológico (corticoides y antifúngico) y con remisión completa tras la retirada del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;50(3): 196-197, jul.-sept. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paraqueratosis granular, una rara entidad. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10430^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10430^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30695^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10430^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30695^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
