<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151671</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Caregivers´perception of patients´ cognitive déficit in schizophrenia and its influence on their quality of life</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: The aim of the study was to explore the relationship between the caregivers&#146; perception of patients&#146; cognitive deficits (i.e., neurocognition and social cognition) and their quality of life (QoL), after adjusting on clinicians&#146; assessment of neurocognitive deficits and sociodemographic confounding factors. Methods: The study included 253 patients with schizophrenia and their caregivers from public mental health clinics in Bolivia, Chile, and Peru. The caregivers&#146; perception of patients&#146; neurocognitive and social cognitive deficits was assessed using the the GEOPTE scale, caregivers&#146; QoL was assessed using the schizophrenia caregiver quality of life questionnaire (S-CGQoL) and clinicians&#146; ratings of patients&#146; neurocognitive deficits was based on the cognitive factor of the positive and negative syndrome scale for schizophrenia (PANSS). Results: The degree of agreement between caregivers&#146; perception and health care professionals&#146; assessment of cognitive deficit of patients with schizophrenia was moderate. Caregivers&#146; perceptions of neurocognitive and social cognitive deficits were significantly associated with their QoL, contrary to clinicians&#146;  assessment. Conclusions: Caregivers&#146; perception of patients&#146; cognitive deficit was significantly associated with their QoL. The caregivers&#146; perception regarding patients&#146; neurocognition and social cognition may enrich the knowledge of clinicians on patients and is important to be considered by clinicians to improve caregiver&#146;s QoL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urzúa, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caqueo Urizar, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boyer, Laurent</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el objetivo fue explorar la relación entre la percepción de los cuidadores respecto a los déficits cognitivos de los pacientes (neurocognición y cognición social) y su calidad de vida (CV), una vez ajustados los modelos con variables de confusión como la evaluación neurocognitiva médica y variables sociodemográficas. Método: incluyó a 253 pacientes con esquizofrenia y sus cuidadores de servicios de salud pública en Bolivia, Chile y Perú. La percepción de los cuidadores respecto a los déficits neurocognitivos y cognición social de los pacientes se evaluó mediante la escala GEOPTE, la CV de los cuidadores mediante el S-CGQoL y la valoración de los médicos fue evaluado con el factor cognitivo de la Escala PANSS. Resultados: el grado de acuerdo entre la percepción de los cuidadores y evaluación de los profesionales respecto al déficit cognitivo de los pacientes fue moderado. La percepción de los cuidadores respecto a los déficits neurocognitivo y de cognición social presentó una asociación significativa con su CV, contrariamente a la evaluación de los médicos. Conclusiones: la percepción de los cuidadores respecto a los déficits neurocognitivos y de cognición social puede enriquecer el conocimiento de los clínicos, siendo de importancia para mejorar la CV del cuidador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);28(2): 150-155, mayo 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de los cuidadores del déficit cognitivo de pacientes con esquizofrenia y su influencia en la calidad de vida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33522^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33522^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1863</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33522^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
