<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88479</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Esophageal dilation as principal of neurological manifestation of congenital chickenpox embryopathy: about a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The chickenpox virus is known for its neurotropism and its abil ity to reinfection. Prevalence in the pregnant woman is of 0.7 per 1,000 but the risk of embryopathy is of 2%. The effects on the fetus can be lethal during the first 20 weeks of pregnancy. We present a newborn baby with hypotonia, difficulty breathing, and skin scarring with metameric distribution. Suspicion of maternal infection at the 15th week of pregnancy is verified with positive serology in mother and newborn baby. The polymerase chain reaction for chickenpox is positive in the cerebrospinal fluid of the patient. A poor oral tolerance and aspiration pneumoniast and out. The CT shows an esophageal dilatation. The objective manometry shows hypoperistatic esophagus and the biopsy shows signs of myenteric plexus inflammation. Chorioretintis, liver and brain calcifications were also evident. Esophageal hypomotility secondary to an extensive viremia is the main neurological manifestation in our case and determines the prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pineda Caplliure, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchis Calvo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abeledo Mezquita, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparici Gonzalo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El virus de la varicela se caracteriza por su neurotropismo y su capacidad de reinfección. La prevalencia en las mujeres embarazadas es de alrededor de 0,7/1.000, pero el riesgo de embriopatía es del 2%. Los efectos en el feto son mortales en las primeras 20 semanas de gestación. Presentamos el caso de un neonato con hipotonía, dificultad respiratoria y lesiones cicatriciales metaméricas. La sospecha de infección materna en la semana 15 se confirmó con la realización de una serología en la madre y el neonato. La reacción en cadena de la polimerasa para la varicela fue positiva en el líquido cefalorraquídeo del paciente. Destacaba una mala tolerancia oral y la presencia de neumonías por aspiración. La tomografía computarizada mostró una dilatación esofágica. La manometría puso de manifiesto un hipoperistaltismo esofágico, y la biopsia, signos de inflamación en los plexos mientéricos. Se constataron calcificaciones hepáticas, cerebrales y coriorretinitis. La hipomotilidad esofágica secundaria a la extensa viremia es la principal manifestación neurológica en este caso, y condiciona el pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;69(3): 137-139, mar. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88479</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dilatación esofágica como principal manifestación neurológica de la embriopatía por varicela congénita: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4151^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5426^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5031^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31925^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
