<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141367</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Protein needs of critically ill patients receiving parenteral nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: assess whether the current protein intake recommendations may improve the biochemical parameters of critical patients receiving parenteral nutrition. Methods: longitudinal study with three evaluations made (during the first 72 hours, on the 7th and the 14th days of PN). The following tests were applied: albumin, C-reactive protein, prealbumin, total cholesterol, HDL, triglycerides, lymphocytes, and glutathione peroxidase. The severity was determined by SOFA. The statistical analysis included the Spearman and Mann-Whitney tests, as well as ANOVA (analysis of variance). Results: among the 53 patients evaluated, 20 (37.74%) died. The mean calorie was 24.68±9.78 kcal/kg (beginning of PN), 26.49±8.89 kcal/kg (3rd to 7th days of PN), and 30.9±12.19 kcal/kg (7th to 14th days of PN). The mean protein was 1.19±0.44 g/kcal/kg (first 72 hours of PN), 1.29±0.44 g/kcal/kg (3rd to 7th days of PN) and 1.49±0.69 g/kcal/kg (7th to 14th days of PN). Prealbumin, albumin, total cholesterol and HDL were below the reference values, while the CRP levels were high. Throughout the three evaluation times, there was no a significant improvement on the levels of laboratory examinations. A strong and negative correlation was found between SOFA and prealbumin (r=-0.64, p=0.05). Conclusions: the protein offer, according to the traditional recommendations, was not enough to improve the biochemical parameters of critical patients undergoing parenteral nutrition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Freitas, Renata Germano Borges de Oliveira Nascimento</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogueira , Roberto José Negrão</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hessel , Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: evaluar si las recomendaciones de ingesta de proteínas actuales pueden mejorar los parámetros bioquímicos de los pacientes críticos que reciben nutrición parenteral. Métodos: estudio longitudinal con tres evaluaciones realizadas (durante las primeras 72 horas, en el séptimo y los días decimocuarto de nutrición parenteral). Se aplicaron las siguientes pruebas: albúmina, proteína C reactiva, prealbúmina, colesterol total, HDL, triglicé- ridos, linfocitos y glutatión peroxidasa. La gravedad se determinó por SOFA. El análisis estadístico incluyó las pruebas de Spearman y Mann-Whitney, así como ANOVA (análisis de varianza). Resultados: de los 53 pacientes evaluados, 20 (37,74%) fallecieron. La caloría media fue de 24,68±9,78 kcal/kg (comienzo de PN), 26,49±8,89 kcal/kg (tercero-séptimo días de PN), y 30,9±12,19 kcal/kg (séptimo-décimo cuarto días de PN). La proteína media fue de 1,19±0,44 g/ kcal/kg (primeras 72 horas de PN), 1,29±0,44 g/kcal/kg (tercero-séptimo días de PN) y 1,49±0,69 g/kcal/kg (séptimo-decimocuarto días de PN). La prealbúmina, la albú- mina, el colesterol total y la HDL estaban por debajo de los valores de referencia, mientras que los niveles de PCR eran altos. A lo largo de los tres tiempos de evaluación, no hay una mejora significativa en los niveles de los exá- menes de laboratorio. Una correlación fuerte y negativa entre SOFA y prealbúmina (r=-0,64, p=0,05). Conclusiones: la oferta de proteínas, de acuerdo con las recomendaciones tradicionales, no fue suficiente para mejorar los parámetros bioquímicos de los pacientes crí- ticos sometidos a nutrición parenteral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(1): 250-255, jul. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las necesidades proteícas de pacientes en estado crítico que reciben nutrición parenteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23103^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
