<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037224</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consumer perceptions of public health service quality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze consumer perceptions of the quality of the public health service in Málaga (Spain) using adaptations of the SERVQUAL and SERVPERF models. Subjects and method: 400 citizens of the Health District of Málaga, both users and non-users of the public health service. We performed a descriptive study based on a survey using a questionnaire adapted from SERVQUAL and SERVPERF. A multivariate analysis was performed. Results: Citizens gave the quality of public health services a mean score of 3.8337 (on a scale from 1 to 7). Specifically, users of these services gave a score of 3.8932, while non-users gave a slightly lower score of 3.4657. The lowest-rated elements of the public health service were related to organization (coordination between different levels of care, accessibility, the appearance of facilities, ease of processing formal procedures and paperwork, and waiting times). Among the highest rated elements were professionalism and technology. Conclusions: SERVPERF is the most appropriate questionnaire for measuring perceived quality, defined as subjective evaluation of the performance of the attributes of a service. However, there are no standard measurement scales for service quality and consequently these must be adapted to the health sector. Clients perceive the quality of public health services to be average-to-low. Quality was rated higher by users than by non-users</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La presente investigación analiza la calidad del servicio sanitario público en Málaga desde la perspectiva del cliente y adaptando los modelos SERVQUAL y SERVPERF. Sujetos y método: Se incluyó a 400 ciudadanos del Distrito Sanitario Málaga, usuarios y no usuarios de la sanidad pública. Se trata de un estudio descriptivo, basado en la realización de una encuesta a partir de un cuestionario adaptado del SERVQUAL y SERVPERF, con un análisis multivariante. Resultados: El paciente valoró la calidad de la sanidad pública con puntuación media de 3,8337 (en una escala de 1 a 7). Concretamente, la valoración de los usuarios de estos servicios fue de 3,8932, mientras que para los no usuarios fue algo inferior: 3,4657. Los aspectos del servicio con peor valoración están relacionados con la organización (coordinación entre niveles asistenciales, accesibilidad, aspecto de instalaciones, facilidad de trámites y papeleo y tiempo de espera). Entre los mejor valorados destacaron la profesionalidad y la tecnología. Conclusiones: El SERVPERF es el cuestionario más apropiado para medir la calidad percibida, entendida ésta como percepción evaluativa del rendimiento de los atributos del servicio. Sin embargo, no existen escalas estándares para la medida de la calidad del servicio, por lo que necesitamos adaptarlo al sector sanitario. La calidad percibida por los pacientes sobre los servicios sanitarios públicos se califica como media-baja respecto a la mayoría de sus elementos constitutivos, y se observa que la experiencia modifica positivamente la valoración, es decir, los clientes potenciales perciben menor calidad que la que perciben los propios usuarios</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(1): 35-42, ene.-feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La calidad percibida en la sanidad pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24426^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
