<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128977</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Processing of syllables that are prefixes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article reviews experimental data obtained with behavioral methods (reaction times) and event-related potentials on the processing of syllables and prefixes. Syllables are used in Spanish as a mechanism of word pre-activation in the lexical memory and require inhibition of lexical selection. In contrast, prefixes, as a morphological unit &#151; although they are also syllables &#151; produce a facilitating effect on word meaning, this process being free of inhibitory processes. We conclude that the two units employ dissimilar routes and activate a different time-course process. Hypotheses relating these basic discoveries in adults with the child population are tentatively proposed, since these units &#151; syllables and morphemes &#151; constitute basic prelexical units in the acquisition of reading abilities(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuetos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se revisan los datos obtenidos a través de dos tipos de procedimientos experimentales, tiempos de reacción y potenciales relacionados con el evento, en relación con dos unidades lingüísticas, la sílaba y el prefijo. Mientras que las sílabas se utilizan en español como un mecanismo de preactivación de palabras en la memoria léxica y requieren de un procedimiento inhibitorio de selección léxica, los prefijos, como entidad morfológica, aun siendo también sílabas, producen un efecto facilitador del significado de la palabra libre de procesos de inhibición. Se concluye que ambas unidades utilizan vías diferentes y actúan con distinta secuencia temporal. Aunque de manera tentativa, tratamos de avanzar algunas hipótesis que relacionen estos descubrimientos básicos realizados en adultos con la población infantil, en tanto que ambas unidades, sílabas y morfemas, constituyen unidades preléxicas fundamentales en el aprendizaje de la lectura(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);31(1): 28-32, ene.-mar.2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128977</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Procesamiento de sílabas que son prefijos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8258</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29323^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
