<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138184</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing care in hyperbaric oxygen therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hyperbaric medicine emerged from diving to treat decompression, and is being used more and more frequently due to its excellent therapeutic effects in treatments that do not respond to the usual medical and surgical treatments.Hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT), as it is commonly called, is applied inside a chamber that makes it possible to administer oxygen in a pressurised environment. The pathologies treated in a hyperbaric chamber share some degree of hypoxia and the pressurised oxygen acts as a true drug, producing different responses depending on the dose and administration times, and ensuring oxygen levels that are impossible to obtain using other methods. This service requires highly qualified personnel for its proper functioning. The aim of this project is to shed light on the nurse&#146;s role in this service and the specificity of nursing care of patients undergoing this treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cantero Díaz, Iria Flavia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Surgida dentro del ámbito del buceo para tratar casos de descompresión, la medicina hiperbárica se utiliza cada vez más por sus excelentes efectos terapéuticos en enfermedades refractarias a los tratamientos médicos y quirúrgicos habituales. La oxigenoterapia hiperbárica (OHB), como se denomina comúnmente, se aplica en el interior de una cámara que permite la administración de oxígeno en ambiente presurizado. Las patologías tratadas en cámara hiperbárica tienen como común denominador algún grado de hipoxia y el oxígeno presurizado actúa como un auténtico fármaco produciendo diferentes respuestas en función de las dosis y los tiempos de administración y garantizando unos niveles de oxigenación imposibles de conseguir por otros métodos. Este servicio requiere personal especialmente cualificado para su correcto funcionamiento. El propósito de este trabajo es dar a conocer el papel que desempeña una enfermera en este servicio y la especificidad del cuidado enfermero de pacientes con este tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;15(2): 10-16, mar. 2012. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138184</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidado enfermero en hiperoxigenoterapia hiperbárica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7110^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7110^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7110^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d874^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1491</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
