<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10843</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic requirements in active ulcerative proctitis: A single-centre study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Ulcerative proctitis (UP) presents distinctive clinical characteristics, outcomes and therapeutic approaches as compared to left-sided and extensive ulcerative colitis (UC). Aim: To describe the current therapeutic requirements and clinical outcomes in patients with active UP. Methods: Retrospective observational study conducted in a referral IBD centre. Patients with UP in follow-up between 1989 and 2014 were included. The clinical characteristics, as well as the different treatments and drug formulations administered to treat flares, were recorded. Results: Out of 687 UC patients, 101 patients (15%) with UP were included. Median follow-up was 8 years (IQR 3-14) and 49% of patients presented disease activity during the study period. Topical mesalazine monotherapy (90%) was the most commonly administered treatment for disease activity (mostly as suppositories), followed by topical steroids (47%) and oral mesalazine (56%) in monotherapy or combination therapy. Only 14% and 16% of patients required oral prednisone and beclomethasone, respectively. Conclusions: In clinical practice, active UP presents mostly favourable outcomes. Mesalazine suppositories are by far the most used treatment for these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domènech, Eugeni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobatón, Triana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larraín, Macarena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, Noemí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mañosa, Míriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabré, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calafat, Margalida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La proctitis ulcerosa (PU) presenta unas características clínicas, evolutivas y terapéuticas distintas con respecto a la colitis ulcerosa izquierda o extensa. Objetivo: Describir los requerimientos terapéuticos y la evolución clínica en pacientes con PU activa. Métodos: Estudio observacional retrospectivo realizado en un centro de referencia en EII, en el que se incluyeron pacientes en seguimiento entre 1989 y 2014 con PU. Se registraron las características clínicas, así como los diferentes tratamientos y galénicas utilizados para tratar el brote de actividad. Resultados: De un total de 687 pacientes con colitis ulcerosa se incluyeron 101 (15%) con PU. La mediana de seguimiento fue de 8 años (RIC 3-14). El 49% de los pacientes presentó actividad de la enfermedad durante el período a estudio. La monoterapia con mesalazina tópica (90%) fue el tratamiento más utilizado para la actividad de la enfermedad (predominantemente en forma de supositorios), seguida de los esteroides tópicos (47%) y la mesalazina oral (56%) en monoterapia o en terapia combinada. Solo el 14 y el 16% de los pacientes requirieron prednisona oral y beclometasona, respectivamente. Conclusiones: En la práctica clínica, los supositorios de mesalazina son el tratamiento más utilizado en pacientes con PU activa, presentando la mayoría de ellos una evolución clínica favorable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;40(10): 663-668, dic. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Requerimientos terapéuticos en el tratamiento de los brotes de la proctitis ulcerosa. Estudio unicéntrico</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
