<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038377</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Partial bilateral rupture of the achilles tendon associated to levofloxacin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fluoroquinolones-associated tendonitis and tendon rupture are well described in the literature but these are not frequently observed and related to the new agents of this group, as levofloxacin. This is probably due to the recent introduction and expansion. Although epidemiological studies are needed to know the frequency of that levofloxacin-induced tendinopathies, case-report could alert to the physicians about this possible severe adverse reaction. We present a case of bilateral Achiles tendonitis with partial spontaneous rupture probably associated to levofloxacin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Moreno, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Parrondo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moar Calvo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lado Lado, F. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tendinitis y rotura de tendón es un efecto indeseado bien conocido para fluoroquinolonas que también puede producirse con las nuevos agentes de este grupo. Aunque no existen muchos casos publicados para levofloxacino, esto es probablemente debido a lo reciente de su expansión. Aunque la descripción de casos no es el mejor método de valoración de la frecuencia de este problema, puede servir para alertar a los clínicos sobre la importancia de este efecto grave cuya frecuencia consideramos que ha sido infravalorada. En esta nota clínica presentamos un caso de rotura bilateral parcial del tendón aquíleo, probablemente asociado a levofloxacino</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;22(1): 28-30, ene. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038377</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rotura parcial bilateral aquílea asociada a levofloxacino</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d134^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23786^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12795^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
