<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158255</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conservative management of liver trauma and its complications: current gold-standard</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The liver is the second most frequently involved organ in abdominal trauma in children. The aim of this study was to review the characteristics of liver traumas (LT) in children, its treatment and complications. Material and methods. Retrospective study of patients with LT treated between 2010-2014. We analyzed data regarding diagnosis, conservative management (CM), complications and treatment. Results. Twenty-four patients of LT with a mean age of 9.8 years (SD: 3.4) were treated at our center. Liver injury degrees according to the Organ Injury Scale of American Association for Surgery of Trauma (AAST) were: grade I (4), grade II (6), grade III (8), grade IV (5) and grade V (1). CT angiography was performed in 23 patients. Four of the six patients with initial hemodynamic instability required blood transfusion; of those, two required angioembolization for active bleeding in extrahepatic locations and a third required damage control surgery. Three patients presented late-onset complications: 2 large size bilomas which underwent spontaneous resolution and a third patient with a right biloma and section of the left bile duct who required a multidisciplinary approach. Median hospital stay was 6 days (r 1-92). With a mean follow-up of 17.75 months (SD: 16.35) (r: 2-57) long-term survival was 96%. The patient who received surgery died due to a post-traumatic brain injury. Conclusion. CM seems to be the treatment of choice in LT regardless of injury degree. Surgery should be reserved for cases refractory to CM due to the associated high mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guillén, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gander, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giné, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloret, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañadas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molino, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El hígado es el segundo órgano más afectado en traumatismos abdominales en edad pediátrica. El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar las características de los traumatismos hepáticos (TH), su tratamiento y complicaciones. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de pacientes con TH atendidos entre 2010 -2014. Analizamos datos referentes al diagnóstico, tratamiento conservador (TC), complicaciones y tratamiento de las mismas. Resultados. Se trataron 24 casos de TH con una edad media de 9,8 años (DS: 3,4). Los grados de lesiones hepáticas según la Organ Injury Scale of American Association for Surgery of Trauma (AAST) fueron: grado I (4), grado II (6), grado III (8), grado IV (5) y grado V (1). Se realizó angio-TC en 23 pacientes. Cuatro de los 6 pacientes que presentaron inestabilidad hemodinámica inicial requirieron transfusión de hemoderivados; de éstos, 2 requirieron angioembolización por sangrado activo extrahepático y un tercero se intervino de forma urgente. Tres pacientes presentaron complicaciones tardías: 2 bilomas de gran tamaño que se resolvieron espontáneamente y un biloma derecho con sección de vía biliar izquierda que requirió un abordaje multidisciplinar. En los 3 casos se trataba de traumatismos de alto grado (2 grado IV, 1 grado V). La mediana de estancia hospitalaria fue de 6 días (r: 1-92). Con una media de seguimiento de 17,75 meses (DS: 16,35) (r: 2-57) la supervivencia global fue del 96%. El paciente que requirió cirugía falleció por el traumatismo craneoencefálico asociado. Conclusiones. El TC parece ser de primera elección en los TH independientemente del grado aunque no está exento de complicaciones. La cirugía debe reservarse para los casos refractarios al TC dada la alta mortalidad que conlleva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;29(1): 19-24, ene. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158255</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento conservador de los traumatismos hepáticos y sus complicaciones: gold-standard actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54689^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24848^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
