<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142061</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethical and legal implications of biomedical research</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The major advances in biomedical research pose ethical and legal problems for the researchers, institutions and companies responsible for these advances. This new vision of their professional task results from the necessary protection of patients&#146; rights and responsibilities, reflected in international documents and specific legislation in distinct countries, which are globally being adopted by transnational research, linked &#151;in turn&#151; to translational research. The pluridisciplinary nature of current biomedical research is reflected in the field of the rights and responsibilities to be protected. Thus, Ethics, Bioethics and the Law started an ineludible and intense dialogue that has even given rise to new areas of knowledge such as Healthcare Law and Biolaw. Personalized medicine constitutes a new healthcare criterion while pharmacogenetics may be a good study model, able to promote deliberation and prudence in decisions. Finally, Health Economics is essential, not only to benefit from its technical experience but also to rediscover the ethics that gave rise to this discipline (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bandrés Moya, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Bueno, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bandrés Hernández, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los grandes avances de la investigación biomédica sitúan a los investigadores, las instituciones y las empresas responsables ante problemas éticos y legales. Esta nueva mirada a su quehacer profesional resulta de la necesaria protección de los derechos y deberes de los pacientes, que se refleja en documentos internacionales y legislaciones específicas en los diferentes países, que de forma globalizada están asumiendo la investigación transnacional, a su vez vinculada a la traslacional. El carácter multidisciplinario de la investigación biomédica actual encuentra reflejo en el ámbito de los derechos y deberes que hay que proteger. Así, la ética, la bioética y el derecho inician un diálogo obligado e intenso que incluso da nombre a nuevas áreas de conocimiento, como son el derecho sanitario y el bioderecho. La medicina personalizada dibuja un nuevo criterio asistencial, y la farmacogenética puede ser un buen modelo de estudio, capaz de promover la deliberación y la prudencia en las decisiones. Finalmente, la economía de la salud resulta imprescindible no sólo por su experiencia técnica, sino para redescubrir la ética que le dio origen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);131(supl.5): 87-90, dic. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142061</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicaciones éticas y legales de la investigación biomédica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10788</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
