<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043844</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frequency of thiopurine S-methyltransferase alleles in different ethnic groups living in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Thiopurine S-methyltransferase (TPMT) metabolizes thiopurine drugs regulating their cytotoxicity and clinical response. TPMT activity is inherited as an autosomal recessive trait and several mutations in the TPMT gene have been identified which correlate with a low activity phenotype. A variable number of tandem repeat within the TPMT promoter has been reported to modulate the levels of this enzyme activity. The allelic variants of the TPMT gene were analyzed in ethnic groups living in Spain. Subjects and method: The frequency of 4 allelic variants of the TPMT gene as well as the genotype in the promoter region were analyzed in 138 Spanish blood donors, 95 gypsies and 51 Basque subjects. Results: In the group of 138 blood donors, we identified: 13 carriers of a mutated TPMT allele (*3A, *3B, *3C), one homozygous TPMT*3B and a compound heterozygote (TPMT*3A/TPMT*3B). In the Basque group, 3 subjects were TPMT*3A carriers and one case was a TPMT*3B heterozygote. In the gypsy group one subject carried a TPMT*3A allele and 3 were compound heterozygotes TPMT*3A/TPMT*3B. The TMPT*3A was the most frequent mutant alelle. As for the polymorphic tandem repeat in the 5' flanking region of the TPMT gene, alleles with 4 or 5 repeats made up the vast majority (96%) of the chromosomes in the control group of Spanish subjects. This figure decreased to 75% in Basques and to 62% in gypsies, in whom 37% of the alleles contained more than 5 tandem repeats. Conclusions: The frequencies of the mutant TPMT alleles observed in the 3 groups are similar to those reported in Caucasian populations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Río, Elisabeth del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baiget, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gich, Ignasi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corominas, Hector</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doménech, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La tiopurina S-metiltransferasa (TPMT) participa en el metabolismo de diversos fármacos. La presencia de diferentes alelos del gen de la TPMT se relaciona con la actividad de dicha enzima. La existencia de un número variable de repeticiones en tándem en la región promotora del gen de la TPMT parece modular la actividad enzimática. En este trabajo se estudian la frecuencia y la distribución de las variantes alélicas del gen de la TPMT en distintos grupos étnicos españoles. Sujetos y método: Se han analizado 4 variantes alélicas del gen de la TPMT y se define el genotipo en la región promotora del gen en población española (n = 138) y en 2 grupos étnicos diferenciados residentes en España: población gitana (n = 95) y población vasca (n = 51). Resultados: En el grupo de 138 donantes de sangre españoles se encontraron 13 heterocigotos de un alelo TPMT mutado (*3A, *3B, *3C), un homocigoto TPMT*3B y un caso de doble heterocigotia TPMT*3A/ TPMT*3B. En la población de origen vasco (n = 51) se detectaron 3 portadores del alelo TPMT*3A y un sujeto heterocigoto para el alelo TPMT*3B. El estudio de la población gitana (n = 95) mostró un individuo con un alelo TPMT*3A y 3 individuos heterocigotos compuestos TPMT*3A/TPMT*3B. El alelo mutante más prevalente fue el TMPT*3A. En referencia al número de repeticiones en tándem de la región 5' del gen de la TPMT, los alelos con 4 o 5 repeticiones representan el 96,4% de los cromosomas en el grupo de control de población española. Esta cifra desciende hasta el 75% en los vascos y hasta un 62% en el grupo de población gitana. En estos últimos, el 37% de los alelos contienen más de 5 repeticiones en la región promotora del gen. Conclusiones: Las frecuencias alélicas del gen de la TPMT observadas en los 3 grupos estudiados han sido similares a las descritas en otras poblaciones caucásicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(11): 410-412, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia y distribución de las variantes alélicas del gen de la tiopurina S-metiltransferasa en distintos grupos étnicos españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5928^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29550^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33906^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23904^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
