<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64204</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: childhood obesity is a health problem of increasing prevalence and mostprominent, not only because of its persistence in the later stages of life but also due to itsrelationship with pathological conditions during childhood and adolescence such as cardiovasculardisease and diabetes.Objective: to ascertain the prevalence of obesity and overweight in 2003 in childrenaged 2 to 14, seen in one paediatric Primary Care office in Fuenlabrada (Madrid) and thetrends of this prevalence, compared to that observed in previous years.Subject and methods: a descriptive cross study of 318 children calculating their bodymass index (BMI) at ages 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 11 and 14. Obesity is defined as BMI &gt; P95 and overweightas BMI &gt; P85, according to the Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)growth charts from the year 2000. Results are matched with those obtained at the sameages in the cohort of 14 year old children followed in a longitudinal study.Results: the prevalence of obesity in children aged 2 to 14 was 16.03% (18.12% inboys and 14.2% in girls). The prevalence of overweight is 14.46% (11.40% in boys and17.15% in girls). Gender differences are not significant in any of the age groups studied,neither in the whole group.Conclusions: the prevalence of obesity and overweight observed in children aged 2 to14 in our practice are very high and similar to that registered in other Spanish regions.The paediatric practices in Primary Care centers should play a relevant role in the prevention and control of obesity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Martín, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albañil Ballesteros, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Cuesta, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la obesidad infantil es un problema de salud cada vez más frecuente y demayor importancia por su persistencia en etapas posteriores de la vida y por su demostradarelación con entidades patológicas en la población infantil y adolescente, tales como enfermedadcardiovascular y diabetes.Objetivo: conocer la prevalencia de obesidad y sobrepeso en 2003 de la población de 2a 14 años atendida en una consulta de pediatría de un centro de Atención Primaria de Fuenlabrada(Madrid), y la variación de esta prevalencia comparada con la presentada en añosprevios.Pacientes y métodos: para determinar las prevalencias de obesidad y sobrepeso se realizaun estudio descriptivo transversal de 318 niños y niñas y se determina su índice de masacorporal (IMC) a los 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 11 y 14 años. Se considera obesidad IMC &gt; P95, y sobrepesoIMC &gt; P85, según tablas CDC 2000. Para conocer la variación de estas cifras se comparancon los obtenidos a estas mismas edades en la cohorte de niños de 14 años que fueseguida longitudinalmente.Resultados: la prevalencia de obesidad en la población de 2 a 14 años es del 16,03%(18,12% en niños y 14,2% en niñas). La prevalencia de sobrepeso fue del 14,46% (11,40%en niños y 17,15% en niñas). Las diferencias entre sexos no son significativas para el totaldel grupo, ni en ninguna de las edades en las que se realizan determinaciones.Conclusiones: la prevalencia de obesidad y sobrepeso en los niños de 2 a 14 años seguidosen nuestra consulta es muy alta y comparable a las más altas de las registradas en otraszonas de España. Las consultas de pediatría de Atención Primaria son un lugar fundamentalen la prevención y el tratamiento de la obesidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;9(34): 219-230, abr.-jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64204</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
