<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049168</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Right hepatectomy and left hepatectomy performed via hand-assisted laparoscopic surgery. Description of an original technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Laparoscopic liver surgery in solid tumors presents a number of difficulties. This type of surgery is indicated especially in tumors of less than 5 cm located in the left lobe and in anterior segments of the right lobe. Access to posterior lesions of the right lobe (segments VII and VIII) and performing major regulated hepatectomies (more than 3 segments) are at present difficult for liver surgeons. Objective. To present a regulated right hepatectomy (RH) and left hepatectomy (LH) performed via hand-assisted laparoscopic surgery (HALS) using an original technique.  Patients and method. RH was performed in a 70-year-old man with hepatic metastases from colorectal carcinoma (pT2N0M1 sigmoid adenocarcinoma). LH was performed in a 44-year-old woman with a 16-cm hemangioma that had shown tumoral growth. Dissection of the hepatic artery was performed between ligations, and the portal vein was sectioned between ligations or with a vascular endostapler. Division of the bile duct and suprahepatic veins was performed with a vascular endostapler. Parenchymal dissection was carried out with a harmonic scalpel and dissection of intrahepatic veins of over 3 mm was performed with a 10-mm Ligasure Atlas.  Results. The operating time for RH was 360 min, with no transfusion or complications, and length of hospital stay was 5 days. The operating time for LH was 240 min, requiring 2 U of blood, with no morbidity and a length of hospital stay of 4 days.  Conclusions. HALS allows major liver resections to be performed with low morbidity and mortality and with the advantages of laparoscopic surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abellán, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Caridad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Conesa, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La práctica de la cirugía hepática laparoscópica (CHL) de los tumores sólidos entraña muchas dificultades y está indicada, sobre todo, en tumores menores de 5 cm localizados en el lóbulo izquierdo y los segmentos anteriores del lóbulo derecho. El abordaje de lesiones posteriores del lóbulo derecho (segmentos VII y VIII) y la realización de hepatectomías mayores regladas (de más de 3 segmentos) son técnicas de difícil aplicación para los cirujanos hepáticos en la actualidad. Objetivo. Presentar una hepatectomía reglada derecha (HD) y otra izquierda (HI) mediante cirugía laparoscópica asistida (CLA), con una técnica original. Pacientes y método. La HD se realizó en un varón de 70 años de edad, con metástasis hepáticas de carcinoma colorrectal (adenocarcinoma de sigma pT2N0M1). La HI se realizó en una paciente de 44 años de edad, con un hemangioma de 16 cm que había presentado crecimiento tumoral. La sección de arteria hepática se realizó entre ligaduras y la vena porta se seccionó entre ligaduras en un caso y con endograpadora vascular en otro. La sección biliar y de venas suprahepáticas se realizó en ambos casos con endograpadora vascular. La sección parenquimatosa se realizó con bisturí armónico y la sección de las venas intrahepáticas &gt; 3 mm se realizó con Ligasure Atlas® de 10 mm. Resultados. En la HD, el tiempo quirúrgico fue 360 min, no precisó transfusión, no hubo complicaciones y la estancia fue de 5 días. En la HI, el tiempo quirúrgico fue 240 min, precisó transfusión de 2 U de sangre, no presentó morbilidad y la estancia fue de 3 días. Conclusiones. La CLA permite realizar resecciones hepáticas mayores con escasa morbimortalidad y las ventajas de la cirugía laparoscópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);80(5): 326-330, nov. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049168</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatectomía derecha e izquierda por laparoscopia asistida. Descripción de un abordaje original</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3139^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6651^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6651^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
