<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97811</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assimilation processes in the late stages of phonological development</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reports a research on late phonological assimilation processes in child language in order to determine the possible stages in their evolution and the variations in relative frequency as a function of directionality (progressive vs. regressive), distance (contiguous vs. non-contiguous), and type of phonemes involved in assimilations (consonants vs. vowels). The corpus analyzed was collected from 240 children ranging in age between three and six years old. The speech samples were obtained in naturalistic settings of spontaneous conversation with the researchers, and were transcribed and analyzed with the tools provided by the CHILDES Project. Results describe a profile with three stages, reflecting the general dynamics of phonological development. Around the age of four, a general reorganization of the phonological system takes place, and the least frequent assimilation processes (progressive, contiguous and intervocalic) tend to disappear earlier. The most frequent assimilation processes (regressive, non-contiguous and inter-consonant) tend to persist as processing errors in the transition to adult speech. These findings show the functional complexity of late assimilation processes, as well as the need for taking it into account when planning clinical intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Diez-Itza, Eliseo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo presenta una investigación de los procesos fonológicos tardíos de asimilación en el lenguaje infantil con el objeto de determinar las posibles etapas en su evolución y las variaciones en su frecuencia relativa en función de la dirección (progresiva vs regresiva), la distancia (contigua vs no contigua) y el tipo de fonemas implicados en las asimilaciones (consonantes vs vocales). El corpus analizado procede de 240 niños entre tres y seis años y las muestras de habla se obtuvieron en situaciones naturales de conversación espontánea y fueron transcritas y analizadas con los instrumentos del Proyecto CHILDES. Los resultados permiten delinear un perfil evolutivo en tres etapas que reflejan la dinámica general del desarrollo fonológico tardío. En torno a los cuatro años se produce una reorganización del sistema fonológico y los procesos de asimilación menos frecuentes (progresivos, contiguos y entre vocales) muestran una tendencia más temprana de resolución. Los procesos más frecuentes (regresivos, no contiguos y entre consonantes) tienden a persistir como errores de procesamiento en la transición al habla adulta. Los datos hallados confirman la complejidad funcional de los procesos tardíos de asimilación y la necesidad de tenerla en cuenta para planificar la intervención clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(2): 193-198, abr.-jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97811</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Procesos de asimilación en las etapas tardías del desarrollo fonológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2713</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6278^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
