<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036449</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement of physical fitness as anti-aging intervention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several recent important studies  have clearly shown that a low physi-calfitness represents a potent risk factor and even a predictor of bothcardiovascular and all-causes morbidity and mortality. As a consequence, physical fitness assessment should be performed at the clinical level since, when properly assessed, it is a highly valuable healt hand life expectancy indicator. Based on the results of fitness assessment in a particular person and knowing his/her life style and daily physical activity, an individually adapted training program can be prescribed. This training program will allow that person to develop his/her maximal physical potential while improving his/her physicaland mental health and attenuating the deleterious consequences of aging. In fact, physical exercise is today proposed as a highly effective means to treat and prevent major morbidity and mortality causes in industrialized countries. Most of these causes are associated with theaging process. In order to be effective, this type of intervention should be directed to improve the aerobic capacity and strength. In addition, it should be complemented with work directed to improve the general coordination and flexibility. Finally, diet optimization and use of nutritional supplements and legal ergogenic aids are key elements to improve the functional capacity and health, all of which is synonymous of antiaging interventions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Porcel, Francisco B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Ruiz, Jonatan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Garzón, Manuel J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Importantes estudios han demostrado recientemente que un bajo nivel de forma física o condición física constituye un potente factor de riesgo y predictor de morbilidad y mortalidad tanto general (todas las causas) como cardiovascular. En consecuencia, la evaluación de la forma física debería ocupar un lugar privilegiado dentro del ámbito clínico ya que, realizada correctamente, constituye un valioso indicador de salud y expectativa de vida. Partiendo de la evaluación de la forma física, y conociendo el estilo de vida y nivel de actividad física que posee una persona, se puede prescribir un programa adecuado de ejercicio físico que permita al sujeto desarrollar su máximo potencial físico, atenuar las consecuencias del envejecimiento y mejorar el estado de salud físico-mental. De hecho, el ejercicio físico se propone hoy día como un medio altamente eficaz para tratar o prevenir las principales causas de morbimortalidad en los países occidentales, la mayor parte de las cuales se asocian al propio envejecimiento. Este tipo de intervención, para ser efectivo, debe tener como objetivo la mejora de la capacidad aeróbica y el aumento de la fuerza, siendo complementado con trabajo enfocado a mejorar la coordinación general y la movilidad articular. Por último, la optimización de la dieta y el uso de suplementos nutricionales y ayudas ergogénicas legales serán elementos clave para aumentar el rendimiento funcional y la salud, todo lo cual es sinónimo de antienvejecimiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(4): 146-155, feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036449</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora de la forma física como terapia antienvejecimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27892^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
