<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132018</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A prospective study of five years about homocysteinemia levels and cardiovascular risk in patients in a hemodialysis unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease is complex and multifactorial. One of the markers known as independent vascular risk factor is homocysteine. In relation to vascular risk, the increase of 5 mmol/l above the normal range, corresponds to an increase of 20 mg/dl above normal cholesterol. In the general population, slightly elevated homocysteine levels (&gt; 15µmol/l), are associated with increased mortality and cardiovascular events. Also, this factor is present in renal patients, at 3-times higher levels than the general population. Mechanisms by which homocysteine is elevated in renal failure are unclear, since renal excretion represents only 1% of its elimination. However, it has been shown that the use daily of membranes of high flux dialysis, slow nocturnal home dialysis, or on-line hemodiafiltration, significantly reduce these amino acid levels. These treatments could achieve a greater reduction in homocysteine levels and reduce the cardiovascular renal morbid-mortality, therefore, it is advisable to measure homocysteine levels in renal patients annually. The aim was to study the vascular risk in our renal patients in a study of five years, according to the homocysteine levels and determine their relationship with modality and time of treatment, age, sex and ethnicity. A prospective observational study of five year was carried out in our dialysis unit. Data about age, sex, ethnicity, type of treatment (hemodiafiltration versus hemodialysis), duration of treatment and homocysteine levels were collected. 115 patients (68 men and 47 women) with a mean age of 59 years were studied. 107 patients were Mediterranean Caucasians, 4 North African Caucasian and 4 African blacks. 54.8% had less than four years in renal treatment. 63% were on hemodialysis, 27% patients were in alternating hemodiafiltration, and 10% in daily hemodialysis. The mean level of homocysteine in males was 23.47 mmol/l, and in women of 24.29 mmol/l. According to the cultural group, homocysteine levels in the third and fourth year of study, were significant in African black patients, with levels of 51.50 and 69.35 mol/l respectively. In the general population, cardiovascular risk is associated with age and sex. However, homocysteine levels versus these variables in our renal study population are not modified. Other differences are marked by ethnic group: lower in blacks and Asians than in Caucasians, while Latin American had intermediate concentrations. This information do not coincide with our findings, because the Caucasian Mediterranean group (most of our patients) had intermediate values at moderate risk and the African black group had higher values, even of the high risk. We conclude that our patients had a moderate level of vascular risk. When relating homocysteine with sex, age, mode and time of replacement therapy no statistical significant relationship was found. However, ethnicity if present significant variations being the African black the group with higher vascular risk with higher levels in the last three years of the study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Párraga Díaz, Mateo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melero Rubio, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sánchez, María Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad cardiovascular es compleja y multifactorial. Uno de los marcadores conocido como factor de riesgo vascular independiente es la homocisteína; el aumento en 5 µmol/l por encima del rango normal equivale, en riesgo vascular, a un aumento de 20 mg/ dl por encima del colesterol normal. En la población general niveles ligeramente elevados de homocisteína (&gt;15µmol/l), se asocian al incremento de la mortalidad y de los eventos cardiovasculares. Este factor también está presente en pacientes renales, siendo sus niveles 3-4 veces superiores a la población en general. Los mecanismos por los que la homocisteína está elevada en la insuficiencia renal no están claros, ya que su excreción renal sólo representa el 1% de su eliminación; si embargo, si está comprobado que la utilización de membranas de diálisis de alto flujo, diálisis lenta nocturna, o hemodiafiltración on-line diarias reducen significativamente los niveles de este aminoácido. Tal vez estos tratamientos, al conseguir una mayor reducción de los niveles de homocisteína, puedan reducir la morbimortalidad cardiovascular renal y, por ello, es aconsejable medir los niveles de homocisteína anualmente en los pacientes renales. Nos planteamos conocer el riesgo vascular de nuestros pacientes renales a lo largo de cinco años, según valores de homocisteína y determinar su relación con modalidad y tiempo en tratamiento, edad, sexo y grupo étnico. Realizamos un estudio observacional prospectivo en pacientes de una unidad renal durante cinco años. Recogimos datos sobre: edad, sexo, grupo étnico, modalidad de tratamiento (hemodiafiltración versus hemodiálisis), tiempo en tratamiento y valores de homocisteína. Estudiamos 115 pacientes, de edad media 59 años, 68 hombres y 47 mujeres; 107 pacientes caucásicos mediterráneo, 4 caucásicos norteafricano y 4 negroide. El 54,8% llevaba menos de 4 años en tratamiento renal. Un 63% estaba en hemodiálisis, 27% en hemodiafiltración alterna y 10% en diaria. El valor medio de homocisteína en varones fue de 23.47 µmol/l y en mujeres 24.29 µmol/l. Los valores de homocisteína en el tercer y cuarto año de estudio según el grupo cultural fueron en pacientes negroides 51,50 y 69,35 µmol/l respectivamente, con significación estadística. En la población general el riesgo cardiovascular se asocia a la edad y el sexo sin embargo, los niveles de homocisteína versus estas variables en nuestra población renal a estudio no se ven modificados. Otras diferencias vienen marcadas por el grupo étnico: menores en raza negra y asiáticos que en personas de raza blanca, mientras que los latinoamericanos tenían concentraciones intermedias. Estas afirmaciones no coinciden con los resultados de nuestro estudio, ya que el grupo caucásico mediterráneo (la mayoría de nuestros pacientes) que presenta valores intermedios con riesgo moderado y el grupo de etnia negroide valores más elevados incluso de riesgo elevado. Concluimos que nuestros pacientes presentaban un nivel moderado de riesgo vascular. Al enfrentar homocisteína con sexo, edad, modalidad y tiempo de tratamiento sustitutivo no encontramos relación estadística significativa. Sin embargo, el grupo étnico si presentaba variaciones significativas siendo el grupo negroide el de mayor riesgo vascular con niveles más elevados en los tres últimos años del estudio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;17(4): 277-282, oct.-dic. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132018</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio prospectivo de cinco años de los niveles de homocisteinemia y riesgo cardiovascular en pacientes de una unidad de hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32322^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32322^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
