<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97202</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic adherence in smoking therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Therapeutic adherence is a complex and multidimensional concept. The percentage of adherence to treatments involving a change in lifestyle, such as quitting smoking, is lower than in other disorders, a fact which has relevant clinical, psychological and economic consequences. This paper aims to review the associated factors with adherence to therapy in smoking treatment. Strategies to enhance therapeutic adherence involve the adequate choice of treatment, to know the smoker´s characteristics, breaking down organizational barriers in health system and the training of health professionals in communication skills with patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador Manzano, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayesta Ayesta, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La adherencia terapéutica es un concepto complejo y multidimensional. El porcentaje de adherencia a los tratamientos que suponen un cambio en los hábitos de vida, como es dejar de fumar, es más bajo que en otros trastornos, lo cual da lugar a consecuencias clínicas, psicológicas y económicas importantes. El presente trabajo pretende hacer un repaso por los factores relacionados con la adherencia terapéutica en el tratamiento del tabaquismo. Las estrategias para aumentar la adherencia terapéutica implican la elección adecuada del régimen terapéutico, conocer las características del fumador, derribar las barreras organizativas del sistema sanitario y preparar al profesional de la salud para conseguir desarrollar habilidades para una mejor comunicación con el paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;18(3): 233-244, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La adherencia terapéutica en el tratamiento del tabaquismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
