<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136195</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Saccular aneurysm of the azygos vein in a patient with azygos accessory fissure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The saccular aneurysm of the azygos vein is an extremely rare condition, which when located in the path of an accesory pulmonary fissure, becomes a diagnostic challenge because it can be mistaken for tumors arising from the accesory pleura, like solitary fibrous tumor of the pleura or mesothelioma. The diagnosis should ideally be done by non-invasive methods such as CT or MR angiographic technique in multiple phases, thus avoiding unnecessary surgical intervention. This case is exceptional because, to our knowledge, it is the first to report both concomitant clinical situations, an aneurysm of the azygos vein in the pathway of its accessory fissure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Elias Artiga, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba Rovira, S. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guedea Martin, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador Adell,  I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El aneurisma de la vena ácigos es extremadamente raro, y cuando se localiza en el trayecto de una cisura pulmonar accesoria plantea un reto diagnóstico ya que puede confundirse con tumores originados en la pleura accesoria, como el tumor fibroso pleural solitario o el mesotelioma. El diagnóstico se debe hacer idealmente mediante métodos incruentos como la TC o RM con técnica angiográfica en varias fases, evitando así una intervención quirúrgica innecesaria. El caso presentado es excepcional dado que se trata del primero publicado en el que coinciden ambas situaciones clínicas, una cisura accesoria de la ácigos con un aneurisma venoso en ella (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);57(2): 167-170, mar.-abr. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aneurisma sacular de la vena ácigos en un paciente con cisura accesoria de la ácigos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1424^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1424^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11422^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11422^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11422^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11422^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1424^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1424^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
