<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122518</identifier>
<setSpec>2013-6889</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Caregivers of our patients, what know about dementia?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether caregivers of patients with dementia are more familiar with the disease than the general population. Method: Cross-sectional study carried out via a 14-question survey related to general aspects of dementia (concepts, clinical presentation, diagnosis, treatment), filled out by two groups: caregivers and general population, unrelated to the clinical field. The proportion of correct and wrong answers  is analysed considering the variables included in the study (group, age, sex, education level). Results: A similar proportion of right answers was found in both groups, caregivers (n = 40) and general population (n = 40) (70% vs. 72%; NSS). However, a higher proportion of correct answers was detected amongst younger individuals and those with a higher education level (86% and 76%; p &lt; 0.01). Regarding the caregivers&#146; group, questions related to clinical presentation and treatment were answered more successfully (77% and 70% were right; p &lt; 0.01). A positive tendency to greater knowledge was found amongst caregivers who belonged to an association without, however, reaching statistical significance for the results (74% vs. 71%; NSS). Conclusions: Caregivers have a similar level of knowledge about dementia compared to the general population. However, a better understanding of the disease seems directly related to age and level of education. Didactic and supportive interventions could help alleviate the caregiver&#146;s burden and would result in better care for the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Carbonell, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivanco Mora, José Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreras Rodríguez, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gago Veiga, Ana Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar si el hecho de ser cuidador principal de un paciente con demencia supone un mayor conocimiento de esta patología. Material y métodos: estudio transversal, llevado a cabo mediante una encuesta autoadministrada de 14 preguntas relacionadas con aspectos generales de la demencia (conceptos, clínica, diagnóstico, tratamiento), realizada a un grupo de cuidadores y a otro de población general, externa al ámbito asistencial. Se analiza la proporción de aciertos y fallos, considerando los factores incluidos en el estudio (grupo, edad, sexo, nivel de estudios). Resultados: el porcentaje de aciertos del grupo de cuidadores (n = 40) y el de la población general (n = 40) fue similar (70 % frente a 72 %; NS). Se ha detectado una mayor proporción de aciertos en los encuestados jóvenes y con estudios superiores (86 % y 76 %; p &lt; 0,01). En el grupo de cuidadores, los bloques con más aciertos fueron el de clínica y tratamiento (77 % y 70 %; p &lt; 0,01), con una tendencia positiva al mayor conocimiento en aquellos que pertenecían a una asociación, sin alcanzar la significación estadística (74 % frente a 71 %; NS). Conclusiones: un mayor conocimiento sobre la demencia parece independiente de ser cuidador de estos pacientes y está más relacionado  con el nivel de estudios y la edad. Sería importante facilitar más información relacionada con la enfermedad para evitar la sobrecarga del cuidador y conseguir una mejor atención del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alzheimer (Barc., Internet);(57): 13-18, mayo-ago. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122518</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué saben sobre la demencia los cuidadores de nuestros pacientes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35153</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
