<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150533</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Can a heart rate monitor shorten the temporary disability of patients with ischemic heart disease?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Usually cardiologists recommend the use of heart rate monitors in selected patients with ischemic heart disease who want to resume a sport activity. It acts as a safety feature that regulates the intensity of exercise. In the same way that a heart rate monitor is a tool that helps to co-ordinate ischemic heart disease with carrying out certain exercises or physical efforts, could it be used as a tool to help reconcile ischemic heart disease for the completion of certain labor efforts? In certain cases in which there is sufficient medical recovery to return to work, but the patient keeps doubting, the use of the heart rate monitor would provide that security that would facilitate the return to work (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Regal Ramos, Raúl Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Es habitual que los cardiólogos recomienden el uso de pulsómetros en determinados pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica que quieren retomar la práctica deportiva. Actúan como un elemento de seguridad que permite regular la intensidad del ejercicio. Al igual que el pulsómetro es una herramienta que ayuda a compatibilizar la cardiopatía isquémica con la práctica de determinados esfuerzos físicos deportivos ¿podría ser una herramienta que ayude a compatibilizar la cardiopatía isquémica con la realización de determinados esfuerzos físicos laborales? En aquellos casos en los que médicamente existe una recuperación suficiente para la reincorporación laboral pero el paciente mantiene dudas al respecto, el uso del pulsómetro podría proporcionarle esa seguridad que facilitase la reincorporación laboral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;61(241): 480-485, oct.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150533</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Puede un pulsómetro acortar la incapacidad temporal de los pacientes con cardiopatía isquémica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55017^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
