<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054656</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of acromioclavicular luxations using Phemister technique. Revision of long term results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and purpose: Many surgical and conservative        treatments have been developed for acromioclavicular        joint injuries through last decades. Nowadays there is        controversy surrounding the management of these        lesions. Despite the abundant literature regarding this        topic there are few articles referring to long-term outcomes        of treatment, and hardly any about Phemister technique        outcomes.        The purpose of this study is to evaluate the long-term        radiological, functional, cosmetic and subjective results        of Phemister technique for acromioclavicular injuries.        Materials and methods: We retrospectively evaluated all        the acromioclavicular joint injuries treated with the Phemister        technique from january 1996 to december 1996.        Radiographic analysis was based on five parameters:        width of acromioclavicular joint, coracoclavicular interspace,        variation of coracoclavicular interspace, elevation of        the lateral end of the clavicle and percentage of elevation        of the lateral end of the clavicle respecting the opposite        acromioclavicular joint.        Functional evaluation was performed with the Imatani        scoring scale. Cosmetic results were analyzed considering the elevation        of the lateral end of the clavicle and the aspect of the scar.        Analog scale was used for rating overall patient satisfaction.        Results and conclusions: Radiological results were very        good in the immediate postoperative evaluation, but        there was 66% incidence of recurrent acromioclavicular        dislocation at a mean of 9 years follow-up.        Only 66% of the patients obtained a satisfactory functional        result.        Cosmetic alterations at 9 years happened in 66% of the        patients, including prominent lateral end of the clavicle        and hypertrophic scar.        Nevertheless the overall patient satisfaction was very good</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corella Montoya, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Espada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Haro, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Capapé, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocampos Hernandez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: A lo largo de la historia se han desarrollado        multitud de tratamientos tanto quirúrgicos como no quirúrgicos.        Hoy en día sigue sin existir acuerdo sobre el tratamiento        de esta patología. A pesar de existir mucha literatura al respecto        muy pocos artículos hacen referencia a resultados a largo plazo y        menos a los resultados específicos obtenidos con la técnica de        Phemister        El objetivo del presente trabajo consiste en evaluar el resultado,        a largo plazo, radiológico, funcional, estético y la satisfacción global        de los pacientes tras la técnica de Phemister.        Material y métodos: Se ha realizado un estudio retrospectivo        sobre el total de intervenciones tipo Phemister realizadas entre el        1 de enero de 1996 y el 12 de diciembre de 1996.        El estudio radiológico se ha realizado mediante cinco parámetros:        La anchura de la articulación acromioclavicular, la distancia coracoclavicular,        el aumento del espacio coracoclavicular, el desplazamiento        vertical de la clavícula y el porcentaje de desplazamiento        vertical de la clavícula respecto a la articulación acromioclavicular.        El estudio funcional se ha realizado con el test de Imatani.        El resultado estético se ha realizado teniendo en cuenta el desplazamiento        vertical de la clavícula y las características de la        cicatriz La satisfacción del paciente se ha estimado mediante una escala        analógica.        Resultado y conclusiones: Radiológicamente se obtiene muy        buen resultado postoperatorio inmediato, pero a los 9 años la        luxación recidiva hasta en un 66% de los pacientes.        Sólo un 66% de los pacientes tienen un resultado funcional        satisfactorio.        Las alteraciones estéticas a los 9 años ocurren en un 66% de los        pacientes, con prominencia del extremo distal de la clavícula y        con cicatrices hipertróficas.        Sin embargo, la satisfacción objetiva de los pacientes es muy buena</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;4(3): 157-166, jul.-sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054656</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de las luxaciones acromioclaviculares con la técnica de Phemister. Revisión de resultados a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13164^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d179^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
