<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044957</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PurposeThe valproic acid is a drug used frecuently in the pediatrichospital studied and it is used in the main morbidity causesin Mexico. This study was performed to detect the adversereactions, to evaluate the relationships benefit/risk, todetermine its imputability, severity and clinical significationwith the objetive to prevent and minimize the adversereactions and the aim to promote the valproic acid usepolices.MethodsA retrospective study was performed (2002) in threeclinical services, analyzing 425 clinical histories and thepharmacy files, obtaining different data, such as, incidenceand frequency of adverse reactions (AR), imputability andseverity-clinical signification of AR and relationshipbenefit/riskResultsThe incidence and frecuency of adverse reactions was0.263 and 6.68%. The main adverse reactions werehematologic and dermatologic reactions. The imputabilitywas 46% probable, 29% definite and 25% possible.The severity and clinical significations of adverse reactionswas 57% moderate and 32% serious, mainly.Therelationship benefit/risk was 47 cases is same to oneand 40 cases was less than one.ConclusionsThis study permitted to have data both incidence andfrequency of valproic acid adverse reactions, in mexicanpediatric patients, moreover to know some indicators inrelation with benefit and risk of utilization of valproic acid,with the objetive to support the rational use of this drug</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chamorro Cevallos, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Tabche, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Oliván, Leobardo Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Téllez-López, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoDado que el ácido valproico es uno de los medicamentosmás empleados en el hospital pediátrico en estudio y esutilizado en una de las principales causas de morbilidad en México, se realizó este estudio para detectar sus reacciones adversas, valorar la relación beneficio/riesgo, determinar su imputabilidad, gravedad y significancia clínica, con el objetivo de prevenir o minimizar las reacciones adversas, ycon la finalidad de promover políticas del uso de éste. Material y Método Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo (2002) en 3 Servicios Clínicos. Se analizaron 425 expedientes clínicos y notas defarmacia, obteniéndose datos de incidencia y frecuenciade reacciones adversas (RA), imputabilidad y gravedad significancia clínica de las RA y la relación beneficio/riesgo.ResultadosLa incidencia y frecuencia de RA fue 0.263 y 6.68%,principalmente hematológicas y dermatológicas.La imputabilidad: 46% probables, 29% definidas y 25%posibles. La gravedad y significancia clínica: 57%moderadas y 32% graves, principalmente. Relación beneficio-riesgo: 47 casos igual a 1.0 y 40 casosmenor a 1.0ConclusionesEste estudio permitió tener datos de incidencia yfrecuencia de reacciones de ácido valproico en pacientesmexicanos, conocer algunos indicadores relacionadosal beneficio-riesgo, con la finalidad de apoyar el uso racional de éste en el hospital</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;7(1): 8-14, ene.-mar. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de farmacovigilancia de ácido valproico en tres Servicios Clínicos de un Hospital Pediátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31194^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30279^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
