<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2320</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Towards a new anthropological classification of mental disorders in black African immigrants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study, the authors carry out a new classification of the mental problems presented by black African immigrants settled in the province of Almería (Spain). In many of these cases, symptom severity is such that they eventually require admission to the Mental Health Unit of the Hospital de Poniente in order to be treated. In this anthropological classification, two medical models, the biomedical and the traditional African, and two divergent points of view, that of mental health professionals (etic) and that of the affected immigrants and the members of their local networks (emic), become intertwined. On this basis, three clinical profiles are described: ancient madness or negative syndrome, modern madness or positive syndrome, and toxic madness or mixed syndrome. The etiology of each of these three types, its mode of presentation, symptomatology, progress, prognosis, therapeutic itinerary, and its effect on the social network of reference are described (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Checa y Olmos, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Allera, Pedro Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo los autores realizan una novedosa clasificación de las problemáticas mentales que presentan los inmigrantes negroafricanos asentados en la provincia de Almería (España). Muchos de estos cuadros presentan tal gravedad sintomática que finalmente precisan de un ingreso en la Unidad de Salud Mental del Hospital de Poniente, para allí afrontar el comienzo de su tratamiento. En esta clasificación antropológica se entrecruzan dos modelos médicos, el biomédico y el tradicional africano, y dos miradas divergentes, la de los profesionales de salud mental (etic) y la de los inmigrantes afectados y los integrantes de sus redes locales (emic). Partiendo de esta base, se describen tres cuadros diferentes: locura ancestral o síndrome negativo, locura moderna o síndrome positivo y locura tóxica o síndrome mixto. En cada una de estas tres modalidades se especifica su etiología, modo de presentación, sintomatología, evolución, pronóstico, itinerario terapéutico y efecto en la red social de referencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;37(132): 457-475, jul.-dic. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2320</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hacia una nueva clasificación antropológica de las alteraciones mentales de los inmigrantes negroafricanos</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
