<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61698</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of Cushing's disease. transsphenoidal surgery and pituitary radiotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Transsphenoidal surgery is currently considered the treatment of choice for Cushing&#146;s disease. Initial remission is achieved in approximately 70-85%, but 10-15% of patients with remission will suffer a recurrence months or years later. Pituitary irradiation has been used as a therapeutic tool for many years. Nowadays, this option is considered a second-line treatment, to be used when there is postsurgical persistence or recurrence of the disease. The present article reviews the surgical approaches, remission rates reported by different groups, prognostic factors, and the most frequent complications after transsphenoidal surgery. We also review the different techniques that can be used for pituitary irradiation, as well as the efficacy and morbidity reported for each of these techniques in patients with Cushing&#146;s disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estrada García, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lamas Oliveira, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía transesfenoidal se considera, a día de hoy, el tratamiento de primera elección en la enfermedad de Cushing. La curación inicial se consigue en aproximadamente el 70-85% de los casos, pero entre los pacientes con remisión inicial el 10-15% sufrirá una recidiva meses o años después. La irradiación de la hipófisis se ha utilizado como tratamiento de la enfermedad de Cushing desde hace muchos años. Hoy en día se suele considerar un tratamiento de segunda línea, cuando la enfermedad persiste o recidiva tras la cirugía. En este trabajo revisamos las vías de abordaje quirúrgico, las tasas de curación comunicadas por diferentes grupos, los factores pronósticos y las complicaciones quirúrgicas más habituales, así como las distintas técnicas disponibles para la irradiación de la hipófisis, y los resultados y las complicaciones obtenidos hasta la fecha con cada una de ellas en pacientes afectos de enfermedad de Cushing (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;56(3): 123-131, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61698</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la enfermedad de Cushing. Cirugía transesfenoidal y radioterapia hipofisariaTratamiento de la enfermedad de Cushing. Cirugía transesfenoidal y radioterapia hipofisaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13485^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3500^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38634^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11335^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
