<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137981</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9512</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) in adolescents: ineffective or ignored?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ECT is a much maligned therapy that generates strong opinions and feelings, particularly about its use in adolescents. This article reviews the data available about the effectiveness of ECT in adolescents and provides information to clinicians about the current practice of this treatment. Results suggest that ECT is a treatment rarely used but which is safe and effective in adolescents with severe mood disorders, particularIy psychotic depression and bipolar disorder. Many of these patients often receive several trials of medication or combinations of drugs, psychotherapy, develop severe side effects, risk suicide, and suffer considerable impairment. Because it is seldom used- many child psychiatrists have limited experience, knowledge and skills about ECT. As a result, ECT can be ignored or not considered as a valid treatment option (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rapado Castro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soutullo Esperón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Suárez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El TEC es una terapia que ha sido denigrada y que genera diversas opiniones y emociones, sobre todo en relación con su uso en los jóvenes. Este artículo revisa los datos existentes sobre la eficacia del TEC en adolescentes y contribuye información a los clínicos sobre la práctica actual de esta terapia. Los resultados sugieren que el TEC es un tratamiento que se usa raramente pero que es seguro y eficaz en adolescentes con trastornos del humor severos, sobre todo depresión psicótica y trastorno bipolar. Muchos de estos pacientes a menudo reciben diferentes medicaciones y combinaciones de ellas, psicoterapia, desarrollan efectos secundarios serios, tienen riesgo de suicidio y sufren importantes repercusiones en su vida diaria. La mayoría de los psiquiatras infantiles y del adolescente tienen experiencia, conocimientos y habilidades sobre el TEC que son muy limitados. Como resultado, el TEC puede ser ignorado o no considerado como una opción terapéutica valida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. infanto-juv;21(4): 229-237, oct.-dic. 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137981</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia electroconvulsiva (TEC) en adolescente: ¿ineficaz ignorada?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4637^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30515^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
