<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113225</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of haemoperfusion in the treatment of the severe septic patient: an update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Haemoperfusion is an extracorporeal technique that removes endotoxin and/or inflammatory mediators by means of an adsorptive mechanism during the passage of the blood through a porous filter. Most of the studies in the literature use polymyxin B as the adsorptive agent. This treatment is based on the assumption that the removal of endotoxin and inflammatory mediators from the circulation attenuates the inflammatory response in sepsis. This review summarizes the theoretical basis, and the experimental and clinical results published to date with the use of haemoperfusion. Although most of the studies show positive results, some doubts have arisen about the suitability of the methods described (small number of cases, low quality of the experimental design, and excessive mortality in the control groups). There are also some inconsistencies regarding the theoretical basis of its use (lack of positive effects after the removal of endotoxin from the circulation using alternative mechanisms, discrepancies regarding the best moment to initiate the therapy, unexplained beneficial effects in the absence of increased endotoxin levels). It is the opinion of the authors that haemoperfusion represents a promising therapy for the treatment of sepsis, but consider that its usefulness requires confirmation in well designed studies before being included in protocols(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pestaña, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Higuera, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padrón, O. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldecoa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemoperfusión es un procedimiento extracorpóreo que consiste en la retirada de endotoxina y/o mediadores inflamatorios por un mecanismo de adsorción durante el paso de la sangre por un filtro específico. La mayor parte de los estudios publicados han empleado la polimixina B como adsorbente. Este tratamiento se basa en la premisa de que la eliminación de endotoxina y mediadores de la circulación atenúa la respuesta inflamatoria en la sepsis. Se revisan las bases teóricas y los resultados clínicos publicados con el uso de la hemoperfusión. Si bien la mayoría de los estudios que emplean esta técnica presentan resultados positivos, existen dudas acerca de la idoneidad de los métodos empleados (grupos pequeños, baja calidad en el diseño de los estudios, mortalidad excesiva en los grupos control). También existen inconsistencias en la base teórica de su uso (ausencia de beneficios tras la eliminación de endotoxina por otros mecanismos, discrepancias en el momento de iniciar la terapia, aparente utilidad en enfermedades sin elevación de endotoxina). Los autores opinan que la hemoperfusión es prometedora en el tratamiento de la sepsis, pero requiere su confirmación en estudios bien diseñados antes de ser incluida en los protocolos habituales de tratamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(6): 336-343, jun.-jul. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113225</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la hemoperfusión en el tratamiento del paciente séptico grave. Actualización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11549^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29409^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29409^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4809^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29409^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29409^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4809^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4809^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d330^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
