<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117860</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The condition of the cardiovascular prevention in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: In Spain, where cardiovascular diseases are the leading cause of death, control of their risk factors is low. This study analyzes the implementation of cardiovascular risk (CVR) assessment in clinical practice and the existence of control objectives amongst quality care indicators and professional incentive systems. Method: Between 2010 and 2011, data from each autonomous community were collected, by means of a specific questionnaire concerning prevalence and control of major CVR factors, CVR assessment, and implementation of control objectives amongst quality care indicators and primary care incentive systems. Results: Fifteen out of 17 autonomous communities filled in the questionnaire. CVR was calculated through SCORE in 9 autonomous communities, REGICOR in 3 and Framingham in 3, covering 3.4 to 77.6% of target population. The resulting control of the main CVR factors was low and variable: hypertension (22.7-61.3%), dyslipidemia (11-45.1%), diabetes (18.5-84%) and smoking (20-50.5%). Most autonomous communities did not consider CVR assessment and control amongst quality care indicators or incentive systems, highlighting the lack of initiatives on lifestyles. Conclusions: Variability exists in cardiovascular prevention policies among autonomous communities. It is necessary to implement a common agreed cardiovascular prevention guide, to encourage physicians to implement CVR in electronic clinical history, and to promote CVR assessment and control inclusion amongst quality care indicators and professional incentive systems, focusing on lifestyles management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Nuñez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago, Ana de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobos, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armario, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Royo Bordonada, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brotons, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablo, Carmen de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sans, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizcano, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: En España, donde las enfermedades cardiovasculares constituyen la primera causa de muerte, el control de factores de riesgo es bajo. Este estudio analiza la implantación de la valoración del riesgo cardiovascular (RCV) en la práctica clínica y la existencia de objetivos de control entre los indicadores de calidad asistencial y los sistemas de incentivación profesional. Método: Entre 2010 y 2011, mediante un cuestionario diseñado ad hoc, se recogió información de cada Comunidad Autónoma (CCAA) sobre prevalencia y control de los principales factores de RCV, y valoración del RCV y objetivos de control entre los indicadores de calidad y los sistemas de incentivación de Atención Primaria. Quince de las 17 CCAA respondieron al cuestionario. Resultados: El RCV se calcula con SCORE en 9 CCAA, REGICOR en 3 y Framingham en 3, con coberturas del 3,4 al 77,6%. El control de los factores de RCV fue en general bajo y variable: hipertensión (22,7-61,3%), dislipidemia (11-45,1%), diabetes (18,5-84%) y tabaquismo (20-50,5%). Muchas CCAA no incluyeron el RCV entre los indicadores de calidad asistencial o los sistemas de incentivación, escaseando las iniciativas sobre estilos de vida. Conclusiones: Existe variabilidad en las políticas de prevención cardiovascular entre las CCAA. Convendría extender la implantación de una guía consensuada de prevención cardiovascular, la valoración del RCV en la historia clínica electrónica, haciendo especial énfasis en los estilos de vida, y la incorporación de la valoración y control del RCV entre los indicadores de calidad asistencial y los sistemas de incentivación profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);142(1): 7-14, ene. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117860</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El estado de la prevención cardiovascular en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
