<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121294</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Systematic review of health-related utilities in Spain: the case of mental health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives Currently, there is no registry of utility values for the Spanish population that could potentially be used in economic evaluations. Consequently, a systematic review of utilities or preferences for health states in the Spanish population was conducted. The results related to mental health are reported. Methods A systematic review of the literature was conducted. The main databases searched were MEDLINE, CRD, Embase, PsycINFO, CINAHL, and Cochrane. The search strategy combined terms related to utilities and Spain. The inclusion criteria comprised the resident population in Spain, whether affected by any disease or not; the reported utilities had to be evaluated through a tool validated in Spain (i.e., EQ-5D, HUI, SF-6D) and/or following accepted techniques (e.g., time trade-off, standard gamble, or the visual analog scale). A narrative synthesis of articles was undertaken and the results related to mental health summarized. Results A total of 103 articles were finally included, from which 742 utility values were extracted. Sixty-nine utility values related to mental health and behavioral disorders were extracted from 12 studies. The most widely used tool was the E5-QD questionnaire. Most of the excluded articles evaluated quality of life but did not provide an estimation of utilities. Conclusions This review adds value to research on utilities in Spain by gathering values to be included in economic evaluations, as well as by identifying research gaps in this field. The utility values related to mental health identified in this study are similar to those reported in international publications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguiar-Ibáñez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero-Santana, Amado</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinilla-Domínguez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pérez, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arvelo-Martín, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linertová, Renata</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Dada la carencia de un registro de utilidades en población española para su uso en evaluaciones económicas, se desarrolló una revisión sistemática de utilidades o preferencias por estados de salud obtenidas de población española con el fin último de crear un catálogo accesible a los investigadores. En este artículo se detallan las utilidades relacionadas con la salud mental. Método Revisión sistemática de la literatura, con búsquedas en MEDLINE, CRD, Embase, PsycINFO, CINAHL, Cochrane y otras bases de datos. La estrategia de búsqueda combinó términos relacionados con utilidades y con España. Los criterios de inclusión eran población residente, afectada o no por alguna enfermedad; utilidades valoradas con cuestionarios validados en España (EQ-5D, HUI, SF-6D) o siguiendo técnicas directas (equivalencia temporal, standard gamble, escala visual analógica). Se realizó una síntesis narrativa de los artículos incluidos, detallando los resultados relacionados con problemas de salud mental. Resultados Se incluyeron 103 estudios, de los que se extrajeron 742 utilidades. Se identificaron 69 utilidades relacionadas con trastornos mentales y del comportamiento, extraídas de 12 estudios. El instrumento más empleado fue el cuestionario EQ-5D. Gran parte de los artículos excluidos evaluaba la calidad de vida, pero sin ofrecer el valor de la utilidad. Conclusiones La presente revisión añade valor al estudio de las utilidades en España mediante la recopilación de valores que puedan ser incluidos en evaluaciones económicas, permitiendo además identificar lagunas en la investigación en este campo. Los valores relacionados con la salud mental identificados se asemejan a otros informados en la literatura internacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(1): 77-83, ene.-feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121294</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión sistemática de utilidades relacionadas con la salud en España: el caso de la salud mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
