<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79758</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prolonged/continuous cycle</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One suggested goal of contraceptive development has always been that the method should have little or no effect on the menstrual cycle. More specifically, mimicking a normal 28-day cycle was considered desirable. Combination oral contraceptives have thus been formulated in such a way as to provide an artificial but typically regular monthly cycle. For many years, however, clinicians have used hormonal manipulation of the menstrual cycle to provide therapeutic amenorrhea in individuals with underlying medical problems. There is growing interest in the use of combined oral estrogen-progestin contraception in extended «cycles» of 3, 6 and 12 or more months. Extended cycle contraception leads to better compliance than conventional cycle contraception, thus optimizing contraceptive effectiveness. Although this type of contraception is not accepted by all women, some do prefer to have fewer menstrual cycles, minimizing menstrual-related symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Borrego, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una de las justificaciones del desarrollo anticonceptivo ha sido siempre que el método tuviera escaso o ningún efecto en el ciclo menstrual. De forma aún más específica, era deseable imitar un ciclo normal de 28-días. Los anticonceptivos orales combinados se han formulado así para proporcionar un ciclo mensual artificial pero típicamente regular. Desde siempre, los médicos han usado la manipulación hormonal del ciclo menstrual para proporcionar amenorrea terapéutica en las mujeres que presentaban problemas médicos. Existe un creciente interés por el uso de la píldora anticonceptiva en ciclos «prolongados» de 3, 6 y 12 o más meses. La anticoncepción de ciclo prolongado facilita un mejor cumplimiento que la de ciclo convencional con una mayor eficacia anticonceptiva. Aunque no está aceptado por todas las mujeres, algunas de ellas prefieren tener menos ciclos menstruales, minimizando los síntomas relacionados con la menstruación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(5): 189-193, mayo 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79758</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ciclo prolongado/continuado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4796^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3286^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5408^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8766^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3297^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
