<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90187</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the repercussions of ankle sprains on postural balance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The lateral ankle sprain is one of the most common injuries in sports and can affectdifferent components of postural control. This literature review analyses the studies that evaluatethe postural control through static balance tests, dynamic balance tests and dynamicbalance functional tests in subjects who have suffered an ankle sprain and healthy subjectsusing quantitative methods.Injured ankles lead to a greater total path of the centre of pressure and an increased musclelatency time. Furthermore, the antero-posterior time of stabilisation increases and decreasesthe reach distance that can be taken by the centres of pressure. However, in some of the studiesfound, less objective methods are used in the selection of the subjects with an ankle sprain, and in others, non-sensitive tests and variables are used to study the consequences of posturalcontrol deficits after an ankle sprain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Casado, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El esguince lateral de tobillo es una de las lesiones más comunes ocurridas en deporte, pudiendo afectar a diferentes componentes del control postural. Esta revisión bibliográfica analiza los estudios en los que se evalúa el control postural a partir de tests de equilibrio estático, dinámico y dinámico funcional en personas que han sufrido un esguince y personascon tobillos sanos utilizando metodologías cuantitativas. Los tobillos lesionados presentan mayores rangos de desplazamiento del centro de presiones y mayores tiempos de latencia de la musculatura. También presentan mayores tiempos de estabilización en el eje anteroposterior y menor alcance en las posiciones extremas que puede adoptar el centro de presiones. Sin embargo, algunos de los trabajos encontrados usan métodos poco objetivos en la selección de los sujetos con esguince de tobillo y otros utilizan tests y variables poco sensibles para el estudio de las secuelas de déficits de control postural después de un esguince(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);46(170): 97-105, abr.-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90187</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de las repercusiones de los esguinces de tobillo sobre el equilibrio postural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13565^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13565^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13565^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30263^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30263^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30263^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30263^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30263^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13565^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13565^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
