<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104221</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of metabolic syndrome estimated with the new World Health Organization recommendations. The HERMEX study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives The unification of criteria for the diagnosis of metabolic syndrome, together with the subsequent World Health Organization (WHO) proposal to eliminate diabetes and cardiovascular diseases from the diagnostic criteria, will change estimates of the known prevalence of this syndrome. The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence of metabolic syndrome in a health area of Badajoz (Spain) using the latest consensus criteria and eliminating diabetes and cardiovascular disease. Methods We performed a cross-sectional population-wide study of randomly selected individuals aged between 25 and 79 years old in a health area of Badajoz. In all patients, data on their history of cardiovascular risk factors were gathered, waist circumference and blood pressure were measured and a fasting blood sample was collected. The prevalence of metabolic syndrome, following recent criteria, was compared by age and gender. Results We recruited 2,833 individuals (46.5% men). The mean age was 51.2 years The prevalence of metabolic syndrome was 33.6% and was significantly higher in men (36.7% vs 30.9%; p&lt;0.001). The prevalence of metabolic syndrome fell significantly after exclusion of patients with diabetes or cardiovascular disease (20.8%; p&lt;0.001). The difference in prevalence between the distinct criteria was significant for the whole population and by sex (p&lt;0.000). A significant difference in prevalence between genders was observed from the age of 45-54 years in men and 55-64 years in women Conclusions The prevalence of metabolic syndrome in a health area of Badajoz is among the highest reported in population-based studies in Spain. Although estimates of the prevalence are decreased by the new international recommendations, a considerable proportion of the young population requires preventive measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morcillo, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Bergés, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Félix-Redondo, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Palacios, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo, Ana B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Castán, José F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera De León, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos La unificación de criterios para el diagnóstico del síndrome metabólico, junto con la propuesta de la Organización Mundial de la Salud de eliminar de ellos a los pacientes con diabetes o con enfermedades cardiovasculares, cambiará la estimación de su prevalencia. Nuestro objetivo fue determinar la prevalencia del síndrome metabólico en un área de salud extremeña siguiendo ambas recomendaciones. Métodos Estudio transversal, poblacional, con selección aleatoria de individuos entre 25 y 79 años de edad, en un Área de Salud de Badajoz. Se recogieron los antecedentes de factores de riesgo cardiovascular, la presión arterial y el perímetro abdominal, y una muestra de sangre en ayunas. Se comparó la prevalencia del síndrome metabólico siguiendo los recientes criterios, por sexo y edad. Resultados Se reclutaron 2.833 personas, el 46,5% eran hombres, y la edad media 51,2 años. La prevalencia del síndrome metabólico fue del 33,6%, significativamente mayor en los hombres (36,7% frente a 30,9%; p&lt;0,001) y con una disminución significativa al excluir la diabetes y la enfermedad cardiovascular (20,8%; p&lt;0,001). La diferencia de prevalencia con los distintos criterios fue significativa para el total y por sexo (p&lt;0,001), a partir del decenio de edad de 45-54 años en los hombres y de 55-64 años en las mujeres. Conclusiones La prevalencia de síndrome metabólico en el área estudiada es de las más altas halladas en España en estudios poblacionales. Aunque se reduce con las nuevas recomendaciones internacionales, indica una población considerable y joven en la cual aplicar medidas preventivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(6): 519-524, Dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de síndrome metabólico según las nuevas recomendaciones de la OMS. Estudio HERMEX</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
