<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051564</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New prevention and therapy possibilities for thromboembolic venous disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fondaparinux is the leading molecule among a new class of antithrombotic drugs, the &#147;synthetic pentasaccharides&#148;. It acts by inhibiting activated Factor X. It has shown itself to be superior to low-molecular-weight heparins (LMWH) in the prevention of thromboembolic venous disease (TVD) after major orthopaedic surgery, oncologic suregry, and in hospitalised medical patients. It is as safe and effective as LMWH on the initial management of deep venous thrombosis, and as effective as non-fractionated heparin in the acute management of pulmonary embolism without haemodynamic instability. It may well replace LMWH in TVD prophylaxis and in the therapeutic management of deep venous thrombosis with or without pulmonary embolism and of haemodynamically stable pulmonary embolism with or without venous thrombosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maínez Saiz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Mir, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fondaparinux es el primero de una nueva clase de antitrombóticos, los pentasacáridos sintéticos. Actúa inhibiendo el factor X activado. Ha demostrado ser superior a las heparinas de bajo peso molecular (HBPM) en la prevención de la enfermedad tromboembólica venosa (ETEV) tras cirugía ortopédica mayor, cirugía oncológica y enfermos médicos hospitalizados. Es tan eficaz y seguro como las HBPM en el tratamiento inicial de la trombosis venosa profunda y que la heparina no fraccionada en el tratamiento agudo de la embolia pulmonar sin inestabilidad hemodinámica. Puede sustituir a las HBPM en la profilaxis de ETEV y en el tratamiento de la trombosis venosa profunda con o sin embolia pulmonar y de la embolia pulmonar, hemodinámicamente estable, con o sin trombosis venosa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);18(5): 297-302, oct. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051564</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas posibilidades de prevención y tratamiento de la enfermedad tromboembólica venosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24646^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31696^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
