<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115799</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Linaclotide in the treatment of patients with irritable bowel syndrome and constipation - analysis of an opportunity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Linaclotide is a secretagogue that provides a combined effect on visceral pain. The European Medicines Agency has authorized its indication for the symptomatic treatment of moderate to severe irritable bowel syndrome with constipation in adults. The purpose of this review is to discuss the clinical framework for linaclotide use in our setting, the drug&#146;s characteristics and pre-clinical development, and the clinical studies supporting its use in order to establish relevant views regarding its validity and clinical applicability. The results suggest that the only &#151;nonsevere&#151; adverse effect associated with this drug is diarrhea. As regards effectiveness, linaclotide consistently shows favorable, significant differences in absolute risk versus placebo for all objective outcome variables described by regulatory agencies, with a combined pain and constipation response between 12.6% and 22.8% according to the variable and trial under consideration. This response is sustained and drug-related, as it goes away upon discontinuation. To conclude, linaclotide has a safety and efficacy profile that, from a clinical perspective, warrants its use for patients meeting irritable bowel syndrome and constipation criteria, with significant symptoms that cannot be relieved with other less specific measures. In the absence of predictive rules for response, it is recommended that, should the patient fail to respond, he or she should be considered not eligible for linaclotide therapy, and both indication and treatment continuity should be reserved for objective responders alone (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carballo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La linaclotida es un secretagogo que asocia un efecto combinado sobre el dolor visceral. La European Medicines Agency ha aprobado su indicación en el tratamiento sintomático en adultos del síndrome del intestino irritable con estreñimiento moderado o grave. El objetivo de esta revisión es analizar el marco clínico de aplicación de linaclotida en nuestro medio, las características del fármaco, su desarrollo preclínico y los estudios clínicos que apoyan su uso, con el fin de establecer los correspondientes juicios de validez y aplicabilidad clínica. Los resultados indican que el único efecto adverso, no grave, del fármaco es la diarrea. En cuanto a su eficacia, linaclotida presenta consistentemente favorables y significativas diferencias de riesgo absolutas frente a placebo en todas las variables resultado objetivas marcadas por las agencias reguladoras, con una respuesta combinada a dolor y estreñimiento entre el 12,6% y el 22,8%, según la variable y el ensayo considerados. Esta respuesta es sostenida y vinculada al fármaco, pues desaparece tras su retirada. Se concluye que linaclotida presenta un perfil de seguridad y eficacia que justifica, desde una perspectiva clínica, su uso en pacientes que cumplan criterios de síndrome del intestino irritable con estreñimiento con sintomatología de intensidad significativa que no pueda resolverse con otros tratamientos menos específicos. En ausencia de reglas de predicción de respuesta se recomienda que, si tras un periodo de prueba el paciente no responde, debe considerarse que no es candidato a tratamiento con linaclotida, reservando indicación y continuidad del tratamiento solo a los respondedores objetivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(6): 345-354, jul. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115799</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linaclotida en el tratamiento de pacientes con síndrome del intestino irritable con estreñimiento: análisis de una oportunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54525^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54525^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38045^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54525^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38045^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38045^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38045^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52814^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24834</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
