<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107134</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-specific immunoglobulin titres against cytomegalovirus: An alternative to hyperimmune presentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective Specific immunoglobulin against cytomegalovirus has demonstrated its effectiveness in preventing and treating infections in solid organ transplantation. Several studies indicate that non-specific immunoglobulin is just as effective. This study aims to determine anti-cytomegalovirus immunoglobulin titres from one of the non-specific immunoglobulin presentations authorised in Spain. Method This was an observational study, in which we analysed the anti-cytomegalovirus antibody titres from different batches of Flebogamma® 5% 5g used at the Hospital Universitari Vall d'Hebron during 2008 and 2009.ResultsWe analysed 27 batches, which included 18,944 vials of Flebogamma® 5%. Depending on the origin, the median concentration of anti-cytomegalovirus immunoglobulin was 28PEI-U/ml and 22PEI-U/ml per vial of North American and Spanish origin, respectively (CI 95% for the difference of the medians 5 to 6PEI-U/ml; p&lt;0 001ConclusionsThe anti-cytomegalovirus antibody concentration of the non-specific immunoglobulin batches analysed was slightly lower than in the specific immunoglobulin preparations. These differences can be compensated by adjusting the dosage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cardona Pacual, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallvé Alcón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guiu Segura, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monterde Junyent, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campany Herrero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo La inmunoglobulina específica frente a citomegalovirus ha demostrado su eficacia en la prevención y tratamiento de la infección en el trasplante de órganos sólidos. Distintos estudios indican una eficacia similar respecto a las presentaciones de Ig inespecíficas. El objetivo de este estudio es determinar la titulación de inmunoglobulina anti-citomegalovirus de una de las presentaciones de inmunoglobulinas inespecíficas autorizadas en España. Método Estudio observacional en el que se analizó la titulación de anticuerpos anti-citomegalovirus de distintos lotes de Flebogamma® 5% 5g utilizados en el Hospital Universitari Vall d&#146;Hebron durante los años 2008 y 2009.ResultadosSe analizaron 27 lotes, que incluyeron 18.944 viales de Flebogamma® 5%. En función del origen, la concentración mediana de inmunoglobulina anti-citomegalovirus fue de 28UPEI/ml y 22UPEI/ml para los viales de origen norteamericano y español, respectivamente (IC 95 % para la diferencia de las medianas de 5 a 6UPEI/ml; p&lt;0 001ConclusionesLa concentración de anticuerpos anti-citomegalovirus de los lotes de inmunoglobulina inespecífica analizados es ligeramente inferior respecto a las especialidades de inmunoglobulinas específicas. Estas diferencias pueden compensarse mediante un ajuste posológico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;35(1): 23-27, ene. -feb. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107134</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Titulación de inmunoglobulinas inespecíficas frente a citomegalovirus: alternativa a la presentación hiperinmune</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22210^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
