<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14631</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric propierties of the satisfaction with life scale in adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyzed the psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the Satisfaction with Life Scale (SWLS). The subjects in the study were 697 adolescents from the Valencian Community. The exploratory factor analysis showed a single-factor solution accounting for 53.7% of the variance, with a high factor loading of the items. The confirmatory factor analysis indicated that the model fit was acceptable. The reliability analysis showed good internal consistency. The SWLS maintained a significant relationship in expected accordance with classroom satisfaction, feelings of happiness and of loneliness, which showed evidence of construct validity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balaguer, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Merita, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atienza, Francisco Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo analiza las propiedades psicométricas de la versión en Castellano de la Escala de Satisfacción con la Vida (SWLS) en una muestra de 697 adolescentes de la Comunidad Valenciana. El análisis factorial exploratorio mostró una estructura monofactorial que explicó el 53,7 por ciento de la varianza, con elevados pesos factoriales de sus ítems. El análisis de la fiabilidad de la escala señaló que la versión española posee una buena consistencia interna. Por último, la versión española del SWLS mantuvo relaciones significativas y en el sentido previsto con las variables de satisfacción en el ámbito escolar, sentimientos de felicidad y sentimientos de soledad, indicando una validez convergente adecuada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(2): 314-319, mayo 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14631</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades psicométricas de la escala de satisfacción con la vida en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8308^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
