<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166670</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The primary percutaneous coronary intervention program in the Balearic Islands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the main objectives of any health-care strategy for ischemic heart disease is to provide emergency treatment for acute myocardial infarction and especially for ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome (STEACS), where any delay in treatment is crucial. The speed with which treatment (whether mechanical or pharmacologic) can be implemented will be reflected in morbidity and mortality rates. In 2003, in response to scientific evidence that mechanical revascularization (i.e. primary percutaneous coronary intervention) is essential for ST-elevation acute myocardial infarction, this therapeutic technique was introduced at the referral hospital in our region (in a primary percutaneous coronary intervention program). In March 2008, after several meetings between various stakeholders and institutions, a regional trial of treatment for STEACS (i.e. the Balearic Islands myocardial infarction code trial) started. It involved: a) the identification and reporting of all patients diagnosed with STEACS in the region; b) a systematic analysis of the results of treatment for STEACS in comparison with treatment goals (e.g. treatment times, morbidity, mortality, complications and treatment provided); c) identifying and responding to any deviations from targets; d) thorough understanding of and involvement in the project by all parts of the health-care system, and e) follow-up 1 month, 6 months and 1 year after hospital discharge following the STEACS episode (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peral, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Jaume, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Socías, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Palomeque, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fiol, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alameda, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubert, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bethencourt, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los objetivos críticos de la estrategia de salud en la cardiopatía isquémica es la atención urgente del infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del ST (IAMCEST) y más concretamente del síndrome coronario agudo con elevación del ST, en los que el tiempo asistencial es crítico. Esta inmediatez del tratamiento (ya sea mecánica o farmacológica) se debería reflejar en los resultados de morbimortalidad. En 2003, tras la evidencia científica de la necesidad de una revascularización mecánica (intervención coronaria percutánea primaria) en el infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST, se estableció esta opción terapéutica en el hospital de referencia de nuestra comunidad (programa de intervención coronaria percutánea primaria). En marzo de 2008, tras múltiples reuniones con diferentes estamentos y centros, se puso en marcha el Registro Comunitario de la Asistencia al Síndrome Coronario Agudo con Elevación del ST (Registro Código Infarto de las Illes Balears). Se realiza: a) detección y documentación de todos los casos diagnosticados de IAMCEST en la comunidad autónoma; b) evaluación sistemática de los resultados asistenciales del IAMCEST y su ajuste a los objetivos asistenciales (tiempos, morbimortalidad, complicaciones, tratamientos, etc.); c) identificación y abordaje de las desviaciones respecto a los objetivos; d) conocimiento exhaustivo e implicación en el proyecto de todos los dispositivos asistenciales, y e) seguimiento al mes, a los 6 meses y al año del alta hospitalaria tras el proceso agudo del IAMCEST (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);11(supl.C): 35c-43c, 2011. graf, mapas, ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo de intervención coronaria percutánea primaria en las Islas Baleares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
