<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110260</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To measure the prevalence of aggregation of three major cardiovascular risk factors: hypertension, hypercholesterolemia and diabetes mellitus in a population greater than or equal to 14 years in a Health Area of Madrid and study their distribution by sex and age. Methods: We conducted a cross-sectional study by random sampling proportional to the number of patients assigned by health card to the Health Centers in the Area 2 of Madrid. 1733 records of patients greater than or equal to 14 years were finally selected. Were measured data of hypertension, diabetes and hypercholesterolemia,  individually and aggregated.  Results: The prevalence of hypertension and hypercholesterolemiawas higher in women than in men. The proportion of patients  with hypertension and diabetes mellitus was 1.9% with no differences by sex. The proportion of patients with hypercholesterolemia and diabetes mellitus was more frequent in men than in women. The combination of the three cardiovascular risk factors studied was more frequent in women and highest in the age group greater than or equal to 76 years Conclusions: The prevalence of association of two or more cardiovascular risk factors in our population is important, being the  most frequent the association of hypertension and hypercholesterolemia, followed by hypertension and diabetes mellitus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sierra, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Gómez, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novella, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Mª F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo del estudio es medir la prevalencia de agregación de tres de los principales factores de riesgo cardiovascular: hipertensión, hipercolesterolemia y diabetes mellitusen la población mayor o igual a 14 años atendida en las consultas de Atención Primaria de un Área Sanitaria de Madrid y estudiar su distribución por sexo y edades.  Métodos: Se realizó un estudio transversal. Mediante un muestreo aleatorio proporcional al número de pacientes adscritos por tarjeta sanitaria a los Centros de Salud del Área 2 de Madrid, se seleccionaron 1.733 historias de pacientes mayores o iguales a 14 años. Se midieron los datos de registro de hipertensión arterial, diabetes e hipercolesterolemia, de forma  individual y agregada. Resultados: La prevalencia de hipertensión e hipercolesterolemia fue mayor en mujeres que en hombres. La proporción de pacientes con hipertensión y diabetes fue de 1,9% sin diferencias por sexos. La proporción de pacientes con hipercolesterolemia y diabetes fue más frecuente en hombres que en mujeres. La asociación de los tres factores de riesgo cardiovascular estudiados fue más frecuente en mujeres y más alta en el grupo de edad de mayor o igual a 76 años. Conclusiones:  La prevalencia de asociación de dos o más factores deriesgo cardiovascular en nuestra población es importante, siendo la asociación más frecuente la hipertensión e hipercolesterolemia, seguida de hipertensión y diabetes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;18(1): 18-23, ene.-mar. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110260</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la agregación de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en un Área de Atención Primaria en Madrid. Estudio SIRVA2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
