<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99200</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">&#149; Nephrologists should promote the detection of CKD in heart disease patients. The evaluation should include estimation of GFR and detection of microalbuminuria in a recently voided urine sample by the albumin: creatinine ratio. Any patient with stage 3 or 4 CKD and rapid deterioration of GFR should be evaluated by the nephrologist.&#149; Patients with CKD have a high risk of cardiovascular (CV) complications and heart disease patients have a high incidence of CKD and progression is also more rapid (Strength of Recommendation B). The most likely pathophysiological hypothesis is endothelial damage.&#149; The CV risk profile should be established in each patient followed by adequate compliance with control goals for common CV risk factors: smoking, obesity, sedentarism, hypertension, dyslipidemia. Early treatment of anemia and bone mineral disease as CV risk factors requires special mention (Strength of Recommendation B).&#149; Management of these patients will be based on individualization of treatment, close systematic follow-up, and integration (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portolés Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Bou, X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">&#149; Los nefrólogos debemos promover la detección de la ERC en pacientes cardiópatas. El estudio debe incluir la estimación del FG y la detección de microalbuminuria en una muestra de orina reciente mediante el índice albúmina/creatinina. Todo paciente con ERC grado 4 o grado 3 con rápido deterioro del FG debe ser evaluado por nefrología.&#149; Los pacientes con ERC presentan un riesgo elevado de complicaciones cardiovasculares (CV) y los pacientes cardiópatas tienen un mayor incidencia de ERC y la progresiónes al mismo tiempo más rápida. (Fuerza de Recomendación B). La hipótesis fisiopatológica más probable es el daño endotelial.&#149; Debe establecerse el perfil de riesgo CV en cada paciente y seguir un adecuado cumplimiento de los objetivos de control de factores de riesgo CV comunes: tabaco, obesidad, sedentarismo, HTA, dislipemia. Especial mención requiere el tratamiento precoz de la anemia y de la (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(supl.3): 29-32, ene.-dic. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome cardiorrenal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54530^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
