<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037191</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term trends in drug prescription for hospitalized patients with congestive heart failure. Influence of type of dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. To evaluate changes in drug prescription during 1991-2002 in patients hospitalized for congestive heart failure (CHF) with preserved or depressed left ventricular (LV) systolic function. Patients and method. A total of 1252 CHF patients(mean age, 69.4 (11.7) years; 61.3% male) hospitalized in a cardiology department were studied. Ischemic heart disease was present in 616 (49.2%), hypertension in 693 (55.4%),and diabetes in 335 (26.8%). Some 498 (39.8%) had preserved LV systolic function, defined as an echocardiographically determined ejection fraction &amp;#8805;50% at admission. Pharmaco therapy at hospital discharge was recorded for all patients. Results. The changes in drug prescription observed in CHF patients with preserved LV systolic function paralleled those in patients with depressed LV systolic function. Change was influenced by the publication of major clinical trials on CHF and depressed LV systolic function. Consequently, the use of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors, angiotensin-receptor blockers, beta-blockers, and spironolactone progressively increased during follow-up for both types of CHF. Diuretics were prescribed for more than70% of patients, with the rate being higher in those with depressed LV systolic function. Digoxin use decreased markedly in patients with preserved LV systolic function. Conclusions. An increase in the prescription of drugs with proven effects on mortality and morbidity in patients with CHF was observed. Nevertheless, beta-blocker and spironolactone use remains suboptimal. The trend seen after hospitalization in CHF patients with preserved LV systolic function was similar, though slightly less marked</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Virgos Lamela, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grigorian Shamagian, Lilian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela Román, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Juanatey, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Acuña, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rigueiro Veloso, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Evaluar a largo plazo (1991-2002) la prescripción de fármacos en pacientes hospitalizados por insuficiencia cardíaca con función sistólica(FS) ventricular izquierda conservada y deprimida. Pacientes y método. Se ha evaluado a un total de1.252 pacientes ingresados en el servicio de cardiología por insuficiencia cardíaca con una edad media de 69,4 ±11,7 años y 767 (61,3%) varones. El 49,2% (616) de los enfermos presentaba cardiopatía isquémica; el 55,4%(693), hipertensión arterial, y 335 (26,8%), diabetes. La FS ventricular izquierda estaba conservada en 498 enfermos(39,8%) (fracción de eyección determinada ecocardiográficamente durante el ingreso &amp;#8805; 50%). En todos los pacientes incluidos en el estudio se ha evaluado el tratamiento prescrito en el alta hospitalaria. Resultados. Se ha observado un patrón paralelo en la prescripción de fármacos en pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca con FS ventricular izquierda conservada y deprimida, cuya evolución ha coincidido con la publicada en amplios ensayos clínicos de insuficiencia cardíaca con FS ventricular izquierda deprimida. Así, la prescripción de inhibidores de la enzima de conversión de la angiotensina, bloqueadores de los receptores de la angiotensina II, espironolactona y bloqueadores beta se incrementó progresivamente en ambos patrones de disfunción. Más del70% de los pacientes utilizaba diuréticos, con más frecuencia en el grupo con FS ventricular izquierda deprimida; la utilización de digital mostró una marcada reducción en el grupo con FS ventricular izquierda conservada. Conclusiones. Hemos asistido a un incremento del empleo de fármacos con efecto probado sobre la mortalidad y morbilidad de pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca congestiva; sin embargo, el empleo de bloqueadores beta y espironolactona es aún limitado. Hay una tendencia paralela, aunque ligeramente inferior en el grupo de FS conservada, en el empleo de estos fármacos después de la hospitalización de los pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;58(4): 381-388, abr. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037191</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución a largo plazo de la prescripción de fármacos en pacientes hospitalizados por insuficiencia cardíaca congestiva. Influencia del patrón de disfunción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38265^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22832</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31982^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4294</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
