<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141002</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic evaluation of public health interventions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The scarcity of resources available to meet the growing demand for healthcare services has increased interest in economic evaluation as a tool to inform resource allocation. The aim of economic evaluation is to compare various alternatives for action, in terms of their costs and effects on health, by using several techniques: cost minimization analysis, cost-effectiveness analysis, cost-utility analysis, and cost-benefit analysis. Irrespective of the methodology used, any assessment must include scope of the problem, selection of alternatives for comparison, explication of the perspective of analysis and the time horizon, measurement and evaluation of costs and health effects, presentation of results, and sensitivity analysis. In Spain, evaluation of currently ongoing preventive interventions, and adherence to the existing economic evaluation guidelines by researchers would be desirable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Altés, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navas, Encarna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, Ma Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La escasez de recursos disponibles para satisfacer una demanda creciente de servicios sanitarios ha hecho que las miradas se dirijan hacia la evaluación económica como instrumento para informar la asignación de recursos. Su objetivo es comparar diversas alternativas de actuación en términos de sus costes y efectos sobre la salud. Para ello, utiliza diversas técnicas: el análisis de minimización de costes, el análisis coste-efectividad, el análisis coste-utilidad y el análisis coste-beneficio. Sea cuál sea la metodología utilizada, toda evaluación debe incluir la definición del problema, la selección de opciones a comparar, la explicitación de la perspectiva del análisis y del horizonte temporal, la medida y la valoración de los costes y los efectos sobre la salud relevantes, la presentación de resultados, y la realización de análisis de sensibilidad. En España sería conveniente que se evaluaran las intervenciones preventivas actualmente en marcha, y que los investigadores se adhiriesen a las guías de evaluación económica existentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(supl.1): 25-31, jun. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141002</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación económica de intervenciones de salud pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6228^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16645</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
