<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27837</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Severe myoclonic epilepsy in infancy (dravet's syndrome). Its nosological characteristics and therapeutic aspects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims. Severe myoclonic epilepsy in infancy (SMEI) is an epileptic syndrome recognised by the ICE of 1985 and 1989 and in the proposal put forward by the ILAE Task Force on Classification and Terminology in 2001. In this paper, its historical development, nosological characteristics and treatment are described. Development. Although identified by Dravet in 1978, it has been called severe myoclonic epilepsy in infancy since 1981. As an alternative the name polymorphic epilepsy has also been put forward and in 2001 the ILAE recognised the eponym Dravet&#146;s syndrome. We describe how it may be mistaken for febrile convulsions in the early stages and later for Lennox-Gastaut syndrome, Doose&#146;s myoclonic-astatic epilepsy and certain progressive myoclonic epilepsies. We outline the risk factors, recognised in 1992, that facilitate an early diagnosis and the defining clinical criteria established in 1984. We point out the existence of atypical forms due to the absence of some of the defining criteria, which will never be above one, to formulate a diagnosis of SMEI. The frequency with which a family background of febrile convulsions and epilepsy appears seems to point to a genetic origin. Recently, de novo mutations have been found in the alpha subunit of the voltage-dependent sodium channel as well as mutations in the gamma subunit of the GABAA receptor. Nosologically, it is located in group 3 of the 1989 ICE, which corresponds to epileptic syndromes without a focal determination, or which are generalised, and on the list of epilepsy/syndromes that was presented in 2001. SMEI is an epilepsy syndrome which is, in most cases, resistant to classical and new AED, and other more unusual treatment. The drugs that have proved to be more effective, although only relatively so, are topiramate, valproate and the benzodiazepines. At present another alternative that has appeared is stiripentol. Intravenous use of immunoglobulins can be useful. Conclusions. Dravet&#146;s syndrome, admitted as such by the ILAE in 2001 and probably caused by de novo mutations in the sodium channels or in the GABAA receptors, is one of the severest forms of epilepsy in infancy with very little or no response to current antiepileptic drugs. Those that have been seen to be most effective are topiramate, the benzodiazepines, valproate and, more recently, stiripentol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La epilepsia mioclónica grave de la infancia (EMGI) es un síndrome epiléptico reconocido en las ICE de 1985 y 1989 y en la propuesta del Grupo de Trabajo de Clasificación y Terminología de la ILAE en 2001. Se describe su desarrollo histórico, ubicación nosológica y tratamiento. Desarrollo. Identificado por Dravet en 1978, se denomina epilepsia mioclónica grave de la infancia en 1981; se propone, como alternativa, la denominación de epilepsia polimorfa, y se reconoce con el epónimo de síndrome de Dravet por la ILAE en 2001. Se señala su posible confusión inicial con las convulsiones febriles y, posteriormente, con el síndrome de Lennox-Gastaut, la epilepsia mioclonicoastática de Doose y algunas epilepsias mioclónicas progresivas. Se exponen los factores de riesgo, que facilitan un diagnóstico precoz, reconocidos en 1992, y los criterios clínicos de definición establecidos en 1984. Se señala la existencia de formas atípicas por la ausencia de algunos de los criterios de definición, que nunca serán superiores a uno para formular el diagnóstico de EMGI. La frecuencia de antecedentes familiares de convulsiones febriles y epilepsia sugieren un origen genético; se han encontrado recientemente mutaciones de novo en la subunidad a del canal de sodio dependiente de voltaje, y también en la subunidad g del receptor GABAA. Nosológicamente, se ubica en el grupo 3 de la ICE de 1989, que corresponde a los síndromes epilépticos sin determinación focal o generalizada, y en la lista de epilepsia/síndromes que se presentó en 2001. La EMGI es un síndrome epiléptico refractario, en la mayoria de los casos, a los fármacos antiepilépticos clásicos, a los nuevos y a otras terapéuticas no habituales. Los fármacos que han mostrado una mayor eficacia, siempre relativa, han sido el topiramato, el valproato y las benzodiacepinas. Actualmente surge como alternativa el estiripentol. Las inmunoglobulinas por vía endovenosa pueden ser útiles. Conclusiones. El síndrome de Dravet, admitido como tal por la ILAE en el 2001, de muy probable origen genético por mutaciones de novo en los canales de sodio o en los receptores GABAA, es una de las epilepsias más graves de la infancia, con escasa o nula respuesta a los fármacos antiepilépticos actuales. Los que han mostrado una relativa mayor eficacia son el topiramato, las benzodiacepinas, el valproato y, recientemente, el estiripentol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(1): 64-68, jul. 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epilepsia mioclónica grave de la infancia (síndrome de Dravet). Ubicación nosológica y aspectos terapéuticos</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Nieto Barrera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Jiménez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Candau, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27837</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30333</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23832</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
