<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62135</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescent idiopathic scoliosis: Results of treatment with hybrid posterior instrumentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: Report on the clinical and radiological results obtained by surgical treatment of adolescent idiopathic scoliosis by means of hybrid posterior instrumentation. The repercussions of surgery on the patients¿ quality of life are also described. Materials and methods: Retrospective study of 26 patients operated between 2001 and 2006, with a mean follow-up of 37.8 months. In terms of the Lenke classification, 42.3% of patients had type 1 curves, 46.2% type 3 curves, 7.7% type 5 curves, and one case of type VI curves. All patients were subjected to a hybrid posterior instrumentation with distal pedicular screws and proximal hooks. Transfusion needs and complications were duly recorded. A clinical assessment was performed by means of the SRS-22 questionnaire. A radiological assessment was conducted preoperatively, postoperatively and at the end of follow-up. Results: There were three superficial infections, one hemothorax and one hook dislocation. The administration of the SRS-22 questionnaire produced the following mean scores: 4.41 for pain, 4.39 for activity, 3.91 for self-image, 3.98 for mental health and 3.81 for satisfaction. Mean post-surgical radiological correction for thoracic and lumbar curves was 58% and 60%, respectively, with a mean loss of 7 and 5.5 degrees at the end of follow-up. There were no cases of Pseudoarthrosis. Discussion and conclusions: Hybrid posterior instrumentation and fusion is an efficient and safe technique, with a low rate of pseudoarthrosis and failure. Results were good as regards pain and activity, but fair in terms of self-image and personal satisfaction. We found no statistically significant association between the patients´ age, the degree of curve correction and the score on the SRS-22 questionnaire (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Álvarez, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santana-Suárez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Navarro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-García, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirino-Cabrera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina-Cabrillana, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Describir los resultados clínicos y radiológicos así como la repercusión en la calidad de vida del enfermo tras el tratamiento quirúrgico de la escoliosis idiopática del adolescente mediante instrumentación posterior híbrida. Material y método: Estudio retrospectivo de 26 sujetos intervenidos desde 2001 hasta 2006, con un seguimiento medio de 37,8 meses. Se obtuvieron, mediante la clasificación de Lenke de las curvas, los siguientes resultados: el 42,3% fue de tipo i, el 46,2% fue de tipo iii, el 7,7% fue de tipo v y 3,8% fue de tipo vi. Se intervino a todos los sujetos mediante instrumentación posterior híbrida con tornillos pediculares distales y ganchos proximales. Se registraron las necesidades transfusionales y las complicaciones. Se realizó una evaluación clínica mediante el cuestionario SRS-22 (Scoliosis Research Society` Sociedad de Investigación de la Escoliosis¿). Asimismo, se realizó una evaluación radiológica prequirúrgica, posquirúrgica inmediata y al final del seguimiento. Resultados: Se registraron 3 infecciones superficiales, un hemotórax y una luxación de gancho. Mediante el cuestionario SRS-22 se obtuvieron las siguientes puntuaciones medias: 4,41 en dolor; 4,39 en actividad; 3,91 en autoimagen; 3,98 en salud mental, y 3,81 en satisfacción. La corrección radiológica media posquirúrgica en las curvas torácicas fue del 58% y en las curvas lumbares fue del 60%, con una pérdida media de 5,5° a 7° al final del seguimiento. No hubo casos de seudoartrosis. Discusión y conclusiones: La instrumentación y fusión posterior híbrida es una técnica eficaz y segura, con bajo índice de seudoartrosis y fracasos. Los resultados fueron buenos en cuanto al dolor y a la actividad, pero fueron discretos en cuanto a la autoimagen y a la satisfacción personal. No se encontró asociación estadísticamente significativa entre la edad de los sujetos, el grado de corrección de la curva y la puntuación del cuestionario SRS-22 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);53(3): 173-184, mayo-jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62135</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del tratamiento de la escoliosis idiopática del adolescente mediante instrumentación posterior híbrida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12265^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12265^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14088^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
