<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147634</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Guidelines for the follow up of patients with bronchopulmonary dysplasia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) is the most common complication of preterm birth, and remains a major problem in pediatric pulmonology units. The decision of discharging from the Neonatal Unit should be based on a thorough assessment of the condition of the patient and compliance with certain requirements, including respiratory and nutritional stability, and caregiver education on disease management. For proper control of the disease, a schedule of visits and complementary tests should be established prior to discharge, and guidelines for prevention of exacerbations and appropriate treatment should be applied. In this paper, the Working Group in Perinatal Respiratory Diseases of the Spanish Society of Pediatric Pulmonology proposes a protocol to serve as a reference for the follow up of patients with BPD among different centers and health care settings. Key factors to consider when planning discharge from the Neonatal Unit and during follow up are reviewed. Recommendations on treatment and prevention of complications are then discussed. The final section of this guide aims to provide a specific schedule for follow-up and diagnostic interventions to be performed in patients with BPD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valdesoiro Navarrete, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Gómez de Agüero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrent Vernetta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo Miró, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Callejón Callejón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortell Aznar, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfonso Diego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serna Blázquez, O de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Requena, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilella Sabaté, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda Esteban, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Hernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Tarazona, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo Posadas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Galdó, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pérez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Solís de Querol, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna Paredes, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesa Medina, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La displasia broncopulmonar (DBP) es la secuela más prevalente del recién nacido pretérmino, y sigue suponiendo un motivo frecuente de consulta en las unidades de Neumología Pediátrica. La decisión del alta de la unidad neonatal debe apoyarse en una valoración exhaustiva de la situación clínica del paciente y en el cumplimiento de unos requisitos, que incluyen la estabilidad respiratoria y nutricional, y la instrucción a los cuidadores en el manejo domiciliario. Para un control adecuado de la enfermedad, es necesario que quede establecido, previamente al alta, un calendario de visitas y de exploraciones complementarias, y deben aplicarse las pautas de prevención de exacerbaciones y el tratamiento apropiados. El concepto de DBP como enfermedad multisistémica es fundamental en el seguimiento de los pacientes y debe ser tenido en cuenta para un buen control de la enfermedad. En este documento, el Grupo de Trabajo de Patología Respiratoria Perinatal de la Sociedad Española de Neumología Pediátrica propone un protocolo que sirva como referencia para unificar el seguimiento de los pacientes con DBP entre los diferentes centros y ámbitos asistenciales. Se revisan los aspectos a tener en cuenta en la evaluación previa al alta de la Unidad Neonatal y las principales complicaciones durante el seguimiento. Seguidamente, se detallan las recomendaciones en materia de tratamiento de la enfermedad y prevención de complicaciones, los controles tras el alta y su cronología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);84(1): e1-e9, ene. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147634</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protocolo de seguimiento de los pacientes con displasia broncopulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2024^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1811^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2024^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2024^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2024^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2024^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
