<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156592</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bibliometric analysis of articles on nursing care published in colombian magazines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To accomplished a bibliometric analysis of articles published on nursing care in Colombian journals. Materials and Methods: Descriptive y retrospective bibliometric study. It was analyzed 95 articles published in 18 Colombian indexed journals in Publindex during the years 2010 to 2015. The search was conducted by the care descriptors, nursing models, nursing theory. The descriptive analysis was performed using an Excel spreadsheet and bibliometric indicators of productivity, citation, content and methodology. Results: An increase in publishing in the last 5 years is observed, being the original research articles the ones which are published the most and the institutions that published the most are Universities from Bogota and Antioquia. According to the citation indicators the index price was 37.45%, while the isolation rate was 33.67% and self-citation index was 1.85%. On indicators of collaboration, co-authorship index was 2.7 and the institutional collaboration index was 1.3. Conclusions: An increase in scientific research about Nursing in Colombia is observed, however, it is necessary to expand cooperation indicators (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camacho Rodríguez, Doriam Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Noguera, Tatiana Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oviedo Córdoba, Haidy Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos de la Hoz, Ediltrudis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar un análisis bibliométrico de los artículos sobre cuidado de enfermería, publicados en revistas Colombianas. Materiales y método: Estudio bibliométrico descripti¬vo, retrospectivo. Se analizaron 95 artículos publicados en 18 revistas colombianas indexadas en Publindex, durante los años 2010 a 2015. La búsqueda se realizó mediante los descriptores: cuidado, modelos de enfermería, teoría de enfermería. El análisis descriptivo se realizó mediante una hoja de Excel y se analizaron los indicadores bibliométricos de productividad, citación, contenido y metodológicos. Resultados: Se observa un incremento en la publicación en los últimos 5 años, siendo los artículos de investigaciones originales los que más se publican y las Instituciones que más publican son las Universidades de Bogotá y Antioquia. En relación con los indicadores de citación, el Índice de Price fue de 37,45%, en tanto que el índice de aislamiento fue de 33,67%  y el índice de auto citación fue de 1,85%. Sobre los indicadores de colaboración, el índice de coautoría fue de 2,7 y  el índice de colaboración institucional fue de 1,3. Conclusiones: Se observa un incremento en la producción científica de Enfermería en Colombia, no obstante, se hace necesario ampliar los indicadores de colaboración (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;15(44): 396-405, oct. 2016. tab, graf, mapa</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156592</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis bibliométrico de los artículos sobre cuidado de enfermería publicados en revistas colombianas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d46^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d46^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
