<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056960</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infection in heart transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Heart transplantation has emerged as the therapy of choice for selected patients with life-threatening, irremediable heart disease. Infectious complications are frequent, but are no longer the leading cause of death. Late infections (particularly viral infections), however, are still a threat to long-term graft survival in these patients. Bacterial infections are the most common, particularly of the respiratory tract, which usually appear in the first month or after one year following transplantation in patients with previous COPD. Catheter-related infection is also common, whereas postoperative mediastinitis is much less frequent. The overall incidence of fungal infections has decreased considerably in recent years (2%-15%), but associated mortality remains high. Pulmonary aspergillosis is the most common. Cytomegalovirus is the most important pathogen in heart transplantation, currently affecting 7%-35% of patients. Antiviral prophylactics and pre-emptive therapy have reduced the incidence of acute CMV disease, but the potential role of this microorganism as a cofactor in allograft vascular disease, the most common cause of death in these patients, is a cause for concern. Toxoplasmosis, a particularly severe entity in heart transplant recipients, has decreased with the use of routine prophylaxis in seronegative recipients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gurguí, Mercé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trasplante cardíaco es ya una alternativa terapéutica habitual para numerosos pacientes con cardiopatías graves. Las complicaciones infecciosas agudas han dejado hace tiempo de ser una causa frecuente de mortalidad, aunque persiste, sin embargo, el reto de infecciones tardías, sobre todo virales, que amenazan la supervivencia a largo plazo del injerto.  Las infecciones más comunes son las bacterianas, sobre todo las del tracto respiratorio, que suelen aparecer en el primer mes postrasplante o después del año, en pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) previa. Son también frecuentes las infecciones de catéter, y mucho menos, las mediastinitis posquirúrgicas.  La incidencia de micosis ha descendido de forma significativa (2-15%), aunque su mortalidad continúa siendo muy elevada. La más frecuente es la aspergilosis pulmonar.  Citomegalovirus es el microorganismo más frecuente en el trasplante cardíaco, y puede afectar al 7-35% de los pacientes en la actualidad. Aunque ya es una causa excepcional de enfermedad aguda gracias a los programas de profilaxis y de tratamiento anticipado, preocupa su potencial papel como cofactor en la vasculopatía crónica del injerto, causa fundamental de muerte en estos pacientes.  La toxoplasmosis, especialmente temible entre los trasplantados cardíacos, se ha controlado en la actualidad con la profilaxis administrada a los receptores negativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;25(9): 587-598, nov. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones en el trasplante cardíaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10461^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14515^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21079^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
