<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112816</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of laser Doppler to assess peripheral tissue perfusion in critically ill children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze skin tissue perfusion at different sites in critically ill children. Patients and methods: A prospective observational study was performed on 41 critically ill children with a median age of 12 months and weight of 8.2 kg. Skin tissue flow was measured in each patient using laser Doppler consecutively in the foot, forearm, thigh and hypochondrium, and its association with demographic and hemodynamic variables, as well as lactate and inotropic index, was analyzed. Results: A total of 144 tissue flow measurements were made, with a median flow of 3.2±2.2 ml/min/100 g tissue. There was a moderate correlation between the tissue flow measured in central locations, abdomen-arm (r2: 0.574, P=.001), abdomen-thigh (r2: 0.423, P=0.002) and thigh-arm (r2: 0.703, P&lt;.000), but not with the peripheral measurements (sole of the foot). The limits of agreement, measured between the different locations, were wide (range 6.1 to&amp;#8722;2.5 ml/min/100 g). There was a slight-moderate correlation between the flow in the sole of the foot with weight (&amp;#8722;0.355, P=.039), age (&amp;#8722;0.343, P=.044), peripheral temperature (0.503, P=.017) and inotropic index (&amp;#8722;0.443, P=.008). Conclusions: Tissue flow in the foot correlates with weight, age, peripheral temperature and inotropic index. Further studies are needed to analyze its usefulness in assessing peripheral perfusion in situations of shock (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urbano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-González, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Cortés, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botrán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solana, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Figueruelo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Herce, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar el flujo tisular cutáneo en diferentes localizaciones en niños en estado crítico. Pacientes y métodos: Se realizó un estudio prospectivo observacional en 41 niños críticamente enfermos, con una edad mediana de 12 meses y un peso de 8,2kg. Se midió el flujo tisular cutáneo mediante láser Doppler de forma consecutiva en la planta del pie, el antebrazo, el muslo y el hipocondrio, y se estudió su correlación con variables demográficas, hemodinámicas y lactato. Resultados: Se estudiaron 144 mediciones. El flujo tisular fue de 3,2±2,2ml/min/100g de tejido. Existió una correlación moderada del flujo tisular entre las localizaciones centrales; abdomen-brazo (r2: 0,574; p=0,001); abdomen-muslo (r2: 0,423; p=0,002) y muslo-brazo (r2: 0,703; p&lt;0,000), pero no con la periférica (planta del pie). Los límites de concordancia entre los lugares de medición fueron amplios (rango de 6,1 a &#150;2,5ml/min/100g). Existió una correlación leve-moderada del flujo tisular de la planta del pie con el peso (&amp;#8722;0,355; p=0,039), la edad (&amp;#8722;0,343; p=0,044), la temperatura periférica (0,503; p=0,017) y el índice de inotrópico (&amp;#8722;0,443; p=0,008). Conclusiones: El flujo tisular en la planta del pie se correlaciona con el peso, la edad, la temperatura periférica y el índice inotrópico. Son necesarios estudios que analicen la utilidad del flujo tisular para valorar la perfusión periférica en situaciones de shock (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);78(6): 361-366, jun. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112816</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la perfusión tisular periférica mediante láser Doppler en niños en estado crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23699</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
