<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96428</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Explanatory styles of professional football coaches in the analysis of sports competition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this research was analyzing the explanatory styles of professional coaches at the end of competition matches. We collected 4366 coaches´ declarations in the press belonging to 29 league season fixtures, which are related to the dimensions of the explanatory styles theory and aspects like result, place, stage of the season and category. The results show significant differences in the three dimensions of the explanatory guidelines respected to the analyzed aspects. We discuss the importance of the explanatory styles of coaches to influence on the team performance, as well as the possible difference of attributing according to what was analyzed and the possibilities of psychological counselling to coaches in order to improve the performance evaluation and the feedback to football players (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmedilla, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortín, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar los estilos explicativos de los entrenadores de fútbol profesional al término de los partidos de competición. Se recogieron 4366 declaraciones en prensa pertenecientes a 29 jornadas de liga, las cuales se relacionan con las dimensiones de la teoría de los estilos explicativos y aspectos como el resultado, el lugar, el momento de la temporada y la categoría. Los resultados indican diferencias significativas en las tres dimensiones de las pautas explicativas en alguno de los aspectos analizados. Se discute la importancia de los estilos explicativos de los entrenadores para influir en el rendimiento del equipo, así como la posible diferencia de atribuciones en función de lo analizado y las posibilidades de asesoramiento psicológico a entrenadores para una mejora de la evaluación del rendimiento y el feedback hacia los deportistas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(1): 233-239, ene.-abr. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96428</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos explicativos de los entrenadores de fútbol profesional en el análisis de la competición deportiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
