<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156781</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The term dual disorders approach in legislation and regional planning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fact that has not been reflected the definition of dual disorders in regional legislation, brings consequences not delve into its shortcomings and addressing their resources and take into account only the minimum content. Thus, many patients are lost between the two networks: Mental Health and Addictions, giving the 'wrong door syndrome' since their problems only partly belongs to each of them. Thus, the right to health protection is not equated with other medical disciplines, in terms of care, and in this aspect there is no uniformity among the different Autonomous Communities These arguments, very possibly bring because of historical reasons -asistenciales, who did not want to alleviate. And therefore, it would require a boost of the term dual disorders, to then define and address their materials and assistance gaps and to respond with maximum guarantees (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Dorta, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hecho de que no haya sido plasmada la definición de patología dual en la legislación autonómica, trae como consecuencias que no se profundice en sus carencias y en el abordaje sus recursos y sólo se tenga en cuenta su contenido mínimo. Así, muchos pacientes se pierden entre las dos redes: Salud Mental y Drogodependencias, dándose el 'síndrome de la puerta equivocada', ya que su problemática pertenece sólo en parte a cada una de ellas. De esta forma, el derecho a la protección de la salud no está equiparado a otras disciplinas médicas, en su vertiente asistencial, y en dicha vertiente no existe uniformidad entre las distintas CC.AA. Estos argumentos, muy posiblemente, traigan causa de razones históricas-asistenciales, que no se han querido paliar. Y por tanto, sería preciso un impulso del término patología dual, para seguidamente definir y abordar sus carencias materiales y asistenciales y dar respuesta con las máximas garantías (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;41(3): 85-96, 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156781</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El abordaje del término patología dual en la legislación y planificación autonómica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10531^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6454^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6418^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
