<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140429</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to study the prevalence of maternal lactation of our health area, and its conditioning factors. Methodology: cross-sectional descriptive study, by means of telephone survey, of 200 children born in 2003. Studied variables: type of lactation and duration of the breastfeeding, use of nipple protector, supplements of baby&#146;s bottle, maternal age, level of studies, origin, work situation, number of children, type of childbirth, smoking habit, information on breastfeeding and reason for abandonment. Analysis of data: statistical descriptive, chi square test, and multivariate analysis. Results: 74% of women initiate breastfeeding, 25.5% follow breastfeeding at 6 months, and 3.5% maintain it until 12 months. The average duration of exclusive breastfeeding was of 3.21 months (standard deviation [SD]: 3.32). A significant association has been found between being immigrant and breastfeeding at one month of life (p = 0, 0022) and breastfeeding at 6 months (p &lt; 0, 0005). Odds Ratio (OR) of 6.9 (confidence interval [CI] 95%: 2, 23-23, 05). Also between mothers with higher level of studies and breastfeeding at one month of life (p = 0,007). OR = 1.7 (CI 95%: 1, 05-2,75). The rest of the studied variables do not have statistical meaning. Conclusions: the percentage of mothers who initiate breastfeeding is slightly inferior to other studies of our surroundings; women who initiate breastfeeding, maintain it for longer. A higher level of studies and being an immigrant are helping factors for breastfeeding. We must promote maternal education before and during the first days after hospital discharge (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Crespo García, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa Vázquez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raventós Canet, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: estudiar la prevalencia del tipo de lactancia y de sus factores condicionantes en nuestra Área Básica de Salud (ABS). Material y métodos: estudio descriptivo transversal, mediante encuesta telefónica, en 200 niños nacidos en el año 2003. Variables estudiadas: tipo y duración de la lactancia materna (LM), uso de pezonera, suplementos de biberón, edad materna, nivel de estudios, procedencia, situación laboral, número de hijos, tipo de parto, hábito tabáquico, fuente de información y motivo de abandono de la LM. Análisis de los datos: estadísticos descriptivos, prueba de chi al cuadrado y análisis multivariante. Resultados: el 74% de mujeres inicia LM, el 25,5% sigue LM a los 6 meses, y el 3,5% a los 12 meses. La duración media de la LM exclusiva (LME) fue de 3,21 meses (desviación estándar [DE]: 3,32 meses). Se ha encontrado una asociación significativa entre ser inmigrante y la LM al mes de vida (p = 0,0022) y LM a los 6 meses [p &lt; 0,0005, odds ratio (OR) de 6,9 (intervalo de confianza [IC] 95%: 2,23-23,05]. También entre un mayor nivel de estudios y LM al mes de vida (p = 0,007). OR = 1,7 (IC 95%: 1,05-2,75). El resto de variables estudiadas no tiene significación estadística. Conclusiones: el porcentaje de inicio de LM es ligeramente inferior al de otros estudios de nuestro entorno; las mujeres que inician LM la mantienen durante más tiempo. Factores favorecedores son un mayor nivel de estudios y ser inmigrante. Debemos potenciar la LM antes y en los primeros días después del parto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;8(31): 409-420, jul.-sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la lactancia materna en el Área Básica de Salud Sant Feliu-2 (Barcelona)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9514^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9514^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9514^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9514^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
