<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057883</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptation and validation into Spanish of Schedule for the Deficit Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Schizophrenia is a high prevalent disorder associated with huge economic and sanitary costs. Negative symptoms represent the main prognostic factors, thus to identify them is important to design effective guidelines of treatment. The Schedule for the Deficit Syndrome (SDS) is the only validated method to evaluate those symptoms as primary and stable. We propose its adaptation and validation into Spanish. Patients and method: Patients diagnosed of schizophrenia attended at 2 different hospitals were evaluated with SDS (Spanish version) and PANSS (Positive and Negative Symptom Scale). Stable patients were reevaluated 6 months later. One rater acted as gold standard while two 2 raters, naïve to SDS, evaluated patients too. Results: Twenty-one patients were evaluated (15 men). Raters agreed ranged from * = 0.79 to * = 0.89 with gold standard and * = 0.90 between them. Kappa ranged from 0.60-0.70 for severity criteria and 0.78-0.90 for primary criteria. Temporal stability at 6 months between raters was * = 0.72 and 0.87. We also evaluated interclass correlation index and homogeneity of construct. Conclusions: After a brief training with the Spanish version of SDS, is fast and feasible to categorize patients into deficit or non-deficit forms of schizophrenia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ahuir, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arango, Celso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Egea, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torras, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La esquizofrenia es un trastorno frecuente, que ocasiona enormes costes tanto económicos como asistenciales. Los síntomas negativos son los principales marcadores pronósticos, así que identificarlos es clave para diseñar planes asistenciales efectivos. El Inventario para la Esquizofrenia Deficitaria (SDS) es el único método validado para evaluar estos síntomas como primarios y estables. Se propone su adaptación y validación en castellano. Pacientes y método: Se evaluó mediante el SDS (versión castellana) y PANSS (Escala de Síntomas Positivos y Negativos) a pacientes diagnosticados de esquizofrenia procedentes de 2 centros hospitalarios. Al cabo de 6 meses se revaluó a los pacientes estables. Un evaluador ejercía de referencia y otros 2, sin experiencia con el SDS, puntuaban las escalas. Resultados: Se incluyó a 21 pacientes (15 varones). Los evaluadores obtuvieron acuerdos de * = 0,79 y * = 0,89 con el evaluador de referencia y * = 0,90 entre sí. Los rangos de kappa fueron de 0,60-0,70 para el criterio de gravedad y de 0,78-0,90 para el criterio primario. La estabilidad temporal (6 meses) entre los evaluadores fue de * = 0,72 y 0,87. Asimismo, se evaluaron otros índices de concordancia (coeficiente de correlación interclase) y de homogeneidad del constructo. Conclusiones: Tras un breve entrenamiento con el SDS en castellano, se concluye que este método es rápido, factible y fiable para categorizar a los pacientes con esquizofrenia en deficitarios y no deficitarios</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);129(3): 91-93, jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057883</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación y validación en castellano del Inventario para la Esquizofrenia Deficitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
