<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136443</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">NEUROBEL: Brief neuropsychological screening batteryof oral language in older-adults. First normative data</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">NEUROBEL (Neuropsychological assessment of language in adults) is a brief battery that allows a screening of the basic processes of language comprehension and production. It consists of 8 tasks, assessing oral-language processing from the theoretical model of cognitive neuropsychology. The aim has been to carry out a pilot study of initial normative data for NEUROBEL battery in older-adults. This in mind, we studied a sample of 30 male and female healthy participants aged over 50 without cognitive impairment (MMSE &amp;#8805; 25). The NEUROBEL battery was administered to all the participants, which were split into 2 groups: 'adults' (50-64) and 'older-adults' (&gt; 65). The latter group was also analyzed according to their usual residence (private home or nursing home). In the Results section, it is shown the scores and time performances of the participants in the battery, as well as main percentiles. NEUROBEL is shown as a valid and reliable battery, including high Pearson's correlations among the tasks. Univariate ANOVAs show group and schooling effects in the scores of the battery for younger and more schooled participants. Conversely, sex factor does not influence the results achieved, although it is shown as significant variable in favor of the women for time execution of the tasks. Some differences among participants over 65 years old, depending on their usual place of residence and sex are debated in the Discussion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Adrián, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuetos, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jorquera, Jasmina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La batería NEUROBEL (Evaluación neuropsicológica del lenguaje en adultos) es una prueba breve que permite una valoración de sondeo de los procesos básicos de comprensión y producción del lenguaje. Consta de 8 tareas, que analizan el correcto funcionamiento del lenguaje oral desde el modelo teórico propuesto por la neuropsicología cognitiva. El objetivo de este trabajo ha consistido en realizar un estudio piloto de los valores de referencia normativos iniciales de esta batería en adultos y mayores. Para ello, se ha estudiado una muestra de 30 participantes sin deterioro cognitivo (MMSE &amp;#8805; 25), de ambos sexos y de más de 50 años. La batería NEUROBEL fue administrada a toda la muestra dividida en 2 grupos de edad: «adultos» (50-64) y «adultos-mayores» (&gt; 65). Estos últimos analizados también según su lugar habitual de residencia (domicilio particular o centros de mayores). En el apartado Resultados se presentan las puntuaciones, tiempos de referencia y percentiles principales obtenidos en la batería. NEUROBEL se muestra como una herramienta válida y fiable, con altas correlaciones bivariadas entre las tareas. ANOVA univariantes muestran efectos de grupo y escolaridad en puntuación, a favor de los participantes más jóvenes y escolarizados. Por el contrario, el sexo no influye en los resultados alcanzados, aunque sí se muestra como un factor significativo en el tiempo de ejecución de la batería, a favor de las mujeres. Ciertas diferencias observadas en los resultados entre los participantes del grupo de mayores de 65 años, dependiendo de su lugar habitual de residencia y sexo, se debaten en el apartado Discusión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);35(3): 101-113, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136443</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">NEUROBEL: Breve batería neuropsicológica de evaluación del lenguaje oral en adultos-mayores. Datos normativos iniciales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7985</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29287^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
