<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87552</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Leptin: A peptide with therapeutic potential in the obese</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity is the result of a positive balance between total energy intake and its catabolism. Although many factors are involved in the regulation of energy metabolism, the discovery of leptin led to energy homeostasis being investigated in greater depth. Since its identification, leptin has been considered important in the development of obesity, given its anorexigenic effect and influence on food intake and energy expenditure. Leptin is involved in diverse physiological processes such as energy balance, appetite and body weight control, fat and carbohydrate metabolism, and reproduction. However, to be able to function, this hormone has many specific receptors both centrally (hypothalamus) and peripherally in the skeletal muscle, lungs and kidneys. This study aims to review the key aspects relating leptin to the development of obesity and discusses its potential as an anorectic agent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Cordero, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Carmen de Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla López, Carlos Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Ferre, Judit</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Jiménez, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, Pedro Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad es el resultado de un balance positivo entre la cantidad total de energía ingerida y el catabolismo de esta. Aun siendo muchos los factores implicados en la regulación del metabolismo energético será con el descubrimiento de la leptina cuando se investigue más profundamente sobre la homeostasis energética. Desde su descubrimiento, la leptina ha sido considerada importante en el desarrollo de la obesidad, dado su efecto anorexígeno e influencia sobre la ingesta y gasto energético. La leptina interviene en diversos procesos fisiológicos, como el balance energético, el control del apetito y del peso corporal, el metabolismo de grasas y glúcidos, y en la reproducción. Si bien para su funcionamiento esta hormona cuenta con numerosos receptores específicos a nivel central (hipotálamo) y periféricamente en el músculo esquelético, el pulmón y los riñones. El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido revisar los principales aspectos que llevan a la leptina a ser considerada como un factor relacionado con el desarrollo de la obesidad, así como sobre sus potencialidades como agente anorexígeno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;57(7): 322-327, ago.-sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87552</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leptina: un péptido con potencial terapéutico en sujetos obesos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34404^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
