<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95136</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endovascular treatment and intra-arterial thrombolysis in acute ischemic stroke</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveAnalysis of the safety and efficacy of intra-arterial thrombolysis therapy and endovascular treatment in acute ischemic stroke.Design and areaAn observational prospective study in the Intensive Care Unit.Patients and methods16 patients had endovascular treatment. Epidemiological data, arterial occlusion site, time between stroke onset and treatment, treatment indication, NIHSS scale at admission and discharge from hospital, complications and functional outcome measured by modified Rankin scale (obtained by telephone survey) were collected.ResultsTen male patients with a mean age of 59 years (29&#150;74) were included. The mean stay in the ICU was 6 days (1&#150;33). Seven patients required mechanical ventilation. Treatment indications were: intravenous thrombolysis failure in 4 patients, major vessel occlusion in 5, outside of the therapeutic window in 2, posterior circulation occlusion in 3, outside of the therapeutic window plus major vessel occlusion in 1 and intravenous thrombolysis contraindication in 1. The occlusion site was on posterior circulation in 3 and on carotid territories and branches in 13. Thrombolytic treatment used was Urokinase at a dose of 100,000&#150;600,000IU. Four patients required mechanical embolectomy and 10 stent implantation. Complete recanalization was observed in 11 (69%) and partial in 4 (25%). Three evolved to brain death. Six patients (46%) had a favorable outcome (modified Rankin scale score &amp;#8804;2). Technical complication was 1 femoral artery pseudoaneurysm.ConclusionsWith the intra-arterial treatment, high rates of recanalization and favorable outcome are obtained with few complications. It could be indicated in patients with severe neurological injury (NIHSS &amp;#8805;10), evolution time between 3&#150;6h, intravenous thrombolysis contraindication and proximal arterial occlusion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Viña, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forcelledo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taboada, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murias, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoAnalizar la eficacia y la seguridad de la trombólisis intraarterial y el tratamiento endovascular en pacientes con ictus isquémico agudo.Diseño y ámbitoEstudio prospectivo observacional en una unidad de cuidados intensivos.PacientesDieciséis pacientes recibieron tratamiento endovascular. Se recogieron datos epidemiológicos, localización de la oclusión arterial, tiempo desde el ictus al tratamiento, indicación del tratamiento, National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale al ingreso y al alta hospitalaria, y complicaciones y evolución funcional por escala de Rankin modificada realizada mediante una encuesta telefónica.ResultadosDiez varones, con una edad media de 59 años (29&#150;74) y una estancia media en la unidad de cuidados intensivos de 6 días (1&#150;33). Siete pacientes requirieron ventilación mecánica. Indicación del tratamiento: 4 casos por fracaso de la trombólisis intravenosa, 5 por oclusión de gran vaso, 2 por estar fuera de la ventana terapéutica, 3 por oclusión de la circulación posterior, uno por estar fuera de la ventana terapéutica y tener, además, una oclusión de gran vaso y uno por contraindicación para la trombólisis intravenosa. Localización de la oclusión: 3 en la circulación posterior y 13 en el territorio carotídeo y sus ramas. El fibrinolítico utilizado fue uroquinasa en dosis de 100.000&#150;600.000 UI. Cuatro pacientes requirieron embolectomía mecánica y 10, implantación de stent. Se obtuvo recanalización completa en 11 pacientes (69%) y parcial en 4 (25%). Tres pacientes evolucionaron a muerte encefálica. Seis pacientes (46%) tuvieron una buena recuperación (escala de Rankin modificada &amp;#8804;2). Como complicación técnica destacó un seudoaneurisma de la arteria femoral.(..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);34(6): 370-378, ago.-sept. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95136</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endovascular y trombólisis intraarterial en el ictus isquémico agudo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30742^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54238^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
