<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157793</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotion awareness, mood and personality as predictors of somatic complaints in children and adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The relationships among somatic complaints, emotion awareness and mood have been observed in late childhood and adolescence, but very few studies have been carried out in adult populations like this work. This study also incorporates personality dimensions that can exacerbate or reduce the emergence of somatic complaints. Therefore, the aim of this study is to analyse the combined contribution of emotion awareness, mood, and personality to healthy children and adults&#146; somatic complaints. Method: Self-reported questionnaires about emotion awareness, mood, personality, and somatic complaints were administered to 1,476 children (7-14 years old) and 479 adults (27-56 years old). Results: Emotion awareness and mood were the strongest predictors of somatic complaints (&amp;#916;R2 = .32 for children; &amp;#916;R2 = .36 for adults), and the contribution of personality dimensions was not so relevant (&amp;#916;R2 = .07 for children; &amp;#916;R2 = .12 for adults). Conclusions: Emotional and personality factors must be addressed in health-promotion programmes, tailored differently according to whether they are to be used with children or with adults (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Badenes, Lidón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado-Gascó, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Barrón, Remedio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la relación entre quejas somáticas, conciencia emocional y estados de ánimo se ha comprobado en poblaciones preadolescentes y adolescentes; sin embargo, pocos estudios han analizado esta misma relación en adultos, tal y como se propone en este trabajo. Este estudio también incorpora variables de personalidad que pueden exacerbar o reducir la aparición de quejas somáticas. Por lo tanto, el objetivo de este estudio sería el de analizar la contribución combinada de conciencia emocional, estados de ánimo y personalidad sobre las quejas somáticas de niños y adultos sanos. Método: diferentes auto-informes de estos constructos se administraron a 1.476 niños (7-14 años) y 479 adultos (27-56 años). Resultados: la conciencia emocional y los estados de ánimo fueron los predictores más potentes de las quejas somáticas (&amp;#916;R2sup&gt; = .32, para niños; &amp;#916;R2 = .36, para adultos), siendo la contribución de la personalidad menos relevante (&amp;#916;R2 = .07, para niños; &amp;#916;R2 = .12, para adultos). Conclusiones: los programas de promoción de la salud deberían incluir factores emocionales y de personalidad, adaptándose diferencialmente a niños o a adultos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);28(4): 383-388, nov. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157793</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conciencia emocional, estados de ánimo y personalidad, como predictores de las quejas somáticas en niños y adultos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55715^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12038^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
