<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87952</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family medicine in six European countries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article aims to contextualize the situation of the Spanish family practice in Europe in relation with family practice in Italy, England, France, Germany and Denmark.The Spanish family practice is the only one in Europe where doctors are dependent on the health care system, work in multidisciplinary teams and they are the only ones to be paid through a salary. The population perceive family practice to be the most accessible and to have very good quality doctors. And all of this with Spain being the country that spends the least in health care.Some European health systems are trying to introduce some of the features that the Spanish health system has increasingly introduced over the past 20 years, thus becoming a model for other countries(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Del Río, María del Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo pretende dar una visión de la situación actual de la medicina de familia española en Europa, comparándola con la medicina de familia en Italia, Inglaterra, Francia, Alemania y Dinamarca.La medicina de familia española resulta ser la única donde los médicos son dependientes del sistema sanitario, trabajan en equipo multidisciplinar y son los únicos con un salario fijo. La población española opina que es una de las mejores en cuanto a facilidad de acceso y calidad de los médicos. Todo esto siendo España uno de los países con menor gasto en sanidad.Algunos sistemas sanitarios europeos están introduciendo características en la medicina de familia que el sistema sanitario español ya ha introducido progresivamente en los últimos 20 años, por lo que representa un modelo para otros países(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;42(12): 620-625, dic. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La medicina de familia en seis países europeos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
