<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93727</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-6045</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physiotherapy in distal radius fractures: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The distal radius fracture is a common clinical problem that mainly affects elderly women. The use of different modalities of physiotherapy has recently become a routine indication in rehabilitation process in these patients. A synthesis of the evidence is made using a Systematic Review of Randomized Clinical Trials. Objective. Determine whether there is scientific evidence to support the physiotherapy interventions used in the rehabilitation of patients with distal radius fractures. Search Strategy. Only Randomized Control Trials (RCTs) and Controlled Clinical Trials (CCCs) were included in the search. The databases used were MEDLINE, CINAHL, Central, EMBASE, PEDro and LILACS. Results. A total of 9 papers that met our eligibility criteria were selected. Conclusion. There is moderate evidence that low-intensity ultrasound accelerates bone healing. The evidence that a treatment program by a physical therapist is more effective than a home exercises program in the medium term is contradictory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrera Rivas, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Espinoza, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Monclus, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera Eguía, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fractura de radio distal es un problema clínico común que afecta principalmente a mujeres de edad avanzada, el uso de las diferentes modalidades de fisioterapia en el último tiempo se ha transformado en una indicación de rutina en el proceso de rehabilitación de estos pacientes, se realizará una síntesis de la evidencia a través de una revisión sistemática de ensayos clínicos aleatorizados. Objetivo. Determinar si existe evidencia científica que avale las intervenciones fisioterapéuticas usadas en la rehabilitación de pacientes con fractura de radio distal. Estrategia de búsqueda Solo se incluyeron en la búsqueda ensayos clínicos aleatorizados (ECA) y ensayos clínicos controlados (ECC), las bases de datos usadas fueron: MEDLINE, CINAHL, Central, EMBASE, PEDro y LILACS. Resultados. Se seleccionaron 9 artículos que cumplían con nuestros criterios de elegibilidad. Conclusion. existe moderada evidencia que el ultrasonido de baja intensidad acelera la consolidación ósea y la evidencia es contradictoria que un programa de tratamiento realizado por un fisioterapeuta sea más efectivo que un programa de ejercicios en domicilio a mediano plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fisioter. kinesiol. (Ed. impr.);14(1): 25-37, ene.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fisioterapia en fracturas de radio distal: revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12319^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
