<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108373</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Permanent, continuous and of use Education: revealing its concepts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This is a study about the already found concepts in the literature regarding Permanent Education, Continuous Educatiuon and Education of Use, we settled as an objetctive: to analyze the concepts of Permanent Education, Continuous Education and Education of Use and to see how they are related. The integrative assessment was used as methodology, and it was carried out in the databases: Medline, Lilacs, BDEnf. Through the descriptors, the aplication on the criteria, the selection of the study and after having read the tittles and summaries, we reached a result of 25 articles, and after having read the texts two articles were excluded, adding up 23 articles to be analyzed. The articles are classified in three thematic axis, according to the educative process conceived, and from the interpretation of the data we framed these studies in the following emergent categories: Continuous Education as a factor that influences in the professional development, Permanent Education in Health as a pedagogical practice based on the significative learning and Permanent Education, Continuous Education and Education of use : Differences and conceptual frames. We highlitght that many of them are a knowledge produced about the processes of permanent, continuous and Education of use, and that its concepts are clearly different, so they have a complementary and non-exlcuyent meaning. However, in spite of the fact that they are based on different methodologies, there are conflicts when considering each one of these educative processes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tavares, Claudia Mara de Melo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuzatis Gonçalves, Ludimila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dutra Da Costa, Tiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dantas Cavalcanti, Ana Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sardinha Peixoto, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antunes Cortez, Elaine</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se trata de un estudio sobre los conceptos encontrados en la literatura acerca de Educación Permanente, Educación Continuada y Educación de Servicio, donde trazamos como objetivo: Analizar los conceptos de Educación Permanente, Educación Continuada y Educación de Servicio y cómo se relacionan. Se utilizó como metodología la evaluación integradora, y se llevó a cabo en las bases de datos: Medline, Lilacs y BDEnf. A través de los descriptores, la aplicación de los criterios de selección del estudio, y después de leer los títulos y resúmenes, llegamos a um resultado de 25 artículos, y después de leer los textos se excluyeron dos artículos, totalizando 23 artículos para ser analizados. Los artículos se clasifican en tres ejes temáticos, de acuerdo con el proceso educativo concebido, y a partir de la interpretación de los datos encuadramos estos estudios en las siguientes categorías emergidas: Educación Continuada como un factor que influye en el desarrollo profesional, Educación Permanente en Salud como una práctica pedagógica basada en el aprendizaje significativo y Educación Permanente, Educación Continuada y Educación en Servicio: Diferencias y Marcos conceptuales. Destacamos que muchos son conocimientos producidos sobre los procesos de Educación Permanente, Continuada y en Servicio, y que sus conceptos son claramente distintos, por eso tienen un carácter complementario y no excluyente. Sin embargo, a pesar de estar basadas en diferentes metodologías, hay conflictos al conceptuar cada uno de estos procesos educativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(29): 307-323, ene. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108373</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Educación permanente, continuada y de servicio: desvelando sus conceptos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4579^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
