<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108301</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-concept in young dancers and non-practitioners: confirmatory factor analysis of the AF5 scales</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyses the five-factor structure of the AF5 Self-Concept Questionnaire in dance practitioners and non-practitioners. The responses of 1630 adults (490 dancers and 1.240 non dance practitioners) were analysed using structural equation modelling. The oblique factorial structure, proposed by the author&#146;s scale, resulted in a better fit than two alternative structures (one-factor and orthogonal configurations), and was invariant across the two groups. Nevertheless, the factorial means and correlations of the physical with the professional and family dimensions were higher in the dancer group. Reliability was good for both the dancer and non-practitioners group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Carmela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murgui, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo analizó la estructura pentafactorial del Cuestionario de Autoconcepto AF5 en practicantes de danza y no practicantes. Se analizaron las respuestas de 1630 participantes (490, de la modalidad de danza clásica y contemporánea y 1240 no practicantes) mediante modelos de ecuaciones estructurales. Los resultados indicaron que el modelo pentadimensional oblicuo, propuesto por los autores, se ajustaba mejor que los alternativos unifactorial y ortogonal, y que esta estructura penta-factorial fue invariante entre ambos grupos, si bien el grupo de practicantes relacionaba en mayor grado el ámbito físico-deportivo con el profesional y familiar, y presentó medias superiores en todas las dimensiones del autoconcepto. En ambos grupos, se obtuvieron valores aceptables de fiabilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;21(2): 263-269, jul.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108301</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autoconcepto en jóvenes practicantes de danza y no practicantes: análisis factorial confirmatorio de la escala AF5</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3634^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3634^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
