<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153551</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The palliative treatment and the pain treatment in dementia have a significant importance for the welfare of the patient and the family. Focusing the care and the treatment of these patients requires a correct identification of their palliative needs and an appropriate adaptation of cares and attentions. This adaptation concerns physical, psychological, emotional and spiritual aspects that could affect both the patient and the family in order to achieve their maximum well-being. One of the symptoms which is the most difficult to recognize and treat in the patient with advanced dementia is the pain. For this reason, it is necessary to use adapted scales of assessment and all the therapeutic resources available. The most important problems to treat the pain in an advanced stage of dementia are: the communication with the patient, the information given to the patient and the family and the training and the sensitivity on this issue among the professional caregivers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bertran Muñoz, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento paliativo y el tratamiento del dolor en la demencia tienen una gran importancia para el confort del paciente y de su familia. Enfocar el cuidado y tratamiento de estos pacientes se basa en una correcta identificación de sus necesidades paliativas y en una adaptación exquisita de los cuidados y atenciones. Esta adaptación se dirige a los aspectos físicos, psicológicos, emocionales y espirituales que puedan afectar tanto al paciente como a su familia para conseguir el máximo confort. Uno de los síntomas más difíciles de reconocer y tratar en el paciente con demencia avanzada es el dolor, para el que es necesario usar escalas adaptadas de valoración y todas las terapéuticas que tenemos a nuestro alcance. Los problemas más importantes para enfocar el dolor y su tratamiento en la fase avanzada de la demencia son: la comunicación con el paciente, la información al paciente y su familia y la formación y la sensibilidad sobre este tema entre el personal asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(224): 51-57, abr.-jun. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153551</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento paliativo y del dolor en pacientes con demencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9211^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
