<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102155</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variation of health care cost by the participation of patients in clinical trials. Pilot study in bronchial asthma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In Western Europe, the incidence of asthma has doubled in the last 10 years, generating a greater economic burden for the health care systems. The purpose of this study was to quantify the savings for the health care system derived from the participation of an asthmatic patient in a clinical trial (CT) in a tertiary level hospital. The analysis was conducted with a descriptive and retrospective design. As principal variable, the total cost was obtained for the health care system  during the periods of participation in the CT and during the control period as the secondary variables were cost per complementary tests, cost per consultation and cost per anti-asthma drugs. On an average, participation of an asthma patient in a CT meant a total savings (drugs, consultations, and complementary tests) for the health care system of 21,18 &#128;  per week. When analyzing the medication by itself that the patients receive during the trial treatment period, the savings reaches 9,71 &#128; per patient and week. The gross and net savings could not be adequately explained from the factors considered: control costs, severity, type of trial, age and gender. We conclude that the participation of a patient in an Asthma CT in a tertiary hospital generates a financial benefit for the health care system that becomes clearer as the severity of the condition increases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Francés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Vicente, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almonacid Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo Alonso, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En Europa occidental la incidencia de asma se ha duplicado en los últimos 10 años, generando una gran carga económica para los sistemas de salud. El objetivo de este estudio fue cuantificar el ahorro para el sistema sanitario derivado de la participación de un paciente asmático en un ensayo clínico (EC) en un hospital de nivel terciario. El análisis se realizó  con un diseño descriptivo y retrospectivo. Como variable principal se tomó el coste total para el sistema de salud durante los periodos de participación en el EC y durante el periodo control y como variables secundarias el coste por pruebas complementarias, el coste por consultas y el coste por fármacos antiasmáticos. En promedio, la participación de un paciente asmático en un EC supuso un ahorro total (fármacos, consultas y pruebas complementarias) para el sistema sanitario de 21,18 &#128; por semana. Si se contabiliza como ahorro sólo la medicación que reciben los pacientes durante el período de tratamiento del ensayo, el ahorro asciende a 9,71 &#128; por paciente y semana. El ahorro bruto y neto no pudieron explicarse adecuadamente a partir de los factores considerados: costes control, gravedad, tipo de ensayo, edad y sexo.  Para el ahorro bruto, sólo el nivel de gravedad del paciente reveló una cierta influencia. Concluimos que la participación de un paciente en un EC de asma en un hospital terciario genera un beneficio económico para el sistema sanitario que se hace más patente a medida que aumenta la gravedad del proceso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;12(1): 15-18, ene.-mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variación del gasto sanitario por la participación de pacientes en ensayos clínicos. Estudio piloto en asma bronquial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30355^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32858^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
