<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104919</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Periodontal surgical therapy: Review. Concepts. Considerations. Procedures. Techniques</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Periodontal treatment can be divided in three different phases most frequently superposed: cause related or initial phase, corrective phase and supportive periodontal phase. Because the majority of these pathologies are related to plaque accumulation, periodontal surgical treatment might only be considered as an adjunct to cause-related periodontal therapy. The kind of surgery performed, the number of sites included and the moment at which it should performed is decided after evaluating for the initial cause-related therapy results. The ultimate objective of periodontal surgical treatment is the long term preservation of the periodontium. Periodontal surgery can contribute to this end creating accessibility for an adequate scaling and root planning therefore restoring the gingival morphology which facilitates the automatic plaque control of the patient. Developed surgical techniques must be evaluated on the basis of their potential to facilitate the elimination of subgingival deposits, as well as facilitate plaque control and thus improve the long term preservation of the periodontium. In the present article the authors review the basis of surgical periodontal treatment as well as related concepts and considerations, objectives, indications and contraindications, procedures and factors that determine the selection of one or the other surgical technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Matos  Cruz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascones-Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento global de pacientes con enfermedad periodontal se divide en tres fases diferentes que, con frecuencia, se superponen: fase de terapia causal o fase inicial y la fase correctiva o fase de soporte periodontal o de mantenimiento. Como la mayoría de las formas de enfermedad periodontal son trastornos relacionados con la placa bacteriana, el tratamiento periodontal quirúrgico está considerado como un auxiliar del tratamiento periodontal causal inicial. Así mismo, la decisión respecto a qué tipo de cirugía periodontal debe realizarse, cuántas localizaciones deben incluirse y en qué momento del tratamiento, se adopta tras haberse evaluado el efecto de las medidas iniciales relacionadas con la causa. El objetivo principal del tratamiento periodontal quirúrgico es la preservación a largo plazo del periodonto. La cirugía periodontal puede contribuir, a este propósito, creando accesibilidad para el raspado y alisado radicular correctos, realizados por el profesional y al restablecer una morfología gingival que facilita el autocontrol de placa por parte del paciente. Las diversas técnicas quirúrgicas desarrolladas a lo largo del tiempo deben evaluarse sobre la base de su potencial para facilitar la eliminación de los depósitos subgingivales, bien como facilitar el autocontrol de la placa y así mejorar la preservación a largo plazo del periodonto. En el presente artículo se pretende realizar una revisión de los fundamentos del tratamiento periodontal quirúrgico, conceptos y consideraciones, objetivos, indicaciones y contraindicaciones, procedimientos y factores que determinan la elección de una u otra técnica quirúrgica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;23(3): 155-170, dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104919</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento periodontal quirúrgico: Revisión.Conceptos. Consideraciones. Procedimientos. Técnicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54275^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6032^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6029^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13745^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
