<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98583</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Noninvasive ventilation in acute heart failure: use of continuous positive airway pressure in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Noninvasive ventilation is one of the ventilatory support systems available for treating the patient with acute respiratory failure. Orotracheal intubation is not required. The main modalities are continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) and bilevel positive airway pressure (BiPAP). Both alleviate respiratory distress quickly and have proven useful for treating acute heart failure due to acute pulmonary edema or pulmonary hypertension. The need for intubation and mortality are reduced. More experience has accumulated with CPAP, which is easier to manage and is associated with few complications. BiPAP, which is more complicated and requires more staff training, has been shown to improve respiratory failure more quickly in patients with heart failure and to be more effective in patients with hypercapnia or respiratory muscle fatigue. In spite of these benefits, noninvasive ventilation is little used in hospital emergency departments, probably because of the lack of staff training and commitment, low availability of material resources, and the absence of clear protocols, which ought to be available in all hospitals. This review aims to describe the role that noninvasive ventilation plays in improving oxygen saturation in the treatment of acute heart failure due to acute pulmonary edema or pulmonary hypertension and to define an appropriate protocol for using these modalities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carratala, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masip, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ventilación no invasiva (VNI) es uno de los soportes ventilatorios que se ofrece al paciente con insuficiencia respiratoria aguda (IRA) y que no precisa intubación orotraqueal. Los modos usados con más frecuencia en la IRA son la presión positiva continúa en la vía área (CPAP) y la ventilación con doble nivel de presión (BIPAP). Ambas modalidades han demostrado su utilidad en el tratamiento de la insuficiencia cardiaca aguda(ICA) por edema agudo de pulmón (EAP) o hipertensiva, al mejorar con mayor rapidez la IRA y reducir las necesidades de intubación y la mortalidad en algunos pacientes. Existe una mayor experiencia en el modo CPAP, más sencillo en su manejo y con pocas complicaciones, que con el modo BIPAP, más complejo y que requiere un mayor entrenamiento. Cuando se comparan ambos métodos en pacientes con ICA el modo BIPAP sólo ha demostrado mejorar la IRA con mayor rapidez y es más efectivo en pacientes con hipercapnia o fatiga respiratoria. A pesar de estos beneficios, el uso de la VNI en los servicios de urgencias hospitalarios está poco extendido probablemente debido a la falta de entrenamiento e implicación de los profesionales, la baja disponibilidad de recursos materiales y a la ausencia de protocolos claros, que deberían estar disponibles en todos los hospitales. La presente revisión pretende establecer el papel de la VNI como método de oxigenación en el tratamiento de la ICA por EAP e hipertensiva y definir un protocolo de actuación que facilite su cumplimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(1): 49-55, feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98583</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ventilación no invasiva en la insuficiencia cardiaca aguda: uso de CPAP en los servicios de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
