<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-8095</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nasal Leishmaniasis in an HIV- positive patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Leishmania is currently one of the most clinically important protozoa in otorhinolaryngology. Mediterranean countries, including Spain, have endemic HIV and L. infantum. Dogs are the most important Leishmania reservoir. Leishmaniasis is transmitted basically by the bite of infected female Phlebotomus sandflies. Its clinical development depends mainly on the host's cellular immunity (TCD4+ lymphocyte count). About 400 cases of HIV-visceral leishmaniasis have been reported in Spain. However, exclusively cutaneous presentation of HIV-leishmaniasis coinfection has been observed in only 2-3% of cases. We report the case of a female HIV+ patient who developed cutaneous leishmaniasis of the nasal vestibule by L. infantum. The patient was treated satisfactorily with a combination of parenteral Pentostam (sodium stilbogluconate) and periodic intralesional injections of Pentostam. The patient was included in a secondary prophylaxis protocol for visceral leishmaniasis with a monthly dose of Glucantime (meglumine antimoniate) for life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente, la Leishmania es uno de los protozoos de mayor relevancia clínica en el área ORL. Los países del litoral mediterráneo, entre ellos España, son endémicos para el HIV y la L. infantum, siendo el perro doméstico el reservorio más importante para esta última. La leishmaniasis se transmite, básicamente, a través de la picadura del mosquito flebótomo hembra infectado y su desarrollo clínico depende principalmente del estado de inmunidad celular del huésped (recuento de lin citos TCD4+). Hasta el momento actual, se han descrito alrededor de 400 casos de coinfección HIV-leishmaniasis visceral en España, mientras que la afectación cutánea exclusiva en esta coinfección HIVleishmaniasis sólo se da en el 2-3 por ciento de casos. Presentamos el caso clínico de una paciente HIV+ que desarrolló una leishmaniasis cutánea de vestíbulo nasal por L. infantum y que fue tratada satisfactoriamente mediante la combinación de Pentostam (estilbogluconato sódico) parenteral junto a inyecciones intralesionales periódicas de Pentostam. Esta paciente fue incluida en un protocolo de profilaxis secundaria de leishmaniasis visceral con Glucantime (antimoniato de meglumina) a dosis mensuales, de por vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;51(2): 169-173, mar. 2000. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leishmaniasis nasal en paciente HIV+</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Subirana, FX</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encarnación, LF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pollán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crego, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naches, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grasa, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-8095</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29422^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24794</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28201</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
