<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63842</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The qualitative techniques of social research make up a combination of tools for collection and analysis of information with epistemological rationale that is differentiated from other types of techniques (for example, the quantitative survey). The basic rationales for the development of research through discussion groups and/or comprehensive interviews are introduced in this chapter. There are three axes described in this chapter. In the first one, the place occupied by the so-called qualitative techniques in the group of research is discussed. Those study objects that can be approached through any of these techniques are determined. When useful to clarify the specificity of the qualitative techniques, a brief comparison is also made with the characteristic traits of the commonly called quantitative techniques (specifically, the survey). In the second and third sections, two of the qualitative techniques used most in social research in general and social-health care specifically are summarized to some degree. This refers to the discussion group and comprehensive interview. The characteristics traits are mentioned for both techniques and some suggestions are made for their adequate use. The fourth section deals qualitatively with a central and common problem to all the techniques: sampling and screening of the specific individuals who will participate in the field study phase</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Moreno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las técnicas cualitativas de investigación social constituyen un conjunto de herramientas de recogida y análisis de la información con fundamentos epistemológicos propios y diferenciados de otro tipo de técnicas (por ejemplo, la encuesta cuantitativa). En el presente capítulo se introducen los fundamentos básicos para el desarrollo de investigaciones a través de grupos de discusión y/o entrevistas en profundidad. Tres son los ejes que articulan este capítulo. En primer lugar, se discute el lugar que ocupan las denominadas técnicas cualitativas en el conjunto de la investigación, determinando aquellos objetos de estudio susceptibles de abordaje a través de alguna de estas técnicas. En la medida en que es útil para iluminar la especificidad de las técnicas cualitativas, se procede igualmente a una breve comparación con los rasgos característicos de las comúnmente denominadas técnicas cuantitativas (en concreto, la encuesta). En el segundo y tercer epígrafes se describen con cierta concreción dos de las técnicas cualitativas más utilizadas en la investigación social en general, y sociosanitaria en particular. Se trata del grupo de discusión y de la entrevista en profundidad. De ambas técnicas se mencionan sus rasgos característicos y se ofrecen algunas sugerencias para su adecuada utilización. El cuarto epígrafe se ocupa de un problema central y común a todas las técnicas de carácter cualitativo: el muestreo y la selección de los individuos concretos que participarán en la fase de trabajo de campo</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(2): 75-79, feb. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63842</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
