<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77290</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Approaches to the Principle of Autonomy in dialysis treatment: Informed Consent and Living Will</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At present, the principle of autonomy seeks to provide the framework for relations between healthcare professionals and patients in the context of their care. Currently, the expression of the principle of the patient&#146;s autonomy in decisions concerning his or her treatment is materialized in the Informed Consent and Living Will. The aim of this work is to verify what knowledge terminal chronic renal insufficiency patients undergoing dialysis in our hospital have, with regard to Informed Consent and the Living Will and to know whether patients consider themselves to be well-informed about the state of their health at the start of their kidney disease and at present. A retrospective, observational and descriptive study of 55 patients of our service. The results show that Informed Consent is unknown to the majority of the patients and that the Living Will is not part of the information they receive. The information received at the start of treatment is satisfactory in the case of all the patients. At present, patients undergoing peritoneal dialysis are more satisfied and have also had the possibility of choosing their treatment. Patients on haemodialysis would like greater autonomy in the decisions concerning their treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Julve Ibáñez, Maricel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simal Vélez, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salillas Adot, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Jurado,  Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad el Principio de Autonomía pretende marcar la relación asistencial entre los profesionales sanitarios y los pacientes. Actualmente, la expresión del Principio de Autonomía del paciente en las decisiones referidas a su tratamiento se plasma en el Consentimiento Informado y el Documento de Voluntades Anticipadas. El objetivo de este trabajo, es verificar que conocimientos tiene el paciente con insuficiencia renal crónica terminal en tratamiento de diálisis en nuestro hospital, referido al Consentimiento Informado y el Documento de Voluntades Anticipadas y saber si el paciente se consideró bien informado sobre su estado de salud al inicio de su enfermedad renal y en la actualidad. Estudio retrospectivo, observacional y descriptivo en 55 pacientes de nuestro servicio. Los resultados muestran que el Consentimiento Informado no es conocido por la mayoría de los pacientes y que el Documento de Voluntades Anticipadas no forma parte de la información que recibe. La información recibida al inicio del tratamiento es satisfactoria en todos los pacientes. En la actualidad están más satisfechos los pacientes en diálisis peritoneal y también han tenido más posibilidad de elegir tratamiento. Los enfermos en hemodiálisis desean tener más autonomía en las decisiones referidas a su tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;12(3): 184-188, jul.-sept. 2009. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximaciones al Principio de Autonomía en el tratamientode diálisis: el Consentimiento Informado y las Voluntades Anticipadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28849</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7851^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
