<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131504</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screening for tuberculosis by igra assay in resident physicians incorporated in May 2014 in a Tertiary level hospital of Madrid Community</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Tuberculosis is a communicable disease largely through air by species of the genus Mycobacterium (M. tuberculosis, M. africanum and M. bovis) but the usual etiologic agent is M. tuberculosis. The main objective of this study is to determine the incidence of TB by IGRA technique, in resident physicians from first year who joined in May 2014 in a tertiary hospital of Madrid Community. Material and Methods: This is a cross-sectional study that collects data from the 136 residents (doctors, nurses, psychologists, biologists, physicists, chemists) who joined in May 2014 in a tertiary hospital of Madrid Community and who underwent initial health examination. Results: we have identified 5 cases with latent tuberculosis infection (a Spanish resident and another 4 from abroad) and sent to the Service of Pneumology to receive prophylactic treatment. Not found any case of active TB. Conclusions: residents from abroad have a higher incidence of TB as Spanish nationals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña Picaza, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tenica, Julian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santillán, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marzola, Marco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neyra, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La tuberculosis es una enfermedad transmisible, de forma mayoritaria por vía aérea de paciente con enfermedad activa a individuo sano, producida por especies del género Mycobacterium (M. tuberculosis principalmente, M. africanum y M. bovis). El principal objetivo de este estudio es determinar la incidencia de la TB, mediante la técnica IGRA, en los residentes del primer año que se han incorporado en mayo de 2014 en un hospital de tercer nivel de la Comunidad de Madrid. Material y Métodos: es un estudio transversal que recoge los datos de los 136 residentes (médicos, enfermeros, psicólogos, biólogos, físicos, químicos) que se han incorporado en mayo de 2014 en un Hospital General Universitario de tercer nivel de la Comunidad de Madrid y a quienes se les realizó el examen inicial de salud. Resultados: se han identificado 5 casos con infección latente tuberculosa (un residente español y otros 4 procedentes del extranjero) y se han enviado al Servicio de Neumología para recibir tratamiento profiláctico. No se ha encontrado ningún caso de TB activa. Conclusiones: los residentes procedentes del extranjero presentan mayor incidencia de la TB que los nacionales españoles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;23(4): 432-437, dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Screening de tuberculosis mediante la técnica IGRA en los residentes incorporados en mayo de 2014 en un hospital de tercer nivel de la Comunidad de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
