<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050318</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish version and reliability of the «social network questionnaire», applied to people with severe mental illness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aims of this paperis to present the Spanish version of theSocial Network Questionnaire -SNQ- andits reliability that has been analysed ona sample of people with severe mentalillness in Andalusia (Spain).Method: The questionnaire was translatedinto Spanish and its inter-rate andtest-retest agreement were assessed ina sample of 30 subjects, residents in differentsheltered homes. Afterwards, theinternal consistency was assessed usingthe answerers of 225 subjects of similarcharacteristics. For the statistical analysisIntraclass and Cronbach coefficientswere used.Results: Inter-rate agreement: Intraclassfrom 0.716 to 1.000; Test-retestagreement: Intraclass from 0.412 to 1.000;Internal Consistency: Alfa=0.723.Conclusion: The Spanish version ofthe SNQ (CURES) is an assessment instrumentwith reasonable reliability to assessthe social network of people with severemental illness in residential facilities</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cubillana, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laviana, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perdiguero, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Marcelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna, Juan de Dios</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo de esteartículo es presentar la adaptación españoladel «Questionario Sulla Rete Sociale» -SNQ- (Cuestionario de Red Social-CURES-), cuya fiabilidad se ha analizadoen una muestra de personas con trastornomental severo de Andalucía (España).Metodología: Se tradujo el cuestionarioal español y se valoró la fiabilidad entrejueces y la consistencia entre instantes enuna muestra de 30 sujetos residentes enalojamientos protegidos. Posteriormentese evaluó la consistencia interna a partir delas respuestas de 225 sujetos de similarescaracterísticas. Para el análisis estadísticose utilizaron los Coeficientes CorrelaciónIntraclase y Alfa de Cronbach.Resultados: Fiabilidad entre jueces: Intraclaseentre 0.716 y 1.000; Consistenciaentre instantes: Intraclase entre 0.412 y1.000; Consistencia Interna: Alfa=0.723.Conclusiones: La versión españoladel SNQ (CURES) es un instrumento demedida que presenta niveles razonablesde fiabilidad para evaluar la red social depersonas con trastorno mental severo enestructuras residenciales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;26(97): 135-150, ene.-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050318</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación y fiabilidad del cuestionario de red social, versión española del «questionario sulla rete sociale», aplicado a personas con trastorno mental severo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
