<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88426</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Playing of wind instruments is associated with an obstructive pattern in the spirometry of adolescents with a good aerobic resistance capacity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveThere is controversy in the medical literature regarding the beneficial or detrimental effects of playing wind musical instruments on the respiratory system. The aim of this study is to analyse this relationship, taking the physical condition of the subjects into consideration.DesignCross-sectional observational study.SettingPublic institution with coordinated medium grade musical instruction and primary and secondary education.ParticipantsYoung performers (between 13 and 17 years).DataWe collected basic epidemiological parameters (gender, age, weight, size, heath status), and each subject underwent a fitness test (&#147;course navette&#148; cardiorespiratory fitness test) and a forced spirometry.ResultsWe included 90 students, 53 females and 37 males. Thirty two were wind instrument players and 58 studied other instruments. The two groups were homogeneous with respect to gender, age and body mass index. The maximum oxygen uptake showed no significant difference (P=0.255), further demonstrating an adequate level of fitness compared to the general population. FVC was normal and similar in both groups (P=0.197). The FEV1 percentage and the FEV1/FVC ratio were significantly lower (P&lt;0.0005) in the &#147;wind&#148; group. Practice with wind instruments behaved as a predictor of pathological FEV1/FVC (&lt;70%) in the multivariate analysis (P&lt;0.0005).ConclusionThe study of wind instruments was associated with an obstructive spirometric pattern in young musicians with a normal level of physical fitness(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tapias, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granell, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granell, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoExiste controversia en la literatura médica respecto al efecto beneficioso o perjudicial de la práctica con instrumentos musicales de viento sobre el sistema respiratorio. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar esta relación en sujetos jóvenes en periodo de aprendizaje, ponderando su nivel de condición física.DiseñoEstudio observacional transversal.EmplazamientoCentro Integrado de Enseñanzas Artísticas y Musicales (estudios musicales reglados de Grado Medio) y de Educación Primaria y Secundaria, de titularidad pública.ParticipantesJóvenes estudiantes de entre 13&#150;17 años.Mediciones principalesSe recogieron parámetros epidemiológicos básicos (sexo, edad, peso, talla, estado de salud) y a cada sujeto se le realizó un test de condición física (prueba de aptitud cardiorespiratoria de «course navette»), y una espirometría forzada.ResultadosSe incluyeron 90 alumnos, 53 mujeres y 37 varones, de los cuales 32 eran instrumentistas de viento y 58 de otros instrumentos. Los 2 grupos fueron homogéneos respecto a sexo, edad e índice de masa corporal. El consumo máximo de oxígeno no mostró diferencias significativas (p=0,255), manifestando además un adecuado nivel de condición física respecto a la población general. La CVF fue normal y comparable en ambos grupos (p=0,197). El VEMS porcentual y el cociente VEMS/CVF fueron significativamente menores (p&lt;0,0005) en el grupo de viento. La práctica con instrumentos de viento se comportó como variable predictora de VEMS/CVF patológico (&lt;70%) en el análisis multivariante (p&lt;0,0005).ConclusionesEl estudio de instrumentos de viento se asoció con un patrón espirométrico obstructivo en músicos jóvenes con un nivel normal de condición física(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;43(3): 134-139, mar. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El estudio de instrumentos de viento se asocia con un patrón obstructivo en la espirometría de adolescentes con buena capacidad de resistencia aeróbica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d405^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13530^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1970^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
