<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042361</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consequences of work stress: an application of Warr´s vitamin Model to predict anxiety and depression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Warr's vitamin model (1994, 1996) is a prevalent theoretical model on occupational stress, and it presents hypothesis pretty different to other prevalent model of work stress as well as accurate predictions. Amongst the most relevant hypothesis are those of non-linear relationships between working conditions and worker's well-being, and the moderator effects of personal characteristics on the stressors-well-being relationships. Nevertheless of its theoretical appealing Warr's model has not been widely tested, and when empirically tested the results are contradictory. The aim of this paper is to empirically test the two broad hypothesis of Warr's vitamin model: non-linear effects ofworking conditions on well-being, and moderator effects of personal characteristics on these relationships. The dependent variables used are the general health questionnaire and its two components, anxiety and depression. Results do not support the non-linear hypothesis of Warr's model, and the support for the moderator effects of personal characteristics on the stressors-well being is weak</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tomás, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El modelo vitamínico de Warr (1994, 1996) es uno de los modelos teóricos prevalentes sobre el estrés ocupacional, y presenta hipótesis, con predicciones ajustadas, relativamente diferentes a otros modelos. Entre las hipótesis más relevantes están la de no linealidad en las relaciones entre condiciones de trabajo y bienestar del trabajador, así como el efecto moderador de las condiciones personales sobre estas relaciones. Pese a sus interesantes propuestas se ha puesto a prueba relativamente poco en la literatura, y cuando se ha probado, el apoyo empírico ha resultado parcial. El objetivo de este trabajo es poner a prueba las dos hipótesis principales del modelo de Warr, la no linealidad y los efectos moderadores, en la predicción de la salud general medida mediante el GHQ-12 y sus dos factores, ansiedad y depresión. Los resultados no encuentran apoyo empírico, en nuestros datos, para la no linealidad en las relaciones, y solamente apoyo parcial para los efectos moderadores, de interacción, de las características personales, en las relaciones entre las condiciones de trabajo y la salud</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;11(2/3): 233-245, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042361</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Puesta a prueba de algunas predicciones del modelo vitamínico de Warr en su relación con ansiedad y depresión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
