<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046664</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Insulin resistance as an idependent risk factor for cardiovascular disease: clinical assessment and therapy approaches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Insulin resistance of glucose metabolism is a typical feature of        type 2 diabetes mellitus but it can be observed in several other common        clinical conditions and also in many apparently healthy subjects.        Overall, as many as 30-40% of subjects from the general population        are insulin resistant. The euglycemic hyperinsulinemic clamp        is the gold standard technique in the assessment of insulin resistance        but it cannot be used in epidemiological and clinical settings. In        these situations a feasible surrogate approach might be the Homeostasis        Model Assessment, based upon the measurement of fasting        glucose and insulin concentrations. Insulin possesses a number of        biological effects that can be regarded as anti-atherogenic. These        effects are blunted in insulin resistant states, predisposing to the        development and the progression of atherosclerosis. Yet, insulin        resistance is strongly related to several classic cardiovascular risk factors        such as hyperglycemia, obesity, high triglycerides, low HDL cholesterol,        hypertension and microalbuminuria. Finally, insulin resistance        is related to many non-traditional risk factors like PAI-1, fibrinogen,        CRP and other markers of inflammation. Therefore, insulin        resistance is the common denominator of a constellation of risk factors        and in most cases it plays a causal role: it is a pathogenic factor        of several risk factors. In a number of cross-sectional and longitudinal        studies insulin resistance of glucose metabolism was able to predict prevalent or incident cardiovascular disease also independently        of classic and, in some studies, also of non-traditional risk        factors. Insulin sensitizing strategies based upon changes in life style        (e.g., reducing caloric intake and/or increasing physical activity) in        non-diabetic subjects as well as the use of insulin sensitizers like        metformin or thiazolidinediones in type 2 diabetic subjects yielded        a prevention of cardiovascular disease. These data confirm the major        role played by insulin resistance in cardiovascular disease and suggest        that this common metabolic disorder should be effectively targeted        in order to reduce cardiovascular risk</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bonora, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">No disponible</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;21(4): 255-261, oct.-dic. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046664</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insulin resistance as an independent risk factor for cardiovascular disease: clinical assessment and therapy approaches</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38089^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
