<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101247</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spectral analysis of heart rate variability in trained young men: comparison of endurance and resistance training</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Heart rate variability (HRV) is a non-invasive tool for studying autonomic modulation of cardiovascular function. According to the specificity principle of training, each type of exercise causes specific adaptations. However, whether this concept also applies to HRV has not been established. The aim of this study was to compare the spectral components of HRV between endurance-trained and strength-trained young men. Material and methods: Cross sectional analytical descriptive study. Spectral components of HRV at rest were analysed from short records in 12 runners, 10 weight lifters and 11 not physically active control subjects. Results: Endurance-trained subjects showed the lowest values in the low frequency component (LF) and the highest values at high frequency (HF), but these differences were not statistically significant. Total spectral power was similar in all groups (P=.103), as well as the ratio of low frequency components divided into high frequency (LF/HF) (P=.094). Heart rate at rest in aerobically trained group was significantly lower compared to strength-trained group (P&lt;.01) and controls (P&lt;.001). Conclusions: The results showed no effect of long-term regular aerobic or anaerobic physical training, on spectral components of HRV. In our aerobically trained subjects, rest bradycardia was not explained by changes in the autonomic control of cardiovascular function(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Guzmán, Johan Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbina, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón, Carlos Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Romero, Dario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La variabilidad de la frecuencia cardíaca (VFC) permite estudiar de forma no invasiva la modulación autonómica de la función cardiovascular. Según el principio de especificidad del entrenamiento, cada tipo de ejercicio produce adaptaciones específicas. Sin embargo, no se ha establecido si este concepto también es aplicable a la VFC. El presente estudio tiene como objetivo comparar los componentes espectrales de la VFC en hombres jóvenes entrenados aeróbicamente y anaeróbicamente. Material y métodos: Estudio analítico descriptivo de corte transversal. Se analizaron los componentes espectrales de la VFC en reposo a partir de registros cortos en 12 corredores, 10 levantadores de peso y 11 sujetos control, no activos físicamente. Resultados: Los sujetos entrenados aeróbicamente presentaron los valores más bajos en el componente de baja frecuencia (BF) y los valores más altos en el de alta frecuencia (AF), pero estas diferencias no fueron estadísticamente significativas. El poder espectral total fue similar en todos los grupos (p=0,103), al igual que la relación del componente de BF dividido en el de AF (p=0,094). La frecuencia cardíaca en reposo en el grupo entrenado aeróbicamente fue significativamente menor con respecto al grupo entrenado anaeróbicamente (p&lt;0,01) y al control (p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones: Los resultados no mostraron efecto del entrenamiento físico regular a largo plazo, ya fuese aeróbico o anaeróbico, sobre los componentes espectrales de la VFC. La bradicardia en reposo observada en nuestros sujetos de estudio entrenados aeróbicamente, no se explica por cambios en el control autonómico de la función cardiovascular(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);47(174): 41-47, abr.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101247</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los componentes espectrales de la variabilidad cardíaca en hombres jóvenes entrenados: comparación del entrenamiento aeróbico y anaeróbico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
