<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97544</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Users&#146; perception of a harm reduction program in an outpatient drug dependency treatment center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives We analyzed the perspective of users enrolled in a harm reduction program that provides syringe exchange, an educational room for «warmth and coffee», a methadone maintenance program, a room for supervised drug consumption, a place for personal hygiene, and medical and psychosocial follow-up. The particularity of this program lies in its integration within an outpatient drug treatment center forming part of a general hospital. Methods We performed a descriptive study using qualitative methods. Theoretical sampling was conducted. Twelve in-depth interviews and one focus group composed of eight users were carried out. Information analysis was based on grounded theory. Literal transcriptions were coded and subsequently sorted into broad categories. Three researchers participated in this process and finally a fourth researcher triangulated the results. Results Five dimensions were identified in the users&#146; discourse: accessibility, service, relationship, localization, and identity. Each consisted of several topics that were evaluated based on the participants&#146; experiences and expectations. The dimension of identity emerged as a distinctive element in patient-program bonding. Conclusions The users&#146; overall evaluation of the program was positive. Facilitators and barriers influencing patient-program bonding were identified and participants suggested ways to remove barriers. The coexistence among users of the harm reduction program and patients treated conventionally provoked ambivalence but the team's management was deemed helpful in easing the difficulties arising from this situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Voltes, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daigre, Constanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Cintas, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalvo, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comín, Marina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roncero, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Explorar la perspectiva de los usuarios y analizar los factores que influyen en su vinculación en un programa de reducción de daños (REDAN) que presta los siguientes servicios: intercambio de jeringuillas, espacio educativo de calor y café, programa de mantenimiento con metadona, sala de consumo higiénico supervisado, espacio para la higiene personal y seguimiento sanitario y psicosocial. Este programa presenta la particularidad de estar integrado en un ambulatorio de drogodependencias situado en un recinto hospitalario. Métodos Estudio descriptivo realizado con metodología cualitativa. Se realizó un muestreo teórico. Se saturaron los contenidos mediante 12 entrevistas en profundidad y un grupo focal con ocho participantes. El análisis de la información se basó en la Grounded Theory. Las transcripciones literales fueron codificadas descriptivamente y luego se generaron categorías amplias. Este procedimiento se realizó en un principio por tres investigadores y finalmente un cuarto investigador trianguló la información. Resultados Emergen cinco dimensiones (accesibilidad, servicios, relación, localización e identidad) compuestas por diferentes temas valorados desde las expectativas y experiencias de los usuarios. La dimensión «identidad» otorga un elemento distintivo respecto a la vinculación con el programa. Conclusión En general, los usuarios valoran positivamente el programa REDAN. Respecto a la vinculación, describen aspectos facilitadores y otros deficitarios que pueden suponer barreras, frente a las cuales realizan sugerencias. Aspectos como la convivencia entre los usuarios del programa REDAN y los pacientes en tratamiento orientado a la abstinencia generan ambivalencia, pero se identifica que la gestión por parte del equipo minimiza estas dificultades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(6): 446-452, nov. -dic. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97544</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de los usuarios de un programa de reducción de daños integrado en un ambulatorio de drogodependencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d556^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
