<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116367</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bronchopulmonary dysplasia: definitions and classifications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bronchopulmonary dysplasia is the most common sequelae related to very low birth weight infants, mostly with those of extremely low birth weight. Even with advances in prevention and treatment of respiratory distress syndrome associated with prematurity, there is still no decrease in the incidence in this population, although a change in its clinical expression and severity has been observed. There are, however, differences in its frequency between health centres, probably due to a non-homogeneously used clinical definition. In this article, the Committee of Standards of the Spanish Society of Neonatology wishes to review the current diagnosis criteria of bronchopulmonary dysplasia to reduce, as much as possible, these intercentre differences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Hernando, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botet Mussons, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rite Gracia, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lorenzo, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Luna, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echaniz Urcelay, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Carrillo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La displasia broncopulmonar sigue siendo la secuela más frecuente relacionada con los recién nacidos de muy bajo peso al nacer y especialmente con aquellos con pesos extremadamente bajos. Pese a los avances en la prevención y los cuidados de la insuficiencia respiratoria asociada a la prematuridad, no ha ocurrido un descenso en su incidencia en esta población, aunque sí hemos asistido en los últimos años a un cambio en su expresión clínica y en su gravedad. Existen, sin embargo, diferencias aún importantes entre los distintos centros en cuanto a la frecuencia de su presentación, probablemente debido a la aplicación de un diagnóstico clínico no homogéneo. En este artículo, la Comisión de Estándares de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología quiere revisar los criterios diagnósticos de la displasia broncopulmonar para reducir, en la medida de lo posible, la variabilidad intercentro de la misma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);79(4): 262-262[e1-e6], oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Displasia broncopulmonar: definiciones y clasificación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1244^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2024^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
