<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136416</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional intelligence, quality of interpersonal relationships and empathy in university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to examine the link between emotional intelligence, measured by self-report and ability scales, and the quality of interpersonal relationships and empathy in university students. Besides, this study examined the contribution of these emotional intelligence scales as predictors of these dimensions. One hundred and eighty-four Spanish undergraduates completed a battery of questionnaires which included the Spanish Trait MetaMood Scale-24 (a self-reported emotional intelligence Scale), the MSCEIT managing emotions of Relationships branch (an ability measure subscale of emotional intelligence), the Inventory ofNetwork (a inventory of interpersonal relationship quality) and the Interpersonal Reactivity Index (an empathy questionnaire). Pearson correlations and multiple regression analyses were performed on the data. Results showed significant associations between different aspects of emotional intelligence and dimensions of interpersonal relationships and empathy. In addition, multiple regression analyses showed that the MSCEIT emotions-managing branch was closely associated with dimensions of interpersonal relationships (Intimacy, Affection and Antagonism), but only with one dimension of empathy (empathic concern). On the other hand, TMMS subscales were closely associated with empathy subscales (perspective taking, empathic concern and personal distress) but only with one dimension of interpersonal relationships (antagonism). Findings are discussed with respect to different theoretical conceptualizations and measurement of emotional intelligence within this recent field of research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Berrocal, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Extremera Pacheco, Natalio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue examinar las conexiones entre inteligencia emocional, evaluada con medidas de auto-informe y de habilidad, la calidad de las relaciones interpersonales y la empatía en estudiantes universitarios. Además, se examinó la contribución de la inteligencia emocional como predictor de estas dimensiones. Ciento ochenta y cuatro estudiantes universitarios españoles completaron una batería de cuestionarios que incluía la versión española del Trait Meta-Mood Scale-24 (una escala auto-informada de inteligencia emocional), la rama de manejo emocional del MSCEIT (una subescala de una medida de habilidad de inteligencia emocional), el inventario de redes sociales (un inventario de la calidad de las relaciones interpersonales) y el índice de reactividad interpersonal (un cuestionario de empatía). Para comprobar las hipótesis, se llevaron a cabo una serie de análisis de correlación y de regresión múltiple. Los resultados mostraron asociaciones significativas entre diferentes aspectos de la inteligencia emocional y las dimensiones de relaciones interpersonales y empatía. Por otra parte, los análisis de regresión múltiple mostraron que la rama de manejo emocional del MSCEIT mostraba mayores asociaciones con diferentes dimensiones de las relaciones interpersonales (intimidad, afecto y antagonismo), pero sólo con una dimensión de empatía (implicación empática). En cambio, las subescalas del TMMS mostraron mayor asociación con diferentes subescalas de empatía (toma de perspectiva, implicación empática y malestar personal), pero sólo con una de las dimensiones de relaciones interpersonales (antagonismo). Los hallazgos son discutidos a partir de la existencia de diferentes conceptualizaciones teóricas y medidas de la inteligencia emocional dentro de este reciente campo de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;15(2): 117-137, mayo-ago. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136416</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inteligencia emocional, calidad de las relaciones interpersonales y empatía en estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
