<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046423</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alterations in the pattern of dopaminergic markers in attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is a common neurobehavioral disorder of childhoodonset that can include elements of inattention, hyperactivity and impulsive behavior. It is often treated with stimulantmedications such as methylphenidate hydrochloride (MPH). The neurobiology of ADHD is not well understood, but there isconverging evidence of the involvement of the catecholamine rich frontal-striatal circuitry. A prominent theory of ADHD is thatthere is a dysregulation of dopamine neurotransmission in this circuitry. Given support to this theory is the observation fromhuman imaging studies that MPH blocks the dopamine transporter (DAT), the main mechanism for removing dopamine fromthe synapse; thereby increasing extracellular dopamine levels in the striatum. Genetic and molecular studies have alsodemonstrated an association between dopamine related genes (e.g., DAT, dopamine D4 and D5 receptors) and ADHD.Development. Studies using positron emission tomography (PET) and single photon emission tomography indicate alterationsin dopamine markers in ADHD. The majority of the existing studies have reported increased DAT binding (ranging between 17and 70%) in the striatum of both children and adults with ADHD, while a new PET study reported lower DAT binding in themidbrain (where the dopaminergic neurons of the substantia nigra and ventral tegmental area are located) of adolescents withADHD. Studies using [18F]fluorodopa to assess dopamine synthesis and metabolism have demonstrated abnormalities inpresynaptic activity in patients with ADHD; however the nature of these changes appears to be age-dependent. Some limiteddata also indicate potential alterations in dopamine D2 receptor availability in children with ADHD. Conclusions. The resultsfrom the human brain imaging studies are still not definitive because of discrepancies in the findings. There is a great need toreplicate and expand these findings in treatment-naïve patients with ADHD, taking into consideration potential variables suchas drug and smoking history, ethnicity, and presence of comorbidity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Heijtz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mulas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forssberg, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad(TDAH) es un trastorno neuroconductual frecuente que seinicia en la infancia y puede incluir elementos como la inatención,hiperactividad y conducta impulsiva. El tratamiento habitual consisteen la administración de fármacos estimulantes como el metilfenidatoclorhidrato (MPH). El mecanismo neurobiológico del TDAH nose comprende muy bien, pero hay pruebas que coinciden en la implicaciónde los circuitos frontoestriatales ricos en catecolaminas. Unade las teorías más destacadas es que existe un trastorno de la regularizaciónde la transmisión de la dopamina en estos circuitos. Esta teoría se apoya en los resultados de los estudios de imagen realizadosen humanos, en los que se ha observado que el MPH bloquea eltransportador de dopamina (DAT), el principal mecanismo por elcual se elimina la dopamina de las sinapsis; por ello, aumentan losniveles de dopamina extracelulares en el estriado. Estudios genéticosy moleculares han mostrado una asociación importante entre losgenes relacionados con la dopamina (como el DAT, los receptores dedopamina D4 y D5) y el TDAH. Desarrollo. Los estudios con PET ySPECT señalan alteraciones en los marcadores dopaminérgicos enel TDAH. La mayoría de estudios actuales han descrito un incrementoen la fijación de DAT (entre el 17 y el 70%) en el estriado de niñosy adultos con TDAH, mientras que en un estudio reciente realizadocon PET se encontró una fijación de DAT disminuida en el mesencéfalo(donde se ubican las neuronas dopaminérgicas de la sustancianegra y la zona tegmental ventral) de adolescentes con TDAH. Losestudios con [18F]fluorodopa para evaluar la síntesis y el metabolismode la dopamina han mostrado anomalías en la actividad presinápticade pacientes con TDAH; estos cambios parecen depender dela edad. Algunos datos limitados apuntan a alteraciones potencialesen las cantidades de receptor de dopamina D2 disponibles en niñoscon TDAH. Conclusiones. Los resultados de los estudios de imagencon cerebros humanos no son definitivos todavía debido a ciertasdiscrepancias en los hallazgos. Es necesario replicar y ampliar estosresultados en pacientes con TDAH que no han recibido tratamientoprevio, teniendo en cuenta posibles variables como los antecedentesrelacionados con el consumo de drogas y el tabaquismo, la etnicidady la comorbilidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(supl.2): s19-s23, feb. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046423</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones de los patrones de los marcadores de la dopamina en el trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30566^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30567^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23987^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
