<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84277</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sulcus fixation of an intraocular lens by means of haptic insertions in scleral tunnels: results at one year</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">MethodsWe included seven eyes in which sutureless intrascleral posterior chamber intraocular lens (IOL) fixation was performed. Pre- and post-surgical best-corrected visual acuity (LogMAR) and refraction changes were analyzed. There was a one year follow-up periodConclusionsSutureless intrascleral posterior chamber intraocular lens fixation is, in our experience, a safe technique that allows locating the IOL in the posterior chamber when no capsular support is present. Visual and refractive outcomes were satisfactory(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Herreros, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Guajardo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">MétodoEvaluamos siete casos, sobre los que realizamos fijación de LIO en sulcus mediante inserción de hápticos en túneles esclerales. Analizamos las variaciones pre- y postoperatorias de la mejor agudeza visual corregida LogMAR y la refracción. El periodo de seguimiento fue de un año.ConclusionesLa fijación de LIO en sulcus mediante la inserción de hápticos en túneles esclerales es, en nuestra experiencia, una técnica segura, que en ausencia de soporte capsular adecuado, permite situar el implante en cámara posterior, obteniendo resultados visuales y refractivos satisfactorios(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;85(8): 278-280, ago. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84277</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fijación de lente intraocular en sulcus mediante inserción de hápticos en túneles esclerales: resultados a un año</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33571^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12971^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
