<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121539</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Large epidermoid cyst of the breast</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Epidermoid cysts are located mainly in the subcutaneous tissue of the trunk andare usually small and asymptomatic. Localization in the breast parenchyma is rare and these cysts may become malignant. We report the case of a 23-year-old breastfeeding woman who presented with a lump protruding from her right breast that grew to more than 10 cm. The diagnosis of epidermal inclusion cyst was con&amp;#64257;rmed by the pathological examination. Although distinguishing between an epidermoid cyst and a malignant tumor can sometimes be dif&amp;#64257;cult, surgical excision is justi&amp;#64257;ed because these cysts can undergo malignant transformation. We discuss images of the breast and surgical specimen of this case and review the literature on the topic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campelo Martínez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Urruzola, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobato Miguélez , JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Domingo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Valverde, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Peña , M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ferrer, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los quistes epidérmicos se localizan principalmente en el tejido subcutáneo del tronco, y generalmente son pequeños y asintomáticos. Es rara su localización en el parénquima mamario y pueden ser el origen de un proceso patológico maligno. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 23 años en periodo de lactancia, que consulta por presentar una tumoración grande que protruye en la cubierta cutánea mamaria derecha, alcanzando un tamaño superior a 10 cm. El estudio anatomopatológico confirmó el diagnóstico de quiste de inclusión epidérmica. Aunque a veces el quiste epidérmico es difícil de distinguir de un tumor maligno, la resección quirúrgica está justificada debido a su potencial de malignidad. Se presenta la iconografía de la mama, los especímenes quirúrgicos y se revisa la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);41(2): 92-96, abr.-jun. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121539</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Quiste de inclusión epidérmica gigante de localización mamaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38604^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
