<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112628</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reflections on the Baron and Kenny model of statistical mediation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the 25 years since Baron and Kenny (1986) published their ideas on how to analyze and interpret statistical mediation, few works have been more cited, and perhaps, so decisively influenced the way applied researchers understand and analyze mediation in social and health sciences. However, the widespread use of a procedure does not necessarily make it a safe or reliable strategy. In fact, during these years, many researchers have pointed out the limitations of the procedure Baron and Kenny proposed for demonstrating mediation. The twofold aim of this paper is to (1) carry out a review of the limitations of the method by Baron and Kenny, with particular attention to the weakness in the confirmatory logic of the procedure, and (2) provide an empirical example that, in applying the method, data obtained from the same theoretical scenario (i.e., with or without the presence of mediation) can be compatible with both the mediation and no-mediation hypotheses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los 25 años que han transcurrido desde que Baron y Kenny (1986) publicaran sus ideas acerca de cómo proceder para analizar e interpretar la mediación estadística, pocos trabajos han sido tan citados como éste y, probablemente, ningún otro ha influido de una forma tan decisiva sobre la forma en que los investigadores aplicados entienden y analizan la mediación en el ámbito de las ciencias sociales y de la salud. Pero la utilización masiva de un procedimiento no lo convierte, por sí sola, en una estrategia fiable o segura. De hecho, en estos 25 años no pocos investigadores han puesto de manifiesto las limitaciones de la propuesta de Baron y Kenny para demostrar mediación. El objetivo de este trabajo es (1) realizar una revisión de las limitaciones del método de Baron y Kenny prestando especial atención a la debilidad de la lógica confirmatoria en la que se basa y (2) ofrecer una demostración empírica de que, aplicando la estrategia de Baron y Kenny, los datos obtenidos en el marco de un mismo escenario teórico (sea o no de mediación) pueden ser compatibles tanto con la hipótesis de mediación como con la hipótesis de no mediación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;29(2): 614-623, mayo-ago. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflexiones sobre el modelo de mediación estadística de Baron y Kenny</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34900</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29938</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24884</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
