<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058637</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aplasia cutis congenita</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aplasia cutis congenita (ACC) is a rare condition characterized    by the congenital absence of epidermis, dermis and, in    some cases, subcutaneous tissues. ACC occurs as an isolated    defect (normally localized agenesis of the scalp) or with other    associated anomalies. It was first described by Cordon in 1767,    and more than 500 cases have been reported since, with an    estimated incidence of 3 cases per 10,000 births. There is no    racial or sexual predilection. The pathogenesis is not clear. The    lesion is usually solitary, circular or oval, hairless and welldemarcated,    and it ranges in size from 0.5-2 cm. At birth, the    lesions may have already healed with scarring or may appear    as superficial erosions or deep ulcerations, occasionally invo lving    the dura or the meninges. The best therapeutic option depends    on the size of the defect</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barchino Ortiz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernanz Hermosa, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabeza Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aplasia cutánea congénita (ACC) es una rara alteración caracterizada    por la ausencia congénita de epidermis, dermis y,    en ocasiones, de los tejidos subyacentes. La forma más frecuente    afecta al vértex, y se puede presentar de forma aislada    o asociada a otras malformaciones. Fue descrita por primera    vez por Cordon, en 1767, y desde entonces se han documentado    más de 500 casos. La frecuencia se ha estimado en torno a    3/10.000 recién nacidos. No hay predilección por la raza ni el    sexo. La etiopatogenia no está clara. La manifestación clínica    habitual es una lesión oval o circular, solitaria, sin pelo, bien    delimitada, de 0,5-2 cm, y localizada en el vértex. Al nacer, las    lesiones pueden estar cicatrizadas o presentarse como erosiones    o incluso úlceras profundas, con riesgo de afectar a las    meninges o la duramadre. La mejor opción terapéutica dependerá    del tamaño del defecto</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;65(10): 510-512, nov. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058637</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplasia cutánea congénita</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d508^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22434^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4898^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22434^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
