<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166829</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatocolic fistula managed with a novel Padlock(R) device for endoscopic closure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent advances in endoscopic therapeutics allow conditions such as fistulas of the digestive system to be treated endoscopically. These cases were recently managed with surgery. The Padlock(R) system includes a nitinol clip that was recently introduced for endoscopic therapy. There are few reports with regard to its use in the daily clinical practice. We report a case of a colonic fistula that was endoscopically managed with this novel over-the-scope nitinol clip system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trueba Arguiñarena, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Martín, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmo Martínez, Lourdes del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velayos Jiménez, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Hernández, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El avance de la terapéutica endoscópica está permitiendo abordar patologías que hasta hace poco quedaban reservadas al tratamiento quirúrgico, como las fístulas digestivas. El sistema Padlock(R) consiste en un clip de nitinol introducido recientemente para terapéutica endoscópica. Hasta el momento, son pocas las comunicaciones sobre su utilización en la práctica diaria. Presentamos un caso de fístula colónica tratada mediante este nuevo sistema de clip endoscópico de nitinol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;109(10): 731-733, oct. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fístula hepatocólica tratada con el nuevo dispositivo de cierre endoscópico Padlock(R)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28910^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13906^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
