<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150409</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fitness and quality of life in kidney transplant recipients: case-control study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: We analyzed the levels of fitness, muscle structure and quality of life of adults after kidney transplant and healthy adults. Patients and methods: A total of 16 kidney transplant patients and 21 healthy controls performed several fitness test, isokinetic evaluation of knee flexion and extension and ultrasonography muscle thickness assessment. They also completed the quality of life questionnaire SF-36. Results: Physical fitness, muscle structure and quality of life of the kidney transplant recipients were significantly poorer than the controls. The transplant patients performed less well in the &#147;get up and go&#148; and &#147;sit to stand&#148; test (p &lt; .001) as well as in assessments of muscle structure, strength and power. The patients had a poorer score in their quality of life assessments, differing from the controls in domains of physical function, physical role, general health and social function (p &lt; .001). Discussion: Fitness, strength and muscle mass are diminished in kidney transplant patients, resulting in a poorer quality of life which might entail an increased risk to their health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Alegre, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Jonatan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azael Herrero Alonso, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sánchez, Sonsoles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrero, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: El objetivo del estudio fue analizar los niveles de forma física, estructura muscular y calidad de vida de adultos con trasplante de riñón y adultos sanos. Pacientes y métodos: En este estudio participaron 16 trasplantados renales y 21 controles. Se evaluó la forma física, la fuerza isocinética de flexión y extensión de rodilla, así como el cuestionario de calidad de vida SF-36. Además, se realizó una ecografía muscular para analizar la estructura muscular. Resultados: Se observaron valores inferiores en el grupo de trasplantados en los test de agilidad y sentarse y levantarse de la silla (p &lt; 0,001) y en todos los parámetros de estructura muscular, fuerza y potencia. Los pacientes evaluaron peor su calidad de vida en todos los niveles, encontrándose diferencias significativas con respecto a los pacientes en los dominios de función física, rol físico, salud general y la función social (p &lt; 0,001). Discusión: La forma física, fuerza y masa muscular y calidad de vida de personas trasplantadas de riñón está disminuida, situación que podría conllevar un mayor riesgo para su salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);146(8): 335-338, abr. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150409</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Forma física y calidad de vida en pacientes trasplantados de riñón: estudio de casos y controles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
