<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120667</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Genetic susceptibility to obesity and metabolic syndrome in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity is one of the major public health problems worldwide. It is a chronic, complex, and multifactorial origin disease characterised by body fat excess mainly due to an imbalance between dietary intake and energy expenditure. One of the major complications of obesity is metabolic syndrome, which comprises anthropometrical, clinical, and metabolic dysfunctions that predispose the affected individual to the development of type 2 diabetes mellitus and cardiovascular diseases. It is hypothesized that the variability in the susceptibility to obesity-mediated metabolic complications involves both environmental and genetic factors. Whereas advances in the knowledge of the variations in the human genome have led to the identification of susceptibility genes that con -tribute to obesity and related disorders, relatively few studies have specifically focused on the interactions between obesity and genetic polymorphisms and the development of metabolic complications. Despite these limited efforts, an increasing amount of evidence suggests that the effects of some gene variants on metabolic traits are modified by or present only in the setting of obesity. Fur -thermore, some of these loci may have larger effects on metabolic phenotypes in the presence of certain dietary or lifestyle factors. In the present manuscript, we revie wed the genes and their variants that have been evidenced to play a role in obesity-associated metabolic complications through genetic association studies, including candidate gene and genome-wide association approaches in adults and children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilera, Concepción M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olza, Josune</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad es uno de los principales problemas de salud pública a nivel mundial. Es una enfermedad crónica, compleja y de origen multifactorial que se caracteriza por el exceso de grasa corporal y se desarrolla, fundamentalmente, debido a un desequilibrio entre la ingesta dietética y el gasto energético. Una de las principales complicaciones de la obesidad es el síndrome metabólico, el cual comprende alteraciones antropométricas, clínicas y metabólicas que predisponen el desarrollo de diabetes mellitus tipo 2 y enfermedades cardiovasculares. Existe la hipótesis de que tanto factores ambientales como genéticos participan en la variabilidad a la susceptibilidad de las complicaciones metabólicas mediadas por la obesidad. Mientras que los avances en el conocimiento de las variaciones en el genoma humano, han llevado a la identificación de genes que contribuyen a la susceptibilidad de la obesidad y las enfermedades asociadas, son relativamente pocos los estudios que se han centrado específicamente en la interacción entre la obesidad y polimorfismos genéticos relacionados con el desarrollo de complicaciones metabólicaso directamente con el síndrome metabólico. Además, algunos de estos loci pueden tener mayor efecto en los fenotipos metabólicos cuando está modificado por la dieta u otros factores ambientales. En este manuscrito se revisan los genes y las variantes con mayor evidencia de asociación con las complicaciones metabólicas relacionadas con la obesidad descritas en estudios de asociación genética, incluyendo estudios de genes candidatos y estudios amplios del genoma humano en adultos y niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(supl.5): 44-55, sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120667</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Susceptibilidad genetica de obesidad y síndrome metabólico en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53761^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34583^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52885^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
