<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133328</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Toxic effects of alternariol by in vitro assays: a review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mycotoxins are secondary metabolites produced by genera fungus of: Aspergillus, Penicillium, Fusarium and Alternaria. The most frequent mycotoxins are: aflatoxins (Aspergillus), ochratoxin A (Penicillium), fumonisins, zearalenone, deoxynivalenol (Fusarium) and alternariol (Alternaria). Among all Alternaria spp, A. Alternata is the most producer mycotoxin. All mycotoxins are considered toxic contaminants present in food of daily consumption. This review is based on in vitro studies where response and toxicity in cells of Alternaria mycotoxin, alternariol (AOH) have been carried out. In this sense a bibliographic search of AOH papers available in on-line data bases such as: Pubmed, Scopus, Science Direct and Current Contents in the last fourteen years, have been collected. The main objective of this bibliographic review is to evaluate the AOH effects detected in in vitro assay (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Blanco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Font, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan-García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las micotoxinas son metabolitos secundarios producidos por hongos del genero Aspergillus, Penicillium, Fusarium y Alternaria. Las micotoxinas más abundantes son aflatoxinas (Aspergillus), ocratoxina A (Penicillium), fumonisinas, zearalenona, deoxinivalenol (Fusarium) y alternariol (Alternaria). De las especies de Alternaria, A. alternata es la especie productora más importante de micotoxinas. Todas están consideradas como contaminantes tóxicos que están presentes en alimentos de consumo diario. Esta revisión se centra en estudios in vitro relacionados con la respuesta y citotoxicidad a la micotoxina de Alternaria, alternariol (AOH). Para ello, se ha realizado una búsqueda bibliográfica de los artículos de AOH disponible en bases de datos como: Pubmed, Scopus, Science Direct y Current Contents en los últimos catorce años. Así pues, el objetivo de la revisión bibliográfica es evaluar los efectos de AOH investigados mediante ensayos in vitro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;31(2): 196-203, jul.-dic. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133328</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos tóxicos de alternariol por ensayos in vitro: revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9375^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d529^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34827</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d529^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10601^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5639^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27470^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27470^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5807^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d529^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23584^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27470^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
