<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145314</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Regulatory bases of living-donor kidney transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Living donor kidney transplantation is regulated in Spain by the transplantation law 30/1979 and developed by Royal Decree 2070/1999. These policies permit the living donation of an organ while its function is compensated by the rest of the body. It further specifies that the destination of the organ must be the transplantation in a specific person (this specification allows for the donation, not only among emotionally related, but between people that do not know each other, provided it is done altruistically, without any purpose of profit and without coercion). The donor must be competent, healthy and had reached 18 years old (which is evidenced by a medical certificate) and should be well informed of the consequences of their decision. The donor must give their consent to donation, free from inducement and consciously in the courts of civil registration. In order to guarantee the quality and safety of the procedure, the centers that performed this therapeutic must be authorized both for the nephrectomy and the transplantation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López del Moral, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trasplante renal de donante vivo está regulado en España por la Ley de Trasplantes 30/1979 y desarrollada mediante el Real Decreto 2070/1999. Nuestra ley permite la donación en vida de un órgano si es compatible con la vida y la función del órgano o parte de él compensada por el organismo. Especifica, además, que el destino del órgano será su trasplante a una persona determinada sin que medie condicionamiento econó- mico, psicológico ni social (esta especificación permite la donación no sólo entre personas emocionalmente relacionadas sino también entre desconocidos, siempre que se realice de forma altruista y desinteresada). El donante ha de ser mayor de edad, con plenas facultades mentales y un adecuado estado de salud (que se acredita mediante certificado médico) y deberá ser plenamente informado de las consecuencias de su decisión. El donante debe otorgar su consentimiento de forma expresa, libre y consciente ante el juez del Registro Civil. Los centros que realizan el trasplante renal de donante vivo deben estar autorizados tanto para la extracción como para el trasplante de dicho órgano de donante fallecido (para garantizar la calidad y seguridad del procedimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;30(supl.2): 23-29, feb. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145314</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases legales de la donación de vivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d533</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33201^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
