<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142836</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between executive functioning and behaviour in children with cerebral palsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cerebral palsy is defined as a group of developmental disorders of movement and posture that causes social and cognitive deficits, emotional, and behavior disturbances. Aim. To study the relationship between executive functioning and behavior in children with cerebral palsy from the answers given by parents and teachers on the Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function (BRIEF) and on the System Assessment Adaptive Behavior (ABAS-II). Patients and methods. The sample consisted on 46 children with CP with a mean age of 10.26 ± 2.95 years. Forty-four of the 46 children were distributed in Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) into level I (n = 16), level II (n = 3), level III (n = 11), level IV (n = 10) and level V (n = 4). Results. The results showed a relationship between BRIEF and ABAS-II. Furthermore, discrepancies between the responses from parents and teachers, both in the ABAS-II and in the BRIEF, were obtained. Conclusions. We found a significant relationship between executive functioning in children with cerebral palsy and adaptive behavior. We found discrepancies in the answers given by parents and teachers. Finally, the data showed that the higher motor impairment increases difficulties at home (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muriel, Vega</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enseñat, Antònia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Molina, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio López, Celeste</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig Rovira, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La parálisis cerebral se define como un grupo de trastornos del desarrollo del movimiento y la postura que cursa con déficits cognitivos, alteraciones emocionales, de conducta y sociales. Objetivo. Estudiar la relación entre el funcionamiento ejecutivo y la conducta en niños con parálisis cerebral a partir de las respuestas aportadas por padres y profesores en el Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function (BRIEF) y el sistema de evaluación de la conducta adaptativa (ABAS-II). Pacientes y métodos. La muestra quedó formada por 46 niños con parálisis cerebral, con una edad media de 10,26 ± 2,95 años. Del total, 44 niños se distribuyeron en el Gross Motor Function Classification System (GMFCS) en nivel I (n = 16), nivel II (n = 3), nivel III (n = 11), nivel IV (n = 10) y nivel V (n = 4). Resultados. Los resultados mostraron relación entre el BRIEF y el ABAS-II; además, se obtuvieron discrepancias entre las respuestas aportadas por padres y profesores, tanto en el ABAS-II como en el BRIEF. Asimismo, se halló relación entre el GMFCS y los subíndices de vida en el hogar, índice práctico y autocuidado del ABAS-II. Conclusiones. Se encontró relación entre el funcionamiento ejecutivo y la conducta adaptativa en niños con parálisis cerebral. Se hallaron discrepancias en las respuestas aportadas por padres y profesores. Por último, los datos muestran que, a mayor afectación motora, mayores dificultades en el hogar, en el índice práctico y en el autocuidado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;61(8): 337-343, 16 oct., 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142836</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el funcionamiento ejecutivo y la conducta en niños con parálisis cerebral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53744^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
