<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058149</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dying with dignity in the twenty-first century</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Death is a disturbing reality for humans. The form of death and the interpretation and acceptance of this process have changed over the centuries. For society in general, health professionals --especially those dealing with the terminally ill-- and health services managers, knowledge of the reality of death within their own sociocultural environment is of prime importance. Also important is understanding the changes in dying in the new century from the perspectives of sociology, anthropology, psychology and even philosophy. To a large extent, the approach to death depends on the serenity with which human beings can think about this process, speak about it, accept it as natural, or deny it.         The present study aims to provide a reflection on death in the present time, based on an analysis of historical and cultural changes concerning how people experience death and to underline certain conditions that could favor appropriate death in the twenty-first century</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ogando, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La muerte es una realidad inquietante para el hombre. La forma de morir y la interpretación y aceptación de la muerte han ido cambiando a lo largo de los siglos. Para la sociedad en general, para las profesiones relacionadas con la atención sociosanitaria, sobre todo las que tratan con enfermos que viven su última enfermedad, y para los responsables de la gestión de los servicios sanitarios es de gran importancia conocer la realidad de la muerte dentro del entorno sociocultural propio, así como entender los cambios en el acto de morir en este nuevo siglo, desde una perspectiva sociológica, antropológica, psicológica e incluso filosófica. El modo de afrontar la muerte depende en gran medida de la serenidad con que los seres humanos puedan pensar en ella, hablar de ella, normalizarla o negarla.         El objetivo del presente estudio es colaborar en la reflexión sobre la muerte actual, partiendo de un análisis de los cambios históricos y culturales en la forma de "vivir la muerte", y subrayar algunas condiciones que puedan favorecer el acto de morir de forma apropiada en este siglo xxi</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;22(3): 147-153, may.2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058149</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Morir con propiedad en el siglo XXI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19340^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
