<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166767</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in the treatment of non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome and its consequences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Marked variability in the treatment of patients with acute coronary syndrome has been observed in international and single-country studies for more than 15 years. This variability is associated with specific patient characteristics, such as being female or diabetic, but is also influenced by the center providing treatment and the physician in charge of care. It has repeatedly been demonstrated that, paradoxically, patients at a higher risk receive less complete treatment or are treated less in accordance with guidelines. Knowledge of all the factors that influence treatment variability combined with the implementation of measures to minimize them would help improve patient prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bardají, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La variabilidad en la asistencia a pacientes que tienen un síndrome coronario agudo se viene detectando desde hace más de 15 años en registros internacionales y nacionales. Dicha variabilidad depende de determinadas características de los pacientes, como el hecho de ser mujer o diabético, pero también de los centros y los médicos encargados de la asistencia. Se ha demostrado repetidamente la paradoja de tratar de forma menos completa o menos acorde con las guías cuanto mayor es el riesgo del paciente. Conocer todas las circunstancias que influyen en la variabilidad y aplicar medidas para minimizarlas, ayudará a mejorar el pronóstico de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);11(supl.A): 8a-13a, 2011. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166767</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad en el tratamiento del síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST y sus consecuencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37493^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32647^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
