<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68199</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the nutritional status of orthopaedic patients. Design: Prospective observation study. Setting: Tertiary hospital, Clinical Nutrition Unit. Patients: 107 patients (56,1% women, 43,9% men, 62,1± 20,4 years) are studied at admission to the orthopaedic unit and it is observed the evolution of orthopaedic surgery patients with hip or knee prosthesis. Material and methods: Medical history, anthropometric data and three nutritional screening tools were considered: Mini-Nutritional Assessment (MNA), Malnutrition Universal Screening Tool (MUST) y Valoración Global Subjetiva (VGS). It was assessed the prevalence of malnutrition in patients on admission to hospital, using different methods and determining if a correlation exists between malnutrition and other factors, such as the development of pressure sores of the dependence in activities of daily living. Results: The risk of malnutrition is 22 and 24/100 patients admitted at hospital, if MNA and SGA are used, respectively (SGA caregorized 4% of the group as "malnourished"). 80% patients are considered to be at high risk of malnutrition using MUST. 1,7% patients presented a Body Mass Index (BMI) lower than 18,5. There is a strong agreement between malnutrition and neropsychological status (p = 0,001), and the dependence in activities of daily living (p = 0,002), and between medium and high risk of malnutrition and the development of pressure sores (p = 0,003). If MNA and SGA (p = 0,000) are used, post-surgical patients presents a deteriorating nutritional status. Conclusions: The prevalence of malnutrition in patients on admission to hospital is elevated. Orthopaedic surgery patients with hip and knee prosthesis presented a deteriorating nutritional status, and a higher incidence of pressure sores in a month (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Duque, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Segura, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanavia Morán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Resines Erasun, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrazola Martínez, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juanes Pardo, JR de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Establecer la incidencia y evolución de malnutrición en una cohorte de pacientes ingresados en un servicio de traumatología. Ámbito: Es un estudio observacional y prospectivo, realizado en un hospital terciario que dispone de Unidad de Nutrición Clínica. Pacientes: Se estudian 107 pacientes (56,1% mujeres, 43,9% hombres, edad 62,1 ± 20,4 años) al ingreso en el Servicio de Traumatología y la evolución en la primera consulta externa de los pacientes intervenidos para colocar una prótesis de cadera o rodilla. Intervenciones: Se realizó una historia clínica, recogida de datos antropométricos y tres tests de cribado nutricional: Mini-Nutritional Assessment (MNA), Malnutrition Universal Screening Tool (MUST) y Valoración Global Subjetiva (VGS). Con ellos se calcula la prevalencia de malnutrición al ingreso, comparando las diferencias entre los métodos y la posible existencia de asociación entre la malnutrición y otros factores, tales como úlceras por presión o dependencia para las actividades de la vida diaria. Resultados: Según el MNA el 22% tiene riesgo de malnutrición, en la VGS es un 24% (un 4% están malnutridos) y en el MUST un 80% presenta alto riesgo de malnutrición. Un 1,7% de los pacientes tienen un Índice de Masa Corporal (IMC) menor que 18,5. Existe una relación significativa entre la malnutrición y estado neuropsicológico (p = 0,001), dependencia para las actividades de la vida diaria (p = 0,002) y entre el MUST de alto y medio riesgo con la aparición de úlceras por presión (p = 0,003). Hay empeoramiento del estado nutricional postquirúrgico con 2 tests: MNA y VGS (p = 0,000). Conclusión: En las condiciones del estudio la prevalencia de malnutrición al ingreso en el Servicio de Traumatología es elevada, los pacientes con cirugía protésica de rodilla y cadera muestran al mes un claro empeoramiento de su estado nutricional, así como una mayor incidencia de úlceras por presión (AU</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;23(5): 493-499, sept.-oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68199</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d14586^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33576</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28585</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
