<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150849</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of an uncertainty model for fibromyalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Finding out women's experiences diagnosed with fibromyalgia applying the Theory of Uncertainty proposed by M. Mishel. Design: A qualitative study was conducted, using a phenomenological approach. Location: An Association of patients in the province of Alicante during the months of June 2012 to November 2013. Participants: A total of 14 women diagnosed with fibromyalgia participated in the study as volunteers, aged between 45 and 65 years. Method: Information generated through structured interviews with recording and transcription, prior confidentiality pledge and informed consent. Analysis content by extracting different categories according to the theory proposed. Results: The study patients perceive a high level of uncertainty related to the difficulty to deal with symptoms, uncertainty about diagnosis and treatment complexity. Moreover, the ability of coping with the disease it is influenced by social support, relationships with health professionals and help and information attending to patient associations. Conclusions: The health professional must provide clear information on the pathology to the fibromyalgia suffers, the larger lever of knowledge of the patients about their disease and the better the quality of the information provided, it is reported to be the less anxiety and uncertainty in the experience of the disease. Likewise patient associations should have health professionals in order to avoid bias in the information and advice with scientific evidence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Siles González, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Ruiz, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Triviño Martínez, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las experiencias vividas por las mujeres diagnosticadas de fibromialgia aplicando la Teoría de la Incertidumbre propuesta por M. Mishel. Diseño: Estudio cualitativo con enfoque fenomenológico. Emplazamiento una Asociación de enfermas de fibromialgia de la provincia de Alicante durante los meses de junio 2012 a noviembre de 2013. Participantes: Catorce mujeres diagnosticadas de fibromialgia con edades comprendidas entre 45 y 65 años participaron de forma voluntaria. Método: Generación de información a través de entrevistas semiestructuradas con grabación y transcripción previo compromiso de confidencialidad y consentimiento informado. Análisis de contenido extrayendo diferentes categorías de acuerdo con la teoría propuesta. Resultados: Las pacientes del estudio perciben un elevado nivel de incertidumbre vinculado a la dificultad para hacer frente a los síntomas, incertidumbre ante el diagnóstico y la complejidad del tratamiento. Por otra parte, la capacidad de afrontamiento de la enfermedad se verá influida por el apoyo social, la relación con los profesionales de la salud y la búsqueda de ayuda e información acudiendo a las asociaciones de pacientes. Conclusiones: El profesional de la salud debe ofrecer una información clara sobre la patología a las enfermas de fibromialgia; cuanto mayor es el nivel de conocimientos de las pacientes sobre su enfermedad y mejor es la calidad de la información que se presta, se informa de menor ansiedad e incertidumbre en la vivencia de la enfermedad. Así mismo, las asociaciones de pacientes deberían disponer de profesionales de la salud para evitar sesgos en la información y el asesoramiento con evidencia científica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;48(4): 219-225, abr. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150849</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación del modelo de incertidumbre a la fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54522</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24960</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37587</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
