<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63046</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chemotherapy-induced acral erythema: a clinical and histopathologic study of 44 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Acral erythema, also known as palmoplantar erythrodysesthesia or hand-foot syndrome, is a relatively common cutaneous reaction caused by a variety of chemotherapeutic agents. It presents during cancer treatment as painful erythema and paresthesia affecting the palms and soles. It seems to be dose dependent and its appearance is determined by both the peak plasma concentration and the cumulative dose of the chemotherapeutic agent. The symptoms and histopathology findings are suggestive of direct cytotoxicity affecting the epidermis of the extremities caused by high concentrations of chemotherapeutic agents. The most commonly implicated agents are doxorubicin, 5-fluoracil and its derivatives, cytarabine, and docetaxel. Material and methods. We present the clinical and histologic characteristics of a series of patients diagnosed with chemotherapy-induced acral erythema. The study included all patients who developed acral erythema lesions following chemotherapy between January 2000 and December 2003. Resaults and conclusions. Out of 2186 patients who underwent chemotherapy, 44 cases of acral erythema were identified, representing an incidence of 2.01 % during the study period and 16.75 % of all cutaneous lesions attributed to chemotherapy. The most commonly implicated drug was 5-fluoracil administered by continuous infusion and the highest incidence was observed in patients treated with liposomal doxorubicin. Acral erythema was a dose-limiting toxic effect in 29.5 % of cases. The histologic findings varied according to the clinical severity of the lesions and included interface dermatitis with variable keratinocyte necrosis, dilation of the superficial vascular plexus, and limited inflammatory infiltrate. The most commonly used treatment was pyridoxine, along with topical treatments such as cold compresses, emollients, and topical corticosteroids (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serra-Guillén, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfaro-Rubio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella-Estrada, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueso, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llombart, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanmartín, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nagore, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El eritema acral (EA) es una reacción cutánea relativamente frecuente producida por diferentes agentes quimioterápicos. Otros términos con los que se le conoce son eritrodisestesia palmoplantar o síndrome pie-mano. Se presenta como un eritema doloroso en palmas y plantas asociado a parestesias en el contexto de un tratamiento oncológico. El EA parece ser dosis-dependiente, y tanto el pico plasmático como la dosis acumulada del quimioterápico determinan su aparición. La clínica y los hallazgos histopatológicos sugieren una citotoxicidad directa de la epidermis acral por las altas concentraciones de los quimioterápicos. Los agentes más frecuentemente implicados son doxorrubicina, 5-fluorouracilo y derivados, citarabina y docetaxel. Material y métodos. Se presentan las características clínicas e histológicas de una serie de pacientes diagnosticados de eritema acral por quimioterápicos. Se incluyeron en el trabajo todos los pacientes sometidos a quimioterapia que desarrollaron lesiones de eritema acral durante un período de tiempo comprendido entre enero de 2000 y diciembre de 2003. Resultados y conclusión. Se encontraron 44 casos entre los 2.186 pacientes sometidos a quimioterapia, lo que supuso una incidencia del 2,01 % durante el período de estudio, y el 16,75 % de todas las lesiones cutáneas atribuidas a la quimioterapia. El fármaco más frecuentemente relacionado fue el 5-fluorouracilo en infusión continua, y la mayor incidencia se dio en pacientes tratados con doxorrubicina liposomial. El EA fue toxicidad limitante de dosis en el 29,5 % de los casos. Los hallazgos histológicos variaron según la intensidad clínica de las lesiones, encontrando una dermatitis de interfase con necrosis de queratinocitos variable, dilatación del plexo vascular superficial y un escaso infiltrado inflamatorio. El tratamiento más utilizado fue la piridoxina y las medidas locales como fomentos fríos, emolientes y corticoides tópicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;99(4): 281-290, mayo 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eritema acral inducido por quimioterapia: estudio clínico e histopatológico de 44 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30914^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12173^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d175^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24758^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
