<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-17605</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-perception profile for children: factorial validity and reliability in the Spanish version</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this work, we study the factorial validity and reliability of Self-Perceptions Profile for Children -SPPC- (Harter, 1985). A Spanish version of SPPC was administered to a representative sample of students from the Valencian Community (N= 785) in 6th (6º de E.G.B), 8th ( 8º de E.G.B.) and 10th (2º B.U.P./4º E.S.O) grade. The factorial validity of the specific self-perceptions subscales, the self-worth subscale, the correlations among specific subscales and the reliability of their items and their subscales were analyzed. Our principal results are in accordance with previous works. The Spanish version of SPPC presents acceptable psychometric properties. We also point out the convenience of some considerations with regard to the improvement of its reliability and the ages to which this questionnaire should be administered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balaguer, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atienza, Francisco Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo consiste en estudiar la validez factorial y fiabilidad del PErfil de Autopercepciones para Niños -SPPC- (Harter, 1985). Se administró una traducción del mismo a una muestra representativa de estudiantes de la Comunidad Valenciana (N= 785) de 6º de E.G.B., 8º de E.G.B. y 2º B.U.P./4º E.S.O. Se analizó la validez factorial de las subescalas de autopercepciones específicas y la subescala de autovalía global, las correlaciones entre las subescalas específicas y la fiabilidad de sus ítems y subescalas. Los principales resultados van en la línea de los obtenidos por trabajos previos, mostrando que la versión en castellano de este instrumento presenta propiedades psicométricas aceptables, si bien se señala la necesidad de tener en cuenta algunas consideraciones en relación a la mejora de su fiabilidad y rango de edad de aplicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(3): 659-664, ago. 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-17605</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El perfil de autopercepciones para niños: análisis de la validez factorial y la fiabilidad en la versión castellana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
