<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66389</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The protocol for conventional loading in one or two surgical stages has been evaluated over the last 30 years under all the possible clinical conditions. By comparison, immediate loading is a relatively new protocol that requires strict clinical evaluation. Weconducted a search of the literature published concerning clinical trials on immediate loading according to the different therapeutic options that could be considered. Comparable results were found for both loading strategies in edentulous mandibles. For treatment involving an immediate prosthesis for totally edentulous mandibles, partial and single tooth restorations, patients have to be selected adequately and provisional prostheses have to be designed conservatively. In order to completely confirm the safety of the technique, double-blind, simple, randomized clinical trials have to be carried out with a sufficient number of patients and proper followups that compare precise clinical situations with a provisional prosthesis that has a specific occlusion pattern (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montesdeoca García, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Concejo Cútoli, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El protocolo de carga convencional en una o dos fases quirúrgicas ha sido evaluado durante los últimos 30 años bajo todas las condiciones clínicas posibles. En comparación, la carga inmediata es un protocolorelativamente nuevo que necesita de una estricta evaluación clínica. Realizamos una búsqueda bibliográfica sobre los ensayos clínicos publicadosde carga inmediata en función de las diferentes opciones terapéuticas que se pueden plantear. Se hallaron resultados comparables para las dos estrategias de carga en mandíbulas edéntulas. Para el tratamiento conprótesis inmediata de maxilares totalmente edéntulos, restauraciones parciales e unitarias es todavía necesaria una selección adecuada de pacientesy un diseño conservador de la prótesis provisional. La necesidad de ensayos clínicos sencillos aleatorizados de doble ciego, con suficiente número de pacientes y adecuado seguimiento, que comparen una determinadasituación clínica con un patrón oclusal de la prótesis provisional bien definido, son imprescindibles para acabar de confirmar la seguridad de la técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;27(5): 255-269, sept.-oct. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66389</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35420^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29447^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3838^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
