<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95516</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Compared nutritional assessment for older adults at family medicine settings</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: The nutritional state assessment have important implications to considerer both: prognosis and prevention of diseases related to older adults. This study was designed to compare the assessment of the nutritional state, in alder adults, via Mini Nutritional Assessment with those obtained via evaluation of caloric ingest and anthropometric, biochemical and immunological parameters at family medicine centers. Population and methods: The nutritional status was assessed in 153 older adults, 93 men and 64 women, whose received medical attention at a primary care unit, the age average was 69.66 ± 7.94 years old. The nutritional assessment obtained with Mini Nutritional assessment was compared to those obtained via biochemical and immunological parameters (hemoglobin, serum total proteins, albumin, cholesterol and lymphocytes) and anthropometric parameters (size, weight, body mass index). Resultados: Body Mass Index (BMI) was 26.96 ± 5.1 kg/m2. Once the adults were evaluated with the MNA questionnaire, malnourishment was found in 47 patients (29.9%), risk of malnutrition in 86 patients (54.8%), and no risk for malnutrition 24 patients (15.3%). The MNA questionnaire was the strongest instrument to assess the nutritional status in older adults and to predict the risk of malnutrition in such population, (sensibility =96%, specificity= 98%, positive predictive value=97% and negative predictive value= 88%). The most important relations founded among variables to assess the nutritional status in older adults were the following: MNA-BMI (c2 = 51.314 con gl = 6, p &lt; 0.001); MNA-serum total proteins (c2 = 46.989, gl = 2; p &lt; 0.001); BMI-serum albumin (c2 = 37.508, gl = 3; p &lt; 0.001); MNA-Daily Carbone-hidrate ingestion (c2 = 21.50, gl = 4; p &lt; 0.001); MNA-Daily lipids ingestion (c2 = , gl = 2; p &lt; 0.001). Conclusion: The MNA predicts in opportune form the risk of malnutrition and the state of malnutrition the older adults previously to anthropometric, biochemical and immunological parameters. We recommend to use it, to do nutritional evaluation of older adults one time a year and in those adults in whom the risk of malnutrition or malnutrition have been detected, we recommend to complete the nutritional evaluation via determination of biochemical, immunological and anthropometric parameters mentioned above (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calderón Reyes, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Alonso, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Orozco, AR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarra Ramírez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: La evaluación del estado nutricional del adulto mayor resulta importante como criterio de prevención y pronóstico de enfermedades relacionadas con la vejez. Este trabajo se realizó con el objetivo de comparar el estado nutricional del adulto mayor evaluado a través de la encuesta Mini Nutricional Assessment, MNA), con aquel resultante de la evaluación de la ingesta calórica y parámetros antropométricos, bioquímicos e inmunológicos en consultas de medicina familiar. Población en estudio y métodos: Fue evaluado el estado nutricional de 157 adultos mayores, 93 varones y 64 mujeres, con edades 69,66 ± 7,94 años, que asistían a consulta de medicina familiar con la encuesta Mini Nutritional Assessment y este se comparó con el resultante de la evaluación con recordatorio de 24 horas, con parámetros antropométricos (peso, talla, índice de masa corporal), y marcadores bioquímicos e inmunológicos (hemoglobina, proteínas totales, albúmina, colesterol y linfocitos). Resultados: El índice de masa corporal promedio fue 26,96 ± 5,1 kg/m2. Luego de evaluar a los adultos mayores con el MNA se encontró que tenían malnutrición a 47 pacientes (29,9%), riesgo de malnutrición 86 (54,8%), y sin riesgo de malnutrición 24(15,3%). El MNA fue el instrumento más robusto para evaluar el estado nutricional del adulto mayor y predecir el riesgo de malnutrición en estos (sensibilidad = 96%, especificidad = 98%, valor predictivo positivo = 97% y valor predictivo negativo = 88%). Las asociaciones más importantes entre las variables usadas para realizar la valoración del estado nutricional del adulto mayor fueron MNA-índice de masa corporal (c2 = 51.314 con gl = 6, p &lt; 0,001); MNA-proteínas totales (c2 = 46.989, gl = 2; p &lt; 0,001); IMC-albúmina sérica total (c2 = 37.508, gl = 3; p &lt; 0,001); MNA-Ingesta de hidratos de carbono en 24 horas (c2 = 21.50, gl = 4; p &lt; 0,001); MNAIngesta de lípidos en 24 horas (c2 = , gl = 2; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusión: La MNA predice en forma oportuna el riesgo de malnutrición en el adulto mayor previo a los parámetros antropométricos, bioquímicos e inmunológicos y sugerimos su uso al menos una vez al año para evaluar el estado nutricional del adulto mayor, el cual deberá completarse con la determinación de otros parámetros bioquímicos, inmunológicos y antropométricos en aquellos adultos con riesgo de malnutrición y malnutridos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(4): 669-675, jul.-ago. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95516</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación nutricional comparada del adulto mayor en consultas de medicina familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50320</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
