<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117416</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of pharmaceutical intervention in outpatients pharmacy department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To analize the pharmaceutical interventions made in outpatients pharmacy department of a secondary hospital. Methods: Retrospective and observational study of pharmaceutical interventions made from October 1st 2010 to December 31st 2011. Recorded data: Number of patients, age at the end of the study, diagnostic, prescribing departments, drug-related problems (DRP), negative outcomes associated with medication (NOM), type of pharmaceutical interventions. Results: 231 DRP were found and a pharmaceutical intervention was performed for each DRP in 184 different patients. The main DRPs detected were: drugs interactions (26%), prescription mistakes (15,6%) and non-compliance (15,6%). Only 26 (11,2%) DRP caused a NOM. Most interventions were: recommendating treatment changes (35,6%), promoting the monitorization of the effectiveness of treatment (34,6%) and increasing adherence (15,6%). Conclusion: The pharmacist activity allows individualized monitoring and is crucial to avoid NOM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Horta Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar las intervenciones farmacéuticas realizadas en el Área de Pacientes Externos de un hospital de segundo nivel. Métodos: Estudio observacional, retrospectivo y descriptivo. La recogida de datos se realizó desde octubre de 2010 hasta diciembre de 2011. Variables analizadas: Número de pacientes, edad, Servicio Clínico prescriptor, patología, problemas relacionados con la medicación (PRMs) y resultados negativos asociados a la medicación (RNM), tipo de intervención farmacéutica y principios activos implicados. Resultados principales: Se realizaron 231 intervenciones farmacéuticas, correspondientes a 231 PRMs detectados en 184 pacientes. Principales PRMs detectados: Interacciones farmacológicas (26%), errores en prescripción (15,6%) e incumplimiento terapéutico (15,6%). Sólo 26 (11,2%) PRMs provocaron RNMs. Las intervenciones principales fueron: recomendar modificaciones en el tratamiento (35,6%), potenciar monitorización de la eficacia del tratamiento (34,6%) y potenciar adherencia a los tratamientos (15,6%). Conclusión: La presencia de un farmacéutico optimiza la farmacoterapia de los pacientes evitando que se produzcan elevado número de RNMs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(4): 295-299, jul.-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117416</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las intervenciones farmacéuticas realizadas en el área de pacientes externos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
