<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163411</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Human papillomavirus nonavalent vaccine. Update 2017</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human papillomavirus (HPV) is the causative agent of 5% of human cancers. HPV infection is necessary for the development of cervical cancer and is responsible of a variable percentage of cancers of anus, vulva, vagina, penis, and oropharynx. Since 2007, 2 vaccines against HPV have been commercially available in Spain: bivalent (HPV types 16/18), and tetravalent (HPV types 6/11/16/18). In order to extend the protection afforded by HPV vaccines, a clinical program was launched in 2006 for the new nonavalent vaccine, including 9 HPV types (6/11/16/18/31/33/45/52/58). These types are responsible for 90% of cervical cancers, 82% of high-grade ano-genital pre-cancerous lesions, and 90% of genital warts. The purpose of this publication is to provide healthcare professionals with the scientific evidence that supports the new vaccine, as well as the clinical value that it offers in our environment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bosch, FX</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torné, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El virus del papiloma humano (VPH) es el agente causal del 5% de los casos de cáncer en humanos, siendo causa necesaria para el desarrollo del cáncer cervical y responsable de un porcentaje variable de casos de cáncer de ano, vulva, vagina, pene y orofaringe. Desde 2007, en España se comercializan 2 vacunas frente al VPH: bivalente (tipos VPH 16/18) y tetravalente (tipos VPH 6/11/16/18). Con el fin de ampliar la protección conferida por las vacunas frente al VPH, en el año 2006 se inició el programa clínico de la nueva vacuna nonavalente, que incluye 9 tipos de VPH (6/11/16/18/31/33/45/52/58). Estos tipos son responsables del 90% de cánceres cervicales, del 82% de lesiones precancerosas anogenitales de alto grado y del 90% de verrugas genitales. El objetivo de esta publicación es poner a disposición del profesional sanitario los datos científicos que avalan la nueva vacuna, así como el valor clínico que ofrece en nuestro medio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);43(4): 265-276, mayo-jun. 2017. tab, mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vacuna nonavalente frente al virus del papiloma humano. Actualización 2017</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50450^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14995^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50450^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11665^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23123^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24015^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
