<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139510</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differences in clinical features of two immigrant populations with tuberculosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A study was performed to assess differences in the clinical presentation of tuberculosis between two groups of immigrants. Ninety-four patients seen in the emergency room for newly diagnosed tuberculosis between 2006 and 2012 were included. Forty-nine patients were from Asian countries and 45 from Latin America. Mean age [years (SD)] was 35.3 (13) in Asian patients and 33.9 (10) in Latin American patients. Asian subjects were predominantly male (40/49 vs 25/45; P=0.006). Patients from Latin American countries had a higher rate of pulmonary tuberculosis. A higher percentage of Asian patients lived in overcrowded conditions, whereas HIV infection was more frequent among Latin Americans. Most patients were treated with a quadruple regimen. Resistance to isoniazid was documented in two patients from Latin America (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Álvarez, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Supervía, August</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallàs, Oriol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piccari, Lucilla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baño, Francisco del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Fernández, Sabina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cirera, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realizó un estudio descriptivo para identificar posibles diferencias en la presentación clínica de la tuberculosis entre 2 grupos de población inmigrante. Se incluyeron 94 pacientes visitados en urgencias y que fueron diagnosticados de tuberculosis activa en el periodo 2006-12. Cuarenta y nueve pacientes era originarios de Asia Central (A) y 45 de Latinoamérica (LA). La edad media (años [DE]) fue de 35,3 (13) años en los procedentes de A por 33,9 (10) en los de LA. Existía un predominio de varones en asiáticos (40/49 vs. 25/45; p = 0,006). Los pacientes procedentes de LA tenían mayor porcentaje de tuberculosis pulmonar. Los pacientes de A vivían en condiciones de hacinamiento con mayor frecuencia. Los pacientes de LA tenían más antecedentes de seropositividad para el VIH. La mayoría recibió tratamiento cuádruple. Dos pacientes latinoamericanos eran resistentes a isoniazida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(6): e29-e31, jun. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139510</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en los hallazgos clínicos en dos grupos de población inmigrante afecta de tuberculosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1216^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19039^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
