<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052787</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitions as determinants of (mal)adaptive emotions and emotionally intelligent behavior in an organizational context</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study applies the theoretical concepts of Rational Emotive Behavior Therapy (REBT; Ellis, 1962,     1994) to the analysis of functional and dysfunctional behaviour and emotions in the workplace and     tests central assumptions of REBT in an organizational setting. We argue that Ellis' appraisal theory     of emotion sheds light on some of the cognitive and emotional antecedents of emotional intelligence     and emotionally intelligent behaviour. In an extension of REBT, we posit that adaptive emotions resulting     from rational cognitions reflect more emotional intelligence than maladaptive emotions which     result from irrational cognitions, because the former lead to functional behaviour. We hypothesize that     semantically similar emotions (e.g. annoyance and rage) lead to different behavioural reactions and     have a different functionality in an organizational context. The results of scenario experiments using     organizational vignettes confirm the central assumptions of Ellis' appraisal theory and support our hypotheses     of a correspondence between adaptive emotions and emotionally intelligent behaviour. Additionally,     we find evidence that irrational job-related attitudes result in reduced work (but not life) satisfaction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Spörrle, Matthias </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Welpe, Isabel M </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Försterling, Friedrich </dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio aplica los conceptos teóricos de la Terapia Racional Emotiva Conductual (TREC; Ellis, 1962, 1994) al análisis del comportamiento y las emociones funcionales y disfuncionales en el lugar de trabajo y pone a prueba las asunciones centrales de la TREC en un escenario organizacional. Proponemos que la teoría de valoración de la emoción de Ellis arroja luz sobre algunos de los antecedentes cognitivos y emocionales de la inteligencia emocional y del comportamiento emocionalmente inteligente. Como extensión de la TREC, postulamos     que las emociones adaptativas producto de las cogniciones racionales reflejan más la inteligencia emocional     que las emociones mal adaptativas (no adaptativas) que son producto de las cogniciones irracionales,     porque las primeras llevan al comportamiento funcional. Hipotetizamos que emociones semánticamente     similares (e. g., enojo y rabia) llevan a reacciones comportamentales diferentes y tienen una funcionalidad distinta en un contexto organizacional. Los resultados de experimentos con escenarios utilizando viñetas organizacionales confirman las asunciones centrales de la teoría de evaluación de Ellis y apoyan nuestras hipótesis de correspondencia entre emociones adaptativas y comportamiento emocionalmente inteligente. Además, encontramos evidencias de que las actitudes irracionales relacionadas con el trabajo reducen la satisfacción con el trabajo (pero no con la vida)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(supl.1): 165-171, sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las cogniciones como determinantes de las emociones (mal) adaptativas y del comportamiento emocionalmente inteligente en el contexto organizacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12053^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10112</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d282^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
