<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158162</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy and safety of empagliflozin in combination with other oral hypoglycemic agents in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To analyze the efficacy and safety of empagliflozin combined with other oral hypoglycemic agents in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus. Methods: Pooled analysis of three phase III trials in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus (n=1,801) who received placebo or empagliflozin 10 or 25mg once daily for 24 weeks, in combination with metformin, metformin+sulphonylurea or pioglitazone ± metformin. Results: Empagliflozin significantly decreased HbA1c (adjusted mean reduction vs placebo with empagliflozin 10mg: &#150;0.58% [95% CI: &#150;0.66; &#150;0.49]; P&lt;.0001, and with empagliflozin 25mg: &#150;0.62% [95% CI: &#150;0.70; &#150;0.53], P&lt;.0001), weight (adjusted mean reduction vs placebo with empagliflozin 10mg: &#150;1.77kg [95% CI: &#150;2.05; &#150;1.48]; P&lt;.0001, and with empagliflozin 25mg: &#150;1.96kg [95% CI: &#150;2.24; &#150;1.67], P&lt;.0001), and systolic and diastolic blood pressure (SBP/DBP). Adverse effect rates were 64% with placebo, 63.9% with empagliflozin 10mg, and 60.9% with empagliflozin 25mg. Documented episodes of hypoglycemia (is less than or equal to70mg/dL and/or requiring care) occurred in 3.9% of patients with placebo, 6.9% of patients with empagliflozin 10mg, and 5.3% of patients with empagliflozin 25mg. Urinary tract infections developed in 9.4% of patients with placebo, 10.2% of patients with empagliflozin 10mg, and 8.3% of patients with empagliflozin 25mg. Genital infections were reported in 1.0% of patients with placebo, 4.6% of patients with empagliflozin 10mg, and 3.5% of patients with empagliflozin 25mg. Conclusions: Empagliflozin combined with other oral treatments decreased HbA1c, body weight, and SBP/DBP as compared to placebo, with a good safety and tolerability profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romera, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariño, Bernat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kis, Sanja Giljanovic</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naderali,  Ebrahim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ampudia Blasco, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pfarr, Egon</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Analizar la eficacia y la seguridad de empagliflozina en combinación con otros hipoglucemiantes orales en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2. Métodos: Análisis de 3 ensayos fase III en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (n=1.801) que recibieron placebo, empagliflozina 10 o 25mg, una vez al día, durante 24 semanas, en combinación con metformina, metformina+sulfonilurea o pioglitazona±metformina. Resultados: Empagliflozina redujo significativamente la HbA1c (reducción media ajustada vs. placebo con empagliflozina 10mg: &#150;0,58% [IC 95%: &#150;0,66; &#150;0,49]; p&lt;0,0001 y con empagliflozina 25mg &#150;0,62% [IC 95%: &#150;0,70; &#150;0,53], p&lt;0,0001), el peso (reducción media ajustada vs. placebo con empagliflozina 10mg: &#150;1,77kg [IC 95%: &#150;2,05; &#150;1,48]; p&lt;0,0001 y con empagliflozina 25mg: &#150;1,96kg [IC 95%: &#150;2,24; &#150;1,67], p&lt;0,0001) y la presión arterial sistólica y diastólica. La frecuencia de efectos adversos fue del 64% con placebo, del 63,9% con empagliflozina 10mg y del 60,9% con empagliflozina 25mg. Las hipoglucemias confirmadas (menor o igual a70mg/dl y/o requiriendo asistencia) ocurrieron en un 3,9% de los pacientes con placebo, un 6,9% con empagliflozina 10mg y un 5,3% con empagliflozina 25mg. Las infecciones del tracto urinario acontecieron en un 9,4% con placebo, un 10,2% con empagliflozina 10mg y un 8,3% con empagliflozina 25mg. Las infecciones genitales se comunicaron en un 1,0% de los pacientes con placebo, un 4,6% con empagliflozina 10mg y un 3,5% con empagliflozina 25mg. Conclusiones: Empagliflozina en combinación con otros tratamientos orales vs. placebo disminuyó significativamente la HbA1c, el peso corporal y la presión arterial sistólica/diastólica, con un buen perfil de seguridad y tolerancia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(10): 519-526, dic. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158162</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia y seguridad de empagliflozina en combinación con otros hipoglucemiantes orales en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11350^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50911^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13841^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
