<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167994</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Finding of choriocarcinoma during the puerperium following a vaginal delivery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Choriocarcinoma is a highly malignant epithelial tumour consisting exclusively of trophoblastic elements without chorionic villi and myometrial invasion. It is part of malignant gestational trophoblastic disease and is characterised by elevated blood levels of the hormone chorionic gonadotropin. Its prevalence is 1 in 50,000 pregnancies. Choriocarcinoma may arise from any trophoblastic tissue: molar pregnancy (50%), abortion (25%), ectopic pregnancy (2.5%) or normal pregnancy (22.5%). We present a case of choriocarcinoma diagnosed during the puerperium by the obstetrics emergency department (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Troncoso Saleh, AC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada Villar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Jiménez, LC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerrillos Morales, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Serrano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El coriocarcinoma es un tumor epitelial altamente maligno, constituido exclusivamente por elementos trofoblásticos con ausencia de vellosidades coriónicas e invasión del miometrio. Forma parte de la enfermedad trofoblástica gestacional maligna y se caracteriza por producir elevados niveles sanguíneos de hormona gonadotrofina coriónica. Su frecuencia es de uno por cada 50.000 gestaciones. El coriocarcinoma puede surgir de cualquier tejido trofoblástico: embarazo molar (50%), aborto (25%), embarazo ectópico (2,5%) y gestación normal (22,5%). Hemos de presentar un caso que nos surgió en la consulta de urgencias en obstetricia, que durante el puerperio fue diagnosticada de coriocarcinoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);44(4): 179-180, oct.-dic. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167994</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hallazgo de coriocarcinoma tras un puerperio de un parto eutócico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37265^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6210^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37265^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9407^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
