<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041933</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality and heroin: two words united by a project</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since 1999 when we asked ourselves if the heroin prescription were an alternative of treatment for heroin addicted people until today when we already have finished the Experimental Drug Prescription Program in Andalusia (PEPSA), we have walked a long way. After the works made in Switzerland, Holland and Andalusia, and the others running or starting in Germany, Canada, Catalonia, and United Kingdom, it can be affirmed that the prescribed heroin is a safe and feasible medicine to drug dependents patients for whom other available treatments were not effectives. The experience lived during nine months by the participants of this clinical trial, has been a process that started from the "fear", the "uncertainty" and the "doubt" to the stable situations in which today this patients live. To feel "respected and understood", plenty of "hope and future" and being able to accede a medicine that has restored "their dignity", give the answer to the initial question: heroin is an alternative to their treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oviedo, María E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marchab, Joan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Manolo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde que en 1999 nos preguntábamos si la prescripción de heroína era una alternativa de tratamiento para los adictos a ella hasta hoy, en que ya hemos terminado el Proyecto Experimental de Prescripción de Estupefacientes en Andalucía (PEPSA), hemos andado un largo camino. Después del trabajo realizado en Suiza, Países Bajos y Andalucía, y los que se están haciendo en Alemania, Canadá, Cataluña y Reino Unido, se puede afirmar que la heroína es un medicamento seguro y prescribible a drogodependientes para los que otros tratamientos actualmente disponibles no han sido efectivos. La experiencia vivida durante 9 meses por los participantes de este ensayo clínico ha sido un proceso en que se ha pasado del "miedo", la "incertidumbre" y la "duda" a las situaciones estables en las que hoy aquellos pacientes viven. Sentirse "respetados y comprendidos", llenos de "esperanza y futuro" y que pueden acceder a un medicamento que les ha devuelto "la dignidad", dan la respuesta a la pregunta inicial: la heroína es una alternativa para su tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(7): 396-399, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041933</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad y heroína: dos palabras unidas por un proyecto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3959^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6715^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6715^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
