<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051318</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We have made a historic account of tuberculosis. Tuberculosis was one of the greatest calamities that afflicted Humanity for centuries which made this disease to be known as the White Plague in the Middle Ages.    Its epidemiology reflects the social character of this condition and it was considered by some authors as late as the beginning the XX century, as the most deadly one in the civilized world.    At the same time, we revise the different criteria kept in the fight against tuberculosis. Special attention is paid to the c1inical and surgical treatments used until the appearance of streptomycin. The discovery of streptomycin brought a dramatic change to the prognosis of those affected by tuberculosis.    This artic1e contributes to widen the iconography of relevant figures related to the field, as well as to the presentation and discussion of events and other aspects in relation to tuberculosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galicia, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berbe, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Torga, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Realizamos una revisión histórica de la tuberculosis, enfermedad que durante siglos supuso uno de los mayores azotes que sufrió la humanidad, lo que hizo que en la Edad Media fuera conocida como la peste blanca.    Su epidemiología refleja el carácter social de esta enfermedad, considerada por algunos autores, todavía a comienzos del siglo XX, la más mortífera en los países civilizados.    Se revisan, asimismo, los criterios mantenidos en la lucha contra la tuberculosis y, especialmente, el tratamiento médico y quirúrgico utilizado hasta el descubrimiento de la estreptomicina, que cambió radicalmente su pronóstico.    El artículo aporta iconografía alusiva a figuras relevantes, acontecimientos y otros aspectos relacionados con la enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;11(3): 41-47, jul.-sept. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051318</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La tuberculosis, recuerdo histórico e iconografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23466^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28566^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37541^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
