<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164139</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9218</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk of negative results associated with proton pump inhibitors: review of electronic prescription in polymedicated patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Extensive use of proton pump inhibitors (PPI) can result in an increased risk of drug interactions. Aged polypharmacy patients are a source of particular concern. A systematic electronic prescription (EP) review allows detection of potential drug - drug interactions. Material and methods: Retrospective, transversal, observational study: review of e-prescription orders received during 2015 in our community pharmacy. Results: 1186 EP dispensed to 164 patients (age 65.7±17.2), 52 patients in 71-80 range. 11.0±5.6 medicines per patient. 27% IBP EP with no approved indication. 77% EP used as gastroprotective agent. As far as omeprazole is concerned, risk of negative outcomes associated with medication (NOM) detected in 29 patients (30%), 15 of them taking the drug without approved indication. Most prevalent comorbidities: hypertension (n=81), dyslipidemia (n=61) and diabetes (n=36). Drugs responsible for potential interaction: acenocoumarol, iron, cyanocobalamin, escitalopram, benzodiazepines and clopidogrel. Discussion: 80% of omeprazole EP were dispensed to patients aged 61-90. Coupled with multimorbidity and polypharmacy, the duration of the treatment exceeded directions for use in most of the cases. Chronification and increase of NOM may be due to lack of an appropriate patient follow-up procedure. Many of the drugs responsible for omeprazole interactions were prescribed to treat most prevalent health problems. Thus, risk of NOM does not appear to depend on PPI appropriate indication. Conclusions: EP review let us to assess the risk of suffering from a NOM. Reviewing pharmacokinetic PPI interaction profile allows to depict the basics for a later intervention. During EP review, safety and necessity NOMs were recorded in similar percentages. Most relevant interactions found for omeprazole occur during metabolism of the drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez López, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El elevado consumo de inhibidores de la bomba de protones (IBP) puede incrementar la probabilidad de aparición de interacciones clínicamente relevantes. Pacientes mayores, polimedicados y pluripatológicos representan un grupo de alto riesgo. Se espera que la revisión sistemática de las prescripciones electrónicas (PE) permita detectar potenciales interacciones farmacológicas. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo, transversal y observacional: revisión de las PE de IBP dispensadas entre enero y diciembre de 2015 en una farmacia comunitaria rural. Resultados: 1.186 PE, 164 pacientes (edad 65,7±17,2). Mayor número de pacientes en rango de edad 71-80 (n=52). Medicamentos por paciente: 11,0±5,6. PE IBP sin indicación aprobada: 27%. Indicación mayoritaria: protección frente a gastrolesión (77%). 29 pacientes (30%) con riesgo de resultados negativos asociados a la medicación (RNM) por omeprazol, 15 de ellos sin indicación. Patologías concomitantes más prevalentes: hipertensión arterial (n=81), dislipemia (n=61) y diabetes (n=36). Principios activos implicados: acenocumarol, hierro, cianocobalamina, escitalopram, benzodiazepinas y clopidogrel. Discusión: El 80% de las PE de omeprazol corresponde a pacientes entre 61 y 90 años, la mayoría con comorbilidad y polifarmacia, y supera el tiempo de tratamiento recomendado. Relacionamos la cronificación y el aumento del riesgo de RNM con la ausencia de un seguimiento adecuado. Muchos fármacos corresponsables del riesgo tratan los problemas de salud (PS) más prevalentes de nuestra población: la probabilidad de interacción resulta independiente de la correcta indicación del IBP. Conclusiones: La revisión de las PE permite valorar el riesgo de RNM y evaluar la información básica relativa al riesgo de interacción. Se detectaron RNM de no necesidad y de inseguridad en proporciones comparables. Un número elevado de PE de omeprazol tienden a cronificarse. Las interacciones más relevantes registradas ocurren a nivel metabólico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. comunitarios (Internet);9(2): 39-45, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de resultados negativos asociados a inhibidores de la bomba de protones: revisión de las prescripciones electrónicas en pacientes polimedicados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53392^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51446</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4424^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30587^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30587^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
