<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102706</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vitamin D: pathophysiology and clinical applicability in paediatrics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vitamin D has always been associated with calcium &#150;phosphate metabolism, but vitamin D receptors or its metabolites have been found in different body cells, indicating a possible involvement in other physiological mechanisms. Vitamin D deficiency has been associated with an increased risk of infections, autoimmune diseases, diabetes, metabolic syndrome, obesity, asthma and certain neurological diseases such as schizophrenia. Currently there are different techniques for measuring 25 (OH) cholecalciferol in blood, but the results are variable and controversial. It is important to achieve standardization of these techniques to be able to compare the results obtained in different studies. Normal physiological vitamin D levels have not yet been established, but they must be higher than 20 ng/ml (50 nmol/l) in order to perform it physiological function. It is still under discussion on how to achieve these minimum levels. Since the main source of vitamin D is sunlight, we should look for strategies that do not contradict the messages of prevention of skin cancer. In recent years, recommendations for vitamin D intake have changed, involving prophylactic activities carried out in Primary Care. This manuscript reviews the physiology, actions, laboratory determination, desirable levels, and vitamin D intake recommendations, and it highlights many questions raised by new research(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Masvidal Aliberch, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baraza Mendoza, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia-Algar, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortigosa Gómez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La vitamina D se ha relacionado siempre con el metabolismo fosfocálcico, pero se han encontrado receptores de la vitamina D o de sus metabolitos en diferentes células del organismo, lo que indica que puede estar implicada en otros mecanismos fisiológicos. El déficit de vitamina D se ha relacionado con un mayor riesgo de infecciones, enfermedades autoinmunitarias, diabetes, síndrome metabólico, obesidad, asma y ciertas enfermedades neurológicas, como la esquizofrenia. Actualmente existen diferentes técnicas para la determinación del 25 (OH) colecalciferol en sangre y hay discrepancias entre ellas en cuanto a los resultados obtenidos en una misma muestra. Es importante conseguir una uniformización de las técnicas que permitan estudios de investigación comparables. Todavía no se han establecido los valores adecuados de vitamina D en el organismo que aseguren todas sus funciones, pero se considera que no debe ser inferior a 20 ng/ml (50 nml/l), estando en discusión cómo conseguir estos niveles mínimos en toda la población. Dado que la principal fuente de vitamina D es la irradiación solar, hay que buscar estrategias que no entren en contradicción con los mensajes de prevención del cáncer de piel. En los últimos años se han producido variaciones en cuanto las recomendaciones de ingesta de vitamina D que implican a las actividades profilácticas que se realizan en el ámbito de la atención primaria. Este texto revisa la fisiología, las acciones, la determinación de laboratorio, los niveles deseables en el organismo y las recomendaciones de ingesta de la vitamina D, y resalta las numerosas cuestiones que plantean nuevas investigaciones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);77(4): 279-279[e1-e10], oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102706</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vitamina D: fisiopatología y aplicabilidad clínica en pediatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13860</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
