<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84777</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work is to present a clinical case of a patient who suffered from plantar fasciitis and plantar lipomas and its treatment. On the one hand, a literature review has been made in order to revise the anatomy, functionality and pathology of the plantar aponeurosis. On the other hand, the most important lipoma features and its different treatments are analysed. There is a wide range of treatments for the plantar fasciitis, but according to our experience, custommade orthoses have been proven to be effectively enough. Due to the custom-made orthoses, the feet experience a rebalancing force that leads to a relaxation of the plantar aponeurosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro Gabriel, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Olaizolâ, Idoia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo tiene como objetivo exponer un caso clínico en el que la paciente presenta fascitis y lipomas plantares con su posterior tratamiento. Se realiza una revisión bibliográfica, haciendo un recordatorio anatómico, funcional y patológico de la aponeurosis plantar. Por otro lado se analizan las características más importantes del lipoma y sus distintos tratamientos. Hay gran variedad de tratamientos para la fascitis plantar pero con la experiencia clínica obtenida, se considera eficaz realizar un tratamiento ortopodológico. Gracias a la incorporación de un soporte plantar se produce un reequilibrio de fuerzas en el pie y esto conlleva una relajación de dicha aponeurosis plantar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Peu;30(4): 194-201, oct.-dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento ortopodológico en un caso de fascitis plantar y lipoma en el pie</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37269^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37270^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14366^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37269^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37270^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
