<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108738</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1837</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Advances in the etiopathogenesis of hypertension: update on preclinical research</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Currently, multidisciplinary approaches are used to study the causes of increased blood pressure and its mechanisms and the pharmacological treatments of hypertension. Although many advances have been produced, there are still concepts, mechanisms and questions that remain to be elucidated. Participants at the Vascular Physiopathology Research Meetings of the Spanish Society of Hypertension-Spanish League Against Hypertension have been able to learn about and better understand the etiopathogenes is of hypertension and the diseases in which it is one of the main risk factors. This review summarizes the most novel aspects presented at the last 4 meetings and which have been published in journals indexed by Journal Citation Report (JCR) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Rosa, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras, Natalia de las</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio de las causas y mecanismos por los cuales se produce un aumento de los niveles de presión arterial así como el tratamiento farmacológico en hipertensión comprende un abordaje multidisciplinar en el que, pese a que se han producido múltiples avances, aún quedan conceptos, mecanismos y preguntas sin responder. Con motivo de la acertada creación de la Reunión de Investigación en Fisiopatología Vascular (RIFV) de la Sociedad Española  de Hipertensión Liga Española para la Lucha contra la Hipertensión Arterial (SEH-LELHA), los asistentes a la misma hemos podido aprender y comprender mejor la etiopatogenia de la hipertensión arterial así como las enfermedades a las que afecta siendo uno de los principales factores de riesgo. En esta revisión vamos a resumir aquellos aspectos más novedosos que se presentaron en las 4 últimas ediciones de la RIFV y que &amp;#64257;nalmente se han publicado en revistas cientí&amp;#64257;cas indexadas en el Journal Citation Report (JCR) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertens. riesgo vasc;29(3): 86-95, Jul. -Sep. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108738</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances en la etiopatogenia de la hipertensión arterial: actualización en la investigación preclínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
