<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73613</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Although every country has its own sanitary system ofemergencies, arisen based on a few needs and suitableresources, they all coincide with the creation of a structureof vehicles available and attended by specific personnelwith sanitary matter, stipendiary well or of voluntary form,that across a joint coordination, they attend of the possiblemost rapid and effective form to the population needed toattend in the place to some, and others also, to transport itto a center sanitary. The above mentioned systems of emergencyanswer habitually to these welfare needs and oftrasporte and are usually coordinated by a few centers towhich one gains access in some parts of the world acrossthe only phone as 112 (Europe) and 911 (America).According to the political sanitary ones of every country,there has been formed a model different from sanitary systemof emergencies in every region of the world. Every systemis construed in turn for a profile different from sanitarypersonnel(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caravaca Caballero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunque cada país tiene su propio sistema de emergenciassanitario, surgido en base a unas necesidades y recursosadecuados, todos coinciden en la creación de unaestructura de vehículos disponibles y atendidos por personalespecífico en materia sanitaria, bien remunerados o deforma voluntaria, que a través de una coordinación conjunta,atienden de la forma más rápida y eficaz posible a lapoblación necesitada para atenderla en el lugar algunos, yotros además, transportarla a un centro sanitario. Dichossistemas de emergencia responden habitualmente a estasnecesidades asistenciales y de trasporte y suelen estar coordinadospor unos centros a los que se accede en algunaspartes del mundo a través de un teléfono único como son el112 (Europa) y 911 (América). Según las políticas sanitariasde cada país, se ha configurado un modelo diferente de sistemade emergencias sanitario en cada región del mundo.Cada sistema está constituido a su vez por un perfil diferentede personal sanitario(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;9(1): 51-56, ene.-mar. 2009. ^f51^l56</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73613</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los sistemas de emergencias sanitarios en el mundo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24425</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52888^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52888^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35146</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
