<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142346</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Limitation of therapeutic effort. Opinion by Universtity Nursing Students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to learn the opinion of Nursing students about the Limitation of Therapeutic Effort (LTE). Method: a transversal descriptive study on 97 students of the 3rd and 4th year at the Virgen de las Nieves University School of Nursing in Granada, through the self-administered anonymous questionnaire validated by Llaja Rojas et al. Other variables: profession, gender, marital status, age, years of experience at work, and religion. Data treatment and analysis: descriptive analysis of variables and bivariate analysis through Chi Square Test. Results: a 48.4% of participants defined themselves as nonpracticing Catholics. For 91.8% of them, patients have the higher burden of decision regarding LTE. Regarding euthanasia, 88.9% of them agreed that it should be made legal, and 92.5% of them would apply it. 92.5% of non-practicing Catholics agreed with making euthanasia legal, vs. 100% of non-believers (p&lt; 0.000). For 90.9% of non-believers, vs. 54.5% of practicing Catholics, there is no quality of life if connected to a mechanical ventilator (p= 0.026). Conclusions: nursing students will take into account to a high extent the opinion of the patient about LTE. The majority are in favour of making euthanasia legal and applying it, as well as antidysthanasia and orthotanasia. Religious beliefs have impact on some of the matters explored. A high majority considered that situations such as living in a wheelchair, having a permanent colostomy, receiving chemotherapy or having a definitive tracheostomy, could provide a certain quality of life, showing a very positive opinion about the disease process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cobos Vargas, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardia Mesa, Manuel Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Carmona, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Vega, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer la opinión de los estudiantes de Enfermería sobre la limitación del esfuerzo terapéutico (LET). Método: estudio descriptivo transversal sobres 97 alumnos de 3º y 4º curso de la Escuela Universitaria de Enfermería Virgen de las Nieves de Granada, mediante el cuestionario anónimo autoadministrado, validado por Llaja Rojas et al. (15). Otras variables: profesión, sexo, estado civil, edad, años de experiencia laboral y religión. Tratamiento y análisis de los datos: análisis descriptivo de las variables y análisis bivariante mediante la prueba Ji Cuadrado. Resultados: el 48,4% se declaraba católico no practicante. Para el 91,8% la decisión de mayor peso en cuanto a la LET la tiene el paciente. En cuanto a la eutanasia, un 88,9% estaba de acuerdo con legalizarla y un 92,5% la aplicaría. El 92,5% de los católicos no practicantes estaban de acuerdo con legalizar la eutanasia, frente al 100% de los no creyentes (p&lt; 0,000). Para un 90,9% de los no creyentes, frente a un 54,5% de los católicos practicantes, no hay calidad de vida si se está conectado a un ventilador mecánico (p= 0,026). Conclusiones: los estudiantes de Enfermería tienen muy en cuenta la opinión del paciente ante la LET. Mayoritariamente están a favor de legalizar la eutanasia y aplicarla, así como la antidistanasia y ortotanasia. Las creencias religiosas tienen influencia sobre algunas de las cuestiones exploradas. Una gran mayoría considera que situaciones como vivir en silla de ruedas, tener colostomía permanente, recibir quimioterapia o tener traqueostomía definitiva, pueden otorgar cierta calidad de vida, mostrando una opinión muy positiva del proceso de enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;18(8): 20-24, oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142346</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Limitación del esfuerzo terapéutico. Opinión de estudiantes universitarios de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5201^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
