<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107804</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retrospective assessment of effective and safety of cinacalcet for the treatment of secondary hyperparathyroidism depending on basal iPTH level</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective Cinacalcet is a calcimimetic agent, recommended for treating refractory secondary hyperparathyroidism in patients undergoing dialysis. The aim of this study was to evaluate the efficacy and safety of cinacalcet, comparing patients with baseline iPTH &gt; 300 pg/ml with those with iPTH &lt; 300 pg/ml. Method Observational retrospective study of patients being treated with cinacalcet 30mg/day from January 2008 to January 2009.We studied 26 patients, 15 with iPTH &gt; 300 pg/ml and 11 with iPTH &lt; 300pg/ml. The primary efficacy outcome was that there was a reduction between baseline and final iPTH (4 month). The secondary efficacy outcome were the reduction between basal and final calcium, phosphorus, Ca x P, and the percentage of patients with an iPTH decrease &gt; 30%. The safety was evaluated based on the most frequent adverse effects and the levels of serum calcium &lt; 8.6mg/dl. Results Patients with initial iPTH &gt; 300 had significant differences before and after cinacalcet treatment in iPTH (563.49+286.88 pg/ml vs 315.15+201.948 pg/ml; P=.017) and serum calcium (9.1+1.77mg/dl vs 8.15+1.2mg/dl; P=.02). There were no significant differences in patients with initial iPTH &lt; 300 pg/ml. A decrease greater than 30% from baseline iPTH was observed in 60% of patients with baseline iPTH &gt; 300pg/ml, and only in 27.3% of those with basal iPTH &lt; 300 pg/ml (P=.098). Patients did not show gastric intolerance. Conclusions Cinacalcet is an effective and safe drug for controlling secondary hyperparathyroidism in dialysis, mainly when it is used in patients with baseline iPTH &gt; 300 pg/ml. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blasco Mascaró, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercadal Orfila, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Cinacalcet es un calcimimético recomendado para el tratamiento del hiperparatiroidismo secundario en pacientes en diálisis. El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar la eficacia y seguridad de cinacalcet comparando pacientes con PTHi basal &gt; 300 pg/ml vs. PTHi &lt; 300 pg/ml. Métodos Estudio observacional retrospectivo de pacientes en tratamiento con cinacalcet 30mg/día desde enero de 2008 a enero de 2009.Estudiamos 26 pacientes, 15 PTHi &gt; 300 pg/ml y 11 PTHi &lt; 300 pg/ml.La variable principal de eficacia fue la reducción entre el valor basal y final de PTHi (4 meses).Como variables secundarias se registró la reducción entre valor basal y final de calcio, fósforo, CaxP, y porcentaje de pacientes con reducción de PTHi superior al 30%.La seguridad se evaluó por los efectos secundarios más frecuentes y nivel de calcio &lt; 8,6mg/dl. Resultados Los pacientes con PTHi &gt; 300 presentaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre valor basal y final de PTH (563,49+286,88 pg/ml vs. 315,15+201,948 pg/ml; p=0,017) y calcio (9,1+1,77mg/dl vs. 8,15+1,2mg/dl; p=0,02). No hubo diferencias en los pacientes con PTHi &lt; 300 pg/ml. Se observó reducción de más del 30% de la PTHi basal en el 60% de pacientes con PTHi basal &gt; 300 pg/ml, y en el 27,3% de los que tenían PTHi basal &lt; 300 pg/ml (p=0,098). No se reportó intolerancia gastrointestinal. Conclusión Cinacalcet es un fármaco efectivo y seguro en el tratamiento del hiperpartiroidismo secundario en pacientes dializados, con valores basales de PTHi &gt; 300 pg/ml (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;36(1): 11-15, ene. -feb. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107804</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación retrospectiva de la efectividad y seguridad de cinacalcet para el tratamiento de hiperparatiroidismo secundario dependiendo del valor basal de paratohormona intacta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7141^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28245^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16735</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54038^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
