<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053862</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Excimer excilite. Advances in the use of 308 nm. monochromatic light in Dermatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The advance in the therapeutic for some chronic dermatosis disease, lead to target new areas of action at molecular levels with the less damage on    normal skin. The selective irradiation to the affected skin with 308-nm. UVB light to produce a local immunomodulator effect, decrease the T cells    number in epidermic and dermic level. As UVB narrow-band, this delivery system is usefulla for the treatment of some localized chronic dermatosis    such as psoriasis, vitiligo, eczemas, alopecia areata, skin lymphoma (mycosis fungoide, stage 1A), liquen and so on. The 308-nm. laser/lamp offers    some advances over current therapy modalities in the treatment of localized dermatosis: they can treat exclusively afectted skin, with less risk for    the uninvolved surrounding skin, higher dose-increase schemes, leading to faster healing and reduced cumulative dosis. We present the 308-nm.    monochromatic light excimer excilite and its indications in dermathology</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galimberti, Gastón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrario, Damián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galimberti, Ricardo Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giusti, Camila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galimberti, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Chiapetta, Florencia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los avances en la fototerapéutica de ciertas enfermedades dermatológicas crónicas, apuntan a encontrar nuevos sitios de acción a niveles    moleculares con el menor daño de estructuras sin patología. La luz UVB a 308 nm. sobre la piel, produce un efecto inmunomodulador local,    con disminución de los linfocitos T a nivel epidérmico y dérmico. Estos sistemas se sumarían a la batería terapéutica que dispone el dermatólogo    para el tratamiento de ciertas dermatosis crónicas como: psoriasis, vitíligo, eccemas, alopecia areata, linfoma cutáneo (micosis fungoide, estadio    1A), liquen plano, etc. Las ventajas de los sistemas láser/lámpara de 308 nm. sobre las actuales modalidades terapéuticas en el tratamiento de    ciertas dermatosis crónicas, son: la posibilidad del tratamiento selectivo de la piel afectada, con menor riesgo de efectos adversos sobre la piel    sana circundante, aplicación de esquemas a altas dosis, lo que lleva a una rápida curación con una menor dosis acumulada. Presentamos la luz    monocromática 308 nm. excimer excilite y sus avances en la utilización en dermatología</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;34(3): 99-108, mayo-jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053862</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Excimer excilite. Avance en la utilización de luz monocromática de 308 nm. en Dermatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29459^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15222^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d509^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
