<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054074</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic radical prostatectomy: learning curve with a mentor training program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Material and Methods: From March 2004 through December 2005, we have performed 105 (LRP). Three    groups have been analysed: Group 1: The mentor as the first surgeon with the trainee acting as the assistant.    Group 2: The trainee as the first surgeon with the mentor acting as the assistant. Group 3: The trainee    as the first surgeon with another trainee/resident as the assistant. We have evaluated operative, postoperative    data and surgical/oncological control.    Results: There was no statistical difference in mean operative time in Groups 2 and 3 (200&#146;-198&#146;), but    there was a difference from Group 1 (148,4&#146;) (p&lt;0,05) we have observed a progressive operative time decrease    only in Group 1. Blood loss, surgical-oncological control, pathological stage and hospital stay have been    similar in the three groups.    Conclusions: Skills for LRP can be effectively and safely taught by the presence of an experienced mentor.    Waiting for long term results according to potency and continence, it was not associated to higher patient risk,    neither to a worse surgical/oncologic outcome. We consider that this program is reproducible and allows a    shorter learning curve</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orsola de los Santos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas Morin, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trilla Herrera, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raventós Busquets, C. X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>ecchini Rosell, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morote Robles, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Exponer con detalle el sistema de aprendizaje de la prostatectomía radical laparoscópica (PRL)    con tutor llevado a cabo en nuestro centro así como los resultados.    Material y métodos: Se realiza el análisis de variables intraquirúrgicas, postoperatorias y del control quirúrgico    y oncológico de la pieza, de 105 PRL (marzo 2004-diciembre 2005) según los siguientes grupos:    Grupo 1: tutor como primer cirujano y alumno como asistente. Grupo 2 alumno como primer cirujano y el    tutor como ayudante. Grupo 3: alumno como primer cirujano y otro alumno/residente como ayudante.    Resultados: No se han observado diferencias significativas en cuanto la media de tiempo quirúrgico (TQ)    entre el grupo 2 y 3 (188&#146;-170&#146;, p=0,09). Ésta ha sido menor en el Grupo 1 (150&#146;, p&lt;0,05), disminuyendo con    el tiempo. La pérdida sanguínea, el control quirúrgico-oncológico, el estadio patológico y el tiempo de estancia    hospitalaria han sido similares en los tres grupos.    Conclusiones: La presencia de un laparoscopista experto como tutor permite aprender la PRL de manera    segura y efectiva. En espera de los resultados funcionales y oncológicos a largo plazo, este sistema de    aprendizaje no se asocia ni con un mayor riesgo para el paciente ni con un peor control quirúrgico/oncológico.    Consideramos que este método es fácilmente reproducible y permite un acortamiento de la curva de    aprendizaje</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(3): 205-210, mar.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054074</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prostatectomía radical laparoscópica: la curva de aprendizaje con tutor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
