<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111139</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Positive effects of physical exercise on reducing the relationship between subcutaneous abdominal fat and morbility risk</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The consequences related to the accumulation of abdominal fat above healthy levels create a considerable organic damage. Among the physiological consequences we can highlight heart diseases, hypertension, type-2 diabetes, obesity and metabolic syndrome, which drastically reduce life expectancy and quality. Evidence shows that health improvement is correlated to greater levels of physical activity. However, physical exercise can create oxidative damage on organs and muscular tissue, more relevant in subjects with a high percentage of abdominal fat. This piece of work determines which are the fundamental variables of the exercise program in order to optimize its advantages while minimizing oxidative stress. Main purpose: To know the key variables in the accumulation of abdominal fat above healthy levels, and the role of exercise in prevention and improvement of such issue. Specific purposes: 1) to identify the key variables in an exercise program aimed at reducing abdominal fat; 2) to understand the relationship between abdominal fat, health and exercise; 3) to review the latest research related to physical exercise and its effect on abdominal adipose tissue. Methodology: A search and identification of original and reviewed articles will be carried out in indexed impact journals within the main databases. Discussion: Regular physical exercise, most notably aerobic one, reduces body adipose tissue deposits in general, and abdominal ones in particular, both in obese and overweight subjects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pozo Rosado,  P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Calvo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sánchez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Justificación: Las consecuencias derivadas de la acumulación de grasa abdominal por encima de niveles saludables infligen un considerable daño a nivel orgánico. Entre las consecuencias fisiológicas destacan las enfermedades cardiovasculares, hipertensión, diabetes tipo 2, obesidad y síndrome metabólico, que reducen drásticamente la calidad y esperanza de vida. Hay evidencias de que la mejora de la salud es proporcional al incremento de actividad física. No obstante, el ejercicio físico puede ocasionar daño oxidativo en órganos y tejidos musculares más acusado en personas con un elevado porcentaje graso abdominal. En este trabajo se determinan cuáles son las variables fundamentales del programa de ejercicio para optimizar sus beneficios y minimizar el estrés oxidativo. Objetivo principal: Conocer las variables determinantes de una acumulación de masa grasa abdominal por encima de los niveles saludables y el papel que juega el ejercicio en su prevención y mejora. Objetivos específicos: 1) Identificar las variables fundamentales de un programa de ejercicio enfocado a reducir la grasa abdominal; 2) Comprender la relación entre grasa abdominal, salud y ejercicio; 3) Revisar las últimas investigaciones en relación a la práctica de ejercicio físico y su efecto sobre el tejido adiposo abdominal. Metodología: Se llevará a cabo una búsqueda e identificación en artículos originales y de revisión publicados en revistas de impacto indexadas en las principales bases de datos. Discusión: El ejercicio físico habitual, fundamentalmente el de carácter aeróbico, produce una disminución en los depósitos de tejido adiposo corporal y abdominal en las personas obesas y con sobrepeso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(4): 685-691, jul.-ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre tejido graso abdominal y riesgo de morbilidad: efectos positivos del ejercicio físico en la reducción de esta tendencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38802^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50376^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53563^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34404^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
