<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130225</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Minimally invasive video-assisted parathyroidectomy without intraoperative parathyroid hormone monitoring</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: surgical treatment of primary hyperparathyroidism has evolved from the classical bilateral neck exploration to minimally invasive techniques due to recent advances in preoperative localisation methods. The additional value of intraoperative parathyroid hormone (PTH) monitoring is questioned. The aim of this study was to analyse the results of minimally invasive video-assisted parathyroidectomy (MIVAP) without intraoperative PTH monitoring. Methods: the patients who underwent MIVAP without PTH monitoring for primary hyperparathyroidism between 2007 and 2013 were evaluated. In all cases the suspected enlarged gland was identified preoperatively by 99Tc-sestamibi scintigraphy, ultrasound or computed tomography. Results: 71 patients were studied (56 females and 15 males), with a mean age of 60 years. In 3 cases (4%) the technique was converted to open parathyroidectomy. Calcium and PTH levels were normalised after first surgery in 69 cases (97%), and after a second surgery in the remaining 2 cases (a second contralateral and a second intrathyroid adenoma). One patient developed a postoperative wound infection, 1 postoperative hypocalcaemia, and 4 transient vocal fold paralysis. No permanent vocal fold paralysis or other complications were observed. Conclusions: MIVAP is a safe, effective surgical technique to cure primary hyperparathyroidism. Intraoperative PTH monitoring may not be routinely necessary in patients treated with this technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coca Pelaz, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, Juan Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Marquez, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La cirugía del hiperparatiroidismo primario ha evolucionado desde la clásica exploración bilateral del cuello hacia las técnicas mínimamente invasivas gracias a la mejora en los métodos de localización preoperatoria. La necesidad de emplear la determinación intraoperatoria de hormona paratiroidea (PTH) como adjunto a estas técnicas es debatida. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar los resultados de la paratiroidectomía mínimamente invasiva videoasistida (MIVAP) sin la determinación de PTH intraoperatoria. Métodos: Se estudia a los pacientes intervenidos mediante MIVAP entre los años 2007 y 2013 por hiperparatiroidismo primario sin realizar determinación de PTH intraoperatoria. En todos los casos, había una localización preoperatoria del posible adenoma mediante gammagrafía con 99Tc-sestamibi, ecografía o tomografía computarizada. Resultados: Se incluyó en el estudio a 71 pacientes (56 mujeres y 15 varones) con una edad media de 60 años. Hubo que convertir la técnica a paratiroidectomía abierta en 3 casos (4%). Se consiguió la normalización de los niveles de calcio y PTH en la primera cirugía en 69 pacientes (97%) y en los 2 restantes (un segundo adenoma contralateral y otro segundo adenoma intratiroideo) en una segunda intervención. Un paciente presentó una infección de la herida quirúrgica, otro una hipocalcemia, y 4 una parálisis recurrencial transitoria. No hubo parálisis permanentes ni otras complicaciones. Conclusiones: La MIVAP es una técnica eficaz y segura para el tratamiento quirúrgico del hiperparatiroidismo primario. La determinación de PTH intraoperatoria no parece ser necesaria de rutina en los pacientes operados mediante esta técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;65(6): 355-360, nov.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130225</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paratiroidectomía mínimamente invasiva videoasistida sin determinación intraoperatoria de hormona paratiroidea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50516^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55043^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34526^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29078^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
