<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14561</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New forms, old interests: neosexism among Spanish men</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the present paper the construct of «Neosexism», as one of the new forms of sexism, and the Spanish version of the Neosexism scale (Tougas, Brown, Beaton &amp; Joly,(1995) are presented. Using a sample of 1191 men, we tested the psychometric properties of the scale and the relationship between Neosexism and some other sociodemographic characteristics and with old-fashioned sexism, attitudes toward affirmative action and men&#146;s collective interest. Ours results show that «Neosexism», a construct created in a cultural and economic context different to Spain, could be applied to a Spanish context. We also found that the Neosexism scale can be an appropriate instrument to measure modern forms of sexism, specially in organizational and work settings. A mediational analysis performed on the data suggest that, among men, neosexist beliefs influence subjective threat to collective interests, this perceived threat triggering an opposition to affirmative action programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Expósito, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se presenta el constructo "Neosexismo", como una de las nuevas formas de sexismo, y la versión e castellano de la escala de Neosexismo de Tougas,Brown, Beaton &amp; Joly (1995). En una muestra de 1191 varones se analizan las propiedades psicométricas de la escala y la relación del Neosexismo con algunas características sociodemográficas de los participantes y con el sexismo tradicional, la actitud hacia las políticas de acción positiva y la percepción de amenaza que estas políticas exponen para los intereses colectivos de los varones. Los resultados muestran que el constructo "Neosexismo" elaborado en un contexto cultural y económico distinto al español, es aplicable a la realidad de nuestro país y que la escala de Neosexismo puede ser un instrumento adecuado para medir formas modernas de sexismo, especialmente en el campo laboral. Los resultados de un análisis mediacional sugieren que, entre los varones, las creencias neosexistas llevan a la percepción de amenaza hacia los intereses colectivos y eso facilita la oposición hacia las medidas de acción positiva, (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(4): 643-649, nov. 2001. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14561</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas formas, viejos intereses: neosexismo en varones españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28895</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15330^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
