<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63756</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES. To analyze the patients seen and referred to the reference hospital by an out-patient emergency service in order to know their profile and characteristics as well as the quality of the information, to optimize this process and to produce an improvement in the quality of service. MATERIAL AND METHODS. Retrospective cross-sectional descriptive observational study of all the patients seen and referred to the reference hospital by the emergency service of Campoo during year 2002. Sociodemographic, care and report quality variables were collected. For the descriptive statistics, the mean and standard deviation for the quantitative variables and percentages for the qualitative ones were used. The Student's t test for independent samples was used for the comparison of two means and the chi-square for qualitative variables. RESULTS. A total of 707 patients, average age of 53.9 years and masculine predominance, were referred. The most frequent cause of referral was bone fractures and by code CIPSAP-2, traumatisms and poisoning (XVII). Most of the referrals occurred in the afternoon. Medication is usually not required and the quality of the clinical report was mostly good. CONCLUSIONS. The level of resolution of the service was 94% and the main cause of referral is traumatological. Therefore facilitating access to tests of diagnose and therapeutic at level of the out-patient emergency service, improving the formation and qualification of the sanitary staff and making referral protocols can optimize and reduce hospitable referrals. The quality of the referral report can be considered good</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río Madrazo, J. A. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Lanza, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dierssen Sotos, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa Puente, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raba Oruña, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS. Analizar a los pacientes atendidos y derivados al hospital de referencia por un servicio de urgencias extrahospitalarias (SUE), a fin de conocer el perfil y las características, así como la calidad de los informes, para intentar optimizar este proceso y producir una mejora de la calidad del servicio. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS. Estudio observacional descriptivo transversal retrospectivo de todas las asistencias atendidas y derivadas al hospital de referencia por el SUE de Campoo durante el año 2002. Se recogieron variables sociodemográficas, asistenciales y de la calidad del informe. Para la estadística descriptiva se usó la media y la desviación estándar para las variables cuantitativas y porcentajes para las cualitativas; para la comparación de dos medias se ha utilizado la prueba de la t de Student para comparar muestras independientes y la Chi cuadrado para variables cualitativas. RESULTADOS. Se derivaron 707 pacientes, con media de edad de 53,9 años y predominio masculino. La causa más frecuente de derivación fueron las fracturas óseas y por código CIPSAP-2 los traumatismos y envenenamientos (XVII); la mayor derivación se produce por las tardes; no suele requerirse medicación; la calidad del volante fue mayoritariamente buena. CONCLUSIONES. El nivel de resolución del servicio fue del 94%; la principal causa de derivación es traumatológica, por lo que facilitar el acceso a pruebas diagnósticas y terapéuticas a nivel del servicio de urgencias hospitalarias, mejorar la formación y capacitación del personal sanitario y la realización de protocolos de derivación pueden optimizar y reducir las derivaciones hospitalarias. La calidad del volante en general puede considerarse buena</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(7): 341-348, ago. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63756</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29873^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
