<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134926</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of eating disorders in college students and associated factors: uniHcos project</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: eating disorders (ED) are particularly common in young people. Objective: To determine the prevalence of eating disorders in college students and its associated factors. Methods: Study of prevalence in young Spanish university uniHcos project. Using unconditional logistic regression have determined the magnitude of the association between the risk factors associated with lifestyle and ED measured by questionnaire Sick, Control, One, Fat, Food (SCOFF). Results: The prevalence of ED was 19.5%, being higher in women (ORa=1.59; p=0.006). In boys, have criteria of developing an eating disorder was associated with living in halls of residence, &#147;binge drinking&#148; and problematic Internet use. In women studying different courses at Health Sciences (ORa=1.50) and problematic Internet use (ORa=2.33). Those women at risk of ED more frequently had depression (ORa=2.02), menstrual pains (ORa=1.81) and perceived poor health (ORa=1.70). In men, those at risk for eating disorders more frequently had poor perceived health (ORa=2.42). Conclusions: The risk of a positive outcome in the scoff in our study is similar to that reported for other populations of students as well as their association with certain health problems and addictions. By gender differences that need attention in the design of prevention and control strategies were observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Villa, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno Cavanillas, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina de la Torre, Antonio José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Sánchez, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayán Pérez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos Campos, Ramona</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capelo Álvarez, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-González, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria (TCA) son especialmente frecuentes en los jóvenes. Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de TCA en jóvenes universitarios y sus factores asociados. Metodología: Estudio de prevalencia en jóvenes universitarios españoles del proyecto uniHcos. Mediante regresión logística no condicional se determinó la magnitud de la asociación entre los factores de riesgo asociados al estilo de vida y padecer un TCA medido mediante el cuestionario Sick, Control, One, Fat, Food (SCOFF). Resultados: La prevalencia de TCA fue del 19,5%, siendo mayor en mujeres (ORa=1,59; p=0,006). En los chicos, tener criterios de padecer TCA se asoció con vivir en colegios mayores, con realizar &#147;binge drinking&#148;, y uso problemático de internet. En las mujeres el estudiar titulaciones diferentes a las ciencias de la salud (ORa=1,50) y el uso problemático de internet (ORa=2,33). Aquellas mujeres con riesgo de TCA presentaban con mayor frecuencia depresión (ORa=2,02), dolores menstruales (ORa=1,81) y mala salud percibida (ORa=1,70). En los hombres, aquellos con riesgo de TCA presentaban con mayor frecuencia una mala salud percibida (ORa=2,42). Conclusiones: El riesgo de obtener resultados positivos en el SCOFF en nuestro estudio es similar a lo publicado para otras poblaciones de estudiantes, así como su asociación con determinadas adicciones y problemas de salud. Se observaron diferencias en función del sexo que precisan atención en el diseño de estrategias de prevención y control (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(4): 927-934, oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134926</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de trastornos de la conducta alimentaria en universitarios españoles y factores asociados: proyecto uniHcos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
