<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107387</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low back pain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 67 year old male with a history of high blood pressure, dyslipidemia, obesity, diabetes mellitus and chronic ischemic cardiomyopathy, seeking medical assistance for low back pain, which had commenced 15 days before without an obvious triggering factor and which, although it was initially centred in the back, now affected the buttock, the posterosuperior side of the right thigh and inguinal area. He experienced moderately intense pain and felt relief on resting and taking analgesics. The biggest challenge in diagnosing low back pain is to differentiate between those cases originating in benign musculoskeletal processes and those produced by specific disease which require fast and appropriate treatment. Although it is not usually recommended to carry out imaging tests (X-rays, RNM, TAC) on patients with acute low back pain without clear warning signs, they were carried out on the patient due to the above criteria. The X-ray showed degenerative signs and the presence of calcification and possible infrarenal aortic dilation. An ultrasound scan was carried out, corroborating the presence of a 5cm diameter abdominal aortic aneurysm. He was sent to a hospital emergency department where a TAC was carried out, confirming the diagnosis and was referred to vascular surgery, given its size and the possible association of symptoms(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sastre, José Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Losáñez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbayo García, José Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Varón de 67 años de edad, con antecedentes de hipertensión arterial, dislipemia, obesidad, diabetes mellitus y cardiopatía isquémica crónica, que consulta por presentar dolor en la parte baja de la espalda. Dolor iniciado hace 15 días sin un desencadenante claro y que, aunque inicialmente estaba centrado en la espalda, actualmente también afecta a la nalga, la cara posterosuperior del muslo derecho y región inguinal. Dolor de moderada intensidad y mejora parcialmente con el reposo y con analgésicos. El reto más importante en el diagnóstico de la lumbalgia es diferenciar los casos cuyo origen son procesos musculoesqueléticos benignos de los producidos por enfermedades específicas que precisan un rápido y adecuado tratamiento. Aunque habitualmente no se recomienda la realización de pruebas de imagen (radiografía, RNM, TAC) en pacientes con dolor lumbar agudo sin signos de alarma, en el paciente se realizó por los criterios antes descritos. La Radiografía muestra signos degenerativos y la presencia de calcificación y posible dilatación aortica infrarrenal. Se realiza ecografía abdominal que corrobora la presencia de aneurisma de aorta abdominal de 5 cm de diámetro. Es enviado a urgencias hospitalarias donde se realiza TAC, que confirma el diagnóstico y se deriva a cirugía vascular dado el tamaño que presenta y la posible asociación de síntomas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;5(2): 140-143, 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107387</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lumbalgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
