<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115369</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social anxiety and dysfunctional cognitive schemas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study assessed the association between cognitive schemas (Young Schema Questionnaire-Short Form, YSQ-SF; Young &amp; Brown, 1994) and social anxiety (Social Interaction Questionnaire for Adults-Revised, CISO-AR; Caballo, et al., 2006) in a sample of 639 students (309 men and 327 women). The following findings were obtained: (1) Social anxiety is mainly associated with schemas that involve abandonment, failure, and emotional inhibition. (2) There are some peculiarities depending on the situation in which the individuals experienced anxiety, with the schema of subjugation linked with anxiety in situations that imply the expression of upset, and the defectiveness/shame schema linked to anxiety in the relationship with people of different sex. (3) Participants who showed generalized social anxiety scored higher than participants with specific social anxiety in abandonment, defectiveness, failure, dependency, emotional inhibition, and lack of self-control. (4) Finally, although women scored higher on social anxiety, we did not find gender differences in the relationship between schemas and social anxiety, with the exception of abandonment and subjugation which were more intensively associated with anxiety among men</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvete, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orue, Izaskun</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio evaluó la asociación entre esquemas cognitivos (&#147;Cuestionario de esquemas de Young, versión reducida&#148;; Young Schema Questionnaire-Short Form, YSQ-SF; Young y Brown, 1994) y síntomas de ansiedad social (&#147;Cuestionario de interacción social para adultos &#150; revisado&#148;, CISO-AR; Caballo et al., 2006) en una muestra de 639 estudiantes (309 hombres y 327 mujeres). Los resultados fueron: (1) la ansiedad social se asoció fundamentalmente con esquemas relacionados con el  abandono, fracaso e inhibición emocional. (2) Se encontraron peculiaridades según la situación concreta en la que se experimentaba ansiedad social, con el esquema de subyugación asociado a la ansiedad en situaciones de mostrar disgusto y el esquema de imperfección/vergüenza asociado a la relación personas de distinto sexo. (3) Las personas con ansiedad social generalizada puntuaron más alto que quienes presentaban ansiedad social específica en los esquemas de abandono, imperfección, fracaso, dependencia, inhibición emocional y autocontrol insuficiente. (4) Finalmente, aunque las mujeres puntuaron más alto en ansiedad social, no se encontraron diferencias de sexo en la relación entre esquemas y ansiedad social, salvo en el caso de los esquemas de abandono y subyugación, los cuales se asociaron más intensamente a la ansiedad en el caso de los hombres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;16(1): 5-21, ene.-abr. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115369</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad social y esquemas cognitivos disfuncionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
