<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108531</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hemostasis and technology. Energy. Development of new technologies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The hemostasis systems applied in surgery are based on endothermic heat production resulting from the interaction between energy and tissue. The most frequently used energy source is electrocoagulation, applied through two systems: monopolar and bipolar. More sophisticated electrocoagulation systems have progressively been developed such as the Argon beam, in which coagulation is superficial and does not injure the deep tissues, or Liga Sure TM, based on the use of a bipolar system with an inbuilt feedback system allowing vessels to be sealed without excessive heat and a consequent reduction of collateral lesions. Another system that has been developed in the last few years is the ultrasonic scalpel, based on the ability of the cell membrane proteins to denature as a result of ultrasonic vibration. This system avoids some of the risks involved in the use of electrical energy such as accidental burns due to stray electrical current or faulty insulation of an instrument. Moreover, the harmonic scalpel reaches a temperature of no more than 100º and the effect of lateral tissue destruction is much lower than with electrosurgery, although this reduction is negligible when compared with the electrosurgical methods developed in the last few years such as Liga Sure. Another system that is also used is laser energy, consisting of a photon beam containing a specific wavelength; each photon moves in step with the others in both time and space. This system has not become widely used due to its high cost, the difficulty of controlling this type of energy, and the lack of objective advantages over conventional electrosurgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balagué, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los sistemas de hemostasia aplicados en cirugía se basan en la producción de calor endotérmico como resultado de una interacción entre la energía y el tejido. La fuente de energía utilizada con más frecuencia es la electrocoagulación, aplicada a través de dos sistemas: monopolar y bipolar. Progresivamente se han desarrollado sistemas de electrocoagulación más sofisticados, como el «Emisor de Argón», en el cual la coagulación es superficial sin lesionar tejidos más profundos, o el Liga Sure®, basado en la utilización de un sistema bipolar con integración de un sistema de control feedback que permite el sellado de los vasos sin excesivo calor y la consecuente disminución de lesiones colaterales. Otro sistema desarrollado en los últimos años ha sido el bisturí ultrasónico basado en la capacidad de desestructuración de las proteínas de la membrana celular como consecuencia de la vibración ultrasónica. Con este sistema desaparecen algunos de los riesgos de la utilización de energía eléctrica, como son la quemadura accidental por falsos contactos o pérdidas del aislamiento de algún instrumento. Además, la temperatura que se alcanza con el bisturí armónico no supera los 100 ºC y el efecto de destrucción tisular lateral es mucho menor que con la electrocirugía, aunque esta lesión tisular menor no se aprecia cuando se compara con los mecanismos de electrocirugía desarrollados en los últimos años, como es el Liga Sure. Otro sistema de hemostasia utilizado ha sido la energía por láser, un haz de fotones de una determinada longitud de onda que están en fase tanto en tiempo como en espacio. Este sistema no se ha popularizado debido al coste de los dispositivos, a la dificultad en el control de este tipo de energía y porque no ofrece ventajas objetivas sobre la electrocirugía convencional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);85(supl.1): 15-22, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108531</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemostasia y tecnología. Energía. Desarrollo de las nuevas tecnologías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6508^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6642^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4636^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
