<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146444</identifier>
<setSpec>0377-4732</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study and rating of changes in the new scale relating to the traumatic aftermath in four limbs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The orthopaedic sequelae affecting any of the members of the sections are of more prevalence and interest in the valuation of bodily harm. They are usually present in any multisystem trauma patients as well in any kind of aggression in both the aggressor and the aggrieved. These aftereffects result from any damage or injury either osteo-articular soft tissue either of the aforementioned members. Whatever the damaged structure the result will be a deficit or limitation in mobility in this segment with the consequent loss of function. When we use the word &#145;deficit&#146; we are referring to any type of residual state (amputation, joint limitation, stiffness, deviation, pains, etc.) altering and impairing the functionality of that member. The purpose of this scale is none other than to serve the coroner to frame and weigh any sequel with the sole purpose of &#145;trying&#146; to financially compensate the injured. This scale object of this study has been able to improve the above in certain respects. It has been rearranged and has added different effects that did not exist in the previous one, and improved their score in both the average value and the limits of each range to avoid any overlaps. However, there is no uniformity in the joint sequels, the burden of some of them is not adequately assessed and there are gaps in relation to certain deficits and deformities that are not included in this new scale (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Cervigón, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las secuelas traumatológicas que afectan a cualquiera de los miembros constituyen uno de los apartados de más prevalencia e interés en la valoración del daño corporal. Suelen estar presentes en cualquier politraumatizado así como en cualquier tipo de agresión, tanto del agresor como del agredido. Estas secuelas tienen como origen cualquier daño o lesión, bien osteoarticular, bien de las partes blandas de los referidos miembros. Sea cual fuere la estructura dañada, el resultado va a ser un déficit o limitación en la movilidad de dicho segmento con la consiguiente pérdida funcional. Cuando usamos la palabra «déficit» nos estamos refiriendo a cualquier tipo de estado residual (amputación, limitación articular, rigidez, desviación, algias, etc.) que altere y menoscabe la funcionalidad de dicho miembro. El objeto del presente baremo no es otro que el de servir al perito médico para encuadrar y ponderar la secuela con la única finalidad de «tratar» de resarcir económicamente al lesionado. El baremo objeto del presente estudio ha mejorado el anterior en determinados aspectos. Ha reordenado y añadido distintas secuelas que en el anterior no existían y ha mejorado la puntuación de las mismas tanto en el valor promedio como en los límites de cada rango para evitar coincidencias con los adyacentes. No obstante, no existe uniformidad en las secuelas articulares, la ponderación de alguna de ellas no es la adecuada y existen lagunas en relación con determinados déficits y deformidades que no vienen recogidas en este nuevo baremo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. legal;41(4): 173-178, oct.-dic. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146444</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio y valoración de los cambios introducidos en el nuevo baremo relativos a las secuelas traumatológicas en los cuatro miembros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8840^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8048^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22748^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5519^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22748^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8048^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22748^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36039^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
