<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121717</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic adherence in kidney transplant patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In patients with chronic kidney disease who have a kidney transplant, adherence to treatment is crucial to prevent rejection, graft loss and additional morbility. Objective: to know current scientific production on adherence to treatment by kidney transplant patients and the variables that can affect it. Method: A search was conducted in the databases of Scielo, PubMed, The Chocrane, Science Direct and Google Scholar. Scientific articles written in English and Spanish were included. Articles that dealt with adherence to immunosuppressive treatment by kidney transplant patients were analysed, excluding paediatric patients. Results: Adherence to immunosuppressive treatment by these patients is relatively low due to the influence of several factors. The complexity of the treatment and time after the transplant have an important negative correlation to adherence. Forgetfulness or other occupations are related significantly to unintentional non-adherence by patients. The age groups with the lowest adherence are the youngest followed by the most elderly, while the most adherent are adults. In some countries, the lack of adherence is due to the fact that the high cost of the immunosuppressive treatment has to be paid by the patient. On the other hand, variables that do not appear to have a conclusive influence are: marital status or lifestyle, side effects, socio-economic and educational level, job situation, race, beliefs about their necessity and psychological factors. Finally, the variable of gender is clearly the only one that does not affect lack of adherence, as most studies show that gender does not influence adherence compared to only two that consider that men are less adherent. Conclusions: kidney transplant patients present higher percentages of lack of adherence to treatment, fundamentally related to the complexity of the treatment, the time since the transplant, forgetfulness, or other occupations and age (young and elderly) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Calzado, María Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica portadores de un trasplante renal, la adherencia al tratamiento es crucial para prevenir el rechazo, pérdida del injerto, y la morbilidad adicional. Objetivo: conocer la producción científica actual de la adherencia al tratamiento de pacientes trasplantados de riñón y las variables que pueden influir. Método: Se realizó una búsqueda en las bases de datos de Scielo, PubMed, The Chocrane, Science Direct y Google académico. Se incluyeron artículos científicos escritos en inglés y español. Se analizaron los artículos que trataban la adherencia al tratamiento inmunosupresor de pacientes trasplantados de riñón, excluyendo los pacientes pediátricos. Resultados: La adherencia al tratamiento inmunosupresor por parte de estos pacientes es relativamente baja debido a la influencia de varios factores. La complejidad del tratamiento y el tiempo postrasplante, tienen una importante correlación negativa con la adherencia. El olvido u otras ocupaciones, se relaciona de forma significativa con la no adherencia no intencional por parte de los pacientes. Los grupos de edad con menos adherencia son los más jóvenes seguidos de los más mayores, y los más adherentes los adultos. En algunos países, la falta de adherencia se debe a que el elevado coste del tratamiento inmunosupresor corre por cuente del paciente. Por otro lado, las variables que no parecen influir de forma concluyente, son: el estado civil o modo de vida, efectos secundarios, nivel socioeconómico y educativo, situación laboral, raza, creencias en la necesidad y factores psicológicos. Por último, la variable de género es claramente la única que no influye sobre la falta de adherencia, ya que una mayoría de estudios demuestran que no influyen frente a solo dos que consideran que los varones son los menos adherentes. Conclusiones: los pacientes trasplantados de riñón presentan altos porcentajes de falta de adherencia al tratamiento, estando relacionados fundamentalmente la complejidad del tratamiento, el tiempo postrasplante, el olvido u otras ocupaciones y la edad (jóvenes y mayores) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;16(4): 258-270, oct.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121717</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La adherencia terapéutica en el paciente trasplantado renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6235^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6235^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
