<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138370</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of advanced nursing practice on staff development and evidence-based practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. At international level, there is abundant evidence of the positive impact that the Advanced Practice Nurse (APN) has on patients, health care organizations and nursing professionals. At national level, such evidence is incipient and should be developed in order to justify investments in the introduction of APN roles. The present study provides evidence on the impact of the APN in the professional development of nurses in one outpatient clinic of a hospital in Northern Spain. Material and methods. The advanced practice nursing student (APNS) developed a change project aimed at improving knowledge of evidence based practice (EBP) among nurses in the cited outpatient clinic. To that end, the APNS followed the steps of the PEPPA (participatory, evidence-based, patient-focused process, for guiding the development, implementation, and evaluation of advanced practice nursing) framework and conducted unstructured observations, literature reviews, personal interviews and group discussions with 8 patients, 2 nurses and 4 cardiologists. The evaluation of the change project included personal interviews with nurses in the outpatient clinic before and after the intervention. Results. Nurses notably increased their knowledge on formulating clinical questions, developing and executing bibliographic searches, synthesizing and criticizing evidence, and applying and evaluating research results. Discussion and conclusions. The results suggest that the positive impact of the integration of APNs into the Spanish clinical setting is not restricted to just patients and the hospital setting, but extends to the professional development of nurses and the outpatient clinic setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ara Lucea, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón-Ricart Cenizo, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pumar-Méndez, M Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo Guinea, Talia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. A nivel internacional existe abundante evidencia del impacto positivo que la enfermera de práctica avanzada (EPA) tiene en pacientes, organizaciones sanitarias y profesionales de enfermería. A nivel nacional esta evidencia es incipiente y debe incrementarse para justificar la inversión en la introducción de perfiles de EPA. El presente estudio aporta evidencia sobre el impacto de la EPA en el desarrollo profesional de las enfermeras de una consulta externa de un hospital del norte de España. Material y métodos. La estudiante de práctica avanzada (EEPA) desarrolló un proyecto de cambio dirigido a mejorar los conocimientos sobre práctica basada en la evidencia de las enfermeras de dicha consulta. Para ello, la EEPA siguió los pasos del marco Proceso Participativo para la Enfermería de Práctica Avanzada centrado en el Paciente y basado en la Evidencia (PEPPA) y realizó observaciones desestructuradas, revisiones bibliográficas, entrevistas personales y discusiones grupales con 8 pacientes, 2 enfermeras y 4 cardiólogos. La evaluación del proyecto de cambio incluyó entrevistas personales con las enfermeras de la consulta previa y posteriormente a la intervención. Resultados. Las enfermeras incrementaron notablemente sus conocimientos sobre formulación de preguntas clínicas, diseño y ejecución de búsquedas bibliográficas, síntesis y crítica de la evidencia y aplicación y evaluación de resultados de investigación. Discusión y conclusiones. Los resultados sugieren que el impacto positivo de la incorporación de EPA al ámbito clínico español no se restringe tan solo a los pacientes, ni al ámbito hospitalario, sino que es extensible al desarrollo profesional del personal de enfermería y al ámbito de Consultas Externas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(7/8): 512-517, jul.-ago. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138370</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la práctica avanzada en enfermería en el desarrollo del personal y la práctica basada en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55050^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55050^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29599^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29599^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29599^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
