<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134321</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of Alpha lipoic acid on cadmium induced oxidative damage on heart, Brain, kidney, liver and lung of rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study investigated the protective effect of alpha lipoic acid (ALA) on cadmium induced oxidative damage in rats. Cadmium (100ppm) fed to normal rats resulted in significant increase in the level of serum glutamate oxaloacetate transaminase (SGOT), serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) and Alkaline Phosphatase (ALP). Animals exposed to cadmium also showed a significant increase in level of lipid peroxidation (LPO) and decreased levels of reduced glutathione (GSH), superoxide dismutase (SOD) , catalase (CAT) and membrane bound ATPases (Na+K+ATPase,Ca2+ATPase and Mg2+ATPase) in brain, lung, kidney, liver and heart as compared to control group. Co administration of ALA (25mg/kg/day, i.p.) along with cadmium for thirty days significantly decreased the levels of SGOT, SGPT and Alkaline Phosphatase in the serum to near normal levels. ALA also reduced the level of MDA and increased the levels of SOD, CAT, GSH and membrane bound ATPases in all the organs of the animals treated with cadmium to near normal levels. This study demonstrates the free radical damage caused by administration of cadmium on different organs and the antioxidant effect of ALA which protects the organs from this damage when it is given along with cadmium (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prabhu, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Upaganlawar, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balaraman, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente estudio se investigó el efecto protector del ácido alfa lipoico (ALA) sobre el daño oxidativo inducido por el cadmio en ratas. El cadmio (100 ppm) suministrado a ratas normales dio lugar a un aumento significativo de los niveles de transaminasa glutámico-oxalacética sérica (SGOT), transaminasa glutámico-pirúvica sérica (SGPT) y fosfatasa alcalina (ALP). En los animales expuestos al cadmio se observó igualmente un aumento significativo del nivel de peroxidación lipídica (LPO) y una disminución de los niveles de glutatión reducido (GSH), superóxido dismutasa (SOD), catalasa (CAT) y ATPasas de la membrana (Na+K+-ATPasa, Ca2+-ATPasa y Mg2+-ATPasa) en cerebro, pulmón, riñón, hígado y corazón en comparación con el grupo de control. La administración conjunta de ALA (25mg/kg/día, i.p.) y cadmio durante treinta días dio lugar a una disminución significativa de los niveles de SGOT, SGPT y fosfatasa alcalina en suero hasta niveles cercanos a los normales. El uso de ALA también supuso una reducción del nivel de MDA y un aumento de los niveles de SOD, CAT, GSH y ATPasas unidas a la membrana en todos los órganos de los animales tratados con cadmio hasta niveles cercanos a los normales. El presente estudio demuestra el daño inducido por radicales libres derivados de la administración de cadmio sobre distintos órganos y el efecto antioxidante del ALA que protege a los órganos frente a este daño cuando se administra conjuntamente con cadmio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;49(4): 293-307, oct.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134321</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del ácido alfa lipoico sobre el daño oxidativo inducido por cadmio en corazón, cerebro, riñón, hígado y pulmón de ratas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23743^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2138^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33519^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29256^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
