<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137421</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Women receiving preconception care in Granada</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the percentage of women who receive preconception care, which information they have about it, the number of  components and the professional providing care. Subjects and method: Cross sectional study with a convenient  sample of puerperal hospitalised  women at the University Hospital «San Cecilio» in Granada. Results:  Among 109 women studied,  37.6% (41) performed some element of the preconception care consultation. No differences between first gestation and multigestation women were found. One hundred and one women (92.66%) had not received previous information about preconception care. Conclusions: One third of women wanting a pregnancy visit a health professional to prepare them for gestation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dios Berlanga, S de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bru Martín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Galiano, J M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Determinar el porcentaje de mujeres que reciben asistencia preconcepcional, la información que tienen de ella, el número de componentes y el profesional que la realiza. Personas y método: Estudio transversal con una muestra de conveniencia de puérperas ingresadas en el Hospital Universitario «San Cecilio» de Granada. Resultados: Se estudiaron 109 mujeres, de las que 41 (37,6%) realizaron algún componente de la consulta preconcepcional. No se observaron diferencias entre las primigestas y multigestas. No habían tenido información previa de la asistencia preconcepcional 101 mujeres (92,66%). Conclusiones: Una tercera parte de las mujeres con deseo de embarazo acude a un profesional sanitario para prepararse para la gestación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;9(1): 11-14, ene.-mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137421</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mujeres que reciben asistencia preconcepcional en Granada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29875</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29154</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
