<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168566</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Refeeding syndrome in children: symptoms, diagnosis, prevention and management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Refeeding syndrome (RFS) is a term that describes the metabolic and clinical changes that occur on aggressive nutritional rehabilitation of a malnourished patient. A shift from carbohydrate metabolism to fat and protein catabolism occurs. Hypophosphatemia is the hallmark of RFS. Other electrolyte abnormalities are associated with RFS, however, such as hypokalemia and hypomagnesemia. RFS is associated to any nutritional support (more frequently to parenteral nutrition) in malnourished patients'. A proper nutritional support is required to avoid RFS, checking daily liquid balance, electrolytes and vital signs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Ruzafa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moráis López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero de la Rosa, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros Arnal, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de realimentación es un proceso fisiopatológico asociado a trastornos de la glucosa y desequilibrio hidroelectrolítico que involucran principalmente a los iones intracelulares (fosfato, potasio y magnesio). Este síndrome se asocia con el soporte nutricional (oral, enteral o parenteral) en pacientes con riesgo de desnutrición o con desnutrición severa. Es muy importante valorar la presencia de factores de riesgo, estudiar los iones séricos e iniciar la alimentación de manera progresiva. El apoyo nutricional correcto es fundamental, con la supervisión diaria de los electrólitos séricos, los signos vitales y el equilibrio de líquidos, así como un correcto diseño del soporte nutricional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;75(9/10): e159-e163, sept.-oct. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168566</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de realimentación en pediatría: clínica, diagnóstico, prevención y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15272^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53105^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4645^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53105^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29390^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
