<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-1429</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survival in epidermoid carcinoma oral cavity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study aims to analyse the survival of 94 patients with squamous cell carcinoma of the oral cavity. They were 86 men and 8 women with a mean age of 61. Seventy four percent were smokers and 70% consumed alcohol regularly. Eighty three percent had unhealthy teeth. A great majority of patients (76) were in the advanced stages (III-IV) and 61% showed neck nodules. The overall survival at 5 years was the following: 70% for patients in stage I, 85% in stage II, 58% stage III and only 17% for the patients in stage IV. The most significant prognostic factor that affected the survival was the N stage. For the patients in N0 and N1 we only found significant differences when the lymph nodes were histologically affected by the tumor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un estudio sobre 94 casos de carcinoma epidermoide de cavidad oral. La muestra consta de 86 varones, con una edad media de 61 años, siendo fumadores el 74 por ciento y bebedores regulares de alcohol el 70 por ciento. El 83 por ciento presentaba un estado buco-dental malo. La mayoría de los casos eran estadios avanzados III-IV (76 por ciento), con un 61 por ciento de adenopatías clínicamente significativas. La supervivencia a 5 años en estadio I fue del 70 por ciento, estadio II 85 por ciento, estadio III 58 por ciento y estadio IV 17 por ciento. Encontramos que la clasificación que tiene mayor valor pronóstico es la evaluación del estado ganglionar, pero en el caso de N0 y N1 la evaluación clínica es insuficiente, siendo necesario el estudio histológico tras la realización del vaciamiento ganglionar oportuno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;52(5): 381-386, jun. 2001. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Supervivencia en el carcinoma epidermoide de cavidad oral</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Herrera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Pérez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santa Cruz Ruiz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Palacios, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez González, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-1429</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22570^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
