<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146438</identifier>
<setSpec>0377-4732</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ocular sequelae in the new traffic scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We have been making constructive criticism about traffic scale failures for more than ten years. These deficiencies are going to be solved in the new scale. It eliminates some scientific errors, definitely clarifies that visual acuity exploration must be the corrected visual acuity for far vision, and introduces typical posttraumatic aftereffects previously unconsidered. Also, the new scale simplifies the evaluation of the traumatic diplopia, visual field defect and aftermath of the eyelid. In addition, it introduces new posterior pole sequelae and rightly eliminates the table B. Therefore, we consider all these changes very appropriate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Menéndez de Lucas, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hace más de 10 años que criticamos constructivamente las deficiencias del baremo de tráfico. En el nuevo baremo se subsanan estas deficiencias: elimina algunos errores científicos, aclara definitivamente que la exploración de la agudeza visual debe hacerse con corrección y para visión de lejos, introduce secuelas típicamente postraumáticas que no estaban, simplifica mucho la valoración de la diplopia postraumática, de los defectos campimétricos y de las secuelas palpebrales. Además, introduce lesiones postraumáticas del polo posterior y elimina muy acertadamente la tabla B. Consideramos, por lo tanto, muy favorables todas estas modificaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. legal;41(4): 149-152, oct.-dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las secuelas oculares en el nuevo baremo de tráfico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4229^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28111^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7666^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3252^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4229^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
