<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92385</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cyclooxigenase-2 Levels are Increased in the Lung Tissue and Bronchial Tumors of Patients with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IntroductionThe expression of cyclooxygenase 2 (COX-2) is usually increased in inflammation and cancer. This study examines the expression of COX-2 in the lung of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients with lung cancer.MethodsWe studied 44 male patients with bronchial cancer (27 squamous carcinoma and 17 adenocarcinoma). Samples were obtained from the pulmonary parenchyma, from the bronchial mucosa adjacent to the tumor and from the tumor itself. Lung tissue specimens from 14 patients with pneumothorax were used as control. The mRNA and the COX-1 and COX-2 proteins were assessed by RT-PCR and Western blot, respectively.ResultsCOX-1 and COX-2 mRNA levels were significantly higher in the lung parenchyma of COPD patients than in the control subjects. COX-2 mRNA levels were also higher in the lung parenchyma than in both tumor and airway tissue samples procured from COPD patients. There were no differences in the COX-2 mRNA levels between squamous carcinoma and adenocarcinoma. In contrast, COX-2 protein levels were significantly higher in tumors than in lung parenchyma and airways. COX-2 protein levels were higher in adenocarcinoma compared with squamous carcinoma.ConclusionThis study shows that in COPD, the pathway of cyclooxygenase is activated and associated with an increase in the expression of COX-2 in lung tumors. These observations suggest that COX-2 is possibly involved in the association between COPD and cancer(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agusti, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picado, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujols, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca-Ferrer, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xaubet, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimferrer, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mullol, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónLa ciclooxigenasa 2 (COX-2) está aumentada en la inflamación y en el cáncer. En este estudio se evaluó la expresión de la COX-2 en el pulmón y en el cáncer bronquial de pacientes con EPOC.MétodosSe estudiaron 44 pacientes varones con cáncer bronquial (27 escamosos y 17 adenocarcinomas). Se obtuvieron muestras del parénquima pulmonar, de la mucosa bronquial adyacente al tumor y del tumor mismo. El tejido pulmonar de 14 pacientes con neumotórax se empleó como control. El ARNm y la proteína de la COX-1 y de la COX-2 se midieron mediante RT-PCR y western blot, respectivamente.ResultadosLos niveles de ARNm de la COX-1 y de la COX -2 en el parénquima de los pacientes con EPOC fueron superiores a los de los controles. Los niveles del ARNm de la COX-2 en pacientes con EPOC fueron más altos en el parénquima pulmonar que en las vías aéreas y los tumores. No hubo diferencias en los niveles del ARNm de la COX-2 entre escamosos y adenocarcinomas. En contraste, la proteína de COX-2 mostró niveles más altos en los tumores que en el parénquima y las vías aéreas. Los niveles de la proteína de COX-2 fueron más altos en los adenocarcinomas que en los carcinomas escamosos.ConclusiónEste estudio muestra que en la EPOC la vía de la ciclooxigenasa está activada y asociada a un aumento en la expresión de la COX-2 en los tumores. Cabe la posibilidad de que la COX-2 esté involucrada en la asociación de EPOC y cáncer(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(12): 584-589, dic. 2011. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92385</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La ciclooxigenasa-2 está regulada al alza en el pulmón y en los tumores bronquiales de pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50591^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
