<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165970</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical trials in cardiovascular regenerative medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Previous clinical trials of stem cell therapy have demonstrated that the technique can promote the recovery of heart muscle after the acute phase of myocardial infarction and can improve cardiac function in chronic ischemic heart disease. However, some studies have produced conflicting results, and there are still questions about underlying mechanisms of action and about the best treatment strategy for optimizing cardiac repair. This article contains a review of recent findings in translational cardiovascular research and of the results and limitations of phase-I and -II clinical trials, discusses key issues in the design of future trials, and summarizes new areas for investigation in this fascinating field (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Ruiz, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa Arranz, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez García, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Santos, María Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Ibañes, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Avilés, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Fernández, Pedro L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los primeros ensayos clínicos han demostrado que la terapia celular puede mejorar el proceso de recuperación cardiaca tras la fase aguda del infarto de miocardio y la función cardiaca en la cardiopatía isquémica crónica. Sin embargo, algunos estudios han mostrado resultados contradictorios y aún existen dudas acerca de los mecanismos de acción y sobre la estrategia de tratamiento ideal para conseguir una mayor reparación cardiaca. En este capítulo se revisa la evidencia disponible actualmente, se analizan los ensayos clínicos de fases I y II y sus limitaciones, se discuten los puntos clave para el diseño de futuros estudios y se anticipa el futuro de los nuevos campos de investigación en este fascinante campo de la investigación cardiovascular traslacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);13(supl.E): 81e-91e, 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados clínicos de las técnicas regenerativas en medicina cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38363^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
