<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117872</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The patients with advanced cancer express feelings of hopelessness, wish to advance the death, and high levels of anxiety and depression associated to the loss of sense of life. Aims: The main aim of the Meaning-Centered Group Psychotherapy is to help to the patients with cancer to live with sense, of a full way, keeping and expanding the sense of his life, living in peace and with an aim in the life. Participants and Method: At present, we are conducting the pilot study, as first step of the project of validation of the Meaning-Centered Group Psychotherapy Model. We have performance two of the three groups of patients with advanced cancer that corresponds to the present pilot study, and are doing the transcription of each one of the sessions of the groups, for his back qualitative analysis. Results: The Meaning-Centered Group Psychotherapy show a reduction of anxiety and depression, hopelessness and wish to advance the death in patients with advanced cancer, at the same time to increase the spiritual welfare and the feeling of sense (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Moncayo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Breitbart, William</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los pacientes con cáncer avanzado expresan sentimientos de desesperanza, deseo de adelantar la muerte, y niveles elevados de ansiedad y sintomatología depresiva asociada a la pérdida de sentido de vida. Objetivos: El principal objetivo de la Psicoterapia de Grupo Centrada en el Sentido (PGCS) es ayudar a los pacientes con cáncer a vivir con sentido, de una manera plena, manteniendo y ampliando el sentido de su vida, viviendo en paz y con un objetivo en la vida. Participantes y Método: Actualmente, estamos realizando el estudio piloto, como primer paso del proyecto de validación del Modelo de Psicoterapia Centrada en el Sentido. Hemos realizado dos de los tres grupos de pacientes con cáncer avanzado que corresponde al presente estudio piloto, y estamos realizando las trascripción de cada una de la sesiones de los grupos, para su posterior análisis cualitativo. Resultados: Los grupos de psicoterapia centrada en el sentido muestran una reducción de la sintomatología ansiosa y depresiva, desesperanza y deseo de adelantar la muerte en pacientes con cáncer avanzado, a la vez de aumentar el bienestar espiritual y la sensación de sentido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);10(2/3): 233-245, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicoterapia centrada en el sentido: "Vivir con Sentido". Estudio Piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54741</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
