<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111135</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The psychiatric interview to children and adolescents (II): Psycho-affective and cognitive development of the child</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The primary care pediatrician must know the basics of psycho-affective and cognitive development of the child, in order to perform a scan of his mental health or to provide appropriate intervention. This article addresses the most basic aspects of emotional and cognitive development of the child. To understand their development, we must take into account the interdependence between the affective, cognitive and motor development, and considering the human being comprehensively, as a bio-psychosocial unit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escribano Ceruelo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Soto, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duelo Marcos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pediatra de Atención Primaria tiene que conocer los aspectos básicos del desarrollo psicoafectivo y cognitivo del niño, tanto para realizar una exploración de su salud mental como para proporcionar una intervención adecuada. En este artículo se abordan los aspectos más básicos del desarrollo emocional y cognitivo del niño. Para entender su desarrollo, hay que tener en cuenta la interdependencia entre el desarrollo afectivo, cognitivo y motor, y considerar al ser humano de forma integral, como una unidad biopsicosocial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;15(57): 89e41-89e55, ene.-mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111135</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La entrevista en salud mental infantojuvenil (II): el desarrollo psicoafectivo y cognitivo del niño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29823^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29823^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33145^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33145^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29823^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
