<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056025</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is the use of statins justified in all diabetic patients?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Today, diabetes mellitus is considered to be one of the most important    public health problems around the world. The correlation between    hyperglycemia and cardiovascular events has been well established.    Among the risk factors for these events, dyslipidemia and    platelet hyperactivity are of special importance because both are associated    with diabetes. The objective of the present review is to provide    an update on these risk factors. In addition to the well-known    effect of statins on plasma lipid levels, they have also been reported    to exert a certain action on platelet activation. For this reason, we    considered the question as to whether it would be of interest to administer    statins even to diabetic patients with minimum dyslipidemia.    The literature reviewed demonstrates the lack of agreement among    the different authors in relation to which statin should be administered    and at what dose, for how long and to what type of patients in    order to achieve better protection against thrombotic events, which    occur more frequently in diabetic patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mosquera, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiroga, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente se considera la diabetes mellitus como uno de los más    importantes problemas sociosanitarios en todo el mundo. Está bien    establecida la correlación entre la hiperglucemia y los episodios cardiovasculares.    Entre los factores de riesgo de tales episodios, cabe    destacar la dislipemia y la hiperactivación plaquetaria, ambos asociados    a la diabetes, cuyo conocimiento intenta poner al día la presente    revisión. Dado que se ha descrito que las estatinas, además    de su conocido efecto sobre los lípidos plasmáticos, también ejercen    una cierta acción sobre la activación plaquetaria, puede plantearse    la pregunta de si resultaría efectiva su administración, incluso a los    pacientes diabéticos con una mínima dislipemia. La bibliografía revisada    pone de manifiesto la falta de acuerdo entre los diversos autores    respecto a qué estatinas, en qué dosis, durante cuánto tiempo y    a qué tipo de pacientes deben administrarse para alcanzar una mejor    protección contra los episodios trombóticos más frecuentes en la    diabetes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;23(3): 215-220, mayo-jun. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056025</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Está justificado el uso de estatinas en todo paciente con diabetes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24837^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24837^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
