<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63843</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Restless legs syndrome is a prevalent neurological disorder that is common in the elderly. It is manifested as unpleasant sensations in the lower limbs and in the need to move the legs when the patient is at rest. It has circadian rhythm and idiopathic etiology. Its pathogeny could be due to iron, ferritin and dopamine deficit. Its diagnosis is clinical and there is currently a wide range of therapeutic options, among them, dopaminergic drugs, benzodiazepines, antiepileptics, opioids and non-pharmacological measures. As this is a complex syndrome that is insufficiently diagnosed, the help of the medical practitioner to be able to identify it is essential</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de piernas inquietas es un trastorno neurológico prevalente, frecuente en ancianos, que se manifiesta como sensaciones desagradables en miembros inferiores y la necesidad de mover las piernas cuando el paciente está en reposo. Tiene ritmo circadiano. De etiología idiopática. La patogenia podría deberse a un déficit de hierro o ferritina y dopamina. Su diagnóstico es clínico y actualmente hay un abanico amplio de opciones terapéuticas, entre otros los fármacos dopaminérgicos, las benzodiazepinas, antiepilépticos, opioides y medidas no farmacológicas. Al ser un síndrome complejo e insuficientemente diagnosticado resulta imprescindible ayudar al médico de familia a poder identificarlo</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(2): 80-86, feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63843</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12568^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9489^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12568^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
