<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149752</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tales effect in real and perceived aquatic competence in preschoolers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Even though a growing interest exists in the study of the renewal of the traditional &#145;play&#146; curriculum, as well as the utilization of the aquatic medium as an educational resource, at present, very few studies link both areas. For this reason, the objective of this quasi-experimental study was to confirm the effect of aquatic motor tales over perceived motor competency and real motor capacity. We studied 16 preschoolers among 3 to 5 years of age for their real and perceived aquatic motor competency. After a non-parametric test was administered, the results show that administration of aquatic mobility stories contributed positively and significantly on the perceived motor competence of the experimental group. The results are discussed in favor of inclusion of aquatic educational programs in order to promote the self-esteem of this age-group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Huéscar Hernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Murcia, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meseguer, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Pese a existir un interés creciente en los estudios por la renovación de los contenidos lúdicos tradicionales, así como en la utilización del medio acuático como recurso educativo, en la actualidad existen muy pocas investigaciones que relacionen ambos aspectos. Por ello, el objetivo de este estudio cuasi-experimental fue comprobar el efecto de los cuentos motores acuáticos sobre la competencia motriz percibida y la capacidad motriz real. Los participantes fueron 16 infantes de 3 a 5 años a los que se le midió la competencia motriz real y percibida acuática. Tras una prueba no paramétrica los resultados mostraron que la administración del programa de cuentos motores contribuyó de manera positiva y significativa sobre la competencia motriz percibida del grupo experimental. Se discuten los resultados en pro de incluir en los programas educativos acuáticos los cuentos motores de cara a fomentar el autoconcepto infantil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;16(61): 127-138, mar. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149752</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de los cuentos en la competencia acuática real y percibida en infantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11416</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37586</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
