<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137993</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the ICE Model to assess social class in the adult population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Social class has commonly been defined by the type of employment and it is assessed as a categorical variable. However, this approach has a number of drawbacks. The objective of this article is to develop and validate a readily standardizable quantitative indicator of social class and to show its ability to measure the impact of social class as a health determinant. Methods: In 6729 individuals we measured income, crowding index, education, occupation and employment status. Two models were adjusted to study the neighborhood, dietary pattern and health problems. Results: The model that included only income, crowding index and education (ICE) yielded an indicator that correlated with age (r = &#150;0.28; p &lt; 0.001) and consumption of potatoes (r = &#150;0.17; p &lt; 0.001) and salads (r = 0.10; p &lt; 0.001). This indicator estimated that poor social classes were at significant risk for unemployment (OR=5,), blue collar jobs (OR=40,9), residing in poor neighborhoods (OR = 30.2), low salad consumption (OR = 2.2) and high consumption of potatoes (OR = 4.5). They also had, especially in women, a higher risk of sedentarism (OR = 1.8), obesity (OR = 4.4), metabolic syndrome (OR = 3.4) and diabetes mellitus (OR = 2.0). Conclusions: The ICE index was valid, not based on occupation or employment status, readily standardizable, and suitable for measuring social class and its impact of on health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Álvarez, Cristobalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Coello, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Jaime, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera de León, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, María C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Díaz, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La clase social generalmente se mide de manera categórica y basada en la ocupación laboral, lo cual tiene múltiples limitaciones. El objetivo de este trabajo es elaborar un indicador cuantitativo de clase social, fácilmente estandarizable, validarlo en población adulta y comprobar su aptitud para medir el impacto de la clase social como determinante de salud. Métodos: estudio transversal de 6.729 individuos para medir la clase social con las variables: Renta familiar per cápita, Índice de hacinamiento, Estudios realizados, Ocupación laboral y Situación laboral. Se crearon dos modelos y mediante curvas COR se seleccionó el mejor para validarlo analizando su capacidad de estimar los riesgos relativos de: residir en barrio pobre o rico, mantener un patrón dietético típico de clases sociales pobres y presentar problemas de salud actualmente asociados a la pobreza. Resultados: el modelo sólo incluyó las variables Renta, Estudios e Índice de hacinamiento (REI), produjo un indicador con rango de valores entre 4 y 21 y mostró correlación inversa con la edad (r= -0,28; p&lt;0,001), con el consumo de papas (r= -0,17; p&lt;0,001) y con el consumo de legumbres (r= -0,03; p=0,01), además de correlación directa con el consumo de ensalada (r = 0,10; p&lt;0,001); su sensibilidad para detectar la residencia en barrio pobre alcanzó el 97% para valores menores a 10. REI estimó que las clases sociales pobres presentan riesgos significativos de situación laboral de desempleo (OR=5,4), ocupación laboral de baja cualificación (OR=40,9), habitar en barrios pobres (OR =30,2), bajo consumo de ensaladas (OR = 2,2), gran consumo de papas (OR = 4,5) y alto consumo de legumbres (OR = 1,6). En ambos sexos las clases pobres presentaron mayor riesgo de problemas de salud, con mayor fuerza en las mujeres: sedentarismo (OR = 1,8), obesidad (OR = 4,4), obesidad abdominal (OR = 5,4), síndrome metabólico (OR = 3,4) y diabetes mellitus (OR = 2,0). Conclusiones: REI es un indicador válido, no basado en la ocupación ni en la situación laboral, fácilmente estandarizable, apto para medir cuantitativamente la clase social en estudios que precisen analizar el impacto de la misma como determinante de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;83(2): 231-242, mar.-abr. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137993</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación del modelo REI para medir la clase social en población adulta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9975</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24446</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7360</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
