<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-10399</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary intraoral epithelioid hemangioendothelioma case. Report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Epithelioid Hemangioendothelioma (EH) is a vascular neoplasm of soft tissue, recently described by Weiss and Enzinger. The biologic al behavior of the tumor has a intermediate malignant potential, in the sense that it has an indolent course, with the potential for recurrence, but rarely metastasizes. This tumor arises from medium- to large-sized vessels, primarily involves the soft tissues of the extremities, as well as the liver, lung, and bone, and rarely occurs in the head and neck region. Only fifteen well--documented cases of Epithelioid Hemangioendothelioma involving the head and neck region have been reported. Nine cases have been recently reported in the oral cavity. This is a report of one additional case in the tongue. Because of the intermediate malignant potential of Epithelioid Hemangioendothelioma, complete tumor resection is recommended for intraoral lesions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Hemangioendotelioma Epitelioide (HE) es una neoplasia vascular de tejidos blandos, descrita recientemente por Weiss y Enzinger. Su potencial maligno es intermedio, en el sentido de tener un curso indolente, posible recurrencia y raras metástasis. Se presenta a lo largo de los vasos, principalmente involucra los tejidos blandos de las extremidades, además de hígado, pulmón y hueso, siendo infrecuente en cabeza y cuello. Sólo se han descrito quince casos en cabeza y cuello. De éstos, recientemente se han descrito nueve casos en cavidad oral. Aportamos un caso adicional en lengua.Debido al moderado potencial maligno del hemangioendotelioma epitelioide se recomienda la resección completa de las lesiones intraorales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;53(3): 215-218, mar. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemangioendotelioma epitelioide primario intraoral. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Cervantes Góngora, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Tortosa, CL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de la Torre, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde Pérez de la Blanca, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Palma, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-10399</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d813^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22700^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
