<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113212</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Elective primary total hip arthroplasty in octogenarians. A case-control study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the results and efficacy of cementless total hip arthroplasty (THA) in octogenarians with osteoarthritis. Material and methods. Matched case-control study with ratio 1:2. Consecutive selection of 54 octogenarians (55 hips), and 106 control patients (110 hips) with age ranging from 70 to 79 years. Mean follow-up of 7 years (range: 5-12). Before 5 postoperative years, 1 and 4 patients, respectively, died and they were excluded. Clinical assessment was performed using ASA grade, comorbidities, and Harris and Merle D&#146;Aubigné hip scores, and radiographic, complications, and mortality evaluations were made. Results. There were no perioperative deaths in either cohort. The rates of postoperative medical complications (P=.601) and survival (P=.360) were similar. The survival at 7 years was 89.8% in octogenarian and 95.3% in controls, with no influence of the preoperative variables. There were no differences in postoperative functional outcomes (P=.761), but improvement respect to the preoperative was higher in octogenarian (P=.002). In octogenarians there were 2 intraoperative fractures, 2 dislocations and 2 unstable stems, and in control patients 1 deep infection, 1 peri-prosthetic femoral fracture, 2 unstable cups and 4 unstable stems. The rates of aseptic complications, the need for revision, and arthroplasty survival (94% at 7 years) were similar in both cohorts. Discussion. Due to improvement in health status, the octogenarian may have a life expectancy of at least 10 years. The cost arguments and an arbitrary age should not influence the selection of candidates for cementless THA. Conclusions. Cementless THA has been shown to be safe and effective in octogenarian patients with osteoarthritis. The notable increase found in functional outcomes justifies the continued use in these patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Reig, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizaur-Utrilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar los resultados y eficacia de la artroplastia total de cadera (ATC) no cementada en octogenarios con coxartrosis. Material y métodos. Estudio de caso-control con emparejamiento 1:2. Selección consecutiva de 54 octogenarios (55 caderas) y 106 controles (110 caderas) con edad: 70-79 años. Seguimiento medio de 7 años (rango: 5-12). Antes de 5 años de seguimiento murieron uno y 4 pacientes respectivamente, siendo excluidos. Se realizó la valoración clínica mediante ASA, comorbilidades, escalas de Harris y Merle D&#146;Aubigné, y valoración radiográfica de complicaciones y de mortalidad. Resultados. En ambas cohortes no hubo muertes perioperatorias, siendo similar la tasa de complicaciones médicas (p = 0,601) y la supervivencia (p = 0,360) que a 7 años fue del 89,8% en octogenarios y 95,3% en controles, no influyendo las variables preoperatorias. No hubo diferencias en los resultados funcionales postoperatorios (p = 0,761), pero los octogenarios tuvieron mayor incremento (p = 0,002) respecto al preoperatorio. En octogenarios hubo 2 fracturas intraoperatorias, 2 luxaciones y 2 vástagos inestables. En los controles, una infección profunda, una fractura periprotésica femoral, e inestabilidad en 2 cotilos y 4 vástagos. Las tasas de complicaciones asépticas, de necesidad de revisión y de supervivencia de la artroplastia (94% a 7 años) fueron similares en ambas cohortes. Discusión. El incremento en el estado de salud hace que los octogenarios dispongan de una expectativa de vida de al menos 10 años. El argumento de costes y una edad arbitraria no debe influir en la selección de candidatos a ATC no cementada. Conclusiones. La ATC no cementada se ha mostrado segura y efectiva en los octogenarios con coxartrosis. El notable incremento encontrado en los resultados funcionales justifica el continuar utilizándola en estos pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);57(3): 186-193, mayo-jun. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113212</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artroplastia total de cadera primaria electiva no cementada en octogenarios. Estudio de caso-control</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
