<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039494</identifier>
<setSpec>0378-4835</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">PKB/Akt mediates radiosensitivity associated to ataxia telangiectasia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The gene mutated in ataxia telangiectasia (ATM) has been implicated in several functions such as cell cycle,    response to DNA damage, and insulin. Curiously, the PKB/Akt-mediated signaling route is related to the same    cellular responses. We show in this work that ATM is a major determinant of full PKB/Akt activation in    response to insulin or gamma-radiation. This conclusion was inferred from the results obtained in transient    transfection assays using exogenous PKB/Akt and ATM in Cos cells, and also in cell lines derived from ataxia    telangiectasia patients or KO mice. Our study proposes new clues to understand the radiosensitivity associated    to ataxia telangiectasia and supports a critical role for PKB/Akt in the cellular response to ionizing radiation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez-Castillejo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Prieto, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arraiga Aragón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, M. A. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guinea Viniegra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Callejas Valera, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aceves Luquero, C. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán Moya, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villas Sánchez, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El gen mutado en el síndrome de Ataxia Telangiectasia está implicado en múltiples funciones celulares queabarcan desde la respuesta al daño genotóxico causado por la radiación ionizante hasta la respuesta a insulina.Curiosamente la ruta de señalización mediada por Akt esta relacionada con los mismos estímulos. En el presenteestudio demostramos como el gen mutado en Ataxia Telangiectasia (ATM) controla la fosforilación deAkt, en respuesta a estímulos como la radiación ionizante o la insulina. Estos datos han sido obtenidos usandomodelos experimentales como células derivadas de enfermos de Ataxia o de ratones nulos para la expresión deATM. Nuestro estudio propone nuevas explicaciones para entender la radio sensibilidad característica de estosenfermos y destaca el papel primordial de Akt en la respuesta a la radiación ionizante</dc:description>
<dc:source>Oncologia;28(7): 329-337, jul. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039494</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">PKB/Akt media la radio sensibilidad asociada a Ataxia Telangiectasia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22346^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11391^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12279^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22346^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19154^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
