<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108670</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interrater reliability of the Harris Infant Neuromotor Test in the idiom portuguese: use with brazilian children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to evaluate the reliability interrater to characterize the profile of children and his caregivers using the first part of the Harris Infant Neuromotor Test(HINT) into Portuguese idiom. Methods: Methodological and longitudinal study, convenience sample composed by 73 children and her caregivers attended in an public institution in Fortaleza-Ceará-Brazil from September 2007 to September 2008. Results: the reliability interrater at first assessment baby was between 0,501 and 1,000, only two items showed low concordance. Sixteen items showed reliability 100% on third assessment.  The concordance of the total score showed a value of 0,801 (p= 0,001) and 0,898 (p= 0,001) on  first and third assessment, respectively. Conclusions: HINT is a reliable test for the sample researched, however it need be improved aiming represent all children of the Brazilian Nation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Grazielle Roberta Freitas da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cardoso, Maria Vera Lúcia Moreira Leitão</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar la con habilidad interclase con la primera parte de la prueba de Harris (sistema neuromotor infantil) en portugués. Métodos: Se trata de un estudio metodológico, longitudinal, con muestra de conveniencia compuesta 73 niños cuyos padres asistieron a una institución pública en Fortaleza-CE-Brasil, entre Diciembre/2008 Septiembre/2007. Resultados: La habilidad entre clases en la evaluación inicial de los niños oscilaba entre los 0,501 y 1,000, sólo dos ítems presentaron un acuerdo de baja. En el tercero, 16 ítems presentaron 100% de habilidad. El acuerdo de la puntuación total mostró un valor de 0,801 (p = 0,001) y 0,898 (p = 0,001) en la evaluación de la primera y tercera, respectivamente. Conclusiones: HINT es confiable para la muestra estudiada, pero es necesario mejorar para representar a todos los niños brasileños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;15(30): 60-70, mayo-ago. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Con fiabilidad intraclase del Test de Fiabilidad del Sistema Neruromotor del Bebe de Harris en lengua portuguesa: aplicación con niños brasileños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12033^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
