<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041515</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatic abscesses due to actinomycosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Liver actinomycosis is an infrequent infection accounting for 15% of all cases of abdominal actinomycosis and 5% of the total actinomycosis cases. It usually arises via the portal vein from an intestinal focus, but may also develop from neighbouring organs and structures or via the hepatic artery in disseminated infections. It is characterised by usually multiple abscesses with a more indolent course than other pyogenic abscesses. It usually courses with fever, abdominal pain and hepatomegaly. We report one case of hepatic actinomycosis as an infrequent cause of hepatic abscesses, which furthermore began with no clinical signs specific for an acute abdominal condition; an ulcerated neoplasm of the sigmoid colon was identified in the course of the patient&#146;s study as the possible point of origin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Souto, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agustín Cembellín, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Rojas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La actinomicosis hepática es una infección rara que representa el 15% de los casos de actinomicosis abdominal y el 5% de los casos totales. Generalmente se produce a través de la vena porta desde un origen intestinal, pero también puede ocurrir por contigüidad o por la arteria hepática en una infección diseminada. Se caracteriza por la aparición de abscesos generalmente múltiples que presentan un curso más indolente que otros abscesos piógenos. Suelen cursar con fiebre, dolor abdominal y hepatomegalia. Presentamos un caso de actinomicosis hepática como causa infrecuente de abscesos hepáticos que además comenzó sin signos específicos de proceso agudo abdominal, descubriéndose en el curso de su ingreso una neoplasia de sigma ulcerada como posible origen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);17(5): 228-230, oct. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041515</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abscesos hepáticos por actinomicosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d204^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8273^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8273^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8273^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d204^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d204^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d204^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
