<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93742</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital infection due to cytomegalovirus: the great unknown</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cytomegalovirus (CMV) is a low infectivity virus of the Herpes virus family. CMV is the main cause of child morbidity and mortality of congenital origin. CMV infection is very frequent and generally asymptomatic. Its importance lies in the potential seriousness when it affects newborns and inmunocompromised patients. Four per cent of symptomatic newborns at birth die and 90 percent suffer sequelae (including 13 per cent of asymptomatic patients). There are no comprehensive data on the prevalence of congenital disease. In our country not performed Systematic screening for CMV in pregnancy is not performed in our country(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casado García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collados Navas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El citomegalovirus (CMV) es un virus de baja contagiosidad perteneciente a la familia Herpesviridae. Es el principal responsable de la morbimortalidad infantil de origen congénito. La infección es muy frecuente, cursa de modo asintomático en la mayoría de las ocasiones y su importancia radica en la potencial gravedad cuando afecta a neonatos e inmunodeprimidos. El 4% de los recién nacidos sintomáticos y el 90% sufren secuelas. El 13% de los asintomáticos también desarrolla secuelas. No hay datos globales de prevalencia de enfermedad congénita por CMV. En nuestro país no se realiza cribado serológico sistemático para CMV durante la gestación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(10): 549-553, dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93742</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección congénita por citomegalovirus: la gran desconocida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32282^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31818^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31818^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31818^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31818^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
