<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120986</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complications of peripheral parenteral nutrition. Clinical observations of 2 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Peripheral parenteral nutrition (PPN) is arti&amp;#64257;cial nutrition used when digestive absorption is insuf&amp;#64257;cient. It supplies the nutritional needs of the patient and permits administration through a peripheral catheter. We present 2 clinical cases.: The &amp;#64257;rst one entails an epidermolisis through extravasation masked by temporo-spatial disorientation of the patient with appearance of &amp;#64258;ictenes (blisters).Prolonged treatment and consultation with plastic surgery were required. The second case entails a chemical phlebitis with early detection by nursing professionals. It was resolved with short term treatment and did not require consultation with the plasticsurgeon. Planning care: We elaborated a care plan aimed at identifying real or potential problems related with possible complications of intravenous PPN administration, such as phlebitis and extravasation. The aim of this research was prevention, early detection and treatment. Discussion: Phlebitis is related with catheter characteristics, in-dwelling time and high osmolarity of PPN. Early action decreases injury of the affected tissue. In case 1, the patient requires 19 days of curing. This was only 72 h in case 2.Conclusion: The nursing staff plays an essential role in catheter election, localization, administration and preventing complications. Staff training and a procedure protocol greatly reducethe incidence of phlebitis, avoid discomfort for the patient and reduce health care cost (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Juan, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomàs Tomàs, MM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorós Cerdá, SM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La nutrición parenteral periférica (NPP) es una nutrición artificial utilizada cuando la absorción por vía digestiva es insuficiente. Suple las demandas nutricionales del paciente. Permite su administración por vía periférica. A continuación se presentan 2 casos clínicos. El primero es una epidermólisis por extravasación enmascarada por desorientación temporoespacial del paciente, con aparición de flictenas. Requirió tratamiento prolongado y consulta a cirugía plástica. El segundo caso es una flebitis química con detección precoz por parte de los profesionales de enfermería. Se resolvió con tratamiento a corto plazo y no precisó interconsulta. Plan de cuidados Se elaboró un plan de cuidados dirigido a identificar los problemas potenciales o reales relacionados con las posibles complicaciones de la administración intravenosa de la NPP, como son la extravasación y la flebitis, actuando en la prevención, detección precoz y tratamiento. Discusión La flebitis está relacionada con las características del catéter, con el tiempo de permanencia y con la alta osmolaridad de la NPP. Una actuación precoz disminuye la lesión del tejido afectado. En el caso 1 el paciente requiere curas durante 19 días, mientras que en el caso 2 solo las precisa 72 h. Conclusión La enfermera desempeña un papel primordial en la elección del catéter, localización, administración y prevención de complicaciones. El adiestramiento del personal y la protocolización del procedimiento minimizan la incidencia de flebitis, evita molestias a los pacientes y reduce el gasto sanitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;25(1): 30-34, ene.-mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120986</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones de la nutrición parenteral periférica. Observación clínica de 2 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5219^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
