<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124471</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infection due to Rothia mucilaginosa. A respiratory pathogen?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To describe the spectrum of infections caused by Rothia mucilaginosa. Methods: Retrospective study of 20 cases diagnosed with R. mucilaginosa from 2009 to 2012.Results: Pulmonary infection was the most frequent clinical presentation (n = 14, 70%): bronchiectasis infected (10), followed by pleural empyema (2), pneumonia (1) and acute bronchitis (1). Two episodes were of gastrointestinal origin: cholangitis secondary to biliary drainage and secondary peritonitis. Two episodes included bacteremia in patients with hematological malignancy. One patient had a surgical wound infection with bacteremia, and another had a bacteremic urinary tract infection in a patient withnephrostomy. Discussion: R. mucilaginosa may be responsible for infections of the lower respiratory tract in predisposed Patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mateo, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portilla , Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosillo, Eva M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Describir el espectro de las infecciones causadas por Rothia mucilaginosa. Métodos Estudio retrospectivo de 20 casos de infección por R. mucilaginosa entre los años 2009 y 2012.ResultadosLa infección pulmonar fue la forma clínica más frecuente (n = 14; 70%): bronquiectasias sobreinfectadas (10), empiema pleural (2), neumonía (1) y bronquitis aguda (1). Dos episodios fueron digestivos: colangitis bacteriémica y peritonitis secundaria. Dos bacteriemias afectaron a pacientes con neoplasia hematológica. Hubo una infección bacteriémica de herida quirúrgica y otra infección urinaria bacteriémica en portador de nefrostomía. Discusión R. mucilaginosa puede ser responsable de infecciones de vías respiratorias bajas en pacientes con bronquiectasias pulmonares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(5): 306-309, mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124471</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección por Rothia mucilaginosa. ¿Un patógeno respiratorio?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30071^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32073^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30345^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30137^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
