<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138159</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunogenicity of an anti-HBV short schedule vaccination programme and its relationship with HCV</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Hepatitis B vaccine is recommended in those subjects with infection by hepatitis C virus, although the response is not well established. Subjects, material and methods: A retrospective observational study was designed involving all the subjects included in an anti-HBV. A short schedule was established (0,1,2) with 10 mcgr/ml of HBV surface antigen. Response to vaccination was assessed according to two criteria: 10 IU/L antiHBs or higher; and 100 IU/L antiHBs or higher. Variables associated with a vaccine response with P &lt; 0,1 were included in the logistic regression analysis. Results: 124 subjects were included in the study, mostly young men, 20% with infection by HCV. In 76.6 % (95% C.I. = 69,2-84,1) of subjects titles of circulating antibodies of 10 IU/L of anti-Hbs or higher were found. The response was three ti- mes more frequent in those not infected with HCV and 6% less frequent for each year of age. In 49,2% (95% C.I. = 40,4-58) of subjects titles of circulating post-vaccination antibodies of 100 IU/L of anti-HBs or higher were found, men responding three times less than women and 8% less for each year of age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canto, M. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jorquera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>ML Morís, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olcoz, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La vacuna frente a la hepatitis B (HB) está recomendada en aquellos sujetos con infección por virus C de la hepatitis (VCH), aunque la respuesta no está bien establecida. Sujetos, material y métodos: Se diseñó un estudio observacional retrospectivo que incluyó a todos los sujetos incluidos en un programa de vacunación frente a la HB. Se utilizó una pauta corta (0,1,2) con 10 mcgr/ml de antígeno de superficie del VBH. La respuesta a la vacunación se evaluó según dos criterios: 10 o más UI/L de antiHBs; y 100 o más UI de antiHBs. Las variables que se asociaron con una respuesta de la vacuna con una P &lt; 0,1 fueron incluidas en el análisis de regresión logística. Resultados: 124 sujetos fueron incluidos en el estudio, la mayoría hombres jóvenes, con una prevalencia de infección por VCH del 20%. En 76,6% (I.C. del 95% = 69,2-84,1) de los sujetos se observaron títulos de anticuerpos circulantes iguales o superiores a 10 UI/L de anti-Hbs. La respuesta fue tres veces más frecuente en aquellos no infectados con VCH y 6% menos frecuente por cada año de edad. El 49,2% (I.C. del 95% = 40,4-58,0) de los sujetos presentaron títulos de anticuerpos circulantes anti-Hbs postvacunales iguales o superiores a 100 UI/L. Los hombres respondieron tres veces menos que las mujeres y 8% menos por cada año de edad. Discusión: Nuestros resultados parecen indicar una respuesta más baja a la vacuna frente a la HB de los sujetos infectados por VCH, recomendándose la realización de marcadores postvacunales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;6(2): 28-32, mayo-ago. 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138159</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inmunogenicidad de una pauta corta de vacunación frente al virus B de la hepatitis y su relación con la infección por virus C de la hepatitis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23125^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33343^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30702^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
