<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131677</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dermatomyositis. Presentation of a mild to moderate case with early dysphagia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a twelve year old female patient with juvenile dermatomyositis. The diagnosis was made in our unit a few days after starting with proximal muscular weakness and a skin rash. A combination of oral corticosteroids and methotrexate was administered. There was an initial improvent in the skin lesions, but with no changes in the muscle weakness. The appearance of dysphagia a few days after starting the treatment led us to add three pulses of parenteral methylprednisolone to her initial treatment. We report the case to illustrate the difficulties in deciding initial treatment options (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paricio Talayero, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leandro Fonseca, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escrivá Tomás, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Carbonell, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent Antoli, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 12 años de edad afectada de dermatomiositis juvenil, que fue diagnosticada en nuestra unidad a los pocos días de presentar debilidad muscular proximal y rash cutáneo. Inició tratamiento con la combinación de corticoides por vía oral y metotrexato, con mejoría inicial de la afectación cutánea, sin modificarse la debilidad muscular. La aparición de disfagia a los pocos días de iniciado el tratamiento nos llevó a cambiar la estrategia terapéutica inicial, añadiendo pulsos de metilprednisolona parenteral. Aportamos  el caso como ilustrativo de la dificultad en la toma de decisiones sobre la opción de tratamiento inicial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): e86-e89, ene. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131677</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatomiositis. Aportación de un caso de afectación leve-moderada y disfagia precoz</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3902^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3902^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3902^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3902^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3902^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5520^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5520^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13252^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5520^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
