<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95651</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aesthetic assesment of 5 computer-modified facial profiles images: influence of evaluator age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Attractive facial aesthetics is undoubtedly one of the primary treatment goals of orthodontics. However, perception of anatomical features having an aesthetic component is influenced by subjectivity. The aim of this study was to compare the aesthetic assessment of five different computer-modified facial profiles of the same individual based on evaluations provided by one group of children and teenagers and another comprised of adults. Statistically significant differences were found according to the age of the evaluators, though not their sex. Overall, the participants rated the image depicting mandibular prognathism as the least attractive, although the younger group displayed greater tolerance for profiles with mandibular and maxillary hypoplasia.Conclusion: Aesthetic perception evolves with age,with adolescents and adults sharing a similar view of facial anomalies, while children tend to be less influenced by such features (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mahíllo Fernández, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llidó Tejedor, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rosas, Santiago J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela Morales, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cotrina Llorente, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Camba Varela, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Mosquera, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thams Baudot, Verena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conseguir una estética facial armoniosa es uno de los principales objetivos del tratamiento de ortodoncia, pero la valoración de cualquier aspecto anatómico que comporte un cierto componente estético está impregnada de subjetividad. La finalidad de este estudio fue comparar la valoración estética dada por un grupo de niños/adolescentes y otro de adultos a cinco perfiles, obtenidos a partir del de un mismo individuo mediante modificaciones por ordenador. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en función de la edad del evaluador, pero no así en función del sexo. Si bien el prognatismo mandibular fue el perfil peor considerado por todos los evaluadores, los niños/adolescentes mostraron mayor aceptación de los perfiles con hipoplasia mandibular y maxilar que los adultos. Conclusión: La apreciación estética del perfil facial se modifica con la edad, de manera que los adolescentes y adultos tienen una percepción similar de las anomalías, mientras que los niños más pequeños tienden a infravalorarlas. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);7(3): 173-178, sept.-dic.  2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95651</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración estética de 5 perfiles faciales modificados por ordenador: influencia de la edad del evaluador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35153</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5246</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1522</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
