<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152008</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nosocomial influenza outbreak in a tertiary hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Describe a nosocomial flu outbreak. Material and methods: The Service of Digestive Medicine where cases appeared is here described. Patients admitted (n=47) between February 17 and March 10, 2012 an epidemiological survey was does to each of them, obtaining their clinical and epidemiological characteristics (entry reason number of hospitalization days until the beginning of the symptoms, etc.) of the influenza cases. The vacunal coverage and the presence of respiratory symptoms in the health personnel were evaluated (n- 44). Moreover, the descriptions of all the infectious diseases control measures that were initiated are also described. Results: There were 10 patients (six of them confirmed) and 12 health professionals (two of them confirmed) with flu suspicion. The vaccination coverage in the health care workers of the unit was 18, 2% (8/44). Conclusions: An association was established between those cases of nosocomial influenza and the low influenza vaccination coverage of healthcare workers, which also had poor adherence to Standard Precautions. This may have been decisive risk factors for the emergence of this nosocomial outbreak of influenza (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mendoza García, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Román, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva Ruiz, CO</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Lucas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conesa Peñuela, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Payá, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Shimizu, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portilla Sogorb, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir un brote nosocomial de gripe A. Material y métodos: Se describe el Servicio de Medicina Digestiva donde aparecieron los casos. A los pacientes ingresados (n=47), entre el 17 de febrero y el 10 de marzo de 2012, se les realizó una encuesta epidemiológica, y a partir de esta, se describen sus características clínico-epidemiológicas (motivo de ingreso, días de hospitalización hasta el inicio de los síntomas, etc.) de los casos de gripe. Se evaluó la cobertura vacunal y la presencia de sintomatología respiratoria entre el personal sanitario (n=44), y se describen las medidas de control de infecciones puestas en marcha. Resultados: Hubo 10 pacientes con sospecha de gripe (seis de ellos confirmados) y 12 profesionales sanitarios con sospecha (dos confirmados). La cobertura vacunal en el personal sanitario de la unidad era del 18,2% (8/44). Conclusión: Se ha producido una asociación temporo-espacial de casos de gripe de adquisición nosocomial, donde la baja cobertura de la vacunación antigripal y la escasa adherencia a las Precauciones Estándar por parte del personal sanitario han podido ser factores determinantes para su aparición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;21(2/4): 11-16, 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152008</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote nosocomial de gripe A en un hospital de tercer nivel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50229</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
