<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100344</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conradi-Hünermann Chondrodysplasia punctata: anaesthetic implications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chondrodysplasia punctata syndrome is a group of rare congenital diseases that give rise to malformations, mainly skeletal, linked to the premature calcification of structures. There is little in the literature in the field of Anaesthesiology on this despite there being some clinical manifestations, particularly the possibility of difficult airway, which may be of importance during the peri-operative period. During the first years of life, the patients affected are often subjected to repeated surgery to correct their malformations. We describe the anaesthetic treatment during orthopaedic surgery of a paediatric patient with Conradi-Hünermann type chondrodysplasia punctata, highlighting the management of the airway using a laryngeal mask in combination with balanced general anaesthesia with remifentanil. We also present a review of the characteristics of the different entities of these syndromes, with special emphasis on the aspects most relevant to the anaesthesiologist(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Freire Vila, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesia López, A. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ventosa Fernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Aguiar, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">EL síndrome de condrodisplasia punctata es un grupo de enfermedades congénitas raras que dan lugar a malformaciones, fundamentalmente esqueléticas, vinculadas con la calcificación prematura de estructuras. Existe escasa bibliografía en el ámbito de la anestesiología, pese a que algunas de sus manifestaciones clínicas, especialmente la posibilidad de una vía aérea difícil, pueden tener relevancia durante el perioperatorio. Los pacientes afectos, durante los primeros años de vida, se verán frecuentemente sometidos a cirugías frecuentes para corrección de sus malformaciones. Presentamos el tratamiento anestésico durante una intervención quirúrgica ortopédica de un paciente pediátrico afecto de una condrodisplasia punctata tipo Conradi-Hünnermann. Se destaca el tratamiento de la vía aérea mediante una mascarilla laríngea en combinación con una anestesia general balanceada con remifentanilo. Asimismo presentamos una síntesis de las características de diversas entidades de estos síndromes, con especial énfasis en los aspectos más relevantes para el anestesiólogo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;59(2): 98-101, feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condrodisplasia punctata de Conradi-Hünermann: implicaciones anestésicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2856^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2856^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8569^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
