<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79450</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of the complexity of the training plan on the evaluation of knowledge of the peritoneal dialysis process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The assessment of knowledge after training fro PDis a routine activity; in our unit it is carried out using indicators relating to the following results criteria: H and ling of the process, of infection, of hydration, of nutrition/diet. Knowledge is assessed in 71 patients. Three levels of complexity in training were defined: Level 3 (teaching about peritoneal dialysis given simultaneously with teaching on handling of the cycler), Level 2 (training in CAPD and subsequently in handling the cycler) and Level 1 (standard training with personally tailored objectives).The highest evaluations appear in the option of direct Level 3 training which we have considered to be the most complex, which coincide with the youngest patients with the highest educational levels. This appears in all the indicators evaluated with slight modifications. In the Level 2 option the time used in learning is significantly higher to obtain a similar level of knowledge as patients in the CAPD option, which consider the least complex. Based on the results obtained, we consider that patients can complete learning in their chosen option, provided that they have a minimum educational level(they know how to read and write) and this does not entail a reduction in the level of knowledge acquired which appears to be more closely related to the age and educational level of the patient than with the complexity of the process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ojeda Guerrero, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Concepción Gómez Castilla, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de conocimientos tras el entrenamiento para DP es una actividad rutinaria; en nuestra unidad se realiza mediante indicadores relacionados con los siguientes criterios de resultados: Manejo el proceso, de la infección, de la hidratación, dela nutrición/dieta. Se evalúan los conocimientos de 71 pacientes. En el entrenamiento se definieron 3 niveles de complejidad: Nivel 3 (simultanear enseñanza sobre conocimientos de diálisis peritoneal y manejo de la cicladora). Nivel2 (entrenamiento en DPAC y posteriormente en el manejo de la cicladora) y) Nivel 1 (entrenamiento estándar con personalización de objetivos).Las valoraciones más altas aparecen en la opción de entrenamiento Nivel 3 directo que hemos considerado el de mayor complejidad, que coinciden con los pacientes más jóvenes y con mayor formación. Y esto aparece en todos los indicadores valorados con leves modificaciones. En la opción Nivel 2 el tiempo utilizado en el aprendizaje es significativamente mayor para obtener un nivel de conocimientos similar que los pacientes de la opción DPAC que consideramos la de menor complejidad. En razón a los resultados obtenidos consideramos que los pacientes pueden hacer el aprendizaje en la opción de elección, siempre que tengan un nivel mínimo de formación (saber leer y escribir) sin que ello conlleve la disminución del nivel de conocimientos adquiridos que parece estar más relacionado con la edad y nivel de formación que con la complejidad del proceso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;13(2): 120-125, abr.-jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79450</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la complejidad del plan de entrenamiento en la valoración del conocimiento del proceso diálisis peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27923^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16541</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
