<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82187</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epilepsy. The disease never spoken about</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">According to the WHO, epilepsy is the most frequent neurological disease in the world. Epilepsy affects 400,000 Spaniards and calculations indicate that worldwide some 50 million people suffer epilepsy, without any distinctions made among social classes, sex, race or geographical locations. 20,000 new cases are diagnosed in Spain annually. Three out of every four patients respond to pharmaceutical treatment while 15% benefit from brain surgery, but 10% of those patients who suffer epilepsy are pharmaceutical-resistant, which means that their families must keep an eye on them 24 hours per day(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Asensio Vicente, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La epilepsia es, según la OMS, la enfermedad neurológica más frecuente en todo el mundo. Afecta a 400.000 personas en España y se calcula que la padecen unos 50 millones en todo el mundo, sin distinción entre clases sociales, sexo, raza o límites geográficos. En España cada año se diagnostican 20.000 nuevos casos. Tres de cada cuatro pacientes responden al tratamiento farmacológico y un 15% se beneficia de la cirugía cerebral, pero existe un 10% de ellos que padece epilepsia fármaco-resistente, por lo que sus familias tienen que estar pendientes «las 24 horas del día»(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(10): 694-702, oct. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82187</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La epilepsia. La enfermedad de la que nunca se habla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13024^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
