<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83021</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results of the screening program for colorectal cancer screening in Cantabria, Spain, during the period november 2008-march 2010</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The colorectal cancer (CCR) is a Public Health problem because of its high incidence and mortality. Screening programs are important for early detection of CCR. An early detection of this illness could decrease its mortality. The objectives of our study are to present the colorectal cancer screening program in Cantabria and its main results. Methods: Descriptive study of a two-year screening program for population in the 55 &#150; 69 years age range, according to the Cantabria Health Service data base (92,605 people). The screening test used a qualitative immunochemical method in search of faecal occulted blood (FOB), complemented by optical colonoscopy confirmation. Eligible people were invited to participate in the screening program by means of personal letter and, in case of acceptance, they were dated in their primary Health Center. After application of exclusion criteria, selected people with a positive result test were submitted to optical colonoscopy. Those in which an invasive cancer was detected were directly addressed to the Digestive Service. Results: The program was offered to 35,005 (37.8 %) of the eligible population of Cantabria at the end of study period. 2,384 persons participated (32.1%). The main colonoscopy findings were 1 «in situ» cancer, 2 invasive cancer and 43 high-risk adenomas. Conclusion: Due to its integration into primary care, lack of apparatus, ease use and fast implementation, qualitative immunochemical test FOBT facilitates the extension of screening, with similar results to those of quantitative immunochemical test(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brugos-Llamazares, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terán-Lantarón, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vada-Sánchez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Aledo Linos, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Por su elevada incidencia y mortalidad el cáncer colorrectal (CCR) se considera un importante problema de Salud Pública. Los programas de cribado están adquiriendo cada vez mayor relevancia en su abordaje dada la importancia del diagnóstico precoz en la disminución de la mortalidad por esta causa. El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar el desarrollo y resultados del programa de cribado poblacional de CCR en Cantabria. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo del programa de cribado de carácter bienal diseñado para la población de 55 a 69 años a partir de la base de datos de la Tarjeta Sanitaria (92.605 personas). La determinación de sangre oculta en heces (SOH) por método inmunoquímico cualitativo es la prueba de cribado, empleándose la colonoscopia óptica como confirmación. La población recibe una carta de invitación, debiéndose citar en su Centro de Salud si aceptan participar. Tras aplicar los criterios de exclusión, las personas con resultado positivo en el test son citadas para colonoscopia. Aquellos en los que se detecta un carcinoma invasivo son remitidos directamente al Servicio de digestivo. Resultados: En el periodo de estudio estaban cubiertas por el programa 35.005 personas (37,8 % de la población diana). De las invitadas (7.406) participaron 2.384 (32,1%). Fueron detectados un carcinoma «in situ», 2 invasivos y 43 adenomas de alto riesgo. Conclusión: Por su integración en Atención Primaria, ausencia de aparataje, fácil uso y rápida realización, el test de detección de SOH inmunoquímico cualitativo facilita la extensión del cribado, con resultados similares a los de los test inmunoquímicos cuantitativos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;84(6): 575-770, nov.-dic.2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83021</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del programa de detección precoz de cáncer colorrectal en Cantabria durante el período noviembre de 2008 a marzo de 2010</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3139^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
