<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74988</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of voriconazole in critically ill patients with invasive mycoses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This observational study of the use of voriconazole conducted in Spain hasidentified reasons, characteristics, and forms of use of voriconazole in criticallyill patients admitted to the ICU. Voriconale was used for directed treatment(63%), by the intravenous route (75%), as rescue treatment (41%) in severelyill patients (APACHE 21) with high need of resources and therapeuticinterventions. Satisfactory clinical response was obtained in 50% of cases,related adverse events were scarce (16%), and withdrawal of voriconazole wasnot necessary. Clinical indications included empirical, etiologic, and rescuetreatment of infections caused by Aspergillus, Candida albicans and mostspecies different than C. albicans. Voriconazole can be used for preemptivetherapy in patients at risk of invasive candidasis. When selecting voriconazole,liver function, renal function (i.v. formulation) and history of azoles use shouldbe considered, although none of these circumstances is an absolutecontraindication for the prescription of voriconazole in critically ill patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Lerma, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un estudio observacional de uso de voriconazol realizado en España haidentificado los motivos, características y formas de empleo de esteantifúngico en pacientes críticos ingresados en UCI. Destaca su utilización enforma dirigida (63%), por vía endovenosa (75%), como tratamiento de rescate(41%) en una población de elevada gravedad (APACHE 21) y altasnecesidades de recursos e intervenciones terapéuticas. La respuesta clínicaha sido satisfactoria en el 50% de los casos y los efectos adversosrelacionados escasos (16%) no siendo necesaria su retirada en ningún caso.Las indicaciones clínicas incluyen el tratamiento empírico, dirigido y derescate de infecciones producidas por Aspergillus, Candida albicans y lamayoría de especies de Candida diferentes de C. albicans. Puede utilizarse enel tratamiento anticipado de pacientes con riesgo de candidiasis invasora.Para su elección debe evaluarse la función hepática, función renal(formulación i.v.) y el antecedente de empleo de azoles, aunque ninguno deellas contraindica de forma absoluta la indicación de voriconazol en pacientescríticos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;24(3): 209-212, 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel de voriconazol en pacientes críticos con micosis invasoras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14625^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1235^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7852^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1414^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8285^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
