<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141699</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Decision making and skill development in youth football players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents how decision-making and skills are developed in high level of expertise players from 6-7 to 13-14 years. The framework is based on the dynamical systems and teaching games for understanding approaches. Participants were 57 first team players of each age (n = 13 to 16) of Albacete Balompié: U-8, U-10, U-12 and U-14. The Game Performance Assessment Tool (GPET) was the instrument used for assessment, which measures decision-making and execution from an ecological view in relation to tactical principles (Bayer, 1992), comparing the game situation with the decision applied. The results are based on inferential and correlation analysis. The evolution of knowledge evolves attack to defensive. We have found significant differences in variables between the four age categories studied. These differences have been shown in attack: the progress toward goal tactical principle and shake off; on defence: marking and cover (off-ball defenders) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Contreras-Jordán, OR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-López, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Víllora, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo presenta como se desarrolla la toma de decisiones y la habilidad técnica en jugadores con alto nivel de pericia desde los 6-7 a 13-14 años. El marco teórico está basado en la perspectiva de los sistemas dinámicos y la enseñanza comprensiva de los deportes. Se tomó como muestra a 57 jugadores del primer equipo de cada categoría de edad del Albacete Balompié: prebenjamín, benjamín, alevín e infantil. El instrumento usado fue la Herramienta de Evaluación del Rendimiento de Juego (HERJ), que mide la toma de decisiones y la ejecución, incluyendo el análisis ecológico atendiendo a principios tácticos (Bayer, 1992),comparando la situación en el juego con la decisión aplicada. Los resultados se basan en el análisis inferencial y correlacional. La evolución del rendimiento de juego se orienta desde el ataque hasta la defensa. Se han encontrado diferencias significativas en las variables entre las cuatro categorías de formación estudiadas,especialmente en el principio táctico de progresar hacia la portería contraria y en el desmarque, así como en el marcaje y la ayuda en defensa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;15(59): 467-487, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141699</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la toma de decisiones y la habilidad técnica en fútbol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
