<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149456</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of regulatory policies: the prevention of traffic accidents in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traffic accident injuries may be reduced with public policies. We review regulatory policies extending beyond the health sector by studying the case of traffic accident injuries. They have been the object of other analyses in Spain by both health professionals and professionals from other sectors, but we have not found a previous thorough review including regulatory aspects. We analyze the evolution of fatal victims of traffic accidents as collected by the Dirección General de Tráfico, stratifying for pedestrians, two-wheel vehicle occupants and occupants of other vehicles, and breaking down accidents between those occurring in roads and in urban settings. Despite the increase in exposure factors between 1970 and 2003, we observe a strong impact of regulatory policies in accident mortality. A favorable impact is seen for regulations and enforcement actions on motorcycle helmets, speed limits and the control of alcohol use, and a lower impact for safety belts, perhaps because its actual effective implementation was not equally sharp. The adoption of comprehensive plans or complex legislation packages seems to have had a positive impact, perhaps attributable to its triggering of more effective enforcement of already existing regulations. Although the existence of legal norms is not enough in itself, as its impact is low without active enforcement, compliance improves over time. In any case, the existence of specific initiatives to influence this field is important to obtain the best results of regulatory policies in public health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Catherine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalbí, Joan R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las lesiones por accidentes de vehículos de motor pueden reducirse con la adopción de determinadas políticas públicas. Se revisan las aportaciones de una política regulatoria que desborda al sector sanitario evaluando el caso de las lesiones por accidentes de tráfico. Éste ha sido objeto ya de estudios de profesionales de la salud pública y de otros sectores en España, pero no hemos encontrado una revisión integral que incluya la valoración de aspectos regulatorios. Se analizan las víctimas mortales de los accidentes de tráfico tal como las contabiliza la Dirección General de Tráfico, estratificando el análisis entre peatones, ocupantes de vehículos de dos ruedas, y ocupantes de otros vehículos, y distinguiendo entre accidentes en carretera y en vías urbanas. Pese al incremento de los factores de exposición entre 1970 y 2003, se aprecia un fuerte efecto de las políticas regulatorias dirigidas al tráfico en la mortalidad por accidentes. Se sugiere un impacto favorable de las regulaciones y las acciones para hacerlas cumplir sobre el casco para motoristas, los límites de velocidad y el control del consumo de alcohol, y no tanto respecto de los cinturones de seguridad, probablemente por que la exigencia efectiva de su uso se produjo de forma más escalonada. Parece que la adopción de planes integrales o de paquetes legislativos complejos tuvo un efecto favorable, quizá estimulando el cumplimiento efectivo de regulaciones ya existentes. Aunque se pone de manifiesto que la existencia de normas legales no es suficiente por sí misma, pues si no se hacen cumplir su efecto es mínimo, también se documenta cómo el cumplimiento se refuerza con el tiempo. En cualquier caso, se puede apreciar cómo la existencia de iniciativas concretas para influir en este terreno es importante para obtener los mejores frutos en salud pública de las políticas regulatorias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;20(supl.1): 79-87, mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149456</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de políticas regulatorias: prevención de las lesiones por accidentes de tráfico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32679^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32679^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d439</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11926^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33550</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
