<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137666</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-1342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of safety and efficacy of a new multipurpose disinfecting solution on silicone hydrogel contact lenses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To evaluate the safety and efficacy of a new multipurpose disinfecting solution (MPDS) with a formulation that includes aloe vera on its composition. Methods: This is a prospective, randomized, double-masked clinicaltrial with a crossover design that included seven examinations. Two different MPDSs, Avizor Alvera® (study solution) and All Clean Soft® (control solution), each were used for 1 month. Comfilcon A silicone hydrogel contact lenses were used during the trial. The main outcome variables were corneal staining and deposits on the surfaces of the contact lenses. Other parameters including ocular surface response, contact lens wettability, user satisfaction, and adverse events, were analyzed according to the International Organization for Standardization (ISO) 11980:2010 guidance for clinical investigation. Results: Twenty subjects (10 women, 10 men) (mean age, 27.7 ± 5.6 years; range, 20---41) were included. No differences between both MPDSs were found in the percentage of subjects with corneal staining &gt;0 at day 30 (study: 35%, control: 50%; p = 0.46); neither in the percentage of subjects with deposits on the surface of the contact lens &gt;0 at day 30 (study: 26.32%, control: 52.63%; p = 0.18). The study MPDS received higher rates in comfort (study: 8.14 ± 1.09, control: 7.94 ± 0.92; p = 0.56) and satisfaction at day 30 (study: 8.63 ± 0.91, control: 8.29 ± 0.80; p = 0.19), however the scores were not significantly different with the control MPDS. Conclusions: The clinical trial showed that the study MPDS is safe, efficient, and has acceptable physiologic tolerance, according to the ISO 11980:2010 guidance for clinical investigation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blázquez Arauzo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinto-Fraga, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbano Rodríguez, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-García, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la seguridad y la eficacia de una nueva solución única desinfectante (MPDS), con una formulación que incluye aloe vera en su composición. Métodos: El estudio consistió en un ensayo clínico prospectivo, aleatorio y de doble ciego, con un diseño cruzado que incluyó siete exámenes. Se utilizaron durante un mes dos MPDS diferentes, Avizor Alvera® (solución en estudio) y All Clean Soft® (solución de control). Durante el ensayo se utilizaron lentes de contacto de hidrogel de silicona Comfilcon A. Las principales variables evaluadas fueron la tinción corneal y los depósitos sobre la superficie de las lentes de contacto. Se analizaron otros parámetros, que incluían la respuesta de la superficie ocular, la humectabilidad de las lentes de contacto, y los eventos adversos, de acuerdo con la normativa 11980:2010 de la Organización Internacional de Normalización (ISO) para investigación clínica. Resultados: El estudio incluyó a veinte sujetos (10 mujeres, 10 hombres) (edad media, 27,7 ± 5,6 años; rango, 20-41). No se hallaron diferencias entre ambas MPDS en cuanto al porcentaje de sujetos con tinción corneal &gt; 0 al mes (estudio: 35%, control: 50%; p = 0,46), ni el porcentaje de sujetos con depósitos en la superficie de las lentes de contacto &gt; 0 al mes (estudio: 26,32%, control: 52,63%; p = 0,18). La MPDS en estudio obtuvo valoraciones superiores en cuanto a confort (estudio: 8,14 ± 1,09, control: 7,94 ± 0,92; p = 0,56) y satisfacción (estudio: 8,63 ± 0,91, control: 8,29 ± 0,80; p = 0,19); sin embargo, las puntuaciones no fueron significativamente diferentes en relación a la MPDS de control. Conclusiones: El ensayo clínico reflejó que la MPDS en estudio es segura y eficaz, mostrando una tolerancia fisiológica aceptable, de acuerdo con la normativa ISO 11980:2010 para investigación clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>J. optom. (Internet);8(1): 40-47, ene.-mar. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137666</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la seguridad y eficacia de una nueva solución multipropósito en lentes de contacto de hidrogel de silicona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32300^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10063^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3282</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
