<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74148</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A methodologycal approach to the study of mental disorders in the prison population. The Preca study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This project aims to provide knowledge of reality in a psychiatric population neglected as the prison. The objectives of thestudy are: to estimate the prevalence of mental disorders in a Spanish prison sample, to analyze their association with sociodemographicand criminal as well as assess the impact on quality of life and describe and evaluate the health and social carereceived by People with mental disorders. Interviewing a total of 708 inmates sentenced to prison 5 distributed in 3Autonomous Communities. Assessment instruments have been used SCID, IPDE, TONI II to assess the presence of mentaldisorders, quality of life scale (EuroQol and Social Weather CIES) and utlización service.Results: The field project began in October 2006 to October 2007. There have been a total of 94.4% of planned interviewswith results that allow for data on the epidemiology of mental disorders in prison unprecedented so far (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicens Pons, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente proyecto pretende dar conocimiento de la realidad psiquiátrica en una población poco estudiada como es lapenitenciaria. Los objetivos del estudio son: estimar la prevalencia de los trastornos mentales en una muestra representativapenitenciaria española; analizar su asociación con variables sociodemográficas y delictivas así como evaluar la repercusión sobrela calidad de vida y describir y evaluar la atención sanitaria y social que reciben las personas con trastornos mentales. Se entrevistaa un total de 708 internos penados de 5 centros penitenciarios distribuidos en 3 Comunidades Autónomas. Los instrumentosde evaluación utilizados han sido la SCID, IPDE, TONI II para evaluar la presencia de trastornos mentales; escalas calidadde vida (EuroQol y Clima Social CIES) y de utilización de servicio.Resultados: El trabajo de campo del proyecto se inició en octubre de 2006 finalizando en octubre de 2007. Se han realizadoun 94,4% (708) del total de entrevistas previstas (750) con unos resultados que permiten disponer de datos sobre la epide -miología española de los trastornos mentales en medio penitenciario sin precedentes hasta el momento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;11(1): 17-25, mar.-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74148</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación a la Metodología para el estudio de los Trastornos mentales en población penitenciaria. El estudio PreCa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11765^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
