<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165920</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acquired heart disease in adults: what can a chest X-ray tell us?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The last 25 to 30 years have seen enormous advances in imaging techniques for the diagnosis of heart disease (echocardiography, cardiac MRI, CT angiography, etc.). Nevertheless, the first imaging test done in patient with heart disease continues to be plain-film chest X-rays. This economical, widely available technique makes it possible to follow up patients with heart disease and even to assess the severity of disease in some cases. This article explains how to read a chest X-ray systematically and the radiologic signs that make possible to suspect heart disease; it also provides detailed information about the signs of heart failure and the meaning of cardiac calcifications. Conclusion. Plain-film chest X-rays provide valuable additional information in the diagnosis and management of adult patients with heart disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Mondéjar, MR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tovar Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos 25-30 años se ha producido un enorme avance en las técnicas de imagen aplicadas al diagnóstico de la patología cardiaca (ecocardiografía, cardio-RM, angio-TC, etc.). Sin embargo, la radiografía de tórax sigue siendo la primera prueba a realizar, dado su bajo coste, amplia disponibilidad y el hecho de que permite realizar el seguimiento de pacientes con enfermedad cardiaca, e incluso en algunos casos valorar su gravedad. El objetivo del estudio es describir cómo realizar una adecuada lectura sistemática de la radiografía de tórax y de los signos radiológicos que permiten sospechar la presencia de enfermedad cardiaca, así como detallar los signos de insuficiencia cardiaca y el significado de las calcificaciones cardiacas. Conclusión. La radiografía de tórax en el adulto aporta información adicional valiosa en el diagnóstico y manejo terapéutico de pacientes con enfermedad cardiaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);59(5): 446-459, sept.-oct. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165920</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La patología cardiaca adquirida del adulto: ¿qué se puede decir con la radiografía de tórax?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9132^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9394^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1028^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6478^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9132^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9135^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6478^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
