<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94142</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body shape model, physical activity and eating behaviour</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Research on the influence of body shape model on adolescent males is scarce. The current study aimed to assess this influence among adult males involved in intense physical activity and to determine its relationship to eating behaviour. Possible variations between 1998 and 2008 were also analysed. Method: A total of 950 males (672 in 1998 and 278 in 2008), all aspiring professional soldiers, were studied using the Questionnaire of Influences on Body Shape Model (CIMEC-V) and the Eating Attitudes Test-40 (EAT-40), as well as by assessing their physical/sporting activity and body mass index (BMI). Results: Scores on the CIMEC-V were significantly correlated with the EAT-40 and BMI. As regards physical activity the only positive correlation referred to gym-based exercise. A cluster analysis revealed two subgroups with respect to physical activity, BMI, and scores on the CIMEC-V and EAT-40. One of them scored higher on these three variables and they also had a BMI &gt; 25. The comparative study of data from 1998 and 2008 showed significant changes in some variables. Conclusions: Generally, the results differ considerably from those reported for younger samples (which would suggest a lower risk of disordered eating behaviour). However, there is a higher risk group in which the influence of body shape models, physical activity and eating behaviour are related to greater body volume. The influence of the body shape model on males has increased, especially as regards the influence of friends and in terms of behaviours aimed at weight loss (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jáuregui Lobera, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolaños Ríos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomillo Cid, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santiago Fernández, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La investigación sobre la influencia del modelo estético corporal en varones adolescentes es escasa. El presente estudio analiza tal influencia en varones con intensa actividad física y su influencia en la conducta alimentaria. También fueron analizadas las posibles variaciones entre 1998 y 2008. Método: Un total de 950 varones (672 en 1998 y 278 en 2008), aspirante a soldado profesional, fueron evaluados usando el Cuestionario de Influencia del Modelo Estético Corporal (CIMEC) y el Test de Actitudes Alimentarias (EAT), así como evaluando su actividad físico-deportiva y el Índice de Masa Corporal (IMC). Resultados: Las puntuaciones del CIMEC correlacionaron significativamente con el EAT-40 y el IMC. En cuanto a la actividad física, la única correlación positiva fue la referente a la actividad física en el gimnasio. El análisis de conglomerados mostró dos grupos con respecto a actividad física, IMC y puntuaciones del CIMEC-V y EAT-40. Uno de ellos puntuó más en esas tres variables, presentando un IMC &gt; 25. La comparación de datos de 1998 y 2008 mostró cambios significativos en algunas de las variables. Discusión: Los resultados difieren considerablemente de los recogidos en muestras de menos edad (lo que podría indicar menos riesgo de alteraciones alimentarias). Sin embargo, hay un grupo de mayor riesgo en el que la influencia del modelo estético corporal, la actividad física y la conducta alimentaria están relacionados con un mayor volumen corporal. La influencia del modelo estético en varones ha aumentado, especialmente la de los amigos y la relacionada con conductas dirigidas a perder peso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(1): 201-207, ene.-feb. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94142</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo estético corporal, actividad física y conducta alimentaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
