<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95213</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Foot perforator flaps: problems and possible solutions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traditional medial plantar flap is widely described in the literature, but foot perforator flap is a relatively new subject which still needs more detailed anatomical investigation. We need to amplify our knowledge about this surgically challenging region, dissection difficulties and possible solutions. We performed anatomical dissection on 10 cadaver feet with dyed latex intravascular injection and then dissected out the perforators arising from the medial plantarartery. We measured the origin of the dominant perforators in relationship to 3 reference points, diameter and length of each perforator. We analyzed the application of flaps based on these perforators as local and freeflaps in relation to pedicle length and diameter, flapthickness and donor site morbidity. Foot perforator flaps are a good option for local and distant reconstruction. Donor site morbidity is low and functional result is good due to tissue characteristics of the foot region when used for hand reconstruction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prousskaia Peregudova, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador Sanz, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gabilondo Zubizarreta, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de diversas publicaciones existentes sobre el colgajo mediano plantar tradicional, los colgajos de las perforantes del pie no están suficientemente estudiados. Es necesario ampliar nuestros conocimientos sobre la anatomía vascular de esta región, los problemas que pueden surgir durante la disección de la zona y las posibles soluciones. Realizamos disección anatómica de 10 pies de cadáver utilizando relleno vascular con látex coloreado. Definimos la secuencia de la disección de las perforantes de la arteria plantar medial. Medimos los puntos de salida de las perforantes dominantes en relación con 3 puntos de referencia, diámetro y longitud de cada perforante. Evaluamos la utilidad de cada colgajo para su uso en reconstrucción local o a distancia en función del diámetro y la longitud de la perforante, grosor del colgajo y morbilidad de la zona donante. Los colgajos de los vasos perforantes del pie son una buena opción para la reconstrucción tanto local como a distancia, con una mínima morbilidad de la zona donante y con un buen resultado funcional gracias a las características del tejido del pie cuando se usa para reconstrucción en mano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;36(2): 89-96, abr.-jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colgajos de las perforantes del pie: problemas y posibles soluciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5665^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4271^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
