<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047033</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">VII European Framework Program of Research and Development</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The last 1 of June 2006, the European Parliament has adopted the first "Competitiveness and Innovation Framework Programme" (CIP). Between 2007 and 2013, the EU will invest 3.6 billion Euros. The CIP will bring together a range of European actions into a single comprehensive programme. The programme has a clear objective: increasing European competitiveness and innovation. This is a direct response to the call of the Lisbon mid-term review for simpler, more visible and more targeted European Union action to boost growth and jobs. In this paper the main changes of this Competitiveness and Innovation Framework Programme are approached, mainly in the field of health research</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana Trias, Octavia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pasado día 1 de junio de 2006, el Parlamento Europeo adoptaba el primer Programa Marco de Competitividad e Innovación (CIP), otorgándole un presupuesto de 36.000 millones de euros para el período 2007-2013. El CIP reunirá una serie de acciones europeas en un sólo programa. El programa tiene un objetivo claro: aumentar la competitividad y la innovación. Ésta es una respuesta a la llamada de la revisión a medio plazo de Lisboa de simplificar, hacer más visibles y dirigidas las acciones de la Unión Europea para estimular el crecimiento y los trabajos. En este artículo se abordan los principales cambios de este programa, principalmente en el ámbito de la investigación en ciencias de la salud</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(4): 214-218, jul. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047033</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">VII Programa Marco Europeo de Investigación y Desarrollo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19089^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24459^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5160</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
