<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049090</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Waterborne outbreak of gastroenteritis caused by Norovirus transmitted through drinking water</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The aim of this study was to conduct an investigation into an outbreak of waterborne disease caused by Norovirus due to the consumption of contaminated drinking water.                 Methods. The first week after the school summer holidays we detected an outbreak of gastroenteritis at a school in Borges Blanques (Lleida, Spain).                 A retrospective cohort study was carried out to investigate: water consumption and food (six items). We assessed RNA Norovirus by RT-PCR in 6 stool samples. The risk of gastroenteritis was assessed by applying adjusted risk ratio (RRa) analysis at 95% confidence intervals (CI).                 Results. The overall attack rate was 45% (96/213). The main symptoms were: abdominal pain, 88.4% (84/95); nausea, 65.9% (62/94), and vomiting, 64.6% (62/96). The consumption of school dinking water was statistically associated with the disease (RRa: 2.8; 95% CI: 1.3-6.2). The school water tank was dirty, but this drinking water was qualified as potable. Six stool samples gave positive results for Norovirus.                 Conclusions. Norovirus caused this waterborne outbreak of gastroenteritis transmitted through treated drinking water. It should be obligatory to regularly clean school drinking water deposit tanks, especially after the summer holidays</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Apellidos, Nombre</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo fue investigar un brote de gastroenteritis por Norovirus originado por el consumo de agua de suministro público.                 Métodos. La primera semana después de las vacaciones de verano se detectó un brote de gastroenteritis en la escuela pública de Les Borges Blanques (Lleida). Se realizó un estudio de cohortes retrospectivo. Se tomaron muestras de agua y se determinó la presencia del ARN de Norovirus (reacción en cadena de la polimerasa previa transcripción inversa [PCR-RT]) en las muestras de seis pacientes. El riesgo de gastroenteritis se determinó con el riesgo relativo ajustado (RRa) y su intervalo de confianza (IC) del 95%.                 Resultados. La tasa de ataque global fue del 45% (96/213). Los síntomas más frecuentes fueron: abdominalgias, el 88,4% (84/95); náuseas, el 65,9% (62/94), y vómitos, el 64,6% (62/96). El consumo de agua procedente del depósito, el cual estaba en malas condiciones higiénicas, se asoció con el riesgo de gastroenteritis (RRa: 2,8; IC 95%: 1,3-6,2), aunque esta agua fue calificada como potable. En las seis muestras de heces se detectó Norovirus.                 Discusión. Norovirus causó un brote originado por agua calificada como potable. Se recomienda limpiar los depósitos de agua después de las vacaciones estivales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;206(9): 435-437, oct. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049090</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de gastroenteritis por Norovirus causado por el consumo de agua de suministro público</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35604^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31799^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31799^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31799^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15275</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
