<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138508</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sex-related impact on clinical outcome of everolimus-eluting versus bare-metal stents in st-segment myocardial infarction. Insights from the EXAMINATION trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The use of second-generation drug-eluting stents compared with bare-metal stents in patients with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction reduces the rate of major adverse cardiac events. We aimed to evaluate the impact of sex on the performance of everolimus-eluting stents vs bare-metal stents in ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction at 2-year follow-up. Methods: This is a sub-study of the EXAMINATION trial that randomized 1498 patients with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention to everolimus-eluting or bare-metal stents. Primary end point was combined all-cause death, any recurrent myocardial infarction, and any revascularization. All end points were analyzed according to sex at 2-year follow-up. Results Of 1498 patients included in the trial, 254 (17.0%) were women. Women were older and had higher prevalence of hypertension and lower prevalence of smoking compared with men. In contrast with men, stent diameter was smaller in women. After multivariate analysis, the primary end point was similar between women and men (hazard ratio = 0.95; 95% confidence interval, 0.66-1.37), and among women, between those treated with bare-metal vs everolimus-eluting stents (hazard ratio = 2.48; 95% confidence interval, 0.95-6.46). Women showed a lower rate of repeat revascularization than men (hazard ratio = 0.55; 95% confidence interval, 0.32-0.95) despite worse baseline characteristics. This difference was driven by better performance of the everolimus-eluting stent in women. Conclusions: Despite poorer baseline clinical characteristics, women with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction treated with percutaneous coronary intervention showed outcomes similar to men. The use of everolimus-eluting stents may represent an added value in women as it showed a reduced rate of repeated revascularization compared to men (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Yuste, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Rodríguez, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Íñiguez, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regueiro, Ander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freixa, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugaletta, Salvatore</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masotti, Monica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serruys, Patrick W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabaté, Manelé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cequier, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Los stents liberadores de fármaco (farmacoactivos) de segunda generación, en comparación con los stents metálicos sin recubrimiento, reducen la tasa de eventos adversos cardiacos mayores de los pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST. El objetivo es evaluar la influencia del sexo del paciente en el resultado obtenido con los stents liberadores de everolimus en comparación con los stents metálicos sin recubrimiento en pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST a los 2 años de seguimiento. Métodos: Se llevó a cabo un subestudio del ensayo clínico EXAMINATION, en el que se aleatorizó a 1.498 pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST tratados con intervención coronaria percutánea al grupo de stents liberadores de everolimus o al de stents metálicos sin recubrimiento. El objetivo principal fue la combinación de muerte por cualquier causa, cualquier recurrencia de infarto agudo de miocardio y cualquier revascularización. Todos los objetivos se analizaron en función del sexo del paciente en el seguimiento realizado a los 2 años. Resultados: De los 1.498 pacientes incluidos en el ensayo, 254 (17,0%) eran mujeres. Las mujeres eran de más edad y tenían mayor prevalencia de hipertensión arterial y menor prevalencia de tabaquismo que los varones. Respecto a los varones, el diámetro máximo del stent en las mujeres resultó menor. Tras realizar un análisis multivariable, el objetivo principal fue similar entre mujeres y varones (hazard ratio = 0,95; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,66-1,37), y en el análisis realizado sobre las mujeres, fue similar entre tratadas con stents metálicos sin recubrimiento y tratadas con stents liberadores de everolimus (hazard ratio = 2,48; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 0,95-6,46). Las mujeres presentaron una tasa de revascularización repetida menor que los (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(5): 382-389, mayo 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138508</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del sexo en los resultados clínicos de los stents liberadores de everolimus en comparación con los stents metálicos sin recubrimiento en el infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST. Perspectivas del ensayo EXAMINATION</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
