<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050496</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contributions of systematic review and meta-analysis to public health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Meta-analysis has several precedents; even in Confucius (VIBC) one can found a sentence about the synthesis of knowledge.Meta-analysis is a consequence of the paradigm of induction.Within this paradigm of research, meta-analysis gives an analysisof the principle of consistency of a causal association (2nd principleof Hill). It has promoted the development of evaluation questionnairesand protocols for different designs, mainly clinical trials. Itfavoured the movement of evidence-based medicine, which isbehind the creation of agencies for the evaluation of health technologies,and the recognition of public health professionals dedicatedto research methods (mainly epidemiologists). The contributions ofmeta-analysis to public health are not distinguishable from othersmade to other specialties, although in the field of research methodsit has contributed to the study of publication bias and to the searchof determinants of heterogeneity, the lack of consistency among theindividual studies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palma Pérez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Rodríguez, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El metaanálisis tiene precedentes, incluso en Confucio (siglo VIAC) se puede apreciar una frase relativa a la síntesis del conocimiento.El metaanálisis es fruto del paradigma inductista de investigaciónque nos gobierna. Dentro de él nos ofrece un análisis del principio deconsistencia para una asociación causal (2º principio de Hill). Hamotivado el desarrollo de cuestionarios y protocolos de evaluaciónde diferentes tipos de diseños, principalmente de ensayos clínicos.Todo esto fue uno de los detonantes de lo que se ha dado en llamarmedicina basada en la «evidencia» (mejor «pruebas» en castellano).Ha impulsado la creación de agencias de evaluación de tecnologíassanitarias y favorecido el reconocimiento de los profesionales desalud pública más conocedores del método de investigación. Suscontribuciones a la salud pública no se pueden separar de las realizadasen otras especialidades, pero en el campo de la metodología deinvestigación ha contribuido de manera decisiva al estudio del sesgode publicación y la búsqueda de variables que influyen en la heterogeneidad,la existencia de discrepancia entre los estudios individuales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(5): 483-489, sept.-oct. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050496</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportaciones de la revisión sistemática y del metaanálisis a la salud pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31152</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
