<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162856</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors for mortality after surgery of osteoporotic hip fracture in patients over 65 years of age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate, from a clinical perspective, and with easily identifiable variables, those factors that influence the survival of patients admitted to a care unit designed for the comprehensive treatment of patients with hip fracture after being surgically treated. Material and methods. A prospective study was conducted on a cohort of patients (n=202) aged 65 years or older with a low impact hip fracture, who were surgically intervened in a tertiary hospital. An analysis was performed to determine mortality at 90 days, and at one and 2years after surgery using demographic, clinical, analytical, and functional variables. Results. The independent risk factors of mortality in the 3periods analysed were age (P=.047, P=.016, and P=.000 at 90 days, 1, and 2 years, respectively) and a low Barthel index (P=.014, P=.005, and P=.004 to 90 days, 1, and 2 years, respectively). Male sex (P=.004) and a high risk for anaesthesia (P=.011) were only independent risk factors of mortality at 2years after surgery. Discussion and conclusion. Age and dependency were the major determining factors of mortality at 30 days, 1, and 2 years after surgery for hip fracture. Both are easily measurable to identify patients susceptible to poor outcomes, and could benefit from a more thorough care plan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arnáez-Solis, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arteaga-Mazuelas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranguren-Ruiz, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jarne-Betrán, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas-Fernández de Tejerina, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acha-Arrieta, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar desde una perspectiva clínica y con variables fácilmente identificables aquellos factores que influyen en la supervivencia de los pacientes ingresados en una unidad asistencial diseñada para el tratamiento integral de pacientes con fractura de cadera, tras ser intervenidos quirúrgicamente. Material y método. Estudio prospectivo de una cohorte de pacientes (n=202) de edad igual o mayor de 65 años con fractura de cadera de bajo impacto, intervenidos quirúrgicamente en un hospital terciario, que analizó la mortalidad a 90 días, 1 y 2años tras la intervención con relación a variables demográficas, clínicas, analíticas y de funcionalidad. Resultados. Los factores de riesgo independientes de mortalidad en los 3periodos analizados fueron la edad (p=0,047; 0,016 y 0,000 a 90 días, 1 y 2 años, respectivamente) y el bajo índice de Barthel (p=0,014; 0,005 y 0,004 a 90 días, 1 y 2 años respectivamente). Sin embargo, el sexo masculino (p=004) y el riesgo para anestesia (p=0,011) resultaron ser solo factores de riesgo independientes de mortalidad a los 2años de la intervención quirúrgica. Discusión y conclusión. Tanto a corto plazo (30 días) como hasta los 2 años de la intervención quirúrgica por fractura de cadera los mayores condicionantes de mortalidad fueron la edad y la dependencia. Ambos son parámetros fácilmente medibles que permiten identificar a pacientes susceptibles de mala evolución desde el ingreso y que podrían beneficiarse de una atención más exhaustiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);61(3): 185-192, mayo-jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo de mortalidad tras intervención quirúrgica de fractura de cadera osteoporótica en pacientes mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
