<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165281</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical activity, self-esteem and social situation of the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This presentation examines some of the research carried out in southern Spain into the relationship between ongoing physical-sporting activity and the functional capacity of (non-institutionalised) elderly people, and their psycho-social profile, self-esteem and social situation. This was a joint study involving the Physical Education and Sports Department of the University of Seville, the Andalusia Centre for Development Biology at the Pablo de Olavide University-CSIC, CIBERER, the Carlos III Health Institute, and the Social Work and Social Policy Research Group (PAIDI Sej-452). Some of the data from the research has already been published. An experimental methodology was used to analyse a group of 8 physically-active subjects and a control group of 8 subjects with sedentary lifestyles. Using different scales, including VATAD and the Rosenberg scale, it is established that: Firstly, physical activity in the elderly correlates with higher levels of self-esteem. Secondly, physical activity in the elderly correlates with a better social situation. And thirdly, physical activity in the elderly correlates with a &#145;Healthy Old Age&#146; profile. The data also show us a better sociability and relationship with the environment, more community participation activities, more activities with friends, and more activities outside (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrera-Algarín, Evaristo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo recoge parte del estudio de investigación realizado en el Sur de España sobre la vinculación que la realización de actividad físico-deportiva continuada tenía sobre la capacidad funcional de personas mayores (no institucionalizadas), su perfil psicosocial, su autoestima, y su situación social. El estudio que se realizó de manera conjunta entre el Departamento de Educación Física y Deporte (Universidad de Sevilla), el Centro Andaluz de Biología del Desarrollo (Universidad Pablo de Olavide-CSIC), CIBERER, Instituto de Salud Carlos III, y grupo de Investigación en Trabajo Social y Político Social (PAIDI Sej-452), ya ha publicado datos parciales de la investigación. A partir de una metodología experimental se analizan un grupo (8 sujetos) que realizan actividad física, y otro grupo control (8 sujetos) con perfiles sedentarios. Utilizando diferentes escalas, incluyendo VATAD y Rosenberg, se establece que: En primer lugar, la actividad física en los ancianos se correlaciona con mayores niveles de autoestima. En segundo lugar, la actividad física en los ancianos se correlaciona con una mejor situación social. Y en tercer lugar, la actividad física en los ancianos se correlaciona con un perfil de «ancianidad saludable». Los datos también nos muestran una mejor sociabilidad y relación con el medio ambiente, más actividades de participación comunitaria, más actividades con amigos y más actividades al aire libre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.4): 10-16, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165281</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad física, autoestima y situación social en las personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54367^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
