<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144025</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic mesenteric ischemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic mesenteric ischemia (CMI) is a rare condition that presents with non-specific symptoms such as postprandial abdominal pain, fear of eating, weight loss and diarrhea. Untreated symptomatic patients progress to severe malnutrition, and death due to septic complications of acute mesenteric ischemia. The most common cause is atherosclerosis, although other causes have been described, such as fibromuscular dysplasia, trauma, dissection, ruptured mesenteric aneurysm, polyarteritis nodosa, and Takayasu's disease. The diagnosis of CMI is based on clinical suspicion and differential diagnosis of other causes of abdominal pain. Doppler ultrasound is the initial method of study for evaluation of arterial occlusive disease of the celiac trunk (CT) and superior mesenteric artery (SMA), with sensitivity and specificity greater than 80% by expert teams. Angiography is the definitive study to show the lesions and for surgical planning. Significant stenosis has been described in two mesenteric vessels in 91% of patients, and of three arteries in 55%. The computed tomography angiography has shown to be effective in describing the anatomy of the SMA and CT. In addition, it is useful to detect other abdominal conditions, extravascular compressive causes and monitoring of patency after open or endovascular surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Río Solá, ML del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Fajardo, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La isquemia mesentérica crónica (IMC) es una entidad poco frecuente. Se presenta con síntomas inespecíficos como dolor abdominal posprandial, miedo a comer, disminución de peso y diarrea. Los pacientes sintomáticos no tratados evolucionan hacia una desnutrición severa y muerte debido a las complicaciones sépticas de la isquemia mesentérica. La causa más frecuente es la aterosclerosis, aunque se han descrito otras causas como la displasia fibromuscular, traumatismos, disección, rotura de aneurisma mesentérico, poliarteritis nodosa y la enfermedad de Takayasu. El diagnóstico de IMC se basa en la sospecha clínica y el diagnóstico diferencial con otras causas de dolor abdominal. El ecodoppler es el estudio inicial de elección para la evaluación de la enfermedad arterial oclusiva del tronco celíaco (TC) y arteria mesentérica superior (AMS), con sensibilidad y especificidad superiores al 80% en equipos expertos. La arteriografía, sin embargo, es el estudio definitivo para detallar las lesiones y planificar la cirugía. Se ha descrito estenosis significativa en 2 vasos mesentéricos en el 91% de los pacientes y en 3 arterias en el 55%. La angiotomografía axial computarizada ha demostrado ser efectiva en describir la anatomía de los vasos digestivos. Además, es útil para detectar otras enfermedades abdominales, causas extravasculares compresivas y para el control de la permeabilidad después del tratamiento quirúrgico abierto o endovascular. Los objetivos del tratamiento son aliviar los síntomas de forma permanente, modificar los factores de riesgo cardiovascular, mejorar el estado nutricional y prevenir el infarto mesentérico, lo cual se logra mediante revascularización mesentérica (cirugía abierta o endovascular) y apoyo multidisciplinario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;67(6): 497-506, nov.-dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144025</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Isquemia mesentérica crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30893^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55562^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5488^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5488^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55562^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55562^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30893^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
