<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133880</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing diagnosis proposal for gender violence syndrome in nanda-i taxonomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gender-based violence is a widespread and muted problem in public health that particularly affects millions of women worldwide. The situation being relegated to the private sphere is difficult to know the exact number of women who suffer and causes much of the morbidity and the mortality of women. However, at some point in their lives women visit health services and health professionals, especially nursing, is supposed to be the first to detect cases of abuse. The need to include gender-based violence as a nursing diagnosis is evident because nursing diagnoses names health problems which nurses can approach independently. We have conducted a literature search in order to propose violence as nursing diagnosis to NANDA-I, in order to recognize that this is really a serious health problem and that nursing has an important role in detecting and monitoring of women victims of violence. The aim of this paper is to describe the development phases of «Gender Violence Syndrome» as a proposal for inclusion in the NANDA-I taxonomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almansa Martínez, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Martínez, Myriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antonio Flores, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas Martínez, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frapolli Gómez, Griselda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pina Roche, Florentina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La violencia de género es un problema de salud pública muy extendido y silenciado que afecta particularmente a millones de mujeres en todo el mundo. Al estar la situación relegada a la esfera privada, es difícil saber el número exacto de mujeres que la sufren y es causa de gran parte de la morbilidad y la mortalidad femeninas. Sin embargo, en algún momento de su vida la mujer visitará los servicios de salud, así que los profesionales de salud, especialmente los de enfermería, serán los que detecten primero los casos de maltrato. Dado que los diagnósticos de enfermería nombran los problemas de salud que las enfermeras pueden abordar de forma independiente, es evidente la necesidad de incluir la violencia de género como un diagnóstico enfermero. Hemos realizado una búsqueda en la literatura con el fin de proponer la violencia de género como diagnóstico enfermero a NANDA-I, de modo que se reconozca que esto es realmente un problema grave de salud y que la enfermería tiene un papel importante en la detección y el seguimiento de las mujeres víctimas de este tipo de violencia. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir las fases de desarrollo del «Síndrome de Violencia de Género» como propuesta para su inclusión en la taxonomía diagnóstica de NANDA-I (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(3): 28-32, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133880</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta del diagnóstico enfermero del síndrome de violencia de género para su inclusión en la taxonomía nanda-i</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32346^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
