<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105132</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Literature as a complementary educational resource in the teaching and learning of dermatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. To classify literary texts from a medical perspective facilitates their application in the teaching and learning of medicine and dermatology. Materials and methods. Qualitative analysis of multiple literary texts and selection of those texts that contain references to a common skin disease (acne), which was selected as a paradigm. Results. A classification was carried out of the literary texts analyzed, based on five groups: autobiography of the skin disease; the writer describing skin disease in others; skin disease as a stylistic device in literature; the physician as writer: stylistic devices in the medical description of the disease; and medical texts related to selected literary texts. Conclusions. The literary texts, from a medical perspective, can be classified into five groups; this classification facilitates their implementation as a didactic resource in medical education and specialised dermatology teaching (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-López, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Vigil, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gotor-Corrales, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La reflexión sobre los recursos literarios puede mejorar su aplicación como herramienta de aprendizaje para profesionales de la salud, tanto en contextos transversales como específicos de especialidad. Proponemos una novedosa clasificación de los recursos literarios, desde una perspectiva médica, con el objetivo de facilitar su aplicación en la ense-ñanza y aprendizaje de dermatología. Materiales y métodos. Análisis cualitativo de múltiples textos literarios y selección de aquellos textos que incluían referencias a una enfermedad cutánea frecuente (acné), que se seleccionó como paradigma. Resultados. Se realizó una clasificación basada en cinco grupos: autobiografía de la enfermedad cutánea, el escritor en la descripción de la enfermedad cutánea de otros, la enfermedad cutánea como recurso estilístico en la literatura, el médico como escritor: recursos estilísticos en la descripción médica de la enfermedad, y literatura médica relacionada con los textos seleccionados. Conclusiones. Los recursos literarios, desde una perspectiva médica, se pueden clasificar en cinco grupos; esta clasificación puede facilitar su aplicación docente y su integración como recurso didáctico en la enseñanza especializada de la dermatología y en la enseñanza médica en general. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);15(1): 31-36, mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La literatura como recurso didáctico complementario en la enseñanza y aprendizaje de la dermatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3900^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8684</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
