<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90469</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence, awareness, treatment and control of cardiovascular risk factors in the Extremadura population (Spain). HERMEX study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo estimate the prevalence, detection, treatment and degree of control of cardiovascular risk factors in Extremadura.DesignCross-sectional study.SettingPopulation study in Don Benito-Villanueva de la Serena health area (Badajoz).ParticipantsA random sample of the people between 25 and 79 years, who lived in this area, was selected.MethodsHistory of cardiovascular risk factors and its treatment were obtained by questionnaire. Blood pressure and blood sample were obtained for all participants. We calculated the prevalence of each variable standardized for age and gender for the population of Extremadura.ResultsOf the 3521 eligible, 2833 (80.5%) participants were included, mean age 51.2 years, male 46.5%. Adjusted prevalence of current smoking in men: 40.5% (37.8-43.2), hypertension 39.5% (37.3-41.7), hypercholesterolemia, 37.9% (35.4-40.4), obesity 36.5% (33.9-39.1), diabetes 13.7% (12.1-15.4). Adjusted prevalence of hypercholesterolemia in women: 35,0% (32.9-37.2), hypertension 33,0% (31.3-34.7), obesity 30.7% (28.6-32.8), current smoking 26,6% (24.5-28.7), diabetes 12,0% (10.5-13.5). The detection level of each factor was above 70%, and the degree of control among those treated of 51, 62.3 and 74.7% for hypertension, diabetes and hypercholesterolemia, respectively.ConclusionsExtremadura's population is highly exposed to major cardiovascular risk factors, especially men. Smoking, obesity and diabetes stand in the national context as the most prevalent in our community(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Bergés, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernando Pérez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Palacios, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Félix-Redondo, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaro, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoEstimar la prevalencia, detección, tratamiento y grado de control de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular en Extremadura.DiseñoEstudio observacional descriptivo transversal.EmplazamientoEstudio poblacional del área de salud Don Benito-Villanueva de la Serena (Badajoz).ParticipantesMuestra aleatoria de la población entre 25 y 79 años residentes en dicha área.MétodosSe encuestó sobre antecedentes de factores de riesgo y su tratamiento, se midió la presión arterial y se extrajo muestra sanguínea a todos los participantes. Se calculó las prevalencias de cada variable estandarizándose por edad y género, para la población extremeña.ResultadosDe los 3.521 elegibles participaron 2.833 (80,5%), edad media 51,2 años, género masculino 46,5%. Prevalencia ajustada en hombres de tabaquismo activo 40,5% (37,8-43,2), HTA 39,5% (37,3-41,7), hipercolesterolemia 37,9% (35,4-40,4), obesidad 36,5% (33,9-39,1), diabetes 13,7% (12,1-15,4). Prevalencia ajustada en mujeres de hipercolesterolemia 35,0% (32,9-37,2), HTA 33,0% (31,3-34,7), obesidad 30,7% (28,6-32,8), tabaquismo activo 26,6% (24,5-28,7), diabetes 12,0% (10,5-13,5). El grado de conocimiento global de la situación de riesgo fue superior al 70% para cada factor y el grado de control entre los tratados con fármacos del 51,0, 62,3 y 74,7% para HTA, diabetes e hipercolesterolemia respectivamente.ConclusionesLa población extremeña está muy expuesta a los factores de riesgo principales, sobre todo en hombres. Tabaquismo, obesidad y diabetes destacan, dentro del contexto nacional, como los de mayor prevalencia en esta comunidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;43(8): 426-434, ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90469</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia, detección, tratamiento y grado de control de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular en la población de Extremadura (España). Estudio HERMEX</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
