<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050465</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intravenous immunoglobulin therapy: ELISA measurement of antidesmogleins 1 and 3 in three patients with pemphigus vulgaris</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intravenous immunoglobulin therapy (IVIg) has been used in the treatment of autoimmune bullous diseases unresponsive to conventional therapy in recent years. The action mechanism, which is not well known, suggests a wide spectrum of immunoregulation. In the last five years, several studies on patients with unresponsive pemphigus vulgaris with a clinical and serological outcome after IVIg administration in 80%-90% of cases have been published. We report the case of  3 patients with pemphigus vulgaris in whom we measured autoantibody titers to desmoglein 3 and 1 during 8 months. In spite of the clinical improvement, no significant decrease in antibody concentration was observed. Therapy with IVIg, although it has clinical benefit, did not decrease antibody values in our patients and thus it may need to be combined with immunosuppressant that inhibit pathogen antibody production</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Longo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avilés, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Mahou, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia con inmunoglobulinas intravenosas (IgIV) es utilizada en los últimos años en pacientes con enfermedades ampollosas autoinmunes resistentes a la terapia convencional. Su mecanismo de acción, no bien conocido, supone un amplio espectro de inmunorregulación. En los últimos 5 años se han publicado varios trabajos en pacientes con pénfigo vulgar resistente con un beneficio clínico y serológico en el 80%-90% de los casos. Presentamos 3 casos de pénfigo vulgar con determinación seriada mediante la técnica de ELISA de anticuerpos antidesmogleína 1 y 3 (AcDsG1 y AcDsG3) durante un período de 8 meses en los que, a pesar de la mejoría clínica, no se objetivó disminución significativa en la concentración de anticuerpos. La terapia con IgIV, aun con beneficio clínico, no disminuyó en nuestros pacientes las cifras de anticuerpos y por ello debería quizá combinarse con inmunosupresores que inhiban la producción de anticuerpos patógenos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;206(10): 499-503, nov. 2006. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050465</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia con inmunoglobulinas intravenosas: medición seriada mediante ELISA de anticuerpos antidesmogleína 1 y 3 en tres pacientes con pénfigo vulgar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1329^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29503^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29503^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30039^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
