<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047418</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis by confocal and direct optical micrometry of chitosan in cultivated osteoblasts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. Chitosan is a potentially useful materialfor the transportation, fixation and development ofosteoblasts. OBJECTIVES. To analize the structure and distributionof pores in chitosan-based materials in order tojustify the selection of structurally compatible materialswith the transportation, fixation and development of osteoblasts.human cells carrier human cells carrier RESULTS.It has been shown the dependency of the pore sizewith the chitosan and, also, it is seen a possible graphicmodel of structural distribution of pores that justifies thecompatibility of the micrometrical results with those measuredby mercury vapor diffusion</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piedra, C. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cáceres, D. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabeu, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicario, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Brea, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larena, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarzábal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. El quitosano es un material potencialmenteútil en el transporte, fijación y desarrollo de osteoblastosOBJETIVOS. Analizar la estructura y distribuciónde poros en materiales con base quitosano parajustificar la selección de materiales estructuralmente compatiblescon el transporte, fijación y desarrollo de osteoblastos.RESULTADOS. Se pone de manifiesto la dependenciadel tamaño de poro con el contenido de quitosanoy, también se induce un posible modelo gráfico de distribuciónestructural de los poros que justifica la compatibilidadde los resultados micrométricos con los de medida dela porosidad por difusión de vapor de mercurio</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;3(2): 144-151, abr.-jun. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047418</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis por micrometría óptica directa y confocal de quitosano en medio de cultivo de osteoblastos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2732^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32333^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19241^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29085</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32146^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10184^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
