<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30891</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical characterisation and power simulations to detect genetic linkage in attention deficit hyperactivity disorder in antioquian families</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is a neurobehavioural disorder whose essential characteristic is a persistent pattern of inattention or hyperactivity and impulsiveness. Recent studies into prevalence carried out on the Antioquian population by our group found an overall prevalence of 15.8%, which confirms ADHD as one of the most frequent problems in infancy. The cause of this disorder is still not altogether clear; familial aggregation of ADHD points towards a genetic component. Although to date no model of inheritance has been defined, its high prevalence rate, the difficulties involved in its diagnosis and its effects on the cognitive functions, as well as the social and educational repercussions, make this disorder a problem in children&#146;s public health. Aims. Our aim was to carry out power simulations to detect genetic linkage. Patients and methods. The Slink programme, which is part of Linkage package, was used in six families from the city of Medellín-Antioquia, which is a region where a founding effect is likely to have taken place; this makes it a strategic zone for genetic linkage studies in complex diseases such as ADHD. Results. Assuming the population to be homogenous, the lod score (Z) is greater than 3 (Z &gt; 3) and individual lod score values of between 0 and 6 were obtained for each family. Conclusions. In this paper we discuss the benefits of having multigenerational families, in Antioquia, to conduct gene mapping studies and we examine the different strategies to be developed with the findings reported here (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad (TDAH) es un trastorno neurocomportamental cuya característica esencial es un patrón persistente de inatención o hiperactividad e impulsividad. En algunos estudios recientes sobre prevalencia realizados por nuestro grupo en la población antioqueña se ha encontrado una prevalencia total del 15,8 por ciento; esto confirma al TDAH como uno de los problemas más frecuentes en la infancia. La causa del trastorno todavía no se ha esclarecido; la agregación familiar del TDAH sugiere un componente genético; aunque todavía no se ha definido un modelo de herencia, su alta prevalencia, sus dificultades en el diagnóstico y sus efectos en las funciones cognitivas, sociales y escolares, convierten a este trastorno en un problema de salud pública infantil. Objetivos. Realizar las simulaciones de poder para detectar ligamiento genético. Pacientes y métodos. Se empleó el programa Slink del paquete Linkage, en seis familias de la ciudad de Medellín-Antioquia, en cuya zona, probablemente, ocurrió un efecto fundador; ello la ubica como una zona estratégica para estudios de ligamiento genético en enfermedades complejas, como el TDAH Resultados. El lod score(Z), asumiendo la homogeneidad de la población, es mayor de 3 (Z &gt; 3), y se obtienen valores individuales por familia que oscilan entre 0 y 6. Conclusiones. En este estudio se discuten los beneficios de tener familias multigeneracionales en Antioquia, para realizar estudios de cartografiado de genes, y se examinan las diferentes estrategias que se deberían desarrollar a partir de los hallazgos aquí presentados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(4): 319-322, feb. 2004. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización clínica y simulaciones de poder para ligamiento genético en el trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad en familias antioqueñas</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Rivas, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuartas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bedoya, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrizosa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cornejo, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Uribe, LF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30891</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9147</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8215</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
