<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78256</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rotator cuff calcifying tendonitis: results of arthroscopic treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To analyze the results of arthroscopic treatment of calcifying tendonitis of the shoulder. Materials and Methods: This study analyzes 18 cases of calcifying tendonitis treated between 1999 and 2006 with a mean follow-up of 6 months; mean patient age was 46 years. The Constant scale was used to assess shoulder function; the patients&#146; satisfaction with the final result of surgery was also evaluated. Pre- and post-operative radiographs were compared. Results: In 88.8% of patients an acromioplasty was added to the main procedure, and in 3 cases the tendinous lesion caused when resecting the calcified area was sutured. Mean pre- and postoperative Constant scores were 63.66 and 97.6 respectively. The calcification was absent from postoperative X-rays in 16 patients; a certain amount of calcification persisted in 2 cases. Statistically significant differences were observed in the Constant score before and after the procedure (p&lt;0,001). No significant relation was found between performing or failing to perform an acromioplasty, type and size of calcifications, persistence of calcium deposits and using or failing to use sutures and the final result. 100% of patients were satisfied with the result of surgery. Conclusions: Arthroscopic resection in calcifying tendonitis has a very high success rate, with high levels of patient satisfaction. No significant relationship was found between cases with residual post-operative calcium deposits and a poorer final result, although it would seem logical to try and remove calcification as thoroughly as possible without causing excessive damage to the tendon (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrera Cadenas, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campa Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallina García-Prendes, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar los resultados del tratamiento artroscópico de las tendinitis calcificantes del hombro. Material y métodos: Se analizaron de forma retrospectiva 18 tendinitis calcificantes tratadas entre 1999 y 2006 con un tiempo de seguimiento mínimo de 6 meses y una edad media de 46 años. Se evaluó la función del hombro mediante la escala de Constant y la satisfacción del paciente con el resultado final de la cirugía. Se realizó un examen comparativo radiológico preoperatorio y postoperatorio. Resultados: En el 88,8% de los casos se asoció la realización de la acromioplastia y en 3 ocasiones una sutura de la lesión tendinosa producida tras la resección de la calcificación. El resultado del test de Constant medio preoperatorio fue de 63,66 y el postoperatorio de 97,6. En la radiología postoperatoria la calcificación estaba ausente en 16 pacientes y se evidenciaban restos de la calcificación en 2 casos. Se observaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre la puntuación de Constant antes y después de la intervención (p&lt;0,001). No se encontró asociación significativa entre la realización o no de acromioplastia, el tipo y tamaño de la calcificación, los restos de depósito cálcico y la realización o no de sutura y el resultado final. El 100% de los pacientes se halló contento con el resultado de la cirugía. Conclusiones: La resección artroscópica en las tendinitis calcificantes tiene una tasa de éxito muy elevada, con una satisfacción muy importante por parte del paciente. No se ha encontrado una relación significativa entre aquellos casos con depósito cálcico residual y un peor resultado final, si bien parece lógico intentar eliminar la mayor cantidad posible de calcificación, sin dañar en exceso el tendón (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(2): 100-105, mar.-abr. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados del tratamiento artroscópico de las tendinitis calcificantes del manguito de los rotadores del hombro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1189^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
