<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93439</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Using of WHO guidelines for the management of severe malnutrition to cases of marasmus and kwashiorkor in a Colombia children's hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In 2007, the Hospital Infantil Los Ángeles (HILA) in Colombia implemented a slightly-modified version of the WHO guidelines for the diagnosis and management of malnutrition during childhood. Objective: To evaluate the efficacy of the WHO-HILA protocol in children hospitalized with severe, chronic marasmus and kwashiorkor malnutrition (MS-KWK) in 2007 and 2008. Material and methods: In this descriptive retrospective study the records of 100 children hospitalized with MSKWK were initially evaluated. Of these, 30 fulfilled the inclusion criteria: children of both sexes with a primary diagnosis of MS-KWK. Patients with any chronic disease liable to cause malnutrition were excluded. Anthropometric parameters, clinical signs and biochemical indicators of malnutrition were assessed upon admission and again at discharge following application of the WHO guidelines. Univariate analysis was performed for each study variable; serum hemoglobin and albumin levels on admission and at discharge were compared, and data were subjected to bivariate analysis. Results: Marasmus was diagnosed in 23.3% of children, kwashiorkor in 73.3% and marasmic kwashiorkor in 3.3%. The major clinical findings were: edema (70%), emaciation (40%), "flag sign" hair (42.86%), low serum albumin (93%) and anemia (80%). Thirteen children following the WHO-HILA protocol showed a significant nutritional status improvement (p &lt; 0.05), whereas no improvement was noted in the 17 children not treated according to the protocol.Conclusions: Application of the WHO-HILA protocol was associated with reduced morbimortality in children with marasmus-kwashiorkor malnutrition. Implementation of this protocol should therefore be considered in all children´s hospitals in countries where this disease is prevalent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Campos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Patino, CA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Prada, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Navero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En 2007, el Hospital Infantil de Los Ángeles (HILA) en Colombia implementó una versión del protocolo-OMS para el diagnóstico y tratamiento de la malnutrición en la infancia. Objetivo: Evaluar la aplicación del protocolo de la OMS-HILA en niños hospitalizados con marasmo y/o kwashiorkor (MS-KWK) durante 2007-2008. Material y métodos: En este estudio retrospectivo, se evaluaron 100 niños hospitalizados con MS-KWK; 30 cumplieron los criterios de inclusión: niños de ambos sexos con MS-KWK primario. Los pacientes con enfermedades crónicas que pudieran causar desnutrición fueron excluidos. Se evaluaron determinados parámetros antropométricos, y signos clínicos y bioquímicos de desnutrición según el protocolo de la OMS, al ingreso y al alta. Se realizó un análisis univariante; los niveles de hemoglobina y albúmina séricas fueron comparados al ingreso y al alta, y los datos fueron sometidos a análisis de dos variables. Resultados: Se diagnosticaron de marasmo al 23,3% de los niños, de kwashiorkor al 73,3% y de kwashiorkor marásmico al 3,3%. Los hallazgos clínicos más importantes fueron: edema (70%), emaciación (40%), "signo de bandera" (42,86%), albúmina baja (93%) y anemia (80%). Trece niños mostraron mejoría significativa del estado nutricional tras aplicar el protocolo OMS-HILA (p &lt; 0,05), mientras que no ocurrió en 17 niños no tratados según el protocolo. Conclusiones: La aplicación del protocolo de la OMSHILA se asoció con una reducción de la morbimortalidad en los niños con desnutrición marasmo-kwashiorkor. La aplicación completa y continuada de este protocolo debe ser considerada en los hospitales infantiles de todos los países donde esta enfermedad es prevalente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(5): 977-983, sept.-oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93439</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación del protocolo de la OMS de malnutrición marasmo-kwashiorkor en un hospital de Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24212^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30409^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24223^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
