<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107048</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Encoding, recording and analysis of the action of success in soccer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents the creation of an observation tool for encoding, recording and analysis of successful actions in soccer. Through the instrument we propose a system of ad hoc constructed category, we performed semi-registers with the software Match Vision Studio (Castellano, Perea and Alday, 2006) using a sample of 688 goals scored by FC Barcelona's National League Fútbol Profesional (LFP). Subsequently, there have been different data analysis entity most notably the significant differences between the categories underlying criterion Last Action Zone (Zuá) and the criteria Goals Scored (GF) and Area Auction (ZR) in addition to the significant interaction between criteria and ZR Zuá (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oliva-Millán, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Villaseñor, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio presenta la creación de un instrumento de observación para la codificación, el registro y el análisis de acciones de éxito en fútbol. A través del instrumento que proponemos, un sistema de categoría construido ad hoc, hemos realizado registros semiautomáticos con el software Match Vision Studio (Castellano, Perea y Alday, 2006) usando una muestra de 688 goles marcados por el FC Barcelona de la Liga Nacional de Fútbol Profesional (LFP). Posteriormente, se han realizado distintos análisis de datos ente los que cabe destacar las diferencias significativas que existen entre las categorías que subyacen al criterio de Zona de Última Acción (ZUA), así como entre los criterios Goles a Favor (GF) y Zona de Remate (ZR) además de la interacción significativa entre los criterios ZUA y ZR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;11(2,supl): 97-103, ene.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107048</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Codificación, registro y análisis de la acción de éxito en fútbol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3194</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
