<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163655</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validity Study of Catalan, Galician and Basque Language Versions of the COPD Assessment Test and Equivalence With the Spanish Version</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To assess the linguistic equivalence of the COPD Assessment Test versions in Catalan (CAT-C), Galician (CAT-G) and Basque (CAT-V) with the validated Spanish version (CAT) in COPD patients able to use both official languages. Methods: Study performed in primary care centers in Catalonia, Galicia and the Basque Country. Half of the patients completed the questionnaire in their local language followed by the CAT in Spanish, while the other half did so in reverse order. Results: 151 COPD patients were included in the study, with a mean age of 69.0 (SD: 9.7) years. Most (79.5%) were men, 11.3% were educated up touniversity level, and 31.8% were current smokers. Mean FEV1 was 61.4% (SD: 16.8) predicted and 83.9% of patients were GOLD grade I or II. Concordance between CAT-C, CAT-G and CAT-V and CAT was high, with differences between scores from 0.4 to-0.5. Reliability (Cronbach's alpha) ranged from 0.72 to 0.86. Convergent validity, when correlated with the Medical Research Council Dyspnea scale (P =.003) and Saint George's Respiratory Questionnaire (ICC, r = 0.74) scores, was significant. Conclusions: CAT-C, CAT-G and CAT-V scores were similar to CAT scores, with high correlation and concordance. These results show the equivalence between the validated Spanish CAT and the versionin other languages, so CAT-C, CAT-G and CAT-V can be used in individuals whose main language is Catalan, Galician or Basque (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Losa, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agustí, Alvar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Villar, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capelastegui, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar la equivalencia lingüística de las versiones del cuestionario COPD Assessment Test en catalán (CAT-C), gallego (CAT-G) y vasco (CAT-V) con la versión en castellano (CAT) en pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica que hablan indistintamente las 2 lenguas cooficiales. Métodos: Estudio realizado en centros de atención primaria de Cataluña, Galicia y País Vasco. La mitad de los pacientes completó primero el CAT en castellano seguido del CAT en la lengua correspondiente de este estudio; la otra mitad lo hizo en orden inverso. Resultados: Se incluyó a 151 pacientes con edad media (DE) de 69,0 (9,7) años. Un 79,5% eran hombres, el 11,3% tenía estudios universitarios y el 31,8% eran fumadores. El valor medio (DE) de la FEV1 fue del 61,4% (16,8) del valor de referencia. La mayoría de pacientes (83,9%) tenía un grado GOLD I/II de limitación al flujo aéreo. La concordancia entre las puntuaciones de las diferentes versiones del CAT fue alta, con diferencias entre 0,4 y -0,5 puntos. Su fiabilidad (Cronbach) fue de 0,72-0,86. La validez convergente al correlacionar con el nivel de disnea de la escala Medical Research Council Dyspnea scale (p = 0,003) y con el Saint George's Respiratory Questionnaire (ICC, r = 0,74) fue significativa. Conclusiones: Las puntuaciones obtenidas con CAT-C, CAT-G y CAT-V fueron similares a las de CAT, con una alta correlación y concordancia entre ellas. Estos resultados muestran la equivalencia entre las versiones de CAT en diferentes lenguas e indican que este cuestionario puede ser utilizado indistintamente en pacientes cuya lengua principal sea catalán, gallego o vasco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;53(6): 311-317, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la validez de las versiones en catalán, gallego y vasco del cuestionario COPD assessment test y equivalencia con la versión en castellano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
