<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155436</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-randomised trial of an educational intervention based on cognitive-behavioural principles for patients with chronic low back pain attended in Primary Care Physiotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the influence of an educational intervention in reducing «fear-avoidance» (FA) and «pain catastrophising» (CAT) in a population with unspecific chronic low back pain (UCLBP), attending physiotherapy in Primary Health Care. A pragmatic quasi-experimental study was conducted in Health Centres of a Costa del Sol Health District. Design: Quasi-experimental study. Setting: Primary Health Care physiotherapy Back Schools in Health Centres of a Costa del Sol Health District. Participants: The selection criteria were: UCLBP; 18-65 years; understanding of the Spanish language; absence of parallel educational interventions; absence of red flags; not showing cognitive impairment or fibromyalgia; absence of thoracic-lumbar surgery, and exercise tolerance. Interventions: The control group received the usual Back Schools program. The experimental group also received a written document for home reading, plus the subsequent sharing, clarifying doubts, and beliefs and goals restructuring during the development of the sessions. Both interventions lasted about 280 minutes (7 sessions × 40min). Results: The main variables included FA and CAT. Pain and disability were also assessed. Some «demographic» and «related disorder» variables were considered in the analysis. Statistically significant differences were observed in the experimental group versus control, in the variation of FA &amp;#8722;14 (&amp;#8722;25.5; 0) vs &amp;#8722;4 (&amp;#8722;13; 0) (P=.009), and CAT &amp;#8722;9 (&amp;#8722;18; &amp;#8722;4) vs &amp;#8722;4,5 (&amp;#8722;8.25; 0) (P=.000), were observed. Also differences in disability (P=.046), but not in pain (P=.280). Conclusions: These results should be considered in light of possible limits imposed by the study. Its pragmatic nature would allow a potential transfer to usual care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rondón Ramos, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clavero Cano, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Cerrillo, Juan Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez González, Rita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la influencia de una intervención educativa en la reducción del «miedo-evitación» (ME) y del «catastrofismo al dolor» (CAT) en población con lumbalgia crónica inespecífica (LCI) atendida en fisioterapia de atención primaria (AP). Diseño: Estudio cuasiexperimental. Emplazamiento: Centros de salud (CS) del Distrito Sanitario Costa del Sol. Participantes: Pacientes con LCI entre 18-65 años con comprensión del idioma español; ausencia de intervenciones educativas paralelas; ausencia de banderas rojas; ausencia de deterioro cognitivo y/o fibromialgia; ausencia de cirugía dorsolumbar, y tolerancia al ejercicio físico. Intervenciones: El grupo control recibió la EdE grupal habitual. El experimental recibió, además, un instrumento escrito para lectura domiciliaria, más la posterior puesta en común, aclaración de dudas y reestructuración de creencias y metas durante el desarrollo de las sesiones. Ambas intervenciones duraron unos 280 min (7 sesiones de 40 min). Resultados: Las variables principales incluyeron ME y CAT. Secundariamente se valoraron dolor y discapacidad. Algunas variables «sociodemográficas» y «relacionadas con el trastorno» fueron tenidas en cuenta en el análisis. Se observaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el grupo experimental versus control en la variación del ME &amp;#8722;14 (&amp;#8722;25,5; 0) vs &amp;#8722;4 (&amp;#8722;13; 0) (p=0,009), y del CAT &amp;#8722;9 (&amp;#8722;18; &amp;#8722;4) vs &amp;#8722;4,5 (&amp;#8722;8,25; 0) (p=0,000). Igualmente se observaron diferencias en discapacidad (p=0,046), pero no en dolor (p=0,280). Conclusiones: Los resultados deben ser considerados a la luz de las posibles limitaciones que plantea el estudio. Su naturaleza pragmática permitiría una potencial transferencia a la dinámica asistencial habitual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;48(7): 440-448, ago.-sept. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ensayo no aleatorizado de una intervención educativa basada en principios cognitivo-conductuales para pacientes con lumbalgia crónica inespecífica atendidos en fisioterapia de atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54294^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3104</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54294^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
