<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101811</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation long term of lymphadenectom y relevance in the surgery of gastric cancer prognosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION AND AIMS. The type of lymphadenectomy in the surgery of gastric cancer is not clearly defined. Our aim was to evaluate long term prognosis of patients with gastric cancer who underwent curative surgery and the influence of the type of lymphadenectomy. MATERIAL AND METHODS. We performed a retrospective study with prospective phases of 454 patients who underwent surgery for gastric adenocarcinoma to analyze the influence of type II  lymphadenectomy in gastric cancersurvival in patients treated with curative intention. RESULTS. A total of 454 patients, 264 men and 190 women, averaging 70 years of age. It held 45.2% of subtotal gastrectomy. 35.3% of total gastrectomy and 19.6% palliative surgery. In curative surgery group, 65.3% were type II  lymphadenectomyand 34.7% lymphadenectomy type I. In the logistic regression analysis type II lymphadenectomy acted as a protective factor 0.3 (0.1 to 0.750), similar results if applied Cox regression 0.5 (0.4-0.8). Sex, age, stage III and IV, the location and number of infiltrated lymph nodes behaved as a prognostic factors in gastric cancer. Overall survival of patients treated with curativesurgery was 34% at 5 years and 23% at 10 years. CONCLUSIONS. The prognosis of gastric cancer remains a very poor today. Overall survival at 5 years exceeds one third of thepatients operated with curative intent. Lymphadenectomy type II behaves as an independent factor which improves long-termsurvival (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santaclara, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diago, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muinelo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Minelo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN Y OBJETIVOS. El tipo de linfadenectomía en la cirugía curativa del cácer gástrico sigue siendo tema de controversia.Nuestro objetivo fue analizar la influencia del tipo de linfadenectomía en la supervivencia a largo plazo en los pacientescon cáncer gástrico, sometidos a cirugía con intención curativa. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS. Se realiza un estudio retrospectivo, con fases de prospectivo sobre 454 pacientes sometidos a cirugía por adenocarcinoma gástrico para analizar la influencia de la linfadenectomía tipo II en la supervivencia de los pacientes tratados con intención curativa. RESULTADOS. Se incluyeron 454 pacientes, 264 varones y 190 mujeres, con una edad media de 70 años. Se llevaron a cabo un 45,2% de gastrectomías subtotales, 35,3% de gastrectomías totales y un 19,6% cirugía paliativa. Del grupo de cirugía curativa, se realizaron un 65,3% de linfadenectomía tipo II y un 34,7% de linfadenectomía tipo I. En el análisis de regresiónlogística la linfadenectomía tipo II se comportó como un factor protector 0,3 (0,1-0,750), resultado similar si se aplica la regresión de Cox 0,5 (0,4-0,8). El sexo, la edad, los estadios III y IV, la localización y el número de adenopatías infiltradas se comportaron como factores de mal pronóstico en el cáncer gástrico. La supervivencia global de los pacientes tratados concirugía curativa fue de 34% a 5 años y 23% a 10 años. CONCLUSIONES. El pronóstico del cáncer gástrico sigue siendo a día de hoy bastante pobre. La supervivencia global a los 5años supera ligeramente el tercio de los pacientes intervenidos con intención curativa. La linfadenectomía tipo II se comportacomo un factor independiente que mejora la supervivencia a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;15(2): 64-70, abr.-jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101811</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la linfadenectomía tipo II en la supervivencia a largo plazo del cáncer gástrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
