<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118818</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-5434</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Technological quality traits and volatile compounds of Andean alpaca (Vicugna pacos) charqui freshly prepared and after five months of storage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Selected technological quality traits (pH, water holding capacity, yield, colour and oxidative stability), and headspace volatile compounds in alpaca Andean charqui have been assessed. The determinations were carried out in both, fresh charqui and stored charqui (for 5 months at 15 ºC, packaged with a moisture impermeable and high oxygen permeability film). A total of thirty shredded charqui samples made from alpaca legs elaborated by thirty different producers from the Puno region in Peru were analysed. Stored charqui showed significantly higher values if total solids losses during hydration, pH, thiobarbituric acid substances and colour parameters than the fresh charqui. In addition, a decrease in most of the volatile compounds of headspace was detected after storage, which could be responsible for flavour time-related changes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvá-Ruiz, B. K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Delgado, D. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Diez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se han determinado los valores de diversos parámetros de interés tecnológico (pH, capacidad de retención de agua, rendimiento, color, estabilidad oxidativa), así como el contenido de compuestos volátiles en el espacio de cabeza en el charqui andino de alpaca recién elaborado y el producto después de 5 meses de almacenamiento a 15 ºC, protegido con película impermeable al vapor de agua y de alta permeabilidad al oxígeno. Para el estudio se utilizaron 30 muestras de charqui de pierna de alpaca deshilachado procedente de 30 elaboradores de la región de Puno en Perú. Después del almacenamiento se observaron incrementos significativos en las pérdidas de sólidos durante la hidratación, el pH, las sustancias reactivas al ácido tiobarbitúrico y el color, respecto al producto recién elaborado. También se observó una disminución en el contenido en compuestos volátiles en el espacio de cabeza, que podría afectar de forma notoria al sabor del charqui (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. vet. Murcia;28: 97-109, ene.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades tecnológicas y compuestos volátiles del charqui andino de alpaca (Vicugna pacos) recién elaborado y después de cinco meses de almacenamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5658^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22585^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8631^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22373</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
