<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040721</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients&#146; rights: a question of quality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients' rights first arose as a question of quality from the perspective of users themselves in the United States, a cultural environment that differs from our own. This contextual difference led to difficulties in implementing and understanding patients' rights in Spain. Patients' rights are the specification of human rights in the management of the patient's own body and are one more human right. The most salient right concerns informed consent. This right has been, and continues to be, difficult to implement and is usually understood as a formal goal of certain documentation rather than as a demand for quality (of process). Possible future developments may involve concrete guidelines on the right to die (euthanasia, assisted suicide), as well as specification of the benefits of the public health system</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernando, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los derechos de los pacientes nacen como una cuestión de calidad desde la perspectiva de los propios usuarios en Estados Unidos, un entorno cultural que no es el nuestro. Esta diferencia contextual marcó dificultades en la implantación y comprensión de los derechos de los pacientes en nuestro país. Los derechos de los pacientes son la especificación de los derechos humanos en el ámbito de la gestión del propio cuerpo y se convierten en un derecho humano más. Un derecho que destaca por encima de los demás es el del consentimiento informado. La evolución de este derecho ha tenido y tiene dificultades en su implantación y se suele entender más como una finalidad formal de determinada documentación que como una exigencia de calidad (de proceso). Una evolución posible cabe pensarla en la concreción del derecho a una muerte digna (eutanasia, suicidio asistido) así como en la especificación de las prestaciones del sistema público de salud</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;20(6): 353-356, sep. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040721</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los derechos de los pacientes: una cuestión de calidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
