<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131363</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Should the diagnostic and therapeutic protocols for adrenal incidentalomas be changed?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background The prevalence of adrenal incidentalomas is increasing with the aging of the population and the use of high resolution imaging technics. Current protocols propose a comprehensive monitoring of their functional and morphological state, but with no conclusive clinical evidence that endorses it. Method Retrospective study of 96 patients diagnosed with adrenal incidentaloma between 2008 and 2012. We evaluated clinical, functional and imaging at baseline and during follow-up. Results Initially, 9 cases were surgically removed: 4 due to hyperfunction (2 Cushing syndromes and 2 pheochromocytomas) and 5 due to size larger than 4 cm. During follow-up one case of pheochromocytoma was diagnosed and another grew more than 1 cm, needing surgery. In 98.86% of nonfunctional and benign lesions, there was no functional and/or morphological changes in the final evaluation. Conclusions The results of our study challenge the validity of current diagnostic-therapeutic protocols of incidentalomas, which should be reassessed in prospective studies taking into account efficiency characteristics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mateo-Gavira, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Tinoco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Diosdado, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilchez-López, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrán-Escandón, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda-Schuldt, María Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes La prevalencia de los incidentalomas suprarrenales está aumentando por el envejecimiento de la población y el empleo de técnicas de imagen de alta resolución. Los protocolos actuales proponen un seguimiento de su estado funcional y morfológico exhaustivos, sin una evidencia clínica concluyente que lo avale Método Estudio retrospectivo de 96 pacientes diagnosticados de incidentaloma adrenal entre 2008 y 2012. Se evalúan características clínicas, funcionales y de imagen, basales y durante el seguimiento. Resultados Inicialmente, 4 casos fueron intervenidos por hiperfunción (2 síndromes de Cushing y 2 feocromocitomas) y 5 por tamaño superior a 4 cm. Durante el seguimiento, tan solo se diagnosticó un caso de feocromocitoma y otro creció más de 1 cm, indicándose cirugía. En el 98,86% de los incidentalomas diagnosticados inicialmente como benignos y no funcionantes, no se objetivaron modificaciones funcionales y/o morfológicas en la evaluación final. Conclusiones Los resultados de nuestra serie cuestionan la validez de los protocolos de seguimiento de los incidentalomas adrenales vigentes en la actualidad, que deberían ser revaluados atendiendo a características de eficiencia mediante estudios prospectivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(1): 30-33, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131363</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Deberían modificarse los protocolos diagnóstico-terapéuticos de los incidentalomas suprarrenales?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d313^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d318^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3500^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
