<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044828</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Skin lesions from the application of suction cups for therapeutic purposes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The application of suction cups or cupping is a medicinal practice that is very widespread in Asian countries. The presence of circular areas of erythema, ecchymosis or blood blisters symmetrically distributed on the shoulders, back, thorax or lumbar area should suggest the use of this technique. The number of followers of traditional Chinese medicine is increasing in the Western world, so we should be familiar with these practices in order to prevent social and/or legal conflicts that may arise from mistaken diagnoses of abuse.         We present the case of a 65-year-old male with multiple circular, erythematous, bullous lesions, symmetrically distributed, which occurred after the application of suction cups in the context of polymyalgia rheumatica</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Belinchón, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betlloch, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bañuls, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mataix, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aplicación de ventosas o cupping es una práctica medicinal muy extendida en los países orientales. La presencia de áreas circulares de eritema, equimosis o ampollas de contenido hemático distribuidas de manera simétrica en hombros, espalda, tórax o área lumbar deben sugerir la utilización de esta técnica. Los seguidores de la medicina tradicional china están aumentando en el mundo occidental, por lo que debemos conocer estas prácticas para prevenir conflictos sociales y/o legales que pueden provenir de diagnósticos erróneos de malos tratos.         Presentamos el caso de un varón de 65 años con múltiples lesiones circulares, eritematosas y ampollosas, de distribución simétrica, producidas tras la aplicación de ventosas en el contexto de una polimialgia reumática</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;97(3): 212-214, abr. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044828</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones cutáneas por aplicación de ventosas con fines terapéuticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8686</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24507^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36318</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30694^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30507^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30507^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24507^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4502^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4502^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29286^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30694^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30694^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29286^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4977^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
