<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154854</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-2345</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the microstructure of femoral patients with hip osteoarthritis and hip fracture by microCT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Whereas bone mineral density (BMD) is characteristically low in osteoporosis, it has been postulated that in osteoarthritis BMD is increased. We aimed to check this concept by analyzing bone volumen and structure in the femoral heads of patients with hip fractures (n=10) and with hip osteoarthritis (n=9). Unexpectedly, the analysis of microstructural parameters by microCT did not reveal significant differences between both groups. In addition, we did not find a significant decline in the trabecular bone volume across the age range studied. These results suggest that the evolution of the trabecular bone of the femoral head is different from the age-related decrease of bone mass in other regions of the skeleton. Elucidating the mechanism involved could suggest new approaches to treat the bone loss associated with aging (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riancho, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Solana, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreño Blanco, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado del Prado, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ibarbia, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sainz-Aja Guerra, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Núñez, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disminución de la densidad mineral ósea (DMO), es decir, del volumen de tejido óseo por unidad de volumen del esqueleto, es característica de la osteoporosis, mientras que se ha sugerido que la artrosis se acompaña de un aumento de la DMO a nivel local y sistémico. Para comprobar esta hipótesis analizamos mediante microTAC el hueso trabecular de la cabeza femoral de 10 pacientes con fractura de cadera y 9 con coxartrosis. El análisis no reveló diferencias significativas entre ambos grupos en el volumen de tejido óseo trabecular, ni en los demás parámetros estructurales analizados. Tampoco se encontró una caída significativa del volumen de hueso trabecular con la edad. Esto indica que el hueso de esta región tiene una evolución peculiar. Los mecanismos responsables de ese comportamiento son desconocidos, pero su esclarecimiento podría, quizás, abrir la puerta a nuevos abordajes en el tratamiento de la pérdida de hueso asociada al envejecimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. osteoporos. metab. miner. (Internet);8(2): 75-81, abr.-jun. 2016. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la microestructura femoral de pacientes con coxartrosis y con fractura de cadera mediante micro-TAC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5373^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5373^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
