<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125036</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of locally aggressive and malignant tumors of the proximal third of the fibula. Oncology results and functional evaluation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Proximal fibula malignant and locally aggressive benign bone tumors are uncommon and usually treat by surgery. Bloc resection of the knee can compromise knee stability due to of the resection of the posterolateral ligament complex. Material and methods. We analyzed 28 consecutive patients treated for a proximal fibula bone tumor between 1980 and 2006 (osteosarcoma: 9, giant cell tumor: 9, Ewing sarcoma: 8 and chondrosarcoma: 2). Sixty-one percent were male and the median age was 21 years (range: 8-60). The mean follow-up was 86 months. The posterolateral complex was reinserted at tibial metaphyseal level. Patients were evaluated functionally using the Musculoskeletal Tumor Society scale (MSTS). Results. Overall survival rate was 89%, local recurrence rate was 11%, and secondary amputation rate was 6% at 7 years of median follow-up. The average MSTS score was 93%. Five patients had neurological complications. No patient experienced subjective instability or vascular insufficiency. Conclusions. Bloc resection of the proximal fibula for the treatment of aggressive or malignant primary bone tumors allowed us to obtain local tumor control, and overall survival rate for sarcomas of 89% at 7 years. The posterolateral ligament complex tibial reinsertion provided functional knee stability without major functional consequences in the medium term (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farfalli, G. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albergo, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aponte-Tinao, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muscolo, D. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayerza, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los tumores óseos malignos o benignos localmente agresivos del tercio proximal del peroné son infrecuentes y generalmente su tratamiento es quirúrgico. Cuando se requiere una resección en bloque, la estabilidad de la rodilla puede comprometerse por afectación del complejo posterolateral. Material y métodos. Se analizaron 28 pacientes operados de manera consecutiva por un tumor óseo en el tercio proximal de peroné entre los años 1980 y 2006 (osteosarcoma: 9, TCG: 9, sarcoma de Ewing: 8 y condrosarcoma: 2). El 61% eran varones y la edad media fue de 21 años (rango: 8-60). El seguimiento promedio fue de 86 meses. El complejo posterolateral fue reinsertado a nivel de la metáfisis tibial. Los pacientes fueron evaluados funcionalmente con la escala Musculoskeletal Tumor Society (MSTS). Resultados. La supervivencia global fue del 89%, con un índice de recidiva local del 11% y un porcentaje de amputaciones secundarias del 6% a los 7 años de seguimiento promedio. El resultado promedio del MSTS fue del 93%. Cinco pacientes sufrieron secuelas neurológicas, 3 de tipo permanente. Ningún paciente sufrió inestabilidad subjetiva ni insuficiencia vascular. Conclusiones. La resección en bloque del peroné proximal en el tratamiento de los tumores óseos agresivos o malignos depara un buen control local de la enfermedad y una supervivencia a los 7 años, en los casos malignos, del 89%. La reinserción del complejo posterolateral a nivel tibial supone una buena estabilidad de la rodilla, sin secuelas funcionales a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(4): 212-216, jul.-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125036</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de los tumores malignos y localmente agresivos del tercio proximal del peroné. Resultados oncológicos y evaluación funcional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5495^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31274^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5495^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5495^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31274^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
