<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83935</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">was born a woman, the life of Mame: the dramatization of intergenerational inclusion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">I was born a woman, the life of Mame is the dramatization a fictitious intergenerational story. However, the story is based on true events and the feelings of real immigrant women. The dramatization narrates the life of a woman, from the time her parents&#150;who had recently emigrated from Senegal&#150;settled in Andalusia, up to the adolescence of Mame's own daughter. The story is told with one person on stage who, through the use of three costume changes, plays three different generations of women: mother, daughter and granddaughter, with the video-recorded testimonies of other characters (a teacher and a midwife), who express their views of the host society against a background of African music and pictures of their native country. The present article describes their goals, such as communication in conferences, and includes a concise summary of the script, reflections on the process of integrating, and the evaluation made after a performance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lasheras Amat,  M. del Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Awa Ndour, Mame</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muriel Fernández, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llamas Martínez, M. Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Bernal,  Victoriano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bitoden Yaka,  Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dieng,  Ousseynou</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Sevillano, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hallaga Messari, Asmaa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nací mujer, la vida de Mame es la dramatización de una historia intergeneracional ficticia, pero que recoge acontecimientos y sentimientos reales de las mujeres inmigrantes. Narra la historia de una mujer desde la instalación en Andalucía de sus padres, recién inmigrados de Senegal, hasta la adolescencia de su hija. Se desarrolla con un personaje en escena que, a través de las modificaciones del vestuario, va encarnando las tres generaciones de mujeres: madre, hija y nieta, con intervenciones grabadas en vídeo de otros personajes (matrona y maestro) que transmiten sus visiones desde la sociedad de acogida; todo ello ambientado con música africana e imágenes del país de origen. En este artículo se exponen sus propósitos como comunicación en congresos, un resumen muy sintético del guión, reflexiones sobre el proceso de inclusión expuesto y la evaluación realizada después de una representación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(3): 259-261, May. - Jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83935</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nací mujer, la vida de Mame: una puesta en escena sobre la inclusión intergeneracional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4385</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
