<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112218</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comprehensive geriatric assessment of elderly for outpatient emergency services. Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The progressive aging of the Spanish population leads to increased health care for Outpatient Emergency Services (EUS), in this age group. The aim of this paper is to highlight the importance of an overall assessment of the elderly in the household and community context, which involves both the physical and psychosocial in the emergency environmental. To do this, we develop a clinical case, which is based on scientific evidence, to determine the most appropriate action to improve interventions in emergency services. The case analysis is divided into three sections: nursing assessment, data recording and transmission of information to other health teams. In conclusion, it identifies the need to assess and record data on physical and physiological status of the elderly, at the same time it collects information about family background, community or environmental, to provide a comprehensive and quality care. It also recommends the development of specific geriatric assessment tools for use in emergency situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardavila Belio, Miren Idoia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Eito, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivar, Cristina G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El progresivo envejecimiento de la población española conlleva un aumento de la atención sanitaria, por los servicios de urgencias extrahospitalarias (SUE), a este grupo de edad. El objetivo de este trabajo es evidenciar la importancia de realizar una valoración global del anciano en el contexto domiciliario y comunitario, que contemple tanto los aspectos físicos como los psicosociales y ambientales de la persona en situación de urgencia. Para ello, se desarrolla un caso clínico, que se apoya en la evidencia científica, para determinar la actuación más adecuada que mejore las intervenciones de los servicios de urgencias extrahospitalarias. El análisis del caso se estructura entres apartados: la valoración de enfermería, el registro de los datos y la transmisión de la información a otros equipos de salud. Como conclusión, se identifica la necesidad de valorar y registrar datos sobre el estado físico y fisiológico del anciano al mismo tiempo que se recoge información sobre su contexto familiar, comunitario o ambiental, para proporcionar unos cuidados integrales y de calidad. Asimismo, se recomienda el desarrollo de herramientas de valoración geriátrica específicas para utilizar en situaciones de urgencias extrahospitalarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);23(4): 162-168, dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112218</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración geriátrica global del anciano por los servicios de urgencias extrahospitalarias. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
