<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056992</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical evolution of the radiograph-negative acute wrist injuries. Prospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Acute wrist sprain is the most common initial        diagnosis in acute wrist injuries. Nevertheless, acute        wrist sprain is one of the most common erroneous initial        diagnosis in Traumatology. The objective of this study is a        prospective survey on these injuries.        Material and methods: Emergency Department and Consultation        protocols were developped. Complicated Evolution        of Radiograph-Negative Acute Wrist Injury (CERNAWI)        was defined.        Results: Between January and December 2005, data        from 103 patients was collected. 33 patients were lost to        follow up. 11,4% of the patients presented a positive radiograph        image during the follow up. 28,5% of the patients&#146;        injuries were considered CERNAWI. A score (CERNAWI        score) is developped in order to make prognosis of        the evolution of these injuries. Its sensibility was 95% and        its specificity 30%.        Conclusions: A great number of patients having suffered        a radiograph-negative wrist trauma will have a complicated        evolution. The CERNAWI score is an item that could be        used at Emergency Departments to make prognosis of the        acute wrist trauma</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo Lorenzo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayestaran Vega, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El esguince agudo de muñeca es el diagnóstico        más frecuente en traumatismos agudos de muñeca. Sin        embargo, el esguince agudo de muñeca es una de las causas        más frecuentes de error diagnóstico inicial en Traumatología.        El objetivo de este estudio es conocer la evolución de        estas lesiones.        Material y métodos: Se desarrollan protocolos de actuación        en Urgencias y Consultas Externas para pacientes con        traumatismo agudo de muñeca con radiología inicial negativa.        Se define la Mala Evolución de Muñeca Aguda Radiológicamente        Negativa (MEMARNE). Se analiza la asociación entre        MEMARNE y los datos de anamnesis recogidos en        Urgencias.        Resultados: Entre enero y diciembre de 2005 se recogieron        103 casos de traumatismo agudo de muñeca con radiología        inicial negativa. Se produjeron 33 pérdidas de seguimiento.        11,4% de los pacientes presentó radiología positiva en controles        posteriores. 28,5% cumplieron criterios MEMARNE. Se        desarrolla un score de exploración física para pronosticar la        evolución de los traumatismos agudos de muñeca radiológicamente        negativos, con una Sensibilidad de 95% y Especificidad        de 30%.        Conclusiones: Un porcentaje importante de pacientes con        traumatismo agudo de muñeca con radiología inicial negativa        sufre complicaciones. El MEMARNE score es un instrumento        que puede utilizarse para pronosticar la evolución del traumatismo        agudo de muñeca</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(1): 31-39, ene.-mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056992</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de los traumatismos agudos de muñeca radiológicamente negativos. Estudio prospectivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35257^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15352^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
