<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83017</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Breast cancer survival after 10 years of follow up, in Granada and Almeria spanish provinces</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: To describe the overall and disease-free survival at five and ten years after breast cancer diagnosis in women from a previous case-control study, and establish related prognostic factors. Methods: We followed up 202 patients diagnosed between 1996 and 1998 in three public hospitals in Granada and Almeria provinces in Spain. Survival rates were calculated using the Kaplan and Meier method, and the Cox proportional hazards model was applied to identify the most significant variables contributing to survival. Results: Mean age at diagnosis was 54.27±10.4 years. Mean follow-up for overall survival was 119.91 months (95%CI 113.65126.17); the five-year survival rate was 83.9% (95%CI: 78.13-89.66) and the ten-year rate was 71% (95%CI: 63.25-78.74). Mean followup for disease-free survival was 118.75 months (95%CI 111.86125.65); the five-year disease-free survival rate was 81% (95%CI: 74.52-87.47) and the ten-year rate was 71.3% (95%CI: 63.33-79.26). The mortality rate of the study population was 33.17%. Conclusions: Disease characteristics are similar in our population to those in other Spanish and European regions, while the overall survival is higher than the mean rate during the same period in Europe (5-yr rate of 79%) and similar to that in Spain (83%)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Expósito Hernández, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávila Arias, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Vicente, Sabina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olea Serrano, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cabrera, Mariana F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocón Hernández, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Describir la supervivencia global y libre de enfermedad a los cinco y diez años del diagnóstico de cáncer de mama en mujeres participantes un estudio caso control previo, y establecer las variables pronóstico relacionadas. Métodos: Se realizó el seguimiento de 202 mujeres diagnosticadas en tres hospitales públicos de Granada y Almería entre 19961998. La supervivencia se evaluó mediante el método de Kaplan-Meier, y la identificación de factores relacionados mediante el análisis de regresión de Cox. Resultados: La edad media al diagnóstico fue de 54,27±10,4 años. La supervivencia global a los 5 años fue del 83,9% (IC 95%: 78,13-89,66) y a los 10 años del 71% (IC 95%: 63,25-78,74) con un tiempo medio de seguimiento de 119,91 meses (IC 95% 113,65126,17). La supervivencia libre de enfermedad a los 5 años fue del 81% (IC 95%: 74,52-87,47) y a los 10 años del 71,3% (IC 95%: 63,33-79,26) con un tiempo medio de seguimiento de 118,75 meses (IC 95% 111,86-125,65). La mortalidad de la serie fue del 33&#146;17%. Conclusiones: Las características de la enfermedad en las mujeres de la muestra estudiada son similares a las de otras regiones de España y Europa, con una supervivencia global superior a la descrita en Europa y y comparable a la de España amba referidas para el mismo periodo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;84(6): 705-715, nov.-dic.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Supervivencia en cáncer de mama tras 10 años de seguimiento en las provincias de Granada y Almería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50290</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29141^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23307^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
