<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127194</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in the rate of episiotomies and its relation to severe perineal tears and neonatal morbility</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the variability in the use of episiotomy among midwives and its relation to third and fourth-degree tears, and the impact on neonatal morbidity. Method: A study was conducted on historical groups from a total of 2,366 eutocic births with a single live fetus greater than or equal to 37 weeks gestation and 18 midwives over a three year period (2009, 2010 and 2011) in «Mancha-Centro» Hospital (Alcázar de San Juan).The outcomes variables for this analysis were the incidence of episiotomy, perineal lacerations, and neonatal morbidity. Results: The variability in the use of episiotomy ranged from 19.5% to 50.1% among the 18midwives in the study, with an average rate of 34.9% (824). Grouped at intervals, 22.1% (524)had a rate of &amp;#8804; 25%, 26.1% (621) between 26-35%, 38% (898) between 36-44%, and 13.7% (323)a rate of &amp;#8805; 45%, with homogeneity between the groups for all the confounding factors. There was no statistical association between higher rates of episotomy and pH of umbilical artery &lt;7.10, Apgar score after 5 min &lt;7, and the level of neonatal resuscitation type iii and iv. There was also no relationship between the rate of episiotomy with perineal integrity and third and fourth-degree tears. Discussion: The variability in the rate of episiotomy is high, and it is not related to the increased presence of third and fourth-degree tears or increased neonatal morbidity. Episiotomy rates should not be greater than 25%, in order to prevent perineal trauma or loss of fetal well-being (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Melero-Jiménez, María del Rocio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baño Garnés, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual-Pedreño, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Alarcón, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Martínez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Determinar la variabilidad en la práctica de episiotomías entre matronas y su relación con la aparición de desgarros perineales tipo III-IV, así como sus repercusiones sobre la morbilidad neonatal. Método Cohortes históricas sobre 2.366 partos eutócicos con feto vivo único, mayor o igual a 37 semanas de gestación y 18 matronas del Hospital la Mancha-Centro de Alcázar de San Juan durante los años 2009, 2010 y 2011. Las variables principales fueron la incidencia de episiotomías, desgarros perineales y morbilidad neonatal. Resultados La variabilidad en la práctica de la episiotomía osciló entre el 19,5 y el 50,1% entre las 18 matronas a estudio, con una tasa promedio del 34,9% (824). Al agrupar por intervalo, el 22,1% (524) presentaba una tasa &amp;#8804; 25%, el 26,1% (621) entre el 26-35%, el 38% (898) entre el 36-44% y el 13,7% (323) una tasa &amp;#8805; 45%, observándose homogeneidad entre los grupos para todos los factores de confusión. No se observó asociación estadística entre mayores tasas de episiotomías y pH de arteria umbilical &lt; 7,10, puntuaciones de apgar a los 5 min &lt; 7 y grado de reanimación neonatal tipo III y IV. Tampoco encontramos asociación entre tasa de episiotomías con integridad perineal y desgarros tipo III-IV. ConclusiónLa variabilidad en la tasa de episiotomías es alta y no se relaciona con la mayor presencia de desgarros tipo III y IV, ni mayor morbilidad neonatal. No se justifican tasas mayores del 25% de episiotomías para prevenir el trauma perineal ni la pérdida de bienestar fetal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);24(5): 269-275, sept.-oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127194</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad en la tasa de episiotomías y su relación con desgarros perineales graves y morbilidad neonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29038^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50264</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10693^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33125^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
