<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113537</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phobia to contract lymphedema: Clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Clinical case study of a woman  who has been operated on breast cancer and  lymphadenectomy who was referred by her  oncologist in 2009, given because she didn&#146;t  move her arm for fear of acquire lymphedema. Purposes: 1. Psychoeducation about  lymphedema and how to look after the arm.  2. Overcoming fear of moving the arm. 3.  Improving the patient&#146;s quality of life. Method: Designing an exposure therapy in  which the patient has to cope with situations  that arouse great anxiety and fear. These  situations are related to common activities   in the patient&#146;s daily life and has been rated  in a list of increasing level of anxiety: Eating,  getting dressed, housework, personal hygiene  and physical exercise. The patient kept a record book with the  exposure tasks that she confronted. Results: The patient overcame all her fears  for lymphedema, leading a completely normal  life and learning about the measures and cares  to take for lymphedema prevention. Conclusions: Exposure is the most  appropriate treatment option for phobic  disorders in patients who suffer cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Rivas, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Ceballos Reyna, Mª Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: análisis de un caso clínico de  mujer operada de mama con linfadenectomía  remitida por su oncólogo en el año 2009 al no  realizar ningún movimiento con el brazo por  temor a contraer linfedema.  Objetivos: 1. Psicoeducación sobre el linfedema y cuidados del brazo. 2. Vencer el miedo  al movimiento del brazo. 3. Mejorar la calidad  de vida de la paciente. Metodología: eelaboración de un programa de exposición a través de las situaciones  en que la paciente experimentaba gran ansiedad y temor, relacionadas con actividades  habituales de su vida diaria, realizando la siguiente lista de actividades, de menor a mayor  ansiedad:comer, vestirse, labores domésticas,  aseo personal y realizar ejercicio físico. Se utilizó el autorregistro con las tareas de exposición realizadas. Resultados: la paciente superó sus miedos  hacia el linfedema, realizando una vida totalmente normal, conociendo cuáles son los cuidados que debe tener a modo de prevención.  Conclusiones: el tratamiento de exposición  ha mostrado eficacia en el presente caso y  confirma que es una intervención en el caso  de fobias en pacientes oncológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);10(1): 185-196, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fobia a contraer linfedema: caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11124^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8386^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
