<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94982</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The advantages of neuropsychological examination batteries in attention deficit hyperactivity disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. The neuropsychological assessment of the functions of attention and the executive functions in patients with clinical features compatible with a diagnosis of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) is considered a priority study to be able to offer a basic study. It is also necessary to be able to carry out a short- and long-term developmental followup of patients. Development. An algorithm for diagnosing ADHD is proposed that includes both traditional and computerised  tests for assessing the functions of attention and the executive functions. The development of new neuropsychological batteries for this purpose involves the use of several tests in computerised form that offer technical and methodological advantages as regards their use and the later treatment of the data obtained. Conclusions. The advantages of computerised assessment  include management of answer times, minimum expression of the effect exerted by the researcher, savings in time, accurate and fast scoring, statistical management of new scores, and greater proximity to research programmes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abad, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paiva Barón, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Etchepareborda, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. La evaluación neuropsicológica de las funciones de atención y de las funciones ejecutivas en pacientes con una sintomatología compatible con el diagnóstico de trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad (TDAH) supone un estudio prioritario para poder ofrecer un estudio básico, así como para poder llevar a cabo un seguimiento evolutivo a corto y a largo plazo de los pacientes. Desarrollo. Se plantea un algoritmo diagnóstico del TDAH, en el que se incluyen pruebas  tradicionales e informatizadas para evaluar las funciones de atención y las funciones ejecutivas. El desarrollo de nuevas baterías neuropsicológicas con esta finalidad supone el empleo informatizado de diversos test que demuestran ventajas técnicas y metodológicas en cuanto a su empleo y en referencia al manejo posterior de los datos obtenidos. Conclusiones. Entre las ventajas de la evaluación informatizada destacan el manejo temporal de las respuestas, la mínima expresión del efecto experimentador,  el ahorro de tiempo, la precisión y rapidez de las puntuaciones, el tratamiento estadístico de nuevas puntuaciones y la mayor cercanía respecto a los programas de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(supl.2): 89-93, feb. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94982</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ventajas de las baterías de exploración neuropsicológica en el trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
