<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124046</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic features of active surveillance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In a context where there is evidence that not every patient with low risk prostate cancer needs to be treated from the start, active treatments are expensive and public health care systems need to save money, studies on cost-effectiveness are a priority. To elaborate this article, we reviewed the publications on cost and cost-effectiveness of localized prostate cancer treatments that include active surveillance. In patients with low risk localized prostate cancer active surveillance is more cost-effective than active treatment. With time active surveillance may be more expensive than brachytherapy or radical prostatectomy. The frequency of prostatic biopsies and the percentage of conversions to active treatment will be determinant in final costs of active surveillance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribal, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huguet, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musquera, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En un contexto en el que existe evidencia de que no todos los pacientes con cáncer de próstata de bajo riesgo necesitan ser tratados de entrada, los tratamientos activos son caros y los sistemas de salud pública precisan ahorrar, los estudios sobre coste-efectividad son prioritarios. Para elaborar el presente trabajo, revisamos las publicaciones sobre costes y coste-efectividad de los tratamientos del cáncer de próstata localizado que incluyesen la vigilancia activa. En pacientes con cáncer de próstata localizado de bajo riesgo, la vigilancia activa es más coste-efectiva que el tratamiento activo. Con el tiempo, la vigilancia activa puede ser más cara que la braquiterapia y la prostatectomía radical. La frecuencia de las biopsias prostáticas y el porcentaje de conversiones a tratamiento activo serán determinantes en los costes finales de la vigilancia activa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(5): 509-513, jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos económicos de la vigilancia activa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33086^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54396</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
