<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117176</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Professional coaching application in sport: a single case study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objectives of this paper are to perform a critical analysis of the current state of coaching and to illustrate its application with a case study. The concept "coaching" comes from sports and has been developed as a method for the business world. In recent years the concept has returned to the sport context. Coaching comes from the sport model (coach-athlete), its foundations are mainly derives from psychology and is defined as a strategy of psychological intervention on behavior modification. It is concluded that coaching is an psychological strategy effective in behavior modification, although further research on the subject and compare its utility versus other other strategies or multicomponent intervention is required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Naveira Vaamonde, Alejo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos del presente trabajo son el de realizar un análisis crítico del estado actual del coaching y ejemplificar su aplicación con un caso práctico. El concepto del coaching proviene del ámbito deportivo y como método se ha desarrollado en el ámbito empresarial, y en los últimos años ha regresado al contexto deportivo. El coaching proviene del modelo deportivo (entrenador-deportista), sus fundamentos derivan principalmente de la Psicología y se define como una estrategia de intervención psicológica en modificación de la conducta. Se concluye que el coaching es una estrategia psicológica eficaz en modificación de la conducta, aunque se requiere continuar investigando al respecto y comparar su utilidad frente a otras estrategias o intervención multicomponente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;13(2): 110-112, jul.-dic. 2013. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117176</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación profesional del coaching en el deporte: un estudio de caso único</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53814^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
