<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139927</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in the prevalence of pressure ulcers in an acute care tertiary hospital (2006-2013)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyse the trends in pressure ulcer prevalence from 2006 to 2013. To determine the main risk factors associated with pressure ulcers. Method: A descriptive study analysing the prevalence in a series of pressure ulcers collected in the study on the prevalence of nosocomial infections in Spain from 2006 to 2013 in the Clinical University Hospital of Zaragoza. Results: The mean prevalence among the 5,354 patients included over the period of study was 4.5% (95% CI = 3.9-5.0%). No significant difference in its trend or distribution of pressure ulcers was observed over the several years of the study. Prevalence increased up to 5.0% (95% CI = 4.4-5.6%) when short-stay patients (less than 24 hours) and those admitted into low risk units (Paediatrics, Psychiatry and Obstetrics) were removed from the study, but there was still no significant differences in its yearly trend or distribution (p &gt; 0.05). Age, length of stay, presence of coma, in-dwelling urethral catheters, malnutrition, infection, and admission unit were risk factors associated with pressure ulcer prevalence in the logistic regression. Conclusions: Age, length of stay, coma, in-dwelling urethral catheters, malnutrition, infection, and admission unit were independent risk markers for patients with pressure ulcers. No particular trend of pressure ulcer prevalence could be determined to demonstrate any effects from the different strategies of improvement implemented during the period of study, although this fact could be due to the limitations of data used in the study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Lorente, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aibar-Remón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrasa-Villar, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la evolución de la prevalencia de úlceras por presión entre los años 2006 a 2013. Conocer los principales factores de riesgo asociados a las mismas. Método: Estudio descriptivo en el que se analizaron las series de prevalencia 2006-2013 de úlceras por presión del estudio de prevalencia de las infecciones nosocomiales en España del Hospital Clínico Universitario de Zaragoza. Resultados: La prevalencia media de úlceras por presión en los 5.354 pacientes del período de estudio fue de 4,5% (IC95% = 3,9-5,0%). No se encontraron diferencias significativas en la distribución ni en la tendencia a lo largo del período estudiado. La prevalencia aumentó al 5,0% (IC95% = 4,4-5,6% al eliminar de la muestra los pacientes con estancia inferior a 24 horas y los de servicios de bajo riego (Pediatría, Obstetricia y Psiquiatría), pero tampoco había diferencias en su distribución ni tendencia anual (p &gt; 0,05). Los factores asociados a las úlceras fueron la edad, los días de ingreso, la presencia de coma, sonda urinaria, desnutrición, infección y el servicio de ingreso. Conclusiones: La edad, la estancia hospitalaria, la presencia de coma, desnutrición, infección, sonda urinaria y el ingreso en determinadas unidades constituyen marcadores independientes de riesgo de los pacientes con úlceras por presión. No se aprecia una tendencia en la prevalencia de úlceras por presión que sugiera algún efecto de las diferentes estrategias de intervención implantadas en el período de estudio, aunque esta ausencia de hallazgos podría ser debida a las limitaciones de los datos empleados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;30(3): 135-141, mayo-jun. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139927</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de la prevalencia de úlceras por presión en un hospital de agudos de tercer nivel (2006-2013)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
