<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97284</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute Supplementation of L-Arginine does not prevent the hematotoxicity due to neoadjuvant chemotherapy in patients with breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Breast cancer is the first cause of morbid-mortality from neoplasms among Mexican women. Neoadjuvant chemotherapy is the first curse of treatment for patients with locally advances disease; one of its main toxicities is myelo suppression. This can frequently cause the patient to delay her treatment or diminish the dosage. L-arginine can prevent this effect by maintaining a positive nitrogen balance and inducing the proliferation of hematopoietic cells. Objective: To evaluate the efficacy of the supplementation of L-arginine on the prevention of hematologic toxicity in patients with breast cancer undergoing neoadjuvant chemotherapy. response to neoadjuvant chemotherapeutic treatment. Materials and methods: We conducted a randomized clinical trial which administered 30 g of L-argininein each chemotherapy cycle. We determined the values of hemoglobin, hematocrit, leucocytes and lymphocytes after each chemotherapy application. We permormed ANOVA tests in order to evaluate intragrupal changes along the antineoplastic treatment and t-student tests for independent samples for evaluating intergrupal differences. Results: 45 patients were assessed. All of them presented a significant decline in hematologic values eachtime. We did not find significant differences between groups. Conclusions: L-arginine supplementation does not prevent myelosuppression in patients with breast cancer under going neoadjuvant chemotherapy. More clinicaltrials are needs in order to obtain sufficient evidence that allows the recommendation (or not) of L-arginineas part of the integral treatment for the oncology patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Autrique Sierra, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Salmeán, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuchs, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceballos Reyes, Guillermo M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El cáncer de mama ocupa el primer lugar en morbi-mortalidad por neoplasias en la mujer mexicana. La quimioterapia neoadyuvante es el tratamiento de primera línea para las pacientes con enfermedad localmente avanzada; una de sus principal estoxicidades es la mielosupresión, la cual pueda obligar una demora en el tratamiento o disminución en la dosis. La L-arginina es capaz de prevenir este efecto al mantener un balance de nitrógeno positivo y favorecer la proliferación de células hematopoyéticas Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia de la suplementación de L-arginina sobre prevención de la toxicidad hemática en pacientes con cáncer de mama con quimioterapia neoadyuvante. Materiales y métodos: Ensayo clínico de asignación aleatoria que administró un suplemento de 30 g de L-arginina en cada ciclo de quimioterapia neoadyuvante. Se determinaron los valores de hemoglobina, hematocrito, leucocitos y linfocitos después de cada aplicación del tratamiento antineoplásico. Se realizaron pruebas ANOVA para evaluar los cambios intragrupales a lo largo del tratamiento y pruebas t-student para muestras independientes para las diferencias intergrupales. Resultados: Se evaluaron 45 pacientes. Todas las pacientes presentaron una disminución significativa en los valores hemáticos en cada ocasión evaluada. No se encontraron diferencias significativas entre grupos. Conclusiones: La suplementación con L-arginina no previene la mielosupresión en pacientes con cáncer de mama localmente avanzado que reciben quimioterapia neoadyuvante. Es necesario realizar más ensayos clínicos que permitan obtener la evidencia para recomendar o no la administración de L-arginina como parte del tratamiento integral del paciente oncológico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;30(3): 49-54, sept.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97284</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La suplementación aguda con L-Arginina no previene la hematotoxicidad debida a la quimioterapia neoadyuvanteen pacientes con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33511^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1123^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
