<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93941</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric analysis of the resilence scale in the sport of football</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From a strictly athletic perspective, the demands of competition level sport lead to the development of capabilities for psychological tolerance and overcoming adversities related to engaging in sport, which can be related directly or indirectly with the construct of Resilience. One of the instruments designed is the Resilience Scale developed by Wagnield and Young (1993), translated into Portuguese by Pesce, Assis, Avanci, Santos, Malaquias and Carvalhaes (2005), which used a Brazilian sample and was adapted by Vigario, Serpa and Rosado (2009) using a Portuguese sample. Our study aims: 1. &#150;to describe the global resilience level of the scale adapted to Spanish with a sample of footballers, comparing it with the Portuguese study using a sample of students developed by Vigario et al. (2009); 2. &#150;to establish the psychometric characteristics of the adapted scale by developing a confirmatory factorial analysis in which comparisons were made with the structure created by Vigario et al. (2009). The sample uconsisted in 110 footballers from official competitions divided into the age groups: 15 to 16 years old (n = 37), 17 to 18 years old (n = 54) and 19 years old and older (n = 19). The age range encompassed 15 to 21-year-olds with an average age of 16.71 years. The results show higher global Resilience in the footballer sample than in the students&#146; (p &lt; .001). It also partially confirmed the factorial structure of the two factors proposed, which obtained the highest levels of total explained variance in our study (30.36%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega, Ricardo de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosado, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serpa, Sidonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poveda, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde una perspectiva estrictamente deportiva, las exigencias del deporte a nivel competitivo conllevan el desarrollo de capacidades psicológicas de tolerancia y superación de adversidades propias de la práctica deportiva, que pueden relacionarse directa o indirectamente con el constructo de Resiliencia. Uno de los instrumentos diseñados es la escala de Resiliencia desarrollada por Wagnield y Young (1993), traducida al portugués por Pesce, Assis, Avanci, Santos, Malaquias y Carvalhaes (2005) utilizando muestra brasileña, y adaptada con muestra portuguesa por Vigário, Sérpa y Rosádo (2009). Los objetivos de nuestro estudio son: 1.- Describir los niveles de resiliencia globales de la escala adaptada al español con una muestra de futbolistas, comparándola con el estudio en portugués con muestra de estudiantes desarrollado por Vigário et al. (2009); 2.- Determinar las características psicométricas de la escala adaptada desarrollando un análisis factorial confirmatorio donde se establezcan comparaciones con la estructura extraída por Vigário et al. (2009). La muestra utilizada son 110 jugadores de fútbol de competición correspondientes a las categorías cadetes (n = 37), juveniles (n = 54) y senior (n = 19). El rango de edad es de 15 a 21 años, con una edad de media de 16.71 años. Los resultados muestran mayores valores observados de resiliencia global en la muestra de futbolistas que de estudiantes (p &lt; .001). Asimismo, se confirma parcialmente la estructura factorial de dos factores propuesta, obteniendo mayores niveles de varianza explicada total en nuestro estudio (30.36%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;21(1): 143-151, ene.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93941</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis psicométrico de la Escala de Resiliencia en el deporte del fútbol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
