<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162643</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Wheelchair basketball: influence of shoulder pain in sport skills</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Shoulder injuries are a common problem among wheelchair basketball players (WB). The purpose of this study was to detect the influence of shoulder pain (SP) in WB sport skills. Fifty-one WB players aged from 15 to 42 (21 females, 23, 86±1, 38 years and 30 males, 23, 90±1, 46 years) were evaluated. Shoulder Pain Index for Wheelchair Basketball (SPI-WB) was used to determine SP in relation to specific WB skills. Gender and age were compared using T-test and One Factor ANOVA, respectively. The level of significance was set at p&amp;#8804;0, 05. 27, 5% of the sample reported actual SP. Statistical analysis revealed a main effect for gender regarding SP during shooting skills, especially for females. There were no significant differences according to rebounding/one-handed long passes and other sport situations. In conclusion, SP could affect the specific activities of WB according to gender, especially during shooting in females, so ways to promote shoulder health must be develop (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Tejero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Gómez, Saleky</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las lesiones del hombro son un problema común entre los jugadores de baloncesto en silla de ruedas (BSR). El objetivo de este estudio fue detectar la influencia del dolor de hombro (DH) en las habilidades deportivas propias del BSR. 51 jugadores de BSR entre 15 y 42 (21 mujeres, 23, 86 ± 1, 38 años y 30 hombres, 23, 90 ± 1, 46 años) fueron evaluados. El Cuestionario del Dolor de Hombro en BSR se utilizó para determinar el DH en relación a las habilidades específicas del BSR. El género y la edad se compararon mediante la prueba t y ANOVA de un factor, respectivamente. El nivel de significación se estableció en p&amp;#8804;0, 05. 27, 5% de la muestra informó SP en el momento del estudio. Los resultados muestran diferencias significativas de acuerdo al género en relación con DH en habilidades como el tiro, especialmente para las mujeres. No hubo diferencias significativas en función de realizar acciones de rebote y pases largos/una sola mano y otras situaciones propias del BSR. En conclusión, SP podría afectar a las actividades específicas del BSR en función del género, especialmente en las mujeres, por lo que se debe promover la salud del hombro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.1): 45-49, 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162643</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Baloncesto en silla de ruedas: influencia del dolor del hombro en gestos deportivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15310^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55433^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33758^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
