<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114303</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Femur fracture in a neonate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fémur fracture is an infrequent obstetrical injury. It is characterterized to appear for different causes: maternal, obstetrical or fetus related. Clinical manifestations of the injury could be unnoticed at a first moment. Diagnose is based in clinical suspicion and confirmed by x-ray. The treatment consists in the immobilization of the extremity during 4 weeks, prognosis is excellent. We present a clinical case of a femur fracture in a new born by a cesarean in a gemelar gestaction caused by a podalic presentation of the first neonate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Ruiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sastre Huerta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Barrio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubillo Serna, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustamante, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Gómez, I del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fractura de fémur es una infrecuente lesión obstétrica, se caracteriza por presentarse por diferentes causas ya sean maternas, obstétricas o del feto. Las manifestaciones clínicas pueden pasar desapercibidas en un primer momento, basándose el diagnostico en la sospecha clínica y confirmándose el diagnostico en la sospecha clínica y confirmándose mediante la radiografía. El tratamiento consisten en la inmovilización de la extremidad durante unas 4 semanas, el pronóstico de la lesión es excelente. Prestamos un caso clínico de una fractura de fémur en un recién nacido por cesárea en una gestación gemelar por presentación podálica del primer gemelo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;62(6): 518-519, nov.-dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114303</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura de fémur en un neonato</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5212^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7285^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
