<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117522</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stargardt´sdisease, prevalence of the mutation R1129L in affected spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper presents the results of the analysis of the most prevalent mutations in the ABCA4 gene in families diagnosed with Stargardt's macular dystrophy (STGD). Microarray ABCR400 was used containing 600 mutations already described for this gene. The analysis was carried out in 76 Spanish families STGD diagnosed. It was possible to identify 40 mutations associated with the disease in 60% of families (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valverde, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se presentan los resultados del análisis de las mutaciones mas prevalentes en el gen ABCA4 en familias  diagnosticadas de Distrofia macular de Stargardt (STGD). Se ha utilizado el microarray ABCR400 que contiene 600 mutaciones ya descritas para este gen. El análisis se llevó a cabo en 76 familias españolas diagnosticadas de STGD. Se han podido identificar 40 mutaciones relacionadas con la patología en el 60% de las familias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;3(2): 80-82, abr.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117522</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La enfermedad del stargardt, prevalencia de la mutación R1129L en Población española afecta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28243^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
