<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115798</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of combined precut techniques on selective biliary cannulation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: simple biliary cannulation techniques obtain a success rate of 80-95%. Advanced precut techniques are not immediately successful in 10-40% of cases. Between extreme options such as a second attempt a few days later or an immediate attempt by the transparietal route, an alternative precut technique may be used as a rescue strategy for the initially failed procedure. The purpose of this study was to assess the efficacy and safety of the combined use of two precut techniques when immediate biliary access is not granted by an initial procedure. Patients and method: a retrospective analysis of a personal series of precut (needle-knife and transpancreatic) sphincterotomies, both alone and in combination. Results: five hundred sixty nine ERCPs (endocopic retrograde cholangio-pancreatography) met the inclusion criteria for the analysis. Simple cannulation was obtained in 444 (78%) of them. In all, 119 (21%) precuts were attempted and 110 (92.4%) were successful, which raised the overall cannulation rate to 97.4%. Ninety-five (80%) precuts were successful with the initial technique. Rescue with the alternative technique was attempted for 20 failures with a successful outcome in 15, which raised the overall success rate to 92%. The combination of needle-knife precut plus transpancreatic precut raised the success rate from 87% to 94%. The combination of transpancreatic precut plus needle-knife precut raised the success rate from 70% to 90%. Among all 96 patients with available follow-up data, 17 (18%) complications were recorded: 9 bleeding episodes, 4 pancreatitis cases, and 4 retroperitoneal perforations. No mortality was recorded. Conclusions: a combination of precut techniques is effective for biliary cannulation when simple cannulation and initial precut approaches fail. The safety profile differs from that in the delayed strategy, hence both should be considered alternatives, their use depending on the technical and clinical conditions prevailing for each patient, as well as endoscopist experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morena Madrigal, Emilio J. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: las técnicas simples de canulación biliar consiguen un porcentaje de éxitos del 80-95%. Las técnicas avanzadas de precorte no logran el éxito inmediato en un porcentaje del 10-40%. Entre las opciones extremas de un segundo intento diferido varios días o un intento de acceso inmediato por vía transparietal, existe el recurso a una técnica alternativa de precorte como rescate de la inicial fallida. El objetivo del presente estudio es evaluar la eficacia y seguridad del empleo combinado de dos técnicas de precorte cuando la inicial no permite el acceso biliar inmediato. Pacientes y método: análisis retrospectivo de una serie  ersonal de esfinterotomías de precorte (de aguja y transpancreático) simples y combinadas. Resultados: un total de 569 colangio-pancreatografías retrógradas endoscópicas (CPRE) cumplen los criterios de inclusión en el análisis. En 444 (78%) se obtuvo la canulación simple. Se intentaron 119 (21%) precortes, con éxito en 110 (92,4%), lo que elevó la tasa global de canulación al 97,4%. Noventa y cinco (80%) de los precortes tuvieron éxito con la técnica inicial. En 20 fracasos se intentó el rescate con la técnica alternativa, con éxito en 15, elevando la tasa global de éxito al 92%. La combinación precorte de aguja más precorte transpancreático elevó la tasa de éxito del 87% al 94%. La combinación precorte transpancreático más precorte de aguja elevó la tasa de éxito del 70% al 90%. Entre los 96 pacientes con seguimiento disponible se registraron 17 (18%) complicaciones: 9 hemorragias, 4 pancreatitis y 4 perforaciones retroperitoneales. No se registró mortalidad. Conclusiones: la combinación de técnicas de precorte es eficaz para alcanzar la canulación biliar cuando las técnicas simples de canulación y el precorte inicial fracasan. El perfil de seguridad difiere del de la estrategia moratoria, por lo que ambas deben considerarse alternativas y emplearse dependiendo de las condiciones técnicas y clínicas de cada paciente y de la experiencia del endoscopista (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(6): 338-344, jul. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de las técnicas combinadas de precorte sobre la canulación selectiva biliar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
