<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054929</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of helicobacter pylori infection in iron requirements or anaemia of hemodialysis patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Many studies in the general population have shown a link between Helicobacter        pylori infection and iron-deficiency, often resulting in iron-deficient anaemia. Despite        the high prevalence of iron deficiency in hemodialysis patients, no studies have been        performed in this population.        Objective: To evaluate the role of Helicobacter pylori infection in the appearance of anemia        and the iron requirements in our hemodialysis population. Material and methods: After excluding patients with severe pathology and short life expectancy        and those with blood losses secondary to other causes, 79 patients were included.        Iron requirements and anaemia were determined by iron serum, ferritin, and hematocrite        values; and by transfusion, eritropoietin and iron requirements. The diagnosis of        Helicobacter pylori status was stablished by the concordance of at least two of the three        non invasive diagnostic methods performed (breath test, serology and fecal antigen of Helicobacter        pylori).        Results: Prevalence of Helicobacter pylori infection was 43%. No significant differences        between patients infected or not by Helicobacter pylori were found in any of the variables        analysed: hematocrite (33.5% versus 34.1%), serum iron (58.9 versus 63.7 pg/dl), ferritin        (340.3 versus 264.2 ng/ml), transferrin saturation index (22.5% versus 25.2%), dose of eritropoietin        administred (96.6 versus 93.5 U/kg/weekly), and parenteral iron (1,389 versus        1,538 mg/year). A noteworthy finding was that patients with Helicobacter pylori infection        had been on hemodialysis for a shorter period than those without (37.4 versus 63.7 months,        p = 0.04).        Conclusion: Helicobacter pylori infection has no effect on anaemia (hematocrite, Eritropoietin        dose or iron needs) in our hemodialysis patients. Prevalence of Helicobacter pylori        is lower in patients with longer time on dialysis.        We consider that the diagnosis of Helicobacter pylori infection must be reserved for clinical        peptic ulcera suspicion or patients on transplant waiting list (¿?)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvet, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanfeliú, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almirall, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Estudios en determinados grupos de población han demostrado relación        entre la infección por Helicobacter pylori y la anemia ferropénica. Se han postulado como        mecanismos responsables las pérdidas hemáticas digestivas y la competición de la bacteria        por el hierro de la dieta.        Objetivo: Conocer si existe relación entre la infección por Helicobacter pylori y los requerimientos        de hierro, la ferropenia o la anemia en pacientes en hemodiálisis.        Material y métodos: Se estudiaron 79 pacientes en hemodiálisis. Las necesidades de hierro        se establecieron a partir de variables analíticas (sideremia, ferritina, índice de saturación        de transferrina, hematocrito) y terapéuticas (dosis de eritropoyetina y hierro administrado)        para alcanzar los objetivos. La infección por Helicobacter pylori se determinó        mediante tres métodos diagnósticos no invasivos (test del aliento, serología y detección del        antígeno en heces).        Resultados: La prevalencia de la infección por Helicobacter pylori fue del 43%. No existieron        diferencias en ninguna de las variables analizadas entre los pacientes infectados por        Helicobacter pylori y aquellos no infectados. Únicamente se observaron diferencias con        respecto al tiempo de hemodiálisis, de manera que los pacientes infectados por Helicobacter        pylori llevaban menos tiempo en hemodiálisis (37,4 versus 63,7 meses; p = 0,04).        Conclusiones: La infección por Helicobacter pylori no influye en la anemia o las necesidades        de hierro o eritropoyetina en nuestros pacientes. Consideramos, por tanto, que el        estudio sistemático de la infección por Helicobacter pylori en hemodiálisis no aporta información        relevante, debiendo reservarse para situaciones clínicas específicas (sospecha de        patología ulcerosa o pacientes en lista de espera para trasplante renal?)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;26(6): 673-678, nov.-dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054929</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Helicobacter pylori no contribuye al déficit de hierro de los pacientes en hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16595^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
