<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2224</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comorbidity between autism spectrum disorder and schizophrenia spectrum. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The schizophrenia spectrum disorders include a wide variety of cognitive and emotional dysfunctions. These can cause some alterations in the perception of the inferential thinking, in the language and communication, in the behaviour, in the affectivity, in the thinking and language fluency and production, as well as in hedonic capacity and executive functions. Some of these symptoms overlap those in the autism spectrum. Establishing the differential diagnosis and/or the comorbidity could be really complex, especially among adults, who suffer the autism spectrum disorder but having a good functioning in the intellectual and language area. Through this article, the specific case is presented of a patient aged 28 who suffers a wide trajectory of psychiatric symptoms. He was diagnosed with a schizophrenia spectrum disorders and some suspicion of a possible autism spectrum. An analysis and review is presented on the overlapping symptoms and the differences that exist between both diagnoses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cedron-Castro, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortuny-Olive, Juan Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Massó Rodríguez, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belmonte-Padilla, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batlle-Vila, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Golarons, Lucia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Serrano, Jara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos del espectro de la esquizofrenia incluyen un abanico de disfunciones cognoscitivas y emocionales que abarcan alteraciones en la percepción, del pensamiento inferencial, del lenguaje y la comunicación, del comportamiento, de la afectividad, la fluidez y productividad del pensamiento y el habla, de la capacidad hedónica, de las funciones ejecutivas. Algunos de estos síntomas se solapan con los contemplados en el espectro autista. Establecer el diagnóstico diferencial y/o la comorbilidad puede resultar complicado, especialmente en personas adultas con trastorno del espectro autista con buen funcionamiento en el área intelectual y del lenguaje. En este artículo, presentamos un caso de un paciente de 28 años con una amplia trayectoria psiquiátrica, diagnosticado de trastornos del espectro de la esquizofrenia y sospechas de un posible trastorno del espectro autista que nos permite analizar y revisar el solapamiento y las diferencias entre ambos diagnósticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);24(3): 132-136, sept.-dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comorbilidad entre el trastorno del espectro autista y el espectro de la esquizofrenia. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
