<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165440</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implantation of a nutritional and physical activity program in gestation. Randomized clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The type of feeding and physical activity performed during pregnancy has a clinical impact on maternal-fetal health and the newborn. Method: The objective of the study was to demonstrate that a care plan in nursing specifically based on nutritional and physical activity recommendations helps control weight maternal gain, improves the rate of normal deliveries and the rate of newborn appropriate for gestational age. Clinical study with randomization, open and performed in a single center. A sample of 142 pregnant women in the study group and 207 pregnant women in the control group was analyzed. The data were processed using the Statistical Package for Social Sciences establishing a significant value of p&lt; 0.05 program. Results: The control weight maternal gain was lower in the study group vs. control group (6.94 ± 3.24 vs. 10.55 ± 4.78, p = 0.000), presenting the study group pregnant increased rate of weight in the newborn appropriate for gestational age (85 2% - 81.2%, p = 0.038) and vaginal delivery (76.8% - 34.3%, p = 0.000). Conclusions: The proposed care plan in nursing improves maternal control weight maternal gain, increases the rate of appropriate for gestational age newborn and type of vaginal delivery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luna Cano, María Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rempel, Claudete</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Dominguez, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pombo, Carmen Neri</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreschi, Claudete</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El tipo de alimentación y de actividad física realizada durante la gestación tiene una repercusión clínica sobre la salud materna-fetal y del recién nacido. Metodos: El objetivo del estudio ha sido demostrar que un programa en cuidados en enfermería basado específicamente en recomendaciones nutricionales y de actividad física ayuda a controlar la ganancia ponderal, mejora la tasa de partos eutócicos y la tasa de recién nacido adecuado para la edad gestacional. Estudio clínico con aleatorización por conglomerados, abierto y unicéntrico. Se analizó una muestra de 142 gestantes en el grupo estudio y de 207 gestantes en el grupo control. Los datos fueron tratados con el programa Statistical Package for Social Sciences estableciéndose un valor significativo de p &lt; 0,05. Resultados: La ganancia ponderal fue inferior en el grupo estudio frente al grupo control (8,2 ± 4,8 vs 10,2 ± 5,9, p = 0,001), presentando las gestantes del grupo estudio mayor tasa de peso en el recién nacido adecuado para la edad gestacional (85,2% - 81,2%, p = 0,038) y de parto eutócico (76,8% - 34,3%, p = 0,000). Conclusiones: El programa de cuidados en enfermería propuesto en este estudio mejora la ganancia ponderal materna, aumenta la tasa de peso adecuado para la edad gestacional en el RN y el tipo de parto eutócico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;37(2): 107-113, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165440</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implantación de un programa nutricional y de actividad física en la gestación. Ensayo clínico aleatorizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28488</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38862</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
