<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2269</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eating in Patagonia: Argentinean adult women's meals stories. Year 2016</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human feeding is a multidimensional process, where the vital biological function of nurturing is interweave with cultural and social components. Human sciences pursueto understand the imaginary, symbolic and social dimension. The biological dimension has had an exponential scientific development, analyzing basically the processes by which the body metabolizes and takes advantage of nutrients, the bromatological analysis, production models, development of food industry, etc. It is proposed to examine food stories from the symbolic and nutritious functions, and performing a qualitative analysis of seven stories of a Workshop of National University of Comahue. Argentina. The narrations clearly showed the relationship between the two dimensions, with a common culinary grammar. Organoleptic and sensory characteristics of food were identified. All stories included raw foods, proeessed cooking ingredients and processed foods according to the NOVA classification. The stories had an intense display of emotions and feelings, manifested during the telling of the techniques and moments of preparation. It is necessary to continue working in investigations that deepen the study of the relations between the biological and the cultural of the food, incorporating commensality on an equal level with biological variables and in actions of health-illness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Inestal, Ana Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bruveris, Bárbara Bruna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nin, Delia Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arzamendia, Yesica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bruveris, Ana Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Majem, Lluis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, María Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salomone, Anabella</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La alimentación humana es un proceso multidimensional, donde la función biológica vital de nutrir se entreteje con componentes culturales y sociales. Las ciencias humanas buscan comprender la dimensión imaginaria, simbólica y social. La dimensión biológica ha tenido un desarrollo científico exponencial. analizando fundamentalmente los procesos por los cuales el cuerpo metaboliza y aprovecha nutrientes, el análisis bromatológico, modelos de producción, desarrollo de la industria alimentaria, etc. Se propone estudiar relatos de comidas desde la función simbólica y nutritiva, realizándose un análisis cualitativo de un Taller de la Universidad Nacional del Comahue. Argentina. Las narraciones mostraron con claridad la interrelación entre ambas dimensiones, existiendo una gramática culinaria común. Se identificaron características organolépticas y sensoriales de los alimentos. Todos los relatos incluyeron alimentos sin procesar, ingredientes culinarios procesados y alimentos procesados según la clasificación NOVA. Los relatos tuvieron un intenso despliegue de emociones y sentimientos manifestados al narrar las técnicas de elaboración y los momentos de preparación. Es necesario continuar trabajando en investigaciones que profundicen el estudio de las relaciones entre lo biológico y lo cultural de la alimentación. incorporando la comensalidad en un pie de igualdad con variables biológicas. así como en las acciones de salud-enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;23(supl.2): 50-55, oct. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2269</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comer en la Patagonia: relatos de comidas de mujeres adultas argentinas. Año 2016</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
