<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138252</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fine-needle aspiration in an extremely late post-traumatic iris cyst</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical case: A 45 year-old woman with unknown ophthalmology history complained of pain, redness and visual acuity (VA) loss in her left eye for the last three weeks. A serous iris cyst with an overlying peripheral corneal leukoma was located in the iris stroma using ultrasonic biomicroscopy. It was assumed that it was secondary to a penetrating trauma from her childhood. The cyst healed and VA improved after fine-needle aspiration and partial posterior synechiolysis. Discussion: Iris inclusion cysts may appear many years after penetrating trauma or surgery. Fine-needle aspiration is a good choice for its diagnosis and treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Batlle, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador Playà, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedemonte-Sarrias, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fusté Fusares, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Una mujer de 45 años sin antecedentes oftalmológicos conocidos consultó por ojo izquierdo rojo y doloroso con disminución de la agudeza visual (AV) de 3 semanas de evolución. Se localizó un quiste iridiano estromal seroso adyacente a leucoma corneal mediante biomicroscopía ultrasónica. Se orientó como secundario a traumatismo penetrante en la infancia. Tras punción-aspiración con aguja fina (PAAF) y sinequiolisis posterior parcial se resolvió el quiste y mejoró la AV. Discusión: Los quistes iridianos de inclusión pueden aparecer muchos años después de un traumatismo penetrante o cirugía. La PAAF es una buena opción para su diagnóstico y tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;90(7): 324-326, jul. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138252</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Punción-aspiración con aguja fina en quiste iridiano postraumático de aparición muy tardía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7666^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23315^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3969^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
