<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61683</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of an educational intervention in elderly patients with heart failure performed by nurses using a standardized care plan</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo determine the impact of an educational intervention after discharge in patients with heart failure (HF) performed by applying a standardized care plan centered on encouraging self-care and treatment adherence.Material and methodsWe performed a longitudinal study between January, 2006 and May, 2007 in a population of 112 patients selected after being included in a clinical pathway during their hospital stay. Five scheduled visits were made in the first 2 months after hospital discharge; during these visits, an educational care plan was applied to the patients individually and by means of an interview in the HF day hospital. The patients&#146; level of knowledge was quantified by means of a 5-point Likert-like scale. The education was carefully evaluated at each visit. The results were expressed as means. To compare the variables, a repeated measures ANOVA was used.ResultsThe mean age of the 100 patients who finalized both phases of the study was 78 years (SD: 7). The intervention was effective in evaluating the level of knowledge acquired by the patients about their disease (signs, symptoms, complications, etc.) and statistically significant differences were obtained in the education acquired at each visit and throughout the 60-day intervention.ConclusionsHealth education in these patients and their families (main caregiver) improved their adaptation to their disease and increased autonomy and treatment adherence, thus improving quality of life(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Páez-Gutiérrez, Tomás David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yera-Casas, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos-Higuera del Olmo, Sacramento</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrero-Lobo, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoDeterminar el impacto de la intervención educativa de enfermería postalta, en pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca (IC), al aplicar un plan de cuidados estandarizado centrado en fomentar el autocuidado.Material y métodosEstudio longitudinal realizado entre enero de 2006 y mayo de 2007, con una población de 112 pacientes, seleccionados tras ser incluidos en una vía clínica durante su hospitalización. Durante 5 sesiones programadas a lo largo de 2 meses tras el alta hospitalaria se les aplicó un plan de cuidados educativo mediante entrevista y de forma individual en el hospital de día de IC. El nivel de conocimientos adquiridos por el paciente se cuantificó mediante una escala de medida tipo Likert de 5 puntos. La educación se evaluó en cada una de las 5 sesiones realizadas. Los resultados se expresan en medias, y para comparar las variables se ha utilizado el test ANOVA de medidas repetidas.ResultadosLa media de edad de los 100 sujetos que completaron el estudio pre y postintervención educativa fue de 78 años (desviación estándar: 7). La intervención se mostró efectiva al evaluar el nivel de conocimiento adquirido por el paciente con respecto a su enfermedad (signos, síntomas, complicaciones, etc.), y se obtuvieron diferencias estadísticamente significativas acerca de la educación adquirida en cada visita y a lo largo de los 60 días de intervención.ConclusionesLa educación para la salud de estos pacientes y familia (cuidador principal), mejora su adaptación a la enfermedad, se logra una mayor autonomía y adhesión al tratamiento, consiguiendo una mayor calidad de vida(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);19(4): 191-198, jul.-ago. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61683</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la intervención educativa al paciente anciano con insuficiencia cardíaca, realizada por enfermería a través de un plan de cuidados estandarizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
