<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82020</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A program to protocolize nursing care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To decrease variability in clinical practice and to standardise and develop a systematic care programusing nursing care protocols. Materials and methods. The Directorate of Nursing of the Gregorio Marañón Hospital decided to develop a systematic program to produce nursing care protocols in 2004. It followed 5 phases: preparation, processing, dissemination, evaluation and updating. The program was based on the methodology for continuous improvement cycle (PDCA). Particular attention was paid to the evaluation phase, and to the three types of tools used: evaluation of the process and performance indicators and a survey on the perception of professionals. Results. A total of 30 protocols and 80 procedures were developed. They were evidence based, accessible, available for updating and with evaluation indicators. Discussion. Nursing care protocols decrease the variability of clinical practice. They homogenize care and increase the involvement of professionals. The evaluation of the process, outcomes and adherence of professionals is imperative for continuous improvement(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanchidrián de Blas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plá Mestre, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmedo Lucerón, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puente González, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Disminuir la variabilidad de la práctica clínica y homogeneizar y sistematizar los cuidados que prestan los profesionales mediante la protocolización de los cuidados de enfermería. Material y métodos. La dirección de enfermería del Hospital Gregorio Marañón en 2004 decidió desarrollar una sistemática para la protocolización de los cuidados de enfermería en 5 fases temporales: preparación, elaboración, difusión, evaluación y actualización, y que adquiriera el carácter de actividad continuada basada en la metodología del ciclo de mejora continua (PDCA). Se presta especial atención a la fase de la evaluación y a los tres tipos de herramientas utilizadas: evaluación de los indicadores de proceso, evaluación de los indicadores de resultados y encuesta sobre la percepción de los profesionales. Resultados. Elaboración de 30 protocolos y 80 procedimientos basados en la evidencia, accesibles, actualizables y con indicadores de evaluación. Discusión. La protocolización de los cuidados de enfermería disminuye la variabilidad de la práctica clínica, homogeneiza los cuidados y aumenta la implicación de los profesionales. La evaluación de proceso, de resultados y de adhesión de los profesionales es una parte imprescindible para la mejora continua(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(5): 268-274, sept.-oct. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sistemática para la protocolización de los cuidados de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
