<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140807</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Traumatic lesions of oral mucosa in older adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Among the oral pathology associated with geriatric patients we found more often we with traumatic injuries. The physiological changes that occurs during aging, makes that oral structures would be more susceptible to the action of irritants or traumatic agents, so it is important to establish different protocols for prevention and early diagnosis. In this paper we will review the major traumatic injuries found in the elderly patient depending on the time of evolution and so we classify the lesions in acute and chronic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sánchez, AF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Carreras Presas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Somacarrera Pérez, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro de la patología oral asociada con mayor frecuencia al paciente geriátrico nos encontramos con las lesiones con origen traumático. Los cambios fisiológicos que tienen lugar durante el envejecimiento hacen que las estructuras orales sean más susceptibles a la acción de agentes irritantes o agentes traumáticos, por lo que es importante establecer protocolos de prevención y diagnóstico precoz. En este artículo abordaremos las principales lesiones traumáticas que encontramos en el paciente anciano en función del tiempo de evolución, así clasificaremos las lesiones en agudas y crónicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;31(3): 129-134, mayo-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones traumáticas en la mucosa oral de los adultos mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28906^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19050^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
