<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057681</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Blood pressure and lipid control and coronary risk in the hypertensive population attended in Primary Care setting in Spain. The PRESCOT study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives and methods. The aim of this cross-sectional and multicenter study was to determine the coronary risk of hypertensive patients attended in Spanish Primary Care and to evaluate whether blood pressure and LDL-cholesterol (LDL-c) control rates could change according to the ATP-III risk groups. Good blood pressure control was considered &lt;140/90 mmHg (&lt;130/80 mmHg for diabetics) and LDL-c according to the established by ATP-III for every risk group.                 Results. A total of 12,954 patients were included in the study (49.9 % women, mean age 62.1±10.7 years). Of these, 12.6% belonged to the group of low risk, 45% to the medium risk group and 42.4% to the high risk group. The control rates were different according to the risk group (p &lt;0.0001). Blood pressure control: 37.5 % in low risk, 30.2 % in medium and 15.4 % in high risk group. LDL-c control: 65.6 % in low risk group, 28 % in medium risk group and 12.3 % in high risk group. Only 25.8 % of the patients of low risk were controlled for both blood pressure and LDL-c, 9.6 % of medium risk group and 2.7 % of high risk group.                 Conclusions. The majority of hypertensive patients daily attended in Primary Care setting in Spain belongs to the medium or high coronary risk groups. Blood pressure and LDL-c controls rates in hypertensive population are low, and very few patients have both risk factors controlled. The control rates decline when the risk increases. In fact, less than 3% of high-risk patients have both parameters well controlled, what may result in significant clinical implications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llisterri, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matalí, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegría, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo y métodos. El objetivo de este trabajo, de diseño transversal y multicéntrico, fue conocer el perfil de riesgo coronario de los pacientes hipertensos que acuden a la consulta de Atención Primaria, y evaluar si el control de presión arterial y de colesterol LDL podía variar según el grupo de riesgo coronario ATP-III. Se consideró buen control de presión arterial cifras menores a 140/90 mmHg (&lt; 130/80 mmHg en diabéticos) y de colesterol LDL los establecidos para ATP-III para cada grupo de riesgo.                 Resultados. Se incluyeron 12.954 pacientes (49,9% mujeres, 62,1 ± 10,7 años). El 12,6% pertenecía al grupo de bajo riesgo, el 45% al de riesgo medio y el 42,4% al de riesgo alto. El grado de control fue diferente según el grupo de riesgo (p &lt; 0,0001). Así, para la presión arterial se alcanzó en un 37,5% de los sujetos de riesgo bajo, en un 30,2% de los del grupo de riesgo medio y en un 15,4% de los de riesgo alto, y para el colesterol LDL se consiguió en el 65,6% del grupo de riesgo bajo, el 28% del de riesgo medio y el 12,3% del de riesgo alto. Globalmente, si consideramos el control adecuado de presión arterial y de colesterol LDL, sólo el 25,8% de los de bajo riesgo estaba controlado, el 9,6% de los de riesgo medio y el 2,7% de los de riesgo alto.                 Conclusiones. La mayoría de los hipertensos asistidos diariamente en Atención Primaria en España son de riesgo medio o alto. Las cifras de control de presión arterial y colesterol LDL en los hipertensos en general son bajas y son muy pocos los pacientes que tienen cifras adecuadas de ambos factores de riesgo. Pero las tasas de control son aún peores según aumenta el riesgo coronario; de hecho, menos del 3% de los pacientes de alto riesgo tienen bien controlados ambos parámetros, con las implicaciones clínicas que ello conlleva</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(4): 172-178, abr.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057681</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control de presión arterial y lípidos y riesgo coronario en la población hipertensa asistida en Atención Primaria en España. Estudio PRESCOT</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8252^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
