<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166532</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transcultural study of perceived competence in physical education and leisure time</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective was to analyze the influence of perceived competence on gender, the pattern of physical-sport activity and the stages of change in the practice of physical activity in leisure. The sample was of 2168 students of the first course of Compulsory Secondary Education, of Costa Rica (423), Mexico (408) and Spain (1337). Chi-square (x2), t-student, ANOVA and univariate linear model analyzes were performed. The students with the highest index of practice and in active stages presented a greater perceived competence, also being superior in the boys than in the girls. From the results of this research, it is very probably that most schoolchildren will not become physically active. Therefore, in the three countries there is a low level of physical-sport activity that could be improved through methodological designs in Physical Education aimed at improving perceived competence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vílchez, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Juan, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo fue analizar la influencia de la competencia percibida en el sexo, el patrón de actividad físico-deportiva y las etapas de cambio en la práctica de actividad físico-deportiva de tiempo libre. La muestra fue de 2168 estudiantes del primer curso de Enseñanza Secundaria Obligatoria, de Costa Rica (423), México (408) y España (1337). Se realizaron análisis de Chi-cuadrado (x2), t-student, ANOVA y modelo lineal univariante. Los alumnos con mayor índice de práctica y en etapas activas presentaron una mayor competencia percibida, siendo superior también en los chicos que en las chicas. Por los resultados de esta investigación, hay pocas posibilidades de que la mayoría de los escolares lleguen a ser físicamente activos. Por tanto, en los tres países existe un nivel bajo de actividad físico-deportiva que podría mejorar a través de diseños metodológicos en la Educación Física escolar orientados a la mejora de competencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;17(67): 573-587, sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio transcultural de la percepción de competencia escolar y tiempo de ocio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52938^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8076</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
