<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044630</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Survival in patients with myeloma treated with dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Renal failure is a common complication of myeloma. Renal replacement        therapy in these patients is controversial due to poor survival outcomes and        low tolerance to treatment. We reviewed our experience on patients with myeloma        undergoing dialysis therapy at one centre.        Patients and methods: Between 1980 and 2000, 28 patients (21 men and 7        women) with myeloma were admitted to chronic dialysis programme and the following        variables were analysed: sex, age when starting dialysis, lapse of time between        diagnosis of myeloma and admission to dialysis (TD), disease stage, comorbidity,        mode of presentation, calcium, creatinine at diagnostic, albumin and Hb at        the beginning of dialysis, and cause of death. We studied survival among these patients        (Kaplan-Meier), identified predictors of survival outcome (Cox&#146;s regression) and        compared survival between the two decades studied.        Results: Mean age was 65 years, median TD was 0.4 months, and modes of presentation        were: end-stage renal failure (18 patients), acute renal failure (8), amyloldosis        (2). Eleven patients (39%) had myeloma IgG, four (14%) lgA and thirteen (46%)        had light chains. Kappa light chain was the most frequent one. In 75% of patients        myeloma was at Illb stage. Cause of death were: Cardiovascular disease (5 patients),        infections (4), suspension of treatment (4), tumours (4), and others causes (2). Median        survival for all patients was 16.8 months (range 0.4-78) and 25% survived over        39 months. Hb level was the only significant predictor in the multivariant analysis        (p = 0.02). In the 80&#146;s median survival was 6.17 months versus 17 months in the        90's but this difference was not significant with long- rank test.        Conclusion: Although survival of patients with myeloma treated with dialysis is        still short, 25 percent survives over 3 years, being Hb level the only predictive factor.        Moreover, we observed an improvement of survival in recent years</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Reyes, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Novales, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La insuficiencia renal es una complicación frecuente del mieloma        (MM). La indicación de tratamiento sustitutivo de la función renal en estos pacientes        es controvertida, debido a mala supervivencia y tolerancia. Se revisa la experiencia        de nuestro centro con todos los pacientes diagnosticados de MM durante        los últimos 20 años y admitidos a programa de diálisis crónica.        Pacientes y métodos: Se estudian 28 pacientes (21 hombres y 7 mujeres) con        MM y que iniciaron tratamiento con diálisis entre los años 1980 y 2000 en los que        se evaluaron variables clínicas y analíticas: sexo, edad al inicio de diálisis, tiempo        entre el diagnóstico y la entrada en diálisis (TD), estadio de la enfermedad, presencia        de comorbilidad, forma de presentación, calcio sérico, creatinina en el momento        del diagnóstico, albúmina, hemoglobina al inicio de la diálisis (Hb) y causa        de muerte. Se estudia también la supervivencia (método de Kaplan-Meier) y se trató        de identificar variables predictoras con el análisis de regresión de Cox. Para valorar        la respuesta al tratamiento se dividieron los casos aparecidos en dos períodos        de diez años.        Resultados: Con una edad media de 65 años, la mediana para el intervalo diagnóstico        inicio diálisis (TD) fue de 0,4 meses. En 18 casos la afectación renal se presentó        como insuficiencia renal crónica, fracaso renal agudo en 8 y amiloidosis en        2. Once pacientes (39%) fueron MM IgG, 4 (14%) IgA, y 13 (46%) con cadenas ligeras.        El 75% presentaban un estadio IIIb. Las causas de muerte fueron: cardiovasculares        en 5 casos, infecciones en 4, cese del tratamiento en 4, tumoral en 4 y        otras en 2. La mediana de la supervivencia fue de 16,8 meses para todo el grupo        (rango 0,4-78), y en el análisis multivariante sólo las concentraciones de hemoglobina        resultaron predictivas (p = 0,02). El 25% de los pacientes sobrevivió 39 meses.        En la década de los ochenta la mediana fue de 6,17 meses y para los noventa de        17 meses. Esta diferencia no alcanzó significación estadística con el log-rank test (p        = 0,12).        Conclusión: Aunque la supervivencia de los pacientes con MM en diálisis sigue        siendo baja, una proporción estimable sobrevive más de tres años y además se evidencia        una tendencia hacia una mayor supervivencia en la última década. La Hb        fue la única variable predictora encontrada</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;23(2): 131-136, mar.-abr. 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044630</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Supervivencia de pacientes con mieloma tratados con diálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22198^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8281^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22288^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
