<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129604</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Simulation and deception in assessing practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">When a patient goes to the welfare doctor, its main interest is, in general, cured being of its disease; but in the evaluator medicine usually they are in game other very different interests (mainly economic, although also another type of social benefits, for example), reason why is not infrequent that the patient, or subject object of the valuation, tries to obtain the greater possible benefit of his situation, even using all type of ruses (exaggeration, simulation, dissimulation, etc.) to try to deceive the evaluator doctor on the gravity or functional affectation that produces the pathology to him that presents/displays or alleges. This is not something new, and we can find numerous antecedents throughout History, as much religious (Bible, for example), like civilian (Greek books of history, Literature, etc.) and medical (Hippocrates, Galen, etc.). The purpose of the simulation is always the same one, and some of the methods also used, but also they have been developed diverse techniques to obtain it and, therefore, also to detect it. Diverse medical authors have tried to describe the indicators that can orient towards the existence of some type of simulation, they have established technical to try to arrive at his diagnosis and differentiation from the real affectation, and have described to the different forms or modalities in which it is possible to be presented/displayed. With this article it is tried "to ignite" in the conscience of the evaluator doctor "the light bulb" that makes think him about its existence, and to indicate some tools to him that him can be useful in their daily task (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Salazar, César Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Cuando un paciente acude al médico asistencial, su principal interés es, en general, ser curado de su enfermedad; pero en la medicina evaluadora suelen estar en juego otros intereses muy distintos (principalmente económicos, aunque también otro tipo de prestaciones sociales, por ejemplo), por lo que no es infrecuente que el paciente, o sujeto objeto de la valoración, intente obtener el mayor beneficio posible de su situación, incluso utilizando todo tipo de artimañas (exageración, simulación, disimulación, etc.) para intentar engañar al médico evaluador sobre la gravedad o afectación funcional que le produce la patología que presenta o alega. Esto no es algo nuevo, y podemos encontrar numerosos antecedentes a lo largo de la Historia, tanto religiosa (Biblia, por ejemplo), como civil (libros de historia griegos, literatura, etc.) y médica (Hipócrates, Galeno, etc.). La finalidad de la simulación es siempre la misma, y algunos de los métodos empleados también, pero también han ido desarrollándose diversas técnicas para lograrla y, por ende, también para detectarla.  Diversos autores médicos han intentado describir los indicadores que pueden orientar hacia la existencia de algún tipo de simulación, han establecido técnicas para intentar llegar a su diagnóstico y diferenciación de la afectación real, y han descrito las distintas formas o modalidades en que se puede presentar. Con este artículo se intenta "encender" en la conciencia del médico valorador "la bombilla" que le haga pensar en su existencia, y señalarle algunas herramientas que le pueden ser útiles en su quehacer diario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;60(235): 379-391, abr.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129604</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La simulación y disimulación en medicina evaluadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8479^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
