<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106574</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of urotherapy in the management of urinary incontinence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this essay is to present our initial results in applying urotherapy to patients with urinary incontinence not responding to pharmacological treatment. We performed ach art review of all the patients treated with urotherapy in our institution. We included all children with incontinence refractory to pharmacological treatment, giggle incontinence, underactive bladder, overactive bladder and dysfunctional voiding. 12 patients completed follow up. Mean age was 8.5 years. The most frequent finding in cystomanometry was detrusor over activity (58.33%). We achieved full response in 83.3% of our patients, 8 of them without any pharmacological treatment, and another 2 with associated administration of desmopressin. Only two patients did not respond to therapy. Urotherapy is an important part of management of lower urinary tract dysfunction in children. Careful selection of the patients and adequate use of every intervention are crucial for its effectiveness(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Vázquez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Zegarra, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Herrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Fraile, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aransay Bramtot, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Carretero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezalí Barbancho, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morante Valverde, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maruszewski, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar nuestros resultados del abordaje de la incontinencia diurna refractaria al tratamiento médico mediante uroterapia. Para ello, se han revisado retrospectivamente las historias de los niños sometidos a este tipo de tratamiento en nuestro centro. Los criterios de inclusión fueron niños con incontinencia diurna refractarios al tratamiento farmacológico, incontinencia de la risa, vejiga hipoactiva y niños en los que se detectó en la cistomanometría una hiperactividad del detrusor y/o incoordinación vesicoesfinteriana. Doce pacientes completaron el seguimiento, con una media de edad de 8,5 años. La indicación más frecuente fue la incontinencia con hiperactividad del detrusor (58,33%). Los resultados fueron satisfactorios en el 83,3% de los casos, con desaparición de los síntomas en 8 pacientes sin tratamiento médico asociado, y 2 más con tratamiento asociado para la eneuresis nocturna. Sólo dos pacientes no presentaron mejoría. La uroterapia es una parte importante del abordaje de la disfunción del tracto urinario inferior en la edad pediátrica. Cabe destacar la importancia de la correcta selección de pacientes y la aplicación adecuada de las diferentes intervenciones, entre las que el biofeedback con imágenes animadas desempeña un papel fundamental(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;70(8): 322-325, sept. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106574</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uroterapia en el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12623^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12623^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30747^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1700</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4855^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8961^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
