<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163614</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of immunomodulatory therapy with interferon-&amp;#946; or glatiramer acetate on multiple sclerosis-associated uveitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To analyse the role of interferon-&amp;#946; or glatiramer acetate in reducing the inflammatory episodes of intra-ocular inflammation in multiple sclerosis-associated uveitis. Method: A study was conducted on a non-randomised, retrospective case series of 13 patients with proven multiple sclerosis and uveitis (minimum follow-up, 12 months). All patients were given immunomodulatory treatment (interferon-&amp;#946; or glatiramer acetate) to control the course of the multiple sclerosis. Patients were compared to themselves before initiating the treatment, in order to assess the difference in uveitis episodes. The main outcome measurements were the number of uveitis episodes with/without immunomodulatory treatment. Results: Uveitis was bilateral in 10 (77%) out of 13 patients. Intermediate uveitis was observed in 11 patients, retinal vasculitis in 3 patients, and one patient was classified as a posterior uveitis. The patients had a mean of 4.15±3.1 episodes of uveitis (range 1-10) during the follow-up period (148.6±84.3 months). When compared to their pre-treatment status, patients on treatment with interferon-&amp;#946; or glatiramer acetate showed a significant decrease of 0.36 episodes of ocular inflammation per year (P =.02). Mild side effects related to immunomodulatory treatment were observed in 6 (46%) patients, 3 (23%) patients with a flu-like syndrome, and 3 (23%) patients with a skin rash. Conclusions: Interferon &amp;#946; or glatiramer acetate could be effective in reducing the uveitis episodes in patients with multiple sclerosis-associated uveitis, and was well tolerated in most patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Macia-Badia, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura-García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcos-Algaba, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Arumí, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velazquez-Villoria, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velez-Escola, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor Idoate, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la eficacia del interferón-&amp;#946; o acetato de glatirámero en reducir los episodios de inflamación intraocular en pacientes con uveítis asociada a esclerosis múltiple. Método: Estudio no aleatorizado, retrospectivo de serie de casos de 13 pacientes con diagnóstico definitivo de esclerosis múltiple y uveítis (seguimiento mínimo, 12 meses). Todos los pacientes fueron tratados con terapia inmunomoduladora (interferón-&amp;#946; o acetato de glatirámero) para controlar el curso de la esclerosis múltiple. Los pacientes fueron comparados con ellos mismos antes de iniciar el tratamiento inmunomodulador para valorar la diferencia en los episodios de uveítis. Variable principal de medida: número de episodios de uveítis con/sin tratamiento inmunomodulador. Resultados: Los brotes de uveítis fueron bilaterales en 10 de 13 pacientes (77%). Once pacientes fueron clasificados como uveítis intermedias, 3 pacientes como vasculitis retiniana y un paciente como uveítis posterior. Los pacientes tuvieron una media de 4,15±3,1 episodios de uveítis (rango 1-10) a lo largo del seguimiento (148,6±84,3 meses). Los pacientes bajo tratamiento con interferón-&amp;#946; o acetato de glatirámero mostraron una reducción significativa de 0,36 episodios de inflamación intraocular al año (p = 0,02) comparados con ellos mismos antes de iniciar el tratamiento. Seis pacientes (46%) mostraron efectos secundarios leves asociados al tratamiento inmunomodulador (3 pacientes [23%] síndrome seudogripal; 3 pacientes [23%] rash cutáneo). Conclusiones: El interferón-&amp;#946; o acetato de glatirámero podrían ser efectivos en reducir los brotes de inflamación intraocular en pacientes con uveítis asociada a esclerosis múltiple, siendo bien tolerados por la mayoría de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(6): 273-279, jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163614</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia del tratamiento inmunomodulador con interferón-&amp;#946; o acetato de glatirámero en las uveítis asociadas a esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55963^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30032^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30674^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
