<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66894</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The prostate biopsy is the only valid tool to diagnose the existence of cancer of prostate. The indications of the biopsy, according with EAU, are the existence of high PSA, increased velocity PSA and a rectal suspicious tact. Objectives: validation of the utility of the prostate biopsy, to know the value of the PSA as a marker of prostate cancer in our way and to value the indication and efficiency of repeated biopsies. Material and methods: we practice a manual review of the biopsies in our hospital, between the years 1990 and 2002. We study the level of PSA before the biopsy, number of prostatic cores and histologic information of the biopsy. A statistical descriptive and inferencial study has been performed by SPSS 12.0 package. Results: The total number of biopsies registered was a 1202, with 36.96 % of biopsy positive. The PSA before the biopsy (available in the biopsies realized between the year 1999 and 2002: 578 biopsies, 48.08 % of the whole) was&gt; 10 ng/ml in 55,88 % of these patients, 4-10 ng/ml in 39.27 % and 0-4ng/ml in 4.84 %. The average and PSA&#146;s median is of 19.09 (standard error: 1.87) and 10.6, respectively. The positividad of the biopsy increases with PSA&#146;s level: 48,61 % with PSA&gt; 10; 25.11 % with PSA 4-10and 21,4 % in patients with PSA &lt;4. There was realized prostate rebiopsy (2 ó more biopsies) in 132 patients (21,97 % positive) 88,36 % of the cancers was diagnosed in the first biopsy, and 6.62 % in the second one (94,98% of the diagnoses of cancer of prostate carried out with the first 2 biopsies).Conclusions: The information obtained in the study by means of the descriptive analysis of our series meets in conformity the published in other studies and publications. There exists a need to increase the diagnostic profitability of the biopsy of prostate, for which we have introduced a protocol of biopsy under local anesthesia in order to be able to increase the number of obtained cylinders (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escudero Bregante, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, P. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rigabert Montiel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Albacete, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cao Avellaneda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maluff Torres, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Cubillana, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tornero Ruíz, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gómez, G. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La biopsia prostática es la única herramienta válida para diagnosticar la existencia de cáncer de próstata. Las indicaciones para su realización según la Asociación Europea de Urología son la existencia de PSA elevado, velocidad aumentada y la evidencia de un tacto rectal sospechoso. Objetivos: Valoración tanto de la utilidad clínica de la biopsia prostática, como del PSA como marcador de cáncer de próstata en nuestro medio y la indicación y eficacia de sucesivas biopsias. Material y Métodos: Efectuamos una revisión manual de las biopsias realizadas en nuestro servicio entre los años 1990 y 2002, valorando nivel de PSA previo a la biopsia, número de cilindros obtenidos y datos de la biopsia. Se llevó a cabo un estudio estadístico descriptivo mediante el programa estadístico SPSS 12.0. Resultados: Se han realizado 1202 biopsias en este periodo, con un porcentaje de positividad global del 36.96%. El PSA previo a la biopsia (disponible en las biopsias realizadas entre los años 1999 y 2002: 578 biopsias, 48.08% del total) era &gt;10 ng/ml en el 55,88% de estos pacientes, 4-10 ng/ml en el 39.27% y 0-4ng/ml en el 4,84%. La media y mediana de PSA es de 19,09 (error típico: 1,87) y 10,6, respectivamente. La positividad de la biopsia aumenta con el nivel de PSA: 21,4% en pacientes con PSA&lt;4; 25,11% con PSA 4-10 y 48,61% con PSA &gt;10. Fue realizada rebiopsia prostática en 132 pacientes (21,97% positivas) El 88,36%de los cánceres fueron diagnosticados en la primera biopsia, y un 6,62% en la segunda (94,98% de los diagnósticos de cáncer de próstata se realizaron con las 2 primeras biopsias). Conclusiones: Los datos obtenidos en el estudio mediante el análisis descriptivo de nuestra serie se encuentran en concordancia con lo publicado en otros estudios y publicaciones. Existe una necesidad de aumentar la rentabilidad diagnóstica de la biopsia de próstata, para lo cual hemos introducido un protocolo de biopsia bajo anestesia local con el fin de poder aumentar el número de cilindros obtenidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;32(7): 713-716, jul.-ago. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66894</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11912^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
