<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-25877</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attentiveness and activity faced to persons and physical objects in the first year of life: The role of temperament</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This longitudinal study aimed to investigate the extent at what the temperament dimensions of attentiveness and activity can be used to examine the distinctive patterns showed by infants when they were faced with both persons and physical objects in the first year of life. 51 full-term infants, without any pre and post-natal complication, and belonging to a middle-class socioeconomic status took part in this study. These infants were faced, at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months of age, to different situations involving both social (persons) and physical objects in order to assess their attentiveness and activity. The results indicated that the infants showed higher levels of attentiveness and activity when facing to physical objects than to persons. These results are discussed taking into account the infant development, and the main theoretical orientations on the topic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Herrero, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-López, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio pretendemos investigar, con una metodología longitudinal, si las dimensiones temperamentales de atención y nivel de actividad nos permiten examinar patrones distintivos mostrados por los niños, en el primer año de vida, cuando están ante personas y objetos físicos. Participaron 51 niños, nacidos a término, sin complicaciones pre ni postnatales y pertenecientes a un nivel socioeconómico medio. Estos niños, a los 3, 6, 9 y 12 meses de edad, fueron sometidos en el laboratorio a situaciones en las que se enfrentaban a objetos físicos y sociales (personas) para evaluar su atención y nivel de actividad. Los resultados indican que los niños muestran una mayor atención y un nivel de actividad más elevado en presencia de objetos físicos que ante personas. Estos resultados se discuten en función del desarrollo evolutivo del niño y a la luz de las investigaciones actuales sobre el tema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(2): 234-240, mayo 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-25877</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención y nivel de actividad hacia personas y objetos físicos durante el primer año de vida: el papel del temperamento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11416^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13321</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14072</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5690</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
