<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112113</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Invisible care: Is it adequately recognised?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Invisible care is a central and fundamental feature of nursing practice and the base of its professional identity. Nursing has undergone an important and positive process of professionalization in the last 150 years. Nonetheless, invisible nursing care is still under-recognised, despite its importance for the recovery and quality of life of users. In this article, we briefly analyse the major societal transformations, which demands us to rethink the need to make invisible care visible; and then we place key questions to tackle this issue and suggest concrete actions to advance in this recognition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosa Eduardo, Rosanna De la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamora Monge, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cuidados invisibles son un elemento central y fundamental de la práctica de la Enfermería y son la base de su identidad profesional. La Enfermería ha sufrido un importante y positivo proceso de profesionalización en los últimos 150 años, sin embargo, los cuidados invisibles siguen siendo poco reconocidos, a pesar de su importancia en la recuperación y en la calidad de vida de los usuarios. En este trabajo se analizan brevemente las grandes transformaciones sociales actuales que obligan a replantearse la necesidad de visibilizar los cuidados invisibles, se plantean interrogantes clave para abordar esta discusión y se proponen una serie de acciones concretas para avanzar en este reconocimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;21(4): 219-223, oct.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados invisibles: ¿son suficientemente reconocidos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
