<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84719</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional assessment of patients candidates for waiting list simultaneous kidney pancreas transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Simultaneous Kidney Pancreas transplantation is currently the treatment of choice for patients with type 1 diabetes ERD advanced. Scientific studies on the therapeutic benefits of this guarantee acceptance of it as the most suitable for patients. The independence of dialysis and insulin therapy after the transplant represents a significant increase in the quality of life for these patients. In recent years, the importance of nutritional assessment in patients with chronic diseases has increased. There is increasing evidence that malnutrition is associated with an increased risk of morbidity and mortality after surgery. Given the therapeutic choice for these patients and the importance of nutritional status as an independent risk factor for post-transplant complications objective of our work is to describe the nutritional status of patients who are candidates for transplant through objective and subjective parameters of evaluation nutritional. Materials and methods: We included 45 patients with type 1 diabetes ERD interned in the Hospital Italiano of Buenos Aires for assessing pre Transplantation during the period June 2007-June 2008.Se collected data through a sheet produced by themselves. As parameter anthropometric was calculated body mass index (BMI) by the formula Quetelet (post dialysis Weight (kg) / height 2 (m)) and was ranked as the ranges proposed by the committee of experts from WHO. As a subjective argument took place the Subjective Global Valuation (VGS), which ranked patients in well-nourished (A), mild malnourished (B), moderately malnourished (C) and severely malnourished (D). As biochemical parameters of the data was recorded serum albumin (g / dl) to hospitalizations and this data was obtained from the patient's medical history. Results: The value of the average BMI of the total population was 21.83 ± 2.65. According to the sex values were: 21.83 ± 2.39 and 21.82 ± 2.95 for male and female respectively. The nutritional status according to this indicator was anthropometric Normal in 89% of cases. The 6.66% of the cases submitted 13.33% pre malnutrition and obesity. We found no cases with obesity. Taking into account the albumin 47.45% of patients presented moderate risk of morbidity and mortality. According to GSV 62.22% were classified as well-nourished (Class A). It was the equitable proportion of women and hombres.33, 33% were classified as mild malnourished (Class B). Only 2 cases (8.88%) had moderate malnutrition (Class C). None presented malnutrition Graves (Class C). Conclussion: In our study we can see that patients are candidates for waiting list while normal BMI have presented evidence of nutritional risk when one takes into account the VGS and the average value of albumin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sun Ho, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grosembacher, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodota, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delfante, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Koll, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El trasplante renopancreático es en la actualidad el tratamiento elegido para los pacientes diabéticos tipo 1 con ERD avanzada. Estudios científicos sobre los beneficios de esta terapéutica avalan la aceptación de la misma como lo más adecuado para los pacientes. La independencia de diálisis y de tratamiento insulínico luego del trasplante representa un importante incremento en la calidad de vida de esos pacientes. En los últimos años, la importancia de la evaluación nutricional en pacientes con enfermedades crónicas ha aumentado. Existe cada vez más evidencia científica que la malnutrición esta asociada a un riesgo mayor de morbilidad y mortalidad post intervención quirúrgica. Teniendo en cuenta la terapéutica elegida para estos pacientes y la importancia del estado nutricional como factor predictor independiente de riesgo de complicaciones post trasplante es objetivo de nuestro trabajo describir el estado nutricional de los pacientes candidatos a trasplante renopancreatico a través de parámetros objetivos y subjetivos de valoración nutricional. Materiales y métodos: Se incluyeron 45 pacientes Diabéticos tipo 1 con ERD internados en el Hospital Italiano de Buenos Aires para evaluación pre trasplante renopancreático durante el período Junio 2007-Junio 2008. Se recolectaron los datos mediante una ficha de elaboración propia. Como parámetro antropométrico se calculó el Índice de Masa corporal (IMC) mediante la fórmula de Quetelet (Peso post diálisis (kg)/talla 2 (mts)) y se clasificó según los rangos propuestos por el comité de Expertos de la OMS. Como parámetro subjetivo se realizo la Valoración Global Subjetiva (VGS) que clasificó a los pacientes en Bien nutrido (A), desnutrido leve (B), desnutrido moderado (C) y desnutrido severo (D). Como parámetros bioquímicos se registró el dato de albúmina sérica (g/dl) al ingreso hospitalario y este dato se obtuvo de la historia clínica del paciente. Resultados: El valor de la media para IMC del total de la población fue de 21,83 ± 2,65. Según el sexo los valores fueron: 21,83 ± 2,39 y de 21,82 ± 2,95 para el sexo mascureprelino y femenino respectivamente. El estado nutricional según este indicador antropométrico fue Normal en el 89% de los casos. El 6,66% de los casos presentó desnutrición y 13,33% pre obesidad. No se encontraron casos con Obesidad. Teniendo en cuenta la albúmina el 47,45% de los pacientes presenta riesgo moderado de morbimortalidad. Según la VGS el 62,22% se clasificaron como bien nutridos (Clase A). Fue equitativa la proporción de mujeres y de hombres. 33,33% se clasificaron como desnutridos leve (Clase B). Sólo 2 casos (8,88%) presentaron desnutrición moderada (Clase C). Ninguno presentó desnutrición Graves (Clase C). Conclusión: En nuestro estudio se puede observar que los pacientes candidatos a lista de espera si bien presentan valores de IMC dentro de la clasificación normal presentan indicios de riesgo nutricional cuando se tienen en cuenta la VGS y el valor medio de albúmina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(3): 406-413, mayo-jun. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84719</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación nutricional de pacientes candidatos a lista de espera de trasplante renopancreático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
