<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77042</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Digging insistently in the void. Some reflections on the vicissitudes of objects in the work of Marguerite Duras</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Digging insistently in the void. Some reflections on the vicissitudes of objects in the work of Marguerite Duras. Due to an initial lack of psychic inscription and to an identification with the void meant for the subject by a traumatic lack of meaning which takes the form of &lt;nothing&gt;, Marguerite Dura´s writing becomes a specular object where the writer may look at herself in order to exist and to link the overflowing energy which threatens her. As a consequence of the specular catastrophe, Duras tries to return to her origins. Thanks to an actively sought formal regression, from an original feminine position common to both sexes, she will create her own mythographsy, realize her &lt;self-procreation&gt; and attempt to search an &lt;absolute image&gt; of narcissistic fulfillment. Writing of the inability to mourn the primary object, of the longing for the mother, of failure in moving form primary towards secondary identifications, predominance of primary identification contemporary to primary narcissism and primary homosexuality, of active repetition of what was passively endured; these are some of the aspects developed in the article (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burdet, Martina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A partir de una falta de inscripción psíquica inaugural y de una identificación con el vacío que supone para el sujeto una pérdida de sentido traumática  que toma forma de &lt;nada&gt; para Marguerite Duras, la escritura intenta constituirse como objeto especula donde la escritora podrá mirarse para existir y ligar la energía desbordante en la que se encuentra. Como consecuencia de la catástrofe especular ocurrida. Duras intenta volver a sus orígenes. Gracias a una regresión formal buscada activamente, desde su posición femenina originaria común para ambos sexos, va a crear su propia mitografía, realizar su autoengendrameinto, e intenta buscar una &lt;imagen absoluta&gt; de completud narcisista. Escritura de la imposibilidad de duelo con el objeto primario, añoranza de lo materno matricial, fracaso del paso de las identificaciones primarias a las secundarias, predominio de la identificación primaria contemporánea del narcisismo primario y de la homosexualidad primaria, repetición activa de lo padecido pasivamente son unos de los aspectos tratados en este artículo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(48): 251-266, dic. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77042</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cavando insistentemente en el vacío. Algunas reflexiones en torno a los avatares de los objetos en la obra de Marguerite Duras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23910^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7244</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8264</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
