<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101665</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability of the VIDA questionnaire for assessing instrumental activities of daily living (iADL) in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse the inter- and intra-examiner reliability of the VIDA questionnaire, and their concordance with the &#147;timed get up and go&#148; test in people aged + 75 years. Design: Descriptive study of a diagnostic test. Location: Primary Health Care. Subjects-intervention: Application of 71 pairs of VIDA questionnaire, by one (38) or two professionals (33), in people aged + 75 years with no significant sensory or physical-psychic impairment. Stratified sample based on ADL (Barthel index) to obtain a variety of responses that would ensure a range of scores of the questionnaire. Main measurements: Overall score of VIDA questionnaire, &#147;get up and go&#148; test (functional), Pfeiffer questionnaire (cognitive), and risk factors of frailty (comorbidity, falls, recent hospitalisation, sensory disturbance, social impairment, polypharmacy). Results: Mean age 81.3 years±4.8, with a 65.5% moderate-severe change in Barthel index. The mean score of the questionnaire was 31.3±7.9, with a rank of 11 to 38 (maximum). There were no differences according to gender (P= 0 .78). Inter-examiner reliability (n 33): Intraclass Correlation Coefficient (ICC) 0.94, 95% Confidence Interval (CI) 0.88-0.97, P&lt; 0 .0001. Intra-examiner reliability (n 38): ICC 0.96, CI 0.93-0.98, P&lt; 0 .0001. Correlation coefficient (rho of Spearman) with the &#147;get up and go&#148; test (n 67) 0.61 (moderate), P&lt; 0 .0001. Lower score if there are 2 or +  frailty factors (P= 0 .015). Conclusions: VIDA questionnaire is a very reliable tool, with no gender bias. It demonstrates an association with other functionality measures and with frailty factors in the elderly(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ganzarain Oyarbide, Elixabete</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urzay Atucha, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Lesende, Iñaki</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrero Jocano, Juan Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Minaña, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana Cantero, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la fiabilidad inter-intraobservador del cuestionario VIDA, aplicado en personas mayores de  75 años, y su concordancia con el test de «levántate y anda». Diseño: Estudio descriptivo de prueba diagnóstica. Emplazamiento: Centro de Salud, atención primaria. Participantes e intervención: Aplicación de 71 pares de cuestionarios VIDA, por un mismo (38 pacientes) o dos diferentes profesionales (33 pacientes), de personas de mas de 75 años sin déficit sensorial o físico-psíquico importantes. Captación consecutiva a través de un muestreo estratificado según diferentes grados de deterioro en actividades básicas de la vida diaria (ABVD, índice de Barthel). Mediciones principales: Puntuación global del cuestionario VIDA, tests de funcionalidad (Barthel, «levántate y anda»), cuestionario de Pfeiffer (cognitivo) y factores de riesgo de fragilidad (comorbilidad, caídas, hospitalización, polifarmacia, alteración sensorial, deficiencia social). Resultados: Edad media 81,3±4,8 años, 65,5% alteración moderada-severa en el índice de Barthel. Puntuación media en el cuestionario VIDA de 31,3, mediana 35; sin diferencias significativas según género (p 0,78). Coeficiente de correlación intraclase (CCI) para la fiabilidad interobservador 0,94 (IC 95% 0,88-0,97, p&lt;0,0001), y 0,96 (IC 95% 0,93-0,98, p&lt;0,0001) para la intraobservador. Correlación moderada (0,61, p&lt;0,0001), con el test de «levántate y anda», y peor puntuación cuando tenían 2 o mas  factores de riesgo de fragilidad (p=0,015). Conclusiones: El cuestionario VIDA es una herramienta muy fiable, sin presentar sesgo de género. Su medición se asocia con la de otras medidas de funcionalidad y con factores de fragilidad en el anciano(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;44(6): 309-317, jun. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101665</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad del cuestionario VIDA, para valoración de Actividades Instrumentales de la Vida Diaria (AIVD) en personas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
