<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161945</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">PRP into the epidural space for the management of intervertebral disc degeneration and axial pain. Preliminary report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intervertebral disc degeneration is a chronic disease that causes significant disability and dependence and exerts a high cost on society. It is the most common cause of back pain, and may involve any segment of the spine, being the lumbar the most frequently affected area. It is one of the most frequent reasons for consultation in the general population, second only to headache, affecting 80-85 % of people throughout life. Current therapeutic strategies are primary conservative, including physical therapy and anti-inflammatory medication. Surgical techniques are intended only to stabilize the spine and/or decompress the spinal or foraminal canal, searching for relieve of symptoms; however, do not address the cause of the degeneration and even accelerate the degeneration of adjacent segments. Understanding of the biology of platelet-rich plasma (PRP) and its effect on condral repair has led to the use of PRP as a promising biological therapeutic strategy for enhance the regenerative process and healing of the intervertebral disc. Very few studies have been conducted in vitro and there are even fewer clinical studies which link PRP with the management of degenerative disc disease. At present, there is no document linking PRP used in injection into the epidural space as a method of intervertebral disc regeneration in cases of disc disease. This is a preliminary study of pain management in patients with degenerative disc disease and axial pain, by using PRP injected into the epidural space, cervical or lumbar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cortés, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coral, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad discal degenerativa es un proceso crónico que produce importante discapacidad y dependencia y que genera un alto coste en la sanidad. Es la causa más común de dolor de espalda, que puede comprometer cualquier segmento del eje axial, siendo la región lumbar el sitio más frecuentemente afectado. Es uno de los motivos de consulta más frecuente en la población general, sólo superado por la cefalea, que afecta al 80-85 % de las personas a lo largo de la vida. El manejo realizado hasta el presente es usualmente de tipo conservador, incluyendo la terapia física y los antinflamatorios. Las técnicas quirúrgicas tienen como objetivo sólo el de estabilizar la columna y/o descomprimir el canal medular o foraminal, buscando el alivio del dolor; sin embargo, para nada corrigen la enfermedad de base asociada al desgaste de los discos intervertebrales, e incluso estas técnicas se han asociado con una aceleración del proceso de desgaste osteocondral. El conocimiento de los fundamentos biológicos del plasma rico en plaquetas (PRP) ha llevado a la investigación de su uso como regenerador del tejido condral en general, y en este caso como regenerador del disco intervertebral, siendo la terapia PRP una estrategia que se presenta hoy como una alternativa muy prometedora de tratamiento (biológico) de la enfermedad discal. Son muy pocos los estudios realizados in vitro, y menos aún los estudios clínicos que relacionan el PRP con el manejo de la enfermedad degenerativa discal. No existe al presente ningún documento que emplee el PRP en inyección en el espacio epidural como vía de regeneración del disco intervertebral en los casos de patología discal. Presentamos nuestro estudio preliminar de manejo del dolor crónico en los pacientes con enfermedad discal degenerativa, mediante el uso de PRP inyectado en el espacio epidural, cervical o lumbar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;24(2): 85-95, mar.-abr. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161945</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">PRP epidural en el manejo de la enfermedad discal degenerativa y dolor axial. Estudio preliminar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52020^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53493^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4904^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53493^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12460^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7567^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2401^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7567^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
