<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135175</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-734X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Allergy prevalence in adult spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In spite of the worldwide increase in allergic diseases over the recent years, few epidemiological studies have been conducted in Spain. Objective: We wanted to establish the real prevalence of allergy in a sample of adult general population. We then wanted to describe the profile. the causes and the type of caused disease. Methods: We conducted a population-based study among adults in Spain. We questioned 5003 individuals after calculating a simple size for a máximum undetermination level of (p = 50%). assuming a 1.4 error for global results and a 95% confidence interval (95% CI) l. Five thousands and three individual: were randomly selected from the telephone directory and matched according to sex, age and area. The phone survey was performed with each individual employing the Computer-assisted Telephone lnterview technique supported by Taylor elson Phonebus Company (Barcelona, Spain). Results: We found a 21.6% (95% CI: 20.4-22, 7%) prevalence of allergy. The prevalence was higher in wornen (24.6%) than in men (18.3%). Allergy condition was higher from 18 to 24 years old (26.9%). As it was expected. the prevalence was also higher in urban cities &gt; 500.000 habitants (24.3%) than in rural cities with less than 10.000 habitants ( 18. 7% ). We did not find differences among economical status. The most cornrnon manifestation of allergic disease was rhinoconjunctivitis (45..+%) followed by bronchial asthrna (24.99'c), urticaria (24.6%). Dermatitis (21.5% ), and angioedema (6&lt;K ). The triggers were pollens (31.5%). drugs (29.49'c). and house mites (25J9'c). Less frequently the origin were pet animal. (6,8%), metals  ( 4.9% ). foods ( 4,8% ), molds (3,0% ). insect bites (2,5% ).. un exposure ( 1.9%) and latex (0.8% ). Co11c/11sio11: The prevalence of allergy in adult Spanish population was 21.6%. We found higher prevalence in women. We confirrn the higher prevalence in urban cities. The rnost frequent manifestation was rhinoconjunctivitis. Skin manifestations of allergy were also. significant. The main causes of allergy were pollens. house mite and drug  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaig, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olona, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echechipia, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Lejarazu, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Abujeta, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Cocera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lleonart, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduccián: En lo últimos decenios se está registrando un aumento de las enfermedades alérgicas en todo el mundo. Sin embargo hay pocos estudios de prevalencia de alergia en la población general española. Objetivos: Establecer la prevalencia de enfermedades alérgicas en una muestra de  población general adulta del estado español. Así como establecer las causas y las manifestaciones de esta alergia.  Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio observacional de tipo tranversal. El tamaño de la muestra. suponiendo un nivel máximo de indeterminación prevalencia = 50%) y aceptando un error del 1.4% y un nivel de confianza del 95%. Fue de 5.003 sujeto . La muestra e seleccionó de forma aleatoria y automática del listín de teléfono, aplicando el control de cuotas de zona. el número de habitantes, el sexo y la edad. La recogida 1:1e datos se efectuó mediante encuesta telefónica siguiendo la técnica CATI (Computer-assisted Telephone Interview technique) con oporte Omnibus Phonebus de Taylor Ne/son Sofres Market Research.  Resultados: De los 4.949 sujetos incluidos en el análisis. un 21,6% (IC 95% 20,4- 22,7%) refirieron ser alérgicos. La prevalencia fue mayor en mujeres (24,6%), en el grupo de 18 a 24 años de edad (26.9%) y en poblaciones de más de 500.000 habitantes (24,3%). mientras que fue menor en los varones (18,3%), en la región norte-centro ( 17 ,8%) y en poblaciones con menos de 10.000 habitantes ( 18.7% ).  o hubo diferencia significativa en relación al nivel socioeconómico. La rinoconjuntivitis fue la manifestación alérgica más frecuente (45,4%) seguida del asma bronquial (24.9% ), la urticaria (24.6% ), la dermatitis (21,5%) y el angioederna (6% ). Las tres causas más frecuente de alergia fueron con diferencia los pólenes (31,5%). los medicamento (29,4%) y los ácaros del polvo domé tico (25.3%). Mucho menos frecuentes fueron los animales (6,8%). los metales (4.9%). los alimentos (4.8%), los hongos (3%), las picadura de insecto (2.5%), la exposición al sol (1,9%) y el látex (0,8%). Conclusiones:  La prevalencia de alergia en la población adulta española es del 21,6%, y es más frecuente en las mujeres y en los núcleos urbanos de más de 500.000 habitantes. La manifestación más frecuente es la rinoconjuntivitis. Las  manifestaciones cutáneas de la alergia no son despreciables. Las causas más frecuentes de alergia con los aeroalérgeno (pólenes y ácaros) y lo medicamentos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alergol. inmunol. clín. (Ed. impr.);19(2): 68-74, abr. 2004. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135175</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de alergia en la población adulta española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23089^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7145^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12551^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
