<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103712</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Copayment can also be a social measure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychology shows that what is free is poorly valued. Free of cost national health systems may become blocked due to misuse and may even become unfeasible. Copayment already exist in Spain. It was introduced in pharmaceutical prescriptions as a solidarity measure. This copayment has generated abuses. Its introduction has always been seen as a co-financing action to the system or as a discouraging measure to avoid misuse. The truly solidarity action is a proper organization of a copayment system as a social measure together with efficiency measures and rational use of health resources by all participant actors in the system: managers, professionals and users(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Sagrado, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La psicología muestra que se valora poco lo que no cuesta. Los sistemas nacionales de salud gratuitos pueden bloquearse por abuso en su utilización hasta hacerse casi inviables. El copago ya existe en España. Se introdujo en la prescripción farmacéutica como medida social solidaria. Este copago ha generado abuso por los beneficiarios. La introducción del copago siempre se ha concebido desde el punto de vista de una medida cofinanciadora del sistema o disuasoria del abuso que se hace del mismo. La solución verdaderamente solidaria se perfila en una correcta organización de un sistema de copago como medida social junto con medidas de eficiencia y uso racional de los recursos sanitarios por todos los actores que participan en el sistema: gestores, profesionales y usuarios(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;212(9): 453-458, oct. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El copago también puede ser una medida social</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17227</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50213</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
