<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162931</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mortality in patients with psoriasis. A retrospective cohort study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: The immune and inflammatory pathways involved in psoriasis could favor the development of atherosclerosis, consequently increasing mortality. The objectives of this study were: 1) to assess the mortality of a population with psoriasis compared to a control group, and 2) to assess the prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors. Patients and method: A retrospective cohort was analyzed from a secondary database (electronic medical record). All patients with a diagnosis of psoriasis at 1-01-2010 were included in the study and compared to a control group of the same health system, selected randomly (1:1). Subjects with a history of cardiovascular disease were excluded from the study. A survival analysis was performed considering death from any cause as an event. Follow-up was extended until 30-06-2015. Results: We included 1,481 subjects with psoriasis and 1,500 controls. Prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors was higher in the group with psoriasis. The average follow-up time was 4.6±1.7 years. Mortality was higher in psoriasis patients compared to controls (15.1 vs. 9.6 events per 1,000 person-year, P &lt; .005). Psoriasis was seen to be significantly associated with increased mortality rates compared to the control group in the univariate analysis (HR 1.58, 95% CI 1.16-2.15, P = .004) and after adjusting for cardiovascular risk factors (HR 1.48, 95% CI 1.08-2.3, P = .014). Conclusion: In this population, patients with psoriasis showed a higher prevalence for the onset of cardiovascular risk factors as well as higher mortality rates during follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro Estrada, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masson, Walter</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rossi, Emiliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Krauss, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galimberti, María Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galimberti, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cagide, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos y objetivos: Las modificaciones inmunológicas e inflamatorias observadas en la psoriasis podrían favorecer el desarrollo de la aterosclerosis, aumentando consecuentemente la mortalidad. Los objetivos fueron: 1) determinar la mortalidad de una población con psoriasis en comparación con un grupo control, y 2) conocer la prevalencia de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular. Pacientes y método: Se analizó una cohorte retrospectiva a partir de una base de datos secundaria (historia clínica electrónica). Se incluyeron todos los pacientes con diagnóstico de psoriasis a 1-01-2010, comparándolos con un grupo control del mismo sistema de salud, seleccionados de forma aleatoria (relación 1:1). Se excluyeron los sujetos con antecedentes cardiovasculares. Se realizó un análisis de sobrevida, determinando como episodio la muerte por cualquier causa. El seguimiento se extendió hasta el 30-6-2015. Resultados: Se analizaron 1.481 pacientes con psoriasis y 1.500 controles. La prevalencia de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular fue más elevada en el grupo con psoriasis. El tiempo promedio de seguimiento fue de 4,6±1,7 años. La mortalidad fue mayor en los psoriásicos en comparación con los controles (15,1 frente a 9,6 episodios cada 1.000 personas-año, p &lt; 0,005). La psoriasis se asoció significativamente con una mayor mortalidad en comparación con el grupo control en el análisis univariado (HR 1,58, IC 95% 1,16-2,15, p = 0,004) y luego de ajustar por los factores de riesgo cardiovascular (HR 1,48, IC 95% 1,08-2,3, p = 0,014). Conclusión: En esta población, los pacientes con psoriasis mostraron una mayor prevalencia de factores de riesgo cardiovascular en el momento del diagnóstico y una mayor mortalidad en el seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);148(11): 483-488, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad en pacientes con psoriasis. Análisis de una cohorte retrospectiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
