<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145519</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of whole-body vibration training on body composition and physical fitness in recreationally active young adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last decade, it has been suggested that whole-body vibration training (WBV) may increase neuromuscular performance and consequently affect the muscular improvement as either acute response to vibration or chronic adaptation training. Vibrating platforms generate frequencies from 5-45 Hz and vertical oscillations of 1-11 mm peak to peak, affecting more or less intensity acceleration changing by combining frequency and amplitude. Vibration training, in a session as various offers different results in regard to changes in body composition and in increasing the vertical jump, sprint, and the different manifestations of force development. These promising results await further research to establish parameters (duration, frequency and amplitude) with vibration stimulation in young active subjects. This literature review provides an update on the scientific evidence on the body vibrations in order to answer the question whether WBV, meaning the exercise by increasing the gravitational load collection, is a treatment option if the aim is to improve neuromuscular function, flexibility, balance, agility, coordination and body composition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz, Pedro E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio-Arias, Jacobo A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Pardo, Esmeraldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ruiz, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la última década se ha sugerido que la práctica de ejercicio a través de las vibraciones de todo el cuerpo (WBV) puede incrementar el rendimiento neuromuscular y, consecuentemente, incidir en la mejora muscular, ya sea como respuesta aguda a la vibración o como adaptación crónica al entrenamiento. Las plataformas vibratorias generan frecuencias que van de 5 a 45 Hz y desplazamientos verticales de 1 a 11 mm de pico a pico, incidiendo en una mayor o menor aceleración modificando la intensidad al combinar frecuencia y amplitud. El entrenamiento vibratorio, tanto en una sesión como en varias, ofrece diferentes resultados en lo que se refiere a cambios en la composición corporal, así como en el incremento del salto vertical, la velocidad de carrera y las diferentes manifestaciones del rendimiento de la fuerza. Estos resultados tan prometedores aguardan futuras investigaciones que establezcan unos parámetros (duración, frecuencia y amplitud) con estímulo vibratorio en sujetos jóvenes activos. Esta revisión bibliográfica ofrece una recopilación actualizada de la evidencia científica sobre las vibraciones corporales con el fin de responder a la cuestión de si las WBV, entendidas como el ejercicio que incrementa la carga gravitacional, son una opción de tratamiento si el objetivo es mejorar la función neuromuscular, la flexibilidad, el equilibrio, la agilidad, la coordinación o la composición corporal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(5): 1949-1959, nov. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145519</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de las vibraciones de cuerpo completo sobre la composición corporal y las capacidades físicas en adultos jóvenes físicamente activos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15137^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
