<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83227</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atelectasis in children: what appears to be the cause?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report on a case of pulmonary tuberculosis in a fifteen month-old girl who was referred to our practice for tests following recurrent pneumonia. The chest X-ray showed localized condensation in the middle lobe with signs suggestive of atelectasis. Atelectasis is a common problem in paediatric patients, and tends to be secondary to bronchial obstruction due to mucus plugs. We analyse the types of atelectasis and their most common causes. Moreover, we stress the usefulness of certain techniques that are considered to be aggressive, like the fibrobronchoscopy, but which in reality are simple tests with a high level of diagnostic and therapeutic productivity. The approach to atelectases depends on the underlying cause, and it is essential to treat both the underlying disease as well as the collapsed lung; in most cases, a conservative approach is sufficient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ogando, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cimadevilla, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Conde, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo Posadas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huerta Aragoneses, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanavia Morán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de tuberculosis pulmonar en una niña de 15 meses de edad enviada a nuestra consulta para efectuar un estudio de su neumonía recurrente. La radiografía de tórax pone de manifiesto una condensación localizada en el lóbulo medio, con signos sugestivos de atelectasia. La atelectasia es un problema común en los pacientes pediátricos, generalmente secundaria a una obstrucción bronquial por tapones de moco. Se analizan los tipos de atelectasia y sus causas más comunes, y se insiste en la utilidad de ciertas técnicas consideradas agresivas, como la fibrobroncoscopia, que en realidad son pruebas sencillas y con una gran validez diagnóstica y terapéutica. El manejo de las atelectasias depende de la causa subyacente. Es primordial tratar de forma conjunta la enfermedad de base y el colapso pulmonar, y en la mayoría de los casos es suficiente mantener una actitud conservadora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;68(8): 417-420, sept. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83227</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atelectasia en niños: ¿qué es lo que parece estar detrás?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
