<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130255</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing care and spiritual suffering</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">All human beings suffer, especially during the imbalance produced by diseases. This is the reason why knowing what spiritual suffering is and what spiritual health is it is an important objective that must be reached by nursing interventions. Otherwise, person in a whole sense is not being respected, dignity is not recognized, health is dehumanized and there is a lack of quality in the provided nursing care. We also have to bear in mind that this health problem affects other areas of human life, being spirituality one of the factors that can develop a stronger influence in the welfare of the person or in the recovery time. In this article we try to describe human suffering, included in the spiritual area and its nursing care. Without including that, we can't speak about holism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galán González Serna, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Moreno, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Higuera, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Devesa, Aarón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Todo hombre sufre, especialmente durante el desequilibrio que aflige la enfermedad. De ahí la importancia de dar a conocer qué es el sufrimiento espiritual y la salud espiritual como objetivo a alcanzar con las intervenciones enfermeras. De lo contrario, la persona en su unidad bio-psico-social-espiritual no estará siendo respetada, no reconociendo su dignidad, deshumanizando la salud y no otorgando unos cuidados enfermeros globales de calidad. No hay que olvidar la repercusión que tiene este problema de salud en el resto de esferas del hombre, siendo la espiritualidad uno de los factores que puede influir en el bienestar de la persona o en el tiempo de recuperación. En este artículo nos proponemos describir el sufrimiento humano, propio de la dimensión espiritual, y su cuidado en la Enfermería, pues sin otorgar dichos cuidados no podríamos hablar de holismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;23(3): 153-156, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130255</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Enfermería y los cuidados del sufrimiento espiritual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36317</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32725^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
