<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75764</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Project to improve the management of primary care complaints in Santiago de Compostela</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo improve the quality of how Santiago's Primary Care Department manages complaints through two specific objectives: 1) Address patients&#146; claims within a month or less; 2) Use an automated and data management tool to detect and record issues and activities of the health care centers.Resources and methodsThe work consisted of improvements implemented in various phases: a) Quantifying the initial situation; b) Analyzing possible issues; c) Implementing corrective measures; d) Evaluating the implementation and monitoring; period of study 2007-2008.ResultsIn 2008, 83% of claims were addressed in a month or less (79.36% in 2007), taking into account that the number of complaints received in 2008 increased 49.5% from 2007 levels. In 2008, it took 19.46 days to respond to a complaint (22.82 days in 2007). The implementation of the new complaints management protocol in the health care centers allowed 67.9% of all claims in 2008 to be received with all pertinent facts (31.1% in 2007).ConclusionThe application of new protocols and simple corrective measures to the identified issues allowed for a statistically significant improvement in the response rate to the user. The optimization of the automated tool for managing the claims facilitated the identification of breakdowns in the system and prospectively will help undertake improvement actions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leis, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoMejorar el nivel de calidad de gestión de quejas en la Gerencia de Atención Primaria de Santiago de Compostela a través de 2 objetivos específicos: a) responder a la reclamación en menos de un mes y b) detectar y monitorizar problemas relacionados con la actividad en los centros de salud mediante el diseño de una nueva herramienta informática de registro y gestión de datos.Material y métodosEl trabajo se articula como proyecto de mejora y sigue una metodología clásica de mejora de calidad: a) cuantificación de la situación de partida; b) análisis de las causas; c) implantación de medidas correctoras, y d) seguimiento y control. Período de estudio: 2007-2008.ResultadosEl porcentaje de reclamaciones resueltas en menos de un mes en 2008 fue del 83% (el 79,3%, año 2007), y el incremento del número de quejas recibidas en 2008 fue de un 49,5%. La demora media de resolución fue de 19,4 días en el 2008 (22,8 días, año 2007). La instauración de un nuevo protocolo de gestión de quejas en el área sanitaria logró que el 67,9% de las reclamaciones llegara a la Gerencia con las alegaciones pertinentes en el 2008 (el 31,1%, año 2007).ConclusionesLa aplicación de nuevos protocolos y sencillas medidas correctoras a los problemas identificados permitió una mejora en la respuesta al usuario estadísticamente significativa (p=0,01). El diseño de la nueva base de datos facilitará la identificación de fallos en el sistema y ayudará en el futuro a emprender acciones de mejora(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(1): 34-41, ene.-feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proyecto de mejora en la gestión de quejas de la Gerencia de Atención Primaria de Santiago de Compostela</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
