<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90714</identifier>
<setSpec>0465-546X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Goals: To identify the most prevalent resources andpreventive activities in professional long-haul drivers andtheir peculiarities related to the other Spanish productionbranches.Methodology: We develop a descriptive analysis ofdata from the Survey of Health and Working Conditions inprofessional truck drivers and we compare these resultswith the other Spanish production branches through the VNationalSurvey on Working Conditions. The statisticalanalysis applied T-Student test and the Ji square.Results: In this branch 77% of companies have lessthan 50 employees. 41% of drivers referred that it does notexist the "Delegado de Prevención" (workers representative)in their companies and 25% that there is not any PreventiveAction. It is specially relevant the unknowledgeamong drivers about preventive resources in their companies(34.3%). The most frequently introduced preventivemodality in the sector is the employer taking prevention byhimself (13.6%) whilst other sectors are mainly covered byExternal Preventive Services (43%).Conclusions: If Transport branch is compared with thegeneral - reference population it shows an image in whichundersized companies linked to a weak development ofpreventive network could be determinant to their lowestpreventive activities. Also we find a better self perceivedhealth related to a better access to preventive activities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva Mato, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Merino, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordaz Castillo, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asúnsolo Del Barco, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maqueda Blasco, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Identificar los recursos y actividades preventivasmás prevalentes en el sector del transporte demercancías por carretera y los hechos diferenciales con elresto de la población trabajadora española.Metodología: Estudio descriptivo de los datos de laEncuesta de Salud y Condiciones de Trabajo del sector deltransporte y estudio comparativo con el resto de la poblacióntrabajadora a través de la V-Encuesta Nacional deCondiciones de Trabajo. Para el análisis estadístico se haaplicado el ji cuadrado y la t-student.Resultados: El 77% de las empresas de este sector tienenmenos de 50 trabajadores. El 41% de los conductoresseñala que en su empresa no existe Delegado de Prevencióny un 25% no dispone de ningún Recurso Preventivo.Destaca el alto desconocimiento existente entre los conductoresde los recursos preventivos en su empresa(34,3%). La modalidad preventiva más frecuentementeinstaurada en el sector es la asunción de la prevención porparte del empresario (13,6%) a diferencia del resto de sectoresdonde predomina el SP. Ajeno (43%).Conclusiones: Predominio de la pequeña empresa enel Sector del transporte asociado a un escaso desarrollo deltejido preventivo en comparación con la población de referencia.Ambas características pueden ser determinantes dela menor actividad preventiva, más baja que la observadaen la población de referencia. El acceso a actividades preventivasentre los conductores se relaciona con una mejorsalud percibida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;54(212): 79-89, sept. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90714</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Organización y actividades preventivas en el sector del transporte de mercancías por carretera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
