<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130057</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effects of question-generation training on metacognitive knowledge, self regulation and learning approaches in science</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Although much research has examined the impact of question generation on students&#146; reading comprehension and learning from lectures, far less research has analysed its influence on how students learn and study science. The present study aims to bridge this knowledge gap. Method: Using a quasi-experimental design, three complete ninth-grade science classes, with a total of 72 students, were randomly assigned to three conditions (groups): (G1) questioning-training by providing prompts; (G2) question-generation without any explicit instruction; and (G3) no question control. Participants&#146; pre-test and post-test self-reported measures of metacognitive knowledge, self-regulation and learning approaches were collected and data analysed with multivariate and univariate analyses of covariance. Results: (a) MANCOVA revealed a significant effect for group; (b) ANCOVAs showed the highest average gains for G1 and statistically significant between-group differences in the two components of metacognition: metacognitive knowledge and self-regulation; and (c) the direction of these differences seemed to vary in each of these components. Conclusions: Question-generation training influenced how students learned and studied, specifically their metacognition, and it had a medium to large effect size, which was somewhat related to the prompts used (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Justicia, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berbén, A. B. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pichardo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano García, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: aunque muchas investigaciones han examinado el impacto de la generación de preguntas en la comprensión lectora de los estudiantes, pocas de ellas han analizado su influencia en cómo los estudiantes aprenden y estudian en Ciencias. Este estudio pretende reducir ese déficit de conocimientos. Método: utilizando un diseño cuasi-experimental, tres clases de Ciencias de noveno grado (N = 72 estudiantes) fueron asignadas aleatoriamente a tres grupos: (G1) entrenamiento en generación de preguntas mediante indicaciones; (G2) generación de preguntas sin instrucción explícita; y (G3) grupo control. Los participantes proporcionaron medidas de autoinforme pre-test y post-test en conocimiento metacognitivo, autorregulación y enfoques de aprendizaje, las cuales fueron analizadas mediante análisis de covarianza univariados y multivariados. Resultados: a) el MANCOVA reveló un efecto significativo del factor Grupo; b) los ANCOVAs mostraron el cambio promedio más elevado para G1 y diferencias significativas en dos componentes de la metacognición (conocimiento y autorregulación); y c) la dirección de esas diferencias pareció variar en cada uno de esos componentes. Conclusiones: entrenar en generar preguntas influenció el modo de aprender de los estudiantes (e.g., metacognición), influencia de tamaño medio a grande relacionada con las indicaciones utilizadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);26(3): 385-390, jul.-sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130057</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del entrenamiento en generación de preguntas sobre el conocimiento metacognitivo, la autorregulación y los enfoques de aprendizaje en Ciencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12967^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
