<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153374</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Viral hepatitis and immigration: a challenge for the healthcare system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Viral hepatitis is a significant health problem in African countries. The increase in the immigrant population from this continent represents a challenge for the Spanish healthcare system. Material and methods. A descriptive study was conducted on the prevalence of the serological markers of hepatitis B (HBV), C (HCV) and D (HDV) in African immigrants treated in a specialised doctor's office. Results. The study included 2518 patients (87.7% Sub-Saharan natives), with a mean age of 31.3 years. Some 78.8% of the patients had a positive infection marker for HBV, and 638 patients (25.3%) were diagnosed with active hepatitis B (HBsAg +). In 19 cases, antibodies against HDV were detected (4 cases with detection of the viral genome). Sixty-eight patients had antibodies against HCV, 26 of whom had a positive viral load. Conclusions. The high prevalence of viral hepatitis in immigrants, especially HBV infection, represents a significant change in the profile of patients treated in Spain and requires measures aimed at early diagnosis and transmission prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano-Serrano, AB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca-Gómez, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas-Coronas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezas-Fernández, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano-Pérez, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Villegas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las hepatitis virales representan un importante problema de salud en los países africanos. El incremento de la población inmigrante procedente de este continente supone un reto para el sistema sanitario. Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo sobre la prevalencia de marcadores serológicos de hepatitis viral B (VHB), C (VHC) y delta (VHD) en inmigrantes africanos atendidos en una consulta especializada. Resultados. Se incluyó a 2.518 pacientes (87,7% subsaharianos) con una edad media de 31,3 años. El 78,8% presentó algún marcador positivo de infección por el VHB y en 638 pacientes (25,3%) se diagnosticó una hepatitis B activa (AgHBs+). En 19 casos se detectaron anticuerpos frente al VHD (4 con detección del genoma viral). Sesenta y ocho pacientes presentaron anticuerpos contra el VHC, de los que 26 tenían carga viral positiva. Conclusiones. La elevada prevalencia de hepatitis virales en inmigrantes, en especial la infección por VHB, ha supuesto un cambio significativo en el perfil de pacientes atendidos en nuestro país, y precisa de medidas encaminadas a un diagnóstico precoz y prevención de la transmisión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;216(5): 248-252, jun.-jul. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153374</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatitis virales e inmigración: un reto para el sistema sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6676^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15168^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6658^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22669^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22669^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20208^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30685^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15168^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
