<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73832</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effective dose of hydromorphone in patients with chronic oncologic pain: a fouryear experience in the Centro Médico Nacional 20 de Noviembre, a public hospital in Mexico</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Approximately 6.35 million patients are diagnosed with cancer annually. Around 90% of patients with advanced cancer have pain. Treatment of oncologic pain aims to relieve pain by modulating or interrupting transmission in the spine or brain. The World Health Organization (WHO) has developed a three-step ladder for cancer pain management. At step I, non-opioid plus adjuvant drugs are included. Step II includes opioids for mild to moderate pain plus adjuvants, and step III includes opioids for moderate to severe pain plus adjuvants. Material and methods: We reviewed 72 files corresponding to all the patients with chronic cancer pain that had been treated with hydromorphone during the previous 4 years in our hospital and calculated the mean dose at which the patients reported good pain control (Visual Analog Scale [VAS] &lt; 4). We also studied the most common adverse effects, and whether any of the patients discontinued the treatment, and if so, the reasons for discontinuance. The type of cancer in each patient and the length hydromorphone treatment were also noted. Results: The mean dose used was 22 mg + 16 mg in 24 hours. Of the 72 patients, seven did not achieve adequate pain control and one discontinued the treatment due to adverse effects. The most common adverse effects were constipation, nausea, vomiting and drowsiness. Constipation was significantly more frequent than the remaining adverse effects. Constipation is an adverse effect that is highly tolerable when controlled by medication. Conclusions: The mean effective hydromorphone dose is a relatively low dose at which the adverse effects are still tolerable. The most common adverse effect was constipation, which is fairly tolerable with medication. Hydromorphone is a safe and effective drug even for prolonged periods (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Canseco, C. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintero, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rionda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Golzarri, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, L. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bequer, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tenopala, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Coto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, M. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Santos, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Aproximadamente 6,35 millones de nuevos casos de cáncer se diagnostican anualmente. El 90% de los pacientes con cáncer avanzado presentan dolor. El objetivo en el tratamiento del dolor oncológico es aliviar el dolor, interrumpiendo la transmisión o modulándolo a nivel cerebral o espinal. La Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) desarrolló una escala de tres escalones para manejar el dolor oncológico. En el escalón se incluyen analgésicos no opiáceos + coadyuvantes; en el escalón II se incluyen opiáceos leves + coadyuvantes y en el escalón III se incluyen opiáceos potentes + coadyuvantes. Material y métodos: Se revisaron 72 expedientes, en un total de 4 años, de todos los pacientes con dolor crónico oncológico que hayan estado en tratamiento con hidromorfona. En este trabajo obtuvimos la dosis promedio en la que se logró un buen control del dolor (escala analógica visual [EVA] &lt; 4). También reportamos los efectos adversos que más se presentaron, así como si algún paciente abandonó el tratamiento, y sus causas. Se reportó el tipo de cáncer de cada paciente y el tiempo de tratamiento con hidromorfona. Resultados: La dosis promedio que se utilizó fue de 22 mg + 16 mg en 24 h. De estos 72 pacientes, 7 no lograron llegar a un control del dolor y 1 abandonó el tratamiento, ya que no toleró los efectos adversos. Los efectos adversos que más comúnmente se presentaron fueron estreñimiento, náuseas, vómitos y somnolencia. El efecto adverso que más se presentó fue el estreñimiento, con una diferencia estadísticamente significativa respecto de los otros efectos adversos presentados. El estreñimiento es un efecto adverso que, si se controla con un fármaco, es muy tolerable. Conclusiones: El promedio de dosis efectiva de hidromorfona que encontramos es una dosis relativamente baja, a la que los efectos adversos son tolerables (&#133;) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;16(5): 270-274, jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73832</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dosis efectiva de hidromorfona en pacientes con dolor crónico oncológico: experiencia de 4 años en el Centro Médico Nacional &#147;20 de Noviembre&#148; ISSSTE</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4131^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10334^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
