<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84957</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anemia Syndrome. Type 1 Gastric Carcinoid (Role of endoscopic ultrasound in the diagnosis and treatment)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a case of a 74 year old man who was admitted to our Internal Medicine Department for severe symptomatic anemia. He was diagnosed with a type 1 gastric neuroendocrine tumor classified according to Rindi et al, Endoscopic ultrasound was the key for correct diagnosis and patient management. Subsequently, we present a review of the current status of the recommendations for the correct diagnosis and treatment in this type of tumor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gato Díez, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba Soriano, Juan Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Gutiérrez, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Neyra, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de un varón de 74 años que ingresa en Medicina Interna por un cuadro de Anemia grave sintomática, alcanzando el diagnóstico de Tumor Neuroendocrino subtipo Carcinoide Gástrico tipo 1 de la Clasificación de Rindi y cols. El papel de la ultrasonografía endoscópica fue crucial para un correcto diagnóstico y tratamiento del paciente. Posteriormente se expone una revisión del estado actual de recomendaciones para un correcto diagnóstico y tratamiento de este tipo de tumores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;3(3): 217-219, oct.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome Anémico. Carcinoide Gástrico tipo 1. (Papel de la Ultrasonografía endoscópica en el diagnóstico y tratamiento)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d767^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2319^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d767^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
