<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115718</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing texts printed in Spain during the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries available in digital libraries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The texts of nursing printed in Spain during the 16th and 17th century that are supposed to be the bases of Current Spanish nursing are identified. The aim of this work has the twofold aspect of the study of nursing textbooks and the possibilities of recovering and querying digital libraries. To obtain the goal, relevant literature where texts have been identified and some comments were removed has been consulted. Digital libraries have been selected and preceded to search and retrieval. Of the four most significant texts have recovered three (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>León Molina, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se identifican en bibliografía los textos de enfermería impresos en España durante los siglos XVI y XVII, que se supone son las bases de la enfermería española actual. El objetivo del trabajo tiene la doble vertiente del estudio de los manuales de enfermería y de las posibilidades de su recuperación y consulta en bibliotecas digitales. Para la obtención del objetivo se ha consultado bibliografía pertinente donde se han identificado los textos y extraído comentarios. Se han seleccionado bibliotecas digitales y se ha procedido a la búsqueda y recuperación. De los cuatro textos más significativos se han recuperado tres de ellos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(32): 280-287, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115718</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Textos de enfermería impresos en España durante los siglos XVI y XVII disponibles en bibliotecas digitales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29491^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38903^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38903^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38879</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38903^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38903^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38903^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
