<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037806</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relation between anomalous eating behaviors and other health behaviors in children 11-14 years old</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work is to analyze the existing relation among anomalous eating behaviors and among these eating behaviours and other behaviors, such as sleep habits, school absenteeism, consumption of alcohol and other drugs, poor self-esteem, emotional welfare, control of impulses, physical  exercise and sexual behaviour. We have administered to a sample of 819 adolescents 11-14 years old, the Questionnaire of Information, Attitudes and Behaviors related to Health (CIACS II). The results evidence important relations among specific anomalous eating behaviors, as avoidance of fat food, weight control, to do exercise in order to burning calories and vomiting after an abundant meal. Also, we have found significant correlation among specific problematic eating behaviors and other behaviors as having difficulties to get to sleep, school absenteeism, to feel sad when they believe to have injured the feelings of the others, difficulty to control impulses, consumption of alcohol or the desire to change many things of oneself. The aim of this work is to analyze the existing relation amonganomalous eating behaviors and among these eating behaviours and other behaviors, such as sleep habits, school absenteeism, consumption of alcohol and other drugs, poor self-esteem, emotional welfare, control of impulses, physical exercise and sexual behaviour. We have administered to a sample of 819 adolescents 11-14 years old, the Questionnaire of Information, Attitudes and Behaviors related to Health (CIACS II). The results evidence important relations among specific anomalous eating behaviors, as avoidance of fat food, weight control, to do exercise in order to burning calories and vomiting after an abundant meal. Also, we have found significant correlation among specific problematic eating behaviors and other behaviors as having difficulties to get to sleep, school absenteeism, to feel sad when they believe to have injured the feelings of the others, difficulty to control impulses, consumption of alcohol or the desire to change many things of oneself</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guirado Martínez, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester Arnal, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo es analizar la relación existente entre conductas alimentarias anómalas y entre estas conductas alimentarias y otros comportamientos, como los hábitos de sueño, el absentismo escolar, el consumo de alcohol y drogas, la baja autoestima, el bienestar emocional, el control de impulsos, el ejercicio físico y la conducta sexual. Para ello, administramos a una muestra de 819 adolescentes, cuyas edades estaban comprendidas entre los 11 y los 14 años, el Cuestionario de Información, Actitudes y Comportamientos relacionados con la Salud (CIACS-II).Los resultados nos sugieren la existencia de importantes relaciones entre determinados comportamientos alimentarios anómalos, como la evitación de alimentos considerados de gran aporte calórico, controlarse el peso, hacer ejercicio con el fin de quemar calorías y provocarse el vómito después e una comida abundante. Del mismo modo, también hemos encontrado correlaciones significativas entre determinados comportamientos alimentarios problemáticos y conductas como tener dificultades para dormirse por las noches, el absentismo escolar, sentirse triste cuando se cree que se han herido los sentimientos de los demás, la dificultad para controlar los impulsos, consumir alcohol los fines de semana o desear cambiar muchas cosas de uno mismo</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;21(1): 58-65, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037806</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre conductas alimentarias anómalas y otros hábitos de salud en niños de 11 a 14 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24007^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24007^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
