<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052240</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuous positive airway pressure used by adults with obstructive sleep apneas after prescription in a public referral Hospital in Mexico city</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to analyze the frequency of initiation of continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) in patients with obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS) in a referral hospital in Mexico City serving mainly patients without public health insurance coverage and to assess their level of adherence.         Patients and methods: Patients with OSAS diagnosed by polysomnography or by simplified respiratory polygraphy for whom nasal CPAP was prescribed were enrolled in the study. Titration of CPAP was performed during polysomnography or with an automatic CPAP device. Compliance with treatment was assessed during a medical visit or by telephone interview.                 Results: A total of 304 patients were enrolled upon prescription of nasal CPAP; 169 (55.5%) either purchased a device or were provided with one by the social security system. The patients most seriously ill and who had public health insurance coverage were the ones who most often acquired a device. These patients took 1.5 months to obtain the equipment and had a compliance rate of 80% at a mean 34 months of follow-up. The respiratory events index was correlated with compliance, whereas excessive daytime sleepiness (Epworth scale score) and body mass index were predictors of therapeutic CPAP pressure.                 Conclusions: Nearly half the patients who were prescribed CPAP did not acquire the device. Most of those who acquired a device adhered to the treatment. In Mexico access to procedures for diagnosing OSAS is limited and access to treatment is also restricted for patients who do not have public health insurance coverage</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torre Bouscoulet, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meza Vargas, María Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Padilla, Rogelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez García, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castorena Maldonado, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Escárcega, Elodia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito del estudio ha sido analizar la frecuencia de inicio de tratamiento con presión positiva continua de la vía aérea (CPAP) y su cumplimiento en pacientes con síndrome de apneas obstructivas durante el sueño (SAOS), en un hospital de referencia de la Ciudad de México que atiende predominantemente a pacientes sin seguridad social.                 Pacientes y métodos: Se incluyó a pacientes con SAOS diagnosticados por poliomnografía o poligrafía respiratoria simplificada, a quienes se prescribió CPAP nasal. La titulación de ésta se realizó durante la polisomnografía o con un equipo automático de CPAP. El cumplimiento del tratamiento se evaluó en consulta o por entrevista telefónica.                 Resultados: Se incluyó a un total de 304 pacientes con prescripción de CPAP nasal. De ellos, 169 (55,5%) adquirieron el equipo (ya fuera por compra o gratuitamente a través de la seguridad social). Los pacientes más graves y con seguridad social fueron los que más frecuentemente lo adquirieron. Este grupo tardó 1,5 meses en obtener el equipo y tuvo un 80% de cumplimiento a los 34 meses de seguimiento medio. El índice respiratorio se asoció al cumplimiento, mientras que la somnolencia diurna excesiva (puntuación de Epworth) y el índice de masa corporal fueron predictores de la presión terapéutica de CPAP.                 Conclusiones: Casi la mitad de los pacientes a quienes se prescribió CPAP no adquirió el equipo. La mayoría de quienes lo adquirieron cumplió el tratamiento. En México, además del limitado acceso a los métodos diagnósticos de SAOS, el tratamiento está restringido en los pacientes diagnosticados que carecen de seguridad social</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;43(1): 16-21, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052240</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de CPAP en adultos con síndrome de apneas obstructivas durante el sueño después de prescripción en un hospital público de referencia de la Ciudad de México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
