<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114645</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing care in males with spinal cord injury and sexual dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The impact of spinal cord injury and its sequels requires important efforts of adaptation. In several studies, people with spinal cord injury claim to have covered most of their needs at physical, emotional and social level, but they are not yet fully satisfied with their sexual life. Sexual function is usually impaired in men with spinal cord injuries, and is sometimes related to problems of erection, ejaculation and/or orgasm. This issue is not a priority in the first phase, but it appears over the subsequent periods when patients often ask for a solution to this problem. A case-study is presented of a 25 year old male with chronic complete spinal cord injury (ASIA A), L4-L5 level, who reported sexual dysfunction and attended an annual review in the National Hospital for Paraplegics. After performing a nursing assessment using the functional health patterns of Gordon, the team proposed a nursing care plan according to the taxonomy of NANDA (North American Nursing Association), NOC (Nursing Outcome Classification) and NIC (Nursing Intervention Classification).Nurses are the healthcare professionals who have more direct and continuous contact with these patients. Specific programs need to be designed to provide them with the sexual education, which should contain adequate emotional and sexual information. We believe that an appropriate and systematic assessment of patient's sexuality, as well as the application of the (NANDA, NOC, NIC) nurse methodology, may be very helpful in improving the outcomes of these specific interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cobo-Cuenca, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Espinosa, Noelia M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Píriz Campos, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El impacto de la lesión medular y sus secuelas suponen grandes esfuerzos de adaptación. En distintos estudios las personas con lesión medular tienen cubierta la mayoría de sus necesidades, tanto físicas como afectivas y sociales. Sin embargo, manifiestan carencias en todo lo relacionado con el ámbito sexual. La función sexual en hombres con lesión medular suele estar alterada, pudiendo existir problemas en la erección, en la eyaculación y/o en la percepción orgásmica. Durante la fase aguda no se suele abordar, pero es después, en las etapas más tardías, cuando se demanda solución a este problema. Se presenta el caso de un varón de 25 años con lesión medular crónica completa (ASIA A), nivel L4-L5, que refiere tener disfunción sexual y acude a su revisión anual en el Hospital Nacional de Parapléjicos. Tras realizar la valoración enfermera por patrones funcionales de salud de Gordon, se propone un plan de cuidados enfermeros según taxonomía de la North American Nursing Association (NANDA), Nursing Outcome Classification (NOC) y Nursing Intervention Classification (NIC).Las enfermeras son los profesionales de la salud que más contacto directo y continuado tienen con estos pacientes, por lo que sería necesario diseñar programas de educación sexual que incluyeran información afectiva y sexual. Tras la realización de este trabajo pensamos que la valoración sistemática y adecuada de la sexualidad del paciente, y además la aplicación de la taxonomía enfermera (NANDA, NOC, NIC), puede resultar de gran ayuda para mejorar los resultados de las intervenciones en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);23(3): 128-132, mayo-jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114645</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados enfermeros en el varón con lesión medular y disfunción sexual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
