<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045917</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7309</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Flaps in head and neck reconstructive oncologic surgery. Our experience in 15 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The reconstructive surgery has supposedan increase of the possibilities in the surgical managementof the advanced head and neck cancer, improving themargins of resection, the postoperative sequels and thefunction of the affected organ, and achieving a better qualityof life of the patient as a better aesthetic and functionalresults.Material and methods: We reviewed retrospectively a seriesof sixty-five flaps realized between 1988 and 2003.The subjects included 60 men and 2 women. The meanage was of 54,6 years and ranged from 28 to 76 years.We analyze dates relating to the patient, the tumor, thesurgical technique, the type of flaps and the postoperativecomplications.Results: The site reconstructed more frequently was theoral cavity (22 cases). The flap most used was thepectoralis major (76,9%). 87% of the tumors were instages III-IV. 69% were realized in a single surgical actand 31% were done in delayed procedures. Of the 65flaps, only 5 poor results were registered; and 10 of thempresented some type of complication that did notcompromise the flap survival. In the other 50 the resultswere satisfactory. Complications took place in theimmediate postoperative in 27,7% of the cases, and latein 14,3%. Also we found a significant association betweenprevious radiotherapy and a major incidence of fistula.Discussion: We compare the results in the reconstructivesurgery obtained in our hospital with the published series.Also we review the current indications of the flaps</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mínguez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Martín, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elhendi, Wasim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labella, Torcuato</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rossi, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La cirugía reconstructiva ha supuesto unaumento de las posibilidades del manejo quirúrgico delos tumores avanzados en cabeza y cuello, mejorandolos márgenes de resección, las secuelas posquirúrgicas yla función del órgano agredido, y consiguiendo que lacalidad de vida del paciente en relación al aspecto estéticoo el resultado funcional sea mejor.Material y métodos: Se revisan una serie de 65 colgajosrealizados consecutivamente durante el período de 1988al 2003, con edades comprendidas entre los 28 y 76años. De los que 60 eran hombres y dos mujeres.Analizamos datos referentes al paciente, el tumor, la técnicaquirúrgica, el tipo de colgajo y las complicacionesque surgieron.Resultados: El lugar reconstruido más frecuentementefue la cavidad oral con 22 casos. El colgajo más empleadoes el colgajo de pectoral mayor (76,9%). Un 87% delos tumores estaban en estadios III-IV.El 69% de las reconstruccioneslas realizamos en un solo acto quirúrgicoy el 31% restante de manera diferida. De los 65 colgajosen sólo 5 se registraron malos resultados; en diez sepresentó algún tipo de complicación que no llego a comprometerla supervivencia del colgajo. En 50 los resultadosfueron satisfactorios. Se produjeron complicacionesen el postoperatorio inmediato en el 27,7% de los casos,y tardías en un 14,3%. También se encontró una asociaciónsignificativa entre radioterapia previa y una mayorincidencia de fístulas.Discusión: Comparamos los resultados obtenidos ennuestro servicio con la cirugía reconstructiva con las otrasseries publicadas. Igualmente revisamos las indicacionesactuales de los colgajos</dc:description>
<dc:source>O.R.L.-DIPS;32(4): 178-184, oct.-dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045917</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuestra experiencia en reconstrucción mediante colgajos en cirugía oncológica de cabeza y cuello</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
