<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62022</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enthusiasm for diagnostic tests: health effects and their surveillance. 2008 SESPAS Report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The medicalization of life has been encouraged by an excessiveinterest in health as an end in itself rather than as ameans for a better life. This new concept of health has stimulatedthe growth of the secondary market of health and, inanalogy with the knowledge society, the emergence of whatis known as the &#147;health society&#148;. Among the most popular health&#147;products&#148; are diagnostic tests, explaining the enthusiasmfor screening programs and the new genetic technologies, especiallyin the detection and prognosis of cancer. Because ofthe iatrogenic potential of diagnostic tests and the unnecessarydemand caused by their excessive use, this phenomenonis a matter of public health concern. Health administrationsmust face this challenge with a diverse range ofinterventions that range from clinical management to policyformulation including the improvement of diagnostic research.The contribution of diagnostic research has so far been limitedby its irregular quality(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Aguado, Ildefonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lumbreras, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A la progresiva medicalización de la vida se está añadiendoen los últimos años un desmedido interés por la salud que seconvierte en una finalidad de la existencia y no en un medio.Esta nueva concepción de la salud como fin, ha motivado elcrecimiento del llamado mercado secundario de la salud y deque se hable de la ®sociedad de la salud» al igual que se hablade la sociedad del conocimiento. Entre los ®productos» sanitariosmás populares se encuentran las pruebas diagnósticas;de ahí el entusiasmo surgido por los programas de cribado opor las nuevas tecnologías genéticas, sobre todo en deteccióny pronóstico de cáncer. El fenómeno afecta a la salud públicapor la capacidad iatrogénica de las pruebas diagnósticas y porla carga asistencial prescindible que su uso exagerado provoca.La Administración sanitaria debe encarar este reto con undiverso abanico de intervenciones, que van desde el ámbito dela gestión clínica y sanitaria a la formulación de políticas sanitarias,sin descuidar la mejora de una investigación cuya aportaciónal conocimiento para un diagnóstico clínico fundado es,hasta la fecha, escasa dada su irregular calidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;22(supl.1): 216-222, abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62022</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El entusiasmo por las pruebas diagnósticas: efectos en la salud y formas de control. Informe SESPAS 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
