<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114904</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0620</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evidence on the prevention of cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cancer is one of the main health problems. It includes a set of diseases with multi-causal origins. The tumours with the greatest impact on the health of men are lung, prostate and colorectal cancers, while for women they are breast and colorectal tumours. The best strategies for preventing cancer are ones based on primary prevention and early diagnosis. It is estimated that about to 80-90% of cancers are preventable. As regards primary prevention, there is considerable evidence to suggest that not smoking, regular physical exercise and a diet rich in fruit and vegetables, along with the control of some environmental and occupational risk factors can reduce the incidence of cancer. The early diagnosis of breast, colorectal and cervical cancer is recommended for some groups of the population in a context of organised programs with adequate quality guarantees (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salas, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer es uno de los principales problemas de salud. Engloba a un conjunto de enfermedades que tienen un origen multicausal. Los tumores con mayor impacto en la salud son pulmón, próstata y colorrectal en los hombres y mama y colorrectal en las mujeres. Las mejores estrategias para evitar el cáncer son las basadas en la prevención primaria y en el diagnóstico precoz. Se estima que entre el 80-90% de los canceres son prevenibles. Respecto a la prevención primaria hay fuerte evidencia que no fumar, realizar ejercicio físico regular, y una dieta rica en frutas y verduras junto con el control de algunos factores de riesgo ambientales y laborales, puede disminuir la incidencia del cáncer. Está recomendado el diagnóstico precoz de cáncer de mama, cuello de útero y de cáncer colorrectal en algunos grupos de población en el contexto de programas organizados con la adecuada garantía de calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. sanid. penit;15(2): 66-75, mayo-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114904</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencias sobre la prevención del cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
