<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046952</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exposure to devices: an indicator of nosocomial infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To design a protocol for the systematic surveillance of nosocomial infections associated with the devices most frequently used in pediatric intensive care units (PICUs). Material and methods: We performed a prospective epidemiological surveillance study of nosocomial infections associated with devices such as central venous catheters, mechanical ventilation and urinary catheters in a PICU from April to June 2004. The criteria of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) were used to define bacteremia, pneumonia, and urinary tract infection. Results: A total of 326 pediatric patients were studied (45% with urinary catheters, 30% with venous catheters, and 25% under mechanical ventilation). The nosocomial infection rate was 0.6 cases of bacteremia, 0.4 cases of pneumonia and 0.3 cases of urinary tract infection per 100 device days. Conclusions: Epidemiological surveillance of nosocomial infections using a simple protocol allows risk factor-associated infection rates to be determined in a specific time period and measures for infection control to be implemented. These strategies aim to reduce the frequency of infections and consequent cost per days of hospital stay</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urrea, Mireya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santaolalla, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicolás, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordán, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rozas, Librada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Diseñar un protocolo de vigilancia sistemática de la infección nosocomial (IN) asociada a dispositivos extrínsecos, más frecuentemente usados en una Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Pediátricos (UCIP). Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo de vigilancia de la IN asociada a la exposición de dispositivos extrínsecos tipo catéter venoso central, ventilación mecánica y sonda urinaria en una UCIP, durante el período de abril a junio de 2004. Se tuvo en cuenta las infecciones tipo: bacteriemia, neumonía e infección del tracto urinario, utilizando los criterios del Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Resultados: Se realizó el seguimiento a un total de 326 pacientes pediátricos, el 45% portadores de sonda urinaria, el 30% con catéter venoso central y el 25% expuestos a ventilación mecánica. La tasa de IN fue de 0,6 bacteriemias, 0,4 neumonías y 0,3 infecciones del tracto urinario, por 100 días de exposición al catéter venoso central, ventilación mecánica y sonda urinaria, respectivamente. Conclusiones: La vigilancia epidemiológica de la IN permite conocer las tasas de infección por factores de riesgo asociados a su desarrollo, en un período definido y, por tanto, implementar las medidas de control de la infección, con el fin de disminuir su frecuencia y reducir el coste de estancia hospitalaria secundario a éstas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;21(3): 161-163, may.-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exposición a dispositivos extrínsecos, un indicador de infección intrahospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2446^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23699</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
