<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105196</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Access to health information sources in spain. how to combat &#147;infoxication&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Internet has become a priceless source for finding health information for both patients and healthcare professionals. However, the universality and the abundance of information can lead to unfounded conclusions about health issues that can confuse further than clarify the health information. This aspect causes intoxication of information: infoxication. The question lies in knowing how to filter the information that is useful, accurate and relevant for our purposes. In this regard, integrative portals, such as the Biblioteca Virtual de Salud, compile information at different levels (international, national and regional), different types of resources (databases, repositories, bibliographic sources, etc.), becoming a starting point for obtaining quality information(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navas-Martin, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escandell-García, Cintia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albornos-Muñoz, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Internet se ha convertido en una fuente inestimable para la búsqueda de información sobre salud tanto para pacientes como para los profesionales de los cuidados. Sin embargo, la universalidad y profusión informativa puede desencadenar conclusiones infundadas sobre temas de salud que lejos de clarificar pueden confundir provocando una intoxicación informativa: infoxicación. La cuestión radica en saber filtrar la información de manera que sea útil, rigurosa y relevante para nuestros propósitos. En este aspecto, los portales integradores, como es el caso de la Biblioteca Virtual de Salud, integran la información a diferentes niveles (internacional, nacional y autonómico), diferentes tipos de recursos (bases de datos, repositorios, fuentes bibliográficas, etc.) convirtiéndose en un punto de partida para la obtención de información de calidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);22(3): 154-158, mayo-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105196</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acceso a fuentes de información sobre salud en España: cómo combatir la infoxicación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38903^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50124</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
