<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143713</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paediatric prescribing of anti-asthmatics in primary care in Castilla-León. Geographical variability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Asthma is one of the most prevalent chronic diseases with effective treatment in paediatrics. The aim of this study is to describe the paediatric prescribing of anti-asthmatics in Castilla-León, analyzing its geographic variability and temporal evolution. Material and methods: An analysis was made of prescriptions dispensed in pharmacies of R03 therapeutic subgroup (anti-asthmatic agents), and the active ingredients mepyramine and ketotifen, prescribed in children less than 14 years of age in the Castilla-León health service from 2005 to 2010 in Primary Care. Data is presented in prescribed daily doses per thousand inhabitants per day (PDHD) for each active ingredient being calculated raw rates and age-adjusted to the variables health area, type of health zone and year of study. Results: A total of 462,354 prescriptions of anti-asthmatic agents were dispensed to a population of 1,580,229 persons/year. There was wide variation between areas in the type and intensity of anti-asthmatic agents used, partly explained by differences in the prevalence of asthma. Montelukast predominated as controller drug in most of them (PDHD 3.1 to 7.7), being similar the consumption intensity in the three types of health zones (PDHD 4.7 to 4.8). The annual variability was low. Conclusions: The study describes the paediatric prescribing pattern of anti-asthmatic agents in Castilla-León between 2005-2010. It shows wide geographical variation, as well as inadequacies regarding current recommendations of asthma treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano Garcinuño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Quirós, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casares Alonso, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: El asma es una de las enfermedades crónicas con tratamiento eficaz más prevalentes en pediatría. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la prescripción pediátrica de antiasmáticos en Castilla y León, analizando su variabilidad geográfica y su evolución temporal. Material y métodos: Se estudiaron las prescripciones dispensadas en farmacias del subgrupo terapéutico R03 (medicamentos antiasmáticos) y de los principios activos mepiramina y ketotifeno, realizadas a menores de 14 años en atención primaria en el Sistema Nacional de Salud entre 2005 y 2010. Los datos se presentan en dosis diarias prescritas por 1.000 habitantes/día (PDHD) para cada principio activo, calculándose tasas crudas y ajustadas por edad para las variables área sanitaria, tipo de zona de salud y año del estudio. Resultados: Se realizaron 462.354 prescripciones de antiasmáticos a una población expuesta de 1.580.229 personas-año. Hubo amplia variabilidad entre las áreas en el tipo e intensidad de los antiasmáticos utilizados, en parte explicada por diferencias en su prevalencia de asma. Montelukast predominó como fármaco controlador en la mayoría de ellas (3,1-7,7 PDHD), siendo su intensidad de consumo similar en los 3 tipos de zonas de salud (4,7-4,8 PDHD). La variabilidad anual fue escasa. Conclusiones: El estudio describe el patrón pediátrico de prescripción de antiasmáticos en Castilla y León entre 2005 y 2010. Muestra gran variabilidad geográfica, así como inadecuaciones respecto a las recomendaciones actuales de tratamiento del asma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);83(3): 191-200, sept. 2015. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143713</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prescripción pediátrica de fármacos antiasmáticos en atención primaria en Castilla y León. Variabilidad geográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12175^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32858^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27799^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32493</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33820^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22851^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
