<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167085</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of Policol(R) One in the reduction of midhigh cholesterol levels</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">High serum-cholesterol levels represent one of the most critical risk factors in the development of cardiovascular diseases all over the world. In this paper, the results of an observational prospective study on the efficacy and safety of the product Policol(R) One to reduce low-moderate hypercholesterolemia are shown. The product contains red yeast rice (Monascus purpureus), policosanol, coenzyme Q10 and hypolipidemic and hepatoprotective plants used in folk medicine: extracts of guggul (Commiphora mukul), artichoke (Cynara scolymus) and dandelion (Taraxacum officinale), and birdseed powder (Phalaris canariensis). At a dosage of 1 capsule per day for 3 months, the participants significantly reduced their total cholesterol (16,8%) and LDL-cholesterol (23,8%); with an additional decrease in levels (13,4%) and increasing their HDL-cholesterol levels (9,1%). No side effects were reported in any case. These results indicate that the product is effective and safe to reduce low-moderate cholesterol levels, and it may represent a natural complement to other treatments for these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llabrés, Josep Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araujo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boada, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urcola, Imanol</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los niveles elevados de colesterol en sangre representan uno de los factores de riesgo más críticos a nivel mundial para el desarrollo de enfermedades cardiovasculares. En este artículo se presentan los resultados de un estudio observacional prospectivo que evaluó la eficacia y seguridad del producto Policol(R) One para reducir el la hipercolesterolemia leve-moderada. El producto se compone de extracto de levadura roja de arroz (Monascus purpureus), policosanol, coenzima Q10 y plantas consideradas tradicionalmente como hipolipemiantes y hepatoprotectoras: extractos de gugul (Commiphora mukul), alcachofera (Cynara scolymus), diente de león (Taraxacum officinale) y polvo de alpiste (Phalaris canariensis). A dosis de 1 cápsula al día durante 3 meses, los participantes redujeron significativamente sus niveles de colesterol total (16,8%) y colesterol-LDL (23,8%); reduciendo también los triglicéridos (13,4%) e incrementando el colesterol-HDL (9,1%). No se observaron efectos adversos en ningún caso. Estos resultados demuestran que el producto es eficaz y seguro para la reducción del colesterol leve-moderado, y podría suponer un complemento a otros tratamientos para estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;17(1): 63-70, jun. 2017. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio piloto sobre el efecto de Policol(R) One en la hipercolesterolemia leve-moderada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35728</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27553^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8686^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
