<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103170</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New insights into the pathophysiology of oedema in nephrotic syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Oedema is a common clinical manifestation of nephrotic syndrome. However, the pathophysiological mechanism of sodium retention in nephrotic syndrome has been intensely debated for decades. Several clinical and experimental observations argue against the classic or "underfill" hypothesis of oedema formation in nephrotic syndrome. In many patients, oedema formation in nephrotic syndrome is due to the kidney being intrinsically unable to excrete salt and is unrelated to systemic factors (i.e. hypoalbuminaemia, decreased "effective" arterial blood volume, and secondary hyperaldosteronism). The cortical collecting duct is the nephron site of sodium retention in nephrotic syndrome. Activation of the epithelial sodium channel in the cortical collecting duct is responsible for sodium retention in nephrotic syndrome. In nephrotic syndrome, a defective glomerular filtration barrier allows the passage of proteolytic enzymes or their precursors, which have the ability to activate the epithelial sodium channel, thereby causing the the subsequent sodium retention and oedema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rondon&#150;Berrios, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El edema es una manifestación clínica frecuente del síndrome nefrótico (SN); sin embargo, el mecanismo fisiopatológico responsable de la retención de sodio ha sido un tema de intenso debate durante décadas. Muchas observaciones clínicas y experimentales no apoyan a la hipótesis clásica o del underfill en la formación del edema nefrótico. En numerosos pacientes, el edema propio del SN se produce por un defecto renal intrínseco en la excreción de sodio y es independiente de factores sistémicos (p. ej., hipoalbuminemia, disminución del volumen arterial efectivo o hiperaldosteronismo secundario). El punto de la nefrona donde se produce la retención de sodio en el SN es el túbulo colector cortical. La activación del canal de sodio epitelial a ese nivel es responsable de la retención de sodio en la patología que nos ocupa. Una barrera glomerular defectuosa propia del SN permitiría el paso de enzimas proteolíticas o sus precursores que a su vez activarían el canal de sodio epitelial causando de esa manera su retención y consiguiente edema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;31(2): 148-154, abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103170</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances en la fisiopatología del edema en el síndrome nefrótico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4555^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37287^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9596^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9513</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12506^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52323^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
