<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116749</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effective Programs of Social Skills Training based on Experiential Methods</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This essay examines the question of the evidence based psychological practices applied to the Social Skills Training (SST) programs and, more specifically, the experiential SST programs, as proposed and tested by the authors in the last years. First, we discuss the different models of SST programs. Then, we present the main characteristics of the experiential method, which are: structured situations of experiential training as the context and the support to apply behavioral procedures and techniques; conceptual base directed by both the instrumental and the ethical dimensions of the social competence; emphasis on the promotion of intermediary process skills; focus on the behavior variability; exposition and sensibility to the environment contingencies; functional analysis and self-monitory as supplementary goals; inclusion of generic task in the procedure of home tasks. Finally, we present some characteristics of the experiential SST programs driven in Brazil with evidences of effectiveness, as well as new questions for future investigations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prette, Zilda Aparecida Pereira del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prette, Almir del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este ensayo examina la cuestión de las prácticas psicológicas basadas en la evidencia en lo que se refiere a programas de Entrenamiento en Habilidades Sociales (EHS) y, de manera más específica, los programas vivenciales propuestos y testados por los autores en los últimos años. En la primera parte, se discuten los diferentes modelos de programas de EHS y se presentan las principales características del modelo vivencial: uso de vivencias como contexto y apoyo a los procedimientos y técnicas conductuales; base conceptual fundamentada en las dimensiones éticas e instrumentales de la competencia social; énfasis en la promoción de las habilidades mediadoras o de proceso; énfasis en la variabilidad de la conducta; exposición y sensibilidad a las contingencias; enseñanza del análisis funcional y auto-monitoreo; inclusión del modo genérico en el procedimiento de tareas para casa. Al término, se presentan algunas características de los programas de EHS realizados en Brasil, con evidencias de efectividad, indicándose nuevas cuestiones para investigaciones futuras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;31(1): 67-76, ene.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programas eficaces de entrenamiento en habilidades sociales basados en métodos vivenciales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53366^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
