<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82610</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surface electromyography applications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The electrophysiological techniques (neurography and needle electromyography) allow us an approach to the knowledge of the neuromuscular function. Electromyography obtains the electrical activity from the muscle in rest or in contraction (maximum and static voluntary contraction). In its clinical application, electromyography helps to the diagnosis and follow-up of a process of neuromuscular type. On the other hand, kinesiological or surface electromyography (SEMG) allows the study detecof the muscular activity in dynamics, which we can apply to the biomechanical movement analysis, gait analysis, studies of muscular fatigue, sport performance and applications in work medicine and ergonomics. SEMG brings advantages like the fact that is a bloodless test, of being able to analyze varying muscles at the same time, in motion and in actions of non limited duration. The processed one brings us parameters of amplitude and frequencies, which we will use for descriptive and comparative studies. As a balancing entry, it does not allow us to study deep musculature, and some aspects of definition are lost in the obtained outlines(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Massó, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Germán, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gual, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Dani</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las técnicas electrofisiológicas (neurografía y electromiografía de aguja) permiten una aproximación al conocimiento de la función neuromuscular. La electromiografía obtiene la actividad eléctrica del músculo en reposo o activo (contracción voluntaria máxima y estática). En su aplicación clínica, asiste al diagnóstico y al seguimiento de un proceso de tipo neuromuscular. Por otro lado, la electromiografía de superficie (EMGS) o cinesiológica permite estudiar la actividad muscular en acciones dinámicas, siendo aplicable al análisis biomecánico de un gesto, al análisis de la marcha, en estudios de fatiga muscular y de rendimiento deportivo y en áreas como la medicina laboral y la ergonomía. La EMGS ofrece algunas ventajas: es incruenta y permite analizar simultáneamente distintos músculos en movimiento y en acciones de duración ilimitada. El procesado de la señal electromiográfica proporciona parámetros de amplitud y frecuencia para estudios descriptivos y comparativos. No obstante, no permite valorar la musculatura profunda y aporta menos definición que los electromiogramas de aguja(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);45(166): 127-136, abr.-jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicaciones de la electromiografía de superficie en el deporte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
