<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117419</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of plerixafor in patients undergoing mobilization autologous haematopoietic progenitor cell</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate effectiveness of treatment with plerixafor in patients undergoing posterior mobilization for hematopoietic transplant at our hospital. Methods: Retrospective study of all patients who until September 2012, received plerixafor in their scheme of mobilization into peripheral blood hematopoietic progenitors. We reviewed the medical records and records of drug dispensing outpatient consultation. Effectiveness variables used were: CD34/kg in apheresis product obtained, and day dose received colony stimulating factor (G-CSF) and Plerixafor. Each patient was compared to the effectiveness of the drug results with those obtained earlier mobilization schemes where Plerixafor not used, if present. Data were analyzed using IBM SPSS v19. Results: A total of 24 patients received  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Castillo, I. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Pareja, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidales Mancha, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heiniger Mazo, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruano Camps, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar efectividad del tratamiento con plerixafor en pacientes sometidos a movilización para posterior autotrasplante de progenitores hematopoyéticos en nuestro hospital. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de todos los pacientes que hasta septiembre 2012, recibieron plerixafor en su esquema de movilización de progenitores hematopoyéticos a sangre periférica. Se revisaron las historias clínicas y los registros de dispensación de medicamentos de la consulta de pacientes externos. Las variables de efectividad utilizadas fueron: CD34/kg en producto de aféresis obtenidas, dosis y días recibidos de factor estimulante de colonias (G-CSF) y de plerixafor. Para cada paciente se comparó los resultados de efectividad del fármaco con los obtenidos para anteriores esquemas de movilización en los que no se utilizó plerixafor, en caso de tenerlos. Los datos se (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;37(4): 317-321, jul.-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117419</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de plerixafor en pacientes sometidos a movilización de progenitores hematopoyéticos para autotrasplante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27905^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32203^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
