<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115887</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic agreement between the Personality Diagnostic Questionnaire-4+ (PDQ-4+) and its Clinical Significance Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The Personality Diagnostic Questionnaire-4+ (PDQ-4+) is composed of a self-report and an interview, the Clinical Significance Scale, but no studies have reported joint findings. This study is the first to examine the diagnostic agreement between the Spanish version of the PDQ-4+ selfreport and its corresponding interview. Method: The sample comprised 235 psychiatric outpatients who were assessed with both instruments. Results: The interview reduced to one half the number of diagnoses provided by self-report (83.4% to 38.3%; mean number of diagnoses 3.29 to .62). Diagnostic agreement was between fair and moderate (mean kappa .45 for PDQ-4+ total score). Conclusions: Findings suggest the utility of jointly administering the PDQ-4+ and its Clinical Significance Scale to screen for the presence or absence of personality disorders (PDs). Modifications in the diagnostic cut-offs for individual PDs and the PDQ-4+ total score may improve the efficacy of the instrument (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el Personality Diagnostic Questionnaire-4+ (PDQ-4+) está compuesto por un autoinforme y una entrevista, la Escala de Significación Clínica, pero ningún estudio ha sido publicado con resultados conjuntos. Este trabajo es el primero en examinar la concordancia diagnóstica entre la versión española del cuestionario PDQ-4+ y su correspondiente entrevista. Método: la muestra estaba formada por 235 pacientes psiquiátricos ambulatorios que fueron evaluados con ambos. Resultados: la entrevista reducía hasta la mitad el número de diagnósticos obtenido por el cuestionario (83,4% a 38,3%; número medio de diagnósticos de 3,29 a .62). La concordancia diagnóstica era de escasa a moderada (kappa media de .45 para la puntuación total del PDQ-4+). Conclusiones: nuestros datos sugieren la administración conjunta del PDQ-4+ y su Escala de Significación Clínica para el cribage de presencia o ausencia de trastornos de personalidad (TPs). Modificaciones en los puntos de corte para TPs específicos y para la puntuación total del PDQ-4+ podrían mejorar la eficacia del instrumento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);25(4): 427-432, oct.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115887</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concordancia diagnóstica entre el Personality Diagnostic Questionnaire-4+ (PDQ-4+) y su Escala de Significación Clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
