<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162997</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Different distribution of the common HFE variants between western and eastern Spanish populations evidences an independent haplotype gene flow</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hereditary hemochromatosis is a disease responsible for excess blood iron. The hemochromatosis gene has two predominant variants, H63D and C282Y single nucleotide polymorphisms. Our study aims to analyze the diagnostic utility of genotyping the 63 and 282 loci, and examine the geographic distribution of these mutations in Spain. Methods and materials. Genotyping was performed on 94 healthy control individuals and 324 patients suspected of hereditary hemochromatosis, and also biochemical test to 313 individuals in the patients group. Results. The comparison of allelic frequencies between East and West of Spain, as well as other countries located at a similar longitude, evidenced a west-east distribution gradient of the C282Y allele. In addition, heterogeneous distribution of the H63D mutation in Spain was observed. Patients who carried the 282YY genotype showed significantly higher biochemical parameters (ferritin&gt;300&amp;#956;g/L, Fe&gt;180&amp;#956;g/L, IST&gt;60%, UIBC&gt;355&amp;#956;g/L and CTFH&gt;370&amp;#956;g/dL), which confirmed the correlation between the mutated homozygous genotype and the associated hemochromatosis phenotype. Conclusion. Our results strengthen the importance of executing genetic tests to increase the efficiency of hereditary hemochromatosis diagnosis, which reveal an interesting variability among geographical regions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monzó, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gervasinie, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Muñoz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Bárbara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán, Carola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carlos Collado, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monzó, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lamo, Miguel de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcaida, Goitzane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel-Cabo, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-López, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hemocromatosis hereditaria es una enfermedad responsable del exceso de hierro en sangre. El gen de la hemocromatosis tiene dos variantes predominantes, los polimorfismos de un solo nucleótido H63D y C282Y. Nuestro estudio trata de analizar la utilidad diagnóstica del genotipado de los loci 282 y 63, y examinar la distribución geográfica de estas mutaciones en España. Material y métodos. Se realizó genotipado en 94 controles sanos y 324 pacientes con sospecha de hemocromatosis hereditaria y además, test bioquímico a 313 individuos del grupo de pacientes. Resultados. La comparación de frecuencias alélicas entre poblaciones del este y el oeste de España, así como de otros países localizados en longitudes similares, evidenció una distribución en gradiente del alelo C282Y. Además se observó una distribución heterogénea de la mutación H63D en España. Los pacientes portadores del genotipo 282YY mostraron parámetros bioquímicos significativamente más elevados (ferritina &gt;300&amp;#956;g/L, Fe &gt; 180&amp;#956;g/L, IST &gt; 60%, UIBC &gt; 355&amp;#956;g/L y CTFH&gt;370&amp;#956;g/dL), confirmando la correlación entre el genotipo homozigoto mutado y el fenotipo característico de hemocromatosis. Conclusión. Nuestros resultados refuerzan la importancia de realizar pruebas genéticas para confirmar el diagnóstico de la hemocromatosis hereditaria, teniendo en cuenta la variabilidad de los datos entre ámbitos geográficos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;10(2): 72-78, abr.-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162997</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias en la distribución de las variantes comunes del gen HFE entre poblaciones del oeste y este de España evidencian un flujo independiente de sus distintos haplotipos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33560^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6582^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7668^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11547^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6582^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54727^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6582^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
