<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95917</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">ECG differential diagnosis of narrow QRS complex tachycardia in the emergency department: A review of common rhythms and distinguishing features</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The differentiation of narrow complex tachycardias (NCT) is a commonly encountered diagnostic dilemma in the adult emergency department. Some NCTs (e.g., sinus tachycardia) are secondary to the presenting complaint (e.g., fever, anxiety, pain) and will respond to appropriate treatment of the inciting pathologic insult. Alternatively, other NCTs (e.g., atrial fibrillation, AV nodal reentrant tachycardia) may indeed be the cause of the chief complaint (e.g., palpitations, light headedness from poor perfusion) and must be positively identified and primarily managed. An appreciation of the similarities and differences among these NCTs is necessary for appropriate recognition. This article delineates which demographic, historical, and electrocardiographic characteristics are helpful in identifying the following rhythms: sinustachycardia, sinus node reentrant tachycardia, unifocal atrial tachycardias, multifocal atrial tachycardia, atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, atrioventricular nodal reentrant tachycardia, and atrioventricular reentrant tachycardia. In addition, a discussion of various diagnostic maneuvers, such as adenosine administration, is included (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pines, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borloz, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brady, W. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mark, D. G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico diferencial de las taquicardias de complejo QRS estrecho (TQRSE) es un dilema común en los pacientes adultos que acuden a los servicios de urgencias. AlgunasTQRSE (ej.: taquicardia sinusal) son secundarias a los motivos que propiciaron su consulta (ej.: fiebre, ansiedad, dolor) y responderán al tratamiento apropiado de la patología subyacente. Por otro lado, otras TQRSE (ej.: fibrilación auricular, taquicardia de reentrada nodal AV) pueden ser verdaderamente el origen de la sintomatología principal(ej.: palpitaciones, mareo secundario a la hipoperfusión) y deben ser positivamente identificadas y tratadas. Para un correcto diagnóstico es necesario conocer las semejanzas y diferencias entre las distintas TQRSE. Este artículo comenta cuáles son las características demográficas, clínicas y electrocardiográficas que son de ayuda para identificarlos siguientes ritmos: taquicardia sinusal, taquicardia de reentrada del nodo sinusal, taquicardia auricular unifocal, taquicardia auricular multifocal, fibrilación auricular, flutterauricular, taquicardia de reentrada del nodo auriculoventricular y taquicardia de reentrada auriculoventricular. Además, se realiza un comentario sobre las distintas maniobras diagnósticas, que vincluye la administración de adenosina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(5): 369-380, oct. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95917</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico diferencial electrocardiográfico de la taquicardia de complejo QRS estrecho en el servicio de urgencias: una revisión de ritmos frecuentes y sus características distintivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20206^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13993^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
