<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165005</identifier>
<setSpec>0377-4732</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Features and consequences of gender violence: study of cases confirmed by a conviction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Gender violence is a major public health problem with a significant socio-family and economic impact. The aim of this study was to analyse the characteristics and circumstances of abuse, including the subjects involved (victim and aggressor), their intimate relationship, as well as the peculiarities of abuse and its harmful consequences. Material and methods. Retrospective and descriptive study of cases classified as gender violence from the prosecutor's office of Santiago de Compostela between 2005 and 2012. A total of 398 cases of gender violence with a final conviction were analysed. Results. Victims were mainly young women (mean age 36.6 years), of Spanish nationality (82.91%), married (39.70%), with children (69.85%), employed (40.45%) and with low socioeconomic status (53.52%). Aggressors had an average age of 39.5 years, were predominantly Spanish (85.93%) and of low socioeconomic status (37.44%). At the time of abuse, 56.03% of the couples lived together and 62.22% shared the house with children. The maltreatment, mainly a combination of physical and psychological abuse (43.72%), occurred most often at home (65.08%) and was witnessed by others (64.57%). As a result of the aggression, 53.02% of women suffered physical injuries, generally bruises or haematomas (41.21%) located mainly on the upper limbs (26.88%) and face (24.37%). Conclusions. The information obtained on the characteristics and circumstances of abuse is an essential step in order to formulate evidence-based intervention and treatment strategies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Portomeñe, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Calvo, María Sol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Fernández, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Silva, Isabel María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La violencia de género constituye un importante problema de salud pública con un gran impacto sociofamiliar y económico. El objetivo de este estudio ha sido analizar las características y circunstancias del maltrato, incluyendo a los sujetos implicados (víctima y agresor) y su relación de pareja, así como las peculiaridades del abuso y sus consecuencias lesivas. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo, de tipo descriptivo, de los casos clasificados como violencia de género por la Fiscalía de Área de Santiago de Compostela, durante el período 2005-2012. Se analizaron 398 casos de violencia de género con sentencia firme condenatoria. Resultados. Las víctimas eran, sobre todo, mujeres jóvenes (media 36,6 años), de nacionalidad española (82,91%), casadas (39,70%), con hijos (69,85%), empleo remunerado (40,45%) y nivel socioeconómico bajo (53,52%). Los agresores tenían una edad media de 39,5 años, con predominio de españoles (85,93%), de nivel socioeconómico bajo (37,44%). En el momento de la agresión, el 56,03% de las parejas convivían y un 62,22% compartía la vivienda con los hijos. El maltrato, fundamentalmente combinación de abuso físico y psicológico (43,72%), se produjo sobre todo en el domicilio (65,08%) y fue presenciado por terceras personas (64,57%). Como consecuencia de la agresión, el 53,02% de las mujeres sufrieron lesiones físicas, básicamente contusiones o hematomas (41,21%), localizadas principalmente en los miembros superiores (26,88%) y en la cara (24,37%). Conclusiones. La información obtenida sobre las características y circunstancias del maltrato es fundamental para adaptar, en base a la evidencia, las medidas de intervención y tratamiento de este problema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. legal;43(3): 115-122, jul.-sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165005</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características y consecuencias de la violencia de género: estudio de casos confirmados por sentencia judicial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
