<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93968</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric properties of a Multidimensional Scale of Social Expression to assess social skills in the Internet context</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The increase in the use of New Technologies in social relationships could be generating a new paradigm in social skills. Valid and reliable instruments to assess these changes are needed. The aim of this study is to analyze the psychometric properties of the Multidimensional Scale of Social Expression (EMES) in the assessment of social skills on the Internet and Social Networks. A total of 413 college students from the province of Alicante participated on this study. The scale was applied according to two contexts: Real and Internet/Virtual. High internal consistency was shown. The 12-factor structure found for the Virtual Context scale is similar to that of the original study. The scale had shown to be a good predictor of hours of Internet use. In conclusion, EMES-C is useful for assessing real context and Internet context social skills (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orgilés, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballo, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Jover, M. Virtudes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piqueras, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espada, José P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El incremento en el uso de las Nuevas Tecnologías en las relaciones sociales podría estar creando un nuevo paradigma en las habilidades sociales. Se necesitan instrumentos válidos y fiables para evaluar estos cambios. El objetivo de este estudio es analizar las propiedades psicométricas de la Escala Multidimensional de Expresión Social (EMES) en la evaluación de las habilidades sociales en Internet y las Redes Sociales. En el estudio participaron 413 estudiantes universitarios de la provincia de Alicante. El instrumento se aplicó atendiendo a dos contextos: el Real y el de Internet/Virtual. Los resultados muestran una alta consistencia interna. La estructura factorial de la escala para el Contexto Virtual, de 12 factores, es similar a la del estudio original. La escala se muestra como un buen predictor de las horas de uso de Internet. En conclusión, el EMES es útil para evaluar habilidades sociales en contexto real y el contexto de Internet (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(1): 121-126, ene.-mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93968</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades psicométricas de la Escala Multidimensional de expresión social para la evaluación de habilidades sociales en el contexto de Internet</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
