<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86539</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-5434</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clove oil as an anesthetic for pacu fish (piaractus mesopotamicus)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In order to minimize damage to fish caused by the use of anesthetic substances, this study was to evaluate the concentration of clove oil as an anesthetic most appropriate for pacu (Piaractus mesopotamicus). A total of 40 fishes, with average weight of 716.18 g. The treatments were: anesthetic procedures with solutions of different concentrations of clove oil, 30, 60, 90, 120 and 150 mg.L-1. We used two glass aquariums: one with 20 liters of water containing the anesthetic solution for each treatment and the other with 20 liters of clean water, the animals return to the condition of sedation. Were observed individually: the time to reach deep anesthesia and recovery time of deep anesthesia. The experimental design was completely randomized design with five treatments (concentrations of clove oil) and eight replicates (individuals). The data were submitted to regression, with 5% significance level. There was a linear time of anesthesia and return of fish to increasing concentrations of clove oil, and 30 mg.L-1 is sufficient for the induction of the animals, but higher concentrations of up to 150 mg.L-1, still show inductions faster, without loss in time and conditions for the recovery of fish(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perez Ribeiro, Paula Adriane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solis Murgas, Luis David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Costa, Leandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieira e Rosa, Priscila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Augusto Eloy, Ângelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con el propósito de minimizar el daño causado a los peces por el uso de sustancias anestésicas, se ha evaluado, en este trabajo, la concentración más adecuada de aceite de clavo como anestésico para el pez pacu (Piaractus mesopotamicus). Fueron utilizados 40 peces, con peso promedio de 716,18 g. Los tratamientos fueron compuestos de soluciones con diferentes concentraciones de aceite de clavo, 30, 60, 90, 120 y 150 mg/L. Fueron utilizados dos acuarios de vidrio: uno con 20 litros de agua con la solución anestésica para cada tratamiento y otro con 20 litros de agua limpia, para el regreso de los animales de la condición de sedación. Se observaron de forma individual: el tiempo hasta llegar a la anestesia profunda y el tiempo de recuperación de la anestesia profunda. El diseño experimental fue completamente aleatorizado con cinco tratamientos (concentraciones de aceite de clavo) y ocho repeticiones (peces). Los tiempos hasta anestesia profunda e hasta la recuperación total de los peces fueron evaluados por regresión, con 5% de significancia. Se observó un comportamiento linear de los tiempos hasta la anestesia profunda y hasta la recuperación total de los peces a concentraciones crecientes de aceite de clavo. La concentración de 30 mg/L es suficiente para la inducción anestésica de los animales, por otra parte, las concentraciones más elevadas, hasta 150 mg/L, causaron inducciones aún más rápidas, sin pérdida en las condiciones para la recuperación de los peces(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. vet. Murcia;26: 69-76, ene.-dic. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86539</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aceite de clavo como anestésico para el pez Pacu (piaractus mesopotamicus)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38322^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31643^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22448^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22448^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31643^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38322^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
