<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73027</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Profi le of the patient who wants to quick smoking seen in the Primary Care and Specialized consultations in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the profi le of the smoker who wants to stop smoking. Subjectsand methods. A cross-sectional, multicenter study was conducted in 1634 smokersattended by General Practitioners and Specialized Physicians in Spain who had expressedtheir desire to stop smoking when explicitly asked. Sociodemographic data, backgroundof smoking and related consequences were collected. A descriptive statistical analysiswas performed.Results. 67.1% of patients were seen by General Practitioners. Mean age ± standarddeviation was 45.6 ± 12.0 years old and mean age of onset of usual consumption was 20.6± 7.0. Fifty-six percent of the population studied were men. Most (35.2%) had studiedbeyond high school and 76.4% were active workers. Seventy-one percent had previouslytried to stop smoking (2.7± 3.0 mean attempts). Out of 39.2% smokers who had participatedin some type of smoking cessation treatment the year before, 70.7% were on substitutivetherapy with nicotine. At the time of the visit, 80% admitted they could not stop smokingby themselves.Conclusions. The profi le of the smoker seen in Primary Care and Specialized Consultationin Spain who wants to quit smoking corresponds to a male subject in his 40&#146;s, with studiesbeyond high school, actively working who has made more that two previous attempts tostop smoking, mostly with substitutive therapy with nicotine and who currently believeshe is not being able to achieve it by himself(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo ESFUME</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el perfi l del paciente fumador que desea abandonar el hábito tabáquico.Sujetos y método. Estudio multicéntrico transversal sobre 1.634 fumadores, atendidosen consultas de Atención Primaria y especializada de España, que tras preguntarles explícitamenteexpresan su deseo de abandonar el hábito tabáquico. Se recopilaron datossociodemográfi cos, antecedentes del hábito tabáquico y consecuencias asociadas. Serealizó un análisis de estadística descriptiva.Resultados. El 67,1% de los pacientes se visitó en Atención Primaria. La edad media ± desviaciónestándar fue de 45,6 ± 12,0 años y la del inicio del consumo regular, 20,6 ± 7,0.Los hombres representaban el 55,9% de la población estudiada. La mayoría (35,2%) teníaestudios posecundarios y el 76,4% se encontraba en situación laboral activa. El 70,8% habíarealizado algún intento previo para dejar de fumar, con un promedio de 2,7 ± 3,0. Entre el39,2% de los pacientes que siguieron algún tratamiento de deshabituación durante el añoprevio, el 70,7% realizó terapia sustitutiva con nicotina. En el momento de la visita, el 80%reconoció que se veía incapaz de dejar de fumar por sí mismo.Conclusiones. El perfi l del fumador atendido en consultas de Atención Primaria y especializadade España que quiere dejar de fumar corresponde al del varón en la cuarta décadade vida, con estudios pos-secundarios, en activo a nivel laboral, que ya ha realizado más de dos intentos previos de deshabituación, en la mayoría de los casos con terapiassustitutivas de la nicotina, y que en la actualidad no se cree capaz de abandonar el tabaquismosin ayuda externa(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;209(4): 160-167, abr.2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73027</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil del paciente que quiere dejar de fumar atendido en consultas de Atención Primaria y especializada de España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
