<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85221</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interference due to iodinated contrast media in capillary electrophoresis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The administration of iodinated contrast media may interfere with the capillary electrophoresis (CE) of serum proteins. The aim of the study was to perform an in vitro study to confirm the interference caused by lomeron® administration followed by an in vivo study in patients undergoing coronary angiographies, evaluating the kinetics of iodinated contrast elimination. Material and methods. A serum pool free from monoclonal component (MC) and with an anodyne electrophoretic pattern was prepared. lomeron® up to a concentration of 5.4g/100mL was added to this pool and afterwards, four decreasing dilutions were prepared (2.70g/100mL, 1.35g/100mL, 0.67g/100mL and 0.33g/100mL); all of them were processed by CE to confirm the interference and its decreasing effect as the concentration diminishes. Material and methods. Blood was drawn from patients undergoing coronary angiographies, at several time intervals (5&#150;10min, 1, 3, 5 and 8h post-administration of contrast). Plasma samples were processed by CE, and immunofixation (IFx) of the first sample (5&#150;10min) was performed in order to show that the electrophoretic image did not correspond to a MC. Results. In the in vitro study, CE revealed &amp;#946; fraction-MC peaks, which disappeared at the 0.33g/100mL dilution, and 8h after lomeron® administration in the in vivo study (one patient). On the other hand, no image suggestive of MC was detected on the reference agarose gel electrophoresis (AGE) used for the IFx. Conclusions. Peaks were observed that corresponded to an interference produced by lomeron® in the &amp;#946; fraction of CE, which was not found in AGE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rentería Obregón, Ivy Mariel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Brú, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Moll, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballo Silva, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballeira Pol, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Comella, Margarida</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La administración de contrastes yodados puede interferir en la electroforesis capilar (EFC) de proteínas séricas. El objetivo fue realizar un estudio in vitro para confirmar la presencia de interferencias por Iomeron® en la EFC y otro in vivo en pacientes sometidos a coronariografías, estudiando la cinética de eliminación del contraste yodado. Material y métodos. Se preparó un pool de sueros libres de componente monoclonal (CM), con patrón electroforético anodino, añadiéndose Iomeron® hasta alcanzar una concentración de 5,4g/100ml. Partiendo de esta solución (A) se realizaron cuatro diluciones decrecientes (2,70g/100ml, 1,35g/100ml, 0,67g/100ml y 0,33g/100ml); y se procesaron por EFC para confirmar la interferencia y observar que disminuye proporcionalmente a su concentración. Material y métodos. Se extrajo sangre, pautadamente (5&#150;10min, 1, 3, 5 y 8h postadministración del contraste) a pacientes sometidos a coronariografías. Se procesaron las muestras de plasma por EFC, y se realizó la inmunofijación (IF) de la obtenida entre los 5&#150;10min para demostrar que la imagen electroforética no se correspondía con un CM. Resultados. La EFC reveló picos similares a los observados ante un CM en la fracción &amp;#946;, que desaparecieron en la dilución 0,33g/100ml en el estudio in vitro, y a las 8h postadministración del Iomeron® en el estudio in vivo (una paciente). Por otra parte, en la electroforesis de referencia del gel de agarosa empleado en la IF no se detectó imagen sugerente de CM. Conclusiones. Se demuestra que los picos observados correspondían a una interferencia producida por el Iomeron® en la fracción &amp;#946; de la EFC, no observada en la electroforesis en gel de agarosa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;3(3): 129-135, jul.-sept. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interferencias por contrastes yodados en la electroforesis capilar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32762^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32762^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32762^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23132^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23132</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
