<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106601</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Discontinuous intrabdominal splenogonadal fusion with germ cell Tumor. Excision with robotic assistence. Adult case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Present the case of a patient with a discontinuous intrabdominal splenogonadal fusion with an associated germ cell tumor. METHODS: A case of a man of 29 years with bilateral cryptorchidism and left intra-abdominal discontinuous splenogonadal fusion associated with seminoma as an accidental finding in the context of a robotic pyeloplasty due to ipsilateral ureteropelvic junction stenosis. RESULTS: The total operative time was 80 minutes (atrophic gonad removal and pyeloplasty by the Anderson-Hynes technique) with an estimated blood loss less than 100 cc. The hospitalization time was less than 36 hrs. The pathology and immunohistochemical report was compatible with intratubular germ cell neoplasia (seminoma). CONCLUSION: The splenogonadal fusion is an uncommon pathology. While a high clinical suspicion may avoid unnecessary orchiectomy in young patients, its association with disorders such as cryptorchidism should make us suspect the possible presence of a concomitant germ cell neoplasia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velarde Ramos, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Octavio A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sepulveda, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar el caso de una fusión esplenogonadal intrabdominal discontínua asociada a neoplasia germinal. MÉTODOS: Se presenta el caso de un varón de 29 años con criptorquidia bilateral y fusión esplenogonadal discontinua izquierda intrabdominal, asociada a Seminoma como hallazgo casual en el contexto de una pieloplastía robótica debido a una estenosis pieloureteral ipsilateral. RESULTADOS: El tiempo operatorio total fue de 80 minutos (extirpación de gónada atrófica y pieloplastía según técnica de Anderson-Hynes) con un sangrado estimado menor a 100 cc siendo el paciente dado de alta antes de 36 hrs. El informe anatomopatológico e inmunohistoquímico fue compatible con neoplasia intratubular de células germinales (Seminoma). CONCLUSIÓN: La fusión esplenogonadal es una patología infrecuente. Si bien una alta sospecha clínica puede evitar una orquiectomía innecesaria en pacientes jóvenes, su asociación a alteraciones como la criptorquidia debe hacernos sospechar la eventual presencia de una neoplasia de células germinales concomitante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(8): 762-765, oct. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106601</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fusion esplenogonadal discontinua intraabdominal asociado a neoplasia germinal. Exeresis con asistencia robotica. Presentacion de un caso en adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31051^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31051^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3473^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31051^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3473^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31880</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5994^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31051^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3473^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3473^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
