<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154162</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of the characteristics in hen and quail corneas as experimental models of refractive surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To compare the histological, morphological and the biophysical measurements between hen and quail corneas, in order to determine which of them were better suited for use as an animal model for research into corneal refractive surgery. Material and methods: A study was performed using the biophysical measurements of the cornea (curvature, thickness, refraction, and axial length) of 20 animals (10 hens and 10 quails). The corneas were then prepared for histological analysis under microscopy light. Results: The analysis showed that both groups have the same number of corneal layers as the human cornea and with an evident Bowman's layer. The thickness of the hen cornea and axial length of the eye, 225.3 ± 18.4 &amp;#956;m and 12.8 ± 0.25 mm, respectively, were larger than that of the quail (P &lt; .01 andP &lt; .001, respectively). The radius of curvature for the hen central cornea, 3.65 ± 0.08 mm, was greater than that for the quail (P &lt; .001), but the refractive power of each cornea was similar. The proportion of total corneal thickness of the hen stroma, 82.6%, was more similar to that of the human than was the quail stroma, 72.5%. Within the hen stroma, the density of keratocytes, 8.57 ± 1.49 per 5,000 &amp;#956;m2, was about half that in the quail stroma (P &lt; .005). Conclusions: Because of the large size of the hen cornea, the stromal thickness and proportional similarity of the corneal layers with human cornea, the hen maybe better than the quail as an alternative species suitable for use in studies of corneal refractive surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Merino, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merayo Loves, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barcía, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonçalves, GC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar y comparar la histología, la morfología y las medidas biofísicas corneales de la gallina y la codorniz para determinar qué modelo experimental animal es el más adecuado para la realización de estudios de investigación en cirugía corneal. Material y métodos: Se estudiaron las medidas biofísicas de la córnea (curvatura, espesor, refracción y longitud axial) de 20 animales (10 gallinas y 10 codornices). Después las córneas fueron procesadas para el estudio de histología clásica bajo la luz del microscopio. Resultados: Los 2 grupos analizados poseen una córnea similar a la del humano con respecto al número de capas y con una evidente capa de Bowman. El espesor corneal, así como la longitud axial del ojo de la gallina, 225,3 ± 18,4 &amp;#956;m y 12,8 ± 0,25 mm, respectivamente, fueron significativamente mayores que los de la codorniz (p &lt; 0,01 y p &lt; 0,001). El radio de curvatura de la córnea central de la gallina también fue significativamente mayor que el de la codorniz (p &lt; 0,001). El poder refractivo de las 2 especies fue similar. La proporción del espesor estromal con relación a la córnea en la gallina fue más similar al humano (82,6%) que de la codorniz (72,5%). La densidad de la población de queratocitos en la gallina, 8,57 ± 1,49/5.000 &amp;#956;m2, correspondió a cerca de la mitad del número de queratocitos encontrados en la córnea de la codorniz (p &lt; 0,005). Conclusiones: La córnea de gallina, por su tamaño, espesor del estroma y similitud de proporción en sus capas con la córnea humana, es más adecuada para la cirugía refractiva corneal que la de codorniz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(7): 310-315, jul. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154162</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de las características corneales en gallina y codorniz como modelos experimentales de cirugía refractiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52862^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52866^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2691^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52866^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12221^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52862^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55019^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3333^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12221^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55019^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55019^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3333^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
