<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124129</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health care and patients in the &#147;Hospital de paisanos&#148; in Zamora in the 18th century</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The numerous hospitals in existence in the city of Zamora in the Middle Ages were considerably streamlined in the Early Modern Era. The foundation of the Sotelo hospital in the 16th century and the La Encarnación hospital in the 17th century endowed the city with two main centres offering medical and health care. This study focused on an analysis of the patients who received care at the La Encarnación hospital, which was governed by the City Council and the Cathedral Chapter. A patient profile was constructed from admission and mortality records, depending on the case. However, the main focus was an analysis of the hospital&#146;s area of influence, which was found to amply exceed its immediate geographical context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Álvarez, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El gran número de hospitales que tuvo la ciudad de Zamora durante la Edad Media quedó notablemente simplificado en la época Moderna. La fundación en el siglo XVI del hospital de Sotelo y en el XVII de La Encarnación, supuso dotar a la ciudad con dos importantes centros que ofrecía atención médico-sanitaria. Este trabajo está centrado en el de La Encarnación, entre cuyos administradores se hallaban el Ayuntamiento y el Cabildo de la Catedral, y el objeto de análisis han sido los asistidos. A partir de los registros de ingreso y defunciones, dependiendo del momento, hemos trazado el perfil de los mismos, pero, sobre todo, nos hemos centrado en el radio de influencia del establecimiento, que, como hemos podido comprobar, superaba ampliamente el marco geográfico de emplazamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;66(1): 1-14[p38], ene.-jun. 2014. tab, mapa</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124129</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los Pacientes del &#145;Hospital de paisanos&#146; de Zamora en el Siglo XVIII</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10554^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10537^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53789^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
