<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65554</identifier>
<setSpec>0482-5985</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. Sixty-one cases of juvenile hallux valgus are presented that were treated surgically through a modified Pelet technique. Materials and methods. Between 1996 and 2002, 37 patients were subjected to the above mentioned technique (30 females and 7 males). Mean age was 14 years (range: 9-19). Minimum follow-up was one year. In all cases a subcapital osteotomy of the first metatarsal was carried out according to the technique described by Pelet. The osteosynthesis material used was a bioresorbable rod. Weight-bearing was allowed at 24 hours. Results. Healing was achieved at 5 weeks on average. In all cases an improvement was obtained in the intermetatarsal and hallux valgus angles, with good clinical results and few complications. Conclusions. We believe that Pelet osteotomy is suitable for the treatment of juvenile and adolescent hallux valgus since it is a non-aggressive technique that can correct the most usual pathogenetic alterations seen in these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cepero-Campá, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ullot-Font, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poggio-Cano,  D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lasurt-Bachs, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Se presentan 61 casos de hallux valgus juvenil tratados quirúrgicamente mediante la técnica de Pelet modificada. Material y método. En el periodo comprendido entre 1996 y 2002 se han revisado 37 pacientes, 30 mujeres y 7 hombres, con unas edades comprendidas entre 9 y 19 años, promedio de 14 años, a los que se les practicó dicha técnica. El seguimiento mínimo fue de un año. En todos los casos se ha llevado a cabo una osteotomía subcapital del primer metatarsiano según la técnica descrita por Pelet, colocando como osteosíntesis una barra de material biorreabsorbible. Se autorizó la carga a las 24 horas. Resultados. Se ha conseguido la consolidación en un promedio de 5 semanas. En todos los casos se ha logrado una mejora de los ángulos intermetatarsiano y de hallux valgus con buen resultado clínico y pocas complicaciones. Conclusiones. Creemos que la osteotomía de Pelet es una técnica adecuada para el tratamiento del hallux valgus juvenil y del adolescente ya que es capaz de corregir las alteraciones patogénicas más frecuentes en estos pacientes, al mismo tiempo que nos parece poco agresiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. ortop. traumatol. (Madr., Ed. impr.);51(5): 264-269, sept.-oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65554</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23263^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
