<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83014</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical evidence on the genesis and spread of the concept of &#147;arnica&#148; in Western Europe</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The concept of &#147;árnica&#148; is linked to different species of Asteraceae or other plant families. Unknown to the Classic Greeks and Romans it was not cited in the Early Medieval texts. It was first introduced in 1533 by the editor of St. Hildegard&#146;s Physica to name a magical plant species. Arnica montana L., was described by Linneus in 1753. It was introduced during the 18th century in the medicine for the treatment of inflammation and hematoma, becoming widely used in the 19th and 20th centuries. The nomenclature of Arnica in Western and Central Europe is analyzed in Germanic (German, Walser or Tisch, Mochene) and Romance languages (Francoprovençal, Occitan, French, Italian, Ladino, Spanish, Catalan and Portuguese) and the evolution of the concept in different authors. This allows us to conclude that the use of Arnica is deeply rooted in the Alpine traditions, whereas in the Mediterranean is recent (2nd half of the 18th century), reaching the folk-medicine through physicians and pharmacists(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Verde, Alonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Obón, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fajardo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El concepto de &#147;árnica&#148; está ligado a diferentes especies de la familia Asteráceas o incluso de otras familias. Era desconocido para los clásicos greco-romanos y tampoco se mencionó en los textos de la Alta Edad Media. Lo introdujo el editor de la obra Physica de Santa Hildegarda de Bingen, en 1533, para referirse a una planta con propiedades medicinales, mágicas y fabulosas. La especie Arnica montana L., fue descrita por Linneo en 1753. Alcanzó gran éxito en el siglo XVIII en el tratamiento de golpes e inflamaciones y se popularizó a lo largo de los siglos XIX y XX. Estudiamos la nomenclatura del árnica en la Europa Central y Occidental en lenguas germánicas (alemán, walser o tisch, moqueno) y romances (francoprovenzal, occitano, francés, italiano, ladino, español, catalán y portugués) y la evolución del concepto en diferentes autores botánicos. Esto nos permite concluir que los usos del árnica, muy arraigados en el mundo alpino, son recientes en el mediterráneo (segunda mitad del Siglo XVIII), llegando a la medicina popular a través de médicos y farmacéuticos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;10(2): 157-172, nov.2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencia histórica sobre la génesis y difusión del concepto de &#147;Árnica&#148; en Europa Occidental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32351^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33297^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32351^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1924^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1924^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32351^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
