<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057788</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Case-mix in rehabilitation emergencies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract.--Introduction. In countries with advanced medical systems, there has been a progressive increase in the use of emergency departments. Therefore, it is necessary to create a system to classify patients in function of severity and other parameters for triage to ensure an appropriate response.                 Objectives. a) To know the case-mix of our rehabilitation emergencies; b) to analyze the data statistically; c) to define levels of complexity and emergency with a trial sample and d) to specify the criteria and parameters for a triage system based on the Canadian Triage and Acuity Scale.                 Material and methods. Demographic, administrative, and healthcare data were collected prospectively from 589 patients from 22/07/2005 to 20/12/2005.                 Results. The mean emergency department stay was 94 minutes.                 60.7 % of the sample were women and the mean age was 48 years.                 Men came for low back pain (the most frequent cause for presentation) more than women, and this difference was statistically significant.                 Cervical pain attended in our emergencies was not urgent (p &lt; 0.05).                 Conclusions. The prototypical patient attended in our emergency department is a middle-aged woman with low back pain.                 The application of a triage system enables objective criteria to be used to prioritize care in a tertiary center</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arroyo-Aljaro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Amejeiras, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En los países con sistemas sanitarios avanzados se asiste a un aumento progresivo de los índices de utilización de los servicios de Urgencias. Por ello, se hace necesario adecuar la respuesta asistencial creando sistemas de clasificación de los pacientes en función de su gravedad u otros parámetros de cribaje.                 Objetivos. a) Conocer el case-mix de la población atendida en nuestras Urgencias de rehabilitación; b) analizar estadísticamente los datos obtenidos; c) definir niveles de complejidad y urgencia a través de una prueba piloto, y d) precisar los criterios y parámetros de un sistema de cribaje en base a la Escala Canadiense de Triaje y Gravedad (Anexo 1).                 Material y métodos. Se ha llevado a cabo un estudio prospectivo en el período de 22/07/2005 a 20/12/2005 a partir de una muestra de 589 pacientes en la que se recogieron datos demográficos, administrativos y sanitarios.                 Resultados. La media de permanencia en Urgencias fue de 94 minutos. El 60,7 % de la muestra eran mujeres y la media de edad fue de 48 años.                 Los hombres acudieron por dolor lumbar (motivo más frecuente de consulta) de forma estadísticamente más significativa que las mujeres.                 El dolor cervical atendido en nuestra muestra podría ser catalogado de no urgente (p &lt; 0,05).                 Conclusiones. El paciente tipo atendido en nuestra muestra es una mujer de mediana edad que acude por lumbalgia.                 La aplicación de un sistema de cribaje permite priorizar con criterios objetivos la respuesta asistencial en un centro de tercer nivel</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);41(5): 207-213, sep.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057788</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Case-mix en Urgencias de rehabilitación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
