<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165827</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The epidemiology of secondary cardiovascular prevention in Spain: facts and figures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease is the leading cause of death in developed countries and is a growing problem in developing countries. Increased industrialization, poor eating habits and the greater prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors have all contributed to the situation. Spain is not excluded from this epidemic as incidence and prevalence rates are in line with those in neighboring countries. This escalation is not simply an epidemiological or health problem, it also has an economic dimension because the direct and indirect costs of cardiovascular disease have serious implications for national economies. Despite the efforts made in recent years to develop new therapeutic strategies and implement specially designed programs that together have resulted in the stabilization of cardiovascular disease mortality in Spain, the prevalence of diabetes mellitus, hypertension and obesity continues to rise and each year these conditions are affecting younger and younger individuals. Moreover, patients with established coronary heart disease rarely achieve the disease control and secondary prevention targets established by major scientific societies and the problem of poor treatment adherence has now emerged as a common cause of therapeutic failure. In order to deal with this growing social, health and economic problem, it is essential that effective strategies for monitoring and following up patients with cardiovascular disease are developed, with particular emphasis on the prevention and control of major cardiovascular risk factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamorano Gómez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades cardiovasculares son la primera causa de muerte en los países desarrollados y un problema creciente en los países en vías de desarrollo. Una sociedad cada vez más industrializada, los malos hábitos nutricionales y la prevalencia creciente de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular han contribuido a su incremento. España no es ajena a esta epidemia, con cifras de incidencia y prevalencia en línea con los demás países de nuestro entorno. Este aumento no solo se encuadra dentro de un problema epidemiológico y sanitario, sino que conlleva un componente económico derivado de los gastos directos e indirectos de la enfermedad cardiovascular que suponen un aspecto importante para las economías de los países. Pese a los esfuerzos realizados en los últimos años, con el desarrollo de nuevas estrategias terapéuticas y la puesta en marcha de programas específicos que han desembocado en la estabilización de la mortalidad por enfermedad cardiovascular en nuestro país, la prevalencia de diabetes mellitus, hipertensión arterial y obesidad continúa en ascenso e incide a edades cada vez más precoces. Asimismo, los pacientes con enfermedad coronaria establecida raramente alcanzan los objetivos de control y prevención secundaria establecidos por las principales sociedades científicas, y además surge el problema de la adherencia al tratamiento como una causa común del fracaso terapéutico. Es preciso desarrollar estrategias eficaces para el control y el seguimiento de los pacientes con enfermedad cardiovascular, haciendo especial hincapié en la prevención y el control de los principales factores de riesgo cardiovascular, con la finalidad de hacer frente a un problema sociosanitario y económico creciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);15(supl.E): 2e-6e, 2015. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165827</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de la prevención secundaria en España: hechos y cifras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2358^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
