<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97770</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The pragmatic awareness of adults with Asperger syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pragmatic awareness is a complex concept associated with a hybrid cognitive science such as psycholinguistics. In this case, the process related to the perception of one's own linguistic use and the capacity to report it, is analysed. The first step was to elaborate a Pragmatic Awareness Questionnaire (PAQ), composed of 26 items, using a Likert scale, which was answered by 18 male patients diagnosed with Asperger syndrome (AS), and 18 adults with typical development (TD). The objective was, on the one hand, to study the dimensionality of PAQ, applying an Exploratory Factor Analysis (EFA) and, on the other, to compare the average amongst the answers to each pragmatic item according to the group by performing a Mann-Whitney U test. The results revealed a three-factor structure for the PAQ and the categories were divided into three pragmatic dimensions: enunciative, textual and interactive. Adults with AS, in general, did not show significant differences in items related to textual area (message, lexical and grammatical domains). However, in enunciative and interactive areas they exhibited deficits with regard to TD adults. The present work represents a first approach to the analysis of communicative behaviour (verbal and non-verbal) of young adults with AS(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Muñoz, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La conciencia pragmática es un concepto complejo que se asocia a una ciencia cognitiva híbrida como es la psicolingüística. En este caso, se analiza el proceso relacionado con la percepción del propio sujeto sobre el uso lingüístico y la capacidad para referirlo. El primer paso fue elaborar un Cuestionario de Conciencia Pragmática (CCP), compuesto por 26 ítems, utilizando una escala Likert, al que contestaron 18 varones diagnosticados con síndrome de Asperger (SA) y 18 adultos con desarrollo típico (DT). El objetivo fue, por un lado, estudiar la dimensionalidad del CCP, aplicando un análisis factorial exploratorio (AFE) y, por otro, comparar las medias de las respuestas en cada uno de los ítems pragmáticos en función del grupo, por medio de la prueba U Mann-Whitney. Los resultados revelaron una estructura tridimensional para el CCP y las categorías se agruparon en torno a tres dimensiones pragmáticas: enunciativa, textual e interactiva. Los adultos con SA no mostraron, en general, diferencias significativas en los ítems referidos al área textual (mensaje, dominios léxico y gramatical). No ocurrió lo mismo en las áreas enunciativa e interactiva, donde exhibieron una conciencia pragmática deficitaria en relación con los adultos con DT. El presente trabajo constituye una primera aproximación al análisis del comportamiento comunicativo (verbal y no verbal) de adultos jóvenes con SA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);32(1): 21-31, ene.-mar.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97770</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La conciencia pragmática de adultos con síndrome de Asperger</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12015^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1376^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12015^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
