<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051072</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Febrile hepatosplenomegaly in an infant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fever and splenomegaly are a diagnostic challenge, mainly from Primary Care Centres. We describe here the case of a female infant with intermittent fever over several weeks, in which a giant splenomegaly of 7-8 cm and a smaller hepatomegaly were the main symptoms. Diagnosticprotocol was followed, and normal accounts of leucocytes were found, but also anemia and mild thrombopenia, with increased cholesterol, triglicerydes and ferritine. The procedure included cultures (urine, blood, faeces) and serology from virus, atypical bacteria and leishmania, allof them negative. Increasing anemia was the cause of hospital admission for one week, although no diagnosis was reached. Afterwards, when the patient was being followed in our Primary Care Centre, a positive result for Leishmania sp PCR (Polimerase Chain Reaction) was informed. With a diagnose of visceral leishmaniasis, the patient then received standard doses of liposomal Amfotericin B disappearing afterwards fever and (slowly over a period of several months) splenomegaly. From the beginning of symptoms, our infant showed a scabbed lesionon her scalp, which was biopsied two months after treatment with amfotericin, being "cutaneousleishmaniasis" the new diagnose. The patient did not receive any other treatment and her lesion improved, although it remains as an atrophic scar.Kala-azar or visceral leishmaniasis is endemic in the Mediterranean countries, being L. infantumthe most prevalenfspecies in our afea. Pancytopenia and high fever are common, although afebrile periods of time can also be found in leishmaniasis case series. Splenomegaly is the most common symptom. Classic treatment included pentavalent antimonials but due torecent resistance of Indian species to this drug, visceralleishmaniasis can be treated with liposomalamfotericin B. Concomitant cutaneous and visceral leishmaniasis have been described, moreover among immunodepressed adults. We believe this is a very interesting case, where we describe a healthy infant with both types of leishmaniasis: visceral and cutaneous, which is the first one described in our country</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Gribble, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ibieta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Ventura, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Auñón Martín, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La esplenomegalia febril es un desafío diagnóstico, y más aún desde la Atención Primaria. Describimos un caso de una lactante, con fiebre intermitente de varias semanas de evolución. El hallazgo dominante era una esplenomegalia llamativa de 7-8 cm y una hepatomegaliade menor tamaño. Se realizaron pruebas complementarias siguiendo el protocolo diagnóstico, y se encontraron cifras normales de leucocitos, con anemia y trombopenia leve, aumento de colesterol, triglicéridos y ferritina. Se recogieron cultivos (sangre, heces, orina),que fueron negativos y serologías de virus, bacterias atípicas y leishmania, también negativas.Ante la anemización progresiva se ingresó a la paciente durante una semana, sin llegar a un diagnóstico. Posteriormente, y cuando la paciente se encontraba en seguimiento en la consulta de Atención Primaria, se recibió el resultado positivo para PCR (Reacción en Cadenade la Polimerasa) de Leishmania sp. La paciente reingresó y fue tratada con Anfotericina B liposomal en dosis estándar, con desaparición de la fiebre y disminución progresiva de la esplenomegalia. Desde el inicio de los síntomas presentaba además una lesión costrosa en cuerocabelludo, que fue biopsiada dos meses después del ingreso, y que dio como resultado leishmaniasis cutánea. En poco tiempo la lesión evolucionó a alopecia cicatricial, y no fue necesario ningún otro tratamiento.El kala-azar o leishmaniasis visceral es endémico en el área mediterránea, y es habitualmente causado en nuestro medio por L. infantum. Cursa habitualmente con pancitopenia y fiebre en picos, incluso períodos de defervescencia, yes la esplenomegalia el hallazgo habitual. El tratamiento clásico incluye los antimoniales aunque, debido a las resistencias (sobre todo en lasformas de la India), se puede tratar con anfotericina B liposomal. Se han descrito casos de leishmaniasisviscerales y cutáneas concomitantes, sobre todo en inmunodeficiencias. Creemos interesante este caso en ef que describimos a una lactante, no inmunodeprimida, con ambos tipos de leishmaniasis: visceral y cutánea, que sería el primero descrito en nuestro país</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;8(29): 51-63, ene.-mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hepatoesplenomegalia febril en un lactante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5445^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8072^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24226^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6686^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
