<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045306</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A retrospective study comparing two formulations of valproic acid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Valproic acid is available in two different presentations, Depakine ® and Depakine Crono ®. Equivalencesin plasmatic levels, efficacy and adverse effects between these two formulations are not fully established. Aim. To compareplasmatic levels, efficacy and plasmatic levels between Depakine and Depakine Crono. Patients and methods. We studied aretrospective series of 238 patients in treatment with Depakine or Depakine Crono and compared plasmatic levels, efficacyand adverse effects between both formulations. Results. A total of 173 patients had taken one formulation and 54 both. Plasmaticlevels were similar in both groups. There were more significantly more patients free of seizures among the Depakine Cronogroup. Significantly better outcomes were seen with Depakine Crono with respect to secondary effects. Adverse effects aresignificantly less frequent in men than in women. The higher the dose, the higher the incidence of adverse events. Conclusions.Depakine Crono seems to obtain similar plasmatic levels, is at least as efficacious and is associated with less adverse eventsthat Depakine</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poza-Aldea, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tellería-Elmezábal,  J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Gutiérrez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí-Massó, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El ácido valproico se presenta en dos formulacionesorales, Depakine ® (DP) y Depakine Crono ® (DPC).Existen dudas sobre la equivalencia de los niveles plasmáticos, laeficacia y los efectos secundarios de estas dos formulaciones.Objetivo. Comparar los niveles plasmáticos, la eficacia y los efectossecundarios de pacientes que toman una de las dos formulacionesorales en comprimidos de valproico disponibles en España.Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo sobre un total de 238episodios de pacientes que tomaban DP y DPC, que recoge datossobre niveles plasmáticos, eficacia en el control de las crisis y la incidencia de los efectos secundarios y los compara por subgruposde dosis, edad y sexo. Resultados. Un total de 173 pacientes habíatomado una formulación y 54 ambas. Los niveles plasmáticos fueronsimilares en ambos grupos. En la población total el número depacientes libres de crisis que tomaron DPC es significativamentemayor que con DP. El porcentaje de pacientes que sufren efectossecundarios es significativamente menor con DPC. La incidenciade efectos secundarios es significativamente menor en los varonesque en las mujeres. A mayor dosis de medicación, mayor incidenciade efectos adversos. Conclusiones. DPC parece obtener nivelesplasmáticos similares, es al menos tan eficaz y tiene un mejor perfilde inocuidad que DP</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(3): 129-132, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045306</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio retrospectivo comparando dos formulaciones de ácido valproico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
