<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037637</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lupus miliaris disseminatus faciei associated with epidermal cysts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lupus miliaris disseminatus faciei (LMDF) is a chronic granulomatous disease, which tends to be located on the central part of the face. Its typical histological image is one of epithelioid granulomas with caseous necrosis. Its association with epidermal cysts has been described on few occasions in literature. We present a case of LMDF associated with epidermal cysts in a female Caucasian patient. This association suggests that the rupture of the epidermal cysts may be related to the appearance of LMDF. However, there are probably other factors that may also contribute to its pathogenesis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno de Vega, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Sánchez, Tatiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Díez, Amaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daudén, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraga, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El lupus miliar diseminado de la cara (LMDF) es una enfermedad granulomatosa crónica, con predisposición a localizarse en el área central de la región facial. Su imagen histológica característica corresponde a granulomas epitelioides con necrosis caseosa. Su asociación con quistes epidérmicos se ha descrito en escasas ocasiones en la literatura médica. Se presenta un caso de LMDF asociado a quistes epidérmicos en una paciente de raza caucasiana. Esta asociación sugiere que la rotura de los quistes epidérmicos podría estar relacionada con la aparición de LMDF. Sin embargo, existen probablemente otros factores que pueden también contribuir a su patogénesis</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;96(5): 320-322, jun. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037637</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lupus miliar diseminado de la cara asociado a quistes epidérmicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19232^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19232^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5246^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14782^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14782^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14782^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14782^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
