<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130025</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Family structure and eating behavior disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The modern way of life, characterized by the cult of individualism, discredited authority, and a proliferation of points of view about reality, has modified family structure. This social structure imbues families and the way that its members become ill, in such a way that eating behavior disorders (EDs) have become a typically postmodern way of becoming ill. Methodology. The aim is to understand the systemic structure and vulnerability of families by comparing 108 families with members who have ED to 108 families without pathology. A questionnaire administered by an interview with trained personnel was used. Results. Families with ED have a different structure from the families in the control group. They have more psychiatric history and poor coping skills. The family hierarchy is not clearly defined and the leadership is diffuse, with strict and unpredictable rules, more intergenerational coalitions, and fewer alliances. The relationship between the parents is distant or confrontational, and their attitudes towards their children are complacent and selfish, with ambivalent and unaffectionate bonds. In the case of mothers, this is manifested by separation anxiety and dyadic dependence. Their expectations concerning their offspring are either very demanding and unrealistic, or indifferent, and there is less control of their behavior, in addition to poor organization of the family meals. Conclusions. The structural differences between the two groups of families seem to be important for the  occurrence and maintenance of EDs, although they may not be the only cause. The results suggest strategies for clinical intervention in EDs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vegas Miguel, María I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sebastián Vega, Carlota</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alonso, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Cid, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gándara Martín, Jesús J de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateos-Agut, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Martinez, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El estilo de vida moderno que se caracteriza por el culto al individualismo, el descrédito de la autoridad y la existencia de múltiples realidades, ha modificado la estructura de las familias. Esta estructura social impregna a las familias y la forma de enfermar de sus miembros, de forma que los TCA se convierten en una forma de enfermar típicamente posmoderna. Metodología. El objetivo es conocer la estructura sistémica y la vulnerabilidad de las familias, comparando 108 familias con TCA, con 108 sin patología. Se utilizó un cuestionarioadministrado mediante entrevista por personal entrenado. Resultados. Las familias TCA tienen una estructura distinta de las del grupo de control. Tienen más antecedentes psiquiátricos y escasas habilidades de afrontamiento. Sus jerarquías están poco definidas y el liderazgo es difuso, con normas imprevisibles y rígidas, existiendo más coaliciones intergeneracionales y menos alianzas. La relación entre los padres es distante o de enfrentamiento, y hacia sus hijos tienen actitudes complacientes y egoístas, con vínculos ambivalentes y poco afectuosos, que en el caso de las madres se manifiesta con ansiedad de separación y dependencia diádica. Las expectativas que tienen para su prole son o bien exigentes y poco realistas o bien despreocupadas, y menor control de su conducta, además de una peor organización de las comidas familiares. Conclusiones. Las diferencias estructurales que aparecen entre los dos grupos de familias parecen tener importancia en la aparición y mantenimiento de los TCAs, aunque posiblemente no sean su única causa. Los resultados indican estrategias para la intervención clínica en TCAs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;42(6): 267-280, nov.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130025</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La estructura familiar y los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51232^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
