<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91991</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The severe cases seen as a pathogenetic unity. The sexual trauma in the borderline states and in the neurosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article, the authors try to present the bordeline case, following the Freud-Abraham model, as a pathogenetic unity, basic on a pathology the Freud - Abraham model, as a pathogenetic unity, based on a pathology that takes place in the narcissistic stage; its etiology would be the sexual trauma that occurs in the pre-edipic phase of evolution. As an illustration, the authors present two cases with comparative aims: one with probable prephalic traumatization and another with trauma during the oedipal period</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espiro, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se intenta presentar a los pacientes límites, según el modelo Freud-Abraham, como unidad patogénica basada en una patología de la etapa narcisista, cuya etiología sería el trauma de la sexualidad en una etapa preedípica de su desarrollo. Como ilustración se presentan dos casos, con fines comparativos: uno de probable traumatización prefálica y otro de trauma durante la etapa edípica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(58): 131-151, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91991</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los cuadros clínicos límite como unidad patogenética. El trauma sexual en los estado límite y en la neurosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
