<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153473</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional disorders in children victims of natural disasters</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The effects of disasters on physical health tend to be well-known, with short, medium and long term sequelae. On the other hand, not always is have recognized in the same way the effects on mental health, despite having shown that, in situations of disaster or catastrophe there is a psychological signs of suffering increase and increases to a certain extent the psychiatric morbidity and other problem social. It is estimated that between a third and half of the exposed population, it suffers from some psychological manifestation. It has been erroneously thought that children and adolescents, not suffering with the same intensity of especially traumatic situations. In fact it was presumed, given their reactions so different from that of adults, had some protection. Currently, this has denied and minors are considered to be a group of high risk in cases of disasters and emergencies. Investigations carried out, demonstrate that in children and adolescents, the psychological sequels tend to be frequent and affect directly to the physical, mental and social development. Natural disasters are unexpected situations that will produce a serie of emotional reactions of diverse severity in their survivors, especially children, one of the most vulnerable groups due to a less understanding of what happened and difficulty expressing what they feel, having a personality still developing, and so directly affecting their physical, mental and social development. Therefore suffering the emotional scars, they will take longer to resolve and have a lifetime to live with them. These consequences should be treated by a corresponding community nurse and sometimes, depending on the severity and persistence (more than 3 months), a referral will be made to a qualified mental health professional, taking into account a number of recommendation and assesment canons. Parents or tutors with health professionals have an important role in the recovery of their children and their reactions will be very influenced by these firts. In recent years the interest has increased by the impact of the disaster on the mental health of affected populations and currently has become evident the need for a comprehensive approach that transcends disease care and repair of material damage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castaño García, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Díaz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cernuda Martínez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los efectos de los desastres sobre la salud física suelen ser bastante conocidos, con secuelas a corto, medio y largo plazo. En cambio, no siempre se han reconocido de igual manera los efectos sobre la salud mental, a pesar de haberse demostrado que, en situaciones de desastre o catástrofe se produce un incremento de los signos de sufrimiento psicológico y aumenta en cierta medida la morbilidad psiquiátrica y otros problemas sociales. Se estima que entre una tercera parte y la mitad de la población expuesta sufre alguna manifestación psicológica. Se ha pensado erróneamente que los niños y los adolescentes no sufren con la misma intensidad las consecuencias de situaciones especialmente traumáticas. De hecho, se presumía que, dadas sus reacciones tan diferentes a las de los adultos, tenían una cierta protección. En la actualidad esto se ha desmentido y los menores se consideran un grupo de alto riesgo en casos de desastres y emergencias. Algunas investigaciones realizadas demuestran que, en niños y adolescentes, las secuelas psicológicas suelen ser frecuentes y afectar de manera directa al desarrollo físico, mental y social. La enfermera de Atención Primaria correspondiente deberá tratar estas secuelas y, en ocasiones, dependiendo de su gravedad y persistencia (mayor de 3 meses), se realizará una derivación a un profesional de la salud mental, teniendo en cuenta una serie de recomendaciones y criterios de valoración. Los padres o tutores, junto con los profesionales sanitarios, desempeñan un papel muy importante en la recuperación de sus hijos, ya que las reacciones de los niños van a estar muy influenciadas por las de estos. En los últimos años, ha aumentado el interés por el impacto de los desastres en la salud mental de las poblaciones afectadas y actualmente se ha hecho evidente la necesidad de un abordaje integral, que trascienda la atención a la enfermedad y la reparación de los daños materiales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;39(6): 410-421, jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153473</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones emocionales en niños víctimas de desastres naturales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9515^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9515^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2700^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
