<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101875</identifier>
<setSpec>0558-6291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fragile X Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fragile X syndrome (FXS) is considered the most common known cause of inherited mental retardation, with a frequency of approximately 1:4.000 males and 1:8.000 females in the general population. It is an X-linked dominant disorder. Characteristic clinical features included mental retardation, distinctive phenotype with long face and large prominent ears, joint laxity and macroorchidism after puberty. Affected females usually show a less severe phenotype. In the vast majority of the cases, FXS is caused by an abnormal expansion (&gt;200) of a CGG trinucleotide repeat in the 5´- untranslated region of the FMR1 gene, which is methylated, leading to the absence of the FMRP protein (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Karam, Juan Carlos de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Fuentes, Feliciano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puisac Uriol, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribate Molina, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pié Juste, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnedo Muñoz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Legarreta Maciel, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Rodríguez, María Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome X Frágil (SXF) es la principal causa de retraso mental hereditario, con una incidencia aproximada de ¼.000 varones y 1/8.000 mujeres en la población general. Se hereda de forma dominante ligada al sexo. Clínicamente se caracteriza por retrasomental, fenotipo peculiar con cara alargada y pabellones auriculares grandes y despegados, hiperlaxitud articular y macroorquidismo tras la pubertad. En las mujeres afectadas las manifestaciones clínicas suelen ser menos evidentes. El mecanismo etiológico es una expansión excesiva (&gt;200) del trinucleótido CGG en el extremo 5´ del gen FMR1, que además está metilado, dando lugar a la ausencia de la proteína FMRP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. Fac. Med. Zaragoza;48(2): 38-42, nov. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome X Frágil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5735^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7761^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
