<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148100</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Four surgical tips in the treatment of epicondylitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Lateral epicondylitis is a common injury in the population. Most patients improve with conservative treatment, but in a small percentage surgery is necessary. The aim of this study is to analyse the clinical results obtained by a «4 surgical tips» technique. Materials and method. This is a retrospective study of 35 operated elbows, with a mean follow-up of 5.3 years. In all cases epicondylar denervation, removal of the angiofibroblastic degeneration core, epicondylectomy, and release of posterior interosseous nerve, was performed. Each patient was evaluated using the Broberg and Morrey Rating System (BMRS), Mayo Elbow Performance Score (MEPS), Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), DASH questionnaire, and a survey of subjective assessment. Results. BMRS mean score was 97.2 points, with 95.71 points with the MEPS. The mean decrease in VAS was 8.12 points, and the mean score on the DASH was 1.68 points. The results were rated as excellent or very good by 94.3% of patients. There was one recurrence, which resolved with further surgery. Two neuropraxia of the posterior interosseous nerve occurred, which completely recovered in 10 weeks. Conclusions. Using the «4 surgical tips» technique, clinical resolution of symptoms in 97.1% was achieved at the first operation. Therefore, it appears to be an effective, reproducible technique with few complications, in the surgical treatment of lateral epicondylitis resistant to conservative treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marcos-García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muratore-Moreno, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo. La epicondilitis es una lesión muy frecuente en la población. La mayoría de los pacientes mejoran con el tratamiento conservador, pero en un pequeño porcentaje será necesaria la cirugía. Nuestro objetivo es analizar los resultados clínicos obtenidos mediante una intervención consistente en «4 gestos quirúrgicos». Material y método. Estudio retrospectivo de 35 codos intervenidos con un seguimiento medio de 5,3 años. En todos los casos se realizó denervación epicondílea, extirpación del núcleo de degeneración angiofibroblástica, epicondilectomía y liberación del nervio interóseo posterior. Se recogieron los resultados mediante Broberg and Morrey Rating System (BMRS), Mayo Elbow Performance Score (MEPS), Escala Visual Analógica (EVA), cuestionario DASH y una encuesta de valoración subjetiva por parte del paciente. Resultados. La puntuación media del BMRS fue de 97,2 puntos, MEPS de 95,71 puntos. La reducción media en la EVA fue de 8,12 puntos y la puntuación media en el DASH fue de 1,68 puntos. El 94,3% de los pacientes valoraron el resultado como excelente o muy bueno. Se produjo una recidiva que se solventó con una nueva cirugía y una neuroapraxia del nervio interóseo posterior en 2 casos, recuperados íntegramente en 10 semanas. Conclusiones. Con esta intervención basada en 4 gestos, se ha conseguido la resolución clínica en el 97,1% de los casos en la primera cirugía, por ello, consideramos esta técnica efectiva, reproducible y con una aceptable tasa de complicaciones en el tratamiento quirúrgico de la epicondilitis resistente a tratamiento conservador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);60(1): 38-43, ene.-feb. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148100</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuatro gestos quirúrgicos en el tratamiento de la epicondilitis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14094^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
