<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75805</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coping strategies and psychological well-being in adolescent competition tennis player</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study aimed to examine the types of coping strategies preferred by adolescent competition tennisplayers and specific attention was paid to understanding these strategies&#146; perceived effectiveness and the coping strategy&#146;ssubsequent effects on well-being. The sample for the study was made up of 27 adolescent tennis players with a mean ageof 15 years who participate at a high competitive level. The Approach to Coping in Sport Questionnaire (ACSQ-1) was used tomeasure the coping strategy used by the players and their psychological well-being was assessed by the Psychological Well-Being Scale. The results indicated that the emotional calming strategy was the tennis players&#146; preferred coping strategy in general. At the same time, emotional calming and active planning were the strategies the players&#146; considered to be the mosteffective in terms of improving performance. An additional finding was that players with lower levels of self-acceptancerelied more heavily on the emotional calming strategy and those with higher levels of self-acceptance used mentaldistancing more frequently. Players who perceived greater environmental control relied more heavily upon mentaldistancing as their preferred coping strategy. These findings indicate that individual differences were present in terms ofpreferred coping strategies and that the strategies produced differentiated effects on well-being for young competitiontennis players (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brustad, Robert J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Letelier López, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapata Campbel, Rolando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Mas, Alexandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Carrasco, Alicia Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Quiroz, Rolando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de nuestra investigación fue examinar los tipos de estrategias preferidas por tenistasadolescentes con atención a la efectividad percibida de las estrategias y las consecuencias en el estado de bienestar de losjugadores. Los participantes en la investigación fueron 26 adolescentes tenistas de una edad media de 15 años participandoa un nivel muy alto en Chile. El cuestionario de Aproximación al Afrontamiento en el Deporte (ACSQ-1) fue utilizado paramedir la manera de aproximación al afrontamiento y la evaluación del bienestar psicológico se realizó a través la Escala deBienestar Psicológico. Los resultados indicaron que la estrategia calma emocional fue la estrategia favorecida por lostenistas por lo general. Al mismo tiempo, la calma emocional y la planificación activa fueron las estrategias evaluadas másaltamente en beneficiar el rendimiento de ellos. Otro resultado importante fue que los tenistas que menos se autoaceptaronutilizaron más la estrategia de calma emocional y que aquellos con más autoaceptación utilizaron en mayor frecuencia laestrategia de retraimiento mental. Otro hallazgo fue que los jóvenes que declaran mayor dominio del entorno utilizanmayoritariamente el retraimiento mental como estrategia de afrontamiento. Los resultados indicaron que diferenciasindividuales existen en la preferencia para estrategias de afrontamiento en jóvenes tenistas y que las estrategias tienenefectos diferenciados en el bienestar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;19(1): 117-133, ene.-jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias de afrontamiento y bienestar psicológico en jóvenes tenistas de competición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27850^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24846^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27850^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27850^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24846^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
