<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055963</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleep disorders in Parkinson&#146;s disease and other movement disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurodegenerative processes with movement    disorders is predominant features show a high    incidence of sleep alterations at some point in their    evolution. The degeneration of structures responsible    for maintaining the sleep-wakefulness cycles and the    architecture of sleep could be at their root. Other    factors like the drugs employed in the treatment of    motor problems, the limitations to movement, etc.,    aggravate the problem. Although, at present, there is    no medical therapy able to restore the defects    derived from the degeneration of the key structures of    sleep, an individual analysis of the coadyuvant factors    in each patient could help to improve these problems.    In this article we describe the main sleep disorders in    Parkinson&#146;s disease and other degenerative diseases    such as multi-system atrophies or progressive    supranuclear paralysis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Oroz, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clavero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La práctica totalidad de los procesos neurodegenerativos    cuyos principales síntomas son motores y    que se incluyen bajo el epígrafe de trastornos del movimiento,    presentan una alta incidencia de alteraciones    del sueño en algún momento de su evolución. La degeneración    de estructuras responsables del mantenimiento    de los ciclos sueño-vigilia y de la arquitectura    del sueño puede ser la base de los mismos. Otros factores    como los fármacos empleados en el tratamiento    de los problemas motores, las limitaciones del movimiento    etc., agravan el problema. Aunque en el    momento actual no disponemos de fármacos que puedan    reponer los defectos derivados de la degeneración    de las estructuras claves del sueño, el análisis individual    de los factores que concurren en cada paciente    puede ayudar a mejorar estos problemas. En este capítulo    se describen los principales trastornos del sueño    en la enfermedad de Parkinson y otras enfermedades    degenerativas como las atrofias multisistema o la parálisis    supranuclear progresiva</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;30(supl.1): 143-153, 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055963</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos del sueño en la enfermedad de Parkinson y otros trastornos del movimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34367^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
