<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74320</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: In patients with advanced age conventional treatmentis frequently not feasible depending of age, concomitantdisease or social or family problems. The objective of presentstudy is to analyse the results of weekly hypofractionatedtreatment in these patients.Patients and methods: Patients older than 70 years withassociated diseases or low performance status were included.From 1992 to 2005 an amount of 262 patients were treated,with a mean age of 82.5 ± 7.2 years. The 66.4% of patientsunderwent conservative surgery, 25.2% a mastectomy wasperformed and the remaining 8.4% only a diagnostic biopsywas undertaken. The mean dose was 37.5 Gy with a weekly6.25 Gy fractionation. So, patients received only 6 sessionsoverall, clearly lower than standard treatments.Results: After a follow up period of 42 months the overallsurvival by Kaplan-Meier method was 90.4 ± 5.2% in patientswith conservative surgery, 85 ± 10.6% in mastectomized patients,and 60.8 ± 23.4% in not operated patients. Specificsurvival for the same groups is 97± 3%, 91.4 ± 8.5% and81.8 ± 18% respectively, according to the fact that patientsdie of another disease but not by their tumour. In 66.4% ofpatients a mild dermitis degree I or II was present and only in19% of cases a chronic fibrosis occurred.Conclusions: Treatment of advanced age breast cancer patientswith weekly hypofractionated irradiation is a valid andcomfortable option with similar results in terms of survival, localcontrol and toxicity. Acute and chronic secondary effectsare acceptable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Foro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reig, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Membrive, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algara, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En pacientes de edad avanzada no es factibleplantear un tratamiento convencional en ocasiones por razónde la edad, patología concomitante o problemas socio-familiares.El objetivo del presente estudio es analizar los resultadosdel tratamiento hipofraccionado semanal en estas pacientes.Material y métodos: Se incluyeron pacientes mayores de 70años, con patología asociada o bajo grado funcional. De 1992hasta 2005 tratamos 262 pacientes con una edad media de82,5 ± 7,2 años. El 66,4% de las pacientes fueron sometidas acirugía conservadora, 25,2% a mastectomía y 8,4% se practicósólo biopsia. La dosis media fue de 37,5 Gy a un fraccionamientode 6,25 Gy /día, 1 vez por semana, de forma que laspacientes recibieron en total 6 sesiones, un número inferior alos tratamientos estándar.Resultados: Tras un seguimiento medio de 42 meses la supervivenciaglobal según el método de Kaplan-Meier fue de90,4 ± 5,2% para las pacientes con tratamiento conservador,85 ± 10,6% para las mastectomizadas y 60,8 ± 23,4% paralas pacientes no intervenidas. La supervivencia específica paralos mismos grupos es de 97 ± 3%, 91,4 ± 8,5% y 81,8 ±18% respectivamente, lo que se explica por el hecho de quelas pacientes mueren por causa diferente a su neoplasia. Un66,4% de las pacientes presentaron dermitis grado I-II y sóloun 19% fibrosis crónica.Conclusiones: El tratamiento en el cáncer de mama en pacientesde edad avanzada con esquemas de radioterapia hipofraccionada,resulta una opción válida y cómoda con resultadossimilares en supervivencia, control local y toxicidad. Losefectos secundarios agudos y tardíos son aceptables(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);21(4): 145-150, 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74320</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radioterapia hipofraccionada semanal en pacientes de edad avanzada con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1944^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
