<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84395</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laboratory test markers of graft vascular disease in heart transplant patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Graft vascular disease (GVD) affects over 40% of all heart transplant patients after 5 years of follow-up, and is the first cause of death after the first post-transplantation year. A study is made of the relationship between the concentrations of adiponectin and other cytokines and the development of GVD and its different degrees of severity. Material and methods: The study included 21 patients subjected to coronariography-intravascular ultrasound (IVUS) for the diagnosis of GVD, with the determination of adiponectin levels. GVD was identified by coronariography in 10 patients and by IVUS in 14 patients. Results: There were no statistically significant differences in adiponectin levels according to the existence of GVD diagnosed by coronariography, or according to the severity of GVD as determined by IVUS. Statistically significant correlations were recorded between the presence of GVD diagnosed by IVUS and the concentrations of IL-6 (p=0.025), with higher IL-6 levels in those without GVD or with only mild GVD; and between the presence of GVD determined by coronariography and the levels of BNP (p=0.014) &#150; higher levels of this protein being found in the patients with GVD. A relationship was observed between patient gender and adiponectin levels (p=0.025), with higher concentrations in women. A statistically significant relationship was seen between the appearance of major adverse cardiac events (MACEs) and the existence of GVD as diagnosed by coronariography (p=0.012) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caro Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lage Gallé, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Moreno, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Díaz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad vascular del injerto (EVI) afecta a más del 40% de los pacientes trasplantados cardiacos a los 5 años de seguimiento y es la primera causa de muerte después del primer año postraplante cardiaco. El objetivo es demostrar la relación entre las concentraciones de adiponectina y otras citocinas con el desarrollo de EVI y sus distintos grados de severidad. Material y metodología: incluimos 21 pacientes a los que se realiza coronariografía-IVUS (ecografía intracoronaria) para el diagnóstico de EVI y determinamos las cifras de adiponectina. Tenían EVI por coronariografía 10 pacientes y por IVUS 14 pacientes. Resultados: No se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en los niveles de adiponectina en función de la existencia de EVI diagnosticada por coronariografía ni en función del grado de severidad de la EVI por IVUS. Se encontraron asociaciones estadísticamente significativas entre la existencia de EVI diagnosticada por IVUS y las concentraciones de IL-6 (p=0,025) con mayores concentraciones de IL6 en los que no tenían EVI o era de grado leve y entre la existencia de EVI por coronariografía y los niveles de BNP (p=0,014) con niveles más elevados de BNP en los que tenían EVI. Se encontró una relación entre el sexo y los niveles de adiponectina (p=0,025) con niveles superiores en las mujeres. Había una relación estadísticamente significativa entre la aparición de eventos cardiacos mayores (MACE) y la existencia de EVI diagnosticada por coronariografía (p=0,012) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);19(3): 160-164, jul.-sept. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84395</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Marcadores analíticos de enfermedad vascular del injerto en el trasplante cardiaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50570^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30178^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50570^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
