<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052833</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Questionnaire to assess advertising campaigns impact about HIV/AIDS prevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Present work is concerned with a questionnaire aimed to the impact evaluation of a selection of Spanish advertising campaigns about HIV/AIDS prevention. The work objective is to determine reliability and factorial structure of the instrument. It is described the designed questionnaire and its three scales (affective impact scale, cognitive impact scale and behavioural intention impact scale). The sample was composed by 405 high school teenagers to who were projected the advertising campaigns. So, teenagers filled the designed questionnaire. From a theoretical and psychometric point of view, data show the instrument is appropriate about internal consistency and factorial structure. The final goal of the questionnaire is to become useful tool to assess the persuasive effectiveness of the advertising campaigns within the HIV/AIDS network, as an intervention of primary prevention to reduce the expansion of epidemic</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Buela-Casal, Gualberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bretón-López, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el cuestionario para la evaluación del impacto de una selección de campañas publicitarias españolas sobre prevención del VIH/SIDA con el objetivo de determinar su fiabilidad y estructura factorial. Se describe el instrumento elaborado y las tres escalas que lo componen (escala de impacto afectivo, impacto cognitivo e impacto sobre la intención de conducta). Se empleó una muestra de 405 adolescentes de Enseñanza Secundaria Obligatoria a los que se les proyectaron las campañas publicitarias y se les solicitó que rellenaran el cuestionario. Los resultados, desde un punto de vista teórico y estadístico, reflejan una adecuada consistencia interna y estructura factorial del cuestionario, cuyo objeto es convertirse en una prueba de utilidad para evaluar la eficacia persuasiva que está logrando la publicidad en el marco de la infección por VIH/SIDA, como medida de prevención primaria para disminuir la extensión de la epidemia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(3): 557-564, ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuestionario para la evaluación del impacto de campañas publicitarias sobre prevención del VIH/SIDa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d332^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
