<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-36343</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sydenham's chorea. A clinical analysis of 55 patients with a prolonged follow-up</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Sydenham&#146;s chorea is permanently on the rise in developing countries and may suddenly reappear in developed nations. Patients and methods. We studied a prospective series of 55 cases, involving a total of 89 outbreaks with long-term follow-ups. All the cases were considered to be rheumatic from the outset, whether they were pure choreas or accompanied by the other signs from the Jones criterion, 38 and 17 respectively, in the first outbreak. Ages ranged between 7 and 22 years, with a mean of 15, at the time of the first outbreak; there was a predominance of females (87%). Results. Hemichorea accounted for 54% of cases. Presentation under treatment was mild (60%), moderate (27%) and severe (13%). Duration ranged from 30 to 365 days. Most of the patients presented just one outbreak and only 18% had multiple outbreaks, between 2 and 10 in number. Ballism was observed in five patients, a state of chorea in two of them, another two had chorea mollis and corea gravidarum was found in five of the patients. Chorea was associated to hypotonia, incoordination, fatigue, postural disorders, motor impersistence, dysarthria and altered gait. Psychiatric disorders were frequent and varied, the most predominant being anguish, irritability, psychomotor restlessness, obsessive-compulsive traits and insomnia. The only important sequela involved the heart, with 10 cases, two of which required surgery. Conclusions. Crystalline penicillin was used to eradicate streptococcus, neuroleptic agents were employed to reduce involuntary movements and psychiatric symptoms, and benzathine was utilised as a prophylaxis for relapses and sequelae (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El corea de Sydenham aumenta persistentemente en los países en desarrollo y puede reaparecer bruscamente en los desarrollados. Pacientes y métodos. Se presenta una serie prospectiva de 55 casos, que cursaron un total de 89 brotes, con largo seguimiento. A todos los casos se les consideró reumáticos desde el inicio, ya fueran coreas puros o acompañados de los otros signos del criterio de Jones, 38 y 17, respectivamente, en el primer brote. La edad osciló entre los 7 y los 22 años, con una mediana de 15, en el momento del primer brote, con predominio del sexo femenino (87 por ciento). Resultados. En el 54 por ciento se presentó como hemicorea. La presentación bajo tratamiento fue leve en el 60 por ciento, moderada en el 27 por ciento y grave 13 por ciento. La duración osciló entre 30 y 365 días. La mayoría presentó un brote único, y sólo el 18 por ciento tuvo brotes múltiples, de 2 a 10. Se observó balismo en cinco pacientes, estado coreico en dos, corea mollis en otros dos y corea gravidarum en cinco. El corea se asoció a hipotonía, incoordinación, fatiga, alteraciones posturales, impersistencia motora, disartria y alteración de la marcha. Las alteraciones psiquiátricas fueron frecuentes y variadas. Predominaron la angustia, la irritabilidad, la inquietud psicomotora, los rasgos obsesivocompulsivos y el insomnio. La única secuela importante fue cardíaca, en diez casos, de los cuales dos requirieron cirugía. Conclusión. Se usó penicilina cristalina para erradicar el estreptococo, neurolépticos para disminuir los movimientos involuntarios y los síntomas psiquiátricos, y benzatina para la profilaxis de las recaídas y las secuelas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(9): 810-815, nov. 2004. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Corea de Sydenham. Análisis clínico de 55 pacientes con seguimiento prolongado</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Lay Son, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Guerrero, E del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Grez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-36343</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2869</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
