<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63737</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteoporosis (OP) is a very prevalent disease whose final consequence, fractures, supposes a significant deterioration in the quality of life of those suffering it. We know well that it mostly affects women, although we should not forget that osteoporosis also affects men. The appearance of hip fractures in the male occurs about 10 years later than in the woman, but its mortality is greater. At 60 years, 25% of men will have an osteoporotic fracture and at 90 years, 16.6% will suffer a hip fracture. Most of the cases of OP diagnosed in the male have a secondary cause (40%-60%). The most frequent ones are due to hypogonadism and excess chronic alcohol intake, but also due to glucocorticoids, low calcium intake and limited physical activity. In this article, we summarize the most frequent causes of OP in the male, the way of evaluating these patients, the diagnostic tests needed for their study and the different treatments we can use, all of this being done from the approach of Primary Health Care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Felipe Medina, R. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caba Cuevas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfonso Camús, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La osteoporosis (OP) es una enfermedad muy prevalente, cuya consecuencia final, las fracturas, supone un importante deterioro en la calidad de vida de las personas que las sufren. Conocemos ampliamente que afecta mayoritariamente a la mujer, aunque no por eso debemos olvidar que la osteoporosis también afecta a los hombres. En el varón se retrasa la aparición de fractura de cadera unos 10 años con respecto a la mujer, pero su mortalidad es mayor. A los 60 años el 25% de los hombres sufrirá una fractura osteoporótica y a los 90 el 16,6% sufrirá una fractura de cadera. La mayoría de los casos de OP diagnosticados en el varón son de causa secundaria (40-60%), los más frecuentes son debidos a hipogonadismo y a excesiva ingesta de alcohol de forma crónica, pero también a la ingesta de glucocorticoides, la baja ingesta de calcio o la escasa actividad física. En este artículo resumimos las causas más frecuentes de OP en el varón, la forma de evaluar a estos pacientes, las pruebas diagnósticas necesarias para su estudio y los diferentes tratamientos que podemos utilizar realizando para todo ello un enfoque desde Atención Primaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(5): 269-272, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63737</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13507^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
