<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153753</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Simultaneous diagnosis of pseudomeningocele, tethered cord syndrome and cerebrospinal fluid fistula: Report of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The clinical case is presented on a patient with an extensive sacral dysraphism, a history of myelomeningocele surgical repair in her childhood, as well as tethered cord syndrome. The patient was also diagnosed with pseudomeningocele and a cerebrospinal fluid cutaneous fístula. A surgical approach was used, with encouraging results being obtained in the clinical outcome of the patient. A review of the literature was performed to support the surgical decision in this case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quillo-Olvera, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Partida, Carlos F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velázquez-Santana, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcántara-Gómez, Leopoldo A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zambrano-Velarde, Luis E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velázquez-García, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El caso clínico alude a una paciente con disrafismo sacro extenso, antecedentes de reparación de mielomeningocele en su infancia y signos y síntomas de síndrome de médula anclada. Se diagnosticó además pseudomeningocele y fístula de líquido cefalorraquídeo cutánea. El abordaje quirúrgico fue realizado con resultados alentadores en la evolución de la paciente. Se realizó además una revisión de la literatura, para fundamentar el tratamiento quirúrgico utilizado en este caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);27(4): 194-198, jul.-ago. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153753</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico simultáneo de pseudomeningocele, síndrome de médula anclada y fístula de líquido cefalorraquídeo: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8758^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10481^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55576^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33567^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29127^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9629^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
