<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038872</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional outcome after one year follow-up in cryptogenetic brain infarction and patent foramen ovale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: The presence of patent foramen ovale (PFO) and atrioseptalaneurysm (ASA) has been described as a risk factor in cryptogenetic stroke. Patients with unknown origin stroke and PFO have less severe symptoms compared to the rest of cryptogenetic stroke patients. We evaluated the clinical situation in stroke patients with PFO and describe the factors predictive of a better outcome after a year. PATIENTS AND METHOD: 1118 patients between 18 and 70 years old were evaluated, and 223were classified as having cryptogenetic stroke. Our protocol Included transcraneal Doppler, a transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) and a cranial RM. We used the NIH Stroke Scale (NIHSS) to evaluate the clinical situation, and the modified Ranking Scale for the functional outcome. RESULTS: A total of 117 patients had all inclusion criteria. 66 (56.4%) showed a PFO. We observed a younger age, a higher percentage of females (48.4% in PFO vs. 25.5% in no-PFO) and less risk factors in PFO patients, except for migraine (24.6% in PFO vs. 5.9% in no-PFO; p = 0.01). PFO patients had less severe strokes (NIHSS: 3 -median - in PFO vs. 5 in no-PFO; p = 0.010) and a lower grade of sequelae (p 0.024). Worse outcome was related to male, initial neurological evaluation (NIHSS) and presence of ASA. After a logistic regression, only the initial clinical situation (NIHSS) and the presence of ASA were associated with sequelae. CONCLUSIONS: PFO patients showed a less severe stroke and better functional outcome. The initial neurological involvement and the presence of ASA are predictive of the clinical situation aftera year</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rovira, Álex</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Sabín, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubiera, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Carlos A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Alujas, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamarina, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Evangelista, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO Y OBJETIVO: La presencia de foramen oval permeable (FOP) y aneurisma del septoauricular (ASA) se ha descrito como factor de riesgo en ictus criptogénicos. Los pacientes conictus de origen desconocido y FOP tienen una menor gravedad comparado con el resto de ictuscriptogénicos. El objetivo fue valorar la situación clínica de los ictus con FOP al cabo de 1 año,y qué factores predicen mejor pronóstico.PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: De 1.118 ictus isquémicos de pacientes entre 18 y 70 años, 223 fueronclasificados como criptogénicos. El protocolo incluía Doppler transcraneal, ecocardiogramatransesofágico (ETE) y resonancia magnética (RM) craneal. La situación clínica en fase agudase valoró mediante la escala de ictus de la NIH (National Institute of Health) y la funcional alaño mediante la escala de Rankin modificada.RESULTADOS: Cumplían todos los criterios de inclusión 117 pacientes; 66 (56,4%) tenían FOP y51 (43,2%) no. Se observó en los FOP una menor edad, un mayor porcentaje de sexo femenino(el 48,4% en los FOP frente al 25,5% en los no FOP) y menos factores de riesgo, excepto lamigraña (el 24,6% en FOP frente al 5,9% en los no FOP; p = 0,01). Los FOP presentaban menorgravedad inicial (mediana NIHSS de 3 en los FOP frente a 5 en los no FOP; p = 0,010) yun menor porcentaje de secuelas al cabo del año (p = 0,024). La peor situación funcional serelacionó con el sexo masculino, la valoración neurológica inicial (NIHSS) y la presencia deASA. Con la regresión logística sólo la gravedad neurológica inicial y la presencia de ASA seasociaban con las secuelas.CONCLUSIONES: Los pacientes con FOP presentan una menor gravedad clínica y mejor situaciónfuncional en el seguimiento. El déficit neurológico inicial y la presencia de ASA predicen la situaciónclínica al año</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(15): 561-565, abr. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pronóstico funcional tras un año de seguimiento en pacientes con infarto cerebral de causa desconocida y foramen oval permeable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d794^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d794^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6496^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6496^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2583^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
