<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164072</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vesicovaginal fístula laparoscopic treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vesicovaginal fístula is among the most distressing complications of gynaecological and obstetrical procedures. Management of these fístulas has been better defined and standardised over the last decade. Vesicovaginal fístula repair is most commonly repaired with transvaginal approach in cases of supratrigonal fístula and with abdominal approach in cases of supratrigonal fístula. We report a case of a vesicovaginal fístula after abdominal hysterectomy, which was repaired using a laparoscopic approach. The fístula followed a hysterectomy. We will describe a novel technique for the treatment of vesicovaginal fístula of supratrigonal location by intraperitoneal laparoscopic approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jativa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalá, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escrig, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calpe, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrandis, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montañes, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llueca, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herráiz, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fístulas vesicovaginales están entre las complicaciones más angustiantes de los procedimientos ginecológicos y obstétricos. El manejo de estas fístulas se ha definido mejor y estandarizado en la última década. La reparación de la fístula vesico-vaginal frecuentemente se lleva a cabo a través de un abordaje transvaginal en el caso de las fístulas infratrigonales y mediante un abordaje abdominal transvesical para las fístulas supratrigonales. Presentamos un caso de fístula vesico-vaginal tras histerectomía que fue reparada mediante una abordaje laparoscópico. Vamos a describir una técnica novedosa para el tratamiento de fístula vesico-vaginal de ubicación supratrigonal por vía laparoscópica intraperitoneal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);60(3): 252-255, mayo-jun. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento laparoscópico de fístula vesicovaginal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3576^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29578^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29578^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13890^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15023^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29578^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
