<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78070</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Abnormal dentition in an 8 years old female child</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patient with shortening distal phalanx 1st finger both hands, from the birth and familiar precedents of similar abnormality. At the age of 8 she presented dental alterations with hipertrofia gingival and dental incorporations, and backaches and pain in femoral region. Radiology: increase of bony widespread density, hypoplasia lower jaw and acrosteolisis distal phalanxes. The jaw biopsy (dental piece and alveolar surrounding bone): bony fragments are constituted for coarse and irregular trabeculas with importantly bony resorption and newly formed. Bone densitometry: T+5.2 in c. lumbar and neck femoral. Gamma scan bone: diffuse captation of the axial skeleton. Diagnosis: picnodisostosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bachiller Corral, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Piga, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burguet i Arfelis, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una paciente con acortamiento de la falange distal del primer dedo de ambas manos desde el nacimiento y con antecedentes familiares de similares anomalias. A los 8 años presentó alteraciones dentarias con hipertrofia gingival e inclusiones dentarias, y dolores lumbares y en la región femoral. Las pruebas radiológicas evidenciaron aumento de densidad ósea generalizada, hipoplasia maxilar inferior y acrosteólisis de las falanges distales. Biopsia mandibular (pieza dentaria y hueso alveolar circundante): los fragmentos óseos están constituidos por trabéculas toscas e irregulares con importante resorción y neoformación ósea. Densitometría ósea: T +5,2 en la columna lumbar y el cuello femoral. Gammagrafía ósea: captación difusa del esqueleto axial. Diagnóstico: picnodisostosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);4(5): 207-209, sept.-oct. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78070</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dentición anómala en niña de 8 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13434^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8514^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14461^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
