<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057083</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Post-myocardial infarction depression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Major depression is a common finding among patients recovering    from a myocardial infarction. Additionally, clinically significant depressive    symptoms are present in other patients whose symptom severity or    duration does not meet established criteria for a diagnosis of major    depression. Over the last decade, increasing evidence suggests that in    addition to its effect on patient´s quality of life, post-MI depression also    deserves attention because of a reported relation to increased morbidity    and mortality. This evidence report reviews the studies that have studied    depression or depressive symptoms in patients after an MI and focuses    on the prevalence, clinical significance, treatment, and methods of evaluating    this condition. A large number of studies have evaluated various    aspects of post-MI depression including prevalence, its association with    mortality, and major adverse events, and treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Vicente, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García y García, E. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar Sordo, V. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La depresión mayor es un cuadro común entre pacientes convalecientes    de un infarto agudo de miocardio (IAM). Además, síntomas    depresivos clínicamente significativos se hallan presentes en otros    pacientes cuya severidad sintomática o duración no reúne suficientes criterios    establecidos para configurar el diagnóstico de depresión mayor.    Durante la pasada década, la evidencia creciente sugiere que junto a su    efecto sobre la calidad de vida del paciente, la depresión post-infarto    también merece una atención especial ya que se ha descrito un incremento    de morbilidad y mortalidad asociadas. Este artículo revisa los estudios    que han estudiado la depresión o los síntomas depresivos en pacientes    que han sufrido un infarto agudo de miocardio y se centra en la prevalencia,    significación clínica, tratamiento, y métodos de evaluación de este    cuadro. Un amplio número de estudios han evaluado varios aspectos de    la depresión post-infarto incluyendo la prevalencia, su asociación con    mortalidad, efectos adversos mayores y tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;24(7): 346-351, jul. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057083</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La depresión tras el infarto agudo de miocardio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
