<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055625</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sentinel lymph node dissection for localized prostate cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Proper assessment of lymph node status is of crucial importance in the management of newly diagnosed prostate cancer. Early stage metastatic disease takes the form of microscopic tumor-cell deposits rather than grossly enlarged nodes. So far there is no imaging technique, however, which allows detecting small metastases in the range of a few millimetres. Therefore pelvic lymph node dissection (PLND) is the only reliable method of staging for clinically localized prostate cancer. The cornerstone of radioguided prostate surgery is a radiopharmaceutical - a carrier molecule labeled by radionuclide. After injection to at the prostate, the radiopharmaceutical crosses the lymphatic pores and migrates into the lymph        vessels and from there to the first echelon of lymph nodes. We were the first to show that sentinel PLND can be performed by means of laparoscopy preceding laparoscopic radical prostatectomy. Our most recent publication presents data of 140 patients with clinically localized prostate cancer in which laparoscopic sentinel PLND was performed preceding        radical prostatectomy from November 2001 to January 200514. On the preoperative scintigraphy SLNs were detected bilaterally, unilaterally, not on the pelvic-walls in 113 (80.7%), 20 (14.2%) and 6 (4.2%) patients and intraoperatively in 96 (68.6%), 36 (25.7%), 8 (5.7%) patients respectively. In 99 out of 140 patients (70.7%) intraoperatively SLN was detected        in the same position as on preoperative scan. At least one SLN was detected in 133 patients (95.3%). Whenever PLND is indicated it should not be limited to lymph node sampling as provided by standard limited PLND but has to be performed in the template of extended PLND. There is only limited experience with sentinel PLND, but all the data collected so far indicate that this method has the potential to become an alternative to extended PLND since it        allows for reduction of the extent of PLND without compromising diagnostic accuracy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sega, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Janetschek, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prammer, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ziegerhofer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jeschke, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leeb, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La correcta valoración de la afectación ganglionar es de gran importancia en el manejo de los nuevos casos de cáncer de próstata. El estadio precoz de la enfermedad metastásica se manifiesta como pequeños focos microscópicos más que como ganglios linfáticos engrosados. Sin embargo, hasta ahora no hay ninguna técnica de imagen que permita detectar metástasis cuyo diámetro alcance unos pocos milímetros. Por tanto, la linfadenectomía pélvica (LNDP) es el único método fiable para el estadiaje del cáncer de próstata organoconfinado (CPO).        El pilar de la cirugía prostática radioguiada es el uso de un radiofármaco, una molécula transportadora marcada con radionúclido. Tras la inyección en la glándula prostática, el radiofármaco alcanza el territorio linfático y migra al primer escalón linfático, el ganglio centinela (GC). Fuimos los primeros en demostrar que la LDNP del GC se podía llevar a cabo        mediante abordaje laparoscópico previo a la prostatectomía radical (PTR) laparoscópica. En nuestra publicación más reciente se presentan los datos de 140 pacientes diagnosticados de CPO entre noviembre de 2001 a enero 2005 en los que se realizó LDNP laparoscópica del GC previa a la PTR, también laparoscópica14. En la gammagrafía preoperatoria, se        detectaron GC de forma bilateral en 113 pacientes (80,7%), de forma unilateral en 20 (14,2%) y no se detectaron en 6 (4,2%), mientras que en la realizada durante la cirugía se detectaron en 96 pacientes (68,6%), 36 (25,7%), 8 (5,7%) respectivamente. Los GC se hallaron en la misma localización con ambos procedimientos en 99 de 140 pacientes (70,7%).        Al menos se objetivó un GC en 133 pacientes (95,3%). Cuando la LDNP está indicada, ésta no debería restringirse a la exéresis de adenopatías, según la técnica de LDNP        limitada o estándar, sino que tiene que realizarse siguiendo el patrón de la LDNP extendida. Hay poca experiencia con la LDNP del GC, pero todos los datos publicados hasta ahora indican que este procedimiento puede ser una alternativa a la LDNP extendida, ya que permite reducir la extensión de la LDNP sin comprometer la exactitud diagnóstica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(6): 686-692, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055625</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de la biopsia dinámica del ganglio centinela en el cáncer de próstata organoconfinado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
