<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98357</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability and validity of a Spanish version of the Beck Depression Inventory-II in a sample of the general population of the Canary Islands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyzes the reliability and validity of Sanz, Navarro, &amp; Vázquez&#146;s Spanish version of the Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI-II) within a sample of 373 adults of which two thirds were women. Half of them were students and half workers. On the basis of the exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis and the Schmid-Leiman&#146;s transformation, we can affirm that the BDI-II measures a general dimension of depression composed by two highly related factors. Findings related to internal consistency were high: a= 0.90, 0.87, and 0.83 for the total scale and factors 1 and 2 respectively. Pearson&#146;s correlations with other self-report measures of depression were high; likewise, the correlations with self-report measures of anxiety and stress were high too. Therefore, the convergent and discriminant validity of the BDI-II is called into question. We conclude that the Spanish adaptation of the BDI-II can be recommended as a suitable screening instrument for depressive symptomatology. Nevertheless, it is clear that the BDI-II has discriminant validity problems, specially, with instruments that measure anxiety</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmedo, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaos, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>del Pino, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo analiza la fiabilidad y validez de la versión española de Sanz et al. del &#147;Inventario de depresión de Beck-II&#148; (BDI-II) en una muestra de 373 adultos de los que dos tercios eran mujeres. La mitad eran estudiantes y la otra mitad trabajadores. Los resultados de los  análisis factoriales exploratorios y confirmatorios y la transformación de Schmid-Leiman apoyaron que el BDI-II mide una dimensión general de depresión compuesta por dos factores altamente correlacionados. Los resultados referidos a la fiabilidad por consistencia interna fue alta: a= 0,90, 0,87 y 0,83 para la escala total y los factores 1 y 2 respectivamente. Las correlaciones de Pearson con otros autoinformes de depresión fueron altas, pero también fueron altas las correlaciones con autoinformes de ansiedad y estrés por lo que la validez convergente y discriminante del BDI-II es cuestionable. Concluimos que la adaptación española del BDI-II es recomendable como un instrumento de detección de síntomas depresivos, pero es claro que el BDI-II tiene problemas de validez discriminante, especialmente, con los instrumentos que miden ansiedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;18(1): 35-56, ene.-abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98357</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad y validez de una versión española del Inventario de depresión de Beck-II en una muestra de la población general canaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
