<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76406</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Games, sports and culture in childhood: the meaning of Palin to Mapuche children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyses the role of traditional games within Mapuche culture. Games are rule-based and theiracquisition has been the object of a number of different studies in developmental psychology. A game&#146;s rules and actionsare charged with a cultural meaning often taken for granted and a complexity often overlooked. This article analyses howchildren ages eight to fourteen evolve in their grasp of a game&#146;s meaning and its rules, using a group of children playingPalín, a Mapuche game, as its subject. The data comes from observations and interviews of Mapuche children and adults.Our main conclusion is that the game of Palín has a rich cultural and traditional meaning that is reflected in its rules andrituals. The children&#146;s understanding of this meaning is a complex process described in three broad stages (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Linaza, Josetxu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garoz, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo analiza el significado que un juego tradicional tiene para su cultura. Los juegos son regulados porun conjunto de normas cuya adquisición a lo largo de la infancia han sido objeto de estudio por parte de la psicología deldesarrollo. Pero también sus normas tienen un significado cultural que, con frecuencia, damos por supuesto sin sospecharsu complejidad. Se describe la evolución del conocimiento de los significados del juego y sus reglas en niños, de entre ochoy catorce años, que practican el juego del Palín Mapuche en Chile. Los datos proceden de observaciones y entrevistasrealizadas a niños y adultos mapuche. Se concluye que el juego del Palín tiene un gran significado cultural y tradicional,recogido en sus normas y su ritual, que los jugadores lo construyen a lo largo de un complejo y dilatado procesocaracterizado por tres niveles de conocimiento de su significado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;17(1): 103-121, ene.-jun. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Juego, deporte y cultura en la infancia: el significado del Palín para el niño Mapuche</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11416^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36432</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
