<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139765</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of sensory motor training of lower limb in sedentary elderly as part of functional autonomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Assess the effects of sensorimotor training on the functional autonomy levels of sedentary elderly people. Methods: The sample was composed of 30 women (sedentary, functionally independent, = 65.03 ± 4.93 year), divided randomly into two groups: control (CG, n = 15) and experimental (EG, n = 15). Tests developed by the Latin American Development for the Elderly Group (GDLAM) were used to evaluate autonomy. The EG was submitted to a sensorimotor program three times a week, involving 24 thirty minute sessions. Data were processed using the SPSS program, with a 5% significance level. Results: The EG showed a significant reduction in execution time in all the tasks, while the CG only obtained a significantly better score on the 10-M walk test. Although the EG improved in the GDLAM index (% = &amp;#8722;30, 3%, p = 0.0001), it remained at a &#147;weak&#148; level (GDLAM index &gt;27.42). Conclusion: The results demonstrate that sensorimotor training reduces the execution time of tasks, as well as improving functional performance in activities of daily living (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva Carlotto Herrera, SD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbosa Rezende, AA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rossone Reis, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandes de Miranda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borges Da Silva, JD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martin Dantas, EH</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza Ramalho, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los efectos del entrenamiento sensorio motriz en los niveles de autonomía funcional del anciano sedentario. Método: La muestra se compuso por 30 mujeres (sedentarias, independientes funcionalmente, 65,03 ± 4,93 años) divididas al azar en 2grupos: control (CG, n = 15) y experimental (EG, n = 15). Para la evaluación de la autonomía se utilizaron las pruebas del Grupo del Desarrollo Latinoamericano para la Madurez (GDLAM) antes y después de la intervención. El EG fue sometido a un programa de entrenamiento sensorio motriz, 3veces a la semana, la duración de cada sesión fue de 30 minutos y realizaron 24 sesiones. Los datos se procesaron con el programa SPSS, versión 19, adoptando nivel de significación de la p &lt; 0,05. Resultados: En el grupo experimental se constató una reducción significativa del tiempo de ejecución en todas las tareas, mientras el CG solo obtuvo resultado significativamente mejor en la prueba de caminata de 10 m. En el índice general de GDLAM, el grupo experimental presentó mejora (delta% = -30, 3%, p = 0,0001), pero se mantuvo en un nivel «débil» (Índice GDLAM &gt; 27,42). Conclusión: Los resultados muestran que la práctica del entrenamiento sensorio motriz influye de forma positiva en la reducción del tiempo de ejecución de las tareas, lo que se relaciona con el mejor rendimiento funcional de las actividades cotidianas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;8(2): 61-66, jun. 2015. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139765</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">/ Efectos del entrenamiento sensorio motriz del miembro inferior en ancianos sedentarios como parte de su autonomía funcional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
