<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84852</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: The evalutaion of the operations carried out using endoscopic techniques within the context of major gynaecological outpatient surgery. The definition of pre-operatory selection criteria. The creation of a catalogue of endoscopic instructions for gynaecological ambulatory surgery. DESIGN: A descriptive, retrospective study. FRAMEWORK: Operations carried out in the outpatient surgical unit. PATIENTS: There were 210 operations carried out using endoscopic techniques in the outpatient surgical unit in the year 2000. The type and number of operations, the relationship between the kind of surgery, the time spent under anesthesia and recovering after surgery and the percentage of hospital admissions have been studied. RESULTS: The operation that lasted the shortest time (46 minutes), was a diagnostic hysteroscopy and the longest (79 minutes), a surgical laparoscopy. The quickest recovery time(128 minutes) was after a diagnostic hysteroscopy and the slowest (277 minutes) after a diagnostic laparoscopy. There have been no hospital admissions recorded for a diagnostic hysteroscopy, whereas the percentage of admissions for a surgical hysteroscopy was 1.25%, for a diagnostic laparoscopy, 10 % and for a surgical laparoscopy, 17.4 %.CONCLUSIONS: Hysteroscopy is a technique that is well-suited to outpatient surgery, and diagnostic laparoscopy, a procedure that maybe included in this area. Surgical laparoscopy, in complex pathologies such as endometriosis or myomas, and a correct pre-operatory cases election, may reduce the percentage of hospital admissions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellicer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñoles, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Evaluar los resultados de las intervenciones realizadas con técnicas endoscópicas en el contexto de la Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria Ginecológica. Definir criterios de selección preoperatoria. Crear un catálogo de indicaciones endoscópicas para la Cirugía Mayor Ambulatoria Ginecológica. DISEÑO: Estudio descriptivo, retrospectivo. MARCO: Intervenciones realizadas en la Unidad de Cirugía Sin Ingreso (UCSI).PACIENTES: 210 intervenciones realizadas con técnicas endoscópicas en la Unidad de Cirugía Sin Ingreso durante el año 2000. Se han estudiado el tipo y número de intervenciones, la relación entre el tipo de intervención general los tiempos anestésicos y de recuperación postoperatoria, valoración de los ingresos hospitalarios. RESULTADOS: La intervención de menor duración (46 minutos) ha sido la histeroscopia diagnóstica y la de mayor (79 minutos) la laparoscopia quirúrgica. La intervención con recuperación más rápida es la histeroscopia diagnóstica(128 minutos) y la intervención con recuperación más lenta la laparoscopia diagnóstica (277 minutos).No se han producido ingresos hospitalarios en la histeroscopia diagnóstica, el porcentaje de ingresos en la histeroscopia quirúrgica ha sido del 1.25 %, en la laparoscopia diagnóstica del 10% y en la laparoscopia quirúrgica del 17.4 %.CONCLUSIONES: Las técnicas histeroscópicas son un procedimiento muy adecuado para la cirugía mayor ambulatoria. La laparoscopia diagnóstica se puede incluir como un procedimiento de cirugía mayor ambulatoria. La laparoscopia quirúrgica, en patologías complejas como la endometriosis o los miomas, la adecuada selección preoperatoria de los casos, puede posibilitar que el porcentaje de ingresos hospitalarios sea inferior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;8(2): 80-86, mayo-ago. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Catálogo de indicaciones endoscópicas para la cirugía mayor ambulatoria ginecológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13890^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5967^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
