<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63710</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At present, sports has acquired a degree of really important presence in our lives. We are attracted by its magic, both as spectators and participants. This attraction exists because of the great enthusiasm and allusions and even some frustration, that is, part of our lives, that we express. In other words, sports is a representation of daily life, although in the form of the play. On the other hand, there is unmistakable evidence of the beneficial effect on different body systems, of its help in the prevention of different diseases, especially cardiovascular ones, and as coadjuvant to drug treatment and non-drug treatment of others1-5. That is why the concept of prescribing exercise has begun to prevail, above all in the medical setting, as a process in which a healthy or ill person is recommended and individualized physical activity regime adapted to their needs, on the contrary to the classical concept of prescribing a drug, treatment or procedure3. Treatment of epileptic patient is multidisciplinary and its objective is to improve the quality of life of these patients and their psychosocial and work situation. Sports will be an extremely important instrument to achieve this objective</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Escudero, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El deporte ha adquirido en la actualidad un grado de presencia en nuestras vidas realmente importante. Su magia nos atrae, tanto a espectadores como a practicantes. Esta atracción existe porque en el deporte volcamos mucho entusiasmo e ilusiones y hasta alguna frustración, es decir, parte de nuestras vidas. Por decirlo así, el deporte es una representación de la vida cotidiana, aunque en forma de juego. Por otra parte, se tienen evidencias inequívocas del efecto beneficioso sobre diferentes sistemas orgánicos, de su ayuda en la prevención de distintas enfermedades, especialmente las de tipo cardiovascular y como coadyudante al tratamiento farmacológico y no farmacológico de otras. Es por esto que el concepto de prescripción de ejercicio ha empezado a primar, sobre todo en el ámbito médico, como un proceso por el cual a una persona, sana o enferma, se le recomienda un régimen de actividad física individualizado y adecuado a sus necesidades, a diferencia del concepto clásico de prescribir o recetar un fármaco, un tratamiento o un procedimiento. El tratamiento del paciente epiléptico es multidisciplinario y tiene como objetivo mejorar la calidad de vida de estos pacientes y su situación psicosocial y laboral. El deporte va a ser un instrumento de enorme importancia para conseguir este objetivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);33(3): 127-139, mar. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63710</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
