<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96326</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Socio-cultural, obstetric and anthropometric characteristics of newborn children of mothers who smoke in spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: One in every four women smoke at the beginning of the pregnancy in Spain; of these, 25-50% give up smoking during gestation and most of them smoke again after child birth. Maternal smoking has harmful effects on babies, such as low birth-weight with its resulting morbidity. The objective of this study is to compare the anthropometric and socio-cultural characteristics between newborns from smoking mothers and those from non- smoking ones. Materials and methods: Smoking habits and the socio-cultural characteristics were assessed from a sample of 1499 pregnant women, as well as their newborn anthropometric variables of their newborn babies during 2009 in the Aragon region of Spain. Results: In the sample of 1499 pregnant women the prevalence of smoking during pregnancy was 19.6%; among the Spanish women, 23% of them smoked during the gestation compared with only 11% in women from other countries. The smoker mothers were younger and they had a lower educational level than the non smoker ones; however, there were no statistical differences between their anthropometric characteristics. Newborns from smoker women in Aragon had a lower weigh at delivery (3155 vs. 3295 grams: p &lt; .001) and a relative risk of low weight at birth for their gestational age of 2.1 (95% CI: 1.35 --- 2.97). The length and the rest of newborn anthropometric variables were also affected. Conclusion: The prevalence of smoking during gestation is high in Aragon. The mothers who smoke are younger and have different socio-cultural characteristics compared with non-smoker mothers. Maternal smoking habits have a harmful effect on newborn nutritional status, representing an avoidable risk of low weight at birth (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Sauras, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Pérez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Aznar, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Peña, Y. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrón Andrés, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samper Villagrasa, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares López, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En España, una de cada tres mujeres fuma al inicio del embarazo; de ellas, un 25-50% dejan de fumar durante la gestación y la mayoría reinicia el consumo tras el parto. Entre los efectos del tabaquismo materno en el recién nacido, destaca el bajo peso al nacimiento con su consecuente morbilidad. El objetivo del estudio es comparar las características antropométricas y socioculturales de los hijos de gestante no fumadora con respecto a los de madre fumadora en nuestro medio. Materiales y métodos: Se han evaluado los hábitos de tabaquismo y las características socioculturales de una muestra de 1.499 embarazadas y las variables antropométricas de sus recién nacidos durante el año 2009 en Aragón. Resultados: Se observó en las 1.499 gestantes estudiadas una prevalencia de tabaquismo en la gestación de 19,6%; entre las españolas el 23% fumó durante la gestación frente al 11% de las extranjeras. Las madres fumadoras fueron más jóvenes y con un nivel educativo menor que las no fumadoras; sin embargo no se hallaron diferencias en sus características antropométricas. Los nacidos en Aragón hijos de madre fumadora tuvieron un menor peso al nacer respecto a los de no fumadoras (3.155 g vs 3.295 g: p &lt; 0,001) y un riesgo relativo de nacer con bajo peso para su edad gestacional de 2,1 (IC 95%: 1,35-2,97). La longitud y resto de variables antropométricas del recién nacido también se vieron afectadas. Conclusiones: La prevalencia de tabaquismo durante la gestación en Aragón es alta. Las madres que fuman son más jóvenes y con características socioculturales diferentes a las no fumadoras. El hábito tabáquico materno repercute negativamente en el estado nutricional del recién nacido, suponiendo un riesgo evitable de bajo peso al nacer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);76(1): 4-9, ene. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96326</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características socioculturales, obstétricas y antropométricas de los recién nacidos hijos de madre fumadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32153^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
