<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047351</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of antiepileptic drugs in bipolar disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Bipolar disorder is a chronic disease difficult to treat that generates a high degree of incapacity. Although lithium remains the first choice drug, some patients do not respond and others show adverse reactions. One alternative to lithium is the use of certain antiepileptic drugs. Data on the efficacy of old and new antiepileptic drugs in bipolar disorder obtained in controlled clinical trials are reviewed.    Development. Results in many clinical trial support the use of some old antiepileptic drugs such as carbamazepine and sodium valproate in monotherapy in the acute treatment of severe, mixed or mild manic episodes as well as in the management treatment of bipolar disorder. Overall, new antiepileptic drugs show a better profile of adverse reactions with fewer interactions than lithium, but data on their efficacy in bipolar disorder remain scarce. Oxcarbazepine efficacy in mania is similar to that of the carbamazepine. Lamotrigine is becoming the best alternative to lithium in depressive episodes. Topiramate does not appear to be effective in acute treatment of manic episodes. Levetiracetam seems to produce some benefits, but controlled, randomized and double blind clinical trials are not yet available. Data on gabapentin efficacy are controversial.        Conclusions. Although lithium is still the first choice for the treatment of bipolar disorder, carbamazepine and valproate are also first choice drugs. Oxcarbazepine and lamotrigine may be a good option in some patients. Other new antiepileptic drugs may also be effective in bipolar disorder but more solid evidence of their efficacy is needed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega-Gil, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Ceballos, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armijo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El trastorno bipolar es una enfermedad crónica de difícil manejo terapéutico que genera altos índices de discapacidad. Aunque el litio es el fármaco de primera elección, hay pacientes que no responden o que presentan efectos secundarios. Una alternativa al litio es el uso de determinados antiepilépticos. Se revisan los datos sobre la eficacia de los antiepilépticos clásicos y nuevos en el tratamiento del trastorno bipolar obtenidos en ensayos controlados.    Desarrollo. Los resultados de numerosos ensayos clínicos avalan el empleo de los antiepilépticos clásicos como la carbamazepina y el valproato en monoterapia en el tratamiento agudo de los episodios maníacos severo, mixtos o leves, así como en el tratamiento crónico del trastorno bipolar. Los nuevos antiepilépticos presentan en general un perfil de reacciones adversos e interacciones más favorable que el litio, pero los datos sobre su eficacia en el trastorno bipolar son todavía escasos. La eficacia de la oxcarbazepina en la manía es similar a la de la carbamazepina. La lamotrigina se perfila como la mejor alternativa al litio en episodios depresivos. El topiramato no parece aportar beneficio en la manía aguda. El levetiracetam parece aportar un beneficio, pero no se dispone de ensayos con asignación aleatoria, doble ciego y controlados con placebo, y la gabapentina no está claro si aporta o no un beneficio.        Conclusiones. El litio continúa siendo el tratamiento de elección del trastorno bipolar, pero la carbamazepina y el valproato pueden considerarse también fármacos de primera línea. La oxcarbazepina y la lamotrigina pueden ser una buena opción en algunos pacientes. Otros nuevos antiepilépticos pueden aportar beneficios en el trastorno bipolar, pero se necesitan pruebas más sólidas de su eficacia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;34(1): 55-64, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047351</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de los antiepilépticos en el trastorno bipolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
