<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052835</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish adaptation of the Psychological Well-Being Scales (PWBS)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper is to adapt to Spanish the D. van Direndonck version of Carol Ryff&#146;s Psychological Well-Being Scales, and to analyse its consistency and factorial validity. All the scales exhibited good internal reliabilities, with Cronbach alpha&#146;s ranging from 0,83 (Self-acceptance) to 0,68 (Personal growth). However, confirmatory factor analyses didn&#146;t corroborate the six-factor model (Self-acceptance, Positive relations, Autonomy, Environmental mastery, Purpose in life, and Personal growth) with a second order factor called Psychological Well-Being. To improve the psychometric properties, a new reduced version was proposed that indeed will facilitate the application. The scales of the new version maintain and raise its internal consistency (Cronbach alpha&#146;s 0,84 to 0,70). Furthermore, the scales shown an excellent fit to the theoretical model proposed by D. van Dierendonck</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dierendonck, Dirk van</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Darío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Carvajal, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, Ismael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Jiménez, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, Amalio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo de investigación se ha adaptado al español la versión de D. van Dierendonck de las escalas de bienestar psicológico propuesta por Carol Ryff, y se ha estudiado su fiabilidad y validez factorial. Las escalas mostraron una buena consistencia interna con valores a de Cronbach comprendidos entre 0,83 (Autoaceptación) y 0,68 (Crecimiento personal). Sin embargo, los análisis factoriales confirmatorios no mostraron un nivel de ajuste satisfactorio al modelo teórico propuesto de seis dimensiones (Autoaceptación, Relaciones positivas, Autonomía, Dominio del entorno, Propósito en la vida, Crecimiento personal) y un factor de segundo orden denominado Bienestar Psicológico. Para mejorar las propiedades psicométricas de las escalas, se desarrolló una nueva versión reducida que además facilitará su aplicación. Con esta nueva versión, los niveles de consistencia obtenidos se mantienen e incluso mejoran (a de Cronbach 0,84 a 0,70). Además, las escalas mostraron un nivel de ajuste excelente al modelo teórico propuesto por D. van Dierendonck</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(3): 572-577, ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación española de las escalas de bienestar psicológico de Ryff</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
