<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101449</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors Associated With the Non-Completion of Conventional Anti-Tuberculosis Treatment in Peru</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The non-adherence to tuberculosis treatment is associated with increased infection, antibiotic resistance, increased costs and death. Our objective was to identify factors associated with lack of completion of conventional treatment for tuberculosis in Peru. Patients and methods: An unmatched case-control study in patients diagnosed with tuberculosis from 2004-2005 who completed treatment until September 2006. The cases were defined as patients who discontinued treatment for ¡Ý30 consecutive days, while the controls were defined as those who completed treatment without interruption. The factors were identified by logistic regression, calculating odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence intervals (CI). Results: We studied 265 cases and 605 controls. The non-adherence to treatment in our study was associated with the male sex (OR=1.62; CI: 1.07-2.44), having felt discomfort during treatment (OR=1.76; CI: 1.19-2.62), a prior history of non-compliance (OR=7.95; CI: 4.76-13.27) and illegal drug use (OR=3.74; CI: 1.25-11.14). Also, if we consider the interaction of previous non-adherence history and poverty, the risk of non-completion increases (OR=11.24; CI: 4-31.62). Conversely, having been properly informed about the disease (OR=0.25; CI: 0.07-0.94) and being able to access health-care services within office hours (8am-8pm) (OR=0.52; CI: 0.31-0.87) were associated with better adherence. Conclusions: The non-compliance with anti-tuberculosis treatment was associated with non-modifiable factors (male sex, previous non-compliance) and with others whose control would improve compliance (malaise during treatment, illegal drug use and poverty). Likewise, providing access to the health-care system and improving the information given about tuberculosis should be priorities(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grijalva, Carlos G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munayco E, C¨¦sar V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alva Ch, Kenedy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suarez O, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Culqui, Dante R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cayla, Joan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Horna-Campos, Olivia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: El abandono del tratamiento antituberculoso se asocia a mayor contagio, resistencia antibi¨®tica, aumento de costes y muerte. Nuestro objetivo fue identificar factores asociados al abandono del tratamiento antituberculoso convencional en Per¨². Pacientes y m¨¦todos: Estudio de casos y controles no pareado en pacientes diagnosticados de tuberculosis durante 2004-2005 y que finalizaron tratamiento hasta septiembre de 2006. Se definieron como casos los pacientes que abandonaron el tratamiento por ¡Ý30 d¨ªas consecutivos, y como controles los que completaron el tratamiento sin interrupci¨®n. Los factores se identificaron mediante regresi¨®n log¨ªstica, calcul¨¢ndose las odds ratios (OR) y los intervalos de confianza al 95% (IC). Resultados: Se estudiaron 265 casos y 605 controles. El abandono del tratamiento en nuestro estudio se asoci¨® al sexo masculino (OR=1,62; IC: 1,07-2,44), al hecho de sentir malestar durante el tratamiento (OR=1,76; IC: 1,19-2,62), al antecedente de abandono previo (OR=7,95; IC: 4,76-13,27) y al consumo de drogas recreativas (OR=3,74; IC: 1,25-11,14). As¨ª mismo, si tenemos en cuenta la interacci¨®n antecedente de abandono previo y pobreza, el riesgo de abandono aumenta (OR=11,24; IC: 4-31,62). Por el contrario, recibir buena informaci¨®n sobre la enfermedad (OR=0,25; IC: 0,07-0,94) y poder acceder al sistema sanitario en los horarios ofertados (08.00-20.00h) (OR=0,52; IC: 0,31-0,87) se asociaron a un mejor cumplimiento. Conclusiones: El abandono del tratamiento antituberculoso se asoci¨® a factores no modificables (sexo masculino, abandono previo) y a otros cuyo control mejorar¨ªa el cumplimiento (malestar durante el tratamiento, consumo de drogas recreativas y pobreza). As¨ª mismo, es prioritario facilitar el acceso al sistema sanitario y mejorar la informaci¨®n recibida sobre tuberculosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;48(5): 150-155, mayo 2012. mapa, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101449</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados al abandono de tratamiento antituberculoso convencional en Per¨²</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10757^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
