<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107037</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The perception of pain and fatigue to the state of mind during the  recovering of sport injuries: A case study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article describes the case study of a young footballer from the juvenile category who started training after a six months recovery due to different types of injuries he suffered within a year. The aim of this study is to show, during the different stages of a psychological training, the process of an injury recovery and the return to competition, the variability in the perception of pain and fatigue in connection with the state of mind. POMS was applied and the variables of pain, fatigue and satisfaction were estimated through the scales of  subjective assessment obtaining as a result the highest pain threshold right at the start of the return to competition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Más, Alexandre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liberal García, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo describe el estudio de caso de un futbolista en la categoría juvenil que inicia la práctica deportiva después de seis meses de recuperación tras sufrir diferentes tipos de lesión durante el periodo de un año. El estudio tiene como objetivo mostrar, en las diferentes etapas de un entrenamiento psicológico y durante el proceso de recuperación de una lesión y vuelta a la competición, la variabilidad en la percepción de dolor y de fatiga en relación con el estado de ánimo. Se utilizó el POMS y a través de escalas de valoración subjetiva se midieron las variables de dolor, fatiga y satisfacción, obteniendo como resultado el mayor umbral de dolor al inicio de la vuelta a la competición y, en esta misma etapa, puntuaciones bajas en fatiga y satisfacción (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;11(2): 93-106, jul.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107037</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción del dolor y fatiga en relación con el estado de ánimo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
