<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118970</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adoption and behavioural disturbances in adolescence. A hospital patient sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The number of adoptions has increased in the Western world in recent decades. An over-representation in mental health services and an increased risk of displaying behavioural disorders has been reported among adopted adolescents. In this study, we aim to assess the proportions of adopted and non-adopted adolescents and the presence of externalizing disorders in an inpatient setting. Methods: Prospective data were collected over 56 months (n = 431) from all adolescent admissions (12-17 years of age) to the Child and Adolescent&#146;s Inpatient Psychiatric Unit, which serves the Biscay province (Basque Country, Spain). The sample was divided into adopted (2.6%) and non-adopted adolescents (97.4%), and the following variables were compared: age, gender, cause of admission, prior admissions, main diagnosis, drug use and Overt Aggression Scale score at admission. Results: Adopted adolescents were over-represented in our sample (2.84% vs. 0.6% in the general population of Biscay, P&lt;0.001). Compared to the non-adopted, age at admission was significantly lower (14.09 vs. 15.21 years old, P=.017) and they showed a statistical tendency to be admitted more frequently for behavioural disorders (63.6% vs. 38.1%, P=0.086). Conclusions: The over-representation and the earlier age at admission suggest that the conditions of adopted adolescents are more serious and-or adoptive families are less able to manage them. The data also show that they tend to be admitted more for behavioural disorders, whilst no significant differences in the diagnosis on discharge were found, which suggests that they tend to externalise their symptoms more (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Landa Aqueche, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sesma Pardo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kerexeta, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Torres, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivanco González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rivas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erkoreka, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Cabeza, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En las últimas décadas se han incrementado las adopciones en el mundo occidental. Se ha descrito que los adolescentes adoptados están sobrerrepresentados en los servicios de salud mental y que consultan con mayor frecuencia por trastornos de externalización. Planteamos un estudio para valorar la proporción de adolescentes adoptivos y la presencia de conductas externalizantes en una muestra hospitalaria. Métodos: Se recogen prospectivamente los datos de todos los ingresos de adolescentes (12-17 años) hospitalizados en la Unidad de Hospitalización Infanto-Juvenil, que atiende a todo el territorio de Bizkaia, durante 56 meses (n = 431). Dividimos la muestra en adoptados (2,6%) y no adoptados (97,4%), y comparamos las siguientes variables: edad media al ingreso, sexo, motivo de ingreso, ingresos previos, diagnóstico al alta, consumo de tóxicos y resultados de la Overt Aggression Scale al ingreso. Resultados: Los adolescentes adoptados están sobrerrepresentados en nuestra muestra (2,84% vs. 0,6% en la población general; p &lt; 0,001). Comparándolos con el subgrupo de no adoptivos, ingresan significativamente más jóvenes (14,09 vs. 15,21 años; p = 0,017) y tienden a hacerlo más frecuentemente por alteraciones de conducta (63,6% vs. 38,1%; p = 0,086). Conclusiones: Los adolescentes adoptados presentan más ingresos y lo hacen a una edad más temprana, datos que indican una mayor gravedad de la afección de estos adolescentes o una menor capacidad de contención de las familias adoptivas. Además, observamos que tienden a ingresar más por alteraciones conductuales, sin existir diferencias significativas en los diagnósticos al alta, lo que sugiere una tendencia a expresar la sintomatología de forma más externalizadora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);80(1): 21-27, ene. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118970</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adopción y alteraciones de conducta en la adolescencia. Estudio en población hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
