<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121150</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for the Coordinated Management of Psoriatic Arthritis by Rheumatologists and Dermatologists: A Delphi Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psoriatic arthritis, a chronic inflammatory musculoskeletal disease that is associated with psoriasis, causes joint erosions, accompanied by loss of function and quality-of-life. The clinical presentation is variable, with extreme phenotypes that can mimic rheumatoid arthritis or ankylosing spondylitis. Because psoriasis usually presents before psoriatic arthritis, the dermatologist plays a key role in early detection of the latter. As many treatments used in psoriasis are also used in psoriatic arthritis, treatment recommendations should take into consideration the type and severity of both conditions. This consensus paper presents guidelines for the coordinated management of psoriatic arthritis by rheumatologists and dermatologists. The paper was drafted by a multidisciplinary group (6 rheumatologists, 6 dermatologists, and 2 epidemiologists) using the Delphi method and contains recommendations, tables, and algorithms for the diagnosis, referral, and treatment of patients with psoriatic arthritis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Vivar, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Moreno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daudén, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montilla, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carretero, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Carazo, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Estebaranz, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Queiro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañete, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artritis psoriásica es una enfermedad inflamatoria crónica que afecta al sistema musculoesquelético, se asocia a psoriasis y suele producir destrucción articular con pérdida de función y calidad de vida. Su presentación clínica es heterogénea, con extremos fenotípicos que pueden solaparse con la artritis reumatoide o la espondilitis anquilosante. La psoriasis suele preceder a la artritis psoriásica, y la consulta de dermatología es el lugar clave para su detección precoz. Muchos tratamientos utilizados en psoriasis también se utilizan en artritis psoriásica, por tanto las recomendaciones terapéuticas para la psoriasis deben realizarse teniendo en cuenta el tipo y la gravedad de la artritis psoriásica, y viceversa. El objetivo de este documento es establecer pautas para el manejo coordinado (reumatólogo/dermatólogo) de la artritis psoriásica. Ha sido elaborado mediante la técnica Delphi por un grupo multidisciplinar (6 reumatólogos, 6 dermatólogos y 2 epidemiólogos) y contiene recomendaciones, tablas y algoritmos para diagnóstico, criterios de derivación y tratamiento de la artritis psoriásica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;105(3): 216-232, abr. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121150</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elaboración mediante el método Delphi de recomendaciones para el manejo coordinado (reumatólogo/dermatólogo) de la artritis psoriásica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
