<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043246</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Serum urate levels and urinary uric acid excretion in subjects with metabolic syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Hyperuricemia is considered a feature of the metabolic syndrome (MS) despite serum uric acid (SUA) is not considered a diagnostic criterion. The main physiopathological disturbance leading to the increased SUA is not completely understood. Patients and method: Descriptive study without drug intervention including 141 subjects (NCEP-ATPIII: 105 with MS and 36 without MS). Serum UA levels were compared in subjects with and without MS. The mechanism of the rise in SUA levels was assessed (overproduction or decreased renal excretion). The relation of SUA levels to the HOMA index was also evaluated. Results: Subjects with MS showed significantly higher SUA levels (5.6 [1.6] vs 4.6 [1.7] mg/dl, p = 0.002), and lower urinary UA excretion than subjects without MS (UA clearance 3.60 [2.41] vs 4.65 [3.04] ml/min/m2, p = 0.049; excreted fraction of filtered UA 7.15 [4.72] vs 9.81 [6.78%], p = 0.045). Sex (male 6.1 [1.6] vs female 4.9 [1.6] mg/dl, p &lt; 0.001), alcohol intake (drinkers 6.1 [1.8] vs non-drinkers 5.2 [1.6] mg/dl, p &lt; 0.01), and MS (present 5.6 [1.6] absent 4.6 [1.7] mg/dl, p &lt; 0.002), were significantly associated with SUA. In the multiple regression analysis, sex and MS were independently associated with SUA. Conclusions: This study demonstrates significantly higher SUA levels in subjects with MS. A decreased urinary UA excretion, instead of urate overproduction, was the leading mechanism to explain high SUA. Serum UA levels were not associated with the HOMA index</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bascuñana-Quirell, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez-Rodríguez, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano-Serrano, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elvira-González, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Suárez, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosal-Obrador, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Michán-Doña, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivos: La hiperuricemia es una de las alteraciones características del síndrome metabólico (SM), aunque no incluida como criterio diagnóstico. No se conoce con exactitud el mecanismo que causa la elevación del urato sérico en el SM. Pacientes y método: Estudio transversal, sin intervención farmacológica, sobre 141 individuos (National Cholesterol Education Program Adult Treatment Panel III: 105 con SM y 36 sin SM). Se comparan los valores de urato sérico entre individuos con y sin SM, y se analiza si la elevación del urato sérico se asocia a infraexcreción renal o sobreproducción. Se determina la asociación del urato sérico a índice HOMA. Resultados: El grupo con SM presentó valores de urato sérico significativamente más elevados (media [DE] 5,6 [1,6] frente a 4,6 [1,7] mg/dl, p = 0,002), y menor excreción urinaria (aclaramiento de ácido úrico 3,60 [2,41] frente a 4,65 [3,04] ml/min/m2, p = 0,049; fracción excretada del ácido úrico filtrado 7,15 [4,72] frente a 9,81 [6,78]%, p = 0,045). Las variables asociadas con los valores de urato sérico fueron el sexo (media de urato sérico en varón 6,1 [1,6] frente a mujer 4,9 [1,6] mg/dl, p &lt; 0,001), el alcohol (bebedores 6,1 [1,8] frente a no bebedores 5,2 [1,6] mg/dl, p &lt; 0,01), y el SM (presente 5,6 [1,6] frente a ausente 4,6 [1,7] mg/dl, p &lt; 0,002). En el análisis multivariante, sólo el sexo y el SM se asociaron independientemente con los valores de urato sérico. Conclusiones: El presente estudio muestra unos valores de urato sérico significativamente más elevados entre individuos con SM, relacionado a su vez con una infraexcreción renal de uratos. No se observó asociación significativa de los valores de urato sérico con el índice HOMA</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(9): 321-324, mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043246</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentraciones séricas de uratos y excreción urinaria de ácido úrico en individuos con síndrome metabólico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37291^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14926^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14926^s22050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14902^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
