<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82855</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Demand management of emergencies, I want the doctor to see me now. What do we do?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. Description of the experience of organizational management of demand in our health centre. Assessment of the usefulness, level of satisfaction and perception of improvement on the part of the professionals of the centre using an evaluation survey. Material and methods. DESIGN: Descriptive Study of the experience and an evaluation survey. SETTING: Urban Area with 29,674 patients assigned. PARTICIPANTS: The team of health and non-health professionals of the health centre. INTERVENTIONS: Decrease in previous appointments in the lists of the physicians, with an increase in the visits on the day and creation of a new circuit of patient care using a triage nurse and an emergency physician. Implementation of an evaluation survey of all &#147;professionals of the centre&#148;. MAIN MEASUREMENTS: Analysis of triage nurse visits, as well as the percentage of resolution and analysis of the results of the survey by profession. Results. The average of visits to the nurse triage was 30, with 41% of them being resolved there. The survey was completed by 93.8% of professionals of the centre. Conclusions. There were high appraisals for the triage clinic by all the staff. The improvements and the decrease in workload were mainly administrative and medical (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Font Roura, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciurana Gay, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrent Goñi, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sieira Ribot, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Comet, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rafols Crestani, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objectivo. Descripción de la experiencia organizativa de gestión de la demanda en nuestro centro de salud. Valoración de la utilidad, grado de satisfacción y percepción de mejora por parte de los profesionales del centro mediante una encuesta de valoración. Material y métodos. DISEÑO: Estudio descriptivo de la experiencia y de una encuesta de valoración. EMPLAZAMIENTO: Área urbana con 29.674 pacientes asignados. PARTICIPANTES: Todo el equipo de profesionales sanitarios y no sanitarios del centro de salud. INTERVENCIONES: Disminución de la cita previa en las agendas de los facultativos con aumento de las visitas del día y creación de un circuito nuevo de atención a los pacientes con una enfermera de triaje y un médico de guardia. Aplicación de una encuesta de valoración a todos los «profesionales del centro». MEDICIONES PRINCIPALES: Análisis de las visitas de la enfermera de triaje así como del porcentaje de resolución y análisis de los resultados de la encuesta por estamentos. Resultados. La media de visitas por parte de la enfermera de triaje es de 30 con un 41% de resolución por parte de la misma. Encuesta cumplimentada por el 93,8% de los profesionales del centro. Conclusiones. Valoración elevada por parte de todo el personal de la consulta de triaje. Las mejoras y la disminución de carga de trabajo lo refieren principalmente administrativos y médicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(10): 562-565, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82855</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión de la demanda de urgencias: Quiero que el médico me vea ahora. ¿Cómo lo hacemos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
