<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-14663</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-concept, causal attribution process and academic goals in children with and without learning disabilities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Up to the present, the results of psychological research using samples of students with learning disabilities (LD) that are related to variables such as self-concept, motivation, or causal attribution processes are very often contradictory. Recent reviews suggest a two-fold explanation of this fact: on the one hand, the type of instrument used to assess these variables and, on the other, the comparison of results from groups of students with learning disabilities who receive different instructional treatment (ordinary classes, supplementary instruction outside the ordinary class, etc.). In this study, we attempt to analyze in-depth this confusing situation. Instruments for multidimensional assessment with contrasted reliability and validity were used. We focused on just one type of class (students who receive supplementary instruction outside the ordinary class) and we employed quite a large sample (259 students with LD and 243 without LD). The results of the study indicate that, compared to students without LD, those with LD have a more negative general self-image, especially in academic areas, although in social areas as well. They attribute their failures more frequently to internal causes than to external ones, and they feel less responsible for their successes, although in both cases, they consider effort an important factor in their academic results. They are also less motivated, both intrinsically and extrinsically (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Pienda, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roces, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Pumariega, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González,Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanach, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los resultados de la investigación psicológica realizada hasta la fecha en muestras de estudiantes con dificultades de aprendizaje (DA) respecto a variables tales como el autoconcepto, la motivación o los procesos de atribución causal son, en muchos casos, contradictorios. Revisiones recientes apuntan a una doble explicación de este hecho: por una parte, el tipo de instrumento utilizado para evaluar estas variables y, por otro lado, estaría la comparación de resultados de grupos de estudiantes con DA escolarizados en contextos distintos (clases inclusivas, apoyo fuera de clase ordinaria, etc.). Con la realización de este estudio pretendemos profundizar en el análisis de esta situación ciertamente confusa. Han sido utilizados instrumentos de evaluación multidimensional, de contrastada fiabilidad y validez, un único tipo de clase (apoyo fuera de la clase ordinaria), y un tamaño muestral razonablemente amplio (259 estudiantes con DA y 243 sin DA).Los resultados del estudio muestran que los estudiantes con DA en relación a sus iguales sin dificultades, presentan una imagen de sí mismos más negativa a nivel general y, especialmente, en las áreas académicas, aunque también en las dimensiones de naturaleza social; atribuyen sus fracasos más a causas internas que externas y se responsabilizan menos de sus éxitos, aunque en ambos casos consideran el esfuerzo como factor fundamental de cara a sus resultados académicos; y, finalmente, se encuentran menos motivados hacia el aprendizaje escolar y la búsqueda de aprobación social (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(4): 548-556, nov. 2000. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-14663</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Autoconcepto, proceso de atribución causal y metas académicas en niños con y sin dificultades de aprendizaje</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1248</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6184</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
