<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135864</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">NOTES. History and current situation of natural orifice transluminal endoscopic surgery in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Natural orifice transluminal endoscopic surgery (NOTES), involves a group of new endoscopic approaches to the abdominal cavity, with potential advantages over conventional laparoscopic surgery. It is based on the possibility of performing intra-peritoneal surgical techniques through natural orifices by entering the peritoneal cavity through natural orifices perforating the organ that allows direct access to that cavity (stomach, vagina, rectum, bladder). The possibility of using this same route to access the retroperitoneum and mediastinum has subsequently been postulated. Comments are made on how the technique has been developed, as well as how it has been applied in our country, attempting to give a general view on the risks and benefits of NOTES and the basic requirements to be able to start in this new surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano Salvá, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuadrado García, Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicens Arbona, José C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero Bogajo, María L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Sanz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Soriano, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olea Martínez-Mediero, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noguera Aguilar, José F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía endoscópica transluminal a través de orificios naturales (NOTES, del inglés Natural Orifice Translumenal Endoscopic Surgery), engloba un conjunto de nuevas vías de abordaje endoscópico de la cavidad abdominal, con ventajas potenciales sobre la cirugía laparoscópica convencional. Se fundamenta en la posibilidad de realizar técnicas quirúrgicas intraperitoneales mediante la entrada en la cavidad peritoneal a través de los orificios naturales perforando el órgano que permite la entrada directa a dicha cavidad (estómago, vagina, recto, vejiga). Posteriormente se ha postulado la posibilidad de este mismo acceso para acceder al retroperitoneo y al mediastino. A continuación se comenta como se ha desarrollado la técnica y cómo ha sido la aplicación en nuestro país, intentado dar una visión general sobre los riesgos y beneficios de la NOTES y las necesidades básicas para poder iniciarse en esta nueva cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);88(4): 222-227, oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135864</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">NOTES. Historia y situación actual de la cirugía endoscópica por orificios naturales en nuestro país</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54198^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38897</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
