<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125634</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vabiability of physical activity in 17-18 year-old spanish adolescents by type of day and season</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyze the variability of physical activity levels, according to the season (winter, autumn) and type of day (weekend, school day), in a sample of 395 Spanish adolescents aged 17-18 years old. Physical activity was measured with the Four by one-day physical activity questionnaire. Adolescents showed more energy expenditure in winter (M = 39.97 Kcal/kg/day) than in autumn (M = 37.31 Kcal/kg/day), and during the weekend (M = 39.29 Kcal/kg/day) than the school day (M = 37.99 Kcal/kg/day). Chi-square tests showed that more teens were 'active' and 'moderately active' in these periods in which there were also more energy expenditure. Nevertheless, in autumn adolescents showed more energy expenditure during the school day (M = 38.56 Kcal/kg/day) than the weekend (M = 36.06 Kcal/kg/day), while the opposite happened in winter (M = 42.52 Kcal/kg/day during weekend and M = 37.41 Kcal/kg/day during school day). Results from this study indicate season and type of day may influence adolescents&#146; physical activity levels, but differently compared to other countries or geographical areas. According to this specific variability, several  strategies for the promotion of physical activity in the most inactive periods of the week and the year are suggested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peiró Velert, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Devís Devís, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenciano Valcárcel, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Carrillo, Vicente J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar la variabilidad de los niveles de actividad física de una muestra de 395 adolescentes españoles de 17-18 años, según la estación del año (otoño, invierno) y el tipo de jornada (entre semana, fin de semana). La medida de la actividad física se llevó a cabo a través del cuestionario de recuerdo Four by one-day physical activity questionnaire. Los adolescentes presentaron mayor gasto energético en invierno (M = 39.97 Kcal/kg/día) que en otoño (M = 37.31 Kcal/kg/día), y en fin de semana (M = 39.29 Kcal/kg/día) que en jornada escolar (M = 37.99 Kcal/kg/día). Las pruebas Chi-cuadrado muestran que hay más adolescentes &#145;activos&#146; y &#145;moderadamente activos&#146; en estos periodos en los que también hay mayor gasto energético. No obstante, en otoño los jóvenes presentaron mayor gasto energético durante la jornada escolar (M = 38.56 Kcal/kg/día)  que en fin de semana (M = 36.06 Kcal/kg/día), mientras que en invierno ocurrió lo contrario (M = 42.52 Kcal/kg/día en fin de semana y M = 37.41 Kcal/kg/día durante la jornada escolar). Los resultados de este estudio indican que la estación del año y el tipo de jornada pueden afectar a los niveles de actividad física de los adolescentes, pero de modo distinto en comparación con otros países o zonas geográficas. En función de esta variabilidad particular, se plantean diversas estrategias para la promoción de la actividad física en los periodos más inactivos de la semana y el año (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;23(2): 347-354, jul.-dic. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125634</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad de la actividad física en adolescentes españoles de 17-18 años en función del tipo de jornada y época del año</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25631^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25630^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13002^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
