<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76513</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of the articles published in "Matronas Profesión" and "Enfermería Nefrológica" from 2001 to 2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the characteristics of the articles published in &#147;Matronas Profesión&#148; (MP) and Enfermería Nefrológica&#148; (EN) from 2001 to 2004.Design. An observational, descriptive, cross-sectional study. Material and methods. The study focused on all the articles, with the exception of editorials, published over those four years in the aforementioned journals. Access to the articles was attained, and the data was collected by two independent researchers in order to guarantee the reliability of the information. The characteristics of each article, the authors and the reference list were recorded. The original articles were characterized according to whether the methodology utilized was quantitative or qualitative. Results. The authors analyzed 188 articles, 80 (42.6%) from MP and 108 (57.4%) from EN. Original articles predominated in EN (47.2%), whereas articles focusing on continuing education were most common in MP (36.3%). In EN, the subject most frequently dealt with was hemodialysis (41.7%) and in MP, childbirth (15%). The mean number of authors per article was similar (4) in the two journals, as were the Spanish Autonomous Communities with the greatest production (Catalonia, Andalusia and Madrid), although the distributions differed from one journal to the other. Conclusions. EN offers more original articles, while the quality of the reference lists is greater in MP. Both journals present certain aspects in which they should improve in order to increase their scientific quality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Force, Enriqueta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu, Lola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentelsaz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seguranyes, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer las características de los artículos publicados en las revistas Matronas Profesión (MP) y Enfermería Nefrológica (EN) durante los años 2001-2004. Diseño. Estudio observacional, descriptivo y transversal. Material y método. Las unidades de estudio fueron todos los artículos publicados durante estos 4 años en ambas revistas, excepto los editoriales. Se confeccionó una parrilla para efectuar el vaciado de las revistas. La recogida de los datos se realizó de manera independiente por dos personas para garantizar la fiabilidad de la información. Se recogió información sobre las características de cada uno de los artículos, de los autores y de las referencias bibliográficas. Sobre los artículos originales también se recogió el tipo de metodología utilizada, cuantitativa o cualitativa. Resultados. Se han analizado 188 artículos, 80 (42,6%) de MP y 108 (57,4%) de EN. Los más frecuentes en EN han sido los artículos originales (47,2%) y en MP los de formación continuada (36,3%). El principal tema de estudio de EN ha sido la hemodiálisis (41,7%) y de MP el parto (15%). El número de autores por artículo es similar (4) en ambas revistas, así como las comunidades autónomas con más producción (Cataluña, Andalucía y Madrid), aunque con diferente distribución en ambas revistas. Conclusiones. La revista EN presenta el mayor número de trabajos originales y la revista MP tiene una mayor calidad en el apartado de bibliografía. Cada una de las revistas presenta algunos aspectos que deberían mejorar para aumentar su calidad científica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;9(3): 211-217, jul.-sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76513</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de los artículos publicados en las revistas «Matronas Profesión» y «Enfermería Nefrológica» durante los años 2001-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9958^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9591^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
