<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89802</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to identify and to evaluate quality levels in clinical practice guidelines (CPGs) on spinal infusion using the AGREE (Appraisal of Guidelines Research and Evaluation) tool prior to its possible adaptation to and application in our setting. Material and methods: two authors independently performed a systematic literature search for CPGs. Each selected CPG was evaluated by 4 reviewers using the Spanishadapted AGREE tool. Six assessment areas were examined for each CPG. Finally, according to criteria suggested by Etxeberría and Rotaeche, a definitive global assessment of each CPG was performed based on score standardization for each area. Results: 13 CPGs were selected for evaluation. In the definitive global assessment 7 CPGs were deemed &#147;non-recommended&#148;, 5 were deemed &#147;conditionally recommended&#148;, and 1 was considered &#147;highly recommended&#148;. All 7 non-recommended CPGs remained below the cutoff in all evaluated areas, all 5 conditionally recommended CPGs reached above the cutoff in two areas, and the one highly recommended CPG reached above the cutoff in 4 areas. Conclusions: the quality assessment of existing CPGs on spinal infusion has revealed a wide margin for improvement in most of them. A critical appraisal of CPG quality is crucial before CPG application is encouraged in our setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cid, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle, J. L. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrés, J. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Insausti, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, C. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: identificar y evaluar los niveles de calidad de las Guías de práctica clínica (GPC) sobre infusión espinal con el instrumento AGREE (Appraisal of Guidelines Research and Evaluation), antes de su posible adaptación y aplicación en nuestro entorno. Material y métodos: de forma independiente por dos autores, se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica sistematizada de las GPC existentes. Cada una de las GPC seleccionadas ha sido evaluada por 4 revisores, utilizando el instrumento AGREE en su versión adaptada al español. En cada GPC, se analizaron seis áreas de valoración. Finalmente, siguiendo los criterios propuestos por Etxeberría y Rotaeche, se ha realizado una valoración global definitiva de cada una de las GPC, basada en la estandarización de las puntuaciones de cada una de las áreas. Resultados: se seleccionaron para su evaluación 13 GPC. En la valoración global definitiva, 7 GPC se consideraron como no recomendadas, 5 como recomendadas con condiciones y 1 como muy recomendada. Las 7 GPC no recomendadas, mayoritariamente, no superaron el punto de corte en ninguna de las áreas evaluadas, las 5 recomendadas con condiciones, lo superaron en dos áreas, y la única muy recomendada lo hizo en 4 de ellas. Conclusiones: la evaluación de la calidad de las GPC publicaciones sobre infusión espinal, ha demostrado un amplio margen de mejora de la mayoría de las mismas. Resulta obligado realizar una valoración crítica sobre la calidad de de las GPC, antes de proponer su aplicación a nuestro entorno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;18(3): 187-192, mayo-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89802</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infusión espinal: valoración crítica de las guías depráctica clínica con el instrumento AGREE</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13498^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
