<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101712</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mild emoptysis immigrant child: Diagnostic up-date</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 9 year-old child form Peru with a background of chronic cough and discontinuous hemotoxic expectoration of 3 months evolution in which persistent pulmonary infiltrate was detected don the chest x-ray. We describe the action guidelines with this type of patients as well as the problems created in the detection of the underlying cause of bleeding. Hemoptysis is an uncommon sign in the pediatric practice, however it produces much anxiety for the patient and their family, as well as for the physician, for whom it supposes a diagnostic-therapeutic challenge. Its low incidence in the child may lead to initial delays in its diagnosis and this sign may even go unnoticed. The spectrum of pathological conditions that may cause it is very wide and usually the most frequent ones are infectious causes, although there may be other underlying potentially severe diseases. Therefore, it is of priority to know the exact etiology and t decide the consequent therapeutic attitude (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cimadevilla, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz San Román, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Conde, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo Posadas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo Elorriaga, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Sebastián, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanavia Morán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un varón de 9 años de edad, de origen peruano, con antecedentes de tos crónica y expectoración hemoptoica discontinua de tres meses de evolución en el que se detecta un infiltrado pulmonar persistente en la radiografía de tórax. Describimos la norma de actuación con este tipo de pacientes así como la problemática creada en la detección de la causa subyacente del sangrado. La hemoptisis es un signo infrecuente en la práctica pediátrica pero muy angustiante para el paciente y su familia, así como para el médico, para quién supone un reto diagnóstico-terapéutico. Su baja incidencia e n el niño puede llevar a retrasos iniciales en su diagnóstico e incluso a que este signo pase inadvertido. El espectro de entidades patológicas que pueden causarla es muy amplio y habitualmente las más frecuentes son las causas infecciosas, aunque también pueden subyacer otras enfermedades potencialmente graves. Por ello es prioritario conocer su etiología exacta y decidir la consiguiente actitud terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;67(5): 241-246, sept.-oct. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemoptisis leve en un niño inmigrante. Puesta al día diagnóstica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6621^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
