<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143301</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Internal adaptation evaluation of composite resins: Incremental filling versus Sonic-activated bulk-fill</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Recently, Bulk-Fill resins have been developed and they can be used with a mono-incremental technique, eliminating the traditional oblique incremental technique and shortening the clinical time. The aim of this study is to evaluate the internal adaptation of composite resins using oblique incremental and monoincremental techniques with sonic activation. Material and method: 15 healthy third molars were used and two enamel finished class II cavity was performed on each one of them. Dimensions were: 3 mm mesio-distal, 2.5 mm buccal-lingual, 2 mm occlusal-pulp depth, and 4 mm occlusal-proximal depth. The distal preparations were restored using a conventional FiltekTMZ350 XT (3M ESPE, USA) resin with oblique incremental technique and the mesial ones were restored using Bulk-Fill SonicFillTM (Kerr, USA) resin through mono-incremental technique and sonic activation. The samples were cut in a mesiodistal direction and analyzed with an optical microscopy at 10× and 40× magnification. The percentage of adaptation of both resins was measured, and a two-way ANOVA with Tukey correction was performed. Results: No statistically significant difference was found in the adaptation of both resins, using oblique incremental and mono-incremental techniques with sonic activation (p&gt;0.01). Discussion: Both techniques reported similar values of adaptation, therefore, the mono-incremental technique with sonic activation is a recently introduced technique, which seems to be less sensitive than oblique incremental technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gehrkue Lorca, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gainza Aragonés, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Araneda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Recientemente se han desarrollado las resinas bulk-fill que pueden ser utilizadas con técnica monoincremental, reemplazando la tradicional técnica incremental oblicua y acortando el tiempo clínico. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar la adaptación de las resinas compuestas a las paredes internas cavitarias, utilizando técnica incremental oblicua y monoincremental con activación sónica. Material y método: Se utilizaron 15 terceros molares sanos, a los cuales se les realizó dos preparaciones cavitarias clase II con márgenes en esmalte, de dimensiones en sentido mesiodistal de 3 mm, vestibulolingual de 2,5 mm, profundidad oclusopulpar de 2 mm y profundidad oclusoproximal de 4 mm. Las preparaciones distales se restauraron utilizando la resina convencional FiltekTM Z350 XT con técnica incremental y las mesiales con la resina bulk-fill SonicFillTM con técnica monoincremental y activación sónica. Las muestras fueron cortadas en sentido mesiodistal y analizadas mediante microscopio óptico a aumento de 10× y 40×. Se midió el porcentaje de adaptación de ambas resinas y se realizó un test ANOVA de dos vías con prueba post hoc de Tukey. Resultados: No se encontró diferencia estadísticamente significativa en la adaptación interna cavitaria utilizando la técnica monoincremental con activación sónica y la incremental oblicua (p&gt;0,01). Discusión: La técnica monoincremental con activación sónica, a pesar de tener un menor tiempo en el mercado, menor tiempo de entrenamiento clínico y menor consumo de tiempo clínico presentó valores similares de adaptación a las paredes internas cavitarias que la técnica incremental oblicua (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;31(5): 313-321, sept.-oct. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143301</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la adaptación interna de resinas compuestas: Técnica incremental versus bulk-fill con activación sónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14863^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3219^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11326^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51660^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
