<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165835</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic hypothermia: should it be dropped?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Current international guidelines recommend therapeutic hypothermia for patients who have survived a witnessed cardiac arrest to minimize neurological damage due to postischemic reperfusion. This recommendation is based mainly on the results of two randomized, controlled trials that included 352 patients and on supporting evidence from the field of neonatal asphyxia that also demonstrated the neuroprotective effect of hypothermia. However, the use of hypothermia in the context of a cardiac arrest has been called into question in the wake of a recently published randomized trial that included 939 patients and which found that hypothermia at 33 °C offered no benefits over maintaining a temperature of 36 °C. Moreover, another recent study has questioned the usefulness of starting hypothermia early in the prehospital phase. This article contains a review of the evidence available on the use of hypothermia, areas of uncertainty and strategies for using the technique. It concludes that there is sufficient evidence to support the continued use of hypothermia in the majority of patients who suffer a cardiac arrest and have a heart rhythm susceptible to defibrillation, pending the results of new studies using a range of target temperatures (32-36 °C) and treatment durations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Viana Tejedor, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las guías internacionales actuales recomiendan el uso de hipotermia terapéutica para los pacientes que sobreviven a una parada cardiaca presenciada para disminuir el daño neurológico por isquemia-reperfusión. Esta recomendación se basa fundamentalmente en los resultados de dos ensayos clínicos aleatorizados que incluyeron a 352 pacientes y en la evidencia procedente del campo de la asfixia neonatal, que también demostró los efectos neuroprotectores de la hipotermia. Sin embargo, la hipotermia en el contexto de la parada cardiaca se ha puesto en duda a raíz de la reciente publicación de un estudio aleatorizado que incluyó a 939 pacientes y no encontró beneficio en el uso de hipotermia a 33 °C comparado con el control de temperatura a 36 °C. Además, otro ensayo clínico reciente ha cuestionado la utilidad de la hipotermia iniciada precozmente, en la fase prehospitalaria. En este artículo se revisan la evidencia disponible, las áreas de incertidumbre y la estrategia de utilización de la hipotermia, y se concluye que existe suficiente evidencia para seguir usando la hipotermia en la mayoría de los pacientes que sufren una parada cardiaca con un ritmo desfibrilable, a la espera de los resultados de nuevos estudios que evalúen varios objetivos de temperatura (32-36 °C) y distintas duraciones del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);15(supl.D): 20d-24d, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipotermia terapéutica: ¿lo dejamos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7216^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23813^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56136</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
