<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100787</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of cost-effectiveness in the diagnosis of fever of unknown origin and the role of 18F-FDG PET-CT: a proposal of diagnostic algorithm</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To analyze the costs of Fever of Unknown Origin (FUO) prior to the PET-CT study. To determine the effectiveness of PET-CT in the diagnosis of FUO. A proposal of diagnostic algorithm. Material and methods. A retrospective study was performed that included 20 patients who had been studied between January 2007 and January 2011, with a mean age of 57.75 years and FUO diagnosis. All underwent a PET-CT study with 18F-FDG. Individual and mean costs of FUO in these patients were assessed, including hospitalization days and complementary tests prior to the PET-CT study. The effectiveness of the PET-CT study in the diagnosis of FUO was analyzed. Costs of the FUO process were determined, including those of the PET-CT study, and if it had been done earlier in the diagnostic process. Results. Mean hospital stay per patient until the PET-CT study was 28 days. The cost per hospitalization day was 342 &#128;. Average cost per patient in complementary tests was 1395 &#128;. Total cost of the FUO process until the PET-CT study was around 11167 &#128; per patient. The PET-CT study showed a 78% sensitivity, 83% specificity, 92% PPV and 62% NPV. If PET-CT had been performed earlier in the FUO process, assuming the same effectiveness, 5471 &#128; per patient would have been saved. Conclusion. The PET-CT study could be cost-effective in the FUO process if used at an early stage, helping to establish an early diagnosis, reducing hospitalization days due to diagnostic purposes and the repetition of unnecessary tests(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Vicente, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Narváez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poblete García, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Talavera Rubio, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano Castrejón, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerra Nakayo, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero García, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar los costes previos a la PET-TC del proceso fiebre de origen desconocido (FOD). Determinar la efectividad de la PET-TC en el diagnóstico de FOD. Propuesta de algoritmo diagnóstico. Material y métodos. Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo, que incluyó a 20 pacientes estudiados entre enero de 2007 y enero de 2011, con diagnóstico de FOD y con una edad media de 57,75 años. A todos los pacientes se les realizó un estudio PET-TC con 18F-FDG. Se analizaron los costes individuales y las medias que representó el proceso FOD de estos pacientes, incluyendo días de hospitalización y pruebas complementarias previas a la PET-TC. Se valoró la efectividad de la PET-TC en el diagnóstico de FOD. Se determinaron los costes del proceso FOD, incluyendo el de la PET-TC y si ésta se hubiera realizado de forma precoz. Resultados. La estancia media hospitalaria por paciente hasta la PET-TC fue de 28 días. El coste por día de hospitalización fue de 342 &#128;. El coste promedio por paciente en pruebas complementarias fue de 1.395 &#128;. El coste total del proceso FOD hasta la PET-TC fue de 11.167 &#128; por paciente. La PET-TC mostró una sensibilidad del 78%, una especificidad del 83%, un VPP del 92% y un VPN del 62%. Si la PET-TC se hubiera realizado antes en el proceso FOD, asumiendo la misma efectividad, se hubieran ahorrado 5.471 &#128; en cada paciente. Conclusiones. La PET-TC pudiera ser costo-efectiva en el proceso FOD si se empleara de forma precoz, porque ayudaría a establecer un diagnóstico temprano, reduciendo los días de hospitalización por motivos de estudio y la repetición de pruebas innecesarias(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);31(4): 178-186, jul.-ago.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100787</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de costo-efectividad en el diagnóstico de fiebre de origen desconocido y el papel de la 18F-FDG PET-TC: propuesta de algoritmo diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5445^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5445^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5445^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
