<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057766</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of a new methodology for the assessment of cervical mobility based on photogrammetry techniques</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The non-existence of objective, reliable and precise methods of functional valuation of the cervical spine mobility makes difficult the election of a suitable rehabilitation treatment and subsequent control of its evolution in affected patients of cervical pain. All this has raised the need of developing a new methodology of cervical mobility valuation based on video-photogrammetry techniques and to define the patterns of mobility based on the parameters age and gender.         Material and methods. For the accomplishment of the study a sample of 50 people aged between 20 and 79 years with absence of cervical pathology has been selected. Besides, a pilot study was made with 14 affected people of cervical pain. The measuring equipment is based on a video-photogrammetry system. The movements that were registered were flexo-extension, lateral flexion and rotation of the head.         Results. It is possible to emphasize the high influence of the variables age and sex in the movement ranges, in addition to the diminution of the ranges of mobility in patients affected of whiplash injury whose meaning also is very high.         Discusion. The methodology presented in the present work has been demonstrated as a useful tool for the functional valuation of the cervical spine mobility, improving the accuracy and the reliability of the obtained results and allowing making a rehabilitation treatment in a more effective and controlled way</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baydal-Bertomeu, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra-Añó, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Jaén, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dejoz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pascual, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matey, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La inexistencia de métodos objetivos, fiables y precisos de valoración funcional de la movilidad de la columna cervical dificulta la elección de un adecuado tratamiento rehabilitador y posterior control de su evolución en pacientes afectados de dolor cervical. Todo esto ha planteado la necesidad de desarrollar una nueva metodología de valoración de la movilidad cervical a partir de técnicas de vídeo-fotogrametría y de definición de los patrones de movilidad en función de las variables edad y género.         Material y métodos. Para la realización del estudio se ha seleccionado una muestra de 50 personas de edades comprendidas entre 20 y 79 años, con ausencia de patología cervical. También se ha realizado un estudio piloto con 14 personas afectadas de dolor cervical. El equipo de medida está basado en un sistema de video-fotogrametría. Los movimientos que se registraron fueron el de flexo-extensión, inclinación lateral y el de rotación de la cabeza.         Resultados. Cabe destacar la alta influencia de las variables edad y sexo en los rangos de movimiento, además de la disminución de los rangos de movilidad en los pacientes aquejados de latigazo cervical cuya significación también es muy alta.         Discusión. Se ha demostrado que la metodología presentada en el siguiente trabajo resulta una herramienta muy útil para la valoración funcional de la movilidad de la columna cervical, mejorando la precisión y la fiabilidad de los resultados obtenidos y permitiendo realizar un tratamiento rehabilitador de un modo más eficaz y controlado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);41(2): 53-60, mar.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057766</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de una nueva metodología para la valoración de la movilidad cervical basada en técnicas de fotogrametría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23420^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51780^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
