<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-20048</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurobiological relations and aging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Of the different aspects of a series of neurobiological changes that take place throughout the life cycle of an individual, in this paper we examine those involved in the aging process. These changes have been associated on different scales, including on a macroscopic level, that take into account variations in the shape, weight and volume of the brain and other encephalic structures. A part of the information about the weight seems to be incompatible and hence its incompatibility has been questioned and argued from a quantitative perspective. The functional option has been proposed as an alternative in the maintenance of normal brain functioning, as have changes on the microscopic scale in neuronal processes, the reduction in number of neurons in certain parts of the brain, which has also been questioned for the case of olfactory nerve fibres, and finally changes that take place on the molecular scale in the alteration of some neurotransmitters in certain parts, modifications suffered by mitochondrial enzymes and others that depend on the genome. These aspects have all been taken into consideration along with a resulting physiological relation in an attempt to gain a slightly more holistic, although still fragmented, view of the process, and to consider neoteny as an evolutionary strategy in the human species that serves to maintain brain functioning (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente artículo recoge, entre varios aspectos de una serie de cambios neurobiológicos que se realizan durante el ciclo vital, los que destacan hacia el proceso de envejecimiento, cambios que se han asociado en diversas escalas, pasando por la macroscópica, como las variaciones en la forma, peso y volumen del cerebro y de otras estructuras encefálicas. Parte de la información del peso parece incompatible, por lo que se discute y se argumenta su incompatibilidades de lo cuantitativo; se plantea la opción funcional como alternativa al mantenimiento de la actividad cerebral normal, los cambios en la escala microscópica en los procesos neuronales, la disminución en el número de neuronas en ciertas partes del encéfalo, que también se pone en duda para el caso de las fibras nerviosas olfatorias, y finalmente los cambios en la escala molecular en alteración de algunos neurotransmisores en ciertas partes, modificaciones enzimáticas mitocondriales y otras dependientes del genoma. Los aspectos indicados se han involucrado con una consecuente relación fisiológica, para tratar de tener una visión, además de fragmentada, un poco más holística de dicho proceso, y plantear la neotenia como una estrategia evolutiva en la especie humana para mantener la funcionalidad cerebral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(6): 549-554, mar. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones neurobiológicas y envejecimiento</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Duque Parra, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-20048</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d30577</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
