<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91443</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factor structure of the Spanish adaptation of Tarrant&#146;s Group Identification Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study, the factor structure of the Spanish version of Tarrant&#146;s Group Identification Scale is analyzed. This scale is based on the social identity theory and measures cognitive, evaluative, and affective aspects of group identification. Although this scale has been considered unidimensionally with adolescents, it is based on previous group identification scales considered multidimensionally. From confirmatory analysis, some factor models were tested in two independent samples of adolescents: Spanish (N= 1,795) and Mexican (N= 1,494). The three-factor model (self-categorization, group evaluation, and commitment to the group) produced the best fit in both samples. Results are compatible with the multidimensional structure hypothesis of group identification (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cava, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musitu, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buelga, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analiza la estructura factorial de la versión española de la Escala de Identificación Grupal de Tarrant. Esta escala está fundamentada en la Teoría de la Identidad Social y mide aspectos cognitivos, evaluativos y afectivos de la identificación grupal. Aunque esta escala ha sido considerada unidimensional al utilizarla con adolescentes, está basada en escalas de identificación grupal previas consideradas multidimensionales. Mediante análisis confirmatorios se contrastaron varios modelos factoriales en dos muestras independientes de adolescentes españoles (N= 1.795) y mexicanos (N= 1.494). En ambas muestras el modelo de tres factores (autocategorización, valoración grupal y compromiso grupal) es el que obtuvo mejores índices de ajuste. Los resultados son compatibles con la hipótesis de una estructura multidimensional de la identificación grupal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(4): 772-777, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91443</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estructura factorial de la adaptación española de la Escala de Identificación Grupal de Tarrant</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
