<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047726</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dependence in the elderly&#146;s voice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Elderly and dependence are frequently associated. They are a priority in the actual social politic.Objective: To examine the perception of dependence from the elderly. Methods: Phenomenological study with qualitative research of focus groups. Results: Dependence´s experience change with the personal attitude. Family is the most important relationship but at present is very difficult to take care the old people at home. Participants prefer to die and no suffer with pain.Conclusions: Is necessary to develop the skills to resolve problems associated with dependence: to train professionals and family in advance care planning and counselling</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón Lorda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Bello, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilarranz Redondo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascau González-Garzón, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Cantalejo, I. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La vejez y la dependencia aparecen con frecuencia asociadas. Son un objetivo prioritario de la política social actual.Objetivo: Conocer cómo es percibida la dependencia por la población mayor. Método: Estudio fenomenológico con metodología cualitativa de grupos de discusión. Resultados: La vivencia de dependencia se puede modelar con actitudes personales. La familia es la relación más importante, pero en la actualidad no puede cuidar de los mayores. Los participantes prefieren morir y no sufrir dolor.Conclusiones: Es necesario generar instrumentos para resolver problemas asociados a la dependencia: planificación de decisiones sanitarias y formación de familia y profesionales en técnicas de counselling</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);17(2): 66-74, jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La dependencia en el decir de los mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
