<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047055</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopic staging of low-grade gastric malt lymphoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: endoscopic ultrasonography (EUS) has already proven useful in the assessment of submucosal lesions, and the staging of gastrointestinal cancer, particularly gastric MALT-type lymphoma. The goal of this paper was EUS staging. Patients and method: 24 patients (10 females, 14 males) with a median age of 56 years and possibly gastric MALT lymphoma (25 cases) were studied using videoendoscopy, biopsies, and echoendoscopy with 7.5- and 20-MHz radial EUS, and also with 12- and 20-MHz miniprobes (MPs). Nineteen patients were definitely evaluated (7 females, 12 males) as having 20 MALT-type lymphomas, as five patients were post-hoc disregarded when an invasive, high-grade gastric lymphoma (3c) or plasmocytoma (2c) was subsequently demonstrated. Of these 19 patients, all had T1 lesions except for two with T2 lesions; one patient had a gastroduodenal T1 lymphoma. Echographic findings with MPs were compared to EUS (gold standard) and histology both before and after eradication. Then, patients were followed up every 1-3-6 months using videoendoscopy and MPs. Results: echoendoscopy correctly identified T stages in 90% of cases. MPs identified T stages in 88% of cases, and N stages in 33% of cases, with results being slightly inferior to those obtained with conventional EUS (91 vs. 45%); they were consequently used for follow-up. After eradication, all but two patients are in complete remission and have been followed every 1-3-6 months using MPs without echographic abnormalities, except for a patient who relapsed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Varas, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miquel, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabra, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinós, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turró, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bargalló, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la ultrasonografía endoscópica (USE) ha demostrado ya su utilidad en la evaluación de las lesiones submucosas, en la estadificación del cáncer digestivo en general, y del linfoma gástrico tipo MALT en particular. El objetivo de este trabajo fue la estadificación por USE. Pacientes y método: veinticuatro enfermos (10 mujeres y 14 varones) con edad media de 56 años y con posible linfoma gástrico tipo MALT (25 casos) fueron estudiados con videoendoscopia, biopsias y ecoendoscopia con USE radial de 7,5 y 20 MHz, y con minisondas (MS) de 12 y 20 MHz. Se evaluaron definitivamente 19 pacientes (7 mujeres y 12 varones) con 20 MALT, ya que cinco enfermos se desestimaron por demostrarse a posteriori que presentaban un linfoma gástrico invasivo de alto grado (3c) o un plasmocitoma (2c). De los 19 pacientes todos eran T1 menos dos pacientes que eran T2, y otra presentaba un linfoma T1 gastroduodenal. Los hallazgos ecográficos de las MS fueron comparados con la USE (gold standard) y con la histología antes y después de la erradicación. Después, fueron seguidos cada 1, 3 y 6 meses mediante videoendoscopia y MS. Resultados: la ecoendoscopia identificó el estadio T correcto en el 90% de los casos. Las MS identificaron el estadio T en el 88% de los casos y la N en el 33% de los casos, con resultados discretamente inferiores a los obtenidos con la USE convencional (91 y 45%), por lo que se utilizaron en el seguimiento. Después de la erradicación, todos menos dos están en remisión completa y han sido seguidos cada 1, 3 y 6 meses con las MS sin observar anomalías ecográficas, excepto una paciente que hizo una recidiva</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;98(3): 189-195, mar. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047055</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estadificación por ecoendoscopia en el linfoma gástrico tipo MALT de bajo grado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32160^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32160^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
