<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82504</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk factors associated with eating disorders in Mexican preadolescents with normal weight</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to identify the differences in body self-esteem, general self-esteem and eating attitudes in a representative sample of children, aged 9-12 years, attending school in México DF. The logistic regression model incorporated the variables of sex, general self-esteem, BMI, age and discrepancy between the perceived image and the ideal image. Participants with an increased risk of eating disorders were girls: a) with less general self-esteem; b) BMI at the upper range of normal weight; c) greater negative discrepancy between perceived and ideal image; d) aged 11-12 years. Higher general selfesteem would act as a protector for eating disorders, while the desire for a thinner ideal body would be a risk factor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trujano Ruiz, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limón Arce, gilberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nava Quiróz, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcó Arbonès, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia Blanco, Manuel de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tuvo como objetivo identificar las diferencias en autoestima corporal, autoestima general y actitudes hacia la alimentación en una muestra representativa de niños/as de 9-12 años escolarizados en México DF. El modelo de regresión logística incorporó las variables sexo, autoestima general, IMC, edad y discrepancia entre la imagen percibida y la ideal. Los participantes con un mayor riesgo de presentar TCA fueron niñas con: a) una menor autoestima general; b) un IMC en la franja alta del intervalo de normopeso; c) una mayor discrepancia negativa entre la imagen percibida y la ideal; y d) de edades comprendidas entre los 11-12 años. Una mayor autoestima general actuaría como un factor protector de los TCA, mientras que el deseo de tener un cuerpo ideal más delgado que el real sería un factor de riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(4): 581-586, 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de riesgo asociados a los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria en preadolescentes mexicanos con normopeso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50330</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
