<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78055</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dengue: An emergent disease in our community</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Dengue is an emergent viral disease worldwide. It isthe result of infection with virus dengue serotypes 1-4, whichtransmission is through an arthropod vector of the Aedes genus. Itis a rare disease in our community, but immigration and touristictrips to endemic areas are resulting in an increase in its incidence.The lack of knowledge about this infection among health careproviders in our environment may result in delays in diagnosis.Clinical Observation. Herein we present and discuss a case of denguein a 10 year-old girl. On the first day after a 4-week trip to Colombia,the girl presented to our hospital with high fever, generalizederythrodermia with hypochromic areas, abdominal pain,hepatomegaly, and multiple lymphadenopathies. Diagnostic studiesrevealed mild hemoconcentration (hematocrit 43%), bicytopenia(total leukocyte count 3,700/mmm3 and platelet count69,900/mm3), with mild elevation of liver enzymes (AST 234 IU/L,ALT 122 IU/L). Serology to dengue virus was positive (IgM and IgG).The patient experienced progressive clinical improvement and wasdischarged home after 5 days.Commentary. Dengue should be considered in the differentialdiagnosis of febrile illness in patients arriving from endemic areas.Even though our imported case of dengue had a very favorableoutcome, more severe forms of the disease may occur. Those formsare typically caused by sequential infections by different viral serotypes.Clinical and laboratory criteria to recognize the severeforms of the infection have been proposed by the WHO; however,those criteria must be validated. The development of a vaccine isin progress; however, the most effective prevention is the implementationof prophylactic measures against the mosquito bite(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portolani, Nicola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tobeña, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armangué, Thaís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll, Francis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moraga-Llop, Ferran A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El dengue es actualmente una de las principalesenfermedades virales emergentes a escala mundial. Causado porel virus dengue (VDEN), serotipos 1-4, presenta transmisión inter-Dengue. Una malaltia emergent també al nostremediThaís Armangué 1, Nicola Portolani 1, Francis Coll 1, Marc Tobeña 1, Ferran A. Moraga-Llop 21 Servei de Pediatria. 2 Unitat de Malalties Infeccioses i Immunodeficiències Pediàtriques. Hospital Universitari Vall d'Hebron.Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona. Barcelonahumana a través del vector artrópodo del género Aedes. Aunqueen nuestro medio es una enfermedad poco frecuente, los fenómenosmigratorios y los viajes turísticos a zonas endémicas estánaumentando su incidencia. La experiencia en nuestro medio todavíaes escasa, de modo que esto puede retrasar su diagnóstico.Observación clínica. Presentamos un caso de dengue importado enuna niña de 10 años. Recién llegada de un viaje a Colombia, presentabafiebre alta, eritrodermia generalizada con máculashipocrómicas, dolor abdominal, hepatomegalia y adenopatías múltiples.Analítica general: bicitopenia (leucopenia 3.700/mm3 conlimfomonocitosis; plaquetopenia 69.900/mm3), leve hemoconcentración(Ht 43%) y aumento de las transaminasas (AST 234 UI/L, ALT122 UI/L). Serología IgM e IgG positivas al VDEN. Mejoría clínica yanalítica progresiva hasta remisión completa al quinto día.Comentarios. Debemos considerar el dengue en la evaluación delos pacientes febriles llegados recientemente de países endémicos.Presentamos un caso importado que evolucionó favorablemente,aunque debemos recordar que se trata de una enfermedad potencialmentegrave. Actualmente se discute la idoneidad de los criteriospropuestos por la OMS para identificar las formas más gravesfrecuentemente propiciadas por infecciones secuenciales deserotipos heterólogos del virus...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;69(5): 250-253, sept.-oct. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78055</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dengue. Una enfermedad emergente también en nuestro medio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3727^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3727^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3727^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
