<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036204</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Renal transplantation in patients with HIV infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The prevalence of human immunodeficience virus (HIV) infection among patients under renal replacement therapy varies, with estimates of 1% for Europe and 1.5% for the United States. Survival in HIV infected individuals receiving renal replacement therapy has improved since the introduction of high activity antiretroviral therapy (HAART). Current experience in renal transplantation in HIV-infected patients in the United States indicates that the three-year survival rate is similar to that of HIV-negative transplant recipients, with virological and immunological control of the infection by HAART and no increase in the number of opportunistic infections or tumors. The criteria for selecting renal transplantation candidates in this population are the following: no aids-defining events, CD4 cells &gt; 200 cells/&amp;#956;l and undetectable viral load under HAART. In Spain, where most of these patients are former drug abusers, a two-year period of abstinence from cocaine and heroine abuse is also required, although patients can be participating in the methadone program. The main problems in the post-transplantation period have been interactions between HAART and immunosuppressive drugs, management of hepatitis C virus (HCV) coinfection and the high rate of acute rejection. To date, seven such renal transplantations have been performed in Spain, with favorable patient and graft survival and no progression to aids (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miró, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgos, Francisco-Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oppenheimer, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trullás, Joan-Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tuset, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre-Cisneros, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazuecos, Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barril, Guillermina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Vijande, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La prevalencia de la infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) en pacientes en terapia renal sustitutiva (TRS) es muy variable, pero de forma global se estima que en Europa es del 1% y en Estados Unidos del 1,5%. La supervivencia de estos pacientes en TRS también ha mejorado notablemente con la introducción de tratamiento antirretroviral de gran actividad (TARGA). La experiencia acumulada en la era del TARGA en trasplante renal en pacientes infectados por el VIH en Estados Unidos indica que la supervivencia a los 3 años es similar a la de los pacientes sin infección por el VIH, con un buen control virológico e inmunológico de la infección por el VIH bajo TARGA y sin presentar mayor número de infecciones oportunistas y/o tumores. Los criterios de selección de pacientes infectados por el VIH que han utilizado los diferentes grupos de trasplante han sido: ausencia de manifestaciones oportunistas previas, tener una cifra de linfocitos CD41 superior a 200 cél./&amp;#956;l y una carga viral del VIH suprimible con TARGA. En España, donde la mayoría de pacientes eran antiguos drogadictos, para el trasplante hepático se exigiría además una abstinencia de heroína y cocaína de 2 años de duración, y el paciente podía estar en el programa de metadona. Los principales problemas detectados en el período postrasplante son las interacciones farmacocinéticas y farmacodinámicas entre los antirretrovirales y los inmunosupresores, el manejo de la coinfección por el virus de la hepatitis C y la elevada tasa de rechazo. En España se han realizado hasta la fecha siete trasplantes renales, con buena evolución del paciente y del injerto y sin progresión de la infección por el VIH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;23(6): 363-374, jun.-jul. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036204</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trasplante renal en pacientes infectados por el VIH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6235^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6235^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3982^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3982^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
