<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049572</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health habits, and health beliefs among physicians and medical students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Data availableon health habits and health beliefs in Spanish medical population is scarce. The objectiveof this study was to explore some health habits (i.e., tobacco and alcohol consume) aswell as the knowledge and beliefs regarding those habits among physicians and medicalstudents. The sample was 147 participants from various hospitals in Spain. A questionnairespecifically designed for this study was used to obtain data about the target variables.Results show that 47,6% of participants are smokers, and 71,7% inform to be alcoholconsumers. A positive relation between age and frequency of consumption was found inboth habits. Participants demonstrate to have an adequate level of knowledge and beliefsin relation to the risks for health that the use of tobacco and alcohol entails, contrastingclearly with their consumption patterns. The health habits of this sample do not differfrom those founded in the general population, even though participants show a correctlevel of knowledge and beliefs on these habits, thus emphasizing the lack of correspondencebetween health knowledge, beliefs and health habits</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Roales-Nieto, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Coronado, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno San Pedro, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los datos sobre hábitos y creencias de salud de la población médica española son escasos.Este estudio tiene como objetivo explorar, en una muestra de médicos y estudiantesde Medicina, los hábitos de salud (consumo de tabaco y alcohol) y los conocimientos ycreencias sobre los mismos. La muestra se compuso por 147 participantes de distintoshospitales de España. Se utilizó un cuestionario diseñado para recabar información sobrelas variables estudiadas. Los resultados indicaron que el 47,6% eran fumadores y el71,7% consumidores de alcohol, encontrándose una relación positiva entre edad y frecuenciade consumo en ambos casos. Los participantes mostgraron un adecuado nivel deconocimientos y creencias respecto a los riesgos para la salud del consumo de tabaco yalcohol, que contrasta claramente con sus hábitos de consumo. Los hábitos de salud enla muestra no difieren de los encontrados en la población general, si bien el nivel deconocimientos y creencias es más preciso. Destaca la falta de correspondencia entrecreencias y conocimientos en salud y los hábitos de salud</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);6(1): 99-110, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábitos y creencias de salud en médicos y estudiantes de Medicina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11252^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
