<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110389</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Asthma crisis in emergency departments in Spain: what is our usual practice?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Despite there being various guidelines and consensus statements on asthma, great variability still exists in its treatment approach; although this has been little discussed in Emergency Departments (ED). Objective: To describe the usual management of asthma exacerbations in Spanish ED, and to determine the degree of variability among different professionals, as well as analyse factors that may influence their management. Material and methods: A questionnaire was developed based on clinical cases, which was distributed among members of the Spanish Society of Paediatric Emergencies and attendees at the meeting in 2011. Results: A total of 300 surveys were analysed. In 190 cases the place of work was in a tertiary care hospital. There was high agreement in the assessment of the severity of the cases mentioned. Over 90% use inhaled beta 2 agonists in mild asthma exacerbations, 75.3% used oral corticosteroids in moderate exacerbations, and 79% use ipratropium bromide in severe exacerbations. Almost all (98%) considered Therapeutic Education important in the Emergency Department. Only 8 (2.7%) used peak expiratory flow measurements. Respondents working in a tertiary hospital used severity scales more frequently (90.5% vs 80%, P=0.009) and administered parenteral corticosteroids less frequently (53.2% vs 66.4%, P=0.017). Conclusions: Although a high percentage of paediatricians working in the ED follow Clinical Practice Guidelines, some different points of the approach among professionals have been identified(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Echániz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bilbao Meseguer, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Korta Murua, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde-Molina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sotoca Fernández, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Claret Teruel, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: A pesar de la existencia de múltiples guías y documentos de consenso sobre el asma, persiste todavía una gran variabilidad en su abordaje, situación poco analizada en los Servicios de Urgencias (SU). Objetivo: Describir el manejo habitual de las crisis asmáticas en los SU españoles, conocer el grado de variabilidad entre sus diferentes profesionales y analizar los factores que pueden influir en su manejo. Material y métodos: Se elaboró un cuestionario, basado en supuestos clínicos, que se distribuyó entre los socios de la Sociedad Española de Urgencias de Pediatría y asistentes a la reunión en 2011. Resultados: Se analizan 300 encuestas. En 190 casos, el lugar de trabajo habitual es un hospital de tercer nivel. Existe una alta coincidencia en la valoración de la gravedad de los casos. Más del 90% utiliza beta 2 agonistas inhalados en la crisis asmática leve, el 75,3% utiliza corticoides orales en crisis moderadas y el 79% utiliza bromuro de ipratropio en las crisis graves. El 98% considera importante hacer educación terapéutica en los SU. Solo 8 (2,7%) utilizan la medición del pico de flujo espiratorio máximo. Los encuestados que trabajan en un hospital de tercer nivel utilizan con más frecuencia escalas de gravedad (90,5% vs. 80%, p = 0,009) y administran corticoides parenterales con menos frecuencia (53,2% vs. 66,4%, p = 0,017). Conclusiones: Aunque un porcentaje elevado de pediatras que trabajan en los SU siguen las guías de práctica clínica, se han detectado aspectos en los que el abordaje del asma es discordante entre los diferentes profesionales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);78(4): 216-226, abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110389</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Crisis asmática en los servicios de urgencias en Espa&#152;na, ¿cuál es nuestra práctica habitual?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13610^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
