<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113875</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The association of adherence to a mediterranean diet during early pregnancy and the risk of gastroschisis in the offspring</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. The aim of this study was to study the association of adherence to the Mediterranean diet in early pregnancy maternal and the offspring&#146;s risk of gastroschisis. Methods. Case-control study. We describe 11 cases of gastroschisis in the region of Murcia from 2007 to 2012 and 34 concurrent controls. At the time of diagnosis each of the cases completed a validated Food Frequency Questionnaire (FFQ) consisting of 98 items on the periconceptional diet. Confounding factors: smoking, exposure to cannabis / marihuana, age of the parents, BMI, income and educational level. We conducted a descriptive and multivariate logistic regression statistical analysis.Results. Mothers of children with gastroschisis were younger (20.8 years, 95% CI 17.3 to 24.2) and their diet consisted of less caloric intake, saturated fat and monounsaturated fats and proteins than controls. The Odds Ratio (OR) in the multivariate model controlling for confounding factors: maternal age (year) 0.70 (95% CI 0.51 to 0.96), monounsaturated fatty acids (oleic acid, g) 0.79 (95% CI 0.65 to 0, 97) and vegetable intake (rations/week) 0.70 (95% CI 0.48 to 1.00).Conclusion. A maternal diet rich in oleic acid and vegetable products may prevent vascular risk of onphalomesenteric arteries reducing the risk of gastroschisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de Investigación Translacional sobre Gastrosquisis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. El objetivo de este estudio fue estudiar la asociación de la adherencia a la dieta mediterránea materna al inicio del embarazo y el riesgo de gastrosquisis en la descendencia. Métodos. Estudio de casos-control. 11 casos incidentes de gastrosquisis en la Región de Murcia de 2007 a 2012 y 34 controles concurrentes. Cuestionario validado de Frecuencia Alimentaria (CFA) sobre la dieta periconcepcional de 98 ítems realizado &#145;cara a cara&#146; en el momento del diagnóstico. Factores confundidores: tabaquismo, exposición a cannabis/marihuana, edad materna y paterna, índice de masa corporal, ingresos económicos y nivel de estudios. Estudio descriptivo y regresión logística multivariable. Resultados. Las madres de niños con gastrosquisis son más jóvenes (20,8 años; IC 95% 17,3-24,2) y su dieta tiene un menor aporte calórico, de grasas saturadas y monoinsaturadas y de proteínas que los controles. Odds Ratio (OR) en el modelo multivariable controlado por los factores confundidores: edad materna (años) 0,70 (IC95% 0,51-0,96); ácidos grasos monoinsaturados (oleico, g) 0,79 (IC95% 0,65-0,97) y consumo de vegetales (raciones/semana) 0,70 (IC95% 0,48-1,00).Conclusiones. Una dieta materna rica en ácido oleico y productos vegetales podría contribuir a prevenir el riesgo de oclusión vascular de las arterias onfalomesentéricas, disminuyendo el riesgo de gastrosquisis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;26(1): 37-43, ene. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación de la adherencia a la dieta mediterránea al inicio del embarazo y riesgo de gastrosquisis en la descendencia: un estudio de casos-controles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52505</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33760^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
