<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041847</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-3465</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Glucose tolerance impairment in cystic fibrosis. Should we detect earlier?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Carbohydrate metabolism (CM) alterationsin cystic fibrosis (CF) show up graduallyand have been associated with clinical impairment.They are considered a late manifestation, so its follow-up is usually done since the second decade inlife.Objective. The aims of our study were to assesscarbohydrate metabolism (CM) on paediatric CF populationand to detect how early established was itsimpairment, and if it&#146;s correlated to clinical deterioration.Material and methods. 17 patients less than 16years old with CF were studied. A nutritional andrespiratory assessment was made. CM was studiedthrough an oral glucose tolerance test and patientswere classified according to current criteria, comparingclinical situation among different groups.Results. Mean age was 9,3 ± 4,2 year old. Sixpatients (35,3%) showed glucose tolerance impairment, with 4 under 10 years. No diabetes mellitus(DM) was found in any of them. No significant differenceswere found in clinical situation among patientswith normal or abnormal glucose tolerance.Conclusions. Glucidic alterations may appear inCF patients under 10, therefore CM should be studiedbefore this age to detect its impairment andapply the appropriate follow-up. Among pediatric populationabnormal glucose tolerance without DM seemsnot related to clinical deterioration</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bousoño García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Curros Novo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas Crespo, F, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Hernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández González, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero-Morín, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las alteraciones del metabolismoglucídico (MG) en la fibrosis quística (FQ) se producende manera progresiva y se han asociado a deterioroclínico. Se consideran una manifestación tardíade la enfermedad por lo que su seguimiento serealiza habitualmente desde la segunda década dela vida.Objetivo. Este estudio pretende valorar la situacióndel MG en FQ en edad pediátrica, determinarla edad a partir de la cual aparecen alteracionesglucídicas y si se correlacionan con deterioro clínicoa esa edad.Material y métodos. Se estudiaron 17 pacientesmenores de 16 años diagnosticados de FQ. Se realizóuna valoración nutricional y respiratoria. El MGse estudió a través de un test de sobrecarga oral deglucosa (TSOG), clasificando a los pacientes segúnlos criterios actuales y comparando la situación clínicaen los diferentes grupos de tolerancia glucídica.Resultados. La edad media de los pacientes fue9,3 ± 4,2 años. Seis pacientes (35,3%) presentabantolerancia anormal, siendo 4 de ellos menores de10 años. Ningún paciente presentó diabetes mellitus(DM). No se encontraron diferencias significativasen la situación clínica entre los pacientes contolerancia normal y anormal.Conclusiones. Las alteraciones glucídicas en laFQ pueden aparecer en enfermos menores de 10años, por lo que podría ser necesario estudiar elMG a una edad más temprana para detectarlas precozmentey realizar un seguimiento oportuno.En población pediátrica la tolerancia anormal a laglucosa sin DM no parece relacionarse con una peorsituación clínica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediátrika (Madr.);25(10): 409-415, nov. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041847</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteración de la tolerancia glucídica en la fibrosis quística, ¿debería detectarse antes?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31437^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31437^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
