<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74623</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orthognathic surgery and rhinoplasty in Binder syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Binder syndrome is a disorder characterized bynasomaxillary hypoplasia that results in a short nose, a frontonasalangle of almost 180 degrees, hypoplasia of the frontal sinuses, anabsent anterior nasal spine, a short columella and an acute nasolabialangle. The patient can be treated orthodontically or surgicallydepending on the seriousness of the malformation. We review theliterature on the etiology, differential diagnosis and treatment ofBinder syndrome. We present the case of a boy with this syndromesurgically treated with orthognatic surgery and rhinoplasty with anL-shaped rib cartilage graft(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tito, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Binder es una patología caracterizada por hipoplasianariz-maxilar, ángulo naso-frontal plano, senos frontales hipoplasicos,ausencia de la espina nasal anterior, columela corta y ángulo nasolabialagudo. El tratamiento del los pacientes con síndome de Binder puedeser ortodóntico o quirúrgico según la gravedad de la malformación. En estetrabajo hemos realizado una revision bibliográfica sobre la etiología, el diagnósticodiferential y el tratamiento de la sindrome de Binder y presentamosun caso clínico de un paciente binderiano sometido a intervención decirugía ortognática y rinoplastia con injerto de cartílago costal para recostruirel dorso y la punta nasal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;29(2): 109-116, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74623</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía ortognática y rinoplastia en el síndrome de Binder</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33348^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
