<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136870</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vertebral osteornyelitis and epidural abscess after epidural anesthesia for a cesarean section</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 40-year-old woman underwent cesarean section under epidural anesthesia. The anesthetic procedure was carried out in strict aseptic conditions, the catheter was withdrawn 24 hours after surgery, and the patient was discharged 5 days after surgery. She was readmitted with fever, backache, and pain in the lower limbs, with signs of radiculitis but no indication of inflammation or pain at the site of puncture. Magnetic resonance imaging revealed vertebral osteomyelitis at the fifth lumbar and first sacral vertebrae and an epidural abscess with compression of the nerve root. Treatment consisted of 2 g of ceftriaxone daily for 6 weeks, rest, and measures to assure local immobilization. Symptoms gradually improved and no surgical drainage measures were needed. The cause of osteomyelitis was never ascertained. Vertebral osteomyelitis is an unusual event after epidural anesthesia and there have been few opportunities to demonstrate a relationship. Such infections appear spontaneously in immunodepressed patients who undergo diagnostic procedures and treatments that lead to bacteremias with secondary colonization of spinal structures. The topography and characteristics of the infectious lesion, the patient's susceptibility, and the anesthetic procedure and pathogenic agent may help clarify the cause of the osteomyelitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Veiga Sánchez, AR</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A una paciente de 40 años se le practicó una cesárea bajo anestesia epidural. La técnica anestésica se realizó en perfectas condiciones de asepsia y el catéter se retiró a las 24 horas, siendo dada de alta a los 5 días. Reingresó por fiebre, dolor lumbar y en miembros inferiores, con elementos de radiculitis pero sin signos inflamatorios ni dolor en el sitio de punción. La resonancia magnética mostró una osteomielitis vertebral L5-S1 y un absceso epidural con compresión radicular. El tratamiento consistió en 2 g de ceftriaxona diarios durante seis semanas, reposo y medidas de inmovilización local, evolucionando lentamente hacia la mejoría parcial de su sintomatología. No requirió drenaje quirúrgico del foco. No se logró identificar claramente el agente causal. La osteomielitis vertebral tras una anestesia epidural es un proceso excepcional y en pocas oportunidades se ha demostrado una relación causal entre ambas. Suelen ser infecciones de aparición espontánea en pacientes inmunodeprimidos sometidos a intrumentaciones diagnósticas y terapéuticas que determinan bacteriemias con colonización secundaria de estructuras del raquis. La topografía y características de la lesión infecciosa, los factores predisponentes en el paciente y el procedimiento anestésico y el agente causal pueden ayudar al momento de aclarar su etiopatogenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;51(1): 44-46, ene. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteomielitis vertebral y absceso epidural tras anestesia epidural para una cesárea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34159^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8334</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5017^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12823</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d784</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
