<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99360</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of limping patients in Rheumatology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Limping is a frequent reason for consultation. Our aim is to describe the characteristics of patients who limp and are evaluated in Rheumatology. Material and Methods: Cross-sectional study from October 2009 to June 2010. Variables included: epidemiological data, clinical symptoms and laboratory and imaging tests. Results: A total of 95 patients were studied and classified into four groups according to their diagnosis, inflammatory 22%, infectious 17%, transient hip synovitis 13%, and miscellaneous 48%. There were differences between groups in age (P&lt;0.0001) and arthritis (P&lt;0.0001). In this population, the probability of an infectious/inflammatory limp fulfils the criteria &#147;less than 3 years and fever&#148; was 79% and reached 100% if it was also associated with arthritis. Conclusions: Clinical evaluation and in particular, age, fever and arthritis seem to be the most relevant data in differentiating infectious/inflammation diagnosis in the child who limps(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Murias, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Remesal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiles, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La cojera es un motivo de consulta frecuente. Nuestro objetivo es describir las características de los niños con cojera valorados en Reumatología. Material y Métodos: Estudio de corte transversal desde octubre de 2009 a junio de 2010. Las variables incluyeron: datos epidemiológicos, síntomas clínicos y pruebas de laboratorio e imagen. Resultados: Los 95 pacientes se clasificaron en cuatro grupos de acuerdo con su diagnóstico, inflamatorio 22%, infeccioso 17%, sinovitis transitoria de cadera 13% y miscelánea 48%. Había diferencias entre grupos en la edad (p&lt;0,0001) y la artritis (p&lt;0,0001). En esta población, la probabilidad de presentar una cojera infecciosa/inflamatoria cumpliendo el criterio «menos de 3 años y fiebre» fue del 79% y alcanzó el 100% si además se asociaba artritis. Conclusiones: La evaluación clínica y en particular la edad, la fiebre y la artritis parecen ser los datos más relevantes para diferenciar el diagnóstico de infección/inflamación en el niño que cojea(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);76(5): 290-293, mayo 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de los pacientes con cojera en Reumatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5823^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
