<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116914</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk of eating disorders, consumption of addictive substances and emotional difficulties in adolescent girls</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to estimate the prevalence of risk of developing eating disorders in a sample of 767 adolescent girls aged between 16 and 20, and to study the differences between adolescent girls at high risk and low risk of developing eating disorders in relation to different variables (sociodemographic, anthropometric, body image perception, overvaluation of thinness, substance consumption, alexithymia and anxiety). The prevalence of adolescent girls at high risk was found to be 15%. The results revealed that weight, BMI, body image perception and overvaluation of thinness were key factors in adolescent girls at high risk of developing eating disorders. Also, a higher percentage of at high risk adolescent girls smoked, had tried synthetic drugs and started drinking alcohol at a younger age. Higher levels of alexithymia and anxiety were also found in at-risk adolescents. These results suggest that, in addition to nutritional education and information about the effects of internalizing the thin ideal on adolescent personalities, eating disorders prevention programs should also include techniques for expressing and regulating emotions, in order to prevent young girls from turning to inappropriate weight and body image control behaviors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Sáez, María S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Etxebarria, Itziar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Aitziber</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echeburúa, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo fue estimar la prevalencia de riesgo de trastorno de la conducta alimentaria en una muestra de 767 mujeres de 16 a 20 años, así como estudiar las diferencias entre las adolescentes de alto y bajo riesgo en diferentes variables (sociodemográficas, antropométricas, percepción de la imagen corporal, sobrevaloración de la delgadez, consumo de sustancias, alexitimia y ansiedad). La prevalencia de mujeres adolescentes de alto riesgo fue del 15%. Según los resultados obtenidos, el peso, el índice de masa corporal, la percepción de la imagen corporal y la sobrevaloración de la delgadez eran factores relevantes en las adolescentes con alto riesgo de trastorno alimentario. Asimismo un mayor porcentaje de adolescentes de alto riesgo fumaban, habían probado drogas de síntesis y habían empezado antes a consumir alcohol. También se obtuvieron mayores niveles de alexitimia y ansiedad en estas adolescentes de alto riesgo. Estos resultados sugieren que la prevención de los trastornos alimentarios debería incluir, además de educación nutricional e información sobre el efecto nocivo de la interiorización del ideal de delgadez extrema imperante, técnicas de expresión y regulación emocional a fin de que no tengan que recurrir a conductas inadecuadas de control del peso y de la imagen corporal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;29(3): 724-733, sept.-dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116914</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de trastorno de la conducta alimentaria, consumo de sustancias adictivas y dificultades emocionales en chicas adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
