<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038621</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Isolation of Candida dubliniensis in a teenager with denture stomatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Test several methods that allow the differentiation between Candida albicans and Candida dubliniensis, in an attempt to assess whether C. dubliniensis can be recovered from the oral cavity of teenagers wearing orthopedic oral prostheses. Material and Methods: Twelve Candida strains were isolated from the prosthesis as well as the palatal mucosa in contact with the dental prosthesis from 12 teenager patients wearing orthopedic oral prostheses. Differentiation between C. albicans and C. dubliniensis was achieved by a number of phenotypictests (carbon assimilation by the commercially available ID32C test, growth at 45ºC on Sabouraud glucose agar, abundant chlamydospore production on Casein agar, and reactivity with a C. dubliniensis antiserum) and the polymerase chain reaction(PCR). Serotyping of C. albicans was performed with monoclonalantibody B9E. Results: All 12 patients studied presented a Newton`s type 2 denture stomatitis and in every patient the same Candida species were isolated from the prosthesis and the palatal mucosa in contact with the dental prosthesis. CHRO Magar Candida and the germ tube test allowed the differentiation of isolates giving green colonies and a positive germ tube test from those giving violet colonies and a negative germ tube test. Only the isolate from patient 8 was stained by the C. dubliniensis antiserum and showed abundant chlamydospore production on Casein agar. Eight isolates did not grow at 45 ºC. Identification of all isolates was obtained by the ID 32C test. C. albicans was identified in 75% of patients, C. glabrata in 16,6% and C. dubliniensis in 8,3%. By using specific primers for typing C. dubliniensis, PCRallowed the identification of patient´s 8 isolate as C. dubliniensisgenotype 1. Conclusion: C. dubliniensis can be isolated from the oral cavity of teenagers wearing orthopedic oral prostheses and it is possible and technically amenable, the differentiation between C.albicans y C. dubliniensis using the ID 32C test, the observation of abundant chlamydospore production on Casein agar, there activity with a C. dubliniensis antiserum and the PCR</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mosca, Christian Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brena, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moragues, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pontón, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa, Alcira Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Utilizar varios métodos que permiten la diferenciación entre Candida albicans y Candida dubliniensis en un intento deconocer si C. dubliniensis puede ser aislada de la cavidad oral de adolescentes con prótesis ortopédicas orales. Materiales y métodos: Se aislaron 12 cepas de género Candida procedentes de mucosa palatina y de soporte de prótesis de 12 pacientes adolescentes portadores de prótesis ortopédicas orales. Para la diferenciación entre C. albicans y C. dubliniensis se utilizaron varias pruebas fenotípicas (la asimilación de fuentesde carbono con el método comercial ID 32C, el crecimiento enagar glucosado de Sabouraud a 45 ºC, la producción abundante de clamidosporas en agar caseína, y la reactividad mediante inmunofluorescencia indirecta con un antisuero específico para C. dubliniensis) y la reacción en cadena de la polimerasa(PCR). El serotipado de C. albicans se realizó con el anticuerpo monoclonal B9E. Resultados: Los 12 pacientes estudiados presentaron una estomatitis protésica tipo 2 de Newton y en todos los casos se aislaron las mismas especies de la muestra de mucosa y de la de prótesis del mismo paciente. El CHRO Magar Candida y la prueba de la filamentación en suero permitieron diferenciar los aislamientos que daban lugar a colonias de color verde y filamentaban de los que daban colonias violetas y no lo hacían. Unicamente el aislamiento del paciente 8 fue positivo con el antisuero específico para C. dubliniensis y produjo abundantes clamidosporas en agar caseína, mientras que ocho aislamientos no presentaron crecimiento a 45 ºC. La identificación de todos los aislamientos se consiguió con la prueba ID 32C, identificándose C. albicans en el75% de los pacientes, C. glabrata en el 16,6% y C. dubliniensis en el 8,3%. La PCR con iniciadores específicos para el tipadode C. dubliniensis permitió la identificación del aislamiento del paciente 8 como C. dubliniensis genotipo 1. Conclusión: C. dubliniensis puede ser aislada de la cavidad oral de adolescentes con estomatitis asociada a prótesis ortopédicas y es posible, y técnicamente asequible, la diferenciación entre C. albicans y C. dubliniensis mediante la realización de pruebas como el ID 32C, la observación de abundantes clamidosporas en agar caseína, la reactividad con un antisuero específico para C. dubliniensis y la PCR</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(1): 25-31, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038621</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aislamiento de Candida dubliniensis en un adolescente con estomatitis protésica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13670^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
