<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80315</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison ofnon-fatal occupational in juries by autonomous communities in Spain (1994&#150;2004)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesGiven the differences observed in previous studies with respect to occupational injury rates in Spain's autonomous communities, this study tested the homogeneity hypothesis of occupational injury for specific accident types and economic activity between 1994 and 2004.MethodsWe analyzed non-fatal injuries of a mechanical nature or those due to overexertion taking place in manufacturing or construction companies during the workday and requiring sick leave. The relative risk was adjusted for sex, age and contract type in each autonomous community using standardized injury causes for occupational injury, employing Spanish rates as a reference and stratifying by duration of leave (less than 16 days and more than 15 days).ResultsFor the different types of accidents analyzed, the adjusted relative risk of occupational injury was heterogeneously distributed across the autonomous communities. Murcia, Navarre, the Balearic Islands and the Basque Country were generally found to be amongst the communities with the most elevated risks, while Castilla-León and Extremadura were those with the lowest risks of occupational injury.ConclusionsThe heterogeneity of occupational injury rates across autonomous communities persisted after selecting a series of specific accident types and adjusting for sex, age and contract type. Therefore, in addition to continued analysis of work conditions to explain this variation, other socioeconomic factors should be taken into account when comparing occupational injury rates among autonomous communities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Ruiz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavides, Fernando G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castejón, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosDadas las diferencias observadas en estudios previos de la incidencia de lesiones por accidente de trabajo (LAT) por Comunidades Autónomas (CC.AA.), en este estudio hemos evaluado la hipótesis de homogeneidad de la incidencia de las LAT para tipos específicos de accidentes y en determinadas actividades, entre 1994 y 2004.MétodosLas LAT analizadas fueron no mortales con baja, de tipo mecánico y sobreesfuerzo, ocurridas en jornada en centro para empresas manufactureras y de la construcción. Se calculó el riesgo relativo ajustado por sexo, edad y tipo de contrato en cada una de las CC.AA. mediante la razón de LAT estandarizada, tomando como referencia las tasas de España, y estratificando según duración de la baja (menos de 16 días y más de 15 días).ResultadosEl riesgo relativo ajustado de LAT según los diferentes tipos de accidentes analizados presenta una distribución heterogénea entre CC.AA. Murcia, Navarra, Baleares y País Vasco se encuentran generalmente entre las comunidades con riesgos más elevados, mientras que Castilla-León y Extremadura son las que tienen principalmente menores riesgos de sufrir una LAT.ConclusionesLa heterogeneidad en la incidencia de LAT entre CC.AA. persiste después de seleccionar una serie de formas de accidente específicas y ajustar por sexo, edad y tipo de contrato. Por ello sugerimos que, además de seguir analizando las condiciones de trabajo como explicación de esta heterogeneidad, se tengan en cuenta otras variables socioeconómicas al comparar las incidencias de LAT entre CC.AA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(6): 489-495, dic. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de las lesiones no mortales por accidente de trabajo por Comunidades Autónomas en España (1994&#150;2004)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23892^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
