<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040103</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In the last years seem to be an increasing interest in the topics related to health in the overall population. The objective of this study is to describe the evolution and availability of the Spanish editorial about publications related to health as an indicator of the interest of the population to these topics. Method: A descriptive transverse study of all the printed publications about health using Ariadna Data base -it contains all the bibliographic catalogs from the Spanish National Library. Results: Of the 6.340 books, 51.7% were divulgative. Those of commercial origin represent 87.5% and 12.5% the institutional ones. The more frequent topics were nutrition (22.6%), weight loss (13.3%), health education (11.3%) and sexual issues 11.3%). Conclusions: At present exits a great offer that has been increased over the last years. The institutional production has focussed their offer in drug addiction, AIDS and tobacco/alcohol. A discrepancy exists among what is demanded by the population, specially on topics related with the quality of life, and what is offered by the institutions about risks factors</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ronda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En los últimos años se observa un incremento del interés sobre temas de salud en la población general española. El objetivo de este trabajo es describir la evolución y disponibilidad de la oferta editorial española de obras divulgativas sobre salud como un indicador del interés de la población hacia estos temas. Método: Estudio descriptivo transversal de las publicaciones divulgativas impresas sobre salud, usando como fuente de información la base de datos Ariadna que recoge los fondos de la Biblioteca Nacional de España. Resultados: De las 6.340 obras, 3.278 (51,7%) fueron divulgativas. Las de origen comercial representan el 87,5% y el 12.5%, las institucionales. Los temas más frecuentes fueron: alimentación (22,6%), adelgazamiento (13,3%), educación sanitaria (11,3%) y sexual (11,3%).Conclusiones: Existe una gran oferta de obras incrementada en los últimos años a expensas de editoriales comerciales. La producción institucional ha centrado su oferta en drogadicción, sida y tabaco/alcohol. Existe una discrepancia entre lo demandado por la población, sobre temas relacionados con la calidad de vida, y lo ofertado por las instituciones que se centran en factores de riesgo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;11(1): 32-36, ene.-mar. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040103</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La divulgación de la salud en las publicaciones españolas: una aproximación sobre el interés de la población</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31152^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37728</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12077^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
