<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053561</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescent adjustments. The social support perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article, the authors analyze the relationship which exists among different sources of social support and three health indicators during adolescence: the presence of depressions, alcohol consumption and smoking cannabis. The sources of social support analyzed are: support by the father support by the mother; support by one's steady boy/girl friend, and support by one's best friend. The sample for this study is comprised of 1002 adolescents aged 12 to 20. Results show that a greater perception of support by the father and by the mother leads to lesser incidences of depression. The perception of greater paternal support is also connected to lesser consumption of both alcohol and cannabis. However the perception of greater support by one's steady boy/girlfriend is associated with a higher degree of alcoholic consumption during adolescente</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estévez López, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musitu Ochoa, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Ruiz, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se analiza la relación existente entre distintas fuentes de apoyo social y tres indicadores de salud en la adolescencia: la presencia de ánimo depresivo, el consumo de alcohol y el consumo de cannabis. Las fuentes de apoyo social analizadas son: el apoyo del padre, de la madre, de la pareja y del mejor amigo/a. La muestra está compuesta por 1.002 adolescentes de 12 a 20 años. Los resultados indican que una mayor percepción de apoyo del padre y de la madre se relaciona con un menor ánimo depresivo. La percepción de un mayor apoyo paterno también se relaciona con un menor consumo tanto de alcohol como de cannabis. Sin embargo, la percepción de apoyo de la pareja se asocia con un consumo más elevado de alcohol durante la adolescencia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;30(2): 87-92, feb. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053561</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El ajuste en la adolescencia. La perspectiva del apoyo social</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28235^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
