<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97809</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Developmental pattern of digit span in Spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examined in a Spanish population the developmental pattern of digit span, as an index of one of the components of Baddeley&#146;s working memory-the phonological loop. A verbal digit span was administered to 570 participants ranging from 5 to 17 years old. The results indicated that the digit memory span increases until age 17 as opposed to Anglo-Saxon data-where it is established that this span reaches a peak by age 15. Additionally, these results were compared to the performance in the same task of healthy elderly, Alzheimer disease patients, and Frontotemporal dementia patients, examined in a previous study. The analysis shows that the phonological loop is affected by age and not so much by dementias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sebastián, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Gil, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio examinó el patrón de desarrollo de la amplitud de dígitos, en una población española, como índice de uno de los componentes del modelo de memoria operativa de Baddeley -el lazo fonológico-. Se administró una tarea verbal de amplitud de dígitos a 570 participantes entre 5 y 17 años. Los resultados indicaron que la amplitud de dígitos se incrementa hasta los 17 años, a diferencia de lo que muestran datos anglosajones donde la amplitud máxima se alcanza a los 15 años. Además, estos resultados fueron comparados con el rendimiento en la misma tarea de ancianos sanos, pacientes Alzheimer y pacientes con demencia frontotemporal, que fue examinado en un estudio anterior. Los datos mostraron que el lazo fonológico estaba afectado por la edad y no tanto por las demencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(2): 183-187, abr.-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97809</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón de desarrollo de la amplitud de dígitos en población española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53511^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53512^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8738^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53512^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
