<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057823</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of peripheral artery disease evaluated by ankle brachial index in patients with metabolic syndrome. MERITO I study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Patients with Metabolic Syndrome have high cardiovascular morbidity and mortality rate above that expected when using accepted scales for risk stratification. Ankle brachial index (ABI) is an available, straightforward and reproducible method for the detection of peripheral vascular disease and for improving risk stratification in this population. Our study aimed to evaluate the prevalence of low ABI in patients with metabolic syndrome older than 50 years and to study the risk factors associated with its development.                 Patients and methods. 1519 subjects between 50 and 85 years, 935 of them with metabolic syndrome (Adult Treatment Panel III [ATP III] criteria), in primary prevention, without symptoms of intermittent claudication and who gave their consent to have an ABI measurement in internal medicine offices were included in the study. Cardiovascular risk factors were evaluated in all participants. An ABI &lt; 0.9 was considered low.                 Results. The prevalence of a low ABI in subjects with metabolic syndrome was 27.7 (95% CI: 24.8-30.5). Factors associated with low and a pathological ABI were age, higher serum creatinine levels and presence of proteinuria. After multivariate adjustment, only age (OR: 1.07; 95% CI: 1.04-1.09) and active tobacco use (OR: 1.45; 95% CI: 1.10-1.92) continued to be significant.                 Conclusion. Prevalence of a low ABI is elevated in subjects with metabolic syndrome without known cardiovascular disease and related with age and active tobacco use</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Manzano, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cairols, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mostaza, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palma, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diodado, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los pacientes con síndrome metabólico tienen una alta morbimortalidad cardiovascular, mayor que la esperada al aplicarles las escalas aceptadas para la estratificación de riesgo. El índice tobillo-brazo (ITB) es un método rápido, sencillo y reproducible de detección de enfermedad vascular periférica para mejorar la estratificación de estos pacientes. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la prevalencia de un ITB disminuido en pacientes con síndrome metabólico mayores de 50 años, así como estudiar los factores de riesgo asociados a ello.                 Pacientes y métodos. Se incluyeron 1.519 pacientes entre 50 y 85 años, 935 con síndrome metabólico (criterios Adult Treatment Panel III [ATP III]), en prevención primaria y sin síntomas de claudicación intermitente que dieron su consentimiento para la realización de un ITB en consultas externas de medicina interna. Se evaluó el riesgo cardiovascular en todos los pacientes. Se consideró disminuido un ITB &lt; 0,9.                 Resultados. La prevalencia de un ITB disminuido en sujetos con síndrome metabólico fue de 27,7% (intervalo de confianza [IC] 95%: 24,8-30,5). Los factores asociados con un ITB disminuido fueron la edad, los niveles de creatinina sérica y la presencia de proteinuria. En el análisis multivariante sólo la edad (odds ratio [OR]: 1,07; IC 95%: 1,04-1,09) y el consumo activo de tabaco (OR: 1,45; IC 95%: 1,10-1,92) continuaron siendo significativos.                 Conclusión. La prevalencia de un ITB disminuido en pacientes con síndrome metabólico, sin enfermedad cardiovascular conocida, es elevada y está relacionada con la edad y el consumo activo de tabaco</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;207(5): 228-233, may.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de enfermedad arterial periférica estimada mediante el índice tobillo-brazo en pacientes con síndrome metabólico. Estudio MERITO I</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
