<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038582</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pain in neonates</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pain in children has been traditionally inadequatelymanaged. It was though that children inability to verbalizefeelings and express pain was synonymous of their inabilityto feel and remember pain. Neonates frequently have toundergo invasive procedures and currently there are notenough data to state that the neonate is unable to perceivepain. Inadequate management of pain causes an increaseof morbi-mortality. In the past years there has been manyadvances in the care and management of the neonate.There are several scales for measuring and assessing painin the neonate at term and pre-term. These are based onthe observation and recording of physiological disorders,behavioral changes or a combination of both. In this paper,we review the scales more frequently used. Several generalmeasures are critically relevant for the management ofpain in the neonate, such as avoidance of unnecessarypainful procedures, control of environmental conditions,different types of sweet oral solutions, multisensitive stimulationand breastfeeding of the mother during the painfulprocedure. However, sometimes all these resources are notenough and we have to use pharmacological measures.The most commonly used drugs are local anesthetics, opiatesand non-steroid anti-inflammatory analgesics. Somesituations can be stressful and non-painful for the neonate and in this cases sedations is the appropriate treatment.We consider chloral hydrate, remifentanyl and midazolam</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calderón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzálvez, A </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tradicionalmente, el dolor en el niño se ha tratado deforma insuficiente. Se pensaba que la incapacidad de losniños para verbalizar sus sentimientos y expresar su dolorera sinónimo de incapacidad para experimentarlo y recordarlo.Los neonatos a menudo deben someterse a intervencionesinvasivas, y en la actualidad existen datos suficientespara afirmar que el neonato es capaz de percibir el dolor.El tratamiento insuficiente del dolor conlleva un aumentode la morbimortalidad. En los últimos años se han producidonumerosos avances en el cuidado y manejo del reciénnacido. Existen diversas escalas de medida del dolor para lavaloración de este en neonatos a término y pretérmino.Estas se basan en la observación y recogida de las alteracionesfisiológicas, cambios del comportamiento, o unacombinación de ambos. En este artículo se hace un repasopor las más utilizadas. Hay una serie de medidas generalesde vital importancia en el tratamiento del dolor en neonatos,como es evitar procedimientos dolorosos innecesarios,el cuidado del ambiente que le rodea, distintos tipos de solucionesorales dulces, la estimulación multisensorial, asícomo amamantar el pecho de su madre durante la intervencióndolorosa. Sin embargo, hay ocasiones en las queestos recursos son insuficientes y hemos de recurrir a lasmedidas farmacológicas. Los fármacos más utilizados sonlos anestésicos locales, opioides y analgésicos antiinflamatoriosno esteroideos. Hay situaciones estresantes y no dolorosaspara el neonato, en las que el tratamiento adecuadoes la sedación. Incluimos el hidrato de cloral,remifentanilo o midazolam</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(2): 98-111, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038582</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor en neonatos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24841^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d715^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2743^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30624^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
