<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168052</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterization and risk factors for aortic dilatation in pediatric patients with bicuspid aortic valve</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Dilatation of the ascending aorta associated with bicuspid aortic valve is a major cause of morbidity and mortality in adults. The main objective was to recognize the aortic involvement in children, its characteristics and risk factors. Methods: Aortic measures of all pediatric patients with bicuspid aortic valve followed in a tertiary pediatric hospital between 1997 and 2015 were retrospectively taken. Patients with syndromes associated with aortic dilatation were excluded (n=17). Results: Two hundred and six patients were included, 67.9% males. The commonest opening pattern was horizontal: 137 (66.7%). Half of the patients (101) had a history of surgical aortic coarctation, 46 (22.3%) had&amp;#8805;moderate aortic valve stenosis and 13 (6%) had&amp;#8805;moderate aortic insufficiency. Mean follow-up time was 6.1 (4.9) years; diagnosis of aortic dilatation was made during the first year of follow-up. Progression of the dilatation of the ascending aorta was noted in 17.1%, and of the aortic root in 2.5%. More than one-third (80/206) had aortic dilatation (z-score&gt;2). The ascending aorta was exclusively affected in 70/80 patients, with sparing of the aortic root. In the multivariate analysis, patients with dilatation of the ascending aorta were associated with absence of coarctation (P=.001) and vertical opening pattern (P=.007). Conclusions: Pediatric patients with bicuspid aortic valve warrant medical follow-up for the frequent association with valve impairment and/or dilatation of the ascending aorta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albert Brotons, Dimpna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabidó Sanchez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabaté-Rotés, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosés Noguer, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gran Ipiña, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abella, Raúl F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La dilatación de la aorta ascendente asociada a válvula aórtica bicúspide es una causa mayor de morbimortalidad en adultos. El objetivo principal fue reconocer la afectación aórtica en niños, así como sus características y factores de riesgo. Métodos: Se realizaron retrospectivamente las mediciones aórticas de todos los pacientes pediátricos con válvula aórtica bicúspide seguidos en un hospital pediátrico terciario entre 1997 y 2015. Se excluyeron los pacientes con síndromes asociados a dilatación aórtica (n=17). Resultados: Se incluyeron 206 pacientes, de los cuales el 67,9% eran varones. El patrón de apertura más común fue horizontal: 137 (66,7%). La mitad de los pacientes (101) tenía historia de coartación aórtica, 46 de ellos (22,3%) con estenosis aórtica&amp;#8805;moderada y 13 (6%) con insuficiencia aórtica&amp;#8805;moderada. El seguimiento medio fue de 6,1 (4,9) años; el diagnóstico de dilatación aórtica se realizó durante el primer año de seguimiento. La progresión de la dilatación de la aorta ascendente se documentó en el 17,1%, y en el 2,5% en la raíz aórtica. Más de un tercio (80/206) presentó dilatación aórtica (z-score&gt;2). La afectación exclusiva de la aorta ascendente se produjo en 70/80 pacientes, con preservación de la raíz aórtica. En el análisis multivariado, los pacientes con dilatación de la aorta ascendente se asociaron a ausencia de coartación (p=0,001) y patrón de apertura vertical (p=0,007). Conclusiones: Está justificado el seguimiento en los pacientes pediátricos con válvula aórtica bicúspide debido a la frecuente asociación con disfunción valvular y/o dilatación aórtica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);149(9): 391-396, nov. 2017. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168052</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización y factores de riesgo de dilatación aórtica en pacientes pediátricos con válvula aórtica bicúspide</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1022^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1026^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
