<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97564</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neurodegenerative hypo kinetic disorders are particularly represented by parkinsonism. This category includes Fahr´s disease. We present in this occasion the case of a woman diagnosed with this disease scheduled for surgery, to perform an update of the anesthetic management of patients with these disorders. Female 60 years old, diagnosed with Fahr´s disease for 3 years, scheduled for laparoscopic cholecystectomy. The patient was clinically asymptomatic with mild to moderate degree of muscle stiffness. Fahr's disease is a rare cause of atypical parkinsonism. The suspicion diagnosis is clinical and confirmation was performed using imaging tests. The choice of anesthetic technique depends on the type of patient and surgery. Local anesthesia are preferred versus general anesthesia. The most important points in the anesthetic management of these patients are to control musculoskeletal and autonomic disorders, an appropriate pharmacological management and control of symptoms that may appear in the course of the surgery. It is recommended that the patient is taking anti-parkinsonian medications the day of surgery as close as possible to the onset of anesthesia and restart as soon as practicable after the operation. The safety of anesthesia in these cases is given by a thorough preoperative evaluation of the patient, maintaining the specific drug regimen and its resumption as early as possible after it, as well as avoidance of agents that may play a parkinsonian crisis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Galán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Blanco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Meré, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos neurodegenerativos motores, de características hipocinéticas, se ven especialmente representados por los parkinsonismos. En esta categoría se incluyen la enfermedad de Fahr. Presentamos en esta ocasión el caso de una mujer diagnosticada con esta patología programada para intervención quirúrgica, con el fin de realizar una puesta al día del manejo anestésico de pacientes con este tipo de trastornos. Mujer de 60 años de edad, diagnosticada de Enfermedad de Fahr desde hacía 3 años, programada para colecistectomía vía laparoscópica. La paciente clínicamente se encontraba asintomática con leve-moderado grado de rigidez muscular.  La Enfermedad de Fahr es una causa poco frecuente de Parkinsonismo atípico. El diagnóstico de sospecha es clínico y el de confirmación se realiza recurriendo a las pruebas de imagen. La elección de la técnica anestésica, depende del tipo de paciente y de la intervención quirúrgica. Son de elección las técnicas de anestesia loco-regional frente a la anestesia general. Los puntos más importantes en el manejo anestésico de este grupo de pacientes son el control de las alteraciones músculo-esqueléticas y autonómicas, el manejo farmacológico adecuado y el control de la sintomatología que pudiera aparecer en el curso de la intervención. Se recomienda que el paciente tome sus medicamentos anti-parkinsonianos el día de la cirugía lo más cerca posible al inicio de la anestesia y los reinicie tan pronto sea factible en el postoperatorio. La seguridad anestésica en estos casos vendrá dada por un exhaustivo estudio preoperatorio del paciente, el mantenimiento de la pauta farmacológica específica y su reanudación lo más precozmente posible tras la misma, así como la evitación de agentes que puedan reproducir una crisis parkinsoniana(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;21(3): 54-57, jul.-sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97564</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo anestésico de una paciente con enfermedad de Farh</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
