<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054643</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prescription of the physical exercise and bone health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteoporosis is a health problem of high importance all        over the world, recognised by the WHO. More than 40%        of the women and 10% of the men over 60 in our society        suffer from a significant loss of their osseous mass density        (OMD).        In this research, we have reviewed most of the articles        that have been published during the last 30 years and in        which a relationship between physical exercise, OMD, osteoporosis        and fracture risks has been found.        According to the results of our review, we propose a        physical exercise program (exercise prescription guide according        to the OMD), that can be applied to osteoporosis        prevention and treatment in order to minimize fracture        risks. Physical exercise has certain effects on the OMD        which have been proved and it can play a very important        role as part of the treatment for patients who suffer from        osteoporosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Legido Arce, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya Miñano, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Álvarez, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segovia Martínez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Silvarrey, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La osteoporosis es un problema sanitario de gran importancia        a nivel mundial, así reconocido por la OMS.        Concretamente, en nuestro medio, más del 40% de las        mujeres y el 10% de los hombres mayores de 60 años presentan,        disminución de la densidad de su masa ósea        (DMO).        En el presente trabajo revisamos la mayoría de los artículos        publicados en los últimos 30 años que relacionan el        ejercicio físico con la DMO, la osteoporosis y el riesgo de        fractura debido a la misma.        Basándonos en la revisión realizada, proponemos un        plan de ejercicio físico (guías de prescripción de ejercicios        según DMO), que puede ser aplicado en la prevención y el        tratamiento de la osteoporosis, con objeto de minimizar el        riesgo de fractura. El ejercicio físico, que ha demostrado        efectos concretos sobre la DMO, puede ser un factor muy        positivo en el manejo de estos pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;4(1): 44-65, ene.-mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054643</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prescripción del ejercicio físico y salud ósea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
