<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80647</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gastrointestinal stromal tumor of the rectovaginal septum: a diagnostic challenge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gastrointestinal stromal tumors (GIST) of the rectovaginal septum are highly infrequent entities that pose a challenge due to the lack of diagnostic suspicion. These tumors are often misdiagnosed as leiomyomas or leiomyosarcomas because of the similarity in their structure and size. Histological analysis and immunochemistry play a key role in the choice of therapeutic strategy in these patients. We report the case of a 75-year-old woman with a GIST tumor in the rectovaginal septum. Tumor enucleation was performed and subsequent treatment with imatinib mesylate (Gleevec(R)) was established (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Escoriza, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saco López, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Piñero Sánchez, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fernández, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Sanmartín, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Sánchez, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Candela Hidalgo, M. Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteve Fuster, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muci Añazco, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores del estroma gastrointestinal (GIST) del tabique rectovaginal son entidades muy poco frecuentes, que cuando aparecen plantean grandes dificultades por su escasa sospecha diagnóstica. En la mayoría de los casos, se suelen confundir con leiomiomas o leiomiosarcomas, por su consistencia y tamaño similar, por lo que desempeña un papel clave el análisis histológico e inmunohistoquímico a la hora de planificar el abordaje terapéutico de estas pacientes. Presentamos el caso de una paciente de 75 años con un tumor GIST en el tabique rectovaginal, a la que se realizó resección total de la lesión y posterior tratamiento con Glivec (R) (mesilato de imatinib) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);53(7): 288-291, jul. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80647</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor del estroma gastrointestinal en el tabique rectovaginal, un desafío diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38616^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201070</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
