<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98768</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Organic matter in meteorites</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Some primitive meteorites are carbon-rich objects containing a variety of organic molecules that constitute a valuable record of organic chemical evolution in the universe prior to the appearance of microorganisms. Families of compounds include hydrocarbons, alcohols, aldehydes, ketones, carboxylic acids, aminoacids, amines, amides, heterocycles, phosphonic acids, sulfonic acids, sugar-related compounds and poorly defined high-molecular weight macromolecules. A variety of environments are required in order to explain this organic inventory, including interstellar processes, gas-grain reactions operating in the solar nebula, and hydrothermal alteration of parent bodies. Most likely, substantial amounts of such organic materials were delivered to the Earth via a late accretion, thereby providing organic compounds important for the emergence of life itself, or that served asa feedstock for further chemical evolution. This review discusses the organic content of primitive meteorites and their relevance to the build up of biomolecules (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llorca, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Algunos meteoritos primitivos son objetos ricos en carbono con una gran variedad de moléculas orgánicas, lo que hace de ellos un registro muy valioso de la evolución química orgánica en el universo antes de la aparición de los microorganismos. Las familias de compuestos comprenden, entre otros, hidrocarburos, alcoholes, aldehídos, cetonas, ácidos carboxílicos, aminoácidos, aminas, amidas, heterociclos, ácidos fosfónicos, ácidos sulfónicos, compuestos relacionados con azúcares y macromoléculas poco definidas de alto peso molecular. Para explicar el origen de este material orgánico diverso,  se requieren varios ambientes, tales como procesos interestelares, reacciones gas-sólido en la nebulosa solar y la alteración hidrotermal de los cuerpos asteroidales originales. Es muy probable que una gran cantidad de ese material orgánico llegara a la Tierra durante los últimos estadios de su formacióny que su presencia resultara crucial para el origen de la vida o que sirviesen como material nutritivo para una evolución química posterior. Esta revisión se centra en el contenido orgánico de los meteoritos más primitivos y ensu papel en la síntesis de biomoléculas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int Microbiol;7(4): 239-248, dic. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98768</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Materia orgánica en meteoritos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56142</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10108^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
