<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132850</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevention of active and passive smoking in childhood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Smoking is one of the main Public Health problems. In many western countries, Spain among them. In the last few years in particular, Health authorities are working hard in order to get this important problem under control. In spite of this, it can be seen that tobacco use is still significant, thus in secondary school children, over 20 % of adolescents aged 14-16 years are smokers. Moreover, around 50 % of children younger than 14, have domestic exposure to environmental tobacco smoke. Smoking during pregnancy causes significant morbidity and mortality, not only in neonatal age but also throughout life. There are not enough studies of sufficient quality that evaluate the effectiveness of individual advice in adolescents. School and community programs have a limited efficacy. Anti-smoking counselling to parents in a Paediatric Primary Care setting is recommended. This is of especial importance in pregnant women. We must advise adolescents to stop smoking in a way that is adapted to their development and understanding capacity. We should stress the short-term consequences and the most important motivating aspects for teenagers. A special leaflet for adolescents giving anti-smoking counselling is suggested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galbe Sánchez-Ventura, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tabaquismo es un problema de salud pública de primer orden. En los últimos años, las autoridades sanitarias de muchos países occidentales, entre ellos España, están haciendo serios esfuerzos para controlar este grave problema. No obstante, se percibe que el consumo de tabaco sigue siendo muy importante, alrededor del 20% en la población escolar de 14 a 16 años son fumadores. Además, alrededor del 50% de los menores de 14 años viven en hogares donde se fuma. El consumo del tabaco durante el embarazo es una importante causa de morbimortalidad, tanto neonatal como a largo plazo. No existen estudios de suficiente calidad que evalúen la eficacia del consejo individual antitabaco en adolescentes. Los programas escolares y comunitarios tienen una eficacia reducida. Se recomienda realizar consejo antitabaco en padres y madres que asisten a la consulta de Pediatría. Es especialmente importante el consejo antitabaco en embarazadas. El consejo antitabaco en adolescentes debe ajustarse a su nivel de desarrollo y comprensión. Se debe insistir en las consecuencias a corto plazo y sobre aquellos aspectos más motivadores para los adolescentes. Se propone un folleto para administrar el consejo en adolescentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;11(supl.17): s359-s369, nov. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132850</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención del tabaquismo activo y pasivo en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32153^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
