<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-11370</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients receiving treatment for undernourishment in primary health care, study of 500 real patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The worsening of the nutritional status of certain segments of the population has led to frequent situations of chronic undernourishment even in the healthy population. There are very few data available on the prevalence and causes of malnutrition in Primary Health Care. The present study attempts to provide measurable information, obtained at random from the doctors involved in the country&#146;s Primary Health Care, on the characteristics of the undernourished patients, the cause of the undernourishment, the diagnostic means used, the treatment applied and the progress of the patients regularly treated in Primary Health Care facilities. Materials and Method: A sample of 1,819 doctors in Primary Health Care were surveyed to know their opinions on the nutritional status of their patients. They were asked to complete a &#147;Patient Record&#148; for the first patient to enter their office suffering from undernourishment. A total of 505 Patient Records were received from the different Primary Health Care doctors taking part in the study throughout Spain. Results: Of the patients included, 10% were aged less than 10, while 46.7% were between 16 and 65 years of age and 44.2% were over 65. The main diagnosis in these patients was varied, with cancer patients (22.6%) and anorexics, including anorexia nerviosa and other non-oncological causes, (16.4%) the most common. As for the tests used for diagnosing undernourishment, those most frequently applied were physical examination (61%) and biochemical tests (56.4%). The risk factor most commonly found in these patients was old age / senility (21%). Nutritional support (55.8%) and dietary recommendations (45.3%) were the therapies most often applied. Only 47% of patients correctly implemented their treatment according to the doctors in Primary Health Care and the prognosis was as follows: 31% were expected to improve, 20% to worsen and 44% of cases would remain stable. Conclusions: From this study, it is concluded that most undernourished patients in Primary Health Care are there due to a severe pathology or because of age; that anthropometric and biochemical methods are used for diagnosis purposes although the clinical interview is of basic importance; that a large proportion of patients require some type of nutritional supplements; and finally that, according to the doctors, the expectations of improvement in the nutritional status of these patients are not good (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El empeoramiento del estado nutricional de algunos segmentos de la población ha provocado que las situaciones de desnutrición crónica sean frecuentes incluso en población sana. Se disponen de muy pocos datos de prevalencia y causas de malnutrición en atención primaria. En este estudio se pretende aportar una información mesurable, obtenida de manera aleatoria entre los médicos de atención primaria del país sobre las características de los pacientes desnutridos, la causa de la desnutrición, los medios empleados en el diagnóstico, el tratamiento empleado y la evolución de los pacientes tratados de manera habitual en las consultas de atención primaria. Material y método: A una muestra de 1.819 médicos de atención primaria a los que se les realizó una encuesta de opinión acerca el estado nutricional de sus pacientes, se les pidió que rellenaran una "Ficha paciente" del primer paciente con desnutrición que entrara en su consulta. Se obtuvieron un total de 505 "Ficha paciente" distribuidas entre los diferentes médicos de atención primaria participantes en el estudio en toda España.Resultados: Un 10 por ciento de los pacientes incluidos eran menores de 10 años, mientras que un 46,7 por ciento se hallaban entre los 16 y los 65 años y el 44,2 por ciento eran mayores de 65.El diagnóstico principal de los pacientes era variado, siendo los pacientes oncológicos (22,6 por ciento) y los pacientes anoréxicos (incluyendo anorexia nerviosa y otras causas no oncológicas) (16,4 por ciento) los más frecuentes. En cuanto a las pruebas realizadas para el diagnóstico de la desnutrición, las más frecuentemente usadas fueron el examen físico (61 por ciento) y las pruebas bioquímicas (56,4 por ciento). El factor de riesgo más frecuentemente encontrado en estos pacientes fue la tercera edad/senilidad (21 por ciento). Los soportes nutricionales (55,8 por ciento) y las recomendaciones dietéticas (45,3 por ciento) fueron los tratamientos más comúnmen te aplicados. Sólo un 47 por ciento de los paciente realizaban correctamente el tratamiento según sus médicos de atención primaria y el pronóstico de los mismos era a mejorar en un 31 por ciento, a empeorar en un 20 por ciento y mantenerse estable en el 44 por ciento de los casos.Conclusiones: De este estudio se extrae que la mayoría de los pacientes desnutridos en atención primaria lo están debido a una patología grave o a causa de la edad, que se emplean metodos antropométricos y bioquímicos pero fundamentalmente la entrevista clínica para diagnosticarlos, que un elevado porcentaje de los pacientes requieren suplementos nutricionales de algún tipo, y por último que las expectativas de mejoría del estado nutricional de estos pacientes según sus médicos, no son buenas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;17(1): 10-14, ene. 2002. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pacientes en tratamiento por desnutrición en atención primaria, estudio sobre 500 pacientes reales</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Venegas Moreno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Rubio M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Luna, PP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Sanz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-11370</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
