<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90739</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-4723</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Congenital Chagas disease is caused by the transmission of Trypanosomacruzi from an infected mother to her foetus. Although characteristically found in Latin America countries, this disease is extending to other continents due to the immigration of chronically infected women of reproductive age. The mother to foetus transmission rate varies between 1 and 12% in different regions. The significant population of infected women of child bearing age and the transmission risk during pregnancy highlight the importance of congenital transmission. In the absence of foetal infection, maternal Chagasdoes not appear to influence pregnancy or the foetal development. However, more than 50% of newborns with congenital Chagas are completely asymptomatic at birth. In cases where clinical disease is present, premature birth, low birth weight, hepatomegaly and splenomegally, respiratory distress syndrome, and anasarca have been observed. Diagnosis of a congenital infection can be done at birth by testing for parasites in the umbilical cord blood or bloodstream and by micromethod. Cases that are negative at birth can be followed-up with a second parasitological test between age 1 and 2months and by serological analysis after age 6 months. Early treatment of infected infants with Benznidazol for 30 days cures almost 100% of cases. Treatment success can be confirmed by negative serological tests between6 month and 1 year after treatment is completed. This article presents the results of a congenital Chagas detection and treatment program in three endemic areas of Bolivia. The observed prevalence of infection was more than 30% with a 2.5% transmission rate. Treatment adherence for infectedinfants was 83% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torrico, Faustino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Billot,  Claire</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carlier, Yves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Truyens, Carine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Vega, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Chagas congénita se produce por la transmisión de Trypanosomacruzi de la madre infectada al feto. Esta infección, característica de la América latina, se extiende a otros continentes debido a la importante migración de mujeres crónicamente infectadas y en edad fértil. La tasa de transmisión materno fetal varía de una región a otra entre el 1 y el 12%.La importante población de mujeres en edad fértil infectadas y el riesgo de transmisión presente en cada embarazo realzan la importancia de este modo de transmisión. La infección materna, cuando no hay infección al feto, parece no influenciar ni el curso del embarazo ni el desarrollo fetal. Sin embargo más del 50% de los recién nacidos con Chagas congénito son totalmente asintomáticos al nacimiento. En los casos donde hay una clínica aparente se puede observar prematuridad, bajo peso al nacer, hepato y esplenomegalia, síndrome de distress respiratorio y anasarca. El diagnostico de la infección congénita puede hacerse al nacimiento mediante la búsqueda de parásitos en la sangre del cordón umbilical o la sangre venosa, utilizando el micrométodo en tubo capilar, complementado, en los casos negativos al nacimiento, con una segunda prueba parasitológica entre 1 y 2 meses de edad, y con las pruebas serológicas después de los seis meses de vida. El tratamiento precoz de la infección congénita con Benznidazol durante 30 días cura prácticamente al 100% de los niños infectados y esta curación se puede confirmar por la negativación de las pruebas serológicas entre 6 meses hasta un año después del tratamiento. Este artículo también presenta resultados del programa de detección y tratamiento de Chagas congénito en tres departamentos endémicos de Bolivia, donde se observa una prevalencia de infección materna superior al 30% con una tasa de transmisión de 2,5% y un cumplimiento del tratamiento en un 83% de los niños infectados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. emerg;9(supl.1): 9-16, ene.-dic. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90739</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones materno-fetales en la infección con T. Cruzi y la implementación de un programa nacional de detección y tratamiento de Chagas congénito en Bolivia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d981^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14752^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1863^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
