<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120177</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-123X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orofacial muskuloskeletal pain (Temporomandibular disorders)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study is to provide a closer view about the most common non-odontogenic orofacial pain that shows up in our clinic, Musculoskeletal Orofacial Pain, usually known as Craniomandibular Disorders or Temporomandibular Disorders. We have reviewed the relevant literature on orofacial muscle pain, describing the most common symptons we can find, and exposing its multifactorial etiology, as well as the role that occlusion may play in its pathophysiology. We conclude highlithing the importance of providing an early and adequate diagnosis, that allows us to establish an effective, interdisciplinary and conservative therapeutic management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hoz Aizpúrua, J. L de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Ramos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra González, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este trabajo es conocer un poco más de cerca el dolor orofacial no odontogénico más común que se presenta en nuestra consulta, el Dolor Orofacial Musculoesquelético, comúnmente conocido como Disfunción Craneomandibular (DCM) o Temporomandibular. Revisamos la literatura que existe sobre dolor orofacial musculoesquelético, describiendo los síntomas más frecuentes que nos podemos encontrar y exponiendo su etiología  multifactorial, así como el papel que pudiera tener la oclusión en su desarrollo. Concluimos con la importancia de realizar un diagnóstico precoz y correcto que permita establecer un manejo  terapéutico eficaz, interdisciplinar y conservador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>RCOE;18(3): 161-165, sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120177</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor orofacial musculoesquelético</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30768^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54520^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8582^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24322^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19551^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
