<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114958</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testing a procedure to investigate occupational related diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Data from the National Survey of Safety and Health Management at Companies evidence gaps the investigation of cases of occupational diseases. In this context this project aims to developed and test an investigation procedure of occupational diseases, in order to guide, harmonize and systematize the collection of information in the course of the investigation of this cases. In the first phase a group of researchers from the Safety al Occupational Health of Valencia the National School of Occupational Medicine developed a procedure for investigate cases of occupational diseases that was submitted to a consensus workshop with a group of experts from various key agents: Employees Organizations, Prevention Services, Mutuas, Labour Inspectorate, Technical Institutes from the Autonomous Communities, Societies of Occupational Medicine, Public Research Institutes and University. The resulting procedure was tested on 21 incident cases of occupational diseases, we evaluated a total of 26 indicators in three dimensions: needs, relevance and overall opinion, as measured by a Likert scale, assessing the degree of agreement between applicators by the standardization procedure of the AGREE evaluation method. The results show on 19 indicators a level of consensus upper than 80% and for others 10 indicators a level of consensus upper than 90%, there being no dissent in any of the indicators analyzed. These results leading to the conclusion that the tested procedure covers the information needs in the investigation of cases of occupational diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Roel Valdés, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maqueda Blasco, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los datos de la Encuesta Nacional de Gestión de la Seguridad y Salud en las Empresas pone de manifiesto una escasa práctica en la investigación de casos de enfermedades profesionales o relacionadas con el trabajo. En este contexto se desarrolla este proyecto dirigido al desarrollo y ensayo de un procedimiento de investigación de casos de enfermedades profesionales o relacionadas con el trabajo, que permita orientar, armonizar y sistematizar la recogida de información en el transcurso de la investigación de este tipo de casos. En una primera fase un grupo investigadores del Instituto Valenciano de Seguridad y Salud en el Trabajo y de la Escuela Nacional de Medicina del Trabajo del Instituto de Salud Carlos III desarrollaron un procedimiento de investigación de casos de enfermedades laborales (profesionales o relacionadas con el trabajo), que se sometió mediante un taller al consenso con un grupo de expertos procedentes de distintos grupos de interés: Sindicatos, Servicios de Prevención Propios y Ajenos, Mutuas, Inspección de Trabajo, órganos técnicos de las CCAA, Sociedades de Medicina del Trabajo y Organismos Públicos de Investigación y Universidad. El procedimiento resultante se ensayó en 21 casos incidentes de enfermedades laborales, se evaluaron un total de 26 indicadores en tres dimensiones: necesidad, aplicabilidad y valoración general, medidos por una escala tipo Likert, evaluando el grado de acuerdo entre aplicadores mediante el procedimiento de estandarización del Instrumento AGREE. Los resultados ponen de manifiesto en 19 indicadores un grado de consenso superior al 80% y en 10 un grado de consenso superior al 90%, no existiendo disenso en ningunos de los indicadores analizados, lo que permite concluir que el procedimiento ensayado cubre las necesidades de información en la investigación de casos de enfermedades laborales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;59(231): 227-234, abr.-jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114958</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ensayo de campo de un procedimiento de investigación de casos de enfermedades de origen laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6454</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
