<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87718</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psoriatic arthritis and etanercept</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psoriatic arthritis (PA) is a chronic inflammatory condition whose symptoms generally appear after the skin symptoms. Making an early diagnosis and treatment of the disease is of vital importance because of the potential development of mutilating and deforming arthritis. Classical treatments of PA include the use of non-steroid anti-inflammatory drugs, diseasemodifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARD) such as methotrexate, sulfasalazine, or gold, and finally, leflunomide. Research on the pathophysiology of psoriasis and of the PA has led to the incorporation of biological treatments, specifically anti-TNF drugs. The three treatments used most in PA are etanercept, infliximab and adalimumab. Of all these, we are going to make a systematic review of the principal studies available on etanercept for the treatment of PA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Daudén, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedraz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artritis psoriásica (APs) es una enfermedad inflamatoria crónica cuyos síntomas suelen aparecer después de los cutáneos. Resulta de vital importancia la realización de un diagnóstico y tratamiento precoz de la enfermedad debido al potencial desarrollo de artritis deformante o mutilante. Los tratamientos clásicos de la APs incluyen la utilización de antiinflamatorios no esteroideos, fármacos antirreumáticos modificadores de la enfermedad (FAME), como metotrexato, sulfasalazina o el oro y, últimamente, leflunomida. Las investigaciones sobre la fisiopatología de la psoriasis y de la APs han llevado a la incorporación de los tratamientos biológicos, concretamente los fármacos anti-factor de necrosis tumoral (TNF). Los tres tratamientos más utilizados en APs son etanercept, infliximab y adalimumab. De todos ellos vamos a hacer una revisión sistemática de los principales estudios disponibles de etanercept para el tratamiento de la APs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;101(supl.1): 26-34, mayo 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87718</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artritis psoriásica y etanercept</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24527^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12835^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
