<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89528</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intensive medicine in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract Intensive care medicine is a medical specialty that was officially established in ourcountry in 1978, with a 5-year training program including two years of common core trainingfollowed by three years of specific training in an intensive care unit accredited for training.During this 32-year period, intensive care medicine has carried out an intense and varied activity,which has allowed its positioning as an attractive and with future specialty in the hospitalsetting. This document summarizes the history of the specialty, its current situation, the keyrole played in the programs of organ donation and transplantation of the National TransplantOrganization (after more than 20 years of mutual collaboration), its training activities withthe development of the National Plan of Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation, with a trajectory ofmore than 25 years, its interest in providing care based on quality and safety programs forthe severely ill patient. It also describes the development of reference registries due to theneed for reliable data on the care process for the most prevalent diseases, such as ischemicheart disease or ICU-acquired infections, based on long-term experience (more than 15 years),which results in the availability of epidemiological information and characteristics of care thatmay affect the practical patient&#146;s care. Moreover, features of its scientific society (SEMICYUC)are reported, an organization that agglutinates the interests of more than 280 ICUs and morethan 2700 intensivists, with reference to the journal Medicina Intensiva, the official journal of thesociety and the Panamerican and Iberian Federation of Critical Medicine and Intensive CareSocieties. Medicina Intensiva is indexed in the Thompson Reuters products of Science Citation IndexExpanded (Scisearch®) and Journal Citation Reports, Science Edition. The important contributionof the Spanish intensive care medicine to the scientific (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Junta Directiva de la Sociedad Española de Medicina Intensiva,Crítica y Unidades Coronarias (SEMICYUC)</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La medicina intensiva es una especialidad médica creada oficialmente en nuestro país en 1978, con un programa formativo de 5 años, dos troncales y tres de formación, en una unidad de cuidados intensivos, acreditada para la docencia, habiendo desarrollado durante este tiempo, 32 años, una actividad intensa y variada, lo que ha permitido posicionarse como una especialidad atractiva y con futuro en el mundo hospitalario. Este documento resume la historia de la especialidad, su situación actual, su papel determinante y clave en los programas de donación y trasplante de la ONT (tras más de 20 años de colaboración mutua), su actividad formativa con el desarrollo del Plan Nacional de Reanimación Cardiopulmonar, con más de 25 años de trayectoria, su interés por proporcionar una asistencia basada en programas de calidad y seguridad del paciente grave, y describe también el desarrollo de registros de referencia, ante la necesidad de conocer datos en procesos asistenciales prevalentes, como la cardiopatía isquémica, o en las infecciones en las UCI de largo recorrido (más de 15 años), que han permitido disponer de información epidemiológica y de características asistenciales, que pueden incidir en la práctica asistencial. Además, describe las características de su sociedad científica (SEMICYUC), una organización que aglutina los intereses de más de 280 UCI y de más de 2.700 intensivistas, y también hay referencias a la revista Medicina Intensiva , revista oficial de la Sociedad y de la Federación Panamericana e Ibérica de Sociedades de Medicina Crítica y Terapia Intensiva. Medicina Intensiva está incluida por Thompson Reuters en el Science Citation Index Expanded (Scisearch®), y en el Journal Citation Reports, Science Edition. Se analiza también la importante contribución científica que la medicina intensiva española ha realizado a la comunidad científica, y en relación con su futuro en España y Europa, se apuesta por la especialización mediante la (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);35(2): 92-101, mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89528</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medicina intensiva en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
