<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047504</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-2159</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thinking the truth and selecting the false</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An interesting phenomenonhas been found in two experiments using Wason&#146;s Selection Task. Wecompared a standard abstract version of the task with another equallyabstract version in which participants are asked to select &#147;those cards thatwe should remove for the rule to be true for the rest of the cards&#148;. From thelogical point of view the pattern of responses is the same in this version thanin the original task. However, the participants exhibited a mirror-imageselection pattern (they selected the cards corresponding to the negation ofthe antecedent and the consequent of the rule). This phenomenon occursboth with explicit (Experiment 1) and implicit negations (Experiment 2).The results favour the negation-heuristic hypothesis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santamaría, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espino, Orlando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos dos experimentos realizados con la Tarea de Selección deWason en los que se hace patente un curioso fenómeno. Dichosexperimentos comparan una situación estándar de la tarea abstracta con otra,igualmente abstracta, en la que se pide a los sujetos que indiquen las tarjetasque habría que quitar para que la regla fuese verdadera para el resto de ellas.En esta versión, que tiene la misma respuesta lógicamente válida que laoriginal, se produce mayoritariamente un patrón de seleccióncomplementario al habitual en esta tarea: es decir, los participantesseleccionan las tarjetas que corresponden a la negación del antecedente y elconsecuente de la regla. Este fenómeno ocurre tanto con negacionesexplícitas (experimento 1) como implícitas (experimento 2). Los resultadosse consideran favorables a la hipótesis del heurístico de negación</dc:description>
<dc:source>PsicolÔogica (Valencia, Ed. impr.);27(2): 195-206, jul.-dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047504</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pensar en lo verdadero para seleccionar lo falso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3729</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8304</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
