<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94590</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Substance abuse and health self-perception in Spanish children and adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to analyze substance abuse and health self-perception in children and adolescents from the province of Cádiz (Spain). Methodology: Participants were 738 students, 50.9 boys and 49.1% girls, from elementary school to high school (1st to 12th grade, mean age 12.2. years), who responded a Spanish adaptation of the Health Behavior in School-aged Children Inventory. Results: No difference was observed in percentage of boys and girls reporting to smoke or drink alcohol. Smoking and drinking habits increased with age, being higher in 11th and 12th grade students. Significant differences were observed among the percentage of smokers and non smokers recognizing to have parents, older brothers or friends who smoke. Rates of drug abuse were generally low, being cannabis the most frequently consumed illicit drug. Most respondents had a perception of excellent or good health, with no significant gender differences. About half of subjects considered that health exclusively depends on self behavior, but an important percentage also gave a relevant role to luck. Stomach-ache was the most frequent physical complaint, followed by headache. Psychological complaints mainly corresponded to nervousness and bad temper. Only a small percentage of subjects declared the use of medicines or tablets without prescription. No significant difference in the percentage of respondent who perceived an excellent or good health was observed among substance users and non users. Conclusions: Substance abuse and health self-perception in children and adolescents are the result of the interaction of a complex series of individual and social factors. Activities aimed to improve health focusing on partial aspects of adolescents' lifestyle most probably will have limited results, and global programs are required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molinero, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro-Piñero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salguero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo del estudio ha sido analizar el uso de sustancias tóxicas y la autopercepción del estado de salud en niños y adolescentes de la provincia de Cádiz. Metodología: Participaron 738 alumnos, 50.9% de chicos y 49.1% de chicas, que cursaban educación primaria y secundaria (desde 1o educación primaria a 2o de bachillerato, edad media 12,2 años), a los que se aplicó la versión española del Inventario de Conductas de Salud en Escolares. Resultados: No se observaron diferencias en el porcentaje de chicos y chicas que fumaban o bebían alcohol. Los hábitos de consumo de tabaco y alcohol se incrementaban con la edad, alcanzando sus máximos valores en los alumnos de bachillerato. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en el porcentaje de fumadores y no fumadores que reconocían el tener padres, hermanos mayores o amigos que fumaban. El consumo de drogas ilegales era generalmente reducido, predominando la utilización del cannabis. La mayoría de los sujetos tenían una percepción de su salud como excelente o buena. En torno a la mitad de los encuestados consideraban que la salud depende exclusivamente del propio comportamiento, aunque una parte importante también le otorgaba un papel relevante a la suerte. El dolor de estómago era el síntoma físico más frecuente, seguido del dolor de cabeza. Entre los síntomas psicológicos predominaban el nerviosismo y el estar irritado o enfadado. Solo un pequeño porcentaje declaraba consumir medicamentos o píldoras no prescritos. No se observaron diferencias significativas en el porcentaje de los que reconocían una salud excelente o buena entre los usuarios y no usuarios de sustancias tóxicas. Conclusiones: El abuso de sustancias tóxicas y la auto-percepción del estado de salud en niños y adolescentes es el resultado de la interacción de una compleja serie de factores individuales y sociales. Las actividades diseñadas para la mejora de la salud centradas en aspectos parciales del estilo de vida tendrán probablemente resultados limitados, requiriéndose el desarrollo de programas globales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(2): 402-409, mar.-abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abuso de sustancias y percepción de la salud en niños y adolescentes españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
