<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040909</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Euthanasia in children. Comments on the Groningen protocol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Dutch doctors, E. Vergahen and P. Sauer, at the center of an international controversy about euthanasing infants with extremely poor quality of life have used the New England Journal of Medicine to publicise their ticklist for determining when doctors can legitimately kill children with their parents' consent. Their requirements are simple: hopeless and unbearable suffering, a certain diagnosis and prognosis, confirmation by another doctor, the informed consent of the parents, and accepted medical practice.    Inevitably, such considerations lead to worries about slippery slopes. The arguments given by the authors seem quite simplistic and are based on the utilitarian principie that suffering is the worst possible evil.    Treatment of pain and suffering should be a priority for all the clinicians. Studies over the past 15 years suggest that neonates, infants, and children can receive analgesia and anesthesia safely, with proper age-related adjustements in clinical practice and dosing. Besides the development of palliative care has allowed to improve the quality of life, to maintain the dignity, and to ameliorate the suffering of seriously ill or dying children in ways that are appropriate to their upbringing, culture and community. Palliative care should be accessible in any setting, including home, hospital and school.    Directly bringing about death of children through use of lethal drugs is found ethically unacceptable. Great caution and care are necessary</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villa Elízaga, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Villares, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los doctores holandeses, Eduard Vergahen y Peter Sauer, que trabajan en la Universidad de Groningen, notable por la controversia sobre la autorización para aplicar la eutanasia a recién nacidos y lactantes con una calidad de vida muy pobre, han publicado en New England Journal of Medicine el protocolo en el que explican los distintos pasos para llevar a cabo esta práctica con el consentimiento de los padres de los niños. Los requerimientos son muy sencillos: un sufrimiento incontrolable y desesperado, un diagnóstico y un pronóstico ciertos, la confirmación por otro médico, el consentimiento de los padres y que se trate de una práctica médica aceptada.    Inevitablemente, estas consideraciones llevan a un peligroso plano inclinado. Los argumentos que manejan estos autores son demasiados simplistas y están basados en un criterio utilitarista que considera el sufrimiento como el mayor de los males posibles.    El tratamiento del dolor y del sufrimiento son un deber ineludible de cualquier médico. Existen suficientes estudios elaborados en los últimos 15 años que demuestran que se puede administrar a los recién nacidos y lactantes anestesia y sedación de una forma segura, siempre que se efectúe ajustando adecuadamente las dosis a la edad y a la situación clínica. Además, el desarrollo de los cuidados paliativos ha permitido mejorar la calidad de vida, mantener la dignidad y disminuir el sufrimiento de niños gravemente enfermos y en sus familiares de acuerdo con sus valores, educación y creencias. Los cuidados paliativos deberían estar disponibles en cualquier instancia: el domicilio, el hospital o la escuela.    Causar de manera directa la muerte mediante la administración de dosis letales de fármacos es una práctica éticamente inaceptable. Parece necesario tener una gran precaución y sensibilidad ante iniciativas como el protocolo de Groningen</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;63(8): 307-313, sept. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040909</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eutanasia en niños. Una reflexión sobre el protocolo de Groningen</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24212^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d896^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
