<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137646</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-5887</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bioethics, abortion and public policies in Latin America</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bioethics in Latin America is strongly influenced by religious beliefs, leading to the most restrictive regulation globally of sexual and reproductive health and, most particularly, of abortion. Legal obstacles do not dissuade women from terminating unwanted pregnancies; each year more than 4 million illegal abortions take place, in which the poorest Latin American women risk their health and lives. This text employs the term bioethics within the meaning given to it by its creator, V. R. Potter: &#147;ethics based on scientific knowledge&#148;. It proposes gradualism, sustained on scientific evidence contributed by embryology, genetics, and neurophysiology, as the most appropriate model for the regulation of abortion in Latin America. Gradualism respects every woman&#146;s right to decide on questions related to maternity and holds sway in countries with the highest levels of sexual and reproductive health. Latin America urgently needs effective measures to prevent unwanted pregnancies, which are the main cause of abortion: education on sexual and reproductive health; access to modern and effective contraceptives; and severe sanctions for sexual abuse of women, adolescents and girls (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piekarewicz Sigal, Mina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La bioética en América Latina está fuertemente influida por creencias religiosas, lo que resulta en la regulación más restrictiva del orbe en salud sexual y reproductiva y, muy señaladamente, en aborto. Los impedimentos legales no disuaden a las mujeres que optan por interrumpir embarazos no deseados; cada año tienen lugar más de 4 millones de abortos ilegales en los que las latinoamericanas más pobres arriesgan su salud y su vida. Este texto recupera el sentido que V. R. Potter &#150;creador del término&#150; dio a la bioética: &#147;una ética basada en el conocimiento científico&#148;. Propone el gradualismo &#150;modelo sustentado en la evidencia científica que aportan la embriología, la genética y la neurofisiología&#150; como el idóneo para la regulación del aborto en América Latina. El gradualismo respeta el derecho de toda mujer a decidir sobre su maternidad y es el modelo adoptado por los países con los índices más altos en salud sexual y reproductiva. América Latina está urgida de medidas efectivas para prevenir los embarazos no deseados, que son la causa principal del aborto: educación en salud sexual y reproductiva, acceso a anticonceptivos modernos, y penas severas contra el abuso sexual de mujeres, adolescentes y niñas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. bioét. derecho;(33): 3-13, 2015. tab, mapas</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137646</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bioética, aborto y políticas públicas en América Latina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11709^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15331^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50243</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
