<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118996</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Health and safety professional roles and competencies to promote company-level integration of preventive actions. A delphi study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the view of faculty who train health and safety professionals on the roles and competencies needed to promote the integration of preventive actions at the company level. Methods: We used a Delphi method, in three rounds, on an intentional sample of experts, and asked them to rate the appropriateness, relevance and acceptability of 8 professional roles, on a scale of 1 to 9 points. We also asked them to formulate and rank order the corresponding competencies, in order of importance. Results: Participant responses (n=76, 58%of the initially identified faculty) show a broad consensus when assessing professional roles (over 85% of participants rated two of these roles highly, with scores between 7 and 9) and general agreement on the three most important competencies in terms of knowledge, skills and attitudes to promote the integration of preventive actions .Conclusions: The experts participating in this study agreed that the main roles to be performed by health and safety professionals to promote prevention integration are as advisors and trainers. The competencies considered most important are knowledge about the company activity, its risks and the problems linked to the activity (to know), ability to work in multidisciplinary teams (to know how), and to perform professional duties ethically, with independence and impartiality (to know how to be) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boix Ferrando, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gual Llorens, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velarde Collado, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portell Vidal, Mariona</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer el punto de vista de docentes que forman prevencionistas acerca de cuáles son los roles y competencias necesarios en los profesionales de la salud laboral para promover la integración de la prevención en la empresa. Método: Se utiliza la técnica Delphi en triple vuelta sobre una muestra intencional de expertos a los que se pidió que puntuaran en una escala de 1 a 9 la pertinencia, relevancia y aceptabilidad de un listado de ocho roles, y que enunciaran y ordenaran según su importancia las correspondientes competencias. Resultados: Las respuestas obtenidas de los participantes (n=76, 58% de los docentes en el listado inicial) muestran amplio consenso en la valoración de los roles (más del 85% de los participantes coinciden en otorgar puntuaciones altas&#150;entre 7 y 9&#150; para dos de los ocho roles listados) así como un acuerdo generalizado sobre las tres competencias más importantes en relación con los conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes adecuadas para promover la integración de la prevención en la empresa. Conclusiones: En opinión de los expertos participantes los principales roles que debe ejercer el profesional de salud laboral para promover la integración de la prevención son el de asesor y el de formador. Las competencias consideradas como más importantes son el conocimiento de la actividad de la empresa así como los riesgos y los problemas derivados de dicha actividad (saber), la capacidad de trabajar en equipos multidisciplinares (saber hacer), y el poseer ética profesional, independencia e imparcialidad (saber ser, estar) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);17(1): 10-12, ene.-mar. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Roles y competencias de los profesionales de la salud laboral para promover la integración de la prevención en la empresa. Un estudio Delphi Clara</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28454^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
