<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91294</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The other face of the Multiple Chemical Sensitivity Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Multiple Chemical Sensitivity Syndrome is a chronic disease linkedto the excessive pouring of chemical residues as well as chemical agentsused in daily life into the environment. Neuronal sensitivisation is the underlyingorganic basis that explains from a toxicological point of viewhow tolerance to the products that affect neurons is lost.The objective of this paper is to inform about this syndrome from thepoint of view of the affected individuals; aspects of the disease such asphysical problems, disturbed working capacity, altered family life andleisure time, limitation of self-autonomy, involuntary social isolation towhich the sufferers of this disease are subjected to, the vital, emotionaland economic costs, and how the disease prevents patients from makingany plans for the future (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escudero Peinador, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome de Sensibilidad Química Múltiple es una enfermedad de caráctercrónico y que se relaciona con el exceso de productos tóxicos vertidosen el medioambiente, así como de aquellos otros químicos que formanparte de la vida cotidiana. La sensibilización neuronal es la baseorgánica que subyace en la explicación toxicológica de la pérdida de latolerancia a todos los productos que les afectan.El objetivo de este artículo es dar a conocer este síndrome desde el lugarde los afectados; aspectos de la enfermedad como los problemas físicos,la alteración de la capacidad laboral, la vida familiar y de ocio, lalimitación de su autonomía, el aislamiento social involuntario al que estánsometidos, el coste vital, emocional y económico y como la enfermedadno les permite hacer ningún plan de futuro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;12(6): 58-61, jul. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91294</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La otra cara del Síndromede Sensibilidad Química Múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4865^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32135^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
