<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60988</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the neurology teaching unit in Spain and compliance of accreditation criteria</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Faced with the promulgation of the HealthCare Professionals Ordinance Law and the publication of the newprogram of the Neurology training, the National Committee ofneurology has considered it necessary to know the current situationof the Teaching Units (TU) accredited for the neurology trainingin regards to the existing accreditation criteria (AC). Thepurpose of this study is to know said situation.Methods. A cross-sectional study performed by a voluntarilyfilled-out survey (ad hoc questionnaire) sent by regular mailin the year 2005 to all the TU accredited at that time. It includedspecific questions regarding the structural, human andorganizational requirements contemplated in those accreditationcriteria.Results. A total of 64 questionnaires were sent (response percentage:76.6%). Eighty seven percent of the TU met the structuralrequirements for neurological care, although 21 % had fewerthan 4 offices for visits and fewer than 15 neurology beds. A totalof 25 % of the TU did not met the requirements in regards to fulltimestaff members. Although almost 100% met the quantitativecare organizational requirements, only 69 % reported that therewere neurology duties. However, the grade of the tutorial systemcould not be known due to the survey design. Almost 100% metthe teaching and research requirements.Conclusions. Although the compliance grade of the currentAC is high, there are important deficiencies, basically related tothe number of full-time staff professionals and the availability ofduly tutorized neurology duties (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Pérez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Bona, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín González, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Vila, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Antigüedad, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matías-Guiu Guia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Ortiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Silanes, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frank García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Henández, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Ante la promulgación de la Ley de Ordenación dela Profesiones Sanitarias y la publicación del nuevo programa de laespecialidad de neurología, la Comisión Nacional de Neurología considerónecesario conocer la situación actual de las unidades docentes(UD) acreditadas para la especialidad en lo referente a los criterios deacreditación vigentes. El objetivo de este trabajo es conocer dichasituación.Métodos. Estudio transversal mediante una encuesta de cumplimentaciónvoluntaria (cuestionario ad hoc) remitida por correoen el año 2005 a todas UD acreditadas en ese momento. Incluyópreguntas específicas respecto a los requerimientos estructurales,humanos y de organización contemplados en dichos criterios deacreditación.Resultados. Se remitieron 64 cuestionarios (porcentaje de respuesta:76,6%). El 87 % de las UD cumplían los requisitos estructuralespara la asistencia neurológica, aunque el 21 % tenían menos de4 despachos para consulta y menos de 15 camas neurológicas. El 25%de las UD no cumplían los requisitos en lo referente a los facultativos deplantilla con dedicación a tiempo completo. Aunque prácticamente el100% cumplían los requisitos organizativos cuantitativos asistenciales,sólo el 69 % refirieron tener guardias de neurología, aunque porel diseño del cuestionario no es posible conocer su grado de tutorización.Prácticamente el 100% cumplen los requisitos de docencia einvestigación.Conclusiones. Aunque el grado de cumplimiento de los actualesCA es alto, existen deficiencias preocupantes, fundamentalmente enrelación al número de facultativos de plantilla contratados a tiempocompleto y a la disponibilidad de guardias de neurología debidamentetutorizadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(1): 45-49, ene.-feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las unidades docentes de neurología en España y cumplimientode los criterios de acreditación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
