<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99293</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyperthermia in top level athletes during competition. Importance on health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Hyperthermia (increases in core temperature above 38 ºC) induced by intense exercise causes central fatigue and reduces time to exhaustion during exercise in the heat. Moreover alter the prefontal cerebral area activity. The cited studies have been performed in a laboratory setting. However, it remains unclear if elite athletes experience hyperthermia during their competition and furthermore if that could negatively affect performance and health. Objective: The purpose of this study was to measure core temperature response to regular competition in elite athletes. Methods: Twenty-nine athletes (8 professional cyclists,12 rowers, 3 endurance runners of international level and6 international triathletes) were studied during competition. At least 3 hour prior to the exercise subjects ingested a pill containing a telemetric temperature sensor (Cor Temp TM Ingestible Thermometer, HQ Inc., USA) which signals were collected and recorded (Cor Temp TM 2000 Recorder; HQ Inc., USA) at rest and frequently during exercise. Dry bulb temperature and relative humidity were also recorded(Kestrel 4000 NK; Nielsen-Kelleman, USA). In addition heart rate was recorded using a telemetric unit (Accurex, Polar, Kempele, Finland). Results: The highest core temperatures recorded during competition ranged from 38.1 to 42.3 ºC with (average of 39.5 ºC). 5 out of the 29 athletes (17%) reached core temperatures above 40 ºC. The highest heart rates during competition ranged from 185 to 203 beats/min (average186 beats/min).Conclusion: In endurance sports during long lasting competitions events core temperature reaches high levels in elite athletes (39.5 ºC). Thus it is possible that endurance performance and health during competition could be affected by hyperthermia. It is necessary more research in endurance athletes during competition or training in the heat to evaluate the effect of core temperature in the central fatigue and health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calleja-González, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erauzkin, Julen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terrados, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leibar, Xabier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arratibel, Iñaki</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El ejercicio físico intenso puede causar un aumento de la temperatura central por encima de los 38 ºC (hipertermia), el cual puede inducir fatiga central, alterando la actividad del área prefrontal cerebral durante el ejercicio en ambientes calurosos demostrado en estudios realizados en laboratorio. Sin embargo, a pesar de que cuanto más intenso y duradero sea el ejercicio más podría aumentarla Tn, este fenómeno no ha sido estudiado en deportistas de élite en situaciones reales de entrenamiento regular y/ocompetición y tampoco si dicho incremento pudiera afectar negativamente a su rendimiento y a su salud. Objetivo: El objeto de estudio fue analizar la respuesta de la temperatura central en competición real en deportistas de alto rendimiento. Metodología: Veintinueve atletas (8 ciclistas profesionales,12 remeros, 3 corredores de resistencia internacionales y 6 triatletas de élite) fueron estudiados. Los sujetos ingirieron 3 horas antes de la competición una píldora que contiene un sensor telemétrico de temperatura interna (Cor Temp TM Ingestible Thermometer, HQ Inc., EE.UU.). También se registraron la temperatura ambiente y la humedad, así como la frecuencia cardiaca mediante una unidad telemétrica. Resultados: La temperatura central máxima registrada durante la competición fue de media de 39,5 ºC, con un rango de 38,1 a 42,3 ºC. Cinco de los 29 atletas (17%) llegaron a alcanzar temperatura cercana a los 40 ºC en condiciones ambientales normotermales (25 ºC). La frecuencia cardiaca osciló en rangos de 185 a 203 lat/min (media, 186). Conclusión: En deportes de resistencia de larga duración la temperatura central del deportista de élite puede llegar a valores muy altos, con medias de 39,5 ºC, lo que podría afectar al rendimiento y/o a la salud del deportista. Son necesarios más trabajos en atletas de resistencia durante competición y/o entrenamiento en situaciones ambientales de calor elevado para valorar el efecto del aumento de la Tn en la fatiga central y la salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;26(134): 430-434, nov.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99293</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipertermia en atletas de élite durante la competición. Importancia de su control para la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6508^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1856^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
