<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96415</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of tecnological variables and the university degree in the creativity ideational</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to examine the effects of three variables -computer tools, technological objects and university degree- in the generation of creative ideas so much to individual level as group. The research was carried out by a sample of 112 pupils of the Public University of Navarre (Spain) organized in different experimental and control groups according to the requirements of the raised hypotheses. The intervention consisted of the execution of activities that required the subjects the development of ideas on the following fields: solutions to a problem, utilities of some objects and improvements of other objects. The results revealed that the subjects that worked both with computer tools and with technological objects and that belonged to the degree of Technical Engineering in Computer Science of Management, enunciated major number of ideas in the different activities of intervention that the subjects that worked without computer tools, with conventional objects and that belonged to the degree of Social Work. Finally, some relevant conclusions offer in this study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz de Acedo Lizarraga, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ardaiz Villanueva, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz de Acedo Baquedano, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio fue examinar los efectos de tres variables -herramientas informáticas, objetos tecnológicos y titulación universitaria- en la generación de ideas creativas tanto a nivel individual como grupal. La investigación se llevó a cabo con una muestra de 112 alumnos de la Universidad Pública de Navarra (España) organizados en diferentes grupos experimentales y de control según las exigencias de las hipótesis planteadas. La intervención consistió en la ejecución de actividades que requerían a los sujetos la elaboración de ideas sobre los siguientes campos: soluciones a un problema, utilidades de algunos objetos y mejoras de otros objetos. Los resultados revelaron que los sujetos que trabajaron tanto con herramientas informáticas como con objetos tecnológicos y que pertenecían a la titulación de Ingeniería Técnica en Informática de Gestión, enunciaron mayor número de ideas en las distintas actividades de intervención que los sujetos que trabajaron sin herramientas informáticas, con objetos convencionales y que pertenecían a la titulación de Trabajo Social. Finalmente, se ofrecen en este estudio algunas conclusiones relevantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(1): 107-112, ene.-abr. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de variables tecnológicas y de la titulación universitaria en la creatividad ideacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19133^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19133^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19133^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19133^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51868^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19133^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
