<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-24554</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Asthma is one of the most common chronic chilhood disease. Asthmatic children need a self-management educational program, besides the medical treatment and clinical control. Camps are the ideal place to complete the educational program, to get the right control of the disease and to build the child confidence. Madrid Castilla la Mancha Allergy Society organizes every year a summer camp in a town, near Madrid. Fifty-four children stay for one week with certified allergists, fellows-in-training, nurses and cheer-leaders. Fifty-four children from 8 to 14 years old, with moderate to severe asthma participate in the camp. The camp includes educational, athletic and social activities. Campers participate daily in instructive and didactic teaching sessions. We evaluate quality of life with a questionaire filled in the camp and two months later. Results are analysed into two age groups, one between 8-10 years old and the other from 11 to 14 years old. The first group get a good management and improve their vision of the disease, quite the contrary, adolescents face up to a chronic disease with daily treatment, feeling asthma as a restriction of their autonomy. Even so, they identify crisis and learn to control them in an special risky life period. Asthma camps is a good experience for both groups and also for sanitary equipment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Jara, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapatero Remón, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Iglesias, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Molero, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:publisher>Ediciones Doyma, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El asma constituye una de las enfermedades crónicas más frecuentes de la infancia. Los niños asmáticos precisan una educación sanitaria integral, que abarca el tratamiento médico, el control clínico y un programa de autocuidados que les ayude a conseguir un control adecuado de la enfermedad. Los campamentos son probablemente el lugar más adecuado para impartir dicho programa de autocuidados. La Sociedad Madrid Castilla la Mancha de Alergología e Inmunología Clínica organiza anualmente un campamento de verano para asmáticos, cuyo emplazamiento es un espacio natural de dicha Comunidad Autónoma. Un grupo de 54niños con edades comprendidas entre 8 y 14 años, con asma persistente moderada o grave participan en el campamento. Los niños conviven una semana con alergólogos, residentes de la especialidad, enfermeras y monitores de tiempo libre. Las actividades diarias van de la educación sanitaria impartida por el equipo médico, a juegos y deportes dirigidos por el equipo de monitores. El interés principal es que el niño asmático se instruya en los autocuidados necesarios para un adecuado desarrollo físico y psíquico. El objetivo de nuestro estudio es evaluar la calidad de vida en niños asmáticos y la repercusión que tiene un programa de autocuidados en dicha calidad de vida. Los niños rellenan un mismo cuestionario en el campamento y 2 meses después analizamos los resultados separando dos grupos de edad, uno entre 8-10 años y el segundo entre 11 y 14 años de edad. Los resultados sugieren que el primer grupo adquiere un buen manejo, mejorando su visión de la enfermedad, por el contrario el grupo de adolescentes se enfrenta a una enfermedad crónica que requiere un tratamiento diario, lo que supone una restricción de su autonomía. No obstante aprenden a identificar y a controlar las crisis en un período con especial riesgo vital. Los campamentos para niños asmáticos son una buena experiencia para ambos grupos de edad al igual que para el equipo sanitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);31(4): 231-235, jul. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-24554</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asthma camp. Quality of life questionnaires</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2197</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
