<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96449</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of sociodemographic and clinical characteristics on quality of life and distress of cancer patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several studies have examined a range of clinical and socio-demographics factors as predictors or correlates of adjustment to cancer treatment. Findings varied across different studies by which characteristics were chosen to be examined. In spite of these issues, some factors emerged like modulators to the adjustment to cancer; age, gender, educational level, marital status, length of time since diagnosis, localized of tumor, late effects of cancer and/or its treatment, type of oncology treatment. Two measures are used, quality of life and distress, to assess the different sample characteristics related to cancer treatment. Other variables, coping styles and social support, have to be considered such as mediating factors which may exacerbate or ameliorate the patient&#146;s well-being. Particular areas have been highlighted in this literature review, initial theory research identified characteristics associated with adjustment to cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Costa, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Varios estudios han descrito una serie de factores sociodemográficos y clínicos como predictores o correlacionados con la respuesta adaptativa al tratamiento oncológico. Los hallazgos varían entre los diferentes estudios por las características escogidas para analizar. En este sentido, algunas variables emergen como moduladoras de la respuesta adaptativa al cáncer: edad, género, nivel educativo, estado marital, tiempo desde el diagnóstico, localización del tumor, efectos secundarios de cáncer o del tratamiento, tipo de tratamiento oncológico. Dos medidas son utilizadas, el índice de calidad de vida y malestar emocional, para evaluar las diferentes características de la muestra relacionadas con el tratamiento oncológico. Otras variables, estilo de afrontamiento y apoyo social, deben ser consideradas como factores mediadores que pueden exacerbar o aminorar el bienestar del paciente. En esta revisión teórica se han resaltado determinados aspectos que ayudan a identificar características asociadas a la respuesta adaptativa al cáncer. Several studies have examined a range of clinical and socio-demographics factors as predictors or correlates of adjustment to cancer treatment. Findings varied across different studies by which characteristics were chosen to be examined. In spite of these issues, some factors emerged like modulators to the adjustment to cancer; age, gender, educational level, marital status, length of time since diagnosis, localized of tumor, late effects of cancer and/or its treatment, type of oncology treatment. Two measures are used, quality of life and distress, to assess the different sample characteristics related to cancer treatment. Other variables, coping styles and social support, have to be considered such as mediating factors which may exacerbate or ameliorate the patient&#146;s well-being. Particular areas have been highlighted in this literature review, initial theory research identified characteristics associated with adjustment to cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);7(2/3): 453-462, dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96449</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de las características sociodemográficas y clínicas en la calidad de vida y malestar emocional del paciente oncológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
