<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87569</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adverse reactions to iodinated contrast media</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveThe aim of the study is to determine the incidence of adverse reactions to iodinated contrast media and to characterise them in a group of outpatients, inpatients and emergency patients in a private hospital in Barcelona.MethodA retrospective cohort study was carried out over a 60 months period, from February 2002 to February 2007, analysing the patients who underwent to iodinated contrast radiological examinations. Adverse reactions were evaluated from the manual record format developed following the requirements of the Quality Assurance Program in Radiology. Study variables were, administration route, contrast media dose, adverse reaction type, and signs and symptoms. Statistical analysis was descriptive.ResultsA total of 68 (0.3 %) of adverse reaction were registered of which 64 were mild (94.1%), 4 moderate (5.9%) and none severe. On the basis of the administration route (intravenous or oral) adverse reaction were 67 (94%) and 1 (6%) respectively. With a 40&#150;80ml contrast media dose by injection, mild adverse reactions were 87.5%, moderate 12.5% and severe 0%. With a 90&#150;150ml contrast media dose by injection, mild adverse reaction were 94.9% and moderate 5.1%.ConclusionsThe number of adverse reaction using iodinated contrast media is low and are they are generally mild; however the nurse must be ready to recognise and treat them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pernas-Canadell, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Rodríguez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Aguilar, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galimany-Masclans, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoLos objetivos del estudio fueron determinar la incidencia de las reacciones adversas al contraste yodado, así como conocer las características de las mismas en un grupo de pacientes de procedencia ambulatoria, hospitalizados y urgencias de un centro hospitalario privado de Barcelona.MétodoSe realizó un estudio de cohortes retrospectivo durante un periodo de 60 meses desde febrero de 2002 hasta febrero de 2007, analizando los pacientes sometidos a exploraciones de radiología con contraste yodado. Se evaluaron las reacciones adversas en el registro manual desarrollado en cumplimiento del Programa de Garantía de Calidad en Radiodiagnóstico. Las variables del estudio fueron vía de administración del contraste, dosis de contraste administrado, tipo de reacción adversa, signos y síntomas. El análisis estadístico realizado ha sido de tipo descriptivo.ResultadosLas reacciones adversas fueron 68 (0,3%), 64 leves (94,1%), 4 moderadas (5,9%) y 0 graves. En función de la vía de administración (endovenosa o oral) las reacciones fueron 67 (94%) y 1 (6%) respectivamente. En las inyecciones de contraste endovenoso con dosis entre 40 y 80ml, las reacciones leves fueron 87,5%, las moderadas el 12,5% y las graves el 0%. En la administración con dosis de contraste endovenoso entre 90 y 150ml, las reacciones leves fueron del 94,9% y las moderadas el 5,1%.ConclusionesEl número de reacciones adversas a los contrastes yodados utilizados en radiología es bajo y son leves, sin embargo, la enfermera debe estar preparada para reconocerlas y actuar ante ellas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);20(5): 297-300, sept.-oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87569</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reacciones adversas a los medios de contraste yodados en radiología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31384^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3306^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
