<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043737</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of IgM determination in acute serum for the diagnosis of dengue in an endemic area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We evaluated the clinical usefulness of dengue IgM detection in acute serum using an ELISA test in 167 patients with dengue and 225 patients with acute febrile syndrome of another etiology. The sensitivity of the test was 29.9%, specificity was 99.1%, positive predictive value was 96.2%, and negative predictive value was 65.6%. Because of the test's high specificity and positive predictive value, a positive result could support a diagnosis of dengue in endemic areas with a high degree of certainty; a negative result would require complementary studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ocasiones, Raquel Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Quijano, Fredi Alexander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Vega, Ruth Aralí</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar-Centeno, Luis Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se evaluaron las características operativas de la prueba de ELISA-IgM específica para dengue en el suero agudo de 167 pacientes con dengue y 225 con síndrome febril agudo de otra etiología. La prueba evidenció sensibilidad: 29,9%; especificidad: 99,1; valor predictivo positivo (VPP): 96,2%; valor predictivo negativo: 65,6%. Por su especificidad y VPP altos, un resultado positivo de la prueba podría soportar con alta certeza el diagnóstico de dengue en áreas endémicas; un resultado negativo requeriría estudios complementarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;24(2): 90-92, feb. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043737</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la prueba de IgM en suero agudo para el diagnóstico del dengue en un área endémica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3727^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d922^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3728^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22443</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22207^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
