<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125309</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usage, effectiveness and safety of abiraterone in prostate cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: After the marketing of Abiraterone, an androgen synthesis inhibitor, the aim of the study was to analyze its use, response, and safety in the population of a tertiary care level hospital. Materials and methods: A retrospective observational study was carried out including all patients that were started on Abiraterone within a 21-month period. Demographical, diagnostic, therapeutic, and clinical variables were gathered. The response  was assessed through the decreased of PSA as compared to baseline values. To assess the safety, all treatment-related adverse events were recorded. Results: A total of 45 patients were included of which 88.89%could be assessed for the drug effectiveness. The median baseline PSA value was 457.31 (range 9032-2.81). PSA decrease was &amp;#8805; 50%, &amp;#8805; 90% and &lt; 30% in 16 (40%), 3 (7.5%) y 20(50%), respectively. The most common grade 1-2 adverse events were fatigue (35.6%), increased liver enzymes (28.9%),hipokalemia (13.3%) and fluid retention (11.1%).Conclusions: Abiraterone was a well tolerated drug that has shown to be active in prostate cancer patients previously treated with taxans, so it has been postulated as an alternative in this pathology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrari Piquero, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortijo Cascajares, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Garrote, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro Teller, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano Valenciano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Tras la comercialización de abiraterona, inhibidor de la síntesis de andrógenos, el objetivo del estudio fue analizar el uso, la respuesta y la seguridad de abiraterona en la población de un hospital de tercer nivel. Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio observacional retrospectivo en el que se incluyeron todos los pacientes que iniciaron tratamiento con abiraterona en un periodo de 21 meses. Se recogieron variables demográficas, diagnósticas, terapéuticas y clínicas. La respuesta se evaluó de acuerdo con la reducción del PSA con respecto al basal. Para evaluar la seguridad se registraron todas las reacciones adversas secundarias al tratamiento. Resultados: Se incluyó un total de 45 pacientes de los que, fueron evaluables con respecto a la efectividad del fármaco el (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;38(2): 118-122, mar.-abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125309</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso, efectividad y seguridad de abiraterona en cáncer de próstata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54036^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
