<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97099</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study of violence against Spanish and foreign victims attended in a hospital emergency department in 2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To compare the profile of foreigners in Spain who are victims of violent attacks to the profile of Spanish victims. Methods: Retrospective observational single-centre study of victims of violent attacks who were treated in the emergency department in 2009. Variables collected were nationality, age, sex, type of violence, and diagnosis. Results: Medical records for 1714 victims were analyzed. Foreign and Spanish victims had different profiles. Foreigners suffered 41.2% of attacks, a higher percentage than their weight in the population, and they also sustained more serious injuries. The largest victim groups were from Latin America (14.7%), North Africa (8.8%), and Eastern Europe (8.7%). Chinese victims formed the smallest group (2.4%). The mean (SD) ages of Spanish and foreign victims were 36.4 (14.0) years and 32.1 (9.2) years, respectively (P&lt;.001). Significantly more men than women were victims in all groups (P&lt;.001). The percentages of men were similar for Spanish (59.6%) and foreign (61.0%) victims in general, with the exception of North Africans, a group in which many more men were victims (84%). Gender-related violence was more common among foreign-born victims (30.0%) than among Spanish victims (P&lt;.001). Latin Americans had the highest rate of gender-related violence at 40.2%, followed by Eastern Europeans (30.9%) and sub-Saharan Africans (28.7%). The percentage of gender-related violence among North Africans was low (15.2%). Most cases involved injuries not requiring medical treatment; 91.2% of the Spanish victims and 82.3% of the foreign-born victims were in that group (P&lt;.001). Injuries requiring some form of medical treatment (non specialist emergency care, specialized emergency care and/or hospitalization, and life-threatening injuries) were sustained by 5.5% of the Spanish born victims and 11.7% of the foreigners. North African victims most often required medical attention. (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Samanes Ara, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Egido Martínez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Jarreta, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bell Martínez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morellón Labarta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar el perfil de las víctimas de violencia extranjeras con el perfil de las víctimas españolas. Métodos: Estudio observacional unicéntrico retrospectivo de víctimas de agresiones asistidas en urgencias del Hospital Nuestra Señora de Gracia (HNSG) de Zaragoza durante el año 2009. Resultados: Se analizaron 1.714 pacientes víctimas de violencia. La población extranjera tenía características distintas a la población española, con una mayor tasa de agresiones(41,2%) y mayor gravedad de las lesiones. Los grupos mayoritarios procedían de Iberoamérica (14,7%), norte de África (8,8%) y Europa oriental (8,7%). Las víctimas de origen chino eran las menos numerosas (2,4%). La edad media de los españoles era 36,4 (DE: 14,0) y de los extranjeros 32,1 (DE: 9,2) (p &lt; 0,001). En todos los casos fue significativamente mayor el número de hombres que el de mujeres (p &lt; 0,001). No hubo diferencias entre la proporción de hombres españoles (59,6%) y la de extranjeros(61,0%), con la excepción de África del norte (84%). El número de agresiones a causa de la violencia de género fue mayor (p &lt; 0,001) entre los extranjeros (30,0%) que entre el grupo de españoles (20,5%). Los pacientes procedentes de Iberoamérica tuvieron la mayor tasa de violencia de género (40,2%). Le siguieron Europa oriental (30,9%) y África subsahariana (28,7%). Destaca la escasa presencia proporcional de África del norte con sólo un 15,2%. El diagnóstico más frecuente en todos los casos fue las lesiones que no necesitan ningún tratamiento médico, 91,2% en españoles, 82,3% en extranjeros(..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(4): 266-270, ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97099</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de las agresiones a españoles y a extranjeros atendidas en un servicio de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d378</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
