<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113229</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reliability of fall risk test of the Biodex Balance System ® platform in institutionalized elderly with fear of falling by 12 weeks test-retest</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of the present study was to analyze the reliability of the Fall Risk (FR) test of the Biodex Balance System® (BBS) platform in institutionalized elderly with fear of falling using a 12-weeks test-retest. Material and methods. Fourteen institutionalized elderly (n=14; 75.64±7.47 years; 74.29±15.52 kg) with fear of falling (FES- I score=32.57±7.52) participated in this study. A 12-week test-retest was performed. Each subject performed 3 trials (20 s each) for each measurement in the BBS platform at level 8 with a rest of 10 s between trials. The mean of the three trials was taken for each measurement. Results. The relative reliability of the described test was excellent (ICC=0,97). Regarding absolute reliability, a 9.9% standard error of measurement (SEM) was obtained with a 27.4% small real difference (SRD). The reliability of the BBS platform using Bland-Altman method showed that the systematic error (mean difference between test-retest) for the FR test was 0,25 (bias). Conclusion. The score obtained in the FR test evaluated with BBS platform is replicable for measurements of dynamic balance and fall risk in institutionalized elderly with fear of falling. This study provides new data for interpreting changes in the FR test score on BBS after the application of physical activity programs in this population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Triviño-Amigo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, P. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Mocholí, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adsuar-Sala, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corzo, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo del presente estudio es analizar la fiabilidad de la prueba Fall Risk (FR) de la plataforma Biodex Balance System® (BBS) en las personas mayores institucionalizadas con miedo a caerse mediante un test-retest de 12 semanas. Material y métodos. Participaron en el estudio 14 personas mayores institucionalizadas (75,64 ± 7,47 años; 74,29 ± 15,52 kg) con miedo a caerse (puntuación FES- I = 32,57 ± 7,52). Se realizó un test-retest de 12 semanas. Cada sujeto realizó 3 ensayos (20 s cada uno) en cada medición en la plataforma BBS a nivel 8 con un descanso de 10 s entre ensayos. Para cada medición se tomó la media de los 3 ensayos. Resultados. La fiabilidad relativa de la prueba descrita fue excelente (CCI = 0,97). En cuanto a la fiabilidad absoluta se obtuvo un error estándar de medida (EEM) del 9,9% y un mínimo cambio real (MCR) de 27,4%. La fiabilidad de la plataforma BBS usando el método Bland-Altman mostró que el error sistemático (diferencia de medias entre el test-retest) para la prueba FR fue 0,25 (bias). Conclusión. La puntuación obtenida en la prueba FR evaluada con la plataforma BBS es replicable para las mediciones de equilibrio dinámico y riesgo de caída en personas mayores institucionalizadas con miedo a caerse. Este estudio proporciona nuevos datos para la interpretación de los cambios producidos en la puntuación de la prueba FR de BBS tras la aplicación de programas de actividad física en esta población(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);47(2): 64-70, abr.-jun.2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113229</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiabilidad de la prueba Fall Risk de la plataforma Biodex Balance System® en las personas mayores institucionalizadas con miedo a caerse mediante test-retest de 12 semanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
