<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050497</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The impact of economics on health policy and management in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Despite the intrinsic value of scientific disciplines,such as Economics, it is appropriate to gauge the impact of itsapplications on social welfare, or at least &#150;Health Economics' (HE)case&#150; its influence on health policy and management.Methods: The three relevant features of knowledge (production,diffusion and application) are analyzed, more from an 'emic' perspective&#150;the one used in Anthropology relying on the experience ofthe members of a culture&#150; than from an 'etic' approach seated onmaterial descriptions and dubious statistics.Results: The soundness of the principles and results of HEdepends on its disciplinary foundations, whereas its relevance &#150;thandoes not imply translation into practice&#150; is more linked with the problemsstudied. Important contributions from Economics to the healthsphere are recorded. HE in Spain ranks seventh in the world despitethe relatively minor HE contents of its clinical and health servicesresearch journals. HE has in Spain more presence than influence,having failed to impregnate sufficiently the daily events.Conclusions: HE knowledge required by a politician, a healthmanager or a clinician is rather limited; the main impact of HE couldbe to develop their intuition and awareness</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meneu de Guillerna, Ricard </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortún Rubio, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Las disciplinas científicas, como la Economía,tienen valor per se, conviene, sin embargo, aproximar el impacto desus aplicaciones en el bienestar social, o como mínimo &#150;caso de laEconomía de la Salud (ES)&#150; en la política y gestión sanitarias.Métodos: Se atiende a las tres vertientes relevantes del conocimiento(producción de nuevo conocimiento, difusión y aplicación)utilizando más la perspectiva 'emic' &#150;la empleada en antropologíabasándose en la experiencia de los integrantes de una cultura&#150;, que laperspectiva 'etic' asentada en descripciones materiales y dudosasestadísticas.Resultados: La solidez de los principios y resultados de la ESdepende de la base disciplinaria en la que se apoya, mientras que surelevancia &#150;que no su traslación a la práctica&#150; está vinculada a la delas cuestiones a las que atiende. Se registran las aportaciones relevantesde la Economía al ámbito sanitario. El grado de desarrollo dela ES en España resulta notable: séptima posición mundial pese a losrelativamente menores contenidos de ES en las revistas clínicas y deinvestigación sobre servicios sanitarios de España. La ES tiene enEspaña más presencia que influencia, no habiendo logrado impregnarsuficientemente la práctica diaria.Conclusiones: Los conocimientos de Economía que necesita unpolítico o un gestor sanitario o un clínico son limitados; el impactode la ES pasará, sobre todo, por educarles el olfato</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(5): 491-504, sept.-oct. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050497</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la economía en la política y gestión sanitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6442</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32497</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16672</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
