<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135653</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Greater adherence to a mediterranean dietary pattern is associated with improved plasma lipid profile: the Aragon health Workers Study Cohort</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: There is wide recognition of the importance of healthy eating in cardiovascular health promotion. The purpose of this study was to identify the main dietary patterns among a Spanish population, and to determine their relationship with plasma lipid profiles. Methods: A cross-sectional analysis was conducted of data from 1290 participants of the Aragon Workers Health Study cohort. Standardized protocols were used to collect clinical and biochemistry data. Diet was assessed through a food frequency questionnaire, quantifying habitual intake over the past 12 months. The main dietary patterns were identified by factor analysis. The association between adherence to dietary patterns and plasma lipid levels was assessed by linear and logistic regression. Results: Two dietary patterns were identified: a Mediterranean dietary pattern, high in vegetables, fruits, fish, white meat, nuts, and olive oil, and a Western dietary pattern, high in red meat, fast food, dairy, and cereals. Compared with the participants in the lowest quintile of adherence to the Western dietary pattern, those in the highest quintile had 4.6 mg/dL lower high-density lipoprotein cholesterol levels (P &lt; .001), 8 mg/dL lower apolipoprotein A1 levels (P = .005) and a greater risk of having decreased high-density lipoprotein cholesterol (odds ratio = 3.19; 95% confidence interval, 1.36-7.5; P-trend = .03). Participants adhering to the Mediterranean dietary pattern had 3.3 mg/dL higher high-density lipoprotein cholesterol levels (P &lt; .001), and a ratio of triglycerides to high-density lipoprotein cholesterol that was 0.43 times lower (P = .043). Conclusions: Adherence to the Mediterranean dietary pattern is associated with improved lipid profile compared with a Western dietary pattern, which was associated with a lower odds of optimal high-density lipoprotein cholesterol levels in this population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Uzhova, Irina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sotos-Prieto, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León-Latre, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñalvo, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Franco, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordovás, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos Hay un amplio reconocimiento de la importancia de una dieta saludable para la promoción de la salud cardiovascular. El objetivo de este estudio es identificar los principales patrones alimentarios en la población española y determinar su relación con los perfiles lipídicos plasmáticos. Métodos Se llevó a cabo un análisis transversal de los datos obtenidos en 1.290 participantes de la cohorte del Aragon Workers Health Study. Se utilizaron protocolos estandarizados para la obtención de datos clínicos y bioquímicos. Se evaluó la dieta a través de un cuestionario de frecuencia de alimentación, cuantificando el consumo habitual durante los 12 meses previos. Se identificaron los principales patrones de dieta mediante un análisis factorial. Se evaluó la asociación entre la adherencia a los patrones de dieta y las concentraciones plasmáticas de lípidos mediante regresión lineal y logística. Resultados Se identificaron dos patrones de dieta: un patrón de dieta mediterránea, rica en verduras, frutas, pescado, carnes blancas, frutos secos y aceite de oliva, y un patrón de dieta occidental, rico en carnes rojas, comida rápida, productos lácteos y cereales. En comparación con los participantes que se encontraban en el quintil más bajo de adherencia al patrón de dieta occidental, los que se encontraban en el quintil más alto presentaron cifras de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad 4,6 mg/dl menores (p &lt; 0,001) y de apolipoproteína A1, 8 mg/dl menores (p = 0,005) y mayor riesgo de mostrar una disminución del colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad (odds ratio = 3,19; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,36-7,5; p de tendencia = 0,03). Los participantes con adherencia al patrón de dieta mediterránea presentaron cifras de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad 3,3 mg/dl mayores (p &lt; 0,001) y un cociente de triglicéridos/colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(4): 290-297, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135653</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La mayor adherencia a un patrón de dieta mediterránea se asocia a una mejora del perfil lipídico plasmático: la cohorte del Aragon Health Workers Study</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
