<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121508</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Internal nasal valve and aesthetic rhinoplasty</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper, we sand out the presence of a strait or valve in the nostrils, and about it, it's specifically investigated it's anterior portion known in Plastic Surgery as internal nasal valve (INV). Characteristics, provision and relations of its individual components are discussed, specifically pointing out the ubique behavior of the valvular mucosal epithelium in connection with the triangular and quadrangular cartilage. We warn out the possibility of postoperative complications in case of improper surgical valvular treatment and we attach preparations and their corresponding drawings in order to make easy the understanding of the observed facts (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arruñada, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giacomotti, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ottone, N. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertone, V. H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cirigliano, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oloriz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Distinguimos en las fosas nasales la presencia de un estrecho o válvula y, de ella, investigamos específicamente su porción anterior conocida en Cirugía Plástica como válvula nasal interna (VNI). Analizamos en este artículo las características, disposición y relaciones de sus distintos componentes, puntualizando específicamente el singular comportamiento del mucoepitelio valvular con respecto a los cartílagos triangulares y cuadrangular. Advertimos sobre la posibilidad de complicaciones postoperatorias en el caso de indebido trato valvular durante la cirugía y adjuntamos preparados y sus correspondientes dibujos con el propósito de facilitar la comprensión de los hechos observados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;39(4): 321-326, oct.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121508</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Válvula nasal interna y rinoplastia estética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52966^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9491^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
