<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111894</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis and management of an adult patient with type1A diabetes at disease onset</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 1 diabetes mellitus is a chronic, autoimmune disease, where specific pancreatic &amp;#946;-cell destruction leads to complete insulin deficiency.Management of the patient at diagnosis includes patient education (training in insulin self-injection, self-monitoring of glucose and ketone levels, prevention and management of hypoglycaemia&#133;) and intensive insulin treatment, aimed at achieving glucose concentrations as close to normal as safely possible and avoiding hypoglycaemia. Screening for associated thyroid and coeliac diseases is recommended at the onset of type1 diabetes. Pancreatic auto-antibody measurement, however, is only recommended in case of diagnostic uncertainly. The measurement of stimulated C-peptide after a mixed meal is the reference method to assess endogenous insulin production, although its use is currently limited to intervention trials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serra, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guanyabens, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes tipo1 (DM1) es una enfermedad autoinmune crónica en la que se produce una destrucción progresiva de las células &amp;#946; pancreáticas que conduce a una deficiencia absoluta de insulina.El manejo al principio incluye educación diabetológica básica (administración de insulina, determinación de glucemia capilar y cetonuria, prevención y manejo de la hipoglicemia...). Mediante la instauración de un tratamiento intensivo con insulina se persigue el objetivo de mantener los niveles de glucemia lo más próximos a la normalidad de forma segura, evitando la aparición de hipoglucemias. Se recomienda el cribado de la enfermedad tiroidea y celíaca al inicio, pero no la determinación de los anticuerpos antipancreáticos. La prueba de la tolerancia oral a la comida mixta es la de elección para valorar la función pancreática, pero no se utiliza de forma rutinaria en la práctica clínica habitual y suele reservarse para estudios de intervención al inicio de la DM1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;29(2): 36-43, mar.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico y manejo del paciente adulto con diabetes tipo 1A al inicio de la enfermedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2130</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24529^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24529^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24529^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
