<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045541</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ankle/arm index and cardiovascular risk estimated by SCORE function in non-diabetic subjects in primary prevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The ankle/arm index (ABI) has high sensitivity and specificity in detecting peripheral artery disease (PAD). An abnormal ABI is associated with a high risk of arteriosclerosis in other vascular territories. The objectives of this study were to evaluate the prevalence of an abnormal ABI depending on cardiovascular risk (CVR) status calculated through the Systematic Coronary Risk Evaluation (SCORE) function, to study the variables associated with an abnormal ABI, and to determinate which subjects in the group with moderate risk have a high prevalence of abnormal ABI.   Subjects and methods. A total of 1,001 subjects between the ages of 60 and 79 years, with no history of cardiovascular disease or diabetes were studied. ABI was measured and their cardiovascular disease risk status was calculated using the tables of the SCORE project for populations in southern Europe.   Results. An abnormal ABI was found in 6.4% of the population. High CVR (10-year risk é 5%) was found in 17.5%, moderate CVR (10-year risk between 3-4%) was found in 31.1%, and low CVR (10-year risk 60 years without diabetes or cardiovascular disease indicates the need for therapeutic changes and investigation of arteriosclerosis in other vascular territories in 1 out of every 8 high risk subjects and in 1 out of every 11 moderate risk subjects. In the moderate risk group, ABI determination is more efficient in subjects with glucemia é 110 mg/dl (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lahoz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taboada, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mostaza, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El índice tobillo-brazo (ITB) es una prueba con alta sensibilidad y especificidad para la detección de enfermedad arterial periférica (EAP) y que, cuando es patológico, se asocia a un mayor riesgo de arteriosclerosis en otros territorios vasculares. Los objetivos de este estudio fueron evaluar la prevalencia de un ITB patológico en función del riesgo cardiovascular calculado mediante la función SCORE, estudiar las variables asociadas con un ITB patológico y determinar qué sujetos del grupo con riesgo intermedio presentan una mayor prevalencia de ITB patológico.   Sujetos y métodos. Se ha estudiado a un total de 1.001 sujetos, con edades comprendidas entre los 60 y los 79 años, sin antecedentes de enfermedad cardiovascular o diabetes. A todos se les determinó el ITB y se valoró su riesgo cardiovascular utilizando las tablas del proyecto SCORE para poblaciones del sur de Europa.   Resultados. El 6,4% de la población presentaba un ITB patológico. Un 17,5% de los participantes tenía un riesgo cardiovascular elevado (é 5% a 10 años), un 31,3% intermedio (3-4% a 10 años) y el resto bajo (&lt; 3% a 10 años). El porcentaje de ITB patológico en estos 3 grupos fue del 11,9, 8,9 y 3,3%, respectivamente (p &lt; 0,001). La edad, el consumo de tabaco, la hipertensión arterial, la glucemia y el colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad (cHDL) (de forma inversa) se asociaron significativamente con un ITB patológico en el análisis multivariante. En el grupo con riesgo intermedio sólo aquellos sujetos con una glucemia é 110 mg/dl tenían un significativo mayor porcentaje de ITB patológico que aquellos con una glucemia menor (el 18,9 frente al 7,6%;  p = 0,023).   Conclusiones. La determinación del ITB en sujetos mayores de 60 años sin enfermedad cardiovascular ni diabetes obliga a cambios terapéuticos y a la búsqueda de arteriosclerosis en otros territorios vasculares en 1 de cada 8 sujetos con riesgo cardiovascular elevado, y en 1 de cada 11 con riesgo intermedio. En este último grupo es más eficiente la determinación en aquellos con una glucemia é 110 mg/dl (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);18(2): 45-50, mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045541</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Índice tobillo-brazo y riesgo cardiovascular estimado mediante la función SCORE en sujetos no diabéticos en prevención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1136^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d856^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16843</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
