<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103910</identifier>
<setSpec>1697-641X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Damage to lingual nerve following extraction of third lower molars: Systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Damage to the lingual nerve during surgery on the third lower molar is a relatively frequent complication. The dentist should therefore be aware of what situations may influence an increase in the frequency of damage to that nerve. Aims: Establish the frequency of damage to the lingual nerve during extraction of third molars and identify the principal risk factors, as well as the evolution and the period of time within which most nervous recovery takes place. Material and Method: A bibliographic review was conducted with a PubMed search, obtaining a total of 24 articles published between 1988 and 2011. The variables analysed were age, sex, position of the third molar, lingual flap retraction, the carrying out of ostectomies and tooth sectioning, the lingual split technique and the number of recoveries of the nerve according to the time passed from when the damage occurred. Results: The frequency obtained for the damage was 3.54 %, with a statistically significant relationship being found for the following variables: position, retraction of the lingual flap, conducting ostectomies, the lingual split technique. On the contrary, no relationship was found for sex nor for tooth sectioning. 83.5% of the patients showed nervous recovery three months after the damage occurred. Conclusion: Distoangular position, retraction of the lingual flap, ostectomies and the lingual split technique carry an increased risk of damage to the lingual nerve in surgery on the third lower molar. The majority of cases presented recovery present within the first three months (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barona Dorado, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leco Berrocal, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fábrega, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, Jose M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La lesión del nervio lingual en la cirugía del tercer molar inferior es una complicación relativamente frecuente. Por ello, el odontólogo debe conocer qué situaciones pueden influir sobre un aumento en la frecuencia de damnificación de dicho nervio. Objetivos: Establecer la frecuencia de lesión del nervio lingual tras exodoncias de terceros molares e identificar los principales factores de riesgo, así como su evolución y el periodo de tiempo donde se producen un mayor número de recuperaciones nerviosas. Material y método: Se ha realizado una revisión bibliográfica realizando una búsqueda en la base de datos de PubMed, obteniéndose un total de 24 artículos comprendidos entre los años 1988 y 2011. Las variables analizadas fueron la edad, sexo, posición del tercer molar, retracción del colgajo lingual, realización de ostectomía y odontosección, la técnica lingual split y el número de reparaciones nerviosas en función del tiempo transcurrido desde el inicio de la lesión. Resultados: La frecuencia obtenida de la lesión fue de un 3,54 % encontrándose relación estadísticamente significativa para las variables: posición, retracción del colgajo lingual, realización de ostectomías, la técnica lingual split. Por el contrario no se encontró relación para el sexo y la realización de odontosección. El 83,5% de los pacientes presentaban recuperación nerviosa a los tres meses del inicio de la lesión. Conclusión: La posición distoangular, la retracción del colgajo lingual, la realización de ostectomías y la técnica lingual split conllevan un aumento del riesgo de lesión del nervio lingual en la cirugía del tercer molar inferior. El mayor número de recuperaciones se presentan durante los tres primeros meses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cient. dent. (Ed. impr.);9(2): 23-28, mayo-ago. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103910</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesión del nervio lingual tras exodoncias de terceros molares inferiores. Revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54511^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9154^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14473^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
