<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045094</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Substitution of primary care with specialized care. Some questions about the follow-up of patients with heart failure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Care of chronic patients poses clinical and organizational challenges that are deficiently resolved in the daily practice. The key question is achievement of maximum quality of life. Chronic health problems do not generally pose diagnostic or therapeutic challenges, but those of organization and cooperation (between health care levels and between these with social services, with the patient and their family). Thus, care to patients with heart failure is deficient worldwide, also in Spain. Response to this deficiency is not generally improvement of primary care but rather its substitution by specialized care. Thus, super-specialized programs have been developed. These are dependent on heart failure hospital units, and obtain unquestionable success through the providing of low technology services, characteristic of primary care. The clinical question is extensively reviewed through response to four practical questions and the importance of home care is demonstrated in this text</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Seminario de Innovación 2005</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La atención a los pacientes crónicos plantea retos clínicos y de organización que se resuelven deficientemente en la práctica diaria. La cuestión clave es el logro de la máxima calidad de vida. Los problemas crónicos de salud no suelen plantear retos diagnósticos ni terapéuticos, sino de organización y de cooperación (entre niveles sanitarios, y de éstos con los servicios sociales, con el paciente y con su familia). Por ello, la atención a los pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca es deficiente en todo el mundo, también en España. La respuesta a esta deficiencia no suele ser la mejora de la Atención Primaria, sino su sustitución por la atención especializada. Así, se han desarrollado programas superespecializados, dependientes de unidades hospitalarias de insuficiencia cardíaca, que obtienen indudable éxito a través de la prestación de servicios de baja tecnología, propios de la Atención Primaria. En este texto se revisa a fondo la cuestión clínica, a través de la respuesta a cuatro preguntas prácticas, y se demuestra la importancia de la atención a domicilio</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(3): 125-131, mar. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sustitución de la primaria por la especializada. Algunas cuestiones en torno al seguimiento de los pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29655</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17209^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
