<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74986</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early diagnosis of invasive fungal infections of caused by Aspergillus and other emerging mycelial fungi</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The usefulness of surrogate markers in the diagnosis of invasive fungalinfections caused by Aspergillus and other emerging mycelial fungi is basedon the ability of surrogate markers to detect the infection caused by differentspecies of mycelial fungi. Conventional microbiological methods for diagnosisof fungal disease are slow and insensitive. Antigen based assays ormeasurement of (1-3)-ß-D-glucan in blood have been developed and validatedin clinical laboratories. We review these diagnostic contemporary tools, theirclinical application and impact(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuétara, M. Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacio, Amalia del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alhambra, almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pontón, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilidad de los marcadores serológicos en el diagnóstico de las infeccionesfúngicas invasoras causadas por Aspergillus y otros hongos filamentososemergentes se fundamenta en la capacidad de estos marcadores de detectarla infección causada por las distintas especies de hongos filamentosos.Los procedimientos microbiológicos tradicionales para el diagnóstico de lainfección fúngica son lentos y poco sensibles. La detección de antígenoso de (1-3)-ß-D-glucano en sangre han sido desarrollados y validados enlaboratorios clínicos. Se revisan estas nuevas herramientas diagnósticas,así como su aplicación clínica e impacto(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;24(3): 187-197, 2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74986</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado actual del diagnóstico precoz de las infecciones invasoras causadas por Aspergillus y otros hongos filamentosos emergentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30095^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1235^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
