<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112157</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of Short Dental Anxiety Inventory among mexican adult patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since it is important to assess anxiety during the dental procedures and there is a brief, reliable and valid instrument for this purpose, the Short Dental Anxiety Inventory (SDAI), it would be relevant to contrast its psychometric properties in Mexico where it has not been studied yet. The aims of this study were to contrast a single-factor structure for the SDAI, estimate its internal consistency, describe its distribution, and study its relationship with sociodemographic variables. The SDAI was applied to a non-probability sample of 384 patients (67% female and 33% male) with a mean age of 36 years old (SD = 15.1). By scale-free least squares the single-factor model fit was good; by generalized least squares, it was adequate, and good after introducing four correlations between the residuals. The internal consistency was high. The distribution was positively skewed and showed positive kurtosis. Women averaged significantly higher than men on the SDAI total score. Its use in Mexico is suggested and building normative criteria by percentile scores according to sex is recommended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montoya Flores, Blanca Idalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cázares de León, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moral de la Rubia, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ya que es importante evaluar la ansiedad en procedimientos dentales y existe un instrumento breve, confiable y válido para este fin, como el Inventario de Ansiedad Dental versión corta (SDAI), sería pertinente contrastar sus propiedades psicométricas en México donde no se han estudia-do aún. Esta investigación tuvo como objetivos contrastar la estructura unidimensional del SDAI, estimar su consistencia interna, describir su distri-bución y estudiar su relación con variables socio-demográficas. Se aplicó el SDAI a una muestra no probabilística de 384 pacientes (67% mujeres y 33% hombres) con una media de 36 años de edad (DT = 15.1). Por mínimos cuadrados libres de es-cala el ajuste del modelo unidimensional fue bue-no; por mínimos cuadrados generalizados fue ade-cuado y bueno tras introducir cuatro correlaciones entre residuos. La consistencia interna fue alta y la distribución asimétrica positiva y apuntada. La media de las mujeres fue mayor que la de los hom-bres. Se sugiere su uso en México y su baremación por percentiles diferentes para cada sexo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;19(1): 105-119, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112157</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación del Inventario de Ansiedad Dental Versión Corta en pacientes adultos mexicanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30162^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29368^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
