<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132275</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Guidelines for the Diagnosis and Monitoring of Silicosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Silicosis is one of the occupational respiratory diseases most commonly encountered in our setting. It is caused by inhalation of crystalline silica that triggers a fibrotic response in the lung parenchyma. It presents as diffuse interstitial disease and clinical expression ranges from asymptomatic forms to chronic respiratory failure. Diagnosis is based on clinical history and radiological findings. There is no effective treatment, and once diagnosed, the patient must avoid all sources of occupational exposure. In these guidelines, the clinical, radiological and functional aspects of silicosis are reviewed, and strategies for diagnosis, monitoring and classification of patients are proposed, along with recommendations regarding the occupational implications of this disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Álvarez, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quero Martínez, Aida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Pérez, José Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Fernández, Amador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez González, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carazo Fernández, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La silicosis es una de las enfermedades respiratorias de origen ocupacional más frecuentes en nuestro entorno. Está ocasionada por inhalación de sílice cristalina que desencadena una respuesta fibrótica en el parénquima pulmonar. Se presenta como una enfermedad intersticial difusa y su expresión clínica es variable, existiendo desde formas asintomáticas hasta la insuficiencia respiratoria crónica. El diagnóstico está basado en la historia clínica y los hallazgos radiológicos; no tiene un tratamiento efectivo, y cuando se diagnostica precisa que el paciente sea apartado de toda fuente de exposición laboral. Esta normativa repasa aspectos clínicos, radiológicos y funcionales, sugiriendo también estrategias de diagnóstico y seguimiento para la clasificación de los pacientes, y recomendaciones para las implicaciones laborales de esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(2): 86-93, feb. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132275</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Normativa para el diagnóstico y seguimiento de la silicosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11438^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28165^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
