<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90113</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of effort-induced venous thrombosis of the upper limb</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">IntroductionApplying appropriate treatment for subclavian deep vein thrombosis may reduce long-term sequels.ObjectiveTo analyse the long-term clinical results of those patients treated in for upper body stress thrombosis in our Department.Materials and methodsA retrospective study (period 1986-2009) was conducted on 29 patients diagnosed with Venous Thoracic Outlet Syndrome (TOS) without pacemaker, neoplasia, previous vein access, or history of haemodialysis. The subjects included 11 women and 18 men, with a mean age of 38 years. More than half of the study subjects had jobs or took part in a sport activity involving acute stress of pectoral girdle. The diagnosis was made using Duplex Ultrasound With Venography. Treatment consisted of: anti-coagulation: 5; fibrinolysis: 9; surgery: 2; fibrinolysis+surgery: 13. Fibrinolysis was total or partially successful in 77% of cases (17 out of the 22 treated with Urokinase), two of them needing a further thrombectomy. Decompression surgery was used in 15 cases; 59% of the patients who had been treated with fibrinolysis, 4 via transaxillary approach, 2 supraclavicular and 9 supra- and infraclavicular combined. All patients but one had first rib resection, half of them had scalenectomy.ResultsEarly complications: one patient required post-intervention because of bleeding. There were no late complications. Seven patients were lost during follow up (126 months on average). In the long-term, 68% of interviewed patients remained asymptomatic, 73% of of them were subjected to decompression surgery.ConclusionsIn our series, patients who had a venous TOC decompression surgery after extrinsic compression, showed better long-term clinical results than those not operated on(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Berges, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feijoo Cano, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marzo Álvarez, A. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco Luque, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera Rodríguez, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">IntroducciónEl correcto tratamiento de la trombosis venosa profunda (TVP) subclavia puede disminuir la secuela a largo plazo.ObjetivoAnalizar el resultado clínico a largo plazo de los pacientes tratados en nuestro servicio de trombosis venosa de esfuerzo en el miembro superior.Material y métodosEstudio retrospectivo (1986-2009). Veintinueve pacientes diagnosticados de TVP subclavia sin antecedente de marcapasos, neoplasia, accesos venosos o de hemodiálisis. Once mujeres y 18 hombres, edad media 38 años. Más de la mitad con trabajos o deportes con sobreesfuerzo de la cintura escapular. Diagnóstico: flebografía y/o ecodoppler. Tratamiento: anticoagulación: 5, fibrinólisis y anticoagulación: 9, cirugía y anticoagulación: 2, fibrinólisis, cirugía y anticoagulación: 13. La fibrinólisis (urokinasa) fue total o parcialmente efectiva en el 77% de los casos (17 de los 22 tratados con urokinasa), en 2 de ellos trombectomía adicional. Cirugía descompresiva en 15 casos: el 59% de los tratados con fibrinólisis; 4 abordajes vía transaxilar, 2 supraclavicular y 9 suprainfraclavicular. En todos los pacientes salvo en uno, resección de primera costilla asociando escalenectomía en todos. Evaluamos la secuela mediante test de calidad de vida QuickDASH y permeabilidad de la vena mediante ecodoppler.ResultadosComplicaciones precoces: una reintervención por sangrado. No complicaciones tardías. Seguimiento medio 126 meses. Siete pacientes perdidos en el seguimiento. A largo plazo, el 68% asintomáticos, de estos, el 73% sometidos a cirugía descompresiva.ConclusionesEn nuestra serie, los pacientes con TVP de esfuerzo sometidos a cirugía descompresiva, presentan un mejor resultado clínico a largo plazo que los no intervenidos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;63(2): 51-58, mar.-abr. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la trombosis venosa de esfuerzo en el miembro superior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5453</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23418^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1379^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23502^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13738^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1379^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13738^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
