<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92003</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Defensive Anality and Anal Narcissism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper aims at demonstrating a currently beleaguered assumption: the central importance, the continuing vitality, and the appropriate complexity of Freud´s theory of the drives and of his idea of the primacy of the body ego. It is not enough to consider man a thinking machine or a social being; his animal nature must be given a central place in psychology. The paper postulates that &lt;anal or sphincter defensiveness&gt; is one of the precursors of the repression barrier. Anality has been comparatively neglected in recent psychoanalytic literature, and so has its explorer, Karl Abraham. The paper´s thesis is that there is a special defensive importance to anal erogeneity and libido, and to those aspects of ego and superego that are functionally operative (as the &lt;sadistic - anal organization&gt;; Freud 1917) during the so-called &lt;sadistic-anal&gt; developmental phase. Any of the psychic danger situations can evoke regression to manifestations of &lt;anal narcissism&gt;; an attempt to master overwhelming feeling by a kind of emotional sphincter action, narrowing down the world to the controllable and the predictable. The basic assumption here is Fliess´s idea that the attainment of anal sphincter control functions -with, as-it-were, &lt;psychic resonance&gt; - as a means to master primal (murderous, cannibalistic) affect. For optimal psychic development, a proper balance must be attained between anal control of, and anal expression of, instinctual derivatives - especially of affect laden with aggression (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Shengold, Leonard</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo trata de demostrar un supuesto que con frecuencia se refuta hoy en día: la importancia central, la continua vitalidad y la apropiada complejidad de la teoría de Freud de las pulsiones y su idea de la prioridad del  yo corporal. No es suficiente considerar al hombre como una máquina que piensa o como un ser social; su naturaleza animal debe ocupar un lugar central en la psicología. Este artículo postula que la &lt;defensividad anal o de los esfínteres&gt; es uno de los precursores de la barrera represiva. A la analidad se le ha dado relativamente poca importancia en los escritos analíticos recientes, y lo mismo le ha ocurrido a su explorador: Karl Abraham. En este trabajo se postula que hay una especial importancia defensiva en la erogenidad anal y en la libido, y en aquellos aspectos del yo y del superyó que funcionan y actúan durante la llamada fase evolutiva &lt;sádico-anal&gt; (&lt;organización sádico-anal&gt;; Freud, 1917). Cualquier situación de peligro psíquico puede provocar una regresión a manifestaciones de &lt;narcisismo anal&gt;, un intento de controlar el sentimiento abrumador con una acción emocional semejante a l del esfínter, reduciendo el mundo a lo controlable y predecible El supuesto básico del que partimos es la idea de Fliess de que el logro de funciones de control del esfínter anal con, como si dijéramos, resonancias psíquicas, es un medio de dominar sentimientos primitivos (asesinos, caníbales). Para lograr un desarrollo psíquico óptimo se debe obtener un equilibrio adecuado entre el control anal y la expresión anal de los derivados instintivos, especialmente de los sentimientos cargados de agresión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(60): 33-82, nov. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92003</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analidad defensiva y narcisismo anal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10659</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
