<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036172</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changing trends in HIV epidemics: recent diagnoses in the Spanish VACH cohort (2000-2002)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND. Studying the changing trends of HIV epidemics is a useful means of evaluating the results of current preventive plans as well as of defining future needs and objectives. METHODS. We performed a cross-sectional study of the newly-diagnosed cases of HIV infection included in the Spanish VACH cohort. New HIV cases were defined as those diagnosed between January 2001 and December 2002. Their epidemiologic characteristics were compared with those of patients included in the same cohort who had been diagnosed between January 1998 and December 2000. RESULTS. We studied 603 new cases (27% women). In 146 (24.4%) HIV infection had been acquired by sharing material for intravenous drug use (IVDU), 171 (28,6%) were men who had had sex with other men (MSM) and 247 (41.3%) acknowledged some risk for heterosexual HIV transmission. The median age was 36 years (range: 18-80).Only 1.5% of the patients were younger than 20 years while 32.1% were older than 40 years. This percentage was significantly higher than that corresponding to 1998-2000 (27.5%; p &lt; 0,05). HIV infection was diagnosed simultaneously with an AIDS-defining condition in 13.3% of patients and an AIDS-defining disease was diagnosed in the first month after HIV-diagnosis in another 40 patients (6.6%). CONCLUSIONS. We confirm the trends observed in previous studies: a growing proportion of newly diagnosed cases among women, a decreasing proportion of IVDU, a growth of MSM, and a trend toward diagnosis at a later age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cosín, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca, Bernardino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viciana, Pompeyo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Alcalde, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terrón, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domingo, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guijo, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribas, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teira, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Pepa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Sanz, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Lozano, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Trinitario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergara, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ANTECEDENTES. El estudio de los cambios en las tendencias de la epidemia del virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana(VIH) constituye un método útil para evaluar los resultados de los planes preventivos actuales, así como para definir futuras necesidades y objetivos de los próximos. MÉTODOS. Estudio descriptivo transversal de los casos nuevos incluidos en la cohorte VACH. Definimos &#147;caso nuevo&#148; a los sujetos cuyo diagnóstico de infección por el VIH se realizó entre enero de 2001 y diciembre de 2002. Comparamos sus características epidemiológicas con las de los sujetos incluidos en la misma cohorte diagnosticados de infección por el VIH entre enero de 1998 y diciembre de 2000. RESULTADOS. Estudiamos 603 nuevos casos (27% mujeres).En 146 (24,4%) el riesgo de transmisión había sido el uso de drogas (usuarios de drogas por vía parenteral, UDVP),171 (28,6%) eran hombres que tuvieron relaciones sexuales con otros hombres (HSH) y 247 (41,3%) reconocían alguna exposición heterosexual de riesgo. La mediana de edad fue 36 años (límites: 16-80). Solamente 1,5% tenían menos de 20 años y 32,1% superaban 40 años. Este porcentaje fue significativamente superior al correspondiente al trienio 98-00 (27,5%; p &lt; 0,05). La infección por VIH se diagnosticó simultáneamente con alguna complicación definitoria de sida en 13,3% casos y otros 40 pacientes (6,6%) la desarrollaron durante el primer mes tras el diagnóstico. CONCLUSIONES. Confirmamos las tendencias observadas en estudios previos: crecimiento de la proporción de mujeres con diagnóstico reciente de VIH, progresiva disminución de la proporción de UDVP y aumento de HSH y tendencia al diagnóstico en edades más avanzadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;23(4): 213-217, abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036172</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón epidemiológico de la infección por el VIH en 15 hospitales españoles: casos de nuevo diagnóstico incluidos en la cohorte VACH en 2001 y 2002</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29941</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30862^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30862^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
