<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156097</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of the minimum intervention in smoking cessations of hospitalized patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In Argentina, cigarette smoking generates more than 40,000 deaths per year. Minimal intervention is an effective strategy to help patients to stop smoking. Hospitalization is a good opportunity for this intervention because the patient may be more motivated as well as more sensitive and receptive to health advice. Objective. To address the proportion of patients who have been approached by health personnel during hospitalization with the minimal intervention. Patients and methods. This is an observational, cross-sectional study in which patients answered a questionnaire at hospital discharge. The proportion of cigarette smoking as well as the proportion of patients who were approached with the minimal intervention was calculated. It was used descriptive statistics. Results. Of 327 patients, 31 (9.5%) were current smokers. Ninety percent showed a moderate to high motivation to quit smoking and of these, only 10 (35.7%) received minimal intervention. No patient was offered help to quit smoking during hospitalization. Those patient with greater level of cigarette smoking showed a greater motivation to quit smoking (58.8% vs. 17.3%; p= 0.03). Conclusions. In this study, we showed a high proportion of patients who are motivated to quit smoking. Those patients with higher levels of cigarette smoking seem to be more motivated to quit the habit. However, health professionals do not take advantage on hospitalization for implementing the strategy of minimal intervention, thus losing the opportunity to encourage patients to stop smoking (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Astur Camporro, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El tabaquismo en Argentina genera más de 40.000 muertes por año. Una estrategia efectiva para ayudar al paciente tabaquista a la cesación es la intervención mínima. La internación es una buena oportunidad para aplicar esta estrategia debido a que el paciente presenta mayor motivación y además se encuentra más susceptible y receptivo a los consejos del personal de salud. Objetivo. Conocer el porcentaje de pacientes que reconocen haber sido abordados mediante la intervención mínima por el personal de salud durante la internación, evaluando de esa forma en qué medida se pone en práctica la misma. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio observacional, transversal, analítico. Cuestionario respondido por el paciente al momento del alta. Se calculó la proporción de pacientes que fueron abordados mediante intervención mínima. Se utilizó estadística descriptiva. Resultados. De 327 pacientes, 31 (9,5%) fueron tabaquistas actuales. El noventa por ciento presentó motivación moderada-alta para dejar de fumar y de estos, solo 10 (35,7%) recibieron intervención mínima. A ninguno se le ofreció ayuda para dejar de fumar. Aquellos pacientes con un mayor nivel de consumo de cigarrillos mostró una mayor motivación para dejar de fumar (58,8% vs. 17,3%; p = 0,03). Conclusiones. En este estudio, hemos demostrado una alta proporción de pacientes que están motivados para dejar de fumar. Sin embargo, los profesionales de la salud no aprovechan el ingreso hospitalario para aplicar la estrategia de intervención mínima, perdiendo así la oportunidad de cesación por parte del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;18(2): 67-71, abr.-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156097</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de la intervención mínima en la cesación tabáquica de pacientes internados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
