<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128704</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nosocomial respiratory viral infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nosocomial viral infections have not been well studied. In this context, the aim of this work is to review epidemiological and therapeutic data published on the main viral agents that can produce nosocomial respiratory infection. The study thus aims to expand knowledge of behaviour of these agents in nosocomial infections and provide information to improve the implementation of preventive measures. The concepts of mimivirus, herpes simplex virus, varicella-zoster virus, cytomegalovirus, respiratory syncytial virus, parainfluenza virus, influenza virus, adenovirus, metapneumovirus and measles viruses are discussed in detail (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>March Rosselló, G. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eiros Bouza, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones virales nosocomiales han sido objeto de pocos estudios. En este contexto, el objetivo de este trabajo es revisar los datos epidemiológicos y terapéuticos publicados sobre los principales agentes virales productores de infección nosocomial respiratoria. De este modo se pretende ampliar el conocimiento sobre el comportamiento de estos agentes en las infecciones nosocomiales y proporcionar información para mejorar la aplicación de las medidas de prevención. De manera pormenorizada se exponen conceptos relativos a los mimivirus, virus herpes simple, virus varicela-zóster, citomegalovirus, virus respiratorio sincitial, virus parainfluenza, virus de la gripe, adenovirus, metapneumovirus y virus del sarampión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;37(2): 265-279, mayo-ago. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128704</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección viral respiratoria nosocomial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25381^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25381^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25035^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53474^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53474^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
