<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94077</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">When the nurses are gone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Describing the meaning of rejecting nursing care for patients. Methodology: Research study with phenomenological focus carried out in Medellín, Colombia from march 2008 to April 2009 with twelve mature people among 27 and 54 years who were hospitalized. The interview in depth was used for gathering of information. The data were analyzed according to the outline proposed by Cohen, Kahan and Steeves. Results: Nurses absence at patient's bedside and the lack of interaction during care action lead to mistrust and rejection.Discussion: Acceptance, satisfaction and patients' treatment adherence are influenced by nurse patient relationship. Conclusion: Nursing care depends on nurses closeness to patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beltrán-Salazar, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir el significado para los pacientes del rechazo al cuidado enfermero. Metodología: Investigación con enfoque fenomenológico realizada en Medellín, Colombia entre 2008 y 2009; incluyó a 12 personas adultas entre 27 y 54 años que estuvieron hospitalizados. La entrevista en profundidad se utilizó para la recolección de información. Los datos se analizaron según el esquema propuesto por Cohen, Kahan y Steeves. Resultados: La ausencia de las enfermeras al lado de la cama de los pacientes y la falta de interacciónen el cuidado lleva a la desconfianza y al rechazo.Discusión: La aceptación, satisfacción y adherencia de los pacientes están influenciadas por la relación enfermera paciente. Conclusión: El cuidado enfermero depende de la presencia delas enfermeras al lado de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(4): 240-244, oct.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94077</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuando las enfermeras están ausentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
