<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041604</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vulvar melanoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vulvar cancer accounts for 5% of all female genital cancers and 1% of all malignancies in women. The most common histological type affecting the vulva is squamous cell carcinoma, accounting for approximately 90%-95% of these lesions. Malignant melanoma is the second most common cancer occurring in the vulva, accounting for about 8%-10% of lesions. This uncommon tumor shows a certain predisposition for the vulvar area. Melanomas usually present as raised, pigmented lesions, occurring most commonly on the labia minora or clitoris. Prognosis depends on the size of the lesion and the depth of invasion. Early biopsy of all suspected lesions is mandatory. We present a case of vulvar melanoma and describe our experience in the clinical management of this entity. We also provide a review of the most recent literature on the natural history of this tumor, its distribution among age groups, epidemiological factors, pathology, the microstaging systems used to predict prognosis, treatment, and survival</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lubrano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falcón, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Hernández, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de vulva es el 5% del total de cánceres ginecológicos y corresponde al 1% de afección maligna femenina. La entidad histológica más frecuente es el cáncer de células escamosas (90-95%). El melanoma representa la segunda enfermedad maligna en frecuencia (8-10%). Se trata de un tumor raro con cierta predisposición por el área vulvar. El melanoma se origina frecuentemente como lesión sobreelevada y pigmentada, localizada en labios menores o clítoris. El pronóstico depende del tamaño y grado de invasión tumoral. La biopsia temprana de cualquier lesión sospechosa es mandatoria. Este trabajo presenta un caso de melanoma vulvar y se expone nuestra experiencia en su manejo clínico, se realiza una revisión actualizada de la bibliografía en relación con su historia natural, distribución por edad, factores epidemiológicos, patología, sistemas de microestadificación para predecir pronóstico, tratamiento y supervivencia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);48(12): 606-611, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041604</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Melanoma vulvar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15247^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
