<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162211</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nissen fundoplication in children under 1 year of age: is age important?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. Nissen fundoplication (NF) is a procedure with technical difficulties and variable functional prognosis the lower the patient&#146;s age is. Our objective is to analyze the peculiarities of this procedure when performed in children under 1 year. Materials and methods. Retrospective study of the NF in our center from 1999 to 2014. We review the differences between children under 1 year of age and the leftover of the series: history, indications, surgical approach and postoperative outcomes. Results. A total of 233 patients (57.1% male) were operated at a median age of 2.3years (1 month-17.31years), of which 82 (35.2%) were younger than 1 year. It Open surgery was performed in 118 patients (86.6% of children under 1 year and 31.1% over 1 year, p&lt;0.05) and laparoscopic in 115. The median follow-up was 3.92 ± 3.24 years. Patients under 1 year had a higher number of comorbidities (91.5% vs 81.5%), respiratory symptoms (76.8% vs 49.7%) and postoperative complications (20.7% vs 9.9% OR = 2.4), with statistically significant differences (p&lt;0.05). There were not differences in the Nissen&#146;s failure rate (15.9% vs 8.6%) or the need of reoperation (15.9% vs 7.9%). Conclusions. Patients under 1 year operated by NF form a group with particular indications and comorbidities. Although the outcomes among these patients are favourable, surgical complications are more frequent than in older children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Núñez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amesty, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, CA de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Triana, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Santamaría, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romo, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrena, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La funduplicatura de Nissen (FN) es un procedimiento que plantea dificultades técnicas y un pronóstico funcional variable cuanto menor es la edad del paciente. Nuestro objetivo es analizar las peculiaridades de esta intervención cuando se realiza a niños menores de 1 año. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de las FN en nuestro centro de 1999 a 2014. Se evaluaron las diferencias entre menores de 1 año de vida y el resto de la serie en cuanto a antecedentes, indicaciones, abordaje quirúrgico y evolución postoperatoria. Resultados. Un total de 233 pacientes (57,1% varones) fueron intervenidos a una mediana de edad de 2,3 a (1 mes-17,31 a), de los que 82 (35,2%) eran menores de 1 año. La cirugía fue abierta en 118 pacientes (86,6% de los menores de 1 año y 31,1% de los mayores de 1 año, p&lt;0,05) y laparoscópica en 115. La mediana de seguimiento fue de 3,92 años. Los pacientes menores de 1 año presentaron mayor número de comorbilidades (91,5% vs 81,5%), sintomatología respiratoria (76,8% vs 49,7%) y complicaciones postoperatorias (20,7% vs 9,9%, OR=2,4), siendo estas diferencias estadísticamente significativas (p &lt;0,05). No hubo diferencias en cuanto al fallo del Nissen (15,9% vs 8,6%) ni a la necesidad de reintervención (15,9% vs 7,9%). Conclusiones. Los pacientes menores de 1 año operados mediante FN constituyen un grupo con indicaciones y comorbilidades particulares. Aunque los resultados son favorables, las complicaciones quirúrgicas son más frecuentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;29(4): 153-157, oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162211</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Funduplicatura de Nissen en niños menores de 1 año: ¿la edad importa?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24004^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50293</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32242^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
