<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80303</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The paper provides a short description of some test types that are earning considerable interest in both research and applied areas. The main feature of a computerized adaptive test is that in despite of the examinees receiving different sets of items, their test scores are in the same metric and can be directly compared. Four other test types are considered: a) model-based tests (a model or theory is available to explain the item response process and this makes the prediction of item difficulties possible), b) ipsative tests (the examinee has to select one among two or more options with similar social desirability; so, these tests can help to control faking or other examinee&#146;s response biases), c) behavioral tests (personality traits are measured from non-verbal responses rather than from self-reports), and d) situational tests (the examinee faces a conflictive situation and has to select the option that best describes what he or she will do). The paper evaluates these types of tests, comments on their pros and cons and provides some specific examples (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrada, Juan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olea, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Recientemente se ha producido un considerable desarrollo de los tests adaptativos informatizados, en los que el test se adapta progresivamente al rendimiento del evaluando, y de otros tipos de tests: a) los test basados en modelos (se dispone de un modelo o teoría de cómo se responde a cada ítem, lo que permite predecir su dificultad), b) los tests ipsativos (el evaluado ha de elegir entre opciones que tienen parecida deseabilidad social, por lo que pueden resultar eficaces para controlar algunos sesgos de respuestas), c) los tests conductuales (miden rasgos que ordinariamente se han venido midiendo con autoinformes, mediante tareas que requieren respuestas no verbales) y d) los tests situacionales (en los que se presenta al evaluado una situación de conflicto laboral, por ejemplo, con varias posibles soluciones, y ha de elegir la que le parece la mejor descripción de lo que el haría en esa situación). El artículo comenta las características, ventajas e inconvenientes de todos ellos y muestra algunos ejemplos de tests concretos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;31(1): 94-107, ene. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80303</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tests informatizados y otros nuevos tipos de tests</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3218</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
