<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126014</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Domiciliary parenteral antibiotic therapy: A prospective analysis of the last 12 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives: Parenteral antibiotic treatment has been classically developed in hospitals and is considered as a hospital procedure. The development of Hospital at Home Units (HHU) has led to an increase in outpatient parenteral antibiotic therapy (OPAT) in paediatrics patients. The objective of this study is to describe our experience, as an HHU integrated within a Paediatric Department, in home antimicrobial therapy over a period of 12 years. Patients and methods: This prospective and descriptive study included every patient with a disease requiring parenteral antimicrobial therapy who was admitted to our HHU from January 2000 to December 2012. Results: During the study there were 163 cases on OPAT. The mean age of the patients was 11.1 years, and the sample group was comprised of 33 males and 22 feamales. The main sources of the treated infections were respiratory tract (76%), catheter-related bloodstream (9.2%), and urinary tract infections (5.5%). Amikacin was the most widely used antibiotic. Almost all treatments (96.6%) were via an intravenous route. Catheter-associated complications were more common than drug-associated complications. Successful at-home treatment was observed in 90.2% of cases. Conclusions: OPAT is a good and safe alternative in many paediatric diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Madrid Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jurado Ortiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urda Cardona, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peláez Cantero, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Clásicamente la administración de tratamientos intravenosos se ha asociado a la necesidad de ingreso hospitalario. A partir de la formación de unidades de hospitalización a domicilio (UHD) se han extendido e incrementado el número de tratamientos antimicrobianos administrados por vía parenteral en pacientes pediátricos en su domicilio. El objetivo de este artículo es exponer la experiencia en tratamientos parenterales en domicilio en una UHD pediátrica durante un periodo de 12 años. Pacientes y método: Se realiza un estudio descriptivo, prospectivo. Se incluyeron en el estudio a todos los pacientes atendidos en nuestra UHD por enfermedad subsidiaria de tratamiento parenteral desde enero de 2000 hasta diciembre de 2012. Resultados: Se han instaurado 163 tratamientos parenterales en domicilio. La edad media fue de 11,1 años. Por sexos, 40% mujeres y 60% varones. Las infecciones tratadas han sido, en su mayoría, sobreinfecciones respiratorias (76%), infecciones del catéter central (9,2%) e infecciones del tracto urinario (5,5%). El antibiótico más utilizado ha sido la amikacina. El 96,9% de los tratamientos fue intravenoso. La complicación más frecuente ha sido la extravasación o pérdida de vía (7,4%). Se completó el tratamiento en domicilio en un 90,2% de los casos. Conclusiones: La administración de tratamientos parenterales en domicilio es una opción asistencial buena y segura en pacientes pediátricos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);81(2): 86-91, ago. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento antimicrobiano parenteral domiciliario: análisis prospectivo de los últimos 12 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7438^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
