<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79356</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Can we improve outcomes in patients with previous coronary artery bypass surgery admitted for acute coronary syndrome?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Prognosis and in-hospital management of patients with acute coronary syndrome (ACS) and a history of coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery are still debated. The objective of this study was to characterize ACS patients with a CABG and to compare their in-hospital and postdischarge outcomes with those of patients without a CABG. Methods. This ongoing prospective observational study included 1,495 consecutive patients admitted for ACS to a coronary care unit and followed up for a mean of 19 months. There were two groups: group A (n=73), with CABGs; and group B (n=1,223), without CABGs. Results. Group A patients were more often male (86.3% versus 69.1%; P=.002), and more frequently had a history of diabetes, myocardial infarction and heart failure. Group B patients more frequently had ST-elevation myocardial infarction, and had a higher median ejection fraction (53% [interquartile range, 47%-60%] vs. 50% [42%-55%]; P &lt; .01) and peak troponin-I concentration. There was no difference in the use of invasive techniques. Regarding medication, Group B patients were more likely to receive dual antiplatelet therapy at discharge. No significant difference was observed in in-hospital mortality (9.5% versus 5.9%; P=.2) or mortality at 1 month, 6 months or 1 year (9.8% versus 9.1%; log-rank test, P=.87) and the cumulative major adverse cardiac event rate was equally low in both groups. The presence of a CABG was associated with more readmissions for unstable angina (11.3% vs. 3.1%; P &lt; .01). Conclusions. In our ACS patients, the presence of a CABG had no significant influence on short- or medium-term outcomes, such as all-cause mortality and adverse cardiac events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monteiro, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baptista, Rui</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teixeira, Rogério</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Providência, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>António, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jorge, Elisabete</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lourenço, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendes, Paulo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonçalves, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saraiva, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteiro, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. El pronóstico y el tratamiento en el hospital de los pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo (SCA) y antecedentes de cirugía de bypass coronario (CABG) es motivo de controversia. El objetivo de este estudio es caracterizar a los pacientes con SCA que tienen antecedentes de CABG y comparar su evolución intrahospitalaria y extrahospitalaria con la de los pacientes sin antecedentes de CABG. Métodos. Estudio prospectivo observacional continuo de 1.495 ingresos consecutivos por SCA en una misma unidad coronaria, con un seguimiento medio de 19 meses. Se dividió a los pacientes en dos grupos: grupo A (n = 73) con CABG previa y grupo B (n = 1.223) sin CABG previa. Resultados. Los pacientes del grupo A eran con mayor frecuencia varones (el 86,3 frente al 69,1%; p = 0,002), tenían antecedentes más frecuentes de diabetes mellitus, infarto de miocardio previo e insuficiencia cardiaca. Los pacientes del grupo B tenían más infartos agudos de miocardio con elevación del ST, una fracción de eyección más alta (53% [47%-60%] frente a 50% [42%-55%]; p &lt; 0,01) y valores superiores de concentración máxima de troponina I. No se observaron diferencias en cuanto al uso de una estrategia invasiva. Por lo que respecta a la medicación, los pacientes del grupo B tenían una mayor probabilidad de recibir doble tratamiento antiagregante al alta. No se observaron diferencias significativas en cuanto a la mortalidad hospitalaria (el 9,5 frente al 5,9%; p = 0,2) ni en la mortalidad a 1 mes, 6 meses o 1 año (el 9,8 frente al 9,1%; log-rank test, p = 0,87), y la ausencia acumulativa de eventos adversos cardiovasculares mayores fue también similar en ambos grupos. Los antecedentes de CABG se asociaron a una mayor frecuencia de reingresos por angina inestable (el 11,3 frente al 3,1%; p &lt; 0,01). Conclusiones. En nuestra población con SCA, el antecedente de CABG no influyó de manera significativa en la evolución a corto y medio plazo en cuanto a la mortalidad por cualquier causa o eventos adversos cardiovasculares mayores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(5): 554-563, mayo 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79356</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Podemos mejorar la evolución de los pacientes con antecedentes de cirugía de bypass coronario ingresados por un síndrome coronario agudo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d800^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
