<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99222</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hyperphosphatemia is a complication that appears in the earlystages of chronic kidney disease (CKD) and that has been shownto have serious consequences in kidney disease patients. Newphosphate regulators are currently being studied such as FGF-23, a counter-regulatory phosphaturic hormone for vitamin D,and klotho, a cofactor necessary for activation of FGF-23. Themain consequences of hyperphosphatemia described in CKD patientsnot on dialysis are ectopic calcification, increased mortalityand more rapid progression of CKD. All this indicates the needfor strict control of Pi. The two most currently used drugs for thispurpose are lanthanum carbonate and sevelamer. Althoughthere are no studies specifically designed for this predialysis population,these drugs appear to be effective and safe. Anothercomplication of CKD is vitamin D deficiency which, according torecently published studies, is more prevalent and appears in earlierstages of the disease than was initially thought. There is widedebate on the need to administer vitamin D supplements systematicallydue to the pleiotropic effects of this hormone andwhich are unrelated to development of renal bone disease. Becauseof these doubts, there is no agreement on routine administration,although there is consensus on the need to measure1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D and 25-hydroxyvitamin D values and towait for the result of numerous studies that are being carriedout on the impact of vitamin D on progression of cardiovascularrisk factors in CKD and the possible consequences of its indiscriminateadministration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valdivielso Revilla, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Giráldez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-González, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiperfosfatemia es una complicación que aparece ya enestadios tempranos de la enfermedad renal crónica (ERC) yque ha demostrado tener graves consecuencias en los pa-cientes con nefropatía. En la actualidad se están estudiadonuevos  reguladores del  fósforo  como  son el  FGF-23, unahormona fosfatúrica y contra-reguladora de la vitamina D,y kloto, co-factor necesario para la activación del FGF-23.Las principales consecuencias de la hiperfosfatemia descri-tas en pacientes con ERC no en diálisis son la calcificaciónectópica, el  incremento de  la mortalidad y  la más  rápidaprogresión de la ERC. Todo ello indica la necesidad de bus-car un control estricto del Pi. Para ello, destacan en la ac-tualidad dos fármacos como son el carbonato de lantano yel sevelamer. Aunque no existen estudios diseñados espe-cíficamente para esta población aún no en diálisis, parecenser  fármacos  eficaces  y  seguros. Otra  complicación de  laERC es el defecto en  la síntesis de vitamina D que segúnlos  estudios  publicados  recientemente,  ha  resultado  sermás prevalente y aparecer en estadios más tempranos dela  enfermedad de  lo que  se  creía  inicialmente.  Existe unamplio debate respecto a la necesidad de administrar su-plementos  de  vitamina  D  de  forma  sistemática  por  losefectos pleiotrópicos de dicha hormona, ajenos al desarro-llo de la enfermedad ósea renal. Por esas dudas, si bien nohay acuerdo en la administración rutinaria, sí hay consen-so en la necesidad de medir los valores de 1,25-dihidroxivi-tamina D y 25-hidroxivitamina D, así  como esperar el  re-sultado de los numerosos estudios que se están llevandoacabo acerca del impacto de la vitamina D en la progresiónde factores de riesgo cardiovascular, en la ERC y las posi-bles consecuencias de su administración indiscriminada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(supl.5): 39-45, ene.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99222</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control del fósforo y tratamiento con vitamina D enEnfermedad Renal Crónica antes del inicio de diálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52631^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11186^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
