<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148012</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intervention through a physical exercise program at the company</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: There is evidence of the benefits gained by participating in the Physical Exercise Program (PEP) in the company. The objective of this investigation is to describe the profile of employees who take part and that of employees who do not take part in the PEP. Methods: We used validated questionnaires, the Short Form-36 Health Survey (SF-36); PSS (stress scale perceived); self-esteem questionnaire and a series of selected demographic data. They were answered by the workers of a company who were on a PEP; 17 out of 42 who formed the workforce were participating on it. The sample size is n=31. Participation was voluntary. The source of information is the employees of the company. We performed a cross sectional study.  Results: we found out that most of the workers not involved in the PEP have a fixed-term contract whose result brought statistical significance in showing less stress level in the PSS questionnaire, higher self-esteem in the questionnaire of self-esteem and/or the physical role of the SF-36; they have a better perception of health compared to the other group.  Conclusions: through further studies could investigate the relationship between these profiles and the participation or non- participation in a PEP in the work place, to develop effective strategies to encourage workers to participate in PEP in the work place (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yélamos Rodríguez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Marín, M Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, Manuel Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Existen evidencias sobre los beneficios que conlleva la participación en Programas de Ejercicio Físico (PEF) en la empresa y por ello es importante que la participación en un PEF sea la mayor posible. El objetivo de este trabajo es hacer un estudio piloto que pueda dar información sobre el perfil de los trabajadores que participan y de los que no participan en un PEF en la empresa. Métodos: Se han utilizado los cuestionarios validados SF-36 de calidad de vida; PSS de estrés percibido; cuestionario de autoestima más una serie de datos demográficos seleccionados. Han sido contestados por los trabajadores de una empresa que realizaba un PEF en el que participaban 17 trabajadores de 42 que forman la plantilla. El tamaño muestral es n=31. La participación ha sido voluntaria. La fuente de información son los trabajadores de esta empresa. Se ha realizado un estudio descriptivo transversal.  Resultados: en el grupo de trabajadores que no participaban en el PEF se encontró que la mayoría tienen un contrato de duración limitada (resultado que obtuvo significación estadística), menor nivel de estrés en el cuestionario PSS, mayor nivel de autoestima en el cuestionario de autoestima y/o en el rol físico del cuestionario SF-36; tienen una mejor percepción de salud respecto del otro grupo.  Conclusiones: a través de estudios posteriores se podría investigar la relación entre estos perfiles y la participación en PEF de entrenamiento físico en la empresa, para que la implantación de un PEF sea exitosa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;61(240): 342-353, jul.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148012</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención con un Programa de Ejercicio Físico en la empresa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
