<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106814</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Utility of antibiotic-impregnated cement spacers in septic surgery of the shoulder, a propos of two clinical cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present two cases treated by debridement, removal of unwanted material and placement of a cemented spacer for the proximal humerus impregnated with gentamycin, assessing laboratory, radiological and clinical aspects. Patients had a satisfactory course with a good final result. Osteomyelitis of the proximal humerus is a complication that leads to a dismal functional prognosis of the shoulder. Treatment with removal of unwanted material (osteosynthetic or prosthetic) and placement of a cement spacer may be alternatives to this dreaded complication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Madrigal Cortes, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Najarro Cid, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Yubero, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos dos casos tratados mediante desbridamiento, retirada de material y colocación de espaciador cementado para húmero proximal con gentamicina, valorando aspectos analíticos, radiológicos y clínicos. La evolución de los pacientes tuvo un buen resultado final. La osteomielitis de húmero proximal es una complicación que ensombrece el pronóstico funcional del hombro. El tratamiento con retirada de material (de osteosíntesis o protésico) y la colocación de un espaciador de cemento pueden ser alternativas a esta temida complicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);23(supl.1): 85-89, 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106814</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los espaciadores de cemento con antibióticos en la cirugía séptica del hombro, a propósito de dos casos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13163^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10199^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
