<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045736</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term evolution of liver histopathology in patients with chronic hepatitis C and sustained response</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to evaluate the evolution of histological changes observed in patients with chronic hepatitis C (CHC) and sustained response (SR) compared to non-responders (NR) to antiviral treatment. Methods: a retrospective study was performed in a total of 176 patients with CHC. These were divided into two groups: 132 SR and 44 NR. All had undergone a basal liver biopsy prior to treatment onset. A second biopsy was performed in 143 patients, 104 SR and 39 NR. Inflammatory activity and the degree of liver fibrosis was measured by Metavir units (MU). The progression and regression index of fibrosis was calculated before and after treatment. The time elapsed between the two biopsies was 5.9 ± 0.3 years for SR and 6.6 ± 0.3 years for NR (NS). Results: at baseline, 53% of SR patients had mild, chronic active hepatitis (CAH), while this was moderate in 43% of NR patients (p &lt; 0.0001). The time elapsed between baseline and post-treatment liver biopsies was 5.9 ± 0.3 years for SR subjects and 6.6 ± 0.4 years for NR subjects (NS). After antiviral treatment 47% of SR subjects presented a normal liver or minimal changes, whilst mild CAH persisted in 34.4% and moderate CAH in 37.5% of NR subjects. Necro-inflammatory activity decreased by 50% in SR subjects and by 15% in NR subjects (p &lt; 0.0001), and fibrosis decreased by 82% in SR subjects (p &lt; 0.0001) and by 66% in NR subjects (p &lt; 0.001). Fibrosis progression index was 0.14 MU/year in SR subjects and 0.21 MU/year in NR subjects (NS). Fibrosis regression index was - 0.11 in SR subjects and -0.14 in NR subjects (NS). Conclusions: in our series of patients with CHC and SR, we observed histological normalization in approximately fifty per cent of cases during long-term follow-up. NR subjects also showed improvement, especially in the fibrosis score. Both groups showed a marked regression of liver fibrosis after treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Álvarez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-López, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: estudiar la evolución a largo plazo de la histología hepática, en pacientes con hepatitis crónica por virus C (VHC) con respuesta sostenida (RS) al tratamiento antiviral y compararla con los pacientes no respondedores (NR) al mismo. Métodos: incluimos un total de 176 pacientes con hepatitis crónica por el VHC, 132 con RS y 44 NR. Todos ellos tenían una biopsia hepática basal y se practicó una segunda biopsia post-tratamiento a 143 pacientes, 104 con RS y 39 NR. Se compararon las modificaciones existentes entre ambas, valorandola actividad necro-inflamatoria y la fibrosis hepática medida mediante unidades Metavir (UM). El índice de progresión y regresión de la fibrosis, se calcularon antes y después del tratamiento. El tiempo medio transcurrido entre las dos biopsias fue de 5,9 ± 0,3 años para RS y de 6,6 ± 0,3 años para NR (NS). Resultados: antes del tratamiento un 53% de los pacientes con RS presentaban una hepatitis crónica activa (HCA) leve,mientras que un 43% de pacientes NR, presentaban una HCAmoderada (p &lt; 0,0001). Después del tratamiento, el 47% de los pacientes con RS presentaron hígado normal o cambios mínimos, mientras que los NR presentaron una HCA leve (34,4%) y moderada (37,5%). La actividad necro-inflamatoria disminuyó un 50% en los pacientes con RS y un 15% en NR (p &lt; 0,0001) y la fibrosis disminuyó un 82% en pacientes con RS (p &lt; 0,0001) y un 66% en NR (p &lt; 0,001). El índice de progresión de la fibrosis pre-tratamiento fue de 0,14 UM/año en pacientes con RS y de 0,21 UM/año en NR (NS). El índice de regresión de la fibrosis post-tratamiento fue de (&#150;0,11 UM/año) en pacientes con RS y de (-0,14 UM/año) en NR (NS).Conclusiones: los pacientes con hepatitis crónica por virus C y RS tienden a presentar en el seguimiento una normalización histológica, en la mitad de los casos aproximadamente. Además tanto los pacientes con RS como los NR, mostraron una marcada regresión en el índice de fibrosis a largo plazo, más notable en los pacientes respondedores</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;97(12): 860-869, dic. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045736</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución a largo plazo de la lesión hepática en pacientes con hepatitis crónica C y respuesta sostenida al tratamiento antiviral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
