<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153351</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Supporting autonomy in physical education: perception versus reality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This investigation, on the one hand it focuses on students´ and teachers´ perception about autonomy support during Physical Education instruction, and on the other hand, in the coherence between perception and reality observed in the classes. Two scales were administered to determine the frequency of instructional behaviors favoring the development of autonomy, and teacher´s classes were observed and videotaped. The results show that the observed frequency of instructional behavior favoring autonomy support during classes is significantly lower than that perceived by students and teachers. The observed reality reveals a teacher profile with room for improvement in behaviors such as: communication quality, task functionality, promotion of students&#146; thinking, creation of situations in which students can express their opinions of the tasks, and increasing intrinsic motivation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguado-Gómez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Álvarez, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Cueto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Esta investigación se centró, por una parte en la percepción de apoyo a la autonomía en las clases de Educación física, que tienen tanto el alumnado como el profesorado, y por otra, en la coherencia entre percepción y la realidad observada en las clases. Se aplicaron dos escalas al profesorado y al alumnado con el objeto de conocer con qué frecuencia se producen comportamientos instructivos favorables al desarrollo de la autonomía, y se observaron y grabaron en video clases impartidas por el profesorado. Los resultados muestran que la frecuencia de los comportamientos instructivos de apoyo a la autonomía durante la intervención de enseñanza es significativamente menor que la percibida por el alumnado y el profesorado. La realidad observada muestra un perfil de profesorado con gran margen de mejora en comportamientos como: calidad de la comunicación, funcionalidad de las tareas, fomento del pensamiento del alumnado, situaciones en las que el alumnado pueda expresar su opinión sobre las tareas y motivación intrínseca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;16(62): 183-202, jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153351</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apoyo a la autonomía en las clases de educación física: percepción versus realidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
