<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131045</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Familial presentation of microdeletion and inverted microduplication with array-CGH</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Over the years the field of genetics has advanced significantly. Following the polymerase chain reaction and mass sequencing techniques, the array-CGH technique (comparative genomic hybridization) has helped to improve genetic procedures. A resolution of up to 200 kb is currently being accomplished in the human genome.  Case reports. We report the case of two sisters with delays in developmental milestones and a characteristic phenotype with normal results from initial studies of the karyotype and subtelomeric regions. Array-CGH was later used to detect a deletion and duplication that were different in each of the sisters, this being the result of a balanced paternal translocation. In the two cases, despite being the result of the same translocation, the genetic and phenotype expression were different. Conclusions. The precision achieved by means of array-CGH is making it possible to establish a correlation between minimum gains or losses of the genome and the clinical features. Chromosome 3 codes for genes that play a fundamental role in neurological development (contactins, neurotransmitter modulator proteins, etc.) and chromosome 10 codes for proteins involved in apoptosis and proteins regulating transcription. In the literature there have been reports of chromosome 3 deletion syndrome and monosomy 10. Likewise, there are also descriptions of rearrangements between these chromosomes in individuals from the same family. Nevertheless, we describe two cases of a family with a microdeletion and an inverted microduplication, detected by means of array-CGH, that have not been reported to date. This technique can provide a diagnostic and prognostic approximation as regards development and offer genetic counselling (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Candel, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carpena Lucas, Pedro J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrón Marzal, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beseler Soto, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. A lo largo de los años se han logrado avances en torno a la genética; tras la reacción en cadena de la polimerasa y las técnicas de secuenciación masiva, la técnica array-CGH (comparative genomic hybridization) ha contribuido a mejorar los procedimientos genéticos. Actualmente está consiguiendo una resolución de hasta 200 kb en el genoma humano. Casos clínicos. Se presentan dos hermanas con retraso en los hitos del desarrollo y fenotipo característico con estudio inicial de cariotipo y de regiones subteloméricas normales. Posteriormente, mediante array-CGH se detectó en cada una una deleción y una duplicación diferentes, fruto de una translocación equilibrada paterna. En ambas, siendo fruto de una misma translocación, muestra diferente expresión genética y fenotípica.  Conclusiones. La precisión conseguida mediante el array-CGH está permitiendo correlacionar mínimas ganancias o pérdidas del genoma con la clínica. En el cromosoma 3 se encuentran codificados genes fundamentales en el desarrollo neurológico (contactinas, proteínas moduladoras de neurotransmisores, etc.), y en el cromosoma 10, proteínas implicadas en la apoptosis y proteínas reguladoras de la transcripción. En la bibliografía se han descrito el síndrome de deleción del cromosoma 3 y la monosomía 10. Igualmente, hay descritos reordenamientos entre estos cromosomas en individuos de una misma familia. Sin embargo, aportamos dos casos de una familia con una microdeleción y una microduplicación inversa, detectados mediante array-CGH, no descritos hasta el momento. Dicha técnica puede ofrecer una aproximación diagnóstica y pronóstica en cuanto a la evolución y ofertar consejo genético (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;59(12): 551-554, dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131045</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Microdeleción y microduplicación inversa de presentación familiar con array-CGH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7789</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54730^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2703^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30719</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
