<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60895</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spontaneous pneumothorax in a 32-week pregnant woman</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primary spontaneous pneumothorax is characterized by dyspnea and progressive lung collapse, due to air accumulation in the pleural cavity. Although this entity is an exceptional finding in pregnancy, it can be life-threatening to the mother and fetus. Our Obstetrics and Gynecology Department treated a woman in the 32nd week of pregnancy with a spontaneous pneumothorax, who underwent thoracotomy for a bleb excision and pleurodesis a few days before delivery. A review of the international medical literature yielded only 50 cases reported to date, indicating the limited experience in the diagnosis and treatment of this entity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villaverde Fernández, Secundino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menédez Robledo, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bayón González, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deza Moldes, Jime</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El neumotórax espontáneo es una entidad caracterizada por disnea y colapso pulmonar progresivo debido a la acumulación de aire en la cavidad pleural. Aunque constituye un hallazgo excepcional en gestantes, su presencia puede comprometer seriamente la vida de la madre y el feto. Nuestro servicio de ginecología ha tenido ocasión de tratar a una paciente con neumotórax espontáneo en el curso de semana 32 de gestación, sometida a toracotomía, bullectomía y pleurodesis días antes del parto. La revisión de la literatura médica tan sólo recoge 50 casos hasta la fecha, por lo que la experiencia en el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de esta entidad es muy limitada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(4): 252-259, abr. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60895</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumotórax espontáneo en una gestante de 32 semanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23039^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32076^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
