<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96060</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fetal heart rate in patients with prolonged pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Basal values of fetal heart rate (FHR) and amplitude of the accelerations were determined in patients with prolonged pregnancy and were compared with those in a control group. The study design was open, prospective, comparative and exploratory. The sample consisted of 40 patients divided into two groups. Group 1 (problem group) was composed of 20 patients with prolonged pregnancies. Group 2 (control group) consisted of 20 patients with a normal pregnancy. Ultrasound was used to determine parietal diameter. FHR and uterine contractility were measured for 2 h. Basal FHR and the amplitude of the accelerations in the two groups were compared. In group1, FHR was 3 beats higher and the difference between the means was highly significant. The difference in amplitude was not significant. In two FHR recordings, Type II Dips of moderate amplitude were registered during a reactive pattern. Dispersion diagrams were drawn and the linear regression of the biparietal diameter values of group 1 fetuses was calculated. The equation was y=2.2183x + 7.6909 and the correlation coefficient was R2=0.8877. In group 2 (normal distribution) the linear regression equation was y=2.0344x + 12.944. The correlation coefficient was R2=0.9981.The means of the biparietal diameters of the two groups were also compared but no significant differences were found. The mean values for uterine height and abdominal perimeter were 37.15cm. and 109.10cm, respectively. The physical status of the newborns was evaluated using the Apgar test at 1 and 5 minutes. Three children were born depressed with a score of 2. Three other children were not tested. Fourteen showed a score in the range of 7&#150;8. At 5min their score was 9. Two neonates remained depressed. The weights of the neonates in the two groups were compared and those in group 1 were 418g heavier. The difference between mean weights was significant. Height was not significantly different(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Shea, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Cárdenas, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Cosme, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cavazos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizaola Díaz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Salinas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulido, V. H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se determinaron los valores de la frecuencia cardiaca fetal (FCF) basal y la amplitud de las aceleraciones en pacientes con embarazo prolongado para equipararlos con un grupo testigo. El diseño del estudio fue: abierto, prospectivo, comparativo y exploratorio. La muestra la integraron 40 pacientes, se dividió en 2 grupos: Grupo 1 o problema: 20 pacientes con embarazo prolongado. Grupo 2 o testigo: 20 pacientes con embarazo normal. Con ultrasonido se determinó el diámetro biparietal. Se les practicaron registros de FCF y contractilidad uterina durante 2h.En los grupos problema y testigo, se equipararon la FCF basal y la amplitud de las aceleraciones, en el primer grupo la FCF se incrementó 3 latidos, la diferencia entre medias fue altamente significativa; en la amplitud no lo fue.En 2 trazos de FCF se registraron Dips Tipo II de mediana amplitud en medio de un patrón reactivo. Se elaboraron diagramas de dispersión y se calculó la regresión a una recta, utilizando los valores del diámetro biparietal de productos de embarazo prolongado, la ecuación de la recta fue y=2,2183x+7,6909 y el coeficiente de correlación de R2=0,8877. En el grupo con distribución normal, la ecuación de la recta fue y=2,0344x +12,944; y el coeficiente de correlación de R2=0,9981.En los grupos problema y el testigo, se (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);39(1): 14-20, ene.-feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96060</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La frecuencia cardiaca fetal en pacientes con diagnóstico de embarazo prolongado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19181^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5421^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22263^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
