<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79296</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexual transmission infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The infections of sexual transmission (STI) have a great importance on the health of the world population. Especially its incidence, prevalence and consequence on the health. Sexually transmitted diseases may be contracted by people of any age, race and social standing. More than 20 different diseases are known as STI, they have all in common that they are transmitted during the sexual intercourse. The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that each year there are 340 million new cases of STIs among the ages of 15 and 49 years. STI must be diagnosed and treated early in order to avoid its propagation. The sexual education is the fundamental tool of the prevention of STI(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Vega, Eva María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puigvert Viu, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones de transmisión sexual (ITS) tienen una gran importancia sobre la salud de la población mundial, por su incidencia, prevalencia y repercusiones. Pueden contraerse por personas de cualquier edad, raza y medio social. Con este nombre se han agrupado más de 20 entidades patógenas diferentes que sólo tienen en común el hecho de poder transmitirse durante las relaciones sexuales.  La Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS) estima que cada año se producen 340 millones de casos nuevos de ITS entre las edades comprendidas de los 15 y 49 años. Las ITS se deben diagnosticar y tratar con prontitud, para erradicar su propagación y evitar complicaciones y secuelas. La prevención supone la herramienta fundamental y la metodología por excelencia es la educación sexual(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(4): 282-286, abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79296</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infecciones de transmisión sexual. Existencia de una red comunitaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11750^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13116^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13116^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
