<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142892</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fibre and enteral nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dietary fibre is a mixture of various substances and is essential for maintaining appropriate intestinal functionality and it is currently considered to be a necessary part of a healthy diet. Current recommendations for fibre consumption by adults range from 20 to 35 g/day. Enteral nutrition is an emerging therapeutic variation in both hospital and domestic settings. To a great extent, this development has been made possible thanks to the desing of new formulas that adapt better and better to the clinicla conditions or our patients. The type of fibre used in these preparations varies greatly. Some have only one source of fibre while others use differnet combinations. There are currently 32 formulas available on the Spanish market, without counting the modules or specific preparations of individual types of fibre. Despite the enormous advances in the knowledge of the beneficial effects of fibre, the fact of the matter is that enteral nutrition that we routinely prescribe in normal clinical practice does not contain fibre. The are several explanations for this, perhaps the most plausible is that these formulas may lead to problems in their administration and tolerance. It is necessary to choose the correct calibre of catheter and define the best infusion method and timing. Another difficulty may be the gastrointestinal tolerance of the formulas containing fibre. No large-scale problems of intolerance have however been describied in healthy volunteers nor in patients with acute or chronic pathologies, although it is of fundamental importance to monitor the rhythm of depositions in all patients with enteral nutrition (EN) and ensure proper intake of liquids, which would also be useful to prevent occlusion of the catheter. The theoretical benefits of EN with fibre with a view to maintaing or improving normal intestinal structure and function are very varied. Nonetheless, it has noit yet been possible to prove many of these effects in controlled clinical trials. At the present time, there are sufficient reasons of a physiological nature for using EN with fibre in many patients, particularly in those predisposed to constipation or suffering from diarrhoea, in those requiring long-term EN and in some intestinal pathologies. In the near future, fibre can be expected to form part of EN as standard component and we should define its optimal composition for different pathologies. In the meantime, we need to continue working intensely in this highly promising area of knowledge (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Candela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibra dietética, es una mezcla variada de diversas sustancias, y es fundamental en el mantenimiento de una adecuada funcionalidad intestinal y en el momento actual se considera que debe formar parte de una alimentación saludable. Las recomendaciones actuales de consumo para adultos son de 20 a 35 g/día. La nutrición enteral es una modalidad terapéutica muy emergente tanto a nivel hospitalario como domiciliario. En gran parte este desarrollo ha sido posible gracias al diseño de nuevas fórmulas cada vez más adaptadas a las condiciones clínicas de nuestros pacientes. El tipo de fibra que se utiliza en estos preparados es muy variable. Algunos disponen sólo de una única fuente de fibra y otros de diferentes combinaciones. En la actualidad existen un total de 32 fórmulas disponibles en el mercado español, sin contar con los módulos o los preparados específicos de diferentes tipo de fibra. A pesar del enorme desarrollo del conocimiento de los efectos beneficiosos de la fibra, la realidad es que rutinariamente la nutrición enteral que solemos indicar los clí- nicos no contiene fibra. Hay diversas explicaciones para este fenómeno, quizás la más plausible es que estas fórmulas pueden generar problemas de administración y tolerancia. Elegir el calibre más adecuado de la sonda así como la mejor pauta y método de infusión es necesario. Otro inconveniente puede ser la tolerancia gastrointestinal de las fórmulas que contienen fibra. Sin embargo, no se han documentado problemas considerables de intolerancia ni en voluntarios sanos ni en pacientes con patología aguda o crónica. Aunque es fundamental monitorizar el ritmo de las deposiciones en todos los pacientes con NE y asegurar una ingesta adecuada de lí- quidos, que además sería muy útil para prevenir la oclusión de la sonda. Los beneficios teóricos de la NE con fibra con la intención de mantener o mejorar la normal estructura y función del intestino son muy extensos. Sin embargo, hasta ahora, no ha sido posible demostrar muchos de estos efectos en estudios clínicos controlados. En la actualidad existen suficientes razones de índole fisiológica para utilizar NE con fibra en muchos pacientes, especialmente en aquellos predispuestos al estreñimiento o con diarrea, en aquellos que necesiten una NE de larga duración y en algunas patologías intestinales. En el futuro inmediato es previsible que la fibra forme parte de la NE como un componente estándar y que definamos su óptima composición para diferentes patologías. Mientras tanto precisamos que se siga trabajando intensamente en este área de conocimiento tan prometedora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;17(supl.2): 30-40, 2002. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142892</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fibra y nutrición enteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4387^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
