<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94024</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ecotoxicological assessment of two Neem derivatives in earthworm and honey bees</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of products with low or null impact in surroundingorganisms and the environment constitutes part of the new concept of crop protection. The products NeoNim 60 and OleoNim 80, obtained from the Neem tree, are proposed for its use as insecticide, nematicide and acaricide. With the objective of perform the ecotoxicological assessment of these products, it were carried out the earthworm acute toxicity and the honey bee acute contact toxicity tests. For each assay two Treated and one Control group were established. The assay in earthworms Eisenia andrei was carried out during 14 days using artificial soil, with daily clinical observations, count of animals and study of the changes of the biomass. The test in honey bees Apis mellifera was prolonged for 48 hours, with daily clinical observations and count of animals. A survival of 100% was obtained in the earthworms of the Treated groups, obtaining in the NeoNim 60 group significative lower values of biomass when compared to the Control, while the group treated with OleoNim 80 showed an increase in the biomass from the beginning to the end of the assay. In the assay in bees, the statistical comparison didn't show differences among groups as for the mortality. Taken into account the obtained results, it could be concluded that the Neem derivatives NeoNim 60 and OleoNim 80 don't produce toxic effect on the earthworms and the honeybees (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Triana, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada Ortiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bada Barro, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Torres, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancebo Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Navarro, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La utilización de productos con bajo o nulo impacto en organismos circundantes y el ambiente, constituye parte del nuevo concepto de protección de cultivos. Los productos NeoNim 60 y OleoNim 80, obtenidos del árbol del Nim, están propuestos para su uso como insecticida, nematicida y acaricida. Con el objetivo de realizar la evaluación ecotoxicológica de estos productos, se realizaron los ensayos de toxicidad aguda en lombriz de tierra Eisenia andrei y de toxicidad aguda por contacto en abejas Apis mellifera. Cada ensayo contó con un grupo control y dos tratados. El ensayo en lombrices se realizó durante 14 días utilizando suelo artificial, realizando observaciones clínicas, conteo de animales y estudio del comportamiento de la biomasa. La prueba en abejas se prolongó por 48 horas, realizándose observaciones clínicas y conteo de animales. Se obtuvo un 100% de supervivencia en las lombrices de los grupos tratados, obteniendo en el NeoNim 60 valores de disminución de la biomasa significativamente inferiores al grupo control, mientras que el grupo tratado con OleoNim 80 mostró aumento en la biomasa del inicio al final del ensayo. En el ensayo en abejas, la comparación estadística no mostró diferencias entre grupos en cuanto a la mortalidad. Teniendo en cuenta el conjunto de los resultados obtenidos, se pudo concluir que los derivados del Nim NeoNim 60 y OleoNim 80 no producen efecto tóxico sobre las lombrices de tierra y las abejas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;28(2): 147-151, jul.-dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94024</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación ecotoxicológica de dos derivados del Nim en lombriz de tierra y abejas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52884^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25712^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10020^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1535^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10020^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52884^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52884^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1533^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52884^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
