<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131290</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fear of negative evaluation, self-esteem and choking under pressure: Effects on sport performance in adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to examine the fear of negative evaluation and self-esteem as moderators of choking in sport. One hundred high school students (56% were females) completed the Brief Fear of Negative Evaluation (BFNE) and the Self-Esteem Scale (SES) prior to completing a badminton set in low-pressure and high-pressure conditions. Data based on a series of ANOVAs supported the hypothesis that fear of negative evaluation acts as a moderator of the choking effect under psychological pressure. Participants with high fear of negative evaluation showed a significant drop on sport performance from low- to high-pressure phases. In general, high-self-esteem was associated to high levels of performance. The present study extends the choking literature, including the constructs of fear of negative evaluation and self-esteem as possible relevant variables implicated in the field of sport performance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sandín, Bonifacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valiente, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chorot, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio consistió en examinar el miedo a la evaluación negativa y la autoestima como posibles factores moduladores del choking (caída del rendimiento deportivo asociado a la presión psicológica). Participaron 100 estudiantes de secundaria (el 56% eran mujeres), los cuales cumplimentaron la Brief Fear of Negative Evaluation (BFNE) y la Self-Esteem Scale (SES) antes de participar en un set de bádminton en condiciones de baja y alta presión. Los datos basados en ANOVAs apoyan la hipótesis de que el miedo a la evaluación negativa actúa como modulador del deterioro del rendimiento deportivo. Los participantes con elevado nivel de miedo a la evaluación negativa experimentaron una caída significativa en el rendimiento deportivo durante la condición de alta presión; el efecto de la autoestima se asoció, en general, a mayor rendimiento deportivo. El presente estudio amplía la literatura sobre el choking en el ámbito del deporte, proporcionando evidencia sobre la implicación del miedo a la evaluación negativa y la autoestima en el campo de la psicología de la actividad física y el deporte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;14(3): 57-66, sept.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Miedo a la evaluación negativa, autoestima y presión psicológica: Efectos sobre el rendimiento deportivo en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
