<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60890</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obstetrician gender and vaginal delivery rate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether the instrumental delivery rate changes according to the number of men among third- and fourth-year resident physicians. Materials and methods: The proportion of instrumental deliveries was determined among 54,961 births in a single hospital from 1990 to 2006. Annual rates were calculated based on the gender of third- and fourth-year resident physicians. For each annual rate, a 95% confidence interval was calculated and the &amp;#967;2 test was performed to verify the significance of differences. Results: When the number of male physicians increased so did the rate of instrumental deliveries. Differences were significant for years in which the number of male physicians was equal to three or more. Conclusions: The instrumental delivery rate seems to be related to the gender of third-and fourth-year resident physicians (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez Gutiérrez, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Usadizaga Calparsoro, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Comprobar si la tasa de partos instrumentales varía al cambiar el número de varones entre los médicos residentes de tercer y cuarto año. Material y métodos: Se recogió la proporción de partos instrumentales sobre 54.961 partos atendidos en un mismo hospital desde 1990 hasta 2006. Las tasas anuales se agruparon de acuerdo con el sexo de los médicos residentes de tercer y cuarto año. Para la comparación de las tasas se recurrió al cálculo del intervalo de confianza (IC) del 95% de la diferencia de porcentajes y a la prueba de la &amp;#967;2. Resultados: Al aumentar la proporción de varones se incrementa también la tasa de partos instrumentales. Las diferencias son significativas para los años en los que el número de residentes varones es de tres o más. Conclusiones: Parece que el sexo de los residentes de tercer y cuarto año se relaciona con el porcentaje de partos instrumentales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(4): 221-226, abr. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60890</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El sexo de los obstetras y el género de parto vaginal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9957^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8671^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7923^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13906^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
