<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146231</identifier>
<setSpec>0558-6291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of thrombophilia in young people with ictus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Most ictus appear in people over 50 and are associated with cardiovascular risk factors. Nevertheless, those that occur in young patients are not always caused by arteriosclerosis, so other etiologies such as thrombophilias are sought. The objectives of this study were: 1.-To find out the prevalence of thrombophilias and/or states of hypercoagulation in young patients admitted for ictus in a tertiary hospital. 2.-To find out the frequency with which thrombophilia studies are carried out in such patients. 3.-To find out the characteristics of these patients. To do so, a descriptive and retrospective study was carried out, reviewing the clinical histories of all the patients admitted to the Hospital Cllnico Universitario "Lozano Blesa" (Zaragoza) during the year 2004 with diagnoses of ictus in young patients. The characteristics, interesting antecedents and thrombophilia studies carried out were recorded. 64 patients were reviewed, 32 of them showed ischemia. In 16, some type of thrombophilia study was requested. In the study of plasmatic thrombophilia, the most common alteration was antithrombin III deficiency, followed by resistance to V Leyden factor. In the study of genetic thrombophilias, the mutation of Metiltetrahifrofolato reductase (MTHFR), in all cases heterozygotic, was the most frequent finding. The parameters studied in immunology were variable. Conclusions: 1.- Thrombophilia studies are requested less frequently than would be recommendable 2.-The requests for studies are not uniform for the different types of trombofilias, plasmatic studies being the most requested (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos Lasaosa, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Rull, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Marteles, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flamarique Pascual, Alvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Bergual, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayoría de los ictus aparecen en personas de más de 50 años y asociados a factores de riesgo cardiovascular. Sin embargo, los ocurridos en pacientes jóvenes, no siempre se justifican con la arterioesclerosis, por lo que se buscan otras etiologías como las trombofilias. Los objetivos del estudio fueron 1.-Conocer la prevalencia de trombofilias y/o estados de hipercoagulabilidad en pacientes jóvenes ingresados por ictus en un hospital de tercer nivel. 2.-Conocer con qué frecuencia se realizan estudios de trombofilia en dichos pacientes. 3.-Cuáles son las características de este tipo de pacientes. Para ello se realizó un estudio descriptivo y retrospectivo, revisando las historias clínicas de todos los pacientes ingresados en el Hospital Clínico Universitario Lozano Blesa" (Zaragoza) durante el año 2004 con diagnóstico de ictus en paciente joven. Se registraron características, antecedentes de interés y estudios de trombofilia/s realizados. Se revisaron 64 pacientes, 32 de ellos fueron isquémicos. En 16 se solicitó algún tipo de estudio de trombofilia. En el estudio de trombofilia plasmática la alteración más frecuente fue el déficit de Antitrombina III, seguido de resistencia al factor V de Leiden. En el estudio de trombofilia genéticas la mutación de la Metiltetrahilrofolatorreductasa (IMTHFR), todos heterocigotos, fue el hallazgo más frecuente. Los parámetros estudiados en inmunología fueron variables e inconstantes. Conclusiones: 1.-Los estudios de trombofilias se solicitaron en menor número de lo que sería recomendable 2.-Las peticiones de estudio no son uniformes para los distintos tipos de trombofilias, siendo los estudios plasmáticos los más solicitados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. Fac. Med. Zaragoza;46(2): 47-51, 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146231</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio diagnóstico de trombofilia en pacientes jóvenes con ictus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33772^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33770^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33773^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22270^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32063^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
