<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058951</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Objetivos: Evaluar la adecuación de los sitios web destinados a proporcionar información para la realización de seguimiento farmacoterapéutico a 4 códigos de conducta</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To assess adherence to four codes of conduct in websites providing information useful for pharmacotherapy follow-up.         Methods: We performed a descriptive study of adherence to quality criteria in 19 websites. These sites had been identified in a previous study as being those most frequently used by pharmacists. A descriptive analysis was performed and the kappa coefficient was calculated to evaluate interrater concordance (Fleiss' criteria for evaluation of the kappa index).         Results: The most highly rated source of clinical practice guidelines and that which adhered most closely to the 4 codes of conduct was Fisterra. The websites most highly rated in reviews and secondary sources were the Cochrane Library and PubMed. The most highly rated journals were JAMA and the BMJ, followed by Atención Primaria and Medicina Clínica. Among drug information guides, the highest scores were obtained by BOT and Martindale's. The highest rated drug bulletins were the Boletín Terapéutico Andaluz and Butlletí Groc. The most highly rated agency was the World Health Organization. The journals with the lowest scores were Pharmaceutical Care and Seguimiento Farmacoterapéutico followed by the Spanish Internacional Vademecum MediMedia-Medicom. According to Fleiss's criteria, interrater concordance was acceptable for the 4 codes.         Conclusions: The quality of the web sites evaluated varied widely, although most received scores of more than 60 points (out of 100) in the 4 codes of conduct used for evaluation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valverde Merino, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azpilicueta Cengotitabengoa, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martiarena Ayestaran, Amaia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Gutiérrez, José Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Milena Silva Castro, Martha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faus Dáder, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Pernett, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tuneu Valls, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermúdez Tamayo, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar la adecuación de los sitios web destinados a proporcionar información para la realización de seguimiento farmacoterapéutico a 4 códigos de conducta.         Métodos: Estudio descriptivo del cumplimiento de los criterios de calidad de 19 sitios web seleccionados por ser los de mayor utilización por los farmacéuticos en un estudio previo. Se realizó un análisis descriptivo y se estimó el coeficiente kappa para valorar la concordancia entre evaluadores (criterios de Fleiss) .         Resultados y conclusiones: Fisterra fue la página mejor valorada en los 4 códigos, y la fuente de acceso a guías clínicas mejor calificada. La Cochrane Library y Pubmed las mejor valoradas en revisiones y fuentes secundarias. JAMA y British Medical Journal fueron las revistas mejor calificadas seguidas de Atención Primaria y Medicina Clínica. Entre los vademécums, el BOT y el Martindale obtuvieron las mejores calificaciones y el Boletín Terapéutico Andaluz y el Butlletí Groc recibieron altas calificaciones de entre los boletines de medicamentos. La Organización Mundial de la Salud fue la agencia mejor calificada. Los sitios con menor calificación fueron Pharmaceutical Care, Seguimiento Farmacoterapéutico y el Vademécum Internacional España MediMedia-Medicom. La concordancia entre evaluadores fue aceptable para los 4 códigos.         Conclusiones: La calidad de los sitios web que utilizan los farmacéuticos es muy variable, aunque la mayoría superan los 60 puntos (sobre 100) en los 4 códigos de conducta usados en la evaluación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;21(3): 204-209, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058951</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación a los códigos de conducta para información biomédica en internet de sitios web útiles para el seguimiento farmacoterapéutico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37705</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
