<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60251</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Kleine-Levin Syndrome associated to a pituitary microprolactinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Kleine-Levin syndrome (KLS) is a rare disorder with symptoms that include periodic hipersomnia, cognitive and behavioral disturbances. The disease predominantly affects adolescent males. Case report: We report here a 14 year old male admitted to our hospital two time with the symptoms of hypersomnia, behavioral and cognitive disturbances, compulsive eating behavior and hypersexuality. He also complained of unilateral gynecomatia with galactorrehea. Pituitary magnetic resonance imaging showed an eight millimeters adenoma. Therefore, a microprolactinoma was diagnosed. Discussion: The patient´s history, complete laboratory results, and symptoms are discussed. Possible treatments for this disorder are also mentioned, along with diagnostic criteria. To our knowledge, this is the first reported case of KLS associated with microprolactinoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Fernández-Mayoralas, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Donoso Sanz, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Jaén, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Jareño, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La hipersomnia periódica o recurrente o síndrome de Kleine-Levin (SK) se observa generalmente en adolescentes varones y cursa con crisis recurrentes de hipersomnia excesiva y alteraciones cognoscitivas. Caso clínico: Adolescente varón de 14 años que presentó dos cuadros de somnolencia excesiva, alteraciones del habla y del comportamiento, hiperfagia compulsiva y comportamiento hipersexual típicos de SK. Nuestro paciente presentó ginecomastia, galactorrea y finalmente se realizó el diagnóstico de microadenoma hipofisario de 8 milímetros mediante resonancia magnética cerebral. Discusión: Se realiza una discusión sobre la historia clínica del paciente, los resultados del laboratorio y los síntomas asociados. Se analizan los criterios diagnósticos y los posibles tratamientos disponibles. El microadenoma hipofisario nunca ha sido relacionado hasta ahora con el SK. Es posible que pro medio de alguna alteración neuroendocrina desconocida se haya podido inducir dicho síndrome en nuestro paciente y que este tumor no sea un hallazgo incidental en este caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;64(2): 163-166, mar.-abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60251</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Kleine-Levin asociado a micorprolactinoma hipofisario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24379^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23803^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31370^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6328^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
