<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132193</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Grassroots coaches training in the papa project</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present work was twofold: (1) To describe the features of the motivational education program for coaches Empowering CoachingTM, implemented in the European Project PAPA (Promoting Adolescent Physical Activity) and (2) To assess Spanish grassroots coaches&#146; perception on the education workshops of the program as well as its implications at two different times, once the workshop had finished and after one year. 521 grassroots coaches from five participant countries (Spain, France, Greece, England and Norway) attended the Empowering CoachingTM workshops. Among them, 105 were from Spain (77 from the Valencian Community and 28 from Catalonia). In the follow-up data collection, 52 grassroots coaches from the Valencian Community participated. Questionnaires assessing satisfaction with the workshop, implementation, and barriers revealed that coaches were able to apply the workshop contents in their daily practice. Moreover, what was learned at the Empowering CoachingTM workshops was perceived to be innovative and made the coaches rethink their ideas about training. All of the grassroots coaches attending the workshops reported understanding and feeling able to integrate the Empowering CoachingTM principles in their practices and games, thus feeling able to become empowering coaches. Almost all coaches also reported not having difficulties to create empowering climates in their teams, finding the main difficulties with parents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balaguer, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramis, Yago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo ha sido doble: (1) Describir las características del programa de formación motivacional para entrenadores Empowering CoachingTM, aplicado en el marco del proyecto europeo PAPA (Promoting Adolescent Physical Activity) y (2) Analizar la percepción que tuvieron los entrenadores de fútbol base españoles sobre los talleres de formación de dicho programa y sus repercusiones, en dos momentos distintos,  una vez finalizado el taller y un año después. Un total de 521 entrenadores de fútbol base de los cinco países participantes (España, Francia, Grecia, Inglaterray Noruega) asistieron a los talleres Empowering CoachingTM. De estos entrenadores, 105 acudieron a los talleres realizados en España (77 en la Comunidad Valenciana y 28 en Cataluña). En la fase de seguimiento participaron un total de 52 entrenadores de fútbol base de la Comunidad Valenciana. Los análisis de los cuestionarios de satisfacción con el taller y de puesta en práctica y barreras mostraron que los entrenadores lograron aplicar lo aprendido en el taller en su actividad como entrenador. Asimismo, la formación recibida en los talleres Empowering CoachingTM fue percibida como novedosa y les hizo replantear sus ideas sobre el entrenamiento. La totalidad de los entrenadores de fútbol base asistentes a los talleres informaron entender y poder integrar en sus entrenamientos y partidos los principios de Empowering CoachingTM, para convertirse en entrenadores empowering. Por último, la práctica totalidad de los entrenadores de fútbol base informaron no haber tenido dificultad para crear un clima empowering en sus equipos, habiendo encontrado las mayores dificultades en los padres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(1): 131-138, 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formación de Entrenadores de Fútbol Base en el Proyecto PAPA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
