<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127346</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of lacosamide in the treatment of refractory neuropathic pain: an open observational trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Although different treatments are available for neuropathic pain, these patients are often refractory, which makes it necessary to test treatments that, as they have proven useful in other pathologies, could be effective in neuropathic pain. Patients and methods. The study made use of the medical records of patients who had been treated with lacosamide for neuropathic pain in different hospitals in the central area of the peninsula and who fulfilled similar characteristics in terms of refractoriness to other standard treatments, in a follow-up that lasted at least six months, or who had had to stop treatment with that drug for some reason or another. A sample of 114 patients (61 males and 53 females) with a mean age of 60.5 years was obtained from the data. Results. The most common causes of neuropathic pain were: diabetic polyneuropathy (31.6%), post-herpes neuralgia   (22.8%), trigeminal neuralgia (17.5%), suboccipital and lumbar-radicular neuralgia (both 12.3%). Effectiveness was good/ very good in most patients, with the mean score on the visual analogue scale after six months dropping from 7.7 to 4.8. No serious side effects were reported in any of the patients, but in 12 and 10 patients no recordings were made beyond six months, due to ineffectiveness and intolerance to the treatment, respectively. Conclusions. Treatment with lacosamide in neuropathic pain due to different causes could be considered an effective and well-tolerated alternative for patients who fail to respond to standard treatments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Latorre González, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almajano, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Argüelles, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toribio Díaz, M Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragón, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, M Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morín Martín, M. del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Del Valle, Octavio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo, Pedro E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valenzuela Rojas, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colás, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García del Carrizo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceballos, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa Frossard, Lucienne</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Aunque se dispone de diferentes tratamientos para el dolor neuropático, en muchas ocasiones estos pacientes son refractarios, lo que hace necesario probar tratamientos que, por su utilidad en otras patologías, podrían ser eficaces en el dolor neuropático. Pacientes y métodos. Se recogieron las historias clínicas de pacientes que hubieran sido tratados con lacosamida para el dolor neuropático, en diferentes hospitales de la zona centro peninsular, y que cumplieran unas características similares en cuanto a refractariedad a otros tratamientos estándares, en un seguimiento de al menos seis meses, o que hubiesen tenido que suspender el tratamiento con dicho fármaco por cualquier motivo. Se obtuvo una muestra de 114 pacientes, 61 varones y 53 mujeres, con una edad media de 60,5 años. Resultados. Las causas de dolor neuropático más frecuentes fueron: polineuropatía diabética (31,6%), neuralgia postherpética (22,8%), neuralgia del trigémino (17,5%), neuralgia suboccipital y lumbociatalgia (un 12,3% en ambas). La eficacia fue buena/muy buena en la mayoría de los pacientes, con un descenso medio en la escala analógica visual tras seis meses de 7,7 a 4,8. No se registraron efectos secundarios graves en ningún paciente, pero en 12 y 10 pacientes no hubo registro más allá de seis meses, por ineficacia e intolerancia al tratamiento, respectivamente. Conclusiones. El tratamiento con lacosamida en el dolor neuropático de diferentes causas podría considerarse como una alternativa efectiva y bien tolerada para aquellos pacientes que no respondan a los tratamientos estándares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;59(7): 289-293, oct. 2014. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127346</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectividad de la lacosamida en el tratamiento del dolor neuropático refractario: estudio observacional abierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50489^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10334^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14676^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
