<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15624</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A study of the stage of change and the emotional state applied to pathological gamblers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The purpose of this article is to study the stage of change and the emotional state of pathological gamblers at treatment intake within five drug addiction treatment centres (Unidades de Conductas Adictivas) in the Valencia region, Spain. Material and Method: A descriptive, multi-centre study. Material used: SOGS, BDI, STAI y CBA. Our sample consists of 133 subjects, 14 females and 119 males &#150;all being addicted to gambling. Data was analysed using the Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS). Results: All subjects in our sample meet the SOGS criteria for potential pathological gamblers. Half of the subjects are in a stage of contemplation. The anxiety/state mean percentile is 68.38 and it is 76.17 for anxiety/traits. BDI shows a dysphoric emotional estate. CBA scores show moderate alcohol consumption. 63.2% of them do not need any pharmacological treatments. Conclusions: The high percentage of subjects who drink alcohol while gambling requires a specific intervention. High levels of anxiety and dysphoria shown by the subjects at treatment intake seem to be related to stress factors common to gambling behaviours (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Socidrogalcohol</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: estudiar el estadio de cambio y el estado emocional de los jugadores patológicos al inicio de tratamiento en cinco Unidades de Conductas Adictivas de la Comunidad Valenciana. Material y Método: estudio multicéntrico de carácter descriptivo. Instrumentos utilizados: SOGS, BDI, STAI y CBA. Muestra constituida por 133 sujetos (14 mujeres y 119 hombres) adictos al juego. El análisis de los datos realizado con el paquete stadístico SPSS. Resultados: Todos los sujetos de la muestra cumplían criterios de probable jugador patológico (SOGS). La mitad de la muestra se ubica en el estadio de contemplación. Percentil medio 68.38 para ansiedad/estado y 76.17 para ansiedad/rasgo. El BDI refleja estado emocional disfórico. Las puntaciones del CBA indican consumo moderado de alcohol. El 63.2 por ciento no precisa tratamiento farmacológico. Conclusiones: El alto porcentaje de sujetos que presenta consumo de alcohol concominante con la conducta de juego, exige una intervención específica para estos sujetos. Los altos niveles de ansiedad y disforia que presentan los sujetos al inicio de tratamiento, parecen relacionados con los estresores propios de la conducta de juego (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);14(2): 145-150, abr. 2002. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio del estadio de cambio y estado emocional en jugadores patológicos</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Santos Diez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llinares Pellicer, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palau Muñoz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho Ferrer, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albiach Catalá, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15624</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
