<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138659</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish short-stay-units: results according to department designated to manage the unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To compare the efficiency of short-stay units (SSUs) managed by different departments within hospitals. Methods. Cross-sectional study in 40 hospitals with SSUs. From June 1 to December 31, 2012,we gathered data on clinical caseloads and management. Variables directly related to efficiency were mean length of stay, bed rotation index, and weekend discharge rate. Results. Forty SSUs were studied; 25 (62.5%) were managed by the hospital&#146;s emergency department (ED), 9 (22.5%) were managed by the internal medicine department (IMD), 5 (12.5%) were independent, and 1 was jointly managed by the hospital&#146;s ED and the IMD. A total of 45 140 patients were discharged from the SSUs. The most common diagnoses were exacerbation of chronic heart or respiratory disease, urinary tract infection, and respiratory infection. Age was the only variable that was related to the hospital department designated to manage these SSUs. The mean ages by management type were as follows: independent SSUs (75.6 years) vs ED-managed SSUs (67.2 years) vs IMD-managed SSUs(57.8 years) (P=.02). Group-by-group comparisons showed that the mean length of stay was shorter in ED-managed SSUs than in IMD-managed units (2.65 vs 3.73 respectively; P=.047), and overall mortality was lower in IMD-managed SSUs than in ED-managed SSUs (0.64% vs 3%; P=.033). However, unforeseen mortality (after excluding patients under palliative care or judged to be in the final hours of life) did not differ significantly between groups. Conclusions. We did not detect important differences between SSUs managed by different departments in the hospitals in this series. However, mean length of stay was found to be shorter in ED-managed SSUs than in IMD-managed un (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jacob Rodríguez, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llopis Roca, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ortiz de Zárate, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Pastor, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Bustos, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Sánchez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorens Soriano, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferré Losa, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sempere Montes, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Comparar los resultados de gestión clínica de las unidades de corta estancia (UCE) según su dependencia funcional. Metodología. Estudio de análisis transversal realizado en 40 hospitales con UCE (1 junio-31 diciembre 2012). Se recogieron datos de actividad y gestión clínica, considerando como variables directamente relacionadas con la eficiencia la estancia media, el índice de rotación por cama y el porcentaje de altas en fin de semana. Resultados. Se analizaron 40 UCE, 25 (62,5%) dependientes del servicio de urgencias (UCEU), 9 (22,5%) de medicina interna (UCEMI), 5 (12,5%) independientes (UCEI) y 1 con dependencia mixta (UCEU + UCEMI). El número total de altas fue de 45.140. Los diagnósticos más frecuentes fueron la exacerbación de la patología crónica cardiaca y respiratoria, la infección urinaria y la respiratoria. En relación a su dependencia funcional no se observaron diferencias en los parámetros analizados intergrupos salvo en la edad media (UCEI 75,6 años vs UCEU 67,2 vs UCEMI 57,8; p = 0,02). Al realizar la comparación intragrupos, la estancia media fue menor en las UCEU que las UCEMI (2,65 días vs 3,73;p = 0,047) y la mortalidad global menor en las UCEMI que las UCEU (0,64% vs 3%; p = 0,033), pero sin diferencias al comparar la mortalidad no esperada una vez excluidos los pacientes paliativos y/o en situación de últimas horas. Conclusión. En la serie analizada no se observan diferencias destacables al comparar las UCE en conjunto según dependencia funcional. Sin embargo, en el análisis intragrupos las UCEU lograron menor estancia media que las UCEMI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(2): 109-112, abr. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138659</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de los resultados de gestión de las unidades de corta estancia españolas según su dependencia funcional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17193^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
