<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109566</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis in a 3-year-old girl with no associated pathology involving a tumour</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Encephalitis due to NMDA receptors antibodies is a relatively common condition but it was under diagnosed until recently. It courses predictably and similarly in adults and children, although there are some differences, still less its association with tumours.  Case report. A 3 years-old girl who was admitted to our hospital with symptoms compatible with acute encephalitis, so we started treatment with acyclovir. During admission she was alterning periods of poor response to stimuli with periods of agitation, and progressed to complete silence, adding sleep problems. She suffered epileptic seizures, dystonic movements and autonomic disturbances. Cranial MRI showed mild cortical atrophy and EEG generalized slowing of base tracing. Repeated samples of cerebral spinal fluid were normal from cytological and biochemical point of view. In view  of the torpid evolution she began methylprednisolone therapy and later inmunoglobulins with no improvement. Upon confirmation of the positivity for NMDA receptors antibodies in cerebral spinal fluid and serum, cyclophosphamide was administered, with gradual improvement of symptoms until full recovery. After ten months of follow-up without treatment  she has not presented relapses and has ruled out the presence of tumours. Conclusions. It is important to recognize encephalitis with behavioural changes and abnormal movements, because early diagnosis and the beginning of appropriate therapy could improve the prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Viota, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duque Fernánez, M. Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Reyes, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Mendoza, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Conde, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La encefalitis por anticuerpos contra el receptor de NMDA (N-metil D-aspartato) es una enfermedad relativamente frecuente, aunque infradiagnosticada hasta hace unos años. Cursa de manera predecible y de forma parecida en adultos y en niños, aunque existen ciertas diferencias; su asociación con tumores es menor. Caso clínico. Niña de 3 años que ingresó en nuestro hospital con un cuadro compatible con encefalitis aguda, por lo que  se instauró tratamiento con aciclovir. Durante su ingreso alternó períodos de escasa respuesta a estímulos con períodos de agitación y progresó a mutismo completo, a lo que se sumaron problemas de sueño. Comenzó con crisis epilépticas, movimientos distónicos y alteraciones autonómicas. La resonancia magnética craneal mostró una leve atrofia cortical y el electroencefalograma un enlentecimiento generalizado del trazado de base. Las punciones lumbares fueron repetidamente normales desde el punto de vista citológico y bioquímico. Ante la tórpida evolución se inició tratamiento con metilprednisolona y posteriormente con inmunoglobulinas, sin mejoría. Tras confirmarse la positividad de los títulos de  anticuerpos antirreceptor de NMDA en el líquido cefalorraquídeo y el suero, se administró ciclofosfamida, con mejoría progresiva de la sintomatología hasta su recuperación completa. Tras 10 meses de seguimiento sin tratamiento, no ha presentado recaídas y se ha descartado la presencia de tumores. Conclusiones. Ante un cuadro de encefalitis, asociado a alteraciones del comportamiento y movimientos anormales, es importante sospechar esta enfermedad, ya que un diagnóstico temprano y la instauración del tratamiento adecuado  podrían mejorar su pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;55(10): 593-597, nov. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109566</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encefalitis antirreceptor de NMDA en una niña de 3 años sin patología tumoral asociada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54482^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10445^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53091^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
