<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-8117</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience in the treatment of 98 nasopharyngeal carcinomas: Long-term follow-up and analysis of prognostic factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This was a retrospective study of 98 patients (pts.) with histologically confirmed nasopharyngeal carcinoma. The clinico-demographic characteristics were: median age of 53 years (11-83); 74 males and 24 females (ratio 3:1); histology subtype OMS 2-3 in 89 pts. (90.8%); cranial nerve deficits in 11 pts. (11.2%); 50 (51%) were stage T3T4; 68 pts. (69.4%) N2N3 and 77 pts. (78.6%) stage IV. The therapeutic modalities were: radical radiotherapy (RT) alone in 42 pts., chemotherapy (CT) alone in 4 pts., RT + adjuvant CT in 10 pts. and neoadjuvant CT + RT in 42 pts. RT was delivered in wide fields, doses between 50-75 Gy with conventional fractionation. CT consisted in cisplatinum-based schedules (PF in 34 pts., BEC in 9 and others in 13 pts.). Analyzed by treatment, more males and stages N2N3 and IV were accrued in neoCT + RT arm (p &lt; or = 0.05). For the entire population, the overall complete response was achieved in 65 pts. (66.3%); in 27/35 pts. (77.1%) of the RT group and 30/51 pts. (58.8%) of CT + RT group (p 0.07) of pts. with III-IV stages. With a median follow-up of 74.5 months, 32 pts. (32.65%) are alive and free of disease. The projected OS for all pts. was 40 months (m), 51.4% at 3 years (y) and 45.5% at 5 y with a disease free survival of 37 m (0-236). No differences between treatment arms were found (p 0.4). In univariant analysis for OS in stage III-IV pts., age &gt; 50 y, histology OMS1, cranial nerve deficits, stage T3T4 and N2N3, were considered adverse prognostic factors (p &lt; or = 0.05). In multivariant analysis, only age &gt; 50 y and stages T3-T4, N2-N3 were significant (p &lt; or = 0.05). In conclusion, we demonstrated good long term survival without any differences among treatment modalities in pts. with advanced nasopharyngeal carcinomas. New therapeutic approaches are warranted in order to improve the outcome of this patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha efectuado un estudio retrospectivo de 98 pacientes (pts.) con confirmación histológica de carcinomas de nasofaringe. Las características demográficas fueron: edad mediana de 53 años (11-83); 74 varones y 24 mujeres (ratio 3:1); histología OMS 2-3 en 89 pts. (90,8 por ciento); déficits neurológicos en 11 pts. (11,2 por ciento); 50pts. (51 por ciento)fueron T3-4, 68 pts. (69,4 por ciento) N2-3 y 77 pts. (78,6 por ciento) estadio IV. Los tratamientos fueron: radioterapia radical (RT) en 42 casos, quimioterapia (CT) e n 4, RT+ CT complementaria en 10 y CT neoadyuvante+RT en 4-2. La RTfue liberada con altas energías en campos amplios, dosis entre 50-75 Gy y fraccionamiento convencional. La CT consistió en esquemas basados en cisplatino (PF en 34, BEC en 9 y otros en 13 casos). Analizados por tratamientos, se incluyeron más varones, estadios N2N3 y IV en el grupo de CT+RT (p  50 años, histología OMS 1, déficits de pares craneales y estadios T3-4 N2-3 fueron factores pronósticos desfavorables (p  50 años y estadios T3-4 N2-3 fueron significativos (p &lt; 0,05). En definitiva, logramos supervivencias considerables a largo plazo sin diferencias entre los tratamientos aplicados, aunque se precisan nuevas aproximaciones terapéuticas para mejorar la evolución de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;51(8): 691-696, nov. 2000. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia en el tratamiento de 98 carcinomas de nasofaringe. Seguimiento a largo plazo y análisis de factores pronósticos</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Berrocal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillem, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gaspar, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arribas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vendrell, BJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mengual, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapater, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrándis, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chust, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-8117</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23947^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28208^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
