<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160080</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The practice of sports and leisure activities for vulnerable youth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sports physical activity can be considered an occupation that directly affects the personal and social welfare and closely related to the perception of health, the acquisition of values and teaching life skills. In order to characterize the practice of sports leisure of young people in vulnerable situations, a questionnaire was handed out to 1762 Spanish youth of which 493 are considered within the population of vulnerable youth. The results showed that vulnerable young people consider conducting leisure sports activities in a different way than non-vulnerable young people. Similarly, there are differences in leisure sports preferences depending on the variable sex and type of sport they do. The results derive in psycho-educational implications that arise (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Noguero, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Castilla, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juanas Oliva, Ángel de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La actividad físico deportiva puede considerarse una ocupación que incide directamente en el bienestar personal y social y que guarda una estrecha relación con la percepción de la salud, la adquisición de valores y la enseñanza de competencias de vida. Con el objetivo de caracterizar la práctica de ocio deportivo de los jóvenes en situación de vulnerabilidad, se aplicó un cuestionario a 1762 jóvenes españoles de los cuales 493 son considerados dentro de la población de jóvenes vulnerables. Los resultados pusieron de manifiesto que los jóvenes vulnerables consideran la realización de actividades de ocio deportivo de un modo diferenciado al de los jóvenes no vulnerables. Igualmente, se encuentran diferencias en las preferencias de ocio deportivo en función de la variable sexo y el tipo de actividad deportiva que realizan. Los resultados derivan en implicaciones psico-educativas que se presentan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(supl.2): 27-32, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160080</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La práctica de ocio deportivo de los jóvenes en situación de vulnerabilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8076^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50263</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37735^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37735^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
