<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95408</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pre-surgical nursing visit: Evaluating the effectiveness of nursing intervention and patient perception</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To determine patient satisfaction with the pre-surgical visit, explore the specific contents of interventions performed, and analyse their effectiveness in post-surgical outcomes.Method A quasi-experimental, before-and-after, study was conducted at the San Cecilio University Hospital (Granada), in patients over 18 years. Patients in the intervention group received additional information on surgical procedures in a structured pre-surgical nursing visit between January and June 2008.Results Of the 580 patients included, 41.4% were men, and 58.6% were women, with an average age of 56 years, and of whom 76% had received surgery in the past. The results of this study demonstrate that nursing interventions on surgical patients have positive results on, the level of anxiety, self-control of fear and anxiety, knowledge of patient care, comfort and pain level. They also indicated a high level of patient satisfaction with the pre-surgical visit.ResultsNo statistically significant differences were found between men and women.Conclusions This nursing intervention not only allows us to give personalised and appropriate information to the surgical patient but also improves the satisfaction of these patients, having positive post-surgical effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Ruiz, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zafra-Norte, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-García, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Ramírez, Amanda Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Espinosa, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranda-Salcedo, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orihuela-Pérez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar-Julián, Francisco Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Conocer la satisfacción del paciente con la visita prequirúrgica, explorar los contenidos específicos de las intervenciones realizadas y analizar su efectividad en los resultados postoperatorios.Método Estudio casi experimental realizado en el Hospital Universitario de San Cecilio de Granada en pacientes mayores de 18 años a los que se realizó la visita estructurada preoperatoria de enfermería entre enero y junio de 2008.Resultados Participaron 580 pacientes: 41,4% hombres y 58,6% mujeres de edad media 56 años, teniendo un 76% experiencias quirúrgicas previas. Los resultados ponen de manifiesto que la intervención enfermera realizada en el paciente quirúrgico tiene resultados positivos sobre el nivel de ansiedad, el autocontrol de miedo y ansiedad, los conocimientos de cuidados de enfermedad, el nivel de comodidad y en nivel de dolor. No se reflejan diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre hombres y mujeres. Se evidencia así mismo un alto grado de satisfacción del paciente.Conclusiones Esta intervención enfermera no solo nos permite dar una información personalizada y adecuada al paciente quirúrgico sino que mejora la satisfacción de estos pacientes teniendo efectos positivos en el postoperatorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);20(6): 349-354, nov.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Visita preoperatoria de enfermería: evaluación de la efectividad de la intervención enfermera y percepción del paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
