<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94418</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of overweight and obesity in office administrative clerks</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to determine the prevalence of overweight/obesity in this type of workers, to assess the influence of the gender and the age on the condition, and to consider the associated cardiovascular risk. Material and methods: a cross-sectional descriptive study was carried out. The sample was composed of 639 administrative clerks from 16 City Halls in the province of Vizcaya during 2003, of which 432 were selected and paired by age (216 men and 216 women). The study variables were: sex, age, body mass index, biochemical values, and blood pressure. Descriptive statistics indexes and the Homogeneity T-test of percentages expressing the confidence interval of the percentage difference for comparison of both genders were used to process and analyse data. Results: 67,13% of the women had a normal weight against 39,81% of men. Men presented higher percentages of overweight(type I and II) and type I Obesity than women. Men had significantly higher values than women of creatinine,  uric acid, triglycerides and liver enzymes. The prevalence of highblood pressure was significantly higher in men than in women(11,57% vs 4,63%).Conclusions: overweight and obesity in office clerks in Vizcaya present significant differences between the sexes, with women presenting the higher percentages of normal weight. This demonstrates that female office clerks have less risk of cardiovascular disease than their male counterparts. To achieve an ideal weight, it is essential to follow the health programs offered at healthcare centres, especially those designed by Nursing graduates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Ardanaz, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo de la Hoz, Gorka</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio Avendaño, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hierro Gurruchaga, Maite del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reglero García, Leire</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artetxe Ferrero, Ibon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Ardanaz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: determinar la prevalencia de sobrepeso/obesidad en este colectivo laboral, valorar la influencia del sexo y la edad y considerar el riesgo cardiovascular asociado. Material y métodos: se llevó a cabo un estudio descriptivo transversal. El marco muestral fueron los 639 administrativos de 16 ayuntamientos de la provincia de Vizcaya durante el año 2003, de donde fueron seleccionados 432 individuos apareados por edad (216 hombres y 216 mujeres). Las variables de estudio fueron: sexo, edad, índice de masa corporal, valores bioquímicos y tensión arterial. Para el tratamiento y análisis de los datos se utilizaron índices de estadística descriptiva y el test de homogeneidad de porcentajes con expresión del intervalo de confianza de la diferencia de porcentajes para la comparación entre sexos. Resultados: un 67,13% de las mujeres tenía normo peso frente a un 39,81% de los hombres. Los hombres presentaban mayores porcentajes de sobrepeso (tipo I y II) y de obesidad tipo I que las mujeres. Los hombres tenían valores significativamente mayores que las mujeres de creatinina, ácido úrico, triglicéridos y enzimas hepáticas. La prevalencia de HTA fue significativamente mayor en hombres que en mujeres (11,57%frente a 4,63%).Conclusiones: el sobrepeso y la obesidad en trabajadores administrativos de Vizcaya ofrecen diferencias significativas entre sexos, siendo las mujeres las que presentaron mayores porcentajes de normo peso. Esta situación sugiere un menor riesgo cardiovascular en las mujeres administrativas con respecto a sus compañeros de trabajo. Para lograr un peso adecuado se estima de vital importancia la utilización de los programas de salud que se ofrecen en las instituciones sanitarias; especialmente los diseñados por los Diplomados en Enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;11(3): 8-12, abr. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94418</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad en trabajadores administrativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
