<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050359</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Muscle arquitecture in four groups of young women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Muscle architecture describes the geometric design of a  muscle. It will have a great influence in tue force generating capacity and fue shortening velocity of skeletal muscle. The purposes of this study were to analyse and compare, in four groups of young women with different levels of physical activity, fue architectural characteristics of lower limb extensor muscles, and tue differences between muscles. Twelve elite female volleyball players (ELITE), 12 club level    female volleyball players (MEDIO), 10 physical education    students (EST) and 12 sedentary youngwomen (SED)    volunteered for fue study. Muscle thickness, pennation    angies and fascicle length of vastus lateralis (VL),    gastrocnemius medialis (GM) and gastrocnemius lateralis    (GL) were analysed by means of ultrasonography, and tue    anthropometric characteristics of each group were    determined. The differences among muscles were similar to    those reported in the literature, and were related to fue    functional use of each muscle. The VL muscle architecture    was related to the development of great forces at high    contraction velocities, because of its muscle thickness and fascicle length. There were signillcant differences in muscle thicknesses and fascicle lengths between SED and the groups of volleyball players (MED and ELITE). These differences would be related to the ability to develop higher levels of force and velocity, due to the greater number of in-parallel and in-series sarcomeres. The longer fascicle lengths found in fue ELITE group would have been caused by their specific training, mainly composed by jumps and explosive movements that led to forced stretching of muscle fascicles. The correlations between fascicle lengths and muscle thickness in ELITE and MED are similar to those found in sports where explosive strength and speed are essential for the performance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ureña, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegre, Luis M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abián, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara, Amador J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Linares, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La arquitectura muscular se define como la disposición  geométrica de las fibras musculares, e influye    significativamente en las características funcionales del    músculo. Los objetivos de este estudio han sido analizar y    comparar, en cuatro grupos de mujeres jóvenes, con distinto nivel de actividad física, la arquitectura de la musculatura extensora del miembro inferior, estudiando las diferencias entre músculos. Los grupos analizados fueron 12 jugadoras de voleibol de élite (ELITE), 12 jugadoras de voleibol de nivel medio (MED), la estudiantes de Educación Física (EST) y 12 mujeres sedentarias jóvenes (SED). Se obtuvieron valores del grosor muscular, los ángulos de pennación y la    longitud de fascículos de los músculos vasto lateral (VL),    gastrocnemio medial (OM) y gastrocnemio lateral (01),    mediante ecografía, y se determinaron las características    antropométricas de cada grupo. Las diferencias arquitectónicas entre músculos eran similares a las descritas en la bibliografía, y se correspondían con el tipo de acciones que desempefian. El VL presentaba un disefio orientado a la producción de fuerza a altas velocidades, debido a su grosor ya la longitud de sus fascículos. Se encontraron diferencias significativas en el grosor muscular y las longitudes de fascículos del grupo SED, comparado con los grupos MED y ELITE, lo que se relacionaría con la capacidad de las jugadores de voleibol para desarrollar niveles más altos de fuerza y velocidad debido a un mayor número de sarcómeros en paralelo y en serie. Las mayores longitudes de fascículos encontradas en el grupo ELITE estarían relacionadas con el tipo de entrenamiento que lleva a cabo, que incluye una gran cantidad de saltos y movimientos que producen alargamiento de los fascículos musculares mediante acción mecánica. Las correlaciones entre longitudes de fascículos y grosor muscular en los grupos ELITE y MED concuerdan con aquellas encontradas en deportes donde la fuerza explosiva y la velocidad son fundamentales para el rendimiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;23(114): 265-273, jul.-ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050359</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Arquitectura muscular en cuatro grupos de mujeres jóvenes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32127^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13266</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32124^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32127^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32124^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9324^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
