<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109919</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment alternatives in massive hemorrhage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Massive hemorrhage is the main cause of mortality and morbidity in trauma patients, and is one of the most important causes in any patient following major surgery. Conventional treatment consists of volume replacement, including the transfusion of blood products, so that tissue perfusion and oxygenation may be maintained. Associated hypothermia, acidosis and coagulopathy is a lethal triad. This review focuses on the latest therapeutic management of massive hemorrhage. The authors advocate the use of crystalloids as per protocol (controlled volumes) in order to achieve a systolic blood pressure of 85mmHg. The administration of the three blood products (red cells, plasma, and platelets) should be on a 1:1:1 basis. Where possible, this in turn should be guided by thromboelastography performed at point of care near the patient. Coagulopathy can occur early and late. With the exception of tranexamic acid, the cost-benefit relationships of the hemostatic agents, such as fibrinogen, prothrombin complex, and recombinant F VII, are subject to discussion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puppo-Moreno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Hinojosa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal-Noval, S. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo-Cabezas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hemorragia masiva es la principal causa de morbimortalidad en el paciente traumatizado, y una de las más importantes en el paciente sometido a cirugía mayor. El tratamiento convencional se basaba en la reposición inicial de la volemia con la infusión de grandes cantidades de fluidos y en la transfusión de hemoderivados, con objeto de asegurar la perfusión y oxigenación tisular. Hipotermia, acidosis y coagulopatía se considera triada letal. En esta revisión los autores abordan un enfoque terapéutico actualizado del manejo de la hemorragia masiva. Se preconiza infundir cristaloides de forma pautada (no masiva) para lograr una presión arterial sistólica de 85mmHg. La administración de hemoderivados debe ser precoz y con ratio 1:1:1 (cantidades equiparables de concentrados de hematíes, plasma y plaquetas), y si es posible, guiada por tromboelastograma a la cabecera del paciente. La coagulopatía puede ser precoz y tardía. Salvo el ácido tranexámico, se discute la relación coste-beneficio de fármacos prohemostáticos, como fibrinógeno, complejo protrombínico, y FVII recombinante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);36(7): 496-503, oct. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109919</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alternativas terapéuticas de la hemorragia masiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22179^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30229^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14540^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6626^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14300^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
