<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147279</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of shooting effectiveness and decision-making during shooting according to basket height modifications at the youth stage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present study was to identify the effect of a basketball unit of work that modifies the height of the hoop on the shooting effectiveness, the shooting decision-making process, and the ball possessions ending with a shot. The study was a cuasiexperiment with control and experimental groups measured pre and post intervention. The basketball unit of work was composed of 10 lessons that were applied to a sample of 74 students (14 years old). Control group received the lessons with the regular height of the basket (3.05m) and the experimental group received the lessons with variations in the height of the basket according to each task. The evaluation task was a 3 vs. 3 game situation. The results showed that experimental group increased the number of shots, the shooting effectiveness, as well as the decision-making process related to shooting action. The results enhance the need to modify and adapt the basketball height to the tasks and exercises specificity, and then to improve the shooting efficiency and effectiveness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio fue identificar el efecto de una unidad didáctica de baloncesto en la que se modifica la altura del aro sobre la efectividad de tiro, el proceso de toma de toma de decisiones, y el número de fases de ataque que finalizan en lanzamiento. El estudio fue estudio cuasi-experimental con grupo control y experimental medidos antes y después de la intervención. La unidad didáctica de baloncesto se compone de 10 sesiones que se aplicaron a una muestra de 74 estudiantes (14 años). El grupo control recibió las sesiones con la canasta a una altura normal de (3.05m) y el grupo experimental recibió las sesiones con variaciones en la altura de la canasta de acuerdo a cada tarea. La tarea de evaluación era una situación de juego 3 vs 3. Los resultados mostraron que el grupo experimental aumentó el número de lanzamientos, el número de fases de ataque que finalizan en lanzamiento, así como el proceso de toma de decisiones relacionadas con el lanzamiento. Los resultados señalan la necesidad de modificar y adaptar la altura de baloncesto a las tareas y ejercicios, para mejorar la eficiencia y eficacia del lanzamiento en baloncesto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(supl.1): 93-96, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147279</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicencia del uso de un protopio de canasta con modificación de la altura del cesto sobre la eficacia y la toma de decisió del lanzamiento en el ámbito escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36432^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36432^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36432^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36432^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
