<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83931</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patients&#146; rights. More than a question of attitude</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesTo analyze hospital and primary care physicians&#146; knowledge of certain patients&#146; rights recently modified by Spanish Law 41/2002 (law of patient autonomy).Material and methodsWe performed a voluntary survey of hospital and primary care physicians who were presented with three problem situations drawn from court decisions and the law of patient autonomy.ResultsAmong interviewed physicians, 78% were familiar with the law of patient autonomy. Fifty-three percent knew how to explain what advance wills are. Eighty-eight percent responded correctly to the problem situation concerning the right to privacy. Fifty-seven percent knew the legal age of consent for healthcare. Seventy percent correctly applied patients&#146; right not to be informed. Only 38% responded correctly to all three problem situations. Correct responses were more frequent (odds ratio: 2.4&#150;3.4) among physicians who were familiar with the law of patient autonomy.ConclusionsAt least one out of every 10 physicians could be legally compromised by lack of knowledge of the law of patient autonomy. Patients&#146; rights were most likely to be jeopardized in patients aged between 16 and 18 years old. Prior information on the law of patient autonomy contributes to greater compliance(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Joaquín Mira, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vitaller,  Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guilabert,  Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoAnalizar si determinados derechos de los pacientes (Ley 41/2002 de autonomía del paciente [LAP]) son conocidos entre los profesionales de la medicina.Material y métodoEncuesta a profesionales de hospitales y de atención primaria con situaciones problema extraídas de sentencias judiciales y de la LAP.ResultadosUn 78% dijo conocer la LAP. El 53% sabrían explicar qué son las voluntades anticipadas. A la situación problema sobre derecho a la intimidad respondieron correctamente el 88%. El 57% acertó cuál es la mayoría de edad sanitaria. El 70% aplicó correctamente el derecho del paciente a no ser informado. Sólo un 38% respondió correctamente a los tres problemas planteados. Los aciertos son más frecuentes (odds ratio: 2,4&#150;3,4) entre quienes dicen conocer la LAP.ConclusionesAl menos uno de cada diez profesionales podrían ver comprometida su seguridad jurídica por desconocimiento de la LAP. Los jóvenes entre 16 y 18 años tienen más difícil que se respete su derecho a la autonomía como pacientes. La información previa sobre la LAP ayuda a un mejor cumplimiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(3): 247-250, May. - Jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Derechos de los pacientes. Algo más que una cuestión de actitud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36355</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8671</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11252</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
