<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153292</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Musculoskeletal interventional radiology: ultrasound and CT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We aim to describe imaging-guided (ultrasound and CT) interventional techniques in the musculoskeletal system that can be performed by general radiologists, whether in hospitals, primary care clinics, private offices, or other settings. The first requirement for doing these procedures is adequate knowledge of the anatomy of the musculoskeletal system. The second requirement is to inform the patient thoroughly about the technique, the risks involved, and the alternatives available in order to obtain written informed consent. The third requirement is to ensure that the procedure is performed in accordance with the principles of asepsis in relation to the puncture zone and to all the material employed throughout the procedure. The main procedures that can be done under ultrasound guidance are the following: fine needle aspiration cytology (FNAC), core needle biopsy (CNB), diagnostic and/or therapeutic arthrocentesis, drainage of juxta-articular fluid collections, drainage of abscesses, drainage of hematomas, treatment of Baker's cyst, treatment of ganglia, treatment of bursitis, infiltrations and treatment of plantar fasciitis, plantar fibrosis, epicondylitis, Achilles tendinopathy, and Morton's neuroma, puncture and lavage of calcifications in calcifying tendinopathy. We also review the following CT-guided procedures: diagnosis of spondylodiscitis, FNAC of metastases, arthrography, drainages. Finally, we also mention more complex procedures that can only be done in appropriate settings: bone biopsies, treatment of facet joint pain, radiofrequency treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bueno Horcajadas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agrela Rojas, EW</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martel Villagrán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Nuestro objetivo es describir aquellas técnicas de intervencionismo musculoesquéletico guiadas por imagen (ecografía y/o tac) que pueden ser realizadas por un radiólogo general, ya sea en hospitales, centros de salud, consultas privadas, etc. El primer requisito para la realización de estos procedimientos es el disponer de un adecuado conocimiento de la anatomía del sistema musculoesquelético. El segundo, que el paciente debe ser informado adecuadamente sobre la técnica, riesgos y alternativas al mismo, relativo por tanto, a la obtención del consentimiento firmado. El tercero es que estos procedimientos se realizan siguiendo los principios de asepsia de la zona de punción, así como del material empleado y lo que acontece durante la realización del procedimiento. Los principales procedimientos que pueden realizarse guiados por ecografía son los siguientes: punción aspiración con aguja fina (PAAF), biopsia con aguja gruesa (BAG), artrocentesis diagnósticas y/o terapéuticas, drenajes de colecciones yuxtaarticulares, drenajes de abscesos, drenaje de hematomas, tratamiento de quiste de Baker, tratamiento de gangliones, tratamiento de las bursitis, infiltraciones y tratamiento de la fascitis plantar, la fibrosis plantar, las epicondilitis, las tendinopatía del tendón de Aquiles o del neuroma de Morton, punción- lavado de calcificaciones en la tendinopatía calcificante. En cuanto a los procedimientos guiados por tac, revisaremos los siguientes: diagnóstico de las espondilodiscitis, PAAF de las metástasis, artrografía, drenajes. También haremos un recordatorio de procedimientos más complejos que deben realizarse en el entorno adecuado: biopsias óseas, tratamiento del dolor facetario, radiofrecuencia terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);58(supl.2): 45-57, mayo 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervencionismo en musculoesquelético. Ecografía y tac</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23228^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23228^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52417^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23228^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52417^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
