<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83765</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Updated review on the prevention of biological hazards in the nursing students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">If the carrying out a practices is something extremely important in all degree studies, in the case of nursing this is something even more fundamental and of great educational impact. During that period, students not only put their knowledge and theory into practice, they get in touch with reality and they also expose themselves to a series of risks inherent to our profession. In addition to that, one has to take into account the appearance of various factors that aggravate their susceptibility; their inexperience as professionals, their exposure to some degree of stress due to the variable conditions and uncertainties in their environment, the lack of coverage under the PRL law, makes this group more vulnerable to the risks(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Arroyo, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Si la realización de las prácticas es algo importante en todas las titulaciones, en Enfermería resulta fundamental y tiene un gran impacto educativo. Durante este período los alumnos, además de poner en práctica los conocimientos teóricos, toman contacto con la realidad, donde se exponen a una serie de peligros inherentes a dicha profesión. A este hecho hay que añadir varios factores que agravan la situación: la inexperiencia como profesionales, la aparición de cierto grado de estrés provocado por las situaciones variables y de incertidumbre que los rodean, y la no contemplación de este colectivo por parte de la Ley de Prevención de Riesgos Laborales. Todo ello hace al alumnado más vulnerable frente a los riesgos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(12): 834-839, dic. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83765</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudiantes de enfermería. Prevención de riesgos biológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d61^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51876^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11750^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
