<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162528</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of the HAMC list to patients with polypharmacy in a primary healthcare center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Application of the HAMC list to patients with polypharmacy in a primary healthcare center Objective: To know the use of drugs included in the HAMC List (High-Alert Medications for patients with Chronic illnesses) in polypharmacy patients of a Health Center. Design: Descriptive, observational cross-sectional study using medical records. Location: Primary Healthcare Centre Manzanares II (Ciudad Real). Participants: 266 patients with polypharmacy (&amp;#8805;6 drugs) of both sexes from the Health Area, selected by systematic sampling. Main measures: Age, sex, cardiovascular risk factors, number of drugs (listed by SESCAM), chronic diseases, active drugs (&amp;#8805; 3 months) reflected in the electronic medical history, and prescription of drugs included in the HAMC list. Results: 96,3% (CI 95 % 93.2-98.2 %) of polypharmacy patients take drugs on the HAMC list. The average number of HAMC list drugs is 2.42 (± 1.26) (without differences between sexes). The most widely used are antiplatelet agents (53 %), benzodiazepines (45.1 %), hypoglycemic agents (28.9 %), beta blockers (28.2 %), loop diuretics (2.3 %) and opioids (17.3 %), with gender differences in antiplatelet agents (p&lt;0.01), benzodiazepines (p&lt;0.05) and opioids (p&lt;0.01). In pluripathology patients there are gender differences in the use of loop diuretics (p &lt;0.001), anticoagulants (p &lt;0.01) and NSAIDs (p &lt;0.05). Conclusions: The majority of polypharmacy patients take drugs included in the HAMC List. It is advisable to carry out a proper drug monitoring of chronic and/or pluripathology patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Sánchez-Migallón, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer el uso de los medicamentos del Listado MARC (Medicamentos de Alto Riesgo en el Paciente Crónico) en los pacientes polimedicados del Centro de Salud. Diseño: Estudio descriptivo observacional de carácter transversal sobre historias clínicas. Emplazamiento: Centro de Salud de Manzanares II (Ciudad Real). Participantes: 266 pacientes polimedicados (&amp;#8805;6 medicamentos) seleccionados por muestreo aleatorio sistemático. Mediciones Principales: Edad, sexo, factores de riesgo cardiovascular, número de fármacos (listado del SESCAM), enfermedades crónicas, fármacos activos &amp;#8805; 3 meses reflejados en historia clínica electrónica y prescripción de medicamentos incluidos en el listado MARC. Resultados: El 96,3% (IC 95 % 93,2-98,2) de los pacientes polimedicados tomaban medicamentos incluidos en el listado MARC. El número medio de fármacos del listado fue de 2,42 (DE:1,26) (sin diferencias entre sexos). Los más utilizados fueron antiagregantes (53 %), benzodiazepinas (45,1 %), hipoglucemiantes (28,9 %), beta-bloqueantes (28,2 %), diuréticos del asa (23,3 %) y opioides (17,3 %), mostrando diferencias entre sexos en el consumo de antiagregantes (p&lt;0,01), benzodiazepinas (p&lt;0,05) y opioides (p&lt;0,01). En los pacientes pluripatológicos existieron diferencias entre sexos en el consumo de diuréticos del asa (p&lt;0,001), anticoagulantes (p&lt;0,01) y AINEs (p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones: La gran mayoría de los pacientes polimedicados toman medicamentos incluidos en el listado MARC. Es aconsejable la realización de un adecuado seguimiento farmacológico de los pacientes crónicos y/o pluripatológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;10(1): 5-11, feb. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162528</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación del listado MARC a pacientes polimedicados en un Centro de Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
