<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057965</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hereditary hyperferritinemia cataracts syndrome in a Spanish family caused by the A40G mutation (Paris) in the L-ferritin (FTL) gene associated with the mutation H63D in the HFE gene</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The cataract-associated increase in serum ferritin without any other data of iron overload is known since 1995 as hyperferritinemia-cataract syndrome (HHCS). More than 100 families have been described all around the world with this syndrome and more than 30 mutations in the L-ferritin (FTL) gene. We introduce a family from Madrid (Spain), with the disease phenotype and a genotype with the A40G mutation, named Paris, and besides carrier of the H63D mutation of the HFE gene. Patients and method: The proband and his first grade relatives were studied by determining the hemogram, biochemistry, iron metabolism and HFE gene mutations study, as well as by hepatic magnetic resonance imaging and oftalmologic study. Afterwards a molecular study of the coding region for the IRE (iron responsive element) of the FTL gene was done by sequencing. Results: The proband is a male with early cataracts and hyperferritinemia, heterozygous for the H63D and A40G mutations of the HFE and FTL genes, respectively. The mother has the same phenotype (hyperferritinemia and surgery for early cataracts) and genotype (H63D and A40G alleles in heterozygosis). On the other hand, the sister has no cataracts but has hyperferritinemia, is homozygous for H63D and heterozygous for A40G. The father is heterozygous for H63D, but lacks the A40G mutation and the HHCS phenotype. Conclusions: The HHCS must be included in the differential diagnosis of the hyperferritinemias without iron overload. In turn, hyperferritinemia must be ruled out in an early cataract. The only treatment is ophthalmological, and phlebotomies must be avoided in a false hemochromatosis diagnostic when HFE gene mutations are associated, because of the poor tolerance for causing severe anemia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ruano, Miguel L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Rueda, Alejandro del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El aumento de ferritina sérica asociado a cataratas, sin otros datos de sobrecarga de hierro, se conoce desde 1995 como síndrome hereditario de hiperferritinemia y cataratas (SHHC). Se han descrito más de 100 familias en todo el mundo con este síndrome y más de 30 mutaciones en el gen de la L-ferritina (FTL). Presentamos una familia española, natural de Madrid, con fenotipo de la enfermedad y genotipo con la mutación A40G, denominada París, portadora además de la mutación H63D del gen HFE. Pacientes y método: Se estudió al probando y sus familiares de primer grado, a quienes se realizaron hemograma, bioquímica, estudio del metabolismo del hierro y de las mutaciones del gen HFE, así como resonancia magnética hepática e informe oftalmológico. Posteriormente se efectuó un estudio molecular mediante secuenciación de la región que codifica el IRE (iron responsive element) del gen FTL. Resultados: El probando es un varón con cataratas prematuras e hiperferritinemia, heterocigoto para las mutaciones H63D y A40G de los genes HFE y FTL, respectivamente. La madre tiene los mismos fenotipo (hiperferritinemia y cirugía de cataratas precoces) y genotipo (alelos H63D y A40G en heterocigosis). La hermana, por el contrario, no tiene cataratas, pero sí hiperferritinemia, es homocigota para H63D y heterocigota para A40G. El padre es heterocigoto para H63D, pero carece de la mutación A40G y del fenotipo del SHHC. Conclusiones: El SHHC debe incluirse en el diagnóstico diferencial de hiperferritinemias que no se acompañan de sobrecarga de hierro. A su vez, ante una catarata prematura se debe descartar la presencia de hiperferritinemia. El único tratamiento es el oftalmológico, y se deben evitar las flebotomías debidas a un falso diagnóstico de hemocromatosis cuando hay mutaciones del gen HFE, por su mala tolerancia al provocar anemia grave</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);129(11): 414-417, sept. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057965</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome hereditario de hiperferritinemia y cataratas en una familia española con la mutación A40G (París) en el gen de la L-ferritina (FTL) asociada a la mutación H63D en el gen HFE</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32650^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32960^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5974</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5402^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6582^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32959^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
