<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056491</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rectal cancer staging with endoscopic ultrasonography: correlation with pathological staging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: our aim was to evaluate the accuracy of endosonography        (EUS) in our experience, to stage rectal cancer.        Material and methods: we prospectively included all patients        with rectal cancer staged in our unit from September 2002        until February 2006 in a database. We selected those patients        who had a complete EUS examination and were surgically treated        without neoadjuvant therapy. Once we had the results of the        histopathological staging (pTN), which was considered the gold        standard, we compared the results of the previous EUS staging        (uTN) with those of the pTN. We calculated the sensitivity, specificity,        positive predictive value, negative predictive value and accuracy        for each T stage, and for N staging considered as N positive        or negative. We also calculated the global accuracy for T stage.        We also calculated the agreement of uTN with pTN staging using        the kappa index for N stage, and quadratic weighted kappa index        for T stage.        Results: we staged 120 patients with rectal cancer during the        mentioned period. Of these, 36 patients met inclusion criteria and        were evaluated, 21 women and 15 men. Mean age was 68,53 ±        10,15 yo (range: 48-90). Global T stage accuracy was 83%. N        stage accuracy was 72%. We obtained a S, E, PPV, NPV and A of        91, 100, 100, 96 and 97% for T1; 82, 88, 75, 91 and 86% for        T2; 86, 91, 86, 91 and 89% for T3; and 14, 86, 20, 80 and        72% for N stage respectively. Kappa value for T stage was 0,87        indicating a &#147;very good&#148; agreement between uT and pT according        to the kappa index criteria. Kappa value for N stage agreement        was 0,005; &#147;poor&#148; according to the same criteria.        Conclusions: in our experience, the diagnostic accuracy of        EUS for T and N staging of rectal cancer is 83% and 72% respectively,        similar results as previously published. uT staging for rectal        cancer shows a &#147;very good&#148; agreement with pT staging</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borda, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Irisarri, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorena, e</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: nuestro objetivo fue evaluar la precisión diagnóstica        (PD) en nuestro medio de la ecoendoscopia (USE) para la estadificación        del cáncer de recto (CR).        Material y métodos: incluimos de manera prospectiva a todos        los pacientes con CR estadificados en nuestra unidad entre        septiembre de 2002 y febrero de 2006 en una base de datos. Seleccionamos        aquellos pacientes en los que se había realizado una        estadificación completa con USE(uTN) y fueron intervenidos quirúrgicamente        sin tratamiento neoadyuvante. Consideramos la estadificación        histológica (pTN) como patrón oro, y comparamos        los resultados de la uTN previa con los de la pTN. Calculamos la        sensibilidad (S), especificidad (E), valores predictivos positivo (VPP)        y negativo (VPN) y PD para cada estadio T, y estadio N considerado        como positivo o negativo. Calculamos la concordancia entre la        uTN y la pTN utilizando el índice de kappa para el estadio N, y el        mismo índice con ponderación cuadrática para el estadio T.        Resultados: ciento veinte pacientes con CR fueron estadificados        en nuestra unidad, cumpliendo 36 criterios de inclusión y fueron        analizados en este estudio (21 hombres, 15 mujeres). La edad        media fue de 68,53 ± 10,15 años (rango = 48-90). La PD de la        uT global y uN fueron del 83 y 72% respectivamente. Obtuvimos        una S, E, VPP, VPN y PD de 91, 100, 100, 96 y 97% para el        T1; 82, 88, 75, 91 y 86% para el T2; 86, 91, 86, 91 y 89%        para el T3; y 14, 86, 20, 80 y 72% para el estadio N respectivamente.        El índice de kappa para la estadificación T fue de 0,87        (concordancia &#147;muy buena&#148; entre uT y pT); y de 0,005 para la estadificación        N (concordancia &#147;pobre&#148;).        Conclusiones: en nuestra experiencia, la PD de la uTN del        cáncer de recto alcanza el 83 y el 72% respectivamente, resultados        acordes con lo disponible en la literatura. La uT del cáncer de        recto muestra una concordancia &#147;muy buena&#148; con la pT</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;99(3): 132-137, mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estadificación del cáncer de recto mediante ultrasonografía endoscópica: correlación con la estadificación histológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
