<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145546</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic enteritis in patients undergoing pelvic radiotherapy: prevalence, risk factors and associated complications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: the radiation of tumours located in pelvic organs can cause mucositis in the bowel. The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence, risk factors, and complications of chronic radiation enteritis in patients who had received pelvic radiotherapy. Patients and methods: cross-sectional study recruiting 150 patients that had been treated with radiation therapy during the year 2008 because of a prostate, cervical, endometrial or rectal cancer. The patients were asked about symptoms related to enteritis, and about changes in body weight and in dietary patterns. Sex, age, treatment modalities, acute enteritis, and type of cancer were considered possible risk factors, and were analysed with univariate and multivariate methods. Results: the study included 100 patients, 84% males, median age 72.3 years. Chronic radiation enteritis was found in 20% of the patients, most of them grade 1 (45%). Furthermore, 10% had lost greater than or equal to  5 kg of weight, 3% had been hospitalized due to diarrhoea or bowel obstruction, and 11% had changed their diet, mainly by removing vegetables, legumes and pastry. Male gender, age, previous acute radiation enteritis, and chemotherapy were associated with chronic enteritis, but only chemotherapy remained independently related to bowel toxicity after multivariate analysis (OR = 3.59 [95% CI 1.20&#150;10.73]). Conclusion: chronic enteritis is common among patients treated with pelvic radiotherapy, especially if chemotherapy is associated. The complication rate is low, but a significant number of patients change their usual diet in order to prevent symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal Casariego, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros Pomar, María D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Moreno, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Rodríguez, Isidoro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja Fernández, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kyriakos, Georgios</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar Taibo, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urioste Fondo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la radiación de los tumores de la cavidad pélvica puede provocar mucositis a nivel intestinal. El objetivo de nuestro estudio fue determinar la prevalencia, los factores de riesgo y las complicaciones de la enteritis rádica crónica en los pacientes tratados con radioterapia pélvica. Pacientes y métodos: estudio transversal sobre 150 pacientes tratados con radioterapia pélvica durante el año 2008 debido a un cáncer de próstata, cérvix, endometrio o recto. Se interrogó a los pacientes sobre la presencia de síntomas sugestivos de enteritis y sobre cambios en el peso habitual y modificaciones en su dieta. Los parámetros considerados como posibles factores de riesgo de enteritis crónica (sexo, edad, tratamiento antitumoral, enteritis aguda previa y tipo de tumor) se analizaron con métodos univariantes y multivariantes. Resultados: el estudio incluyó finalmente a 100 pacientes, el 84% varones, con una mediana de edad de 72,3 años. Se encontró una prevalencia de enteritis rádica crónica del 20%, en la mayoría de grado 1 (45%). Por otra parte, el 10% referían una pérdida de peso &amp;#8805; 5 kg, el 3% habían requerido hospitalización debido a diarrea incoercible o a obstrucción intestinal, y el 11% habían modificado su patrón de alimentación habitual, reduciendo principalmente el consumo de verduras, legumbres y dulces. Se encontró asociación entre la enteritis rádica crónica y el sexo masculino, la edad, la enteritis rádica aguda previa y la quimioterapia, pero solo esta resultó asociarse de forma independiente con el desarrollo de enteritis rádica crónica después del análisis multivariante (OR = 3,59 [95% CI 1,20&#150;10,73]). Conclusión: la enteritis crónica es una entidad frecuente en los pacientes tratados con radioterapia pélvica, sobre todo cuando se asocia con quimioterapia. La tasa de complicaciones por esta patología es baja, pero un número importante de pacientes realiza modificaciones en su dieta habitual para aliviar o evitar la sintomatología derivada de aquella (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(5): 2178-2183, nov. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enteritis crónica en pacientes sometidos a radioterapia pélvica: prevalencia, factores de riesgo y complicaciones asociadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12271^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10579^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4831^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
