<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167749</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Beyong the Big Five: The role of extrinsic life aspirations in complusive buying</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The integration of units of differing natures which are found in different parts of some multilevel personality models is one of the most thought-provoking paths in contemporary research. In the field of compulsive buying, little is known about the interrelationships between the comparative and stable units such as personality traits (basic tendencies or Level I units) and goals (a kind of middle-level unit) which are more related to motivational processes and intentions governing people&#146;s behavior. Method: Self-reporting measures  of  compulsive buying, Big Five personality traits, and extrinsic life aspirations were administered to a general population sample consisting of 2,159 participants aged 15 to 65 (48.1% males; Mage= 35.4, SD= 13.24). Results: Our results confirmed statistically significant associations with compulsive buying for the traits as well as the extrinsic goals. Furthermore, an important relationship between both levels in personality &#150; traits vs. extrinsic life aspirations &#150; was found. Finally, extrinsic life aspirations (specially, image, popularity, and conformity) contribute to the potentiation of the prediction of compulsive buying beyond the Five Factor Model. Conclusions: Current findings emphasize the advisability of considering both levels in personality, traits and middle-level units like life aspirations, not only in the prediction of compulsive buying, but also as potential targets for preventive and treatment programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villardefrancos Pol, Estíbaliz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Bolaño, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero-López, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: la integración de unidades de distinta naturaleza, incluidas en distintos niveles en algunos de los modelos multinivel de personalidad, constituye una de las más sugerentes trayectorias de la investigación contemporánea. En el campo de estudio de la compra compulsiva se conoce muy poco acerca de la interrelación entre unidades comparativas y estables como son los  rasgos (tendencias básicas o unidades de Nivel I) y las metas (un tipo de unidad de nivel medio) más vinculadas con procesos motivacionales y con las intenciones que dirigen la conducta de las personas. Método: se administraron autoinformes de compra compulsiva, Cinco Grandes rasgos de la personalidad y aspiraciones vitales extrínsecas a una muestra de población general formada por 2.159 participantes entre 15 y 65 años de edad (48,1% hombres; Medad= 35,4, DT= 13,24). Resultados: los resultados confirman que la compra compulsiva se asocia significativamente  tanto con los rasgos como con las metas extrínsecas. Además, se constata una importante relación entre ambos niveles de la personalidad. Por último, se  confirma que,  más allá de la contribución del Modelo de los Cinco Grandes, las metas  extrínsecas (en particular, imagen, popularidad y conformidad) potencian la explicación de la compra compulsiva. Conclusiones: se confirma la idoneidad de considerar ambos niveles explicativos de la personalidad, rasgos y unidades de nivel-medio tales como las metas vitales, no solo en la predicción de la compra compulsiva sino también como dianas potenciales  de los programas preventivos y de intervención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);29(4): 440-445, nov. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Más allá de los Cinco Grandes: papel de las metas vitales extrínsecas en la compra compulsiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3223^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6184</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
