<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058786</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The infl uence of storage vessel, incubation time and temperature on the stability of 99mTc-tetrofosmin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To determine the stability and radio chemical purity (RCP) of 99mTc-tetrofosmin kept for different time intervals        of up to 12 hours, the maximum recommended by the manufacturers, at different temperatures (18-25º C or room temperature,        32ºC &amp; 2-8ºC), in both reactive equipment vials or in syringes, and to determine whether shorter or longer        incubation times, other than the recommended 20 minute period, could affect the RCP of doses of the radiopharmaceutical.        Materials and Methods: 40 vials of phosphine were labelled in accordance with manufacturer&#146;s recommendations.        Three different storage temperature conditions were studied, in order to determine how possible extremes may affect        dosages of the drug. Results: The average RCP percentages of the radiofarmaceutical incubated in vials and syringes        were 95.79±2.32 &amp; 96.16±2.32 respectively, with no signifi cant differences observed. Stability at different temperatures        and different time intervals was over 90% in all cases. Conclusions: The 99mTc-tetrofosmin complex remains stable for        12 hours, whether it is incubated in the original reactive equipment or within insulin syringes with needle. Additionally,        the radiopharmaceutical also remained stable at the different studied storage temperatures and at all time intervals        for up to 12 hours</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vadillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melgarejo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Observar si el almacenamiento de la 99mTc-tetrofosmina durante el tiempo indicado por el fabricante de estabilidad        del radiofármaco, 12 horas, a diferentes temperaturas (18-25º C o Tª ambiente, 32º C y 4-8º C), podría infl uir en        la PRQ del radiofármaco y en su estabilidad, ya sea en los mismos viales del equipo reactivo como en jeringas. Del        mismo modo, estudiar si la incubación requerida para la preparación del radiofármaco (20 min) va a afectar a la        PRQ de la dosis si ésta ha sido cargada antes o después de ese tiempo. Material y Métodos: Los 40 viales de la fosfi na        se marcaron siguiendo las indicaciones del fabricante. Se estudiaron 3 condiciones de almacenamiento en función        de la temperatura en la que mantuviéramos el radiofármaco, para estudiar las condiciones ambientales extremas        en las que se puede encontrar una dosis del fármaco. Resultados: Los valores medios de la PRQ (%) cuando el        radiofármaco se incubaba en vial o en jeringa fueron de 95,79±2,32 y 96,16±2,32 respectivamente, no observándose        diferencias en los valores. La estabilidad del radiofármaco a distintas temperaturas, y a diferentes tiempos fueron        superiores al 90% en todos los casos. Conclusiones: El complejo 99mTc-tetrofosmina es estable durante 12 horas        tanto si la incubación se realiza en el vial original del equipo reactivo como si se realiza en jeringa de insulina con        aguja. El radiofármaco es estable durante 12 horas a diferentes temperaturas de almacenamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;48(3): 249-257, 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058786</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estabilidad de la 99mTc-tetrofosmina en función de envase, tiempo y temperatura de incubación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30483^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33090^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10914^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
