<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163882</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A computerised clinical decision-support system for the management of depression in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite its clinical relevance and its importance as a public health problem, there are major gaps in the management of depression. Evidence-based clinical guidelines are useful to improve processes and clinical outcomes. In order to make their implementation easier these guidelines have been transformed into computerised clinical decision support systems. In this article, a description is presented on the basics and characteristics of a new computerised clinical guideline for the management of major depression, developed in the public health system in Catalonia. This tool helps the clinician to establish reliable and accurate diagnoses of depression, to choose the best treatment a priori according to the disease and the patient characteristics. It also emphasises the importance of systematic monitoring to assess the clinical course, and to adjust therapeutic interventions to the patient's needs at all times (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Comín, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cavero, Myriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragonès, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palao, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de su relevancia clínica y de su importancia como problema de salud pública existen importantes deficiencias en el abordaje de la depresión. Las guías clínicas basadas en la evidencia son útiles para mejorar los procesos y los resultados clínicos, y para facilitar su implementación se ha ensayado su transformación en sistemas informatizados de apoyo a las decisiones clínicas. En este artículo se describen los fundamentos y principales características de una nueva guía clínica informatizada para el manejo de la depresión mayor desarrollada en el sistema sanitario público de Cataluña. Esta herramienta ayuda al clínico a establecer diagnósticos de depresión fiables y precisos, a elegir el tratamiento idóneo a priori según las características de la enfermedad y del propio paciente, y enfatiza en la importancia de un seguimiento sistemático para evaluar la evolución clínica y adecuar las intervenciones terapéuticas a las necesidades del paciente en cada momento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;49(6): 359-367, jun.-jul. 2017. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163882</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un sistema informatizado de apoyo a las decisiones clínicas para el manejo de la depresión en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56020^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33618^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
