<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80960</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Basis: The increase in life expectancy and consequent ageing of the population have brought about an increase in the number of elderly persons with dementia who are dependent on the care of others. In recent years, researchers have directed increasing attention to this problem, with many studies focusing on the figure of the dependent person&#146;s caregiver. Objective: To analyse the chief psychosocial differences between informal caregivers working with institutionalised and non-institutionalised dementia patients. The study also considered sociodemographic variables of the patient, and place of residence impacts. Method: The sample consisted of 40 informal caregivers and their corresponding 40 patients, of whom 20 were institutionalised and 20 were non-institutionalised. Data were obtained by means of a semi-structured interview on sociodemographic and related questions. SWLS, CAE and DERA questionnaires were used to evaluate personality features and the Zarit scale was used to evaluate subjective burden. Results: The main psychosocial differences between caregivers were observed in sociodemographic variables of the caregiver such as civil status, educational level, hours dedicated to work, degree of assumed responsibility, assistance and other support received. Differences were also observed in subjective burden, but were not found in relation to personality. Conclusion: Significant psychosocial differences exist between the two types of caregiver, principally in relation to sociodemographic profile and subjective care-giver burden (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calero, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Chica, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chica García, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro González, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El aumento de la esperanza de vida y el consecuente envejecimiento de la población conllevan el aumento de personas mayores con demencia que dependen de los cuidados de otro. Por ello los investigadores han orientado sus esfuerzos al estudio de esta problemática, siendo uno de los principales focos de investigación la figura del cuidador de la persona dependiente. Objetivo: El objetivo de esta investigación ha sido analizar las diferencias psicosociales entre cuidadores informales de pacientes con demencia institucionalizados y no institucionalizados. Asimismo, se han contemplado variables sociodemográficas del paciente, y su lugar de residencia. Método: 40 cuidadores informales y los respectivos 40 pacientes formaban la muestra, 20 de ellos institucionalizados, y 20 no. Se ha utilizado una entrevista semiestructurada sobre aspectos sociodemográficos y otras cuestiones de interés, los cuestionarios SWLS, Cae y DERA para medir aspectos de la personalidad y la escala Zarit para evaluación de la carga subjetiva. Resultados: Las principales diferencias psicosociales observadas entre cuidadores se dieron en las variables sociodemográficas del cuidador estado civil, nivel educativo, horas dedicadas al cuidado, responsabilidad asumida, ayuda de otros y otros apoyos, y también en la carga subjetiva. No las hubo en relación a la personalidad. Conclusiones: Hay diferencias psicosociales significativas entre ambos tipos de cuidadores, principalmente a nivel sociodemográfico y de carga subjetiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;18(3): 103-112, jul.-sept. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias psicosociales entre cuidadores informales de pacientes con demencia institucionalizados y no institucionalizados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
