<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103151</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mobbing in health care workers in Ceuta</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the levels of mobbing in health care workers in the Health Area of Ceuta (Spain). Design: Prevalence study. Setting: Ceuta Health Area (Primary and Specialty Care). Participants: A sample of 200 workers stratified by sex, job and workplace. Measurements: The instrument used is the Leymann Inventory Psychological Terrorization (LIPT). We also studied personal variables (age, sex, marital status), work (center, job, age) and blood parameters. Results: 75,1% of workers reported having experienced any harassment strategy in the last 6 months. 11,4% with elevated scores in limited communication and social contact, and personal and professional prestige. There is a relationship between mobbing and the rate of Castelli. Conclusions: The prevalence survey of workplace mobbing strategies is very high and similar to other studies. Should be studied in the health screenings routinely (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Fernández, Julián Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Martín, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla Segura, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Bagur, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Valera, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Fernández, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Espejo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar los niveles de acoso laboral en trabajadores de atención a la salud de Ceuta. Diseño: Estudio transversal de prevalencia. Emplazamiento: Área sanitaria de Ceuta de atención primaria y especializada. Participantes: Muestra de 200 trabajadores estratificada por sexo, puesto y centro de trabajo. Mediciones principales: El instrumento utilizado es el Leymann Inventory Psychological Terrorization (LIPT). Se estudiaron variables personales (edad, sexo, estado civil), laborales (centro, puesto de trabajo, antigüedad) y parámetros sanguíneos. Resultados: un 75,1% de los trabajadores refiere haber sufrido alguna estrategia de acoso en los últimos 6 meses. Un 11,4% puntúa con cifras elevadas en limitación de comunicación y contacto social, y desprestigio personal y profesional. Existe relación entre el acoso laboral y el índice de Castelli. Conclusiones: La prevalencia encuestada de estrategias de acoso laboral es muy elevada y similar a la de otros estudios. Debe incluirse su estudio en los exámenes de salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;58(227): 117-127, abr.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103151</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acoso laboral en trabajadores de atención a la salud de Ceuta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
