<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148381</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do primary health centres and hospitals contribute equally towards achievement of the transversal clinical competencies of medical students? Performance on the Objective Structured Clinical Examination (OSCE) in competency acquisition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The adaptation of the educational programmes of European faculties of medicine to the European Higher Education Area guidelines has focused curricula design on competence acquisition. Competencies are defined as the achievements of a predetermined level of efficacy in real-world scenarios. Our objective was to assess whether performance on a common competence evaluation test, the Objective Structured Clinical Examination (OSCE), resulted in different scores for second-year students after a practical medical training course took place in a primary health centre (PHC) or in a hospital. Design: A descriptive study was conducted during the 2010&#150;2014 academic year of the OSCE test scores obtained by all second-year students. Location: Faculty of Medicine at the University of Lleida (Catalonia, Spain). Main measurements: We performed a correlation analysis between students who completed their practical medical training at the PHC and hospitals utilising Student's t-test for comparison of means. Results: 423 students who completed internships at the PHC and at hospitals obtained OSCE mean scores of 7.32 (SD; IC) (0.82; 7.18&#150;7.47) points and 7.17 (0.83; 6.07&#150;7.26) points, respectively (p = 0.07). Conclusions: Second-year medical students acquired similar competency levels in the two analysed training scenarios. The two areas both serve their teaching purpose (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ayala, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler-González, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boada, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez, Toni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñascal, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buti, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: La adaptación de los programas educativos de las facultades de Medicina europeas a las directrices del Espacio Europeo de Educación Superior se ha centrado en los planes de estudio mediante la adquisición de competencias. Las competencias se definen como los logros de un nivel predeterminado de eficacia en escenarios del mundo real. Nuestro objetivo fue evaluar si el rendimiento en una prueba de evaluación de competencias transversales, mediante un Examen Clínico Objetivo Estructurado (ECOE, dio lugar a diferentes resultados de los estudiantes de segundo año después de un curso de formación médica práctica que se llevó a cabo en la atención primaria o en un hospital. Diseño: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo de los resultados de las pruebas de ECOE obtenidos por todos los estudiantes de segundo año. Emplazamiento: Facultad de Medicina de la Universidad de Lleida (Cataluña, España) durante 2010&#150;2014. Mediciones principales: Se realizó un análisis de correlación entre los estudiantes que completaron su formación médica práctica en la atención primaria de salud y hospitales utilizando la prueba t de Student para la comparación de medias. Resultados: 423 estudiantes que completaron sus prácticas en la atención primaria de salud y en los hospitales de la OSCE obtuvieron puntuaciones medias de 7,32 (DE; IC) (0,82; 7,18&#150;7,47) puntos y 7,17 (0,83; 6.07&#150;07.26) puntos respectivamente (p = 0,07). Conclusiones: Los estudiantes de medicina adquieren niveles de aprendizaje de competencias similares en los dos escenarios de formación analizadas. Las dos áreas docentes cumplen su objetivo de enseñanza (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;48(1): 42-48, ene. 2016. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148381</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Obtienen los mismos resultados en las competencias transversales los alumnos de Medicina que realizan sus prácticas en la Atención Primaria que en el hospital? Análisis de la adquisición de competencias mediante una Evaluación de Competencias Objetiva y Estructurada (ECOE)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50087</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
