<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99894</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cauda equina syndrome secondary to giant lumbar disc herniation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To determine the relation between clinical symptoms at presentation and the outcomes in a group of patients with CES secondary lumbar disc herniation. Patients and method: We present 5 patients with CES secondary to a giant lumbar disc herniation confirmed by MRI, submitted to discectomy and early decompression of the spinal canal. Results: Urgent surgical decompression was performed, all the patients were presenting visceral dysfunction on admission. Despite early treatment, only three patients have experienced a complete recovery of the visceral dysfunction and motor and sensory previous symptoms. Conclusions: The influence in a delay in the surgical treatment may well be overestimated due to the classic recommendations of the first published studies. However, early decompression is not detrimental, and may help to prevent an incomplete lesion progressing to complete sphincter paralysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fajardo-Romero, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomé-Bermejo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madruga-Sanz, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Relacionar los hallazgos clínicos de presentación de síndrome de cauda equina secundario a hernia discal lumbar con el resultado final en cinco pacientes. Pacientes y metodología: Presentamos una serie de 5 pacientes con SCE secundario a hernia discal lumbar gigante confirmado por RMN, sometidos a discectomía más descomprensión temprana del canal medular. Resultados: La descompresión quirúrgica se realizó de forma urgente, todas las pacientes presentaban trastornos viscerales al ingreso. A pesar del tratamiento precoz, solo tres pacientes experimentaron una recuperación completa de la disfunción visceral y de los déficits motor y sensitivo previos. Conclusiones: la descompresión precoz, en ningún caso va en detrimento del pronóstico, y puede ser de ayuda para prevenir que una lesión incompleta progrese hacia una parálisis completa de esfínteres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);23(1): 5-9, ene.-mar. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de cauda equina secundaria a hernia discal lumbar gigante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7165^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31505^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6706^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2459^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31505^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3677^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3677^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6706^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
