<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99944</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pyomiositis as a complication of varicella. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Varicella is the most common exanthematic disease in childhood. It is usually benign and self-limited. Some complications that require hospital treatment and are associated with high morbidity and mortality are reported. Pyomyositis or acute infection of the striated muscle is, although rare, one of the musculoskeletal possible complications of varicella. We present the case of a child that, while convalescing from that disease, presented lower limb cellulites, and later a pyomyositis of the gastrocnemius muscle (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramallo Hermo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez, M. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cameán Hermo, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La varicela es la enfermedad exantemática más frecuente en la infancia. Generalmente es benigna y autolimitada. Están descritas complicaciones que requieren tratamiento hospitalario y que están asociadas a una alta morbimortalidad. La piomiositis o infección aguda del músculo estriado es, aunque infrecuente, una de las posibles complicaciones musculoesqueléticas de la varicela. Presentamos el caso de un niño que durante la convalecencia de dicha enfermedad presentó como complicación una celulitis del miembro inferior y, posteriormente, una piomiositis del músculo gastrocnemio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;14(53): 41-44, ene.-mar. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Piomiosistis como complicación de la varicela. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8141^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52094^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
