<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132639</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1911</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main objective of this study is to describe the experiences of schools which are integrating students with Down syndrome, identifying facilitators and obstacles in this process as well as the effects perceived by the different agents involved. The study was based on qualitative case study methodology, and took place on five educational establishments from the Eastern Area of the Metropolitan Region of Chile(middle-high socioeconomic status). The information collecting methods were semi-structured interviews, focus groups, participant observationsand experiences records. The agents involved were school directors, integration coordinators, teachers, classmates&#146; parents, and Down syndrome students&#146; parents. The data analysis was conducted through the categorization and triangulation of information from the different sources. Among the main results, stands out the positive value assigned, by all the agents involved, to the school integration of Down syndrome students. The most important effects of this process were: the development of values between classmates, the valuation of diversity inside the school culture, the personal and professional development of teachers that work with these students, and the development of the integrated student himself, mainly in the achievement of autonomy and adjustment to rules</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Larrain Vacarezza, Ignacia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Bou, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presente investigación tiene como objetivo general describir experiencias de comunidades  educativas que realizan integración escolar de niños con síndrome de Down, identificando los facilitadores, barreras y efectos percibidos por los distintos agentes involucrados. El estudio se realizó a través de metodología cualitativa, en base a estudios de casos, llevados a cabo en cinco establecimientos educacionales del sector oriente de la Región Metropolitana (nivel socio económico medio-alto). Los métodos utilizados para la recopilación de información fueron entrevistas semi-estructuradas, grupos focales, observaciones participantes y registros de experiencias. Los agentes involucrados fueron directores de establecimientos, coordinadores de integración, profesores, apoderados de compañeros de alumnos integrados y apoderados de alumnos con síndrome de Down. El análisis de la información se hizo a través de la creación de rejillas de categorías emergentes y triangulación de las distintas fuentes. Dentro de los principales resultados destaca la valoración positiva que hacen todos  los agentes considerados respecto a la integración de niños con síndrome de Down en colegios regulares. Se identificaron como principales efectos de este proceso: el desarrollo de valores en los compañeros de curso, la apertura y valoración de la diversidad dentro de la cultura escolar, el desarrollo personal y profesional de los docentes que trabajan con un alumno integrado y el desarrollo para el propio alumno con síndrome de Down, principalmente en el logro de autonomía y ajuste a normas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Síndr. Down;31(123): 170-191, dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132639</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sistematización y análisis de experiencias de procesos de integración escolar de niños con síndrome de Down</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19239^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19239^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11482</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19239^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
