<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89748</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive ultrasound factors of lymphatic invasion in rectal cancer: "extra-corporeal" study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: the accuracy of preoperative endorectal ultrasound in the status evaluation of lymph nodes is around 50-70%, with a lack of eco-morphological patterns of clinical use. Since, accurate local staging is of great value in prognosis and decision-making we decided to analyze the referenced eco-morphological parameters in a try to find a proper predictive tool of clinical help that could improve the accuracy of rectal ultrasound. Material and method: the resected specimens of 24 patients that were operated on by radical surgery because rectal cancer, without preoperative radiotherapy were suspended in warm water and ultrasound scanned (360° circular probe with a transducer of 10 Mhz). All souspicious nodes were recorded and marked for the definitive histological report. Results: from the 24 specimens, 318 nodes were imaged (210 benign and 100 involved). All ultrasound parametes analysed were significant but only lobulation, echogenicity and hilar reflection were independent values. An score system was design with the addition of all parameters that showed a sensitivity of 98% and specificity of 99,1%. Conclusions: our study shows that a careful study of ultrasound lymph node images can get a high level of accuracy and better help in tailoring the treatment of any particular case.(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios Fanlo, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Rodríguez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilella Diago, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortego Fernández de Retana, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Díez, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: la eficacia en la valoración preoperatoria mediante ecografía endorrectal de los ganglios linfáticos se sitúa en torno al 50-70%, no existiendo unos patrones eco-morfológicos de amplio uso clínico. En este estudio valoramos los parámetros morfológicos conocidos para buscar una herramienta de ayuda clínica que mejore la precisión diagnóstica en la valoración de los ganglios linfáticos del mesorrecto. Material y método: las piezas quirúrgicas de 24 pacientes sometidos a cirugía radical por cáncer de recto sin radioterapia previa fueron sumergidas en un baño de agua caliente inmediatamente después de la cirugía y estudiadas mediante ecografía endoluminal (sonda circular de 360° y transductor de 10 Mhz). Se tomaron imágenes de todos los ganglios visualizados que fueron marcados adecuadamente para su estudio anatomopatológico. Resultados: el estudio &#147;in vitro&#148; de las 24 piezas de resección llevó a la identificación de 318 nódulos (218 no neoplásicos y 100 neoplásicos). Todas las variables ecográficas estudiadas se mostraron significativas, pero solo la lobulación, la ecogenicidad y la reflexión hiliar lo fueron independientes. Usando el sumatorio de todos los parámetros morfológicos se diseñó un sistema de puntuación con una sensibilidad del 98% y una especificidad del 99,1%. Conclusiones: el análisis pormenorizado de las imágenes ganglionares ecográficas puede conseguir una eficacia diagnóstica muy elevada y ayudar en la selección del tratamiento más adecuado para cada paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;103(6): 299-303, jun. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89748</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores ecográficos predictivos de invasión linfática en el cáncer de recto. Estudio &#147;ex-corpore&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8375^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8375^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12427^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12427^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5678^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8375^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
