<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69853</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lactic acidosis is a rare entity. Mortality is approximately 50%. Lactic acidosis is characterized by metabolic acidosis with elevated blood lactate and anion gap. We present a case of lactic acidosis in a diabetic woman under treatment with metformin. The patient developed acute renal failure due to dehydration and diarrhea. Treatment with continuous venovenoushemodialysis was successful with clinical improvement and recovery of renal function. We describe the case and review the pathophysiological causes and prognosis of this infrequent and severe complication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herranz, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcázar, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez de Icaya, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmo, Dolores del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Losada, Tomás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López del Val, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La acidosis láctica es una rara enfermedad con una mortalidad en torno al 50%. Se caracteriza por una acidosis metabólica con anión gap y ácido láctico elevado. Presentamos un caso de acidosis láctica en una paciente diabética en tratamiento con metformina, que presentó una insuficiencia renal aguda secundario a  deshidratación por un cuadro de gastroenteritis. El tratamiento con hemodiálisis venovenosa continua fue exitoso con recuperación gradual de la función renal. Se describe el caso clínico, los mecanismos fisiopatológicos, las diferentes causas y el pronóstico de esta infrecuente y grave complicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(9): 496-499, nov. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69853</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d19051^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19051^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19051^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
