<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146485</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Seroprevalence of hepatitis E virus in patients with hepatitis C and / or infected with HIV</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Hepatitis E virus (HEV) can cause chronic infection and cirrhosis. The seroprevalence data of anti-HEV IgG in the patients infected with HIV or with chronic liver disease are scarce. Methods. To document the seroprevalence of HEV infection in HIV patients or with chronic liver disease population, a retrospective study in serum samples from 625 patients was carried on: 200 HIV infected, 200 HCV infected, 25 coinfected by HIV and HCV and 200 healthy controls. Anti-HVE IgG antibodies were determined in serum samples by a commercial immunoassay (EIA) and all positive samples were studied further for the presence of anti-HEV IgM antibodies (HEV IgM 3.0; DiaSorin, Turín, Italy). Positive HEV IgM antibody specimens were examined for HEV RNA by polymerase chain reaction. Results. Anti-HEV IgG were reactive in 25 (12.5%) of the 200 HIV-infected patients, in 47 out of 200 HCV infected patients (23.5%), 10 out of 25 coinfected HIV-HCV group (40%) and 24 out of 200 healthy controls (12%). According to EIA anti-HEV IgM, 11 patients could be considered as acute hepatitis E cases but in only one of them was confirmed recent HEV infection by RT-PCR. Conclusions. The higher seroprevalence was found in HIV-HCV co-infected patients. The only patient with HEV RNA was HIV-HCV coinfected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Fabal, M. Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Garcés, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hepatitis E (VHE) puede causar infección crónica y cirrosis. Los datos de seroprevalencia de IgG anti-VHE en los pacientes infectados con el VIH o con enfermedades hepáticas crónicas son escasos. Métodos. Para documentar la seroprevalencia de infección por VHE en pacientes VIH o con enfermedad hepática crónica, se llevó a cabo un estudio retrospectivo en muestras de suero de 625 pacientes: 200 infectados por VIH, 200 infectados con VHC, 25 coinfectados por el VIH y el VHC y 200 controles sanos. Los anticuerpos anti-VHE IgG se determinaron en muestras de suero por un inmunoensayo comercial (EIA) y todas las muestras positivas se estudió la presencia de anticuerpos anti-VHE IgM (VHE IgM 3.0; DiaSorin, Turín, Italia). Las muestras con anticuerpos IgM VHE se examinaron para VHE ARN por reacción en cadena de la polimerasa. Resultados. Los anticuerpos IgG anti-VHE fueron reactivos en 25 (12,5%) de los 200 pacientes infectados por el VIH, en 47 de los 200 pacientes infectados por el VHC (23,5%), 10 de los 25 del grupo de coinfectados VIH-VHC (40%) y 24 de los 200 controles sanos (12%). Según EIA anti-VHE IgM, 11 pacientes podrían ser considerados como casos de hepatitis E aguda pero la infección por VHE reciente fue confirmada por RT-PCR en sólo uno de ellos. Conclusiones. La mayor seroprevalencia se ha encontrado en los pacientes coinfectados VIH-VHC. El único paciente con ARN positivo para VHE estaba coinfectado VIH-VHC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;28(6): 314-316, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146485</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seroprevalencia del virus de la hepatitis E en pacientes con hepatitis C y/o infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33343^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22286^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24874</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
