<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120566</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of the &#147;protein diet&#148; and bone tissue</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to evaluate the effect of the hyperproteic diet consumption on bone tissue. Methods: The study was conducted during sixty days. Twenty eight Wistar albinus rats, adults, originated from Laboratory of Experimental Nutrition were divided in four groups: (n = 7); Control 1 (C1), Control 2 (C2), Hyperproteic1 (HP1) e Hyperproteic 2 (HP2). The C2 and HP2groups were submitted to 30% of food restriction. The hyperproteic diet was based on the Atkins diet and prepared to simulate the protein diet. At the end of the studythe animals were anesthetized to performer bone densitometry analyses by DEXA and blood and tissue collection. Serum and bone minerals analyses were conducted bycolorimetric methods in automated equipment. Results: The total bone mineral density (BMD) of the pelvis and the spine of the food restriction groups (HP2 eC2) were lower (p &lt; 0.05) than C1 e HP1 groups. While the femur BMD of the HP2 was lower (p &lt; 0.05) related to others groups. It had been observed reduction (p &lt; 0.05)in the medium point of the width of femur diaphysis and in bone calcium level in the hyperproteic groups (HP1 eHP2). It was observed similar effect on the osteocalcinlevel, that presented lower (p &lt; 0.05) in the hyperproteicgroups. The insulin level was lower only in HP2 and serum calcium of the HP1 and HP2 groups was lower than C1.Conclusion: The protein diet promotes significant bonechange on femur and in the hormones levels related to bone synthesis and maintenance of this tissue (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Zoraide Nascimento da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa, Carlos Alberto Soares da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Eduardo de Salvo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azeredo, Vilma Blondet de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jesuz, Vanessa Azevedo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boaventura, Gilson Teles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el efecto de la ingesta de proteínas de la dieta sobre el hueso. Métodos: El estudio duró 60 días. Veintiocho adultos albinas Wistar, del Laboratorio de Nutrición Experimental fueron divididos en 4 grupos (n = 7), Control 1 (C1), de control2 (C2), en la proteína 1 (HP1) y en la proteína 2 (HP2).Los grupos C2 y HP2 fueron alimentados restringido a30%. Los niveles de proteína dietéticos fueron manipulados para simular la dieta de la proteína. Al final del experimento, los animales fueron anestesiados para los procedimientos de densitometría ósea (DEXA) y la recogida de tejidos. Análisis de mineral óseo en suero y se realizaron por el método colorimétrico utilizando un aparato automático. Resultados: La densidad mineral ósea total (BMD), la pelvis y la columna vertebral de los grupos con la restricción dietética (HP2 y C2) fue menor (p &lt; 0,05) que en los grupos C1 y HP1. Mientras que el grupo HP2 fémur fue menor (p &lt; 0,05) en comparación con otros grupos. Disminución(p &lt; 0,05) de la anchura del punto medio de la diáfisis femoral y la concentración de calcio en los grupos de hueso hiperproteicos (HP1 y HP2). Se observó un efecto similar en osteocalcina en suero, que fue menor(p &lt; 0,05) en los grupos de hiperproteicos mientras que la concentración de insulina fue más bajo sólo en el grupo deHP2. Ya hiperproteicos de calcio en suero y los grupos C2mostraron menor (p &lt; 0,05) el grupo C1.Conclusión: La dieta de la proteína promueve cambios significativos en el hueso en el fémur y la concentración de hormonas relacionadas con la formación y el mantenimiento de este tejido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(1): 140-145, ene. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120566</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la "dieta de proteína" y el tejido óseo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30227</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23103^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
