<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107180</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Short term evaluation of transanal pull-through with automatic suture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For the last ten years many centres have adopted transanal pull-through(TP) as the first choice technique for the treatment of Hirschsprung&#146;s Disease (HD) affected children. We present our experience, based on the endorectal pull-through with autosuture, which has not been reported up to now. According to our HD management programme, TP with autosuture should be performed in rectosigmoid forms of HD which are easily handled with outpatient care. Seven patients with HD whose ages ranged from 5 months old to 5 years old underwent EP with autosuture. We present the short term results of the evolution of our patients. Firstly,a laparoscopic procedure is carried out in order to obtain a biopsy from the transition zone. The second stage consists of the TP following the De La Torre technique, modified by the 21 mm circular autosuture. No new surgical operation was necessary. Passage of stools started between the second and fourth postoperative day. The most frequent complication was abdominal distention, found in an 85.7% of patients and resolved before being discharged. Hospital discharge took place (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Sala, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuso, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Couselo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Chacón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mangas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marijuán, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos 10 años el descenso transanal (DT) se ha popularizado en muchos centros como técnica de elección para el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Hirschsprung (EH). Presentamos nuestra experiencia de DT con autosutura, inédita en la literatura. En nuestro programa de tratamiento de la EH aplicamos el DT para las formas de afectación recto-sigmoidea de fácil manejo ambulatorio. Hemos practicado un estudio retrospectivo de la evolución de 7pacientes con edades comprendidas entre 5 meses y 5 años a los que se les ha realizado un descenso transanal con autosutura en los dos últimos años. Nuestra técnica se desarrolla en dos pasos. En un primer tiempo practicamos una biopsia laparoscópica, en el segundo tiempo se realiza un descenso endorrectal según la técnica de De La Torre, modificado con autosutura circular de 21mm. En ningún caso se han precisado reintervenciones. Nuestros pacientes empezaron a realizar deposiciones entre el 2º y 4º día postoperatorio (DPO). La complicación más frecuente fue distensión abdominal en (..) </dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;22(1): 29-33, ene. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107180</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración a corto plazo del descenso transanal con sutura automática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31020^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6786^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29193^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
