<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62171</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Two cases of Wernicke&#146;s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the cases of two men, one of whom was a non-alcoholic 50-year-old man who had been on hunger strike for 50 days and who was admitted to hospital with dysarthria, unstable gait, disorientation, ophthalmoplegia and ataxia.The suspected diagnosis was Wernicke&#146;s encephalopathy and treatment consisted of intramuscular thiamine shots followed by oral administration of the same drug, which produced rapid symptom resolution. In both patients, magnetic resonance imaging showed bilateral and symmetrical injuries around Silvio&#146;s aqueduct and in the periventricular region of both thalami (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simal Fernández, Jesús Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Hidalgo, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-de-Paula, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Serradilla, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de 2 varones, uno de ellos no bebedor de alcohol y en situación de huelga de hambre desde 50 días antes, que ingresan con disartria, inestabilidad para la marcha, desorientación temporoespacial, oftalmoplejía y ataxia. Ante el diagnóstico de sospecha de encefalopatía de Wernicke, se inició en ambos casos tratamiento con tiamina intramuscular y luego por vía oral, con rápida desaparición de los síntomas. La resonancia magnética permitió constatar en ambos casos lesiones bilaterales y simétricas alrededor del acueducto de Silvio y en la región periventricular de ambos tálamos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;56(6): 341-343, jul.-ago. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dos casos de enfermedad de Wernicke</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15301^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3245^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27726^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4464^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14210^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34316^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
