<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148859</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosing early spondyloarthritis in Spain: the ESPeranza program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Spondyloarthropathies are a group of diseases with an important social and health-care impact. Their prevalence is not low, affecting around 1,9% of the general population and represents around 13% of patients of the Spanish Rheumatology departments, according to the National Spondyloarthropathy Validation Study. On the other hand, it is estimated that ankylosing spondylitis, the paradigmatic disease in the group, leads to a mean yearly loss of work of 62 days per patient, leading 20% of patients to change professions and another 20% to a situation of permanent incapacity. However, up to this moment it has not received the same degree of attention as other rheumatic diseases, such as rheumatoid arthritis or osteoporosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Carballido, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las espondiloartropatías (SpA) son un grupo de enfermedades con importante impacto sociosanitario. En España el retraso medio hasta el diagnóstico de las SpA es superior a los 6 años, como señalan los datos de REGISPONSER. La FER ha diseñado un programa mixto de gestión e investigación en EspA de inicio, que en conjunto se ha denominado Programa ESPeranza. Se trata de un plan asistencial, que conforma una «vía clínica» destinada a establecer el diagnóstico precoz en aquellas personas que presentan síntomas sugerentes de EspA. Sus objetivos son: reducir la variabilidad de la práctica clínica en las SpA, facilitar el diagnóstico precoz, mejorar la formación de médicos generales y especialistas, así como estimular la investigación. Se presentan los diferentes instrumentos creados para la implementación de la vía clínica y los resultados preliminares obtenidos en 25 unidades de atención precoz de pacientes con SpA (UESP) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);6(supl.1): 6-10, mar. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148859</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico precoz de las espondiloartropatías en España: el programa ESPeranza</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36004^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36005^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32787^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
