<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136833</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical complications of recreational drug use</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years there has been an increase in the publications in the scientific literature on the toxic reactions, physical complications and deaths associated with &#147;recreations drug&#148; use, parallel to increase in the prevalence of this drug consumption. In addition to the adverse reactions that can be observed associated with acute intoxication, use of these substances may cause cardiovascular complications, cerebrovascular accidents, convulsions, hyponatremia leading to cerebral aedema, as well as important hepatotoxic effects. However, one of the most severe complications that may develop is a hyperthermic syndrome that may evolve to diseminated intravascular coagulation, rhabdomyolysis, and acute renal failure. The treatment of acute intoxication, in light of the absence of a specific antidote the management is primarily symptomatic and supportive (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Gálvez, Bartolomé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera Martínez, Gaspar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabater Ferragut, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Raga, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda Rodríguez, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano Gómez, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A lo largo de los últimos años se ha observado un aumento de las publicaciones en la literatura científica sobre las reacciones tóxicas, las complicaciones físicas y los fallecimientos asociados con el consumo de drogas recreativas, paralelo al aumento en la prevalencia de consumo de estas sustancias. Junto con las reacciones adversas que aparecen asociadas a la intoxicación aguda, el consumo de estas sustancias puede provocar complicaciones a nivel cardiovascular, accidentes cerebrovasculares, convulsiones, un cuadro de hiponatremia con edema cerebral o importantes alteraciones a nivel hepático. Sin embargo una de las complicaciones más graves que pueden desarrollarse es el de un síndrome hipertérmico que puede provocar coagulación intravascular diseminada, rabdomiolisis, e insuficiencia renal aguda. En el tratamiento de la intoxicación aguda o ante la ausencia de un antídoto específico el abordaje es fundamentalmente de tipo sintomático y de soporte (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);15(supl.2): 207-216, 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones físicas del consumo de drogas recreativas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7158</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7189^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53500^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23605^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24318^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1955^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
