<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112585</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cutaneous fusariosis by a species of the Fusarium dimerum species complex in a patient with acute mieloblastic leukemia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fusariosis is an emergent opportunistic hyalohyphomycosis produced by fungi belonging to the genus Fusarium. These molds are capable of producing life-threatening diseases in immunocompromised hosts, especially in those suffering from leukemia. It has also been described in immunocompetent patients, where it usually causes non-invasive localized lesions. Fusariosis in immunocompromised individuals has a high morbidity and mortality mainly because of the low sensitivity of these fungi to the antifungal drugs available. Case report. We describe here the case of a patient with acute mieloblastic leukemia who developed fusariosis by a species of the Fusarium dimerum species complex. The early diagnosis was made on the basis of microscopic observation of samples from cutaneous lesions, and voriconazole treatment was prescribed. A subsequent complete study of the fungal isolate by culture and molecular methods allowed the identification of F. dimerum, a species rarely described as a human pathogen. The sensitivity of the strain was tested using the Sensititre YeastOne® commercial system, which showed sensitivity to voriconazole and posaconazole, as well as to amphotericin B. The patient died after 7 days at hospital due to an hemodynamic failure. Conclusions. Complete identification of new isolates of Fusarium and their antifungal susceptibility patterns is of high interest to improve our knowledge about the epidemiology of the disease and how to best manage patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Colom, María Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baeza, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plazas, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collado, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zorraquino, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. La fusariosis es una hialohifomicosis oportunista, emergente, producida por hongos pertenecientes al género Fusarium. Estos hongos pueden provocar enfermedades que amenazan la vida en pacientes inmunodeficientes, en especial en portadores de leucemia. También se ha descrito en individuos inmunocompetentes, en los que induce lesiones localizadas, no invasivas. En pacientes inmunodeficientes, la fusariosis se asocia a una elevada morbimortalidad, sobre todo debido a la falta de sensibilidad de estos hongos a los antimicóticos disponibles. Caso clínico. Describimos el caso de una paciente con leucemia mieloblástica aguda que experimentó una fusariosis por una especie del complejo Fusarium dimerum. El diagnóstico precoz se estableció en función de la observación microscópica de muestras de las lesiones cutáneas y se prescribió tratamiento con voriconazol. Más tarde, un estudio completo del aislamiento fúngico por cultivo y métodos moleculares permitió la identificación de F. dimerum, una especie apenas descrita como patógeno en el ser humano. La sensibilidad de la cepa se examinó con el método comercializado Sensititre YeastOne®, que reveló su sensibilidad a voriconazol y posaconazol, al igual que a anfotericina B. La paciente falleció a los 7 días del ingreso debido a una insuficiencia hemodinámica. Conclusiones. La identificación completa de nuevos aislamientos de Fusarium y su patrón de sensibilidad a los antimicóticos suscita un gran interés para incrementar nuestros conocimientos sobre la epidemiología de la enfermedad y el tratamiento óptimo de los pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;30(2): 119-121, abr.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112585</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fusariosis cutánea por una especie del complejo Fusarium dimerum en una paciente con leucemia mieloblástica aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54472^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54472^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54472^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54472^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8049^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5807^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5807^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5807^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27953^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
