<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112195</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How to reduce avoidable admissions due to acute diabetes complications? Interrelation between primary and specialized attention in a diabetes unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus is a serious health problem. In the year 2030 it will affect 366 million people around the world. Objective: Evaluate the effectiveness of a mixed intervention and reducing the amount and seriousness of acute complications in diabetics from our Health Area. Materials and method: Protocols of action as well as information documents were produced. Diabetes Unit coordinated educational activities in the different support levels of the Area VII of Murcia. Information talks were provided for the people in charge of the Diabetes Unit in every Care Center and Service of the Health Area. Personalized training was provided for patients treated in the differet Care levels. The study comprised three stages. Information leaflets were spread and talks offered to the patient regarding in house handling of hypo and hyper glycemia. Results: A reduction of 39% of the emergencies due to acute non complicated diabetes was achieved, as well as a reduction of 47.6% of hospital admissions. There was a reduction of 67.8% of the amount of total hospital stays for the group of patients under 35 years who were admitted into the hospital due to type 1 or 2 diabetes mellitus that didn't show any complications (GRD295). Conclusions: There was a reduction of more than thirty percent in the emergencies due to acute decompensations in the disease and a significant reduction in the avoidable hospital stays in the young adult, thus improving the patients' life quality and reducing the social cost of the diabetic patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meoro Avilés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero López-Reinoso, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Cañizares, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lapaz Jorge, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Eustaquio Tudanca, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano Palao, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Olivar, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guirao Sastre, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuñez Sánchez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Talavera Espín, NV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La diabetes mellitus tipo 2 es un problema de salud grave. En el año 2030 afectará a 366 millones de personas en todo el mundo. Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia de una intervención mixta y reducir la cantidad y gravedad de las complicaciones agudas de la diabetes en nuestra Área de Salud. Material y método: Se diseñaron protocolos de actuación y documentos de información. La Unidad de Diabetes coordinó las actividades educativas en los diferentes niveles de soporte de la VII Zona de Murcia. Se realizaron charlas de información para los responsables de la Unidad de Diabetes en cada Centro de Atención y Servicio del Área de Salud. Se dio formación personalizada a los pacientes tratados en los distintos niveles de atención. El estudio constó de tres etapas. Se entregaron folletos informativos y charlas al paciente con respecto a la manipulación domiciliaria de hipo e hiperglucemia. Resultados: Se logró una reducción del 39% de las emergencias debidas a diabetes aguda no complicada, así como una reducción del 39% de las emergencias debidas a diabetes aguda no complicada, así como una reducción del 47,6% de los ingresos hospitalarios. Hubo una reducción del 67,8% de la estancia hospitalaria total para el grupo de pacientes menores de 35 años que fueron ingresados en el hospital debido a diabetes tipo 1 o 2 que no mostraron ningún tipo de complicaciones (GRD295). Conclusiones: Se observó una reducción de más del treinta por ciento en los casos de urgencias por descompensaciones agudas de la enfermedad y una reducción significativa en las estancias hospitalarias evitables en el adulto joven, mejorando así la calidad de vida de los pacientes y reduciendo el costo social del paciente diabético (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(6): 2079-2088, nov.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo reducir los ingresos evitables por complicaciones agudas de la diabetes? Interrelación entre atención primaria y especializada en una unidad de diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
