<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135209</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Procalcitonin action on body temperature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Procalcitonin (PCT), a 116 amino acid protein with identical sequence to the precursor protein of calcitonin hormone, is a new high sensitive and specific diagnostic parameter of bacterial infection and systemic inflammation in the absence of its precur- sor protein. High plasma concentrations of PCT are induced during severe bacterial infection but not in controls. Unlike interleukin-1 (IL-1), interleukin-6 (IL-6), tumor ne- crosis factor (TNF) or other endogenous pyrogens (parameters of the inflammatory re- sponse), PCT is generally not induced by viral infection, operation trauma, autoimmune or allergic disorders. Hence, PCT can be used for differential diagnosis of bacterial and non bacterial inflammation. Although the biological role of this peptide is still largely  unknown, it has been shown that PCT plasma concentrations correlate closely with the onset, course and severity of the inflammatory reaction. Moreover, it has been demon- strated that PCT is released following endotoxin injection and that the increase of plasma PCT levels, are positively correlated with IL-1, IL-6 and TNF. These characteristics of PCT might well give it not only a role as a marker in clinical infections but also a potential role in fever of bacterial origin. The thermosensitive region of the rat is the anterior hypothalamic pre-optic area (AH/POA). Therefore, the rationale for this study was to study the role of PCT in the thermoregulation and in the febrile response induced by a bacterial endotoxin on the CNS. In Wistar rats we carried out a dose-response study with  PCT and body temperature microinjecting different doses of PCT: 2, 4, 10, 100, 1000 and 5000 ng in the rat lateral ventricle (icv) and we measured their body temperature. We also microinjected one dose of PCT 100ng icv half an hour before endotoxin (lipopolysaccharide (LPS) 50&amp;#61549;g/kg). We also designed an immunohistochemical study in the AH/POA to find the peptide PCT and its localization. The results demonstrated that the administration of PCT icv produced a low diminution in the body temperature but not in a dose-response manner. The pre-treatment with PCT lightly reduce the fever induced by endotoxin. We have found the peptide PCT in the endothelial cells of the hy- pothalamic Pars Tuberal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ojeda Murillo, María Luísa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La procalcitonina (PCT) una proteína de 116 aminoácidos precursora de la hormona calcitonina, es un nuevo marcador diagnóstico de infección bacteriana e inflamación sistémica que presenta alta sensibilidad y especificidad, sin que se alteren los valores de calcitonina. En infecciones bacterianas severas se encuentran valores altos de PCT en plasma, sin embargo en personas sanas los niveles de PCT son indetectables. Al contrario que la interleucina-1 (IL-1), interleucina-6 (IL-6), factor de necrosis tumoral (TNF) u otros pirógenos endógenos ( marcadores de la respuesta inflamatoria), los niveles sanguíneos de PCT no se incrementan frente a infección viral, traumas, enfermedades autoinmunes o reacciones alérgicas. Por ello la PCT se usa para el diagnóstico diferencial entre infección bacteriana y viral. A pesar de desconocerse el papel biológico de este péptido, se ha demostrado que sus concentraciones plasmáticas se correlacionan con el inicio, curso y severidad de la inflamación. Así se ha demostrado que la PCT se libera tras la inyección de endotoxina bacteriana, este incremento está relacionado con los niveles séricos de IL-1, IL-6 y TNF. Estas características indican que la PCT puede ser algo mas que un simple marcador y que puede estar implicada en la respuesta febril. La región termorreguladora de las ratas se localiza en el área preóptica del hipotálamo anterior (AH/POA). En este trabajo se estudió el papel de la PCT en la termorregulación y en la fiebre inducida por endotoxina bacteriana a nivel central. En ratas Wistar se hizo un estudio dosis-respuesta de PCT frente a la temperatura corporal microinyectando diferentes dosis de PCT : 2, 4, 10, 100, 1000 y 5000 ng en el ventrículo lateral (icv) y registrando los cambios de temperatura corporal. También se inyectó una dosis de PCT: 100ng icv media hora antes de la endotoxina (lipopolisacárido (LPS) 50&#131;Ýg/kg ip). Asi mismo se realizo un estudio inmunohistoquimico de la presencia y localizacion de PCT en el AH/POA. Los resultados demostraron que la administracion de PCT icv provoca una ligera disminucion de la temperatura corporal pero no de un modo dosis-respuesta. El pretratamiento con PCT disminuye levemente la respuesta febril inducida por LPS. Se demostro la presencia del peptido PCT en la Pars Tuberal del hipotalamo. Este trabajo se ha realizado gracias a la Fundacion Valme y la Junta de Andalucia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;70(2): 357-380, abr.-jun. 2004. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135209</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acción de la procalcitonina sobre la temperatura corporal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1856^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1856^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1447^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
