<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118106</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of an automated coding system to retrieve and analyze diagnostic information stored in hospital emergency department records</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To develop an automated coding system to retrieve information from hospital emergency department (ED)records and to evaluate the performance of the system. Methods: Diagnostic reports written by ED physicians in 27 hospitals of the Andalusian public health service in 2010and 2011 were used. The automated coder was developed based on texts from 3 042 695 records for 2010; the coding system&#146;s performance was tested in texts from 3 072 861 records for 2011. For evaluation, a set of randomly selected records from 2011 were coded by the automated system and by an expert clinical coder. The system&#146;s precision, recall, and F-score were calculated. Results: A total of 2 936 842 records for 2011 contained potentially codifiable information (95.6% of the records). The automated coder identified 3 516 384 different diagnostic texts (1.2 per record) and coded 3 087 243 (87.8%) of them; codes were entered for 2 639 427 records (89.9% of the 2 936 842 with potentially codifiable information). The system&#146;s precision was 0.9760 (95% CI, 0.957-0.990), recall was 0.8784 (95% CI, 0.84-0.910), and the F-score was0.925 (95% CI, 0.903&#150;0.943).Conclusions: This system adapts efficiently to the ED setting, coding millions of records in a few hours and making the diagnostic information available for use. Incorporating probabilistic methods would improve the system&#146;s recall (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Herrera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto García, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canto Casasola, V. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna Téllez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goicoechea Salazar, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo Cabezas,  F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Desarrollar un codificador automático para recuperar información de los registros de urgencias hospitalarios y evaluar su desempeño. Método: Se utilizaron los textos diagnósticos de los urgenciólogos de 27 hospitales durante2010 y 2011: los textos de 3.042.695 registros de 2010 para desarrollar el codificador automático y los de 3.072.861 registros de 2011 para comprobar su funcionamiento. Para su evaluación, se seleccionó una muestra al eatoria de los registros de2011 que fue doblemente codificada por el codificador automático y por un experto en codificación clínica. Se calcularon la precisión, el recall y la F-score del codificador. Resultados: Contenían información potencialmente codificable 2.936.842 registros de2011 (95,6% del total). En ellos, el codificador automático identificó 3.516.384 textos diferentes (1,2 por registro) de los que codificó 3.087.243 (87,8%) y proporcionó códigos a 2.639.427 (89,9% de 2.936.842). La precisión fue 0,976 (CI 95% = 0,957-0.990),su recall 0,878 (CI 95% = 0,844-0,910) y su F-score 0,925 (CI 95% = 0,903-0,943).Conclusiones: Este codificador se adapta eficientemente al entorno de urgencias y permite la codificación de millones de registros en pocas horas, haciendo operativa la información diagnóstica que contienen. El codificador podría mejorar su recall si incorporara un motor probabilístico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);25(6): 430-436, dic. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118106</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de un sistema de codificación automática para recuperar y analizar textos diagnósticos de los registros de servicios de urgencias hospitalarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55136^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54395^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53713^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28405^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
