<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73608</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate the safety, efficacy and conditions for orotracheal intubation (OTI) of nondepolarizingneuromuscular blocker (NMB)rocuronium (R) for rapid sequence intubation (RSI) in the extrahospitalary environment, as well as the possibility of haemodynamic alterationsand the need for using other NMB after the induction dose with R. Methods: Aprospective and retrospective studywas carried out from March 2005 to October 2007, according to the OIT protocol with R (dose 0.6 mg/kg) in the out-of-hospital environment in themobile Advanced Life Support Units (ALSU). The following parameters were evaluated before and at minute 1, 2 and 5 after OTI: age, sex, OTI indication,OTI conditions according to Cormack-Lehane (C-L) classification and Krieg (K) scale, haemodynamic parameters: Mean Arterial Pressure (MAP),Heart Rate (HR), and arterial oxygen saturation (SatO2). The need for other type of NMB and the possible complications were also analysed.Cardiac arrest, neck or maxillofacial injury and patients &lt; 14 years old were excluded. Results: 50 patients: 38 males (12 women) were included. Mean age was 45 ± 24 years old, OTI indications: neurological (GCS &lt; 9) 39 patients,cardiological in 4 and respiratory in 7 patients. The conditions for OTI, according to K scale: grade I (good relaxation, vocal cords open, no coughing) in 36 patients, grade II ( same as grade I, with coughing) in 12 patients, grade III ( vocal cordsmoving) 1 patient and grade IV (epiglotis cannot be seen) in 1 patient and according to C-L: grade I (most of the glotis is seen): 29 patients; grade II(only posterior position of the glottis can be seen): 18 patients; grade III (only the epiglottis can be seen): 2 patients; grade IV (neither epiglottis nor glottis can be seen): 1 patient...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Souto Mata, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Katcher, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz Esquete, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Melgar, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rama Sorribas, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la seguridad, eficacia y condicionesde la intubación orotraqueal (IOT) delbloqueante neuromuscular (BNM) no despolarizanterocuronio (R) durante la secuencia rápidade intubación (SRI) en el medio extrahospitalario,así como las posibles alteraciones hemodinámicasy la necesidad de utilizar otros BNM tras la dosisde inducción con R.Material y método: Se realizó un estudio prospectivodesde marzo de 2005 a octubre de 2007,según un protocolo de IOT con R (dosis: 0,6mg/kg) en el ámbito extrahospitalario en unaunidad de soporte vital avanzado móvil (USVA).Se analizaron: sexo, edad, motivo de IOT, condicionesde IOT mediante la clasificación deCormack-Lehane (C-L) y de Krieg (K), parámetroshemodinámicas: presión arterial media(PAM) y frecuencia cardiaca (FC) y saturaciónperiférica de oxígeno (SpO2), antes de la IOT y al1, 2 y 5 minutos, el uso de otro tipo de BNM yposibles complicaciones.Fueron motivo de exclusión: edad &lt; 14 años,PCR y lesión cervical o maxilofacial. Resultados: Se recogieron un total de 50 pacientes,38 varones (12 mujeres), edad media 45 ± 24años, motivo de IOT: neurológico (GCS &lt; 9) 39pacientes, cardiológico 4 y respiratorio 7 pacientes.Las condiciones de IOT según la clasificación de K:grado I (cuello y cuerdas relajadas, no tose) 36pacientes, grado II (igual pero tose) 12 pacientes,grado III (cuerdas aproximadas) un paciente ygrado IV (imposible la IOT): un paciente y según laclasificación de C-L: grado I (se visualiza la glotis):29, grado II (se visualiza la comisura posterior): 18pacientes, grado III (sólo se visualiza la epiglotis):2 pacientes y grado IV ( no se visualiza la epiglotis):1 paciente...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;9(1): 25-32, ene.-mar. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73608</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia con el uso de rocuronio en la intubación orotraqueal en una unidad de soporte vital avanzada móvil (USVA)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9658^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
