<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96656</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence and epidemiologic characteristics of intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR) in Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To determine the incidence and describe the epidemiologic characteristics of intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR) in 2007 in the Reina Sofia University Hospital in Cordoba. Material and methods We performed a descriptive, cross-sectional study in which the charts of IUGR fetuses born between January 1st and December 31st, 2007 were reviewed. ResultsT he incidence of IUGR during 2007 in the Reina Sofia University Hospital in Cordoba was 411 cases (9.94%), of which 43 cases (10.47%) were preterm fetuses. The mean pH in IUGR newborns with a gestational age of less than 34 weeks was lower than that in newborns with higher gestational age (p=0.065). A total of 24% of IUGR fetuses had a cesarean delivery compared with 19.7% of cesareans in newborns with normal weight (p=0.030). The principal causes of IUGR were maternal age &gt;35 or &lt;20 years old (29.68%), smoking (17.78%), vascular causes (10.46%) and multiple pregnancies (4.37%). In 29.93% of IUGR fetuses no cause was found. The perinatal mortality rate was significantly higher (p&lt;0.001) in IUGR fetuses (17.03×1000) than in the group with normal weight (3.22×1000).Conclusions IUGR is an abnormality of unknown etiology that affects 9.94% of pregnancies in the Reina Sofia University Hospital. In most IUGR fetuses, gestational age is more than 37 weeks and in approximately 70% of these fetuses an underlying cause can be found. Cesarean sections were significantly more frequent in IUGR fetuses than in those with normal weight. Similarly, perinatal mortality was 5.3 times higher in this group than in the normal group. In our hospital the sensitivity rate for the detection of this entity is 78.72%  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, M. D. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, A. J. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arjona, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Determinar la incidencia y describir las características epidemiológicas del crecimiento intrauterino restringido (CIR) en el Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía de Córdoba en el 2007.Material y métodos Estudio descriptivo transversal en el que se revisaron las historias clínicas de los fetos con CIR entre el 1 de enero del 2007 y el 31 de diciembre del 2007.ResultadosLa incidencia de CIR en el Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía en el 2007 fue de 411 casos (9,94%). De éstos, 43 casos (10,47%) fueron pretérmino. La media del pH de la arteria umbilical al nacimiento de los fetos con menos de 34 semanas fue más baja que la media del pH de los fetos de mayor edad gestacional (p=0,065). El porcentaje de cesáreas en los fetos con CIR fue del 24%, frente a un 19,7% en los fetos con crecimiento normal (p=0,030). Las principales causas de CIR encontradas fueron edad materna &gt;35 o &lt;20 años (29,68%), tabaquismo (17,78%), causas vasculares (10,46%) y embarazo múltiple (4,37%). En el 29,93% de los fetos con CIR no se encontró ninguna causa. La tasa de mortalidad perinatal para los fetos con CIR (17,03/1.000) fue significativamente más alta (p&lt;0,001) que en los fetos sin esta patología (3,22/1.000). Conclusiones El CIR es una patología cuya etiología es multifactorial y no del todo conocida, que afectó al 9,94% de las pacientes embarazadas del Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía en el 2007. La mayoría de los casos fueron fetos con más de 37 semanas de gestación y fue posible encontrar una causa subyacente en el 70% de los casos estudiados. El porcentaje de cesáreas fue significativamente mayor en los fetos con CIR; la mortalidad perinatal encontrada en estos fetos fue 5,3 veces mayor a la mortalidad perinatal de aquellos fetos con crecimiento normal. La sensibilidad de nuestras consultas hospitalarias para el diagnóstico de CIR fue del 78,72%  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);36(6): 209-214, nov.-dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96656</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia y características epidemiológicas del crecimiento intrauterino restringido en el Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11353^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38639^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6702^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
