<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98003</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiological alterations and spine mobility in Spanish fighter pilots</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objectives: Back pain is suffered by most fighter pilots. The objectives of this study were evaluated in this population ifthere are early lesions of the spine and their mobility. Material and Methods: The participants were 30 fighter pilots and 16 soldiers as acomparison group (CG), no fighter pilots, stationed in the Air Base in Albacete, Spain. All 6 underwent X-rays (two in the cervical spine,two in the thoracic spine and two in the lumbosacral region). We calculated the prevalence ratio (PR) of the lesions assessed between thetwo groups was considered significant a P value &amp;#8804; 0.05. Results: Both the average age of fighter pilots (31.9 years [SD = 5.9]) as the CG (32.3 years [SD = 3.4]) and body mass index (24 , 4 kg/m2 in fighter pilots compared to 24.4 [SD = 1.9] of the CG) were similar. We foundsignificant differences between the two groups in the following variables: uncoartrosis (PR = 2.4, P = 0.02), apophyseal osteoarthritis (PR = 2.82, P = 0.02), osteophytes (PR = 4.26 P = 0.007), loss of vertebral body height (PR = 11.29, P = 0.008) in the cervical region, subchondral irregularity (PR = 2.82, P = 0.02) in the dorsal region. The mobility of the back (as measured by bending in different areas, extensions, rotations and lateralized) was lower in the fighter pilot. Conclusions: The fighter pilots of our study have a higher stiffness in the spine, aswell as early radiological changes, mainly in the cervical region, compared with a similar CG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abad Ortiz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caldevilla Bernardo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbayo Herencia, J A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Díaz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Nievas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y Objetivos: El dolor de espalda es padecido por la mayoría de pilotos de combate. Los objetivos del presente estudio hansido valorar en esta población si aparecen lesiones precoces de la columna vertebral y la movilidad de ésta. Material y Métodos: Participaron 30 pilotos de combate y 16 militares como grupo de comparación (GC), no pilotos, destinados en la Base Aérea de Albacete, España. A todos se les practicó 6 radiografías (dos en la columna cervical, dos en la columna dorsal y dos en la región lumbosacra). Se calculó larazón de prevalencias (RP) de las lesiones valoradas entre los dos grupos, considerando significativo un valor de P&amp;#8804;0,05. Resultados: Tanto la edad media de los pilotos (31,9 años [DE=5,9]) como la del GC (32,3 años [DE=3,4]), así como su índice de masa corporal (24,4 kg/m2 en los pilotos frente a 24,4 [DE=1,9] del GC) fueron similares. Encontramos diferencias significativas entre los dos grupos en las siguientes variables: uncoartrosis (RP=2,4; P=0,02), artrosis interapofisarias (RP=2,82; P=0,02), osteofitos (RP=4,26; P=0,007), pérdida de alturadel cuerpo vertebral (RP=11,29; P=0,008) en la región cervical, e irregularidades subcondrales (RP=2,82; P=0,02) en la región dorsal. La movilidad de la espalda (valorada por flexiones en las distintas regiones, extensiones, rotaciones y lateralizaciones) fue menor en el piloto de combate. Conclusiones: Los pilotos de combate de nuestro estudio presentan una mayor rigidez en la columna vertebral, asi como alteraciones radiológicas precoces, principalmente en la región cervical, comparados con un GC similar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;67(4): 361-366, oct.-dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98003</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones radiológicas y movilidad de la columna vertebral observadas en pilotos de combate españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13505^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22322^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
