<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165403</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish Society of Cardiology Cardiac Resynchronization Working Group Consensus on Indications for, Programing of and Follow-Up Resynchronization Devices</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac resynchronization is an increasingly important therapeutic option for a subgroup of patients with heart failure. It has been shown that biventricular pacing produces significant hemodynamic and clinical improvements and results in left ventricular remodeling in patients with severe heart failure and left bundle branch block. Some studies also indicate that cardiovascular mortality is decreased. However, this form of treatment is expensive and complex, it is not free of complications, and there are a significant number of non-responders. Therefore, multidisciplinary collaboration is necessary if it is to be used correctly. The Spanish Society of Cardiology Cardiac Resynchronization Working Group has produced this consensus document with the aim of establishing current indications for therapy, and ensuring that device selection is appropriate and that implantation and follow-up are carried out correctly (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ferrer, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sitges, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Madrid, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugada-Terradellas, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal del Ojo, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moro, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Infante, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Bolao, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Lozano, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toquero, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Granell, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mont, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro del arsenal terapéutico de la insuficiencia cardíaca, la resincronización cardíaca cada vez está adquiriendo un papel más importante como coadyuvante del tratamiento médico. Se ha demostrado ampliamente que en los pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca avanzada y bloqueo de rama izquierda, la estimulación biventricular produce una mejoría hemodinámica y clínica, así como un remodelado inverso del ventrículo izquierdo. Algunos estudios sugieren también una disminución de la mortalidad. Sin embargo, es una terapia costosa y compleja que no está libre de complicaciones y con un porcentaje de pacientes que no mejoran. Por ello, para su correcta aplicación es necesaria una colaboración multidisciplinaria. El Grupo de Trabajo de Resincronización Cardíaca de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología ha redactado el presente documento de consenso con especial interés por exponer las indicaciones de esta terapia, así como la correcta selección de los dispositivos y su adecuada técnica de implante y seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);5(supl.B): 3b-11b, 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165403</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso sobre la terapia de Resincronización Cardíaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54223^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54223^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
