<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144207</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Valencian families as health agents in drug prevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. The aims of this study were: 1) to find out the opinions, attitudes and conducts of families in terms of prevention in drug addiction; 2) to establish typologies of families depending on their opinions, attitudes and conducts as regards drugs. Material and methods. The work combines quantitative methodology through the survey and qualitative methodology through group interviews. The survey was conducted on a representative sample of 700 families in the province of Valencia. Two criteria were used for the selection of participants in the 6 group interviews: the parents&#146; consumption and the ages of the children. Results. The first risk factor and the first protection factor for Valencian families are linked to the family. Conducts and attitudes in respect of drugs vary between fathers and mothers, and depending on whether drugs are legal or illegal. The role of families as prevention agents depends on the age of the children and parents&#146; consumption. Families show great interest in being informed, in particular as regards how to detect and address possible consumption by their children. Conclusions. The results show the need for preventive policies considering the diversity of family models. Two types of families have been established, using the following criteria: 1) attitudes and conducts as regards drug use and 2) attitudes to prevention. A need for preventive programs to adapt to the reality that families are experiencing is similarly detected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Coronado González, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Moya, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Sanjuán, Mª Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Los objetivos de este estudio han sido: 1) conocer las opiniones, actitudes y conductas de las familias sobre la prevención en drogodependencias; 2) establecer tipologías de familias en función de sus opiniones, actitudes y conductas en torno a las drogas. Material y método. El trabajo combina la metodología cuantitativa a través de la encuesta y la metodología cualitativa por medio de entrevistas grupales. La encuesta se ha realizado sobre una muestra representativa de 700 familias de la provincia de Valencia. Para la selección de los participantes en las 6 entrevistas grupales se han empleado dos criterios: el consumo de los padres y las edades de los hijos. Resultados. Para las familias valencianas el primer factor de riesgo y el primer factor de protección están vinculados al entorno familiar. Los comportamientos y actitudes frente a las drogas varían entre los padres y las madres, y en función de si las drogas son legales e ilegales. El papel de las familias como agentes de prevención depende de la edad de los hijos y del consumo de los padres. Las familias muestran un alto interés por estar informadas, en particular en lo que se refiere a cómo detectar y afrontar el posible consumo de los hijos. Conclusiones. Los resultados obtenidos muestran la necesidad de que las políticas preventivas contemplen la diversidad de los modelos familiares. Se han establecido dos tipologías de familias según los siguientes criterios: 1) actitudes y conductas en torno al consumo de drogas y 2) actitudes hacia la prevención. Así mismo se constata la necesidad de que los programas preventivos deben adaptarse a la realidad que las familias están viviendo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;40(3): 43-60, 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144207</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las familias valencianas como agentes de salud en la prevención de drogodependencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28468^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
