<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147274</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors of disagreement between coaches and players of a high-level basketball team when assessing individual session perceived exertions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main objective of this study was to evaluate the concordance between the coaches and the players of a Spanish highlevel female basketball team when evaluating the hardness of practice sessions looking into the factors that could modulate the alleged biases of the coaches. The three staff members severely underestimated the players&#146; session perceived exertion, which meant that, as a group, they were not capable of planning the desired intensity along the registered period. Furthermore, this study allowed us to detect what aspects of coaching knowledge should deserve more attention with each staff members if we desired less biased judgments about the players&#146; perceptions, who were the most relevant and common source of bias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Santos, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Los Arcos, Asier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sautu, Luismari</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El principal objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la concordancia entre los entrenadores y los jugadores de un equipo femenino español al valorar la dureza de las sesiones de entrenamiento, prestando especial atención a los factores moduladores de los posibles sesgos en el cuerpo técnico. Los tres entrenadores infravaloraban notablemente los valores de fatiga declarados por los jugadores tras las sesiones, lo que implicaba que, en conjunto, no eran capaces de planificar correctamente la intensidad del ejercicio propuesto en cada periodo. En este sentido, esta investigación nos permitió detectar en qué aspectos del pensamiento de cada entrenador se debía incidir para reducir sus sesgos particulares y el más común entre los tres: los jugadores mismos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(supl.1): 69-72, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147274</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores de sesgo de los entrenadores de baloncesto de elite en la estimación de los esfuerzos de los jugadores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34600^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
