<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133279</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extramammary Paget Disease: A Report of 10 Cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Extramammary Paget disease (EMPD) is a very rare form of intraepithelial adenocarcinoma. We report the cases of EMPD diagnosed in a referral hospital over a 5-year period from 2009 to 2013. Ten cases of EMPD were diagnosed in 4 men and 6 women aged between 50 and 79 years. Erroneous clinical diagnoses led to diagnostic delays of 1 to 5 years in all cases. Six patients had in situ lesions and dermal invasion was observed in the other 4 cases. Four patients had a second neoplasm and 2 of the patients with invasive EMPD died. Because EMPD is rare and its clinical presentation is nonspecific, a high degree of clinical suspicion is required to avoid delays in diagnosis and treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tercedor-Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Colmenero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Castro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco-Morente, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de Paget extramamaria (EPEM) es una forma extremadamente rara de adenocarcinoma intraepitelial. Presentamos los casos de EPEM diagnosticados en los últimos 5 anos en un hospital de tercer nivel (2009-2013). Se trata de 10 casos, 4 varone &#152; s y 6 mujeres, con edades comprendidas entre los 50-79 anos. Todos ellos sufrieron un retraso diagnóstico &#152; de uno a 5 anos debido a sospechas diagnósticas erróneas. Seis casos correspondieron a EPEM &#152; in situ y en 4 existía invasión dérmica. Se localizó una segunda neoplasia en 4 pacientes y 2 con EPEM invasiva fallecieron. La baja incidencia de esta enfermedad y su clínica inespecífica nos debe alertar sobre la necesidad de establecer una alta sospecha clínica para evitar retrasos diagnósticos y terapéuticos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;106(1): 106.e1-106.e5, ene.-feb. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133279</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Paget extramamaria: 10 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31760^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53672</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
