<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042646</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intraoral tumor with rapid growing. Report of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The appearance of an intraoral mass is common in our speciality. Most are benign lesions, but some are primary malignancies.Metastases account for less than 1% of all oral malignances.An 86 year old woman was referred to our department witha large, asymptomatic, intraoral, fast-growing mass. She hadno previous cancer history or other relevant physical findings.The radiology studies showed underlying bone erosion. Thehistological study showed a metastatic adenocarcinoma with asuspected origin in the abdomen. We were unable to identify itby non invasive diagnostic procedures.Given the patient&#146;s general status and despite the ominous prognosisof such lesions, we decided not to perform any aggressivetherapy beyond removing the oral mass, in order to maintainher quality of life. There have been no local recurrences untilthis time</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Val, Daniel del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martín-Moro, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Pardo de Vera, José Luis del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrián Carretero, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de una masa intraoral supone un motivo de consultafrecuente en nuestra especialidad. La mayoría de los casoscorresponden a lesiones benignas y, dentro de las malignas, atumores primarios intraorales. Las metástasis suponen menosdel 1 % de las lesiones malignas.Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 86 años de edad, sin antecedentesoncológicos, que acudió a nuestro servicio presentandouna masa intraoral asintomática, de crecimiento rápido y volumenconsiderable, sin otros hallazgos de interés a la exploración.La lesión se acompañaba de erosión ósea subyacente. Elresultado de la biopsia fue de adenocarcinoma metastático deprobable origen abdominal, si bien el tumor primario no pudoser identificado con las técnicas diagnósticas no invasivas quese llevaron a cabo.Valorando el estado deteriorado de la paciente, así como el malpronóstico de dichas lesiones, se optó por un tratamiento únicamentesintomático, consiguiendo una adecuada calidad de viday sin aparición de recidivas locales en el momento actual</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(5): 440-443, nov.-dic. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042646</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Masa intraoral de rápido crecimiento. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22476^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
