<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87703</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-4723</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Chagas disease mainly affects tropical and subtropical rural populations of America. Its distribution has been modified by migrations, becoming a urban health problem.La Capital department in Santa Fe, Argentina, is considered a low endemicity area for this disease. The aim of the study was to characterize this infection in an epidemiological way in a suburban community of La Capital. Methods: Descriptive and cross- section study. Location: Ángel Gallardo, La Capital department, Santa Fe, Argentina. Period 2006-2007.Sample: Over 14 yo.: random selection, n=72; below 14 yo.: the whole school population with previous agreement, n=116.Results: Positive: 0,8% in &lt;14 yo., 29,2% in &gt;14 yo. Decrease with the school level. Infected:45,4% of rural workers; 46,2% of immigrants from Bolivia, North of Argentina and/or North of Santa Fe; 42,9% know they were infected. Conclusions: The prevalence is much superior to the one estimated for the region. Even in areas without entomological risk, the searching of the infection should be actively taken in communities with particular epidemiological characteristics. Many people do not know they are infected and they do not do the appropiate controls. The control programs should be kept in order to prevent the starting over of the vectorial cicle in the region (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mendicino, Diego A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>María , L. Bizai</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabbro, Diana L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Streiger, Mirtha L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barco, Mónica L. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La Enfermedad de Chagas afecta principalmente a poblaciones rurales tropicales y subtropicales de América. Su distribución se ha modificado por migraciones, emergiendo como un problema de salud urbano. El Departamento La Capital (Santa Fe, Argentina) es considerado de baja endemicidad para esta enfermedad. El objetivo del presente estudio fue caracterizar epidemiológicamente esta infección en una comunidad suburbana de La Capital. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo, de corte transversal. Lugar: Ángel Gallardo, Departamento La Capital, Santa Fe, Argentina. Periodo 2006-2007.Muestra: En mayores de 14 años: selección aleatoria de la muestra, n=72; en menores de 14años: totalidad de la población escolar previo consentimiento, n=116.Resultados: Seropositividad: 0,8% en &lt;14 años, 29,2% en &gt;14 años. Disminuyó con el nivel de instrucción. Resultaron infectados: 45,4% de los trabajadores rurales; 46,2% de los inmigrantes de Bolivia, Norte de Argentina y/o Norte de Santa Fe; 42,9% sabían que estaban infectados. Conclusiones: La prevalencia es muy superior a la estimada para la región. Aún en áreas sin riesgo entomológico, se debe buscar activamente la infección en comunidades con características epidemiológicas particulares. Muchos desconocen que están infectados y no se realizan los controles pertinentes. Se deben mantener los programas de control, para evitar el reinicio de ciclo vectorial en la región (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. emerg;12(2): 110-114, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87703</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección chagásica y antecedentes epidemiológicos relacionados, en un área de baja endemicidad de Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30425^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16091^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33154^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
