<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138808</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurological catastrophes due to medical errors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In 1999, the American Institute of Medicine reported an enormous rate of medical errors, representing the fifth cause of death. In Spain, there is no reliable information on the number and nature of medical adverse events, but the situation is probably similar to that described in the USA in 1999, if not higher. Diagnostic errors account for more than half of neurological adverse events and these errors can be catastrophic if the natural progression of the neurological disorder causes severe sequels or even death when the patient is left untreated. To improve patient safety, research must be undertaken to determine how these errors are produced and to develop strategies to prevent inappropriate conduct. Among many other elements, it is important to create teamwork, improve neurological knowledge among general practitioners and residents, to design clinical practice guidelines aimed at patient safety, and to promote policies that reward the absence of errors. In general, medical errors are neither exclusively due to lack of experience nor to insufficient medical knowledge, but rather to faulty organization of medical care. Therefore, it is preferable to monitor healthcare organization rather than to blame the individual supposedly responsible for the error (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alberca, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Instituto Americano de Medicina desveló en 1999 que en Estados Unidos se producía una enorme cantidad de errores médicos; de hecho, eran la quinta causa de muerte en este país. Aunque no se sabe si en España se produce el mismo número de errores, existen razones para pensar que el problema es similar, si no mayor. Los errores diagnósticos representan más de la mitad del total de efectos adversos, que pueden ser catastróficos &#151;o tener consecuencias catastróficas&#151; si el proceso neurológico, dejado a su evolución natural, causa la muerte o secuelas severas, es decir, el error puede tener consecuencias catastróficas si no se actúa adecuadamente para interrumpir esta evolución. Por ello es necesario investigar cómo se producen los errores y diseñar estrategias para evitarlos y prevenir conductas inadecuadas. Entre otras, es importante organizar equipos de trabajo, mejorar el conocimiento de la neurología entre los médicos generales y residentes que asisten a este tipo de enfermo, elaborar guías orientadas a salvaguardar la seguridad del paciente y promover políticas adecuadas que premien la falta de errores. Los errores médicos no se deben, por lo general, al desconocimiento o a la falta de experiencia; en ellos influye de forma decisiva una organización asistencial inadecuada. Por este motivo será preferible vigilar la organización de la asistencia y no descargar toda la culpa a nivel individual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;25(supl.1): 52-60, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138808</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Catástrofes neurológicas por desconocimiento y retraso diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33121^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12825</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
