<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155888</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-0852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictors of depression severity in a treatment-seeking sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/Objective: Depression is a common mental health disorder and an emerging public health concern. Few studies have investigated prevalence and predictors of depression severity in the Irish context. To investigate the relative contribution of known risk factors that predicts depression severity in a treatment-seeking sample of adults in Ireland. Method: As part of a randomised controlled trial of an internet-delivered intervention for depression participants (N=641) completed online screening questionnaires including BDI-II and information associated with common predictors of depression. Results: The mean score on the BDI-II was 24.13 (SD=11.20). Several factors were shown to predict greater severity of depression in the sample including female gender, younger age, unemployment, being single or partnered as opposed to married, previous diagnosis of depression, recent experience of life stressors. Alcohol use, recent losses, knowing a suicide completer, education level, type of employment and income level were not found to be significant. Conclusions: The study contributes to the profiling of the incidence and predictors of severity of depression in an Irish context. The results confirm some of the known risk factors and highlight the need for further research to be carried out on screening for depression and increasing access to interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mooney, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viganò, Noemi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Richardson, Thomas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Richards, Derek</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Timulak, Ladislav</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doherty, Gavin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hayes, Claire</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sharry, John</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes/Objetivo: La depresión es uno de los trastornos de salud mental más comunes y un incipiente problema de salud pública. Pocos estudios han investigado la prevalencia y factores predictivos de su gravedad en el contexto irlandés. El objetivo del estudio fue investigar los factores de riesgo que predicen la gravedad de la depresión en una muestra de adultos en Irlanda en búsqueda de tratamiento. Método: Los participantes auto-referidos accedieron a una intervención en línea para la depresión. Los participantes (N=641) completaron cuestionarios, incluyendo el BDI-II e información asociada con predictores comunes de la depresión. Resultados: Se encontraron varios factores que predijeron la gravedad de la depresión: ser mujer, ser joven, estar desempleado, estar soltero o con pareja pero no casado, tener diagnóstico previo de depresión y experiencia reciente con factores vitales estresantes. Conclusiones: El estudio contribuye a la elaboración de perfiles de incidencia y factores predictivos en la gravedad de la depresión. Los resultados confirman algunos de los factores de riesgo conocidos y ponen de relieve la necesidad de nuevas investigaciones que lleven a cabo la detección de la depresión así como un mayor acceso a las intervenciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. clin. health psychol. (Internet);16(3): 221-229, sept.-dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155888</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Predictores de la gravedad de la depresión en personas adultas que buscan tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7661</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7661^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
