<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80940</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose of review: Pneumonia developing before hospital admission in patients in close contact with the health system was recently termed "healthcare-associated pneumonia" (HCAP). We focus in the recent literature concerning the epidemiology, causative organisms, antibiotic susceptibilities, and outcomes of and empirical antibiotic therapy for this condition. Recent findings: The reported incidence of HCAP among patients requiring hospitalization for pneumonia ranges from 17% to 67%. Hospitalization with in 90 days before pneumonia, attending a dialysis clinic and residing in a nursing home were the most common criteria for HCAP. Compared with patients with community-acquired pneumonia, those with HCAP are older, have greater co-morbidity, and are more likely to have aspiration pneumonia and pneumonia caused by antibiotic-resistant pathogens. Patients with HCAP also more frequently initially receive an inappropriate antibiotic therapy, have higher case fatality rates and have longer hospital stay. Conclusions: Many patients hospitalized with pneumonia via the emergency department haveHCAP. Physicians should identify patients at increased risk of aspiration pneumonia or infection by multidrug-resistant pathogens to promote a targeted approach when selecting initial antibiotic therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carratalà, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roset, Àlex</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia-Vidal, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Propósito de esta revisión: Recientemente se ha propuesto una nueva categoría de neumonía que engloba a aquellos pacientes con un contacto estrecho con el ámbito sanitario, llamada neumonía asociada al sistema sanitario (NAAS). El propósito de este capítulo es revisar los criterios de NAAS, la epidemiología, microorganismos causales y su susceptibilidad antibiótica, diagnóstico, tratamiento, pronóstico y prevención de la NAAS. Hallazgos recientes: La incidencia de NAAS en pacientes que requieren hospitalización oscila entre el 17 y el 67% según los diversos estudios. La hospitalización en los 90 días previos a la neumonía, recibir hemodiálisis o vivir en un centro sociosanitario son los criterios más frecuentes de relación con el ámbito sanitario. Comparados con la neumonía comunitaria, los pacientes con NAAS tienen una edad más avanzada, presentan más comorbilidades asociadas, mayor riesgo de neumonía aspirativa y de neumonía por gérmenes multirresistentes. Estos pacientes presentan más frecuentemente una antibioterapia inicial inapropiada, mayor tasa de mortalidad y estancias hospitalarias más prolongadas. Conclusiones: Muchos de los pacientes hospitalizados desde el servicio de urgencias tienen NAAS. Es importante identificar los pacientes con neumonía espirativa y aquellos con mayor riesgo de infección por microorganismos multirresistentes, para individualizar el tratamiento antibiótico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;20(2): 51-55, abr.-jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80940</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía asociada al ámbito sanitario (NAAS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11444^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28632^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11444^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
