<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166411</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methodology employed in the study of cardiovascular disease in women in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease is the leading cause of death in both men and women in countries like Spain. Nevertheless, the risk of cardiovascular disease in women is frequently underestimated because of the perception that women are «protected» against ischemic heart disease. Moreover, the clinical manifestations of coronary disease in women can differ from those observed in men. These two factors can lead to poorer care in women with any type of cardiovascular disease, not only coronary disease, and to a worse prognosis. This article reviews some features of the sex differences observed in cardiovascular risk factors for, and in the clinical characteristics, treatment and prognosis of, cardiovascular disease. In addition, the general methodological approach employed in a current study of cardiovascular disease in women in Spain is described (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Palop, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertomeu, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Doblas, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Villacastín, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anguita, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig, Eulàlia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedreira, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades cardiovasculares son la causa principal de mortalidad de varones y mujeres en los países de nuestro entorno. Sin embargo, el riesgo de la enfermedad cardiovascular en la mujer se subestima frecuentemente, debido a la percepción de que las mujeres están «protegidas» contra la cardiopatía isquémica. Además, las manifestaciones clínicas de la enfermedad coronaria en las mujeres pueden ser distintas de las observadas en los varones. Estos factores pueden llevar a una peor atención a las mujeres que sufren enfermedades cardiovasculares, no sólo cardiopatía isquémica, y a un peor pronóstico. En este artículo se discuten algunos aspectos relacionados con las diferencias en los factores de riesgo cardiovascular, las características clínicas, el tratamiento y el pronóstico relacionados con el sexo, y se detalla la metodología general del proyecto de estudio sobre la situación en España de la enfermedad cardiovascular en la mujer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);8(supl.D): 4d-7d, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166411</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño general del proyecto de estudio sobre la situación de la enfermedad cardiovascular de la mujer en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6501^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13113^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
