<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167595</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conceptions about empathy: development of an instrument for formative evaluation based on a teaching experience with pediatrics residents at the Universidad de Antioquia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The empathy is essential to the development of an adequate physician-patient relationship. There is evidence about its benefits, but teaching is erratically incorporated into curricula and available material on didactic strategies employed is scarce. From an experience with pediatric residents at the Faculty of Medicine of the University of Antioquia, IQual-e was generated to facilitate teacher-student feedback. This article presents the instrument and its application. Subjects and methods. Qualitative research experience in the teaching context. Through the analysis of content and argumentative discourse an instrument was generated for the formative evaluation of written productions about empathy in the physician-patient relationship. The instrument was applied to 23 residents of four cohorts of the Pedagogy course in Higher Education in Health in which the empathy in the doctor-patient relationship is addressed. Results. The IQual-e proposes an analysis of content and speech of sentences and global response from three main categories: conceptual adequacy, dimensions and sequence. The application of IQual-e to texts produced by residents reflected the multidimensionality of the empathy construct, replicated differences and contradictions that exist on its definition and showed deficiencies in empathy training. Conclusions. The IQual-e is an instrument that can be adapted to evaluate the content of reflections on a construct on which there are conflicting positions or multiplicity of interpretations. It can be used as a complement to rubrics, to evaluate reflective texts, open-ended questions and tests (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dupuy, Lila P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar Blanco, Olga F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La empatía es fundamental para que la relación médico-paciente se desarrolle adecuadamente. Existe evidencia sobre sus beneficios, pero la enseñanza se incorpora de forma errática en los currículos y el material disponible sobre las estrategias didácticas empleadas es escaso. De una experiencia con residentes de pediatría en la Facultad de Medicina de la Universidad de Antioquia se generó el IQual-e, para facilitar el feedback docente-alumno. Este artículo presenta el instrumento y su aplicación. Sujetos y métodos. Experiencia de investigación cualitativa en el contexto docente. Mediante el análisis de contenido y del discurso argumentativo se generó un instrumento para la evaluación formativa de producciones escritas sobre empatía en la relación médico-paciente. Se aplicó el instrumento a 23 residentes de cuatro cohortes del curso de Pedagogía en Educación Superior en Salud, en el que se aborda la empatía en la relación médico-paciente. Resultados. El IQual-e propone un análisis de las frases y de la respuesta global a partir de tres categorías principales: adecuación conceptual, dimensiones y secuencia. La aplicación del IQual-e a los textos producidos por los residentes reflejó la multidimensionalidad del constructo empatía, replicó diferencias y contradicciones que existen sobre su definición, y mostró deficiencias en la formación sobre empatía. Conclusiones. El IQual-e es un instrumento que puede adaptarse para evaluar el contenido de reflexiones acerca de un constructo sobre el cual haya posiciones encontradas o multiplicidad de interpretaciones. Puede usarse como complemento de rúbricas, para evaluar textos reflexivos, preguntas abiertas y ensayos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);20(5): 227-233, sept.-oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167595</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concepciones sobre empatía: desarrollo de un instrumento para la evaluación formativa a partir de una experiencia docente con residentes de pediatría de la Universidad de Antioquia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
