<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140917</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ulipristal acetate, 5 mg: a new alternative</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Fibroids have a high prevalence (approaching 50%) in the female population. Although they are a benign entity, they represent a health problem of considerable magnitude, causing hemorrhaging, pain and sterility. Surgical treatment is currently safe and effective, but in recent decades numerous less invasive alternatives have appeared, such as uterine artery embolization and thermal ablation (HIFU and radiofrequency). New possibilities for medical treatment have also emerged, such as GnRh analogues, aromatase inhibitors and selective progesterone receptor modulators (SPRMs). SPRMs act through progesterone receptors and behave as agonists or antagonists in various target organs. Among them, ulipristal acetate (UA) inhibits the proliferation and induction of apoptosis and cell death pathways in leiomyoma cells, translating at the clinical level to smaller fibroids and lower uterine volumes, with no significant side effects. UA also produces amenorrhea in most patients. Randomized, phase III (PEARL I and II) clinical trials have shown the efficacy and security of UA versus placebo and leuprolide acetate (LA). UA is similar to LA, and superior to placebo in controlling bleeding and decreasing the size of the fibroid, with fewer side effects than LA. The safety and tolerance of UA have been satisfactory. UA is a reality in the preoperative treatment of fibroids, with broad potential for further development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero, Ainhoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monleón Sancho, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romaguera, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morcillo, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Higueras, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los miomas presentan una elevada prevalencia, cercana al 50% de la población femenina. Aunque son una entidad benigna suponen un problema de salud de gran magnitud, causando hemorragia, dolor o esterilidad. Actualmente, el tratamiento quirúrgico es seguro y eficaz, pero en las últimas décadas han aparecido múltiples alternativas menos invasivas: embolización de las arterias uterinas o ablación térmica (HIFU o radiofrecuencia). Además surgen nuevas posibilidades de tratamiento médico como análogos de la GnRh, inhibidores de la aromatasa y moduladores selectivos del receptor de progesterona (SPRM). Los SPRM actúan a través de los receptores de progesterona comportándose como agonistas o antagonistas en distintos órganos diana. Entre ellos, el acetato de ulipristal (AU) produce inhibición de la proliferación e inducción de las vías de apoptosis y muerte celular en células de leiomioma, traduciéndose a nivel clínico en una disminución del tamaño de los miomas y del volumen uterino, sin efectos secundarios significativos. Además produce amenorrea en la mayoría de las pacientes. Los ensayos clínicos aleatorizados en fase III (PEARL I y II) han demostrado la eficacia y seguridad del AU frente a placebo y acetato de leuprolide (AL). AU es similar a AL y superior a placebo en el control del sangrado y la disminución del tamaño del mioma, con menores efectos secundarios que AL. La seguridad y tolerancia de AU han sido satisfactorias. AU constituye una realidad en el tratamiento prequirúrgico de los miomas, con un amplio potencial por desarrollar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);141(supl.1): 40-46, jul. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140917</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acetato de ulipristal 5 mg: una nueva alternativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9836^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8069^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14995^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32835^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
