<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105651</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">FDG PET/CT in monitoring treatment of retroperitoneal fibrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Retroperitoneal fibrosis is an uncommon disease characterized by inflammatory fibrosis typically surrounding abdominal aorta and iliac arteries. The glucose analogue F18-fluorodeoxyglucose can be used to image inflammatory cell activity non-invasively by PET. In this report we investigated the usefulness of the FDG PET/CT in the disease activity and therapy response evaluation of retroperitoneal fibrosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tan, Y. Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yilmaz, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Halac, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sönmezoglu, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ozhan, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrosis retroperitoneal es una enfermedad poco común caracterizada por fibrosis inflamatoria típicamente en el área de la aorta abdominal y las arterias iliacas. El análogo de la glucosa F18 &#150;fluorodeoxiglucosa puede usarse para obtener imágenes de la actividad celular inflamatoria de manera no invasiva por PET. En este informe, estudiamos la utilidad de FDG PET/TAC en la evaluación de la actividad de la enfermedad y respuesta al tratamiento de la fibrosis retroperitoneal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);31(6): 338-339, nov.-dic.2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105651</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">FDG PET/TAC para monitorizar el tratamiento de la fibrosis retroperitoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12602^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12602^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
