<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82332</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pelvic pain in pregnancy. Pubic symphysis dysfunction. Literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pubic symphysis diastasis in pregnancy is a frequent and underestimated problem that has important repercussions on maternal morbidity and high prevalence of chronic pelvic pain in women. The functional impotence that it causes and the associated severe pain, entails the use of a number of therapeutic alternatives, ranging from bed rest to complex corrective surgery, reinforcing the importance and necessity of a correct approach to this pathology. Our aim is, after studying many cases referred to the Pain Treatment Unit at our centre, to carry out a review of this pathology, contacting patients, reviewing the therapeutic alternatives available for these types of conditions and their repercussions on the quality of life of the maternal-foetal binomial and chronic pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Freire Vila, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesia López, A. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canedo Carballeira, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral Lorenzo, C. del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diástasis de la sínfisis púbica en la mujer embarazada es una entidad frecuente e infravalorada, que se relaciona con importante repercusión sobre la morbilidad maternal y con alta prevalencia de dolor crónico pélvico en las mujeres. La impotencia funcional que llega a ocasionar y el importante dolor con el que se relaciona, implica la utilización de un grupo de alternativas terapéuticas, que van desde el reposo en cama, hasta una compleja corrección quirúrgica que refuerza la importancia y la necesidad de un correcto abordaje de la patología. Nuestro objetivo será, a partir de varios casos remitidos a la Unidad de Tratamiento del Dolor de nuestro centro, el realizar una revisión de esta patología, con una aproximación a las pacientes, revisando las alternativas terapéuticas con las que contamos para este tipo de cuadros y su repercusión sobre la calidad de vida del binomio materno-fetal y cronificación del dolor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;17(7): 321-325, oct. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor pélvico en la embarazada. Disfunción de la sínfisis púbica. Revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38643^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8597^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22708^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12066^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38643^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38643^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
