<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112690</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiation-induced leiomyosarcoma of the posterior neck region</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Leiomyosarcomas are mesenchymal malignant tumours that appear in smooth muscle cells. Their most frequent locations are the uterus and gastrointestinal tract. Their occurrence in head and neck is considered exceptional. We present a patient with a posterior neck region leiomyosarcoma who had received radiation for a nasopharyngeal carcinoma 20 years earlier. The incidence ratio of these tumours in radiated patients (therefore considered radiation-induced) ranges from 0,035 to 0,2%. Radiation-induced sarcomas are difficult to diagnose due to the induration and fibrosis in the radiated area and the non-specific symptoms that they present. Their prognosis is very poor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Herrera, Ángel M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Gorjón, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Melcón, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Calvo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los leiomiosarcomas son tumores mesenquimales malignos, que se originan en las células del músculo liso. Las localizaciones de aparición más frecuentes son el miometrio y el tracto gastrointestinal. En la región de cabeza y cuello los leiomiosarcomas aparecen de forma excepcional. Presentamos el caso de un leiomiosarcoma en la región posterior del cuello, en un paciente radiado 20 años antes por un tumor de nasofaringe. La incidencia de este tipo de tumores que cumple los criterios de tumor radioinducido se sitúa entre el 0,035 y el 0,2%. Los sarcomas radioinducidos son difíciles de diagnosticar en estadios tempranos, debido a la induración y la fibrosis de la zona radiada y a la sintomatología inespecífica que presentan. Su pronóstico es malo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;64(3): 233-236, mayo-jun. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112690</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Leiomiosarcoma radioinducido de la región posterior del cuello</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8070^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9575^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
