<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84283</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical treatment of popliteal artery entrapment syndrome: our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Popliteal artery entrapment syndrome (PAES) is a rare condition with an incidencethat varies from 0.17-3.5 %.Aim: We reviewed patients treated with surgery in our department over the past 15 years.Material and methods: A retrospective study between 1995-2009 recorded demographicvariables, comorbidity, physical examination, diagnostic tests, surgical treatment and outcomeat 15 years.Results: Eight patients (50 % male) were treated with surgery for PAES, with a mean age41.5 years (range, 16-62). Two patients (25 %) had disabling claudication, 5 (62.5 %) pain at rest,and in one case (12,5 %) trophic lesions. The test of choice in all of them was arteriography,although two patients also had a CT and three an angio-MR. Surgery was myotomy with releaseof the popliteal artery in three patients (37.5 %) (one of them involving vein graft), myotomywith popliteal thrombectomy in two patients (25 %), popliteal-popliteal bypass with vein inanother 2 (25 %), and one case of lumbar sympathectomy (12.5 %). Intraoperative arteriographywas normal in all cases. During follow-up to 15 years (mean 7.5 ± 3.98 years), 50 % of patientswere asymptomatic, 25 % had no disabling claudication, and another 25 % died as a result ofdisease.Conclusions: In our experience, the release of the popliteal artery by myotomy abnormal tendoninsertion, with or without conducting a popliteal-popliteal bypass, is the surgical treatment ofchoice(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carpintero Mediavilla, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Puerta, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador Calvo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Fajardo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla Calavia, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Díaz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El síndrome de atrapamiento de la arteria poplítea (SAAP) es una entidad pocofrecuente cuya incidencia varía del 0,17 al 3,5 %.Objetivo: Revisamos a los pacientes tratados quirúrgicamente en nuestro servicio durante losúltimos 15 años.Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo entre 1995 y 2009, en que se registraron variablesdemográfi cas, comorbilidad, clínica, exploración física, pruebas complementarias, tratamientoquirúrgico realizado, así como evolución a los 15 años.Resultados: Se intervino quirúrgicamente a 8 pacientes (el 50 %, varones) por SAAP con una medianade edad de 41,5 (intervalo, 16-62) años; 2 pacientes (25 %) presentaron claudicación invalidante,5 (62,5 %), dolor de reposo y en 1 caso (12,5 %), lesiones trófi cas. La prueba de elecciónen todos ellos fue la arteriografía, aunque también en 2 casos se realizó TC y en 3, angio-RM. Eltratamiento quirúrgico fue miotomía con liberación de la arteria poplítea en 3 pacientes (37,5 %)(en uno de ellos se asoció injerto venoso), miotomía junto a trombectomía poplítea en 2 pacientes(25 %), bypass poplíteo-poplíteo con vena en otros 2 (25 %) y un caso de simpatectomía lumbar(12,5 %). La arteriografía intraoperatoria fue normal. Durante el seguimiento a 15 años (medianade seguimiento 7,5 ± 3,98 años) el 50 % de los pacientes estaba asintomático, el 25 %presentaba claudicación no invalidante y otro 25 % falleció como consecuencia de su afecciónconcomitante.Conclusiones: En nuestra experiencia, la liberación de la arteria poplítea mediante miotomíadel tendón de inserción anómalo, asociada o no a la realización de un bypass poplíteo-poplíteo,es el tratamiento quirúrgico de elección(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;62(5): 169-175, sept.-oct. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84283</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico del síndrome de atrapamiento de arteria poplítea: nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52100^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11592^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
