<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82410</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Truancy in the wave of the epidemic in 2009-2010 influenza seasons schools of the city of Ceuta, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Knowing Influenza absenteeism in the educatio-nal environment. Making health education in the same medium. Methods: Among other actions carried out in the pandemic plan, the absences were monitored by flu-like symptoms in children from kindergarten, primary and secondary public schools and reached epi-demiological week 39/2009 to 4 / 2010, transmitting the data from the Directorate Provincial Ministry of Education to the Ministry of Health and Consumer weekly. These data were compared with the same weeks of Diseases of Compulsory and Ceuta Sentinel Net-work. Was conducted health education through lectures and written material in schools. Results: There were a total of 2055 absences, with a peak at week 45. The peak in the States and Red Sentinel was at week 47. ConclusionsAbsenteeism data are complementary to the tradi-tional indicator(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrientos, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledo, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Conocer el absentismo por la gripe en el medio educativo. Métodos: Entre otras actuaciones llevadas a cabo en el Plan Pan-démico, se monitorizaron las ausencias por síntomas gripales en niños de educación infantil, primaria y secundaria de colegios públi-cos y concertados desde la semana epidemiológica 39/2009 a la 4/2010, transmitiendo los datos de la Dirección Provincial del Minis-terio de Educación a la Consejería de Sanidad y Consumo semanal-mente. Estos datos se compararon con los de las mismas semanas de Enfermedades de Declaración Obligatoria y Red Centinela de Ceuta. Resultados: Se contabilizaron un total de 2.055 ausencias, con un pico máximo en la semana 45. El pico máximo en Edos y Red Centinela fue en la semana 47. Conclusiones: Los datos de absentismo son un indicador com-plementario de otros tradicionales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;84(5): 679-685, sep.-oct.2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82410</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la monitorización del absentismo escolar para la vigilancia de la gripe durante la temporada gripal 2009-2010 en la ciudad de Ceuta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34628</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51282^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28017^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28017^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51281^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
