<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046456</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paroxysmal neurogenetic and neurometabolic disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To provide an overview of those neurological disorders that are mainly characterized by a paroxysmalpattern of involvement, and in which a clear genetic or metabolic etiology has been identified. Development. The term&#145;paroxysmal&#146; refers to the abrupt onset of clinical manifestations in a relatively stereotyped manner, usually upon exposureto specific triggering factors with an almost complete resolution of such findings between attacks. They are commonly notassociated to either a relentless progression or a stepwise deterioration, and the majority of them do not lead to thedevelopment of gross neuropathological abnormalities. Although they are difficult to classify due to the heterogeneity of theirclinical manifestations and underlying deficits, a neuroaxis-based approach is proposed for practical purposes, for example,from those conditions affecting predominantly cortical grey matter (manifesting mainly with seizures) to those with analmost exclusive muscular and/or neuromuscular pattern of involvement. The majority of them are caused by genetic defectsin either transporters or neuronal channels, which can be either ions or neurotransmitters. In recent years, the concept of&#145;channelopathies&#146; has grown in acceptance in the medical field, although not all of the described disorders are caused bydefects in molecular channels. Conclusions. Despite their individual rarity, as a group, they are important to the neurologistdue to the advances that their understanding have provided for the development of the field of neurogenetics and neurosciencesin general</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Charria-Ortiz, G. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Revisar aquellos trastornos neurológicos caracterizadosprincipalmente por un patrón de afectación paroxístico,y en los cuales se ha identificado una etiología genética o metabólicaclara. Desarrollo. El término &#145;paroxístico&#146; hace referencia alinicio repentino de las manifestaciones clínicas de una manerarelativamente estereotipada, normalmente tras la exposición a unosfactores desencadenantes específicos con la resolución casi total deestos signos entre los episodios. Típicamente no se asocian a unaevolución incesante ni a un deterioro gradual, y la mayoría no conducenal desarrollo de anomalías neuropatológicas importantes.Aunque por la heterogeneidad de las manifestaciones clínicas ydeficiencias subyacentes resultan difíciles de clasificar, por motivosprácticos se propone una aproximación basada en el eje cerebroespinalque permite organizarlas, por ejemplo, desde las patologíasque afectan de modo predominante a la sustancia gris de la cortezacerebral (manifestadas principalmente en forma de crisis) hasta lasque tienen un patrón de afectación casi exclusivamente musculary/o neuromuscular. La mayoría está causada por anomalías genéticasen los transportadores o en los canales neuronales, que puedenser iones o neurotransmisores. En los últimos años, el concepto de&#145;canalopatías&#146; ha tenido mayor aceptación en el ámbito médico,aunque no todos los trastornos descritos son causados por defectosen los canales moleculares. Conclusión. A pesar de su poca frecuenciaindividual, como grupo son importantes para el neurólogoporque el conocimiento más profundo logrado ha permitido importantesavances en la neurogenética y las neurociencias en general</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(supl.3): s83-s90, abr. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046456</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos neurogenéticos y neurometabólicos paroxísticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
