<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125736</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Post-freudian variations on Agieren: on listening to enactment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The concept of Agieren is revised, differentiating it from the notion of acting-out, either by the patient or by te analyst; its translation as enactment or dramatization, is suggested. The author proposes tat the notion on enactment, introduced by Freud in 1914, acquired a pathological meaning in the mind-twentieth century psycho-analytic literature due to it having been developed according ti the first structural theory, in which what is actual, not verbally symbolized, remains outside of the psychic apparatus, being discharged as acts not conducive to working throug. A logical consequence of the introduction of the second structural theory, with an Id conceptualized as a container of drive motions which have not been thought verbally, tending towards representation by means of a psychic act, implies a change in analytic listening. The author suggests that the imaginary presence of the enigmatic transferencial object, with which the analyst is identified in the encounter, becpmes thinkable a posteriori of having been eacted, which may provide dramatic figuration. Even though a superficial view of the phenomenon of enactmen may suggest that what is at stake is just the perception of the analyst´s behaviour, the larger issue has to do with the dramatic representation of a certain transferencial and countertransferential configuration, which is unconscious for both members of the analytic couple, and which requires a work of signification a posteriori (Nachträglickeit) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sapisochin, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realiza una revisión del concepto de Agieren diferenciándolo de la noción de acting out, sea del paciente o del analista y se propone traducirlo como puesta en acto o escenificación. Se postula que esta noción de puesta en acto, introducida por Freud en 1914, ha adquirido un sentido patologizante en la literatura psicoanalítica de mediados del siglo pasado debido a conceptualizarlo según la primera tópica freudiana en la que lo actual no simbolizado verbalmente queda, por definición, por fuera del aparato psíquico descargándose como actos que no conducen a la elaboración. Se postula que una consecuencia lógica de la introducción de la segunda tópica freudiana, con un Ello concebido como un continente de mociones pulsionales no pensadas verbalmente, que tienden a la representación mediante el acto psíquico, supone un cambio en la escucha analítica. El autor propone que la presencia imaginaria del enigmático objeto transferencial, con el cual el analista es identificado en el encuentro, deviene pensable a posteriori de una puesta en acto que le proporcione figuración escénica. Se postula que, aunque una mirada superficial del fenómeno de la puesta en acto pudiera llevar a considerar que lo que estaría en juego sería sólo la percepción sensorial de una conducta del analista, de lo que verdaderamente se trata es de la representación escénica de cierta configuración transfero-contratransferencial, inconsciente para ambos miembros de la pareja analítica, que requiere de un trabajo de significación a posteriori (Nachtrdglich) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(50): 73-102, ene.-abr. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125736</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variaciones post-freudianas del "Agieren": sobre la escucha de lo puesto en acto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
