<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038617</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proteic expressión of p53 and cellular proliferation in oral leukoplakias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: We intend to know the protein expression of genetic alterations that take place in the early stages in the field cancerization of oral cavity in our means as well as to study the cellular proliferation by means of Ki-67 and the protein product expression of p53 to value if the alterations in the protein products expression of these markers happen in a sequential pathway through the different stages in the field cancerization of oral cavity. MATERIALS AND METHODS: A study was made by immunohistochemistry on 53 patients that presented lesions of oral leukoplaquia, assisted by the ENT service at University Hospitalof Salamanca, from 1.990 up to 2000. 11 samples of normal epithelium,15 mild to moderate dysplasias, 15 in situ carcinomas and 12 microinvasive carcinomas are included in the study. RESULTS: we find an increased cellular proliferation and p53 over-expression as we advance in the grade of severity histopathologic of these lesions. The most early alterations are a significant increase of cell proliferation in mild and moderate dysplasias and an increased p53 over-expression. CONCLUSIONS: Oral leukoplaquia is a precancerous stage that constitutes a canzerisable lesion due to the genetic alterations that mediate in the evolution of lesion. Routine Immunohistochemical and molecular study of these lesions allow us to know the protein expression of genetic alterations that can help in the early diagnosis and treatment of this pathology, having special relevance the study of Ki-67 in early stages and p53 inadvanced lesions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Hernández, Juan Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fonseca Sánchez, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Hernández, M. Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bullón Sopelana, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer la expresión proteica de las alteraciones genéticas que se producen en las etapas precoces de la cancerización del campo de cavidad oral en nuestro medio. Estudiar la proliferación celular mediante Ki-67 y la expresión de la proteína p53 para valorar si las alteraciones en la expresión proteica de estos marcadores suceden de forma secuencial a través de las distintas etapas en la cancerización del campo de la cavidad oral. Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio mediante técnicas de inmunohistoquímica sobre 53 pacientes que presentaron lesiones de leucoplasia oral, atendidos por el Servicio de O.R.L del Hospital Universitario de Salamanca, desde 1.990 hasta 2000. Se incluyen en el estudio 11 muestras de epitelio normal, 15 displasias leves y moderadas, 15 carcinomas in situ, y 12 carcinomas microinvasores. Resultados: Encontramos la proliferación celular aumentada y sobreexpresión de p53 a medida que avanzamos en el grado de severidad histopatológica de las lesiones. Las alteraciones más precoces son el aumento significativo de la proliferación celular en displasias leves y moderadas y el aumento de expresión de p53. Conclusión: La leucoplasia oral es un estado precanceroso quec onstituye una lesión cancerizable debido a las alteraciones genéticas que intervienen en la evolución de la lesión. El estudio inmunohistoquímico y molecular de las lesiones es un medio rutinario que permite conocer la expresión proteica de las alteraciones genéticas, que puede ayudar en el diagnóstico precoz y tratamientode esta patología, teniendo especial relevancia el estudio de Ki-67 en etapas iniciales y p53 en lesiones más avanzadas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(1): 1-8, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038617</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Expresión proteica de p53 y proliferación celular en leucoplasias orales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33060^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29089^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33060^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29089^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22542^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22542^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2490</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
