<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055227</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary iliac venous aneurysm: a case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Venous aneurysms have appeared sporadically in medical literature around the world for the    last 90 years. Yet, the true clinical picture was not established until 1950 by Abbott. According to their aetiopathogenesis    they can be classified into two types: primary or acquired. Case report. We report the case of a 70-year-old male with a    24-hour history of symptoms of deep vein thrombosis in the left lower limb. A Doppler ultrasound recording revealed    thromboses in the common femoral and external iliac veins. Axial tomography and magnetic resonance angiography    scans showed a thrombosed aneurysm with a diameter of 4.2 cm in the common and external iliac veins. Systemic    anticoagulation was established and clinical progress was good. The patient was discharged with dicumarols, elastic    support, resonance angiography monitoring and outpatient follow-up with Doppler ultrasound. Conclusions. Iliac venous    aneurysms are among the least frequent occurring in the venous system. We found seven primary cases reported in the    literature. This is the first case of a thrombosed external-common iliac vein since Hurwitz reported the first aneurysm of    the iliac vein. Most authors agree that the intra-abdominal location presents a potential risk of pulmonary embolism and    thrombosis; thus, when the aneurysm is symptomatic and even asymptomatic and is not fully thrombosed, prophylactic    surgical resection involving end-to-end anastomosis, lateral phleborrhaphy or repair by means of a graft would be    indicated. The diagnosis and follow-up can be accomplished correctly by duplex, but we believe that the moment it is    detected, a complementary MR angiography should also be performed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Aguilar, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Maldonado, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acín García, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno Bertomeu, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Quintana de Carlos, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañibano Domínguez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los aneurismas venosos han aparecido esporádicamente en la bibliografía mundial en los últimos    90 años. La verdadera entidad clínica no fue establecida por Abbott hasta 1950. Pueden clasificarse según su etiopatogenia    en primarios o adquiridos. Caso clínico. Varón de 70 años, con cuadro de trombosis venosa profunda en miembro    inferior izquierdo de 24 horas de evolución. En el eco-Doppler se objetivó trombosis de vena femoral común e iliaca    externa. En la tomografía axial y en la angiorresonancia magnética se apreció aneurisma trombosado en venas iliaca    primitiva y externa de 4,2 cm de diámetro. Se pautó anticoagulación sistémica, con buena evolución clínica. Alta con    dicumarínicos, soporte elástico, control con angiorresonancia y seguimiento ambulatorio con eco-Doppler. Conclusiones.    Los aneurismas venosos iliacos están entre los menos frecuentes del sistema venoso. Encontramos siete casos primarios    publicados en la bibliografía. Éste es el primer caso descrito de vena iliaca primitiva-externa trombosado desde que    Hurwitz publicara el primero de aneurisma venoso iliaco. La mayoría de autores coinciden en que los de localización    intraabdominal presentan un riesgo potencial de trombosis y embolismo pulmonar, por lo que estaría indicado, cuando    el aneurisma es sintomático e incluso asintomático y no se encuentra totalmente trombosado, la resección quirúrgica    profiláctica, realizando anastomosis terminoterminal, venorrafía lateral o reconstrucción mediante injerto. El diagnóstico    y seguimiento se puede obtener correctamente por dúplex, pero creemos que en el momento de su detección, debe    realizarse una angiorresonancia complementaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;59(3): 277-282, mayo-jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055227</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aneurisma venoso iliaco primario: presentación de un caso y revisión de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7267^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30687^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
