<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86251</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of renal function using cystatin C</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Glomerular filtration is the best index for assessing renal function. Despite being subjected to several sources of variability, serum creatinine is the most common glomerular filtration marker in use. Cystatin C is a low molecular weight protein which is more sensitive than creatinine, particularly for the identification of initial small decreases in renal function. The use of cystatin C in certain groups of patients such as elderly, children or diabetics appears to provide more information than creatinine. However, serum cystatin C can be influenced by non-renal factors. Currently, there is not enough scientific evidence to recommend the use of cystatin C to assess renal function instead of creatinine and creatinine equations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas Fernández, María Cruz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Surribas, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ventura Pedret, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapico Muñiz, Edgar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll, Elisabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermudo Guitarte, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viedma Contreras, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Rius, Mariano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Brú, Cecília</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández García, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Montes, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valldecabres Ortiz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez González, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La medición del filtrado glomerular es el mejor índice de valoración de la función renal. La creatinina sérica es el marcador de filtrado glomerular más utilizado, a pesar de estar sometido a diferentes fuentes de variabilidad. La cistatina C es una proteína de bajo peso molecular propuesta como marcador de función renal más sensible que la creatinina al detectar de forma precoz alteraciones en la función renal. La medida de cistatina C en suero en determinados grupos de pacientes como ancianos, niños o diabéticos parece aportar mayor información que la creatinina. Sin embargo, presenta alteraciones en su concentración sérica por factores diferentes al filtrado glomerular. Actualmente no hay evidencia científica suficiente que justifique el cambio de las ecuaciones de estimación del filtrado glomerular basadas en la concentración sérica de creatinina por la medida de la concentración sérica de cistatina C en la evaluación de la función (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;4(1): 50-52, ene.-mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86251</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cistatina C en la evaluación de la función renal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24594^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11383^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11383^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24594</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
