<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055810</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">'Flowsecure(TM)' artificial urinary sphincter: a new adjustable urinary sphincter concept with conditional occlusion for stress urinary incontinence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To spread de concept of a new artificial urinary sphincter with conditional occlusion for stress incontinence.    The new prototype was conceived and designed in The Institute of Urology and Nephrology of London by    Professor Craggs M. and Professor Mundy A.R.    Methods: The FlowSecure sphincter consists of an adjustable pressure-regulating balloon, a stress relief reservoir,    a control pump and valve assembly unit with self-sealing port and a urethral cuff. The pressure regulating balloon    determinates de operating pressure of the device; the pressure is adjustable in the range 0-80 cm H2O and can be    altered by injection or removal of normal saline through the self sealing port. The stress relief balloon transmits transient    intrabdominal pressure to the cuff during periods of stress. An adjustable circular urethral cuff minimises creasing    and possible stress fractures.    Results: The device is implanted as a one-piece assembly which is pre-filled with sterile saline. The surgical technique    is simple and associated with little handling, reducing risk of infection and potential assembly errors. The adjustable    pressure regulating balloon in association with the stress relief reservoir enables the cuff occluding pressure to    be set at a low range, therefore reducing the risk for atrophy and erosion.    Discussion: The new FlowSecure urinary artificial sphincter with conditional occlusion is designed to provide good    continence rates adjusting regulating pressures when needed and conceived to reduce the risk of potential complications    associated with excessive occluding pressures and mechanical failures</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Montes, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Greenwell, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Craggs, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Knight, S. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mundy, A. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Difundir el concepto de un nuevo esfínter urinario artificial con oclusión condicional para el tratamiento    de la incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo. El prototipo fue concebido y diseñado por los profesores Craggs M. y    Mundy A.R. en el Instituto de Urología y Nefrología de Londres.    Materiales y Métodos: El esfínter FlowSecure es un prototipo de una sola pieza de silicona llena de suero salino    que consta de: 1) Un reservorio regulador de presión, 2) un reservorio de asistencia al estrés, 3) una bomba de control    con un puerto autosellable y 4) un manguito. El reservorio regulador determina la presión de la prótesis y se puede    ajustar desde 0 a 80 cm H2O mediante la inyección o extracción de líquido a través del puerto autosellable (oclusión    basal). El reservorio de asistencia al estrés transmite de forma reversible los aumentos de la presión intra-abdominal    durante los periodos de esfuerzo (oclusión condicional).    Resultados: La técnica quirúrgica de implantación es simple, reduciendo la posibilidad de infección y errores de    ensamblaje. La asociación en serie de un reservorio regulador de presión con un reservorio de asistencia al estrés permite    establecer presiones de oclusión basal bajas y el aumento condicional de la misma durante los periodos de estrés,    reduciendo el riesgo de atrofia y erosión. Tras la implantación, la presión es ajustable dependiendo de las necesidades    clínicas del paciente.    Discusión: El esfínter FlowSecure está diseñado para corregir la incontinencia ajustando la presión de oclusión    según las necesidades individuales de cada paciente, así como para reducir las complicaciones asociadas al exceso de    presión de oclusión y los fallos mecánicos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(7): 752-758, jul.-ago. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055810</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esfínter Urinario Artificial 'FlowSecure(TM)': un nuevo concepto de esfínter artificial regulable y con oclusión condicional para la incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29753</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11917</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14950^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
