<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102093</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of irrigation solutions and their combinations on the microhardness of root canal dentin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The purpose of this study was to compare the root dentin microhardness before and after irrigation with alone and combined solutions. Material and Methods: Thirty-five human maxillary anterior teeth were used in this study. The crowns were removed at the cement-enamel junction, the root canals were enlarged. Each root was transversally sectioned into cervical, middle and apical segments and were mounted in an individual silicon device with acrylic resin. The dentin surface was polished. Prior to application of thest solutions, the Vicker´s hardness values of the specimens were measures. The roots were irrigated: group 1 (n=5) EDTA 17% Ç(n=5), group 2: sodium hypochlorite (NaOCl) 1% (n=5), group 3: chlorhexidine gluconate (CHX) 0,5% (n=5) group 4: saline solution (n=5) group 5: NaOCl 1% + EDTA 17% (n=5), group 6: NaOCl 1% + CHX 0,5% (n=5), group 7; EDTA 17% + CHX 0,5% (n=5). Microhardness measurements were performed on each section at 0,5 mm, and 1mm, from the pulp-dentin interface using 300 g. load perpendicular to the surface for 15 seconds. Results: With three-way Variance with repeated measures on two factors and multiple comparisons Bonferroni, significant differences (p&lt;0,05) in the reduction of microhardness when using 17% EDTA, 17% EDTA + 1% NAOCl, EDTA 17% + CHX 0,5% in the apical, middle and cervical thirds and 1% NaOCl in the cervical and middle thirds. Conclusions: EDTA 17% and theis combinations were more effective than other solutions in microhardness reduction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galván, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cheein, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erimbaue, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bulacio, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: en este trabajo se comparó la microdureza de la dentina radicular antes y después de la irrigación con soluciones empleadas solas y combinadas. Material y métodos: 35 dientes humanos anterosuperiores fueron instrumentados, sus raíces fueron cortadas en tercios, incluidas individualmente en resina acrílica y pulidas. Las piezas fueron divididas al azar en grupos de 5 raíces cada uno. Se pusieron en contacto durante 15 minutos con las siguientes soluciones: grupo1: EDTA 17%, grupo 2: hipoclorito de sodio (NaOCI) 1%, grupo 2: gluconato de clorhexidina (CHX) 05%, grupo 4: solución fisiológica, grupo 5: NaOCl 1% + EDTA 17%, grupo 6: NaOCl 1% + CHX 0,5%, Grupo 7: EDTA 17% + CHX 0,5%. La microdureza Vickers fue medida inicialmente y post irrigación a 0,5mm y 1mm, del conducto radicular, empleando 300 g, durante 15 segundos. Resultados: Mediante Variancia de tres vías con medidas repetidas en dos factores y comparaciones múltiples con ajuste de Bonferroni, se observaron diferencias significtativas (p&lt;0,05) en la reducción de la microdureza al emplear EDTA 17% + NaOCl 1%, EDTA 17% + CHX 0,5% en los tercios apical, medio y cervical y con NAOCl 1% en los tercios medio y cervical. Conclusiones: EDTA 17% y sus combinaciones fueron más efectivas en reducir la microdureza dentinaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);28(2): 63-68, abr.-jun. 2010. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102093</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de soluciones de irrigación y sus combinaciones sobre la microdureza de la dentina radicular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13358^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29816</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33076^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
