<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040567</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ascariasis in children: a study of anti-galactose antibodies using desialylated red blood cells</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The presence of antibodies of the ABO system has been associated with hemolytic disease. The immune antibodies disappear when the antigenic stimulation decreases. Thus, their quantitative determination would allow the evaluation of the clinical course and treatment efficacy. The objective was to study the presence of anti-galactose antibodies in sera of children with ascariasis. Anti-B antibodies were studied in the sera of 15 chil" dren infected with Ascaris lumbricoides to assess their activity in saline and an enzymatic medium, inhibition by agarose, hemolytic capacity and treatment with 2-mercaptoethanol to determine the Ig class. Anti-B antibodies showed more activity in the enzymatic medium and presented hemolytic capacity; half of them were of the IgG class. Agarose inhibition revealed the presence of galactosyl residues. The presence of anti-galactose antibodies was demonstrated in children with ascariasis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ponce de León, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presencia de anticuerpos inmunes del sistema ABO ha sido asociada con enfermedad hemolítica. Los anticuerpos inmunes desaparecen cuando disminuye el estímulo antigénico, por lo que su determinación cuantitativa permitiría la evaluación del curso clínico y la eficacia del tratamiento. El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar la presencia de anticuerpos inmunes antigalactosa en sueros de niños con ascariasis. Se trabajó con 15 sueros de niños con infección por Ascaris lumbricoides. Se estudiaron los anticuerpos anti-B en el suero: actividad en medio enzimático y en medio salino; inhibición con agarosa; capacidad hemolítica y tratamiento con 2-mercaptoetanol para determinar la clase de inmunoglobulina (lg). Los anticuerpos anti-B mostraron mayor actividad en medio enzimático, presentaron capacidad hemolítica y la mitad de ellos fueron de clase IgG. Se evidenció la presencia de residuos de galactosil por inhibición con agarosa. Se demuestra la presencia de anticuerpos inmunes antigalactosa en niños con ascariasis</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;63(9): 371-372, oct. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040567</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ascariasis infantil: estudio de anticuerpos inmunes antigalactosa mediante glóbulos rojos desializados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29208^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13067^s22003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d916^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1202^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5829^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1202^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1202^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13067^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5829^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4999^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
