<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165152</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eating habits, physical  ctivity and lifestyles among adolescents in Mexico City and the State of Michoacán</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Adolescence is considered a critical period in the acquisition and formation of eating habits and a healthy lifestyle for the young future and that will probably be enduring in adulthood. The objective of the present study was to determine the dietary and lifestyle behaviors among adolescents in Mexico City (CDMX) and the State of Michoacán. Methods: The Health Behaviour in School-aged Children (HSBC) survey was applied to 956 Mexican adolescents, who participated voluntarily, under the signing of an informed consent. Results: The adolescents of the CDMX show a greater consumption of sweetened beverages compared to those of Michoacán, which means that 94.2% and 91.44%, respectively, consume them regularly. The adolescents of the CDMX and Michoacán, report a low consumption of fruits represented by 16.3% and 14.86% respectively, and vegetables 10.3% and 16.00% respectively, consume them daily or more than one a day. We found a high percentage of students performing sedentary activities during the day. Conclusions: Low physical activity coupled with low consumption of fruits and vegetables and high consumption of soft drinks predisposes adolescents to present an increased risk of noncommunicable diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Radilla Vázquez, Claudia Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo-Moreno, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Chavez, AE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barquera Cervera, Simón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ernesto Murillo, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega y León, Salador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Nava, Liliana G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barriguete  Meléndez, Jorge Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La adolescencia se considera un periodo crítico en la adquisición y formación de hábitos alimentarios y de un estilo de vida saludable para el futuro joven, y que probablemente perdurarán en la edad adulta. El objetivo del presente trabajo fue determinar las conductas alimentarias y de estilo de vida en adolescentes escolarizados de la Ciudad de México (CDMX) y del Estado de Michoacán. Métodos: Se les aplicó la encuesta Health Behaviour in School-aged Children (HBSC) a 956 adolescentes mexicanos, que participaron voluntariamente, bajo la firma de un consentimiento informado. Resultados: Los adolescentes de la CDMX presentaron un consumo mayor de bebidas azucaradas en comparación con los de Michoacán lo que representa que el 94,2% y 91,44%, respectivamente los consumen regularmente. Los adolescentes de la CDMX  y Michoacán, reportan un bajo consumo de frutas representado por el  16,3% y 14.86% respectivamente, y de verduras del 10,3% y 16,00% respectivamente, las consumen a diario o más de una verdura al día. Se encontró un alto porcentaje de estudiantes que realizaban actividades sedentarias durante el día. Conclusiones: La baja actividad física aunada al bajo consumo de frutas y verduras y el alto consumo de bebidas gaseosas predispone a los adolescentes a presentar mayor riesgo de enfermedades no transmisibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;23(1): 0-0, ene.-mar. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábitos alimentarios, actividad física y estilos de vida en adolescentes escolarizados de la Ciudad de México y del Estado de Michoacán</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16566^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16566^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12953^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
