<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106661</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic analysis of specialised and intensive promotion of breastfeeding in neonatal units in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Although breastfeeding (BF) is the ideal food for newborns because it covers their growing needs and provides active immunity against various diseases, it is often replaced by artificial feeding. We estimated the cost-effectiveness of increased promotion of BF in neonatal units with intensive intervention with specialised nurses or midwives dedicated to this purpose. Methods: An analysis of cost-effectiveness, using a decision analysis model which included data on a specialised intervention for the promotion of BF, its effectiveness in the short-term (sepsis, necrotizing enterocolitis) and long-term (disabled due to neurodevelopmental impairment) of the different types of milk consumed, as well as the mortality, costs and benefits of these. Data was also obtained from current medical literature, studies and Spanish sources. The analysis was limited to three subgroups of low birthweights (500-999g, 1000-1749g, 1750-2500g). Results: In the deterministic analysis, the intervention was &#147;dominant&#148; for the three subgroups of infants, which meant it was more effective and with lower costs, than no intervention. The Monte Carlo probabilistic analysis confirmed the robustness of the result with probabilities of dominance of 100%, 100% and 99.9% for the three subgroups of weights, respectively. The intervention would be cost-effective with costs of puerperal intervention of &#128; 70,504, &#128; 14,742 and &#128; 7,106, respectively. These costs would be well above the estimated maximum (&#128; 12.51). Conclusions: According to this model, the promotion of breastfeeding through an intensive promotion and with specialised nurses or midwives dedicated to this purpose, may be cost-effective in the case of puerperal women with low birth weight neonates (500-2500g)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio-Rodríguez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: A pesar de que la lactancia materna (LM) es el alimento idóneo para el neonato porque cubre sus necesidades de crecimiento y le proporciona inmunidad activa frente a diversas enfermedades; esta es sustituida frecuentemente por la lactancia artificial. Se estimó el coste-efectividad de una mayor promoción de la LM en las unidades neonatales mediante la intervención intensiva y especializada de enfermeras o matronas dedicadas a ese propósito. Métodos: Se hizo un análisis de coste-efectividad, mediante un modelo de análisis de decisiones en el que se incluyeron los datos disponibles sobre una intervención especializada para la promoción de la LM, su efectividad, las consecuencias a corto plazo (sepsis, enterocolitis necrosante) y largo plazo (discapacidad por daño neurológico) de las diferentes formas de lactancia, así como la mortalidad, los costes y las utilidades que conllevan, obtenidos de la literatura médica y de los estudios y fuentes españolas disponibles. El análisis se limitó a 3 subgrupos de neonatos de bajo peso (500-999g, 1.000-1.749g y 1.750-2.500g). Resultados: En el análisis determinístico la intervención fue «dominante» para los 3 subgrupos de neonatos, lo que significa que fue más eficaz, con menores costes, que la no intervención. Los análisis probabilísticos de Monte Carlo confirmaron la estabilidad del resultado, con probabilidades de dominancia del 100, el 100 y el 99,9% para los 3 subgrupos de pesos, respectivamente. La intervención dejaría de ser coste-efectiva con costes de la intervención por puérpera de 70.504 &#128;, 14.742 &#128; y 7.106 &#128;, respectivamente. Estos costes estarían muy por encima del máximo estimado (12,51 &#128;). Conclusiones: Según el presente modelo, la promoción de la lactancia materna mediante una intervención intensiva y especializada de enfermeras o matronas dedicadas a ese propósito puede ser coste-efectiva en el caso de las puérperas con neonatos de bajo peso (500-2.500g)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);77(5): 297-308, nov. 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106661</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis económico de la promoción intensiva y especializada de la lactancia materna en las unidades neonatales en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24747^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9552^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24213^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9552^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50303</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30313^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
