<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047876</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Group intervention in anxiety disorders in Primary Health Care: relaxation and cognitive-behavioral techniques</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. Anxiety disorders are very frequent in Primary Health Care. Relaxation and controlled respiration techniques and cognitive-behavior techniques are included in its treatment. METHODS. The design is pre-post intervention longitudinal and descriptive. Study subjects: patients who did a relaxation technique workshop (18 groups) in the health care center from October 1997 to June 2004 (with attendance to 80% of the sessions) (n = 117). Intervention: workshop of 8 sessions in 2 months includes training in breathing, relaxation techniques (of Jacobson and autogenous training of Schultz) and cognitive techniques (confronting stress, problem solving). Ten to 12 persons participate per weekly session. Variables: gender, age, reason for doing the workshop, treatment with psychodrugs. Goldberg Anxiety-Depression Scale (GADS)-18 items was applied before and after the workshops. Pre-post intervention scores (T test, 95% confidence interval) were compared. RESULTS. Pre-post intervention GADS was done in 95 patients, 93.7% of whom were woman. Mean age was 46.8 years (standard deviation 12.6). The main reasons for taking the workshop were: anxiety 51.6%, somatic symptoms 10.5% and 9.5% are caretakers. A total of 47.4% were taking psychodrug treatment, without differences in the pre-post-intervention GADS scores regarding the group without treatment. The mean decrease in pre-post intervention anxiety in the GADS was 3.2 points (2.79-3.6) (p &lt; 0.0001) and 1 (1.59-2.28) (p &lt; 0.0001) on the depression subscale. CONCLUSIONS. Relaxation technique workshops may be useful in the reduction of anxiety and depression in Primary Health Care</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega Gutiérrez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgos Varo, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bordallo Aragón, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Fernández, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Cobos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. Los trastornos de ansiedad son muy frecuentes en Atención Primaria. Su tratamiento incluye técnicas de relajación y respiración controlada y técnicas cognitivo-conductuales. Nuestro objetivo es valorar la eficacia del aprendizaje grupal de las técnicas mencionadas para reducir la ansiedad. MÉTODOS. El diseño es descriptivo longitudinal pre-post-intervención. Sujetos de estudio: pacientes que realizan los talleres de técnicas de relajación (18 grupos) en el centro de salud de octubre de 1997 a junio de 2004 (con asistencia al 80% de sesiones) (n = 117). Intervención: taller de 8 sesiones en 2 meses que incluye entrenamiento en respiración, técnicas de relajación (de Jacobson y entrenamiento autógeno de Schultz) y técnicas cognitivas (afrontamiento de estrés, resolución de problemas). Participan 10-12 personas por sesión semanal. Variables: sexo, edad, motivo para realizar el taller, tratamiento con psicofármacos. Se realiza escala de ansiedad-depresión de Goldberg (EADG)-18 ítems, antes y tras los talleres; se comparan puntuaciones pre-post-intervención (prueba de la t, intervalo de confianza al 95%). RESULTADOS. Realizan la EADG pre-post-intervención 95 pacientes, de los que el 93,7% son mujeres. La edad media es 46,8 años (desviación estándar 12,6). Los principales motivos para realizar el taller son: ansiedad el 51,6%, síntomas somáticos el 10,5% y el 9,5% son cuidadoras. El 47,4% toman tratamiento psicofarmacológico, sin diferencias en las puntuaciones de la EADG pre y post-intervención respecto al grupo sin tratamiento. El descenso medio de ansiedad pre-post-intervención en la EADG es de 3,2 puntos (2,7-3,6) (p &lt; 0,0001) y de 1,9 (1,59-2,28) (p &lt; 0,0001) en la subescala de depresión. CONCLUSIONES. Los talleres de técnicas de relajación pueden ser útiles en la reducción de la ansiedad y la depresión en Atención Primaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(5): 205-210, mayo 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención grupal en los trastornos de ansiedad en Atención Primaria: técnicas de relajación y cognitivo-conductuales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29189</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
