<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057140</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current status of treatment of inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Inflammatory bowel disease encompasses a group of diseases with poorly defined etiology that affect the digestive tract. These diseases are characterized by their chronic course and by periods of disease activity, of variable severity, that alternate with periods of clinical remission.  In the last few years, inflammatory bowel disease has been the object of intense research, which has increased knowledge of the physiopathogenic mechanisms involved. This has enabled the development of a new generation of biotechnological drugs effective in patients previously considered to be refractory to medical treatment and has allowed the accumulated corticosteroid dose to be reduced and the indications for surgery and hospital admissions to be decreased, thus improving quality of life. In addition, some classical drugs have been demonstrated to be effective in recurrence prevention after surgery for Crohn's disease and in the prevention of dysplasia and colorectal cancer in inflammatory bowel disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soriano-Izquierdo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guardiola, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Moranta, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal engloba un grupo de enfermedades del tracto digestivo de etiología todavía no bien conocida, que se caracterizan por su curso crónico y por la alternancia de períodos de actividad, de gravedad variable, con períodos de remisión clínica. Durante los últimos años, la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal ha sido objeto de una intensa investigación, circunstancia que ha promovido un mejor conocimiento de sus mecanismos fisiopatogénicos. Este hecho ha permitido el desarrollo de una nueva generación de fármacos biotecnológicos capaces de controlar a pacientes considerados previamente refrac-tarios al tratamiento médico, reducir la dosis acumulada de corticoides, y disminuir las indicaciones de cirugía y los ingresos hospitalarios, con un incremento de la calidad de vida. Por otro lado, se ha demostrado la eficacia de determinados fármacos clásicos en la prevención de la recurrencia tras la cirugía de la enfermedad de Crohn, así como su utilidad en la prevención de la displasia y el cáncer colorrectal en los pacientes con enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);82(5): 254-259, nov. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado actual del tratamiento de la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3123^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3123^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29872^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3139^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23973^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27905^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
