<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138282</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The stranger autogiro ambulance 1933, a Spanish innovation predecessor in a decade to the first use of medical helicopter</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The medical helicopter has revolutionized patient transport. It is the only means of escape leading healthcare where the sick, transferring it to quickly and easily without relying on roads or facilities. The Spanish participation in the creation of &#145;rotary wing aircraft&#146; for sanitary use, which the helicopter belongs, is unknown to the vast majority of professionals working in this sector never having been published. In 1920 the Spanish Juan de la Cierva and Codorniú invented the &#145;autogiro&#146; revolutionizing the way to fly and solving the problems of low speed flight. This device solved the limitation that health had fixed wing aircraft to pick up wounded by the need of a field ready for takeoff or landing. They were doctors, engineers and Spanish aviators who realized the possibilities in healthcare application of autogiro promoting their use in multiple forums since 1929. Juan de la Cierva own thought in health application of his invention and it is already used in 30 years for this purpose. The project gyroplane ambulance dates from 1933 describing the health modifying a four-seat gyroplane PA-19 Pitcairn Autogiro Company. The Spanish healthcare innovation autogyro forward in more than a decade to taken first use of a rotary wing aircraft for domestic use in 1944 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Canomanuel, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El helicóptero sanitario ha revolucionado el transporte de enfermos. Es el único medio de evacuación que lleva la atención sanitaria donde se encuentra el enfermo, trasladándolo de forma rápida y cómoda sin depender de vías de comunicación o instalaciones. La participación española en la creación de las &#145;aeronaves de ala rotatoria&#146; para uso sanitario, a la que pertenece el helicóptero, es desconocida por la inmensa mayoría de profesionales que trabajan en este sector no habiendo sido nunca publicada. En 1920 el español Juan de la Cierva y Codorniú inventó el &#145;autogiro&#146; revolucionando la forma de volar y resolviendo los problemas del vuelo a baja velocidad. Este aparato solucionaba la limitación que tenían los aviones sanitarios de ala fija para recoger heridos por la necesidad de un campo preparado para el despegue o aterrizaje. Fueron médicos, ingenieros y aviadores españoles los que se dieron cuenta de las posibilidades en la aplicación sanitaria del autogiro promoviendo su uso en múltiples foros desde 1929. El propio Juan de la Cierva pensó en la aplicación sanitaria de su invento y este se utilizó ya en los años 30 para este fin. El proyecto del autogiro ambulancia data del año 1933 describiendo la modificación sanitaria de un autogiro de cuatro plazas PA-19 de la Pitcairn Autogiro Company. La innovación española del autogiro sanitario adelanta en más de una década a la admitida primera utilización de una aeronave de ala rotatoria para uso sanitario en el año 1944 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;71(2): 125-131, abr.-jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El desconocido autogiro ambulancia de 1933, una innovación española predecesora en una década a la primera utilización del helicóptero sanitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31666^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28845^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28835^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22766</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
