<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142944</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spontaneous heterotopic pregnancy. Early and asymptomatic transvaginal ultrasound diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Heterotopic pregnancy is a potentially fatal situation that rarely occurs in a natural conception. Diagnosis in the absence of symptoms is even more exceptional. Furthermore, due to the low index of suspicion of heterotopic pregnancy in natural conceptions, the incidence of serious clinical complications (hemoperitoneum, tubal rupture, acute abdomen) is greater in this group of patients. We report the case of a 33-year-old primigravida with a spontaneous pregnancy who attended her first prenatal visit at 6 weeks and 3 days of amenorrhea. The patient was asymptomatic. Vaginal ultrasound scan showed two gestational sacs, an intrauterine sac and an extrauterine sac next to the right ovary. A laparoscopic right salpingectomy was performed to remove the ectopic pregnancy. A healthy neonate was delivered at 38 weeks&#146; gestation without complications. Heterotopic pregnancy can be diagnosed after spontaneous conception, even in asymptomatic patients. It is important to carry out routine examination of the adnexae in the first ultrasound scan to exclude ovarian disease and diagnose (or exclude) the presence of asymptomatic heterotopic pregnancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morán López, Valentín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Victoria Gomis, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bou Serra, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El embarazo heterotópico es una situación potencialmente fatal, que es raro que ocurra en una concepción natural, y más raramente todavía se diagnostica en ausencia de síntomas. Además, probablemente debido al bajo índice de sospecha de embarazo heterotópico en las gestaciones no estimuladas, el porcentaje de complicaciones clínicas graves (hemoperitoneo, rotura tubárica, abdomen agudo) es superior en este grupo de pacientes. En nuestro caso se trata de una paciente nulípara de 33 años de edad, con gestación espontánea, que acudió a las 6 semanas y 3 días de amenorrea para su primer control rutinario, en ausencia de síntomas. El estudio ecográfico evidenció una imagen gestacional intraútero y otra junto a ovario derecho. Se realizó una laparoscopia con salpingectomía, incluyendo el embarazo ectópico. A las 38 semanas de gestación dio a luz un recién nacido sano sin complicaciones.  Es posible el diagnóstico de un embarazo heterotópico tras concepción natural, incluso en ausencia de síntomas. Es importante realizar una visualización sistema &amp;#769;tica de los anexos en la primera ecografía, que además de descartar la presencia de enfermedad ovárica, puede diagnosticar la presencia de un embarazo heterotópico, incluso en ausencia de síntomas y complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(5): 242-245, mayo 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestación heterotópica espontánea. Diagnóstico ecográfico precoz y asintomático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d571^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54890^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54890^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54890^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54890^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13150^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
