<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131454</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultralow anterior resection with mechanical anastomosis in the treatment of distal third rectal cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tumors of the lower third of the rectum are a challenge for the surgeon. Among the various techniques of surgical treatment of these lesions, radical surgery and ultra low anterior anastomosis is one of the therapeutic options. This technique is a defy both in the evaluation of the potential patient as in the surgical technique. Such evaluation and treatment processes must be audited in order to keep proper quality indices both in the oncological as in their functional results. This is only possible when both the multidisciplinary and surgical teams have an adequate and ongoing specialized training and a satisfactory volume of patients treated. Details of this technique, its indications and results are reported in this paper (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Espín, Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez García, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallribera, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores del tercio inferior de recto son un reto para el cirujano. Entre las diferentes técnicas de tratamiento quirúrgico de estas lesiones se encuentra la cirugía radical y la anastomosis anterior ultrabaja, en la que solamente se conservan los últimos 2 cm hasta la unión anorrectal. Esta técnica constituye un desafío, tanto en la valoración del paciente candidato a esta como en el mismo gesto quirúrgico. Dichos procesos de evaluación y de ejecución deben mantener en las auditorías unos índices de calidad correctos en los resultados oncológicos y funcionales. Esto solo es posible cuando tanto el equipo multidisciplinar como el quirúrgico tienen una formación especializada adecuada y continua y un adecuado volumen de pacientes tratados. En este artículo se exponen los detalles de esta técnica, sus indicaciones y resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);92(supl.1): 4-12, mar. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131454</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resección anterior ultrabaja con anastomosis mecánica en el tratamiento del cáncer de recto del tercio inferior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
