<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79062</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Informed consent efficient. Communication and autonomous decision-making</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Informed consent belongs to a new way to understand doctor-patient relationships from a perspective permitting a principle of autonomy. Seen from this viewpoint, we speak of a medical relationship understood as being a mutual relationship. For a decision to be autonomous, it must be intentional, taken after adequately understanding all the pertinent information and totally free from outside influences. We must realize that from both theoretical and practical views objections exist; these include paternalism, comprehension difficulties, or patient refusal to exercise informed consent. Informed consent presents a reality and a challenge for our profession since it is much more complex than a simple signature on a document(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nayas Igal, Sofía M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente Martínez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basadre García, M. Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bandrés Moro, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Palacios, Francisco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consentimiento informado se enmarca en una nueva forma de entender la relación médico-paciente desde la perspectiva del principio de autonomía. Desde este punto de vista hablamos de una relación sanitaria entendida como relación de mutualidad. Para que una decisión sea autónoma debe ser intencional, emitida tras comprender adecuadamente toda la información y totalmente libre de influencias. Debemos tener en cuenta que, tanto desde el punto de vista teórico como práctico, existen objeciones tales como el paternalismo, la dificultad de comprensión o el rechazo por parte del paciente, entre otras. El consentimiento informado supone una realidad y un reto en nuestra profesión, ya que es mucho más complejo que la mera firma de un documento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;31(6): 419-424, jun. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79062</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consentimiento informado. Comunicación eficaz y decisión autónoma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
