<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63037</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The professional formation is today promoting the implementation of educational options based on competences. This has the purpose of establishing a reference profile, based on professional competences for the Medical Technology career of the University of Talca, using them as indicators, to know the self perception which graduate students have, regarding the level acquired during their formation. Material and method: According to this, an evaluative and descriptive investigation, throughout a self applied survey was carried out. It contained a group of indicators corresponding to previously settled competences in a reference profile where its structure considers different areas, validated by experts, determining the consistency degree through Serafine coefficient. The construction of the information was carried out according to the graduate answers decoded and represented in percentages and later analyzed under interpretative categories. Results: The evaluation considers the percentage of that valued the profile of the competences by area of performance in the highest levels. The obtained results were: For the assistance area 72.9%,the investigation a 59%, the teaching a 44%, the administrative area a 27.1% and the personal-social area a 91.3%.Conclusions: The evaluation made by graduate students about their formation reflects the valued given to the skills acquired in their formation the interpretative categories, the personal-social area is highly evaluated, indicating a great formation advantage, the assistance and investigation area are satisfactory. The teaching and administration area fairly satisfactory. However the last one is considered the lowest. Curriculum effective it is adapted to assure the profile of competences but one is due to review with the objective to incorporate contents for the profit of those deficient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maldonado Rojas, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La formación profesional está hoy en día promoviendo la implementación de opciones educativas basadas en modelos por competencias. El presente trabajo tuvo como propósito establecer un perfil de referencia basado en competencias profesionales para la carrera de Tecnología Médica de la Universidad de Talca y usando éstas como indicadores, conocer la auto percepción que tienen los egresados respecto del grado en que fueron adquiridas durante su formación. Material y métodos: Se realizó una investigación de tipo exploratoria, mediante una encuesta auto aplicada que contenía un conjunto de indicadores que correspondían a competencias establecidas previamente en un perfil de referencia, cuya estructura considera diferentes áreas de desempeño. El perfil fue validado por juicio de expertos, determinando el grado de congruencia a través del coeficiente de Serafine. La construcción de la información se realizó a partir de las repuestas, las que fueron codificadas y representadas en porcentajes y posteriormente analizadas bajo categorías interpretativas. Resultados: La evaluación que se hace considera el porcentaje de egresados que valoró el logro de las competencias por área de desempeño en los niveles más altos. Los resultados obtenidos fueron: Para el área asistencial el 72,9 %, para el área investigación un 59 %, para el área de docencia un 44%, para el área administrativa un 27,1%y para el área personal-social un 91,3 %.Conclusiones: Siguiendo el criterio de categorías interpretativas, el área personal social indica una gran fortaleza de la formación, el área asistencial y el área investigación se encuentran en un nivel satisfactorio y las áreas docencia y administración en niveles medianamente satisfactorio, siendo esta última la gran falencia de la formación. El currículo vigente es adecuado para asegurar el logro de gran número de competencias, pero se debe revisar con el objetivo de incorporar contenidos para el logro de aquellas deficiente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);10(4): 233-243, dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63037</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
