<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036358</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Gastrointestinal inflammatory fibroid polyps. Clinical characteristics and follow-up in a series of 26 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: Inflammatory fibroid polyp (IFP) is a protuberant lesion, located near the muscularis mucosae and composed of a proliferation of fusiform cells and conjunctive fiberssurrounding capillaries and a variable inflammatoryin filtrate. It is believed to be a poorly controlled inflammatory repair response. Our aim was to study the clinical, pathological and follow up characteristics of a series of patients with IFP.PATIENTS AND METHOD: We studied 26 IFPs from 25 patients(16 women and 9 men) registered between 1985 and 2001 ina specific register of 3 centers in the city of Gerona (Spain).The variables analyzed were age, sex and clinical presentation, IFP localization and size, mucosal characteristics and associated disease, as well as follow-up information. Routine statistical analyses were performed. RESULTS: IFPs were antral in 16 patients, ileal in 7, jejunal in 2and colonic in the remaining patient. Size determined whether they were symptomatic (35 ± 13.6 mm) or asymptomatic (8.4 ±6.3 mm). Gastric polyps were significantly smaller than intestinal polyps. Symptomatic polyps (5 out of 16 gastric polyps and9 out of 10 intestinal polyps) predominated in women and occurred at a significantly lower age than asymptomatic polyps(59.2 versus 74.1 years). Most gastric IFPs were associated with chronic atrophic gastritis while only one ileal polyp was associated with Meckel&#146;s diverticulum. The mean length of follow up was 60.6 months and, except in one patient who underwent in complete resection, no recurrences of IFP were observed. CONCLUSION: IFP is a heterogeneous entity, depending on age at presentation, sex, size and location in the digestive tract. IFP does not recur after resection. The association of gastric IFP and chronic atrophic gastritis could suggest a modulatory effect of the mucosa on IFP growth</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hombrados, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garijo, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldeguer, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acero, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Huix, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adrados, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernadó, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: El pólipo fibroide inflamatorio (PFI) es una lesión protuberante que se localiza cerca de la muscularis mucosae y está constituida por una proliferación de células fusiformes y fibras conjuntivas alrededor de los capilares y un infiltrado inflamatorio variable. Se considera una reacción inflamatoria reparadora mal controlada. El objetivo de este trabajo ha sido estudiar las características clínicas, anatomo-patológicas y de seguimiento de una serie de pacientes con PFI.PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: Se han estudiado 26 PFI (25 pacientes:16 mujeres y 9 varones) recogidos entre los años 1985 y2001 en un registro específico de 3 centros de la ciudad de Girona. Las variables analizadas fueron la edad, el sexo y la presentación clínica, la localización y el tamaño del PFI, las características de la mucosa y las enfermedades asociadas, así como información del seguimiento. Se realizaron las pruebas estadísticas habituales. RESULTADOS: El PFI fue antral en 16 casos, ileal en 7, yeyunalen 2 y colónico en el restante. Su tamaño condicionó su carácter sintomático (35 ± 13,6 mm) o asintomático (8,4 ±6,3 mm). Los pólipos gástricos fueron significativamente más pequeños que los intestinales. Los pólipos sintomáticos(5 de 16 gástricos y 9 de 10 intestinales) predominaron en mujeres y en edades significativamente inferiores que los asintomáticos (59,2 frente a 74,1 años). La mayoría delos PFI gástricos se asociaron a gastritis crónica atrófica, mientras que sólo un PFI ileal lo hizo a divertículo de Meckel. El seguimiento medio fue de 60,6 meses y, salvo en un caso de resección incompleta, no se constató recidiva del PFI. CONCLUSIÓN: El PFI es una entidad heterogénea según la edad de presentación, el sexo de los pacientes, su tamaño y la localización en el tubo digestivo. Tras la resección, el PFI no recidiva. La asociación de los PFI gástricos a gastritis crónica atrófica podría apuntar a un efecto modulador de la mucosa sobre el crecimiento del PFI</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;28(4): 215-220, abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036358</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pólipo fibroide inflamatorio gastrointestinal. Características clínicas y seguimiento de una serie de 26 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28109^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13660^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11564^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28109^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13660^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5898^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28109^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13660^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
