<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97107</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Response protocols: their past, present, and future in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Coordination between levels of health care is a relatively recent phenomenon. Response protocols, which are potentially applicable to all conditions requiring a prompt response, are among the most visible consequences of such coordination The response protocol with the longest history in Spain is the stroke code. Introduced in 1997, this code is now used throughout the country and has improved prognosis in this clinical setting. Some city health care systems have since adopted, with good results , codes for managing non heart-beating donors or acute myocardial infarction. The code for sepsis, on the other hand, has met with the difficulty that clinical recognition is not high in the first few hours of response by emergency services, and outcomes have therefore suffered. Finally, protocols that might potentially benefit patients with other conditions have not been put into practice for a variety of reasons. Examples are one for acute poisoning and another for managing the agitated patient. It is essential, however, to avoid trying to codify all health care responses given that the agility that codes presuppose would suffer. Furthermore, it is important to bear in mind that health care quality does not depend on whether a code is activated or not; instead, a code is one of many quality-related features to consider in the specific clinical situations that call for one. We believe that the future should focus on consolidating our experience with existing codes and on improving registries. New projects should be suggested and results studied and published (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Fàbrega, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espila Etxeberria, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Mena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las estrategias de coordinación entre niveles asistenciales son relativamente recientes. Una de las consecuencias más visibles de esta coordinación son los códigos de activación, los cuales son potencialmente aplicables a toda patología tiempo-dependiente. En España, el código de activación más antiguo es el código ictus, iniciado en 1997, y cuya implantación se ha generalizado y ha permitido mejorar el pronóstico de los pacientes con un accidente vascular cerebral. A éste le han sucedido, en algunas ciudades, otros como el código donante a corazón parado o el código IAM (infarto agudo de miocardio), con los que también se está obteniendo unos buenos resultados. El código sepsis, en cambio, se ha encontrado con la dificultad específica de su bajo reconocimiento clínico en las primeras horas de asistencia por parte de los servicios de urgencias y los de emergencias, lo cual está limitando sus resultados. Finalmente, y por razones diversas, no ha sido posible poner en marcha códigos de activación en otras situaciones que potencialmente podrían beneficiarse de ellos, como son la intoxicación aguda o el paciente agitado. En cualquier caso, no hay que caer en la tentación de codificar la totalidad de la asistencia, ya que ello debilitaría el concepto de agilidad que se les supone a los códigos. Además, debe tenerse en cuenta que el nivel de calidad asistencial no depende de la activación o no de un código, sino que dicho código es un aspecto cualitativo más en determinadas situaciones clínicas que lo requieren. Creemos que el futuro de los códigos de activación pasa por consolidar los proyectos existentes, mejorar los registros, plantear nuevos proyectos y publicar sus resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(4): 311-318, ago. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97107</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Códigos de activación: pasado, presente y futuro en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17209^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4706^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31002^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
