<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147746</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for the use of methotrexate in patients with juvenile idiopathic arthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To develop a consensus document of recommendations for the use of methotrexate (MTX) in patients with juvenile idiopathic arthritis (JIA). Material and method: A group of eleven experts proposed several clinical questions on the use of MTX in patients with JIA. A systematic review was conducted and the evidence and recommendations for each question were extracted. The results were discussed and validated by the experts in a work session to establish the final recommendations. Results: MTX is recommended as the first drug for inducing remission in JIA, and its indication should be made according to the clinical category of the patient. Prior to treatment, it is recommended to perform a complete blood count, including white cells, levels of liver enzymes, serum creatinine, and other analytical parameters according to specific risk factors. Treatment should be initiated with a dose of 10-15mg/m2/week. In cases of uveitis or polyarthritis, an initial dose of 15mg/m2/week should be considered. For a better bioavailability and tolerability, it is preferable to administer MTX parenterally if the dose is &amp;#8805;15mg/m2/week. It is necessary to periodically perform an analytical monitoring of the patient and to assess possible alterations in liver enzymes to make changes if necessary. Combinations with biological agents may be necessary, as well as the concomitant addition of folic or folinic acid. Conclusions: This document describes the main recommendations for the appropriate use of MTX in JIA patients, according to scientific evidence and clinical experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lacruz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Cordovés-Rego, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamir, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Robledillo, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Inocencio, J de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rua, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustabad, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Elaborar un documento de recomendaciones consensuadas para el uso de metotrexato (MTX) en pacientes con artritis idiopática juvenil (AIJ). Material y método: Un grupo de 11 expertos planteó diversos interrogantes clínicos en el uso de MTX en pacientes con AIJ. Se realizó una revisión sistemática y se extrajeron las evidencias y recomendaciones para cada pregunta. Los resultados fueron valorados y consensuados por los expertos en una sesión presencial para establecer las recomendaciones finales. Resultados: Se recomienda el MTX como primer fármaco inductor de remisión en AIJ, cuya indicación se realizará según la categoría clínica del paciente. Previo al tratamiento se recomienda evaluar un hemograma que incluya recuento leucocitario, niveles de enzimas hepáticas y creatinina sérica, así como otros parámetros analíticos conforme a factores de riesgo específicos. El tratamiento se iniciará con dosis de 10-15mg/m2/semana. En casos de uveítis o poliartritis se valorará una dosis inicial de 15mg/m2/semana. Para una mejor biodisponibilidad y tolerabilidad, se administrará preferentemente por vía parenteral si la dosis es&amp;#8805;15mg/m2/semana. Se deberá realizar un seguimiento analítico del paciente periódicamente y evaluar posibles alteraciones en enzimas hepáticas para realizar cambios si fuera preciso. La combinación con biológicos puede ser necesaria, además del uso concomitante de ácido fólico o folínico. Conclusiones: Este documento recoge las principales recomendaciones para el empleo adecuado de MTX en pacientes con AIJ, de acuerdo a la evidencia científica y a la experiencia clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);84(3): 177.e1-177.e8, mar. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147746</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones para el uso de metotrexato en pacientes con artritis idiopática juvenil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4365</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51811^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1177^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35067^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1177^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5629^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
