<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150518</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Latest update on multiple system atrophy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Multiple System Atrophy (MSA) is a neurodegenerative, quickly progressive, sporadic disorder that presents with a combination of dysautonomic, parkinsonian, cerebellar and corticospinal symptoms. The aetiopathogenesis is unknown, but there seems to be an underlying genetic role involving a-synuclein. Early diagnosis of the disease has improved with the new clinical criteria of 2008, backed by structural and functional neuroimaging techniques. Treatment continues to be symptomatic, but recent clinical trails have been conducted with therapeutic options that attempt to curb the natural progression of the disease. www.neurologia.com Rev Neurol 2012; 54 (Supl 4): S45-S51 S51 PONENCIA Aims. The purpose of this study is to review the most significant advances in MSA reported in the scientific literature in the last 5 years. Development. The literature from the last few years was reviewed and we report on the most significant advances in the pathogenesis, diagnosis and treatment of MSA, as well as the main future perspectives in those fields. Conclusions. The pathogenesis of MSA remains unknown, although variations in the SNCA locus of chromosome 4q22.1, which codes for a synuclein, play an important role. The new diagnostic criteria have allowed diagnosis to become more accurate in the early stages of the disease. Several clinical trials have been carried out with promising disease-modifying therapies, although further studies will be needed in the future to determine their true clinical scope (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Duarte Martín, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riveira Rodríguez, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La Atrofia Multisistémica (AMS) es un trastorno neurodegenerativo, rápidamente progresivo, esporádico, que se presenta con una combinación de síntomas disautonómicos, parkinsonianos, cerebelosos, y corticospinales. La etiopatogenia es desconocida, pero parece existir un papel genético subyacente que implica a la &amp;#945;-sinucleína. El diagnóstico temprano de la enfermedad ha mejorado con los nuevos criterios clínicos de 2008, apoyados por técnicas de neuroimagen estructural y funcional. El tratamiento sigue siendo sintomático, pero se han publicado recientes ensayos clínicos con opciones terapéuticas que intentan frenar la progresión natural de la enfermedad. Objetivo. Revisar los avances más notorios publicados en la literatura científica en los últimos 5 años en la AMS. Desarrollo. Se ha revisado la literatura de los últimos años y se presentan los avances más significativos en la patogenia, diagnóstico, y tratamiento de la AMS, así como las principales perspectivas futuras en dichos campos. Conclusiones. La patogenia de la AMS sigue siendo desconocida, aunque las variaciones en el locus SNCA del cromosoma 4q22.1 que codifica la &amp;#945;-sinucleína juegan un papel destacado. Los nuevos criterios diagnósticos han permitido mejorar la precisión diagnóstica en los estadios iniciales de la enfermedad. Existen diversos ensayos clínicos con prometedoras terapias modificadoras de la enfermedad, aunque son necesarios más estudios futuros para determinar el verdadero alcance clínico de las mismas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(supl.4): s45-s51, 3 oct., 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150518</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Último minuto en atrofia multisistémica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1501^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33352^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22586^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33352^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22586^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33352^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22617^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7204^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22617^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1501^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27148^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7204^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27148^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
