<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142013</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are treatments with statins that are considered unsuitable really unsuitable?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the Catalonian Institute of health there are 2 well-established circumstances for indicating lipid-lowering drug treatment with statins in the primary prevention of ischaemic heart disease. These are, severe hypercholesterolaemia, with a low density lipoprotein cholesterol equal to or greater than 240 mg/dL, or above 130 mg/dL when the coronary risk is equal to or greater than 10% at 10 years. There are data that suggest that these 2 criteria are not the only ones used in routine clinical practice, as such that the majority of patients to whom it is indicated, do not meet either of these 2 conditions. This study aims to determine the characteristics of the patients when statins are indicated outside the aforementioned circumstances. It is concluded that around 40% of patients have clinical characteristics that could justify the treatment. The level of suitability could not be established in about 33% of the patients, due to not being able to determine the coronary risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vilaseca Canals, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Ovalle, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Trías, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro Rivera, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jusmet Miquel, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Machado, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrada Alifonso, Cinta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las circunstancias que están bien establecidas, en el ámbito del Institut Català de la Salut, para indicar un tratamiento farmacológico hipolipidemiante con estatinas en la prevención primaria de la cardiopatía isquémica son 2: una hipercolesterolemia severa, con valores de colesterol transportado por las lipoproteínas de baja densidad iguales o superiores a 240 mg/dL, o por encima de 130 mg/dL cuando el riesgo coronario es igual o mayor al 10% a los 10 años. Hay datos que indican que en la práctica habitual estos 2 criterios no son los únicos utilizados, de forma que la mayoría de los pacientes a quienes se indica, de novo, una estatina, no reúnen ninguna de estas 2 condiciones. Este estudio pretende conocer las características que tienen los pacientes cuando estas son indicadas fuera de los supuestos mencionados. Se concluye que cerca del 40% de los pacientes tienen características clínicas que pueden explicar la indicación del tratamiento. En una tercera parte no puede establecerse el grado de adecuación por no poderse determinar el riesgo coronario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);27(4): 175-178, jul.-ago. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142013</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Son realmente inadecuados los tratamientos con estatinas considerados como inadecuados?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1166^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
