<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048256</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk of Suffering from Cardiovascular Diseases because of the Clustering of the Modifiable  Cardiovascular Risk Factors in the Population Older than 15 years of a Health Care Center in Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Over recent decades, the death rate due to cardiovasculardiseases has shown a downward trend in developedcountries, as has also been the case in Spain. However, are still theleading cause of death. This study is aimed at studying the relationshipbetween cardiovascular diseases and different modifiablecardiovascular risk factors related to their clustering.Methods: Descriptive cross-sectional study conducted at anurban healthcare center, which included 2248 individuals ages 15and above selected by simple random sampling of the medical recordfiles. The risk of having some cardiovascular disease (ischemic cardiopathy,cerebrovascular disease or peripheral arteriopathy of lowerlimbs) was calculated in the form of an odds ration (OR) in relationto the clustering of the risk factors of smoking, high blood pressure,hypercholesterolemia, hypertriglyceridemia and diabetes mellitus,adjusted by age, sex and risk factors.Results: The individuals studied had 224 cardiovascular diseases.For smoking, the OR as an isolated risk factor was 1.5 (95% CI:1.0-2.2) and 1.6 (95% CI: 0.9-2.5) with the clustering with the otherfour risk factors; with high blood pressure, respectively of 2.1 (95%CI: 1.5-2.9) and 1.7 (95% CI: 1.1-2.6); with hypercholesterolemia,respectively of 1.7 (95% CI: 1.2-2.4) and 1.6 (95% CI: 1.1-2.4); andwith hypertriglyceridemia, respectively of 1.8(95% CI: 1.2-2.8) and1.3 (95% CI: 0.8-2.1). The OR's showed a similar behavior on layeringby each cardiovascular disease, although the highest OR's (2.4 -3.1 range) corresponded to the clustering of diabetes mellitus andsmoking.Conclusions: The risk of having cardiovascular diseasesremains high with the clustering of cardiovascular risk factors,although differences among them are found to exist</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Val García, José Luis del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raidó Quintana, Eva María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Tejón, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rovira España, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baena Díez, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alemany Vilches, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomàs Pelegrina, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: En la últimas décadas la mortalidad por enfermedadescardiovasculares ha mostrado una tendencia decreciente en lospaíses desarrollados, confirmada asimismo en España. No obstantesiguen siendo la principal causa de mortalidad El objetivo de este trabajoes estudiar la asociación entre las enfermedades cardiovascularesy diversos factores de riesgo cardiovascular modificables en relacióna su agrupación (clustering).Métodos: Estudio descriptivo transversal realizado en un centrode salud urbano, que incluyó a 2.248 personas de 15 o más años,seleccionadas por muestreo aleatorio simple del archivo de historiasclínicas. Se calculó en forma de odds ratio (OR) el riesgo de teneralguna enfermedad cardiovascular (cardiopatía isquémica, enfermedadcerebrovascular o arteriopatia periférica de extremidades inferiores)en relación al clustering de los factores de riesgo tabaquismo,hipertensión arterial, hipercolesterolemia, hipertrigliceridemia y diabetesmellitus, ajustado por edad, sexo y factores de riesgo.Resultados: Las personas estudiadas tenían 224 enfermedadescardiovasculares. En el tabaquismo la OR como factor de riesgo aisladofue de 1,5 (IC95%: 1,0-2,2) y de 1,6 (IC95%: 0,9-2,5) con el clusteringcon los otros 4 factores de riesgo; con la hipertensión arterial de2,1 (IC95%: 1,5-2,9) y de 1,7 (IC95%: 1,1-2,6), respectivamente; conla hipercolesterolemia de 1,7 (IC95%: 1,2-2,4) y de 1,6 (IC95%: 1,1-2,4), respectivamente; con la diabetes de 2,5 (IC95%: 1,7-3,5) y 2,0(IC95%: 1,3-3,0), respectivamente y con la hipertrigliceridemia de 1,8(IC95%: 1,2-2,8) y 1,3 (IC95%: 0,8-2,1), respectivamente. Las OR secomportaron de manera similar al estratificar por cada enfermedadcardiovascular, aunque las OR más elevadas (entre 2,4 y 3,1) correspondieronal clustering de diabetes mellitus y tabaquismo.Conclusiones: El riesgo de tener enfermedades cardiovascularessigue siendo elevado con el clustering de factores de riesgo cardiovascular,aunque se observan diferencias entre ellos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;79(3): 365-378, mayo-jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048256</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de presentación de eventos cardiovasculares según la agrupación de los factores de riesgo modificables en la población mayor de 15 de años de un centro de salud de Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
