<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036877</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fetal intravascular transfusión in the treatment of alloimmunization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess perinatal outcome after fetal intravascular transfusion in the treatment of alloimmunization between 1990 and 2003. Subjects and methods: Fetal blood sampling was offered to immunized pregnant women when significant fetal anemia was suspected. Intravascular fetal transfusion was performed when the fetal hematocrit was below -2 standard deviations for gestational age. Serial transfusions were scheduled every 3 weeks until approximately 34-35 weeks. Results: Cordocentesis was performed in 32 singleton pregnancies. In 11 (34%) of these, no fetal anemia as defined by the established criteria was detected. Fifty intravascular fetal transfusions were performed in 19 pregnancies, from the 21st to the 35th week. No spontaneous fetal losses were observed. At 0-13 years of age, all the children showed normal development for their age. Conclusion: Fetal intravascular transfusion is an effective procedure in the prenatal treatment of fetal anemia with favorable long-term outcome</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borrell, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cararach, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortuny, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puerto, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borobio, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los resultados de la transfusión fetal intravascular en el tratamiento de la isoinmunización, durante el período 1990-2003. Sujetos y métodos: Se ofreció una cordocentesis para realizar un hemograma fetal a las gestantes isoinmunizadas con sospecha de anemia fetal significativa. Se practicó transfusión intrauterina cuando el valor del hematocrito fetal fue inferior a -2 desviaciones estándar para la edad gestacional. Las transfusiones se repitieron aproximadamente cada 3 semanas hasta la semana 34-35. Resultados: Se practicó una cordocentesis en 32 gestaciones, en 11 (34%) de las cuales no se objetivó una anemia fetal significativa de acuerdo con los criterios establecidos. En 19 gestaciones se realizaron un total de 50 transfusiones entre las 21 y 35 semanas. No se observó ninguna pérdida fetal espontánea. A los 0-13 años de vida, todos los niños presentan una evolución correcta para su edad. Conclusión: La transfusión intravascular fetal es una técnica efectiva en el tratamiento prenatal de la anemia fetal con resultados favorables a largo plazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);48(4): 179-185, abr. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036877</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transfusión intravascular fetal en el tratamiento de la isoinmunización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4985^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30770^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1833^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d766^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4985^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
