<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153534</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nurse assessment of paediatric preoperative anxiety in Ambulatory Surgery Unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: Scientific evidence shows the need to treat the child&#146;s anxiety before starting anesthesia to have a child more partner and less traumatic induction. To determine the need for sedative medication the assessment of anxiety is usually based on the judgment, skill or experience of the caregivers. The aim of this study is to evaluate the ability of the nurse in assessing the child&#146;s anxiety before induction of anesthesia. Material and methods: 81 patients aged 2 to 12 years old were selected; they should be operated in an ambulatory surgery unit. The nurses evaluated the child&#146;s anxiety on a scale of two items and scale `modified Yale Preoperative Anxiety Scale`(mYPAS), which had been previously validated by our group to Spanish. This tool was used as the gold standard for calculating the indices of sensitivity of the evaluation of the nurse. Results: the ability of the nurse to classify the anxious child got a very specificity and low sensitivity. Conclusions: The ability of the nurse for detection the child with a high degree of anxiety is very efficient, but in children with anxiety masked by various attitudes or lack of verbalization is shown insufficient, so it requires more accurate diagnostic tools. There are many factors involved in the diagnosis of anxiety, which require more study to make a correct detection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lázaro, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jerez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ullán, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: La evidencia científica muestra la necesidad de tratar la ansiedad del niño antes de iniciar una anestesia para conseguir una mayor colaboración y una inducción menos traumática. La evaluación de la ansiedad se basa por lo general en el juicio, habilidad o experiencia del personal asistencial para determinar la necesidad de medicación sedativa. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar la habilidad de la enfermera en valorar la ansiedad del niño antes de la inducción de la anestesia. Materiales y métodos: Se seleccionaron 8 pacientes de 2 a 12 años de edad que debían ser operado en una Unidad de Cirugía Ambulatoria. Las enfermeras evaluaron la ansiedad del niño utilizando una escala de dos valores y la escala `modified Yale Preoperative Anxiety Scale`(mYPAS), que había sido previamente validada al español por nuestro grupo. Esta herramienta se usó como gold standard para calcular los índices de sensibilidad y especificidad de la evaluación de la enfermera. Resultados: La habilidad de la enfermera para detectar al niño ansioso obtuvo una especificidad muy elevada pero una sensibilidad baja. Conclusiones: La habilidad de la enfermera para detectar la detección del niño con alto grado de ansiedad se muestra muy eficiente, pero en niños con ansiedad enmascarada por diversas actitudes o falta de verbalización se muestra insuficiente, por lo que se precisa de herramientas de diagnóstico más precisas. Son muchos los factores involucrados en el diagnóstico de la ansiedad, lo que obliga a más estudios para poder realizar una correcta detección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;21(1): 10-15, ene.-mar. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153534</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación enfermera de la ansiedad prequirúrgica pediátrica en una Unidad de Cirugía Ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56029^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
