<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83944</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-6157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This work described the photopolymerisation kinetic study of new experimental composites, using hybrid loads of hydroxyapatite. The composites got ready starting from a monomeric mixture (matrix)composed by bis 2,2 [p-(2-hydroxy-3-methacryloxypropoxy) phenil]propane (Bis-GMA) and triethylenglycoldimethacrylate (DMTEG). It was used like load or filling inorganic mixtures of syntherized hydroxyapatite (HAS) and nanometric hydroxyapatite (HAN). It is also analysed the influence, on the kinetic measures, of the content in filling and of the superficial treatment of these loads using coupling agent: malic acid (Mal.) and tri-sodium citrate (Cit.).The photocalorimetric measured has allowed obtaining valuable information with regard to the kinetic behaviour of these materials. The dependence of the polymerisation speed has been evaluated (Rp) with the content and the nature of the used filling, were observed an increase of the same one and of the percentages of the monomer conversion (polymerisation) in the prepared composites with padded HAS and treated superficially with carboxylic compounds. The bestkinetic results are obtained with the employment of you have modified with malic acid (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Argota, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcís Soriano, R. W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murtra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sastre, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Clemente, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo se describe el estudio cinético de la fotopolimerización de nuevos composites experimentales, utilizando cargas híbridas de hidroxiapatita. Los composites se prepararon a partir de una mezcla monomérica (matriz) compuestapor el 2,2 bis [p-(2-hidroxi-3-metacriloxipropoxi) fenil] propano(Bis-GMA) y dimetacrilato de trietilenglicol (DMTEG). Se utilizó como carga o relleno inorgánico mezclas de hidroxiapatita sinterizada (HAS) e hidroxiapatita nanométrica (HAN). Se analiza también la influencia, sobre las medidas cinéticas, del contenido en relleno y del tratamiento superficial de estas cargas empleando como agentes funcionalizantes: ácido málico (Mal.) y citratotrisódico (Cit.).La medidas fotocalorimétricas han permitido obtener una valiosa información con respecto al comportamiento cinético de estos materiales. Se ha evaluado la dependencia de la velocidad depolimerización (Rp) con el contenido y la naturaleza del relleno empleado, habiéndose observado un aumento de la misma y de los porcentajes de conversión del monómero (polimerización) en los composites preparados con relleno hidroxiapatita sinterizada y tratada superficialmente con compuestos carboxílicos. Los mejores resultados cinéticos se obtienen con el empleo de HAS modificada con ácido málico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dentum (Barc.);2(1): 8-13, ene-mar. 2002. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la cinética de fotopolimerización de nuevos materiales compuestos con carga híbrida de hidroxiapatita</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31497^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19241^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3778</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31497^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23143</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
