<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89468</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus: changes in the susceptibility pattern to daptomycin during a 10- year period (2001-2010)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The objective of this study was to evaluate the activity of daptomycin and other agents against methicillinresistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) isolates collected from 2001 to 2010, in order to determine changes and to detect resistance trends. Methods. The study included a total of 1,130 MRSA isolates collected as part of a multicenter surveillance program for antibiotic resistance, Estudio de Vigilancia de Resistencia a los Antimicrobianos (VIRA study), from 51 medical centers throughout Spain between 2001 and 2010. Broth microdilution test was performed according to the Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute guidelines. Results. Daptomycin showed excellent activity and maintained its activity over time; only one MRSA isolate collected in 2001 was nonsusceptible to this agent (MIC=2 mg/L). Based on the MIC90, daptomycin was 2-4 dilutions more active than vancomycin, teicoplanin and linezolid. Daptomycin retained activity against MRSA isolates that were resistant to linezolid, to quinupristin-dalfopristin, or showed intermediate susceptibility to vancomycin. Conclusions. Our data and those of other studies, coupled with daptomycin&#146;s rapid bactericidal activity, suggest that this antimicrobial could be an alternative in the treatment of severe infections caused by multiresistant S. aureus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Picazo, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Culebras, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Fabal, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betriu, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Avial, Iciar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de este estudio ha sido analizar la evolución de la actividad de daptomicina y de otros antimicrobianos frente a Staphylococcus aureus resistente a meticilina (SARM) durante un periodo de 10 años (2001-2010), con el fin de detectar posibles cambios así como la aparición de resistencias. Métodos. Hemos incluido un total de 1.130 aislamientos de SARM procedentes de un estudio multicéntrico de vigilancia de resistencias a los antimicrobianos, estudio VIRA, en el que han participado 51 hospitales españoles a lo largo del periodo 2001- 2010. Los estudios de sensibilidad se han realizado mediante el método de microdilución en caldo según las normas descritas por el Clinical Laboratory Standards Institute. Resultados. Daptomicina ha mostrado excelente actividad frente a todos los aislados, solamente se detectó en el primer año del estudio un aislado no sensible (CMI=2 mg/L). La actividad de daptomicina ha permanecido estable a lo largo de los 10 años. Al analizar los valores de la CMI90, se observó que daptomicina presentaba una actividad de 2 a 4 veces superior a la de vancomicina, teicoplanina y linezolid. Se ha comprobado que daptomicina se mantiene activa frente a aislamientos de SARM resistentes a linezolid, a quinupristina-dalfopristina, o con sensibilidad disminuida a vancomicina. Conclusiones. Teniendo en cuenta la excelente actividad in vitro de la daptomicina observada en este estudio y en diferentes trabajos publicados, así como su potente actividad bactericida, consideramos que este antimicrobiano representa una alternativa en el tratamiento de las infecciones graves por S. aureus multirresistente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;24(2): 107-111, jun.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Staphylococcus aureus resistente a meticilina: sensibilidad a la daptomicina a lo largo de un periodo de 10 años (2001-2010)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23504^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24008^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30482^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13596^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29045^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31518^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31518^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31518^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
