<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134581</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of metabolic syndrome for the development of cardiovascular disease in a cohort of premenopausal women with systemic lupus erythematosus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Systemic Lupus Erythematosus (SLE) is a chronic autoimmune disease of unknown etiology. In lupus patients there is an increased cardiovascular risk due to an accelerated atherogenesis. Furthermore, Metabolic Syndrome (MS) adds an independent risk for developing Cardiovascular Disease (CVD) in the population. Therefore, it is important to determine whether lupus patients have an increased risk of developing Cardiovascular Disease in the presence of MS. To estimate the prognostic value of MS in the incidence of cardiovascular events in a cohort of premenopausal patients with SLE. Methodology: Cohort study in 238 patients was carried out. Clinical, biochemical, dietetic and anthropometric evaluations were performed. Patients were classified according to the prevalence of MS in 2001. There was a patient follow-up from 2001 to 2008. In 2008, after studying the records, we obtained the &#147;cases&#148; (patients with CVD) and the &#147;no cases&#148; (patients without CVD). Results: The basal prevalence of MS in the cohort was of 21.8% (ATPIII). The MS component with the highest prevalence in the population studied in 2001 was low HDL-Cholesterol (&lt;50 mg/dL) with a prevalence of 55.0%. The cumulative incidence of CVD in the group with MS was 17.3% and in the group without MS it was 7.0% with a Relative Risk (RR) of 2.48 (1.12&#150;5.46) and p &lt; 0.05. In the multivariable analysis it was noted that MS is a predictive factor of CVD. Conclusions: We observed the prognostic value of MS for an increased risk of cardiovascular damage in premenopausal patients with lupus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Villegas, Elsy Aidé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lerman-Garber, Israel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Suárez, Luis Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez González, Horacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Salinas, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa-Romero, Antonio Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El Lupus eritematoso sistémico (LES) es una enfermedad crónica, autoinmune, de etiología desconocida que afecta principalmente a mujeres en edad reproductiva. En pacientes con lupus existe un elevado riesgo cardiovascular debido a un proceso aterogénico acelerado. Aunado a esto, el síndrome metabólico (SM) representa un riesgo independiente para el desarrollo de enfermedad cardiovascular (ECV) en población general. Estimar el valor pronóstico del síndrome metabólico en la incidencia de eventos cardiovasculares en una cohorte de pacientes premenopáusicas con LEG. Metodología: Estudio de cohorte en 238 pacientes. Se realizaron evaluaciones clínicas, bioquímicas, dietéticas y antropométricas. Se clasificó a las pacientes con respecto a la presencia de síndrome metabólico en 2001. A partir del 2001 se inició seguimiento de las pacientes hasta el 2008 cuando a partir de la revisión de los expedientes se obtuvo a los &#147;casos&#148; (pacientes con enfermedad cardiovascular) y los &#147;no casos&#148; (pacientes sin enfermedad cardiovascular). Resultados: La prevalencia basal de síndrome metabólico en la cohorte fue 21.8% (ATPIII). El componente del SM con mayor prevalencia en la población estudiada en el 2001 fue el colesterol-HDL bajo (&lt;50 mg/dL) con una prevalencia de 55.0%. La incidencia acumulada de ECV en el grupo con síndrome metabólico (SM) fue de 17.3% y en el grupo sin SM fue de 7.0% con un riesgo relativo (RR) de 2.48 (1.12-5.46) y una p &lt; 0.05. En el análisis multivariado se observó que el SM es un factor predictivo de enfermedad cardiovascular. Conclusiones: El SM es un factor riesgo de daño cardiovascular en pacientes premenopáusicas con lupus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);144(7): 289-296, abr. 2015. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134581</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación del valor pronóstico del síndrome metabólico para el desarrollo de enfermedad cardiovascular en una cohorte de mujeres premenopaúsicas con lupus eritematoso sistémico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8356</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8837</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31157</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
