<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107944</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nodular pseudoangiomatous stromal hyperplasia of the breast in two adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nodular pseudoangiomatous stromal hyperplasia is a very rare benign breast lesion found in 0.4% of biopsies. It usually presents as a fast-growing palpable lesion in women between 30 and 40 years of age and is exceptionally rare in adolescents. Histological examination reveals a proliferation of stromal cells from connective tissue forming anastomosed empty pseudovascular spaces lined with myofibroblasts. We present the cases of two adolescents (13 and 18 years old) with fast-growing palpable breast nodules. Both underwent breast ultrasonography and core biopsy. The ultrasonographic findings of nodular pseudoangiomatous stromal hyperplasia were indistinguishable from those reported for juvenile fibroadenoma and for phyllodes tumor. Thus, histological study was required for the definitive diagnosis. Treatment depends on the size of the nodule. In our two patients, the lesion was surgically excised through tumorectomy and mastectomy(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos Romero, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Muñoz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raya Povedano, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hiperplasia estromal seudoangiomatosa nodular es una lesión benigna de la mama muy rara (el 0,4% de las biopsias). Se presenta como un nódulo palpable de rápido crecimiento en mujeres de entre 30 y 40 años, y es excepcional en adolescentes. Histológicamente consiste en la proliferación de las células estromales del tejido conectivo formando espacios seudovasculares vacíos anastomosados y tapizados por miofibroblastos. Presentamos el caso de 2 adolescentes (13 y 18 años) con un nódulo palpable en la mama de crecimiento rápido. En ambas se realizaron una ecografía mamaria y una biopsia con aguja gruesa. Los hallazgos ecográficos en la hiperplasia estromal seudoangiomatosa nodular fueron indistinguibles de los hallazgos descritos en el fibroadenoma juvenil y en el tumor filoides. Por lo tanto, fue necesario el estudio histológico de la lesión para obtener un diagnóstico definitivo. El tratamiento depende del tamaño del nódulo. En nuestras 2 pacientes, la lesión se extirpó quirúrgicamente mediante tumorectomía y mastectomía(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);54(6): 549-552, nov.-dic.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107944</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperplasia estromal seudoangiomatosa nodular de mama en dos adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30496^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5821</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30496^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31473^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7144^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
