<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044154</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatology of newborns of immigrants parents at Hospital Clínioc San Carlos in Madrid, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify certain perinatal features of the newborn of immigrant parents at Hospital Clínico «San Carlos» (HCSC)in arder to acquire deeper knowledge about the immigration phenomenon in Spain. Material and methods: We studied certain perinatal characteristics of 2.759 newborns of immigrant parents as compared with 3,990        Spanish children, all of them born at HCSC in the last threey ears. We analyzed: birth order, course and health care monitoring during pregnancy, length of hospital stay, length of time between sac rupture and delivery, type of birth and type of anesthesia used.        Results: More than 53% of the newborns were first born infants and 34% were second-born. Nearly 10% of the immigrant mothers underwent no monitoring during pregnancy. The average duration of the predelivery hospital stay was 30 to 36 hours, and the average length of time between sac rupture and delivery        was 5 hours. Eighteen percent of the births were cesarean.        Conclusions: The number of newborns of immigrant parents is increasing, currently accounting for almost 50% of the births at HCSC. The more we know about every factor related to this phenomenon, the better we will be able to assist the immigrant population</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso Chacón, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moro Serrano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armadá Maresca, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Ortiz, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer algunos de los aspectos perinatales de los recién nacidos hijos de inmigrantes, en el Hospital Clínico« San Carlos» de Madrid, con el fin de profundizar en el fenómeno migratorio. Material y métodos: Se analizan comparativamente los aspectos        perinatales de 2.759 hijos de inmigrantes con los de        3.990 hijos de españoles, nacidos en el hospital en los últimos tres años. Se analizan: el orden de nacimiento, el curso y control del embarazo, el tiempo de ingreso y de rotura de la bolsa anteparto, el tipo de parto y la anestesia empleada. Resultados: De los inmigrantes nacidos en este hospital, más del 53% son primogénitos, y un 34% nacidos en segundo lugar. Casi el 10% de las inmigrantes no controlan el embarazo. El tiempo medio de ingreso anteparto es de 30 a 36 horas y el de rotura de bolsa de 5 horas. El porcentaje medio de cesáreas de        estos tres últimos años ha sido de un 18%. Conclusiones: El porcentaje de recién nacidos hijos de inmigrantes va en aumento, y en este hospital se acerca actualmente al 50% de los recién nacidos. Cuanto mejor conozcamosto dos los aspectos relacionados con la inmigración, mejor podremos atender a estos pacientes en todos los aspectos, incluido el sanitario</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;64(2): 61-67, feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044154</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La perinatología del recién nacido hijo de inmigrantes en el Hospital Clínico San Carlos de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10691^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10691^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10487^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10487^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10691^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32092^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
