<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112646</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tropical endomyocardial fibrosis in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endomyocardial fibrosis is a restrictive cardiomyopathy of unknown etiology prevalent in tropical regions. It is characterized by fibrotic obliteration of the apex of one or both ventricles, which can be extended to the ventricular inlet chamber. It predominantly affects children and young adults. There is no specific treatment and usually has a poor prognosis. It is uncommon in Spain, but due to immigration, it appears to be increasing. Four cases of endomyocardial fibrosis in children diagnosed and treated in Spain are presented, as a well as a review of this disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salazar Mena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Ramón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Cunchillos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de la Calzada, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrosis endomiocárdica es una miocardiopatía restrictiva de etiología desconocida, prevalente en regiones tropicales. Se caracteriza por la obliteración fibrótica del ápex de uno o ambos ventrículos, que puede extenderse a la cámara de entrada ventricular. Afecta predominantemente a niños y adultos jóvenes. No existe un tratamiento específico y suele tener un pobre pronóstico. No es una entidad frecuente en nuestro medio pero debido a la inmigración estamos presenciando un auge de la misma. Presentamos 4 casos clínicos de fibrosis endomiocárdica en niños diagnosticados y tratados en nuestro medio, y realizamos una revisión de la misma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);78(5): 326-329, mayo 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112646</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fibrosis endomiocárdica tropical en nuestro medio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19557^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4799^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
