<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90164</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mid-aortic syndrome: case studies from a paediatric nephrology department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Mid-aortic syndrome (MAS) describes a narrowing segment of the abdominal aorta and the branches arising from there. This narrowing frequently involves the renal arteries, with the only clinical sign being arterial hypertension. Objective: To review the cases of MAS diagnosed in the Paediatric Nephrology Department of the Vall D&#146;Hebron Hospital (Barcelona). Methods and materials: A retrospective study was conducted on 5 patients aged from 8 days to 12 years old. We analysed the onset, diagnostic examinations, treatment and outcome. Results: Hypertension was the common reason behind the study. In two of the five cases, it was associated with renal failure. The definitive diagnostic was made using angiography and angio-MR, observing, in all the cases, that the renal arteries were affected (in 3 cases unilateral). The treatment was by medication in 3 cases, 1 required surgery and 1 died at 7 months. Conclusions: MAS, although uncommon, is a very important cause of AHT in infancy. Angiography is the only technique to diagnose it. It is important to rule out cerebral involvement, which could lead to a fatal outcome. Hypertension is very difficult to control through medication. Surgery is required only when the hypertension is not controllable through medication, when there is intermittent claudication, intestinal angina, and renal hypoperfusion. Ideally, it is better to opt for medication as treatment, as the narrowing is progressive up to the end of puberty, after which, the narrowing stabilizes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castellote Alonso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Rey, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enriquez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chocrón de Benzaquen, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madrid Aris, A. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El síndrome de aorta media (SAM) (o su término anglosajón, mid aortic syndrome) describe el estrechamiento segmentario de la aorta abdominal y ramas que de ella derivan. Un alto porcentaje involucrará a las arterias renales, siendo la hipertensión arterial (HTA) la manifestación clínica cardinal. Objetivo: Revisión de los casos diagnosticados de SAM del Servicio de Nefrología Pediátrica del Hospital Vall d&#146;Hebron. Materiales y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de 5 pacientes entre 8 días y 12 años. Se analiza debut, exploraciones diagnósticas, actitud terapéutica y evolución. Resultados: La hipertensión fue el motivo de estudio común. En 2 de los 5 casos se asoció a insuficiencia renal. El diagnóstico definitivo se alcanzo por arteriografía y angio-RM, observándose en todos los casos afectación de las arterias renales (en 3 casos unilateral). El tratamiento fue conservador en 3 casos, 1 caso requirió tratamiento quirúrgico y otro fallece a los 7 meses. Conclusiones: El SAM, aunque poco frecuente, constituye una causa importante de HTA en la infancia. La técnica diagnóstica de elección es la arteriografía. Es importante descartarla posible afectación cerebral ya que condiciona el pronóstico vital. La hipertensión es de difícil manejo médico. Son indicaciones de tratamiento quirúrgico HTA refractaria a tratamiento médico, claudicación intermitente, angina intestinal y compromiso renal por hipoperfusión. De lo contario, se optará siempre por tratamiento médico ya que la lesión es progresiva durante la infancia y tiende a estabilizarse en la pubertad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);75(1): 33-39, jul. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90164</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de aorta media</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52634^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1023^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30921^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
