<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74260</identifier>
<setSpec>0558-6291</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of online teaching tools facilitate the incorporation of methods in self-learning which could provide a good instrument for teaching support and even help in common training activities in an international context. Based on this philosophy and with a view to encouraging convergence in teaching tools and methods in Occupational and Legal Medicine, an initiative was set up within the Master Classes of Legal and Forensic Medicine at Saragossa University, par of the EU funded NetWorm project, with has been led since 1999 by Lud wigMaximilians-Universität in Munich (Germany). This project has proven to be highly efficient in permitting the creation and validation of casus in Occupational Legal Medicine programme imparted to students in the Medicine degree(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Radon, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reichert, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Jarreta, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kolb, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casalod, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso de métodos de aprendizaje online facilita la incorporación de métodos de auto-aprendizaje que pueden ser un buen instrumento de apoyo para la enseñanza en un contexto internacional. Con esta filosofía y con la vista puesta en el compromiso de convergencia en métodos de aprendizaje en Medicina del Trabajo y en Medicina Legal, se pues en marcha una iniciativa desde la Cátedra de Me3dicina Legal y Forense de la Universidad de Zaragoza, como parte del Proyecto NetWorm de la Unión Europea, liderado desde 1999 por la Universidad Ludwig-Maximilians de Múnich (Alemania)  Este proyecto ha resultado ser de una gran eficiencia, permitiendo la creación y validación de casos en Medicina Legal y del Trabajo en el programa de la Licenciatura en Medicina(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. Fac. Med. Zaragoza;48(1): 21-24, mar. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74260</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aprendizaje, mediante casos prácticos online en Medicina del Trabajo. Experiencia de la Universidad de Zaragoza en el proyecto Europeo NetWorm</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
