<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92652</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">National Consensus Document by GESIDA/National Aids Plan on Antiretroviral Treatment in Adults Infected by the Human Immunodeficiency Virus (January 2011 Update)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The update of these adult antiretroviral treatment (cART) recommendations has been carried out by consensusof a panel consisting of members of the Grupo de Estudio de Sida (Gesida, AIDS Study Group) andthe Plan Nacional sobre el Sida (PNS, Spanish AIDS Plan) who have reviewed the antiretroviral efficacyand safety advances in clinical trials, cohort and pharmacokinetic studies published in medical journals(PubMed and Embase), or presented in medical scientific meetings. Three levels of evidence were definedaccording to the data source: randomized studies (level A), cohort or case-control studies (level B),and expert opinion (level C). The decision to recommend, consider or not to recommend antiretroviraltreatment (ART) was established by consensus in each situation. The current treatment of choice for HIVinfection is the combination of three drugs. Combined ART is recommended in patients with symptomaticHIV infection, and guidelines on this treatment in patients with an opportunistic type C infection areincluded. In asymptomatic patients, initiation of ART is recommended on the basis of CD4 lymphocytecounts, plasma viral load and patient co-morbidities, as follows: a) therapy should be started in patientswith CD4 counts &lt;350 cells/ L; b) Therapy should be recommended when CD4 counts are between350 and 500 cells/ L, except when CD4 are stabilized, there is low plasma viral load, or the patient  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Panel de expertos de Gesida y Plan Nacional sobre el Sida</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La actualización de estas recomendaciones de tratamiento antirretroviral del adulto se han consensuado por un panel de expertos del Grupo de Estudio de Sida y del Plan Nacional sobre el Sida. Para ello se han revisado los resultados de eficacia y seguridad de ensayos clínicos, estudios de cohortes y de farmacocinética publicados en revistas biomédicas (localizadas mediante los buscadores PubMed y Embase) o presentados en congresos. Se han definido tres niveles de evidencia según la procedencia de los datos: estudios aleatorizados (nivel A), de cohortes o de caso-control (nivel B) u opinión de expertos (nivel C). En cada una de las situaciones se ha establecido recomendar, considerar o no recomendar el tratamiento antirretrovir&lt;l (TAR). El TAR se basa en combinaciones de tres fármacos y constituye el tratamiento de inicio de elección de la infección crónica por el VIH. Se recomienda iniciar el TAR en los pacientes con infección por VIH sintomática. Se incluyen directrices sobre el inicio de los enfermos con un evento infeccioso tipo C. En los (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;29(3): 209.e1-209.e103, mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92652</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Documento de consenso de GESIDA/ Plan Nacional sobre el Sida respecto al tratamiento antirretroviral en adultos infectados por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (actualización enero 2011)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33075^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
