<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105577</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Facebook pages for the broadcasting of media on evidenced-based nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the change that the Internet suffered earlier this century evolving into Web 2.0, a change in the model of how to manage information has been generated. This fact has not been indifferent to nurses, who are learning how to use 2.0 tools, among other motivations, for the benefit of scientific broadcasting. In turn, social networks have taken on a role such that the combination of social networks and 2.0 tools are the current scenario of the social web. Facebook and its Fan Pages are part of the social web and can be used by science for promoting the communication of information. This descriptive study shows the spreading of the contents of the blog called "Evidence-Based Nursing" through its Facebook page, which has a rapid and cross-cultural range. This describes the social context of Web 2.0 in the service of science (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cornejo Marroquín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santillán García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ausín Lomas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde el cambio que Internet sufrió a principios de este siglo evolucionando hacia la Web 2.0 se ha generado un cambio de paradigma en la manera de gestionar la información. Este hecho no le ha sido indiferente a la enfermería, que está aprendiendo a utilizar las herramientas 2.0 entre otras motivaciones, en beneficio de su difusión científica. A su vez, las redes sociales han cobrado un protagonismo tal que la combinación de redes sociales y herramientas 2.0 forman el escenario actual de la web social. Facebook y sus FanPages forman parte de esta web social y pueden estar al servicio de la ciencia fomentando la difusión de la información y la comunicación. En este estudio descriptivo se muestra la difusión de los contenidos del blog &#147;Enfermería Basada en la Evidencia&#148; a través de la FanPage de su perfil público en Facebook, que ha tenido un alcance rápido y transcultural. Esto nos describe el marco social de la web 2.0 al servicio de la ciencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;11(28): 74-81, oct. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las Fan Page de Facebook como medio de difusión de la Enfermería Basada en la Evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53368^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37606^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4096</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
