<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036373</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9744</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personality and conflict in aged people through the drawing of the river and their writing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article, we propose the Test of the river as a useful tool to study the Profile of the Personality. We suggest an explicit methodology to interpret the proofs, as well as the necessary bibliography. As a practical application, it is expounded a complete analysis made with a group of people, men and women, members of the Aula de Mayores Ciudad de Granada. In this work are described the variables and items more highly relevant on a percentege basis, as well as the most detalled psychological contents in order to interpret, comparatively, the resultant &#147;profile&#148; between men and women. We also add the complement results obtained from a Graphopsycological study, in which are emphasizad, following the same methodology, the common and the divergent characteristics among the aged people tested; finally, we conclude with a convergent study between both methods used</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cid Rodríguez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbano Velasco, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo se propone el Test del río como    un instrumento útil para el estudio del Perfil    de la Personalidad. Para la interpretación de la    prueba se indica una metodología explícita a seguir,    así como la bibliografía necesaria. Como    aplicación práctica se expone el análisis de un    grupo de personas, hombres y mujeres, pertenecientes    al Aula de Mayores Ciudad de Granada.    En el trabajo se describen las variables e ítems    más elevados porcentualmente, así como se detallan    los contenidos psicológicos para interpretar    comparativamente el &#147;perfil&#148; resultante entre    hombres y mujeres. Complementa el informe los    resultados obtenidos con una prueba grafopsicológica    en la que se destacan, siguiendo la misma    metodología, los rasgos comunes y divergentes    entre las personas mayores examinadas, para    terminar haciendo un estudio convergente entre    ambas técnicas utilizadas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Geriátrika (Madr.);21(1): 23-33, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036373</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Personalidad y conflictos en las personas mayores a través del dibujo del &#147;Río&#148; y de su escritura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
