<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055894</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benign paroxysmal vertigo of childhood: categorization and comparison with benign positional paroxysmal vertigo in adult</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The differential diagnosis of vertigo in children is extensive. This implies an additional difficulty in diagnosing dizziness in paediatric population.         Patients and method: Twenty-three children consecutively examined for paroxysmal attacks of dizziness and/or vertigo attacks entered our study, and were compared to a 15 adults group with benign positional paroxysmal vertigo. Fifteen healthy paediatric subjects and 18 adults were selected as control groups. The clinical characteristics of vertigo, presence of triggering factors, family history of migraine, presence of motion sickness, migraine, and other accompanying symptoms were considered. Neurological, vestibular, and auditory functions were assessed including the performance of a posturography in every group of patients.         Results: The presence of migraine, physical activity prior to vertigo, and positional trigger of vertigo were the clinical elements which differentiated both populations of patients with vertigo. There were significant differences in adult posturography between vertigo and control groups. In paediatric population, there were no differences between vertigo and control group in the posturography study.         Conclusions: The benign paroxysmal vertigo of childhood complex is the most frequent aetiology of paediatric dizziness. The duration and triggers of vertigo in children are quite similar to those found in VPPB adults. The instability posterior to vertigo, measured by posturography, were less intense in children than in adult population</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Sanz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barona de Guzmán, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los síntomas vestibulares en la población pediátrica son una queja poco habitual. Esto, unido a la amplia variedad de cuadros clínicos y a las dificultades diagnósticas, hace que el manejo correcto sea más complejo de lo normal.         Pacientes y método: Presentamos 23 casos de pacientes pediátricos consecutivos con síntomas de vértigo y/o desequilibrio. Del mismo modo, presentamos otro grupo de 15 pacientes adultos con vértigo posicional paroxístico benigno. Como grupo control se escogieron dos muestras de sujetos sanos, de los que se incluyó a 15 sujetos en edad pediátrica y 18 sujetos adultos. A todos los pacientes se les realizó una anamnesis completa y exploración otoneurológica en el momento de la consulta. Las exploraciones complementarias realizadas fueron audiometría, videonistagmografía y posturografía con estimulación optocinética.         Resultados: La migraña, la actividad física previa al vértigo y el desencadenante posicional del vértigo fueron los elementos diferenciadores de las dos poblaciones. Las posturografía realizada en el grupo de adultos con vértigo difería significativamente de la realizada en su grupo control, a diferencia de la población pediátrica, en la que no hubo diferencias entre el estudio de las poblaciones control y patológicas.         Conclusiones: El vértigo paroxístico de la infancia es la entidad clínica más frecuentemente hallada en la población pediátrica. La duración y sus desecadenantes son muy similares al vértigo paroxístico benigno. La inestabilidad posterior al vértigo fue menor en la población pediátrica, así como el cortejo vegetativo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(7): 296-301, ago.-sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vértigo paroxístico benigno infantil: categorización y comparación con el vértigo posicional paroxístico benigno del adulto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
