<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86885</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Textual pragmatics in adolescents with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: argument</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Clinical linguistics involves a study of linguistic deficits which focuses on a series of aspects that range from strictly formal, grammatical points to the effective and contextualised use of language. Thus, it is also inevitably concerned with the cognitive, i.e. mental, correlate of such language use, whose basic textual dimensions are narration and argument. Aims. To describe the argumentative skills in adolescents with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and to examine  their relationship with academic achievement and sociability. Materials and methods. We analysed 79 argumentative texts written by adolescents with ADHD, using a methodology from cognitive linguistics and from theories of argumentation with a dialogical foundation. Results and conclusions. Adolescents with ADHD provided a greater number of arguments than those in the control  group, but with a higher predominance of emotional and negative sanction strategies compared with a greater use of fallacious or circular arguments in those in the control group; the difference between the use of rational arguments in the two groups is not significant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Campos, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno Martinez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo Paúls, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La lingüística clínica asume un estudio del déficit lingüístico cuyo foco de atención se desplaza desde los aspectos estrictamente formales, gramaticales, al uso eficaz y contextualizado del lenguaje. En este sentido, resulta también inevitable la preocupación por el correlato cognitivo, mental, de dicho uso lingüístico, cuyas dimensiones textuales básicas son la narración y la argumentación. Objetivo. Descripción de las habilidades argumentativas en adolescentes con trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad  (TDAH), atendiendo a su relación con el rendimiento académico y la sociabilidad. Materiales y métodos. Analizamos 79 textos argumentativos de adolescentes con TDAH, con una metodología propia de la lingüística cognitiva y de las teorías de la argumentación de base dialógica. Resultados y conclusiones. Los adolescentes con TDAH proporcionan mayor número de argumentos que los del grupo control, pero con un mayor predominio de estrategias emocionales y de sanción negativa, frente a un mayor uso de argumentos  falaces o circulares en los del grupo control; no es significativa la diferencia en el uso de argumentos racionales en ambos grupos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(supl.3): s113-s117, mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86885</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pragmática textual en adolescentes con trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad: argumentación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13443</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37586</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
