<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121035</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type II A: Early neurological and skeletal findings</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies are genetic disorders characterized by the loss of sensation including pain, tactile and temperature. Its clinical and molecular features vary widely; the symptoms may begin from birth or be noticed in the first or second decade, with different types of complications of trauma to the extremities such as ulcers, mutilations and acral amputations. They are classified into six groups from I to VI, determined by the abnormality in eleven genes leading to phenotypic variations in the age of onset and the presence or absence of dysautonomia signs. With the exception of type I, all are autosomal recessive. The type II of these neuropathies is characterized by insensitivity to pain, heat and proprioception. We describe three members of a Mexican family with WNK1 gene mutation that caused hereditary neuropathy IIA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esmer, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo Oro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Díaz, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Huerta, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Covarrubias, S. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Zambrano, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las neuropatías sensitivas autonómicas son parte de las neuropatías periféricas y se deben a disfunción de genes involucrados en el funcionamiento de las neuronas sensoriales y autonómicas. Se conocen 6 variantes clínicas con subtipos determinados por anormalidad en 11 genes, los diferentes fenotipos varían en la edad de inicio, presencia de disautonomías y patrón de herencia, que con excepción del tipo i son autosómicas recesivas. La neuropatía sensitiva autonómica tipo II se caracteriza por déficit de la sensibilidad al dolor, temperatura y propiocepción. Puede manifestarse al nacer o iniciar entre los 10 y 20 años de edad con úlceras, mutilaciones y amputaciones acrales. En el presente estudio se describe a 3 miembros de una familia con mutación en el gen WNK1 causante de la forma IIA de esta neuropatía hereditaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);80(4): 254-258, abr. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuropatía sensitiva autonómica hereditaria tipo IIA: manifestaciones neurológicas y esqueléticas tempranas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23777^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31887^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
