<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166224</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of currently available drug-eluting stents. Future developments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Metallic stents were developed to minimize the elastic recoil, acute complications, and restenosis that occur with balloon angioplasty. However, they also led to the new problem of in-stent restenosis, which is associated with a number of factors, including some that can not be modified, such as the patient&#146;s clinical characteristics and the type of lesion. Nevertheless, stent implantation techniques and, most importantly, stent design have undergone an enormous transformation, which has led to the new era of coated stents and drug-eluting stents, or, in the terminology that best defines them, active stents. These new stents are very sophisticated devices, which involve innovative stent technology and design, and research and development into polymer coatings for drug storage and release and into the drugs for inhibiting intimal thickening themselves. Although first-generation drug-eluting stents, which have already been followed up clinically for 5 years, have resulted in significant and sustained improvements in the rates of restenosis and revascularization compared with bare metal stents, they have also been found to have weaknesses and disadvantages that will have to be corrected in future generations of drug-eluting stents. This review contains a detailed description of the importance of stent design, involves a brief exploration of the world of polymers and how they function, and surveys the different drugs used in drugeluting stents. It also summarizes the characteristics of and clinical and angiographic data on the drug-eluting stents that are either currently available or being investigated in clinical trails, and provides a glimpse of future developments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miranda-Guardiola, Faustino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Venegas-Aravena, Reinaldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra-Peñaranda, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los stents metálicos se desarrollaron para combatir el retroceso elástico, las complicaciones agudas y la reestenosis de la angioplastia con balón, pero crearon una nueva entidad, la restenosis intra-stent, ligada a múltiples factores. Entre ellos, las características clínicas del paciente y el tipo de lesión son inmodificables. Sin embargo, la técnica de implante y, muy particularmente, el diseño del stent han experimentado una gran transformación que ha desembocado en la nueva era de los stents recubiertos, stents liberadores de fármacos o el término que mejor los define, stents farmacoactivos. Estos nuevos stents son dispositivos muy complejos que involucran tecnología y diseño de la plataforma o stent, investigación y desarrollo en el terreno de los polímeros que actuan como transportadores y liberadores de los fármacos, y el propio fármaco que debe inhibir la proliferación neointimal. Si bien los primeros diseños, con 5 años de seguimiento clínico a sus espaldas, han mostrado una reducción significativa y sostenida de la reestenosis y las nuevas revascularizaciones frente a los stents metálicos convencionales, también han mostrado debilidades y sombras, que deben irse corrrigiendo en las próximas generaciones de stents farmacoactivos. En esta revisión se lleva a cabo un análisis detallado de la importancia del diseño del stent, se hace una incursión breve en el mundo de los polímeros, sus tipos y su funcionamiento, y se describen los fármacos empleados en los stents farmacoactivos. Se analizan las características y los resultados clínicos y angiográficos de los stents actualmente disponibles o en fase de estudio, y se abre una ventana hacia los futuros desarrollos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);7(supl.E): 8e-28e, 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis y características de los stents farmacoactivos disponibles en la actualidad. Futuros desarrollos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55896^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33809^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30485^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11545^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
