<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134315</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Arginine, nitric oxide and endothelial function</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Arginine is a semi-essential amino acid with major physiological functions. One of the most outstanding of such is its role as an amino acid precursor of nitric oxide, a molecule produced, in many tissues, from arginine by the nitric oxide synthase enzyme. Within the vascular endothelium, nitric oxide behaves as a vasodilator, antiatherogenic, and anti-plaque aggregation agent. The detailed study of this enzymatic reaction indicates that nitric oxide synthase presents high affinity, aggregation agent. The detailed study of this enzymatic reaction indicates that nitric oxide synthase presents high affinity, for its substrate, arginine, which is found in high concentrations in the endothelium. Consequently, it is surprising that for its substrate, arginine, which is found in high concentrations in the endothelium. Consequently, it is surprising that the functionality of this enzyme is conditioned by variations in concentrations of arginine, produced by nutritional intake. the functionality of this enzyme is conditioned by variations in concentrations of arginine, produced by nutritional intake. This is known as «the arginine paradox». However, the existence of an endogenous nitric oxide synthase inhibitor, This is known as «the arginine paradox». However, the existence of an endogenous nitric oxide synthase inhibitor, known as asymmetric dimethylarginine, has been recently demonstrated. This compound would decrease the formation of nitric oxide through competitive inhibition with the natural substrate, arginine. It is for this reason that dietary supplementation with arginine would be important as a means to counteracting such an effect. In addition to arginine, supplementation with (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez de Medina, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Augustin,  O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La arginina es un aminoácido semiesencial con importantes funciones fisiológicas. Entre ellas destaca su papel como precursora del óxido nítrico, una molécula producida a partir de la arginina por la enzima óxido nítrico sintasa en muchos tejidos y que en el endotelio vascular se comporta como vasodilatadora, antiaterogénica y antiagregante plaquetaria. El estudio detallado de esta reacción enzimática indica que la óxido nítrico sintasa tiene una gran afinidad por su sustrato, la arginina, que se encuentra en concentraciones altas en el endotelio. Por tanto, resultaba sorprendente que el funcionamiento de esta enzima estuviera condicionado por las variaciones en las concentraciones de arginina debidas al aporte nutricional. A esto se le llamó «paradoja de la arginina». Sin embargo, se ha demostrado recientemente la existencia de un inhibidor endógeno de la óxido nítrico sintasa denominado dimetilarginina asimétrica. Este compuesto disminuiría la formación del óxido nítrico por inhibición competitiva con el sustrato natural, la arginina. De ahí la importancia de la suplementación con arginina para contrarrestar este efecto. Además de la arginina, existen otros componentes de la dieta que pueden influir también en la síntesis de óxido nítrico por el endotelio vascular. el endotelio vascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;45(4): 303-317, 2004.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Arginina, óxido nítrico y función endotelial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9753^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1123^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32663^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22891^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23103^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
