<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046723</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Structural changes of the anterior chamber angle in primary congenital glaucoma with respect to normal development</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To compare findings of normal angles ;;with those from primary congenital glaucoma in ;;order to clarify the pathogenic mechanisms of the ;;disease and to explain the success of surgical treatment ;;in some of these patients. ;;Methods: Adult normal eyes from cadavers and ;;fragments of surgical trabeculectomies from ;;patients with primary congenital glaucoma previously ;;treated with goniotomy were studied. Eyes ;;were processed for examination using light microscopy ;;and scanning electron microscopy techniques. ;;Results: The following was evident in congenital ;;glaucoma: 1) high iris insertion; 2) no observable pretrabecular ;;membrane, but enlarged trabeculae with ;;diminished inter-trabecular spaces; 3) Schlemm&#146;s ;;canal (SC) apparently normal, with vacuoles in the ;;wall indicating normal functioning; 4) sectioning of ;;the abnormal trabecular tissue during goniotomy allowed ;;repositioning of the angle structures and hence ;;the appearance of the angular recess. Conclusions: Anomalies of the trabecular structures ;;in primary congenital glaucoma do not always ;;parallel an abnormal development of the SC and the ;;collector channels. This fact could explain the success ;;of goniotomy in this type of glaucoma</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Triviño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De-Hoz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar los hallazgos morfológicosobservados en ángulos normales con los observadosen ángulos de pacientes con glaucoma congénitoprimario, para intentar clarificar los mecanismospatogénicos de esta enfermedad, así como explicarel éxito del tratamiento quirúrgico en alguno deestos pacientes.Métodos: Se utilizaron ojos adultos normales procedentesde cadáveres y fragmentos quirúrgicosprocedentes de trabeculectomías, de pacientes conglaucoma congénito primario que habían sido tratadospreviamente con una goniotomía. Los tejidosfueron procesados para su examen a microscopíaóptica (MO) y microscopía electrónica de barrido(MEB).Resultados: En los glaucomas congénitos encontramos:1) inserción alta del iris; 2) No se observauna membrana pre-trabecular, sino que comparandocon los ángulos normales las trabéculas aparecenensanchadas con disminución de los espacios intertrabeculares; 3) el canal de Schlemm (CS) es aparentementenormal, con vacuolas en su pared queindican un funcionamiento normal del mismo; 4) lasección del tejido trabecular anormal que producela goniotomía, permite el reposicionamiento de lasestructuras del ángulo y por tanto la aparición delreceso angular.Conclusiones: En el glaucoma congénito primariolas anomalías de las estructuras trabeculares nosiempre se acompañan de un desarrollo anómalodel CS y de los canales colectores. Este hechopodría explicar que la goniotomía sea un tratamientocon éxito en estos glaucomas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;81(2): 65-71, feb. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046723</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios estructurales del ángulo de la cámara anterior en el glaucoma congénito. Comparación con el desarrollo normal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d881^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14522^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
