<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153702</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of clinical prediction criteria and rapid antigen detection testing for the management of acute pharyngitis in an emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To validate the modified CENTOR score (m-CENTOR) and the rapid antigen detection testing for group A streptococcus (GAS) in acute pharyngitis. Design: Diagnostic test validation study. Location and Participants: 101 eligible patients, who consulted at the emergency department in a third level Hospital with a clinical picture compatible with acute pharyngitis. Main measures: Pharyngeal swabs were obtained for culture and rapid antigen detection testing for group A Streptococcus (FAMR). CENTOR score was calculated for each case. Results: The average age of the patients included in the study was 22.6 years (SD: 13.8). The gender distribution was 48.5% males. The group A Streptococcus (GAS) was the pathogen isolated in the 20.79% of the cases. The m-CENTOR presented a sensibility of 83.3 %(50.9%-97.1%), specificity 45.5% (30.7%-61.0%), positive predictive value (PPV) of 29.4% (15.7%-47.7%) and negative predictive value (NPV) 90.9% (69.4%-98.4%). The FAMR presented a sensibility of 81.5% (61.3%-93.0%), specificity 98.6% (91.4%-99.9%)  PPV 95.7% (76.0%-99.8%)  and NPV 93.3% (84.5%-97.5%). 49.5% of the patients received antibiotics based on medical judgment, which resulted in a 62% increase in antimicrobial indication. Conclusions: The m-CENTOR score evidenced an accurate negative predictive value, and the FAMR presented good sensibility, specificity and positive predictive value for pharyngitis caused by GAS. The use of both methods in emergency care could optimize the management of the pathology and improve antibiotic adequacy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Kilstein, Jorge G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quaglino, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Imbert Tibaudin, Denise</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Validar los criterios de CENTOR modificados (CENTOR-m) y los tests rápidos de detección del antígeno de Estreptococo del Grupo A (SGA) en la faringitis aguda. Diseño: Estudio de validación de pruebas diagnósticas. Emplazamiento y participantes: Ciento un pacientes elegibles, que consultaron al departamento de urgencias de un hospital de tercer nivel con cuadro clínico compatible con faringitis aguda. Mediciones Principales: Se obtuvieron muestras de hisopados faríngeos para la realización del test rápido antigénico para SGA (FAMR) y para cultivo, respectivamente. Se calculó en cada caso los criterios de CENTOR-m. Resultados: La edad media de los pacientes incluidos en el estudio fue de 22,6 años (DE:13,8). El 48,5 % eran varones. El SGA fue el patógeno aislado en el 20,79 % de los casos. El CENTOR-m presentó una sensibilidad del 83,3 % (50,9 %-97,1 %), especificidad del 45,5 % (30,7 %-61,0 %) valor predictivo positivo (VPP) del 29,4 % (15,7 %-47,7 %) y valor predictivo negativo (VPN) del 90,9 % (69,4 %-98,4 %). El FAMR presento una sensibilidad del 81,5 % (61,3 %-93,0 %) especificidad del 98,6 % (91,4 %-99,9 %), VPP del 95,7 % (76,0 %-99,8 %) y VPN del 93,3 % (84,5 %-97,5 %). El 49,5 % de los pacientes recibieron antibióticos basándose en el juicio médico, lo que resultó en una proporción de sobreindicación de antimicrobianos del 62 %. Conclusiones: Los criterios de CENTOR-m demostraron adecuado valor pronóstico negativo y el FAMR  buena sensibilidad, especificidad y valor pronóstico positivo para faringitis por SGA. La utilización de ambos métodos en la atención urgente podría optimizar el manejo de la patología y la adecuación antibiótica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;9(1): 23-30, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153702</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de los criterios de predicción clínica y del test rápido antigénico para el manejo de la faringitis aguda en un servicio de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37387^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37387^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24286^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3981^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d673^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
