<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155538</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alexandrite Laser for the Treatment of Resistant and Hypertrophic Port Wine Stains: A Clinical, Histological and Histochemical Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Port wine stains (PWSs) are commonly treated by the pulsed dye laser. However, treatment of hypertrophic or resistant PWSs is a major therapeutic challenge. The long-pulsed Alexandrite laser could be a safe and effective treatment for resistant PWSs, due to an increase depth of penetration of 50&#150;75% over PDL. Objective: The aim of this study was to assess the efficacy and safety of a long-pulsed Alexandrite laser in patients with hypertrophic, dark and/or resistant PWSs. Pink pale resistant PWS were excluded from the study. Methods: Twenty-one patients (age 20&#150;75 years), phototypes I&#150;IV on the Fitzpatrick scale, with PDL dark resistant PWSs were treated with long-pulsed Alexandrite laser. We excluded high phototypes and PDL pink resistant PWSs. All patients were treated with 3 laser sessions at settings of 3-ms pulse duration, 10-mm spot, 35&#150;55J/cm2, with cooling (Dynamic Cooling Device 50ms with delay 30ms). Laser sessions were repeated approximately every 2 months. Three dermatologists evaluated treatment effectiveness by means of photographs of the patients before and after laser treatment (scale from 0 to 4). Adverse events were registered. Patient satisfaction was also assessed (scale from 0 to 10). Results: Mean global improvement was rated as 2.28. Long-lasting side effects included minimal scarring after blistering in 1 patient. Mean patient satisfaction was 8.5. Conclusions: Our study concludes that long-pulsed Alexandrite laser was effective for treatment of resistant PWSs, although the therapeutical window is narrow with this treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vañó, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Muñoz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaén, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grillo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boixeda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Las manchas en vino de oporto (MVO) son normalmente tratadas con láser de colorante pulsado. Sin embargo, el tratamiento de MVO hipertróficas o resistentes continúa siendo un importante reto terapéutico. El láser de Alejandrita de pulso largo podría ser un método seguro y eficaz para el tratamiento de estas lesiones, debido a que la profundidad que alcanza puede superar entre un 50&#150;75% al láser de colorante pulsado. Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la eficacia y la seguridad del láser de Alejandrita de pulso largo en pacientes con MVO hipertróficas y/o resistentes. Los pacientes con MVO resistentes de color rosa pálido fueron excluidos del estudio. Métodos: Veintiún pacientes (Edades entre 20&#150;75 años), fototipos I-IV en la escala Fitzpatrick, con MVO oscuras, resistentes al tratamiento con láser de colorante pulsado fueron tratados con láser de Alejandrita de pulso largo. Se excluyeron los fototipos altos y las MVO de color rosado pálido. Todos los pacientes fueron tratados con 3 sesiones de láser con los siguientes parámetros: duración de pulso de 3ms, spot de 10mm de diámetro, fluencias comprendidas entre 35 y 55J/cm2, con refrigeración (Dynamic Coolong Device). El intervalo de tiempo entre sesiones fue de 2 meses aproximadamente. Tres dermatólogos evaluaron la efectividad del tratamiento a través de las fotografías de los pacientes antes y después del tratamiento con láser (escala de 0 a 4). Se registraron los eventos adversos acontecidos. La satisfacción del paciente también se evaluó (escala de 0 a 10). Resultados: La mejoría global media fue de 2,28. Los efectos adversos duraderos fueron lesiones cicatriciales mínimas en un paciente. La satisfacción media de los pacientes fue de 8,5. Conclusiones: Nuestro estudio concluye que el láser de Alejandrita de pulso largo puede ser eficaz en el tratamiento de MVO resistentes, aunque la ventana terapéutica es estrecha con este tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;107(7): 591-596, sept. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155538</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Laser de Alejandrita para el tratamiento de malformaciones capilares tipo mancha en vino de Oporto resistentes y/o hipertróficas: estudio clínico, histológico e histoquímico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d56229</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13249^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13248^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13248^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52878^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32955^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52861^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6354^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6354^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13248^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
