<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143391</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Uroflowmetric review of pediatric distal urethroplasty</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Urethral stricture is the most common complication in hypospadias surgery. The monitoring of operated patients allows rapid detection of this complication and the uroflowmetry is the main diagnostic method. Objectives. To study of functional results in patients who underwent distal urethroplasty, using uroflowmetry. Patients and methods. A retrospective chart review was conducted of 81 patients who underwent distal hypospadias repair (7 coronal, 51subcoronal and 23 distal penile shaft) and a postoperatory uroflowmetric study. The patients were divided into two groups, in each type of hypospadias, according to the presence or absence of stenotic complications(0 coronal, 10 subcoronal and 5 distal penile shaft). The functional effects in both groups were studied. Results. All patients with stenotic complications showed maximum flow rates and mean flow rates below 15 and 20 percentiles respectively and a plateauing layout of the urinary flow curve. The treatment of these conditions resulted in the normalization of the maximum flow values (in100% of the subcoronal and 100% of the distal penile shaft hypospadias),as well as in the mean flow values (in 88% of the subcoronal and 75% ofthe distal penile shaft hypospadias). The curve also adapted a bell-shaped in 100% of the H. coronal and 50% of the H. distal penile shaft. The uroflowmetry presented a spontaneous improvement in all patients without stenotic complications but with low flows in their first uroflowmetric. Conclusions. Uroflowmetry is an objective method for the evaluation of hypospadias surgery, being easy to perform, noninvasive and reliable. Obstructed uroflow patterns point to the presence of a stenotic complication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montalvo Ávalos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Segura, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oviedo Gutiérrez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez Muñoz, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Mata, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La estenosis uretral es la complicación más frecuente de la cirugía del hipospadias. El seguimiento de los pacientes intervenidos permite su rápida detección, siendo la uroflujometría su principal método diagnóstico. Objetivos. Estudiar la repercusión funcional, mediante la uroflujometría, en pacientes intervenidos de hipospadias distal. Materiales y Métodos. Se presenta un estudio descriptivo, retrospectivo, en el que se revisaron las historias clínicas de 81 pacientes intervenidos de hipospadias distal (7 balánicos, 51 balanopeneanos y 23 peneanos anteriores) y a los que les realizaron estudios uroflujométricos. En cada tipo de hipospadias, se dividieron los pacientes en dos grupos según la presencia de complicaciones estenóticas (0 balánicos, 10 balanopeneanos y 5 peneanos anteriores) o la ausencia de estas y se estudiaron las repercusiones funcionales en ambos grupos. Resultados. Todos aquellos pacientes con complicaciones estenóticas presentaron flujos máximos y medios por debajo de los percentiles 15 y 20 respectivamente, así como un trazado de la curva anormal. El tratamiento de estas complicaciones estenóticas se tradujeron en una normalización tanto en los valores de flujo máximo (en el 100% de los hipospadias balanopeneanos y en el 100% de los hipospadias peneanos anteriores), como en los valores de flujo medio (en el 88% de los hipospadias balanopeneanos y el 75% de los hipospadias peneanos anteriores). La curva, además, adaptó un trazado en forma de campana en el 100% de los hipospadias balanopeneanos y el 50% de los hipospadias peneanos anteriores. Se detectó una mejoría uroflujométrica espontánea en aquellos pacientes que, sin complicaciones estenóticas, presentaron en su (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;28(1): 6-9, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión uroflujométrica de pacientes intervenidos de hipospadias distales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7200^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12623^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
