<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151166</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Care of the elderly in the family context. Resource assessment by discussion groups</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: in the present study several collectives with knowledge of the reality of family care of the elderly assessed several social and healthcare resources and suggested several possibilities for improvement. Method: four discussion groups were used as a data collection technique. The groups were composed of caregivers, representatives users of associations for the elderly, experts in geriatrics, and social services professionals. Results: the various discussion groups positively evaluated the Home Help Service, the Support Teams of the Home Service Programs, Interdisciplinary Community Health Workers Units, Daytime Care Centres, and the Family Rest Programme but suggested some changes to all of them. The discussion groups also indicated the need to improve the material, economic and emotional assistance given to caregivers and asked for training, institutional coordination, and dissemination of information about available resources and assistance. Conclusions: some changes are required to improve the current social and health resources available to families caring for the elderly within the family unit. Among the suggestions for improvement proposed by the participants, many are useful and could easily be applied, whereas others provide an interesting starting point for debate and reflection. Knowledge and understanding of the situation of caregiving families, based on their own experiences and those of the people who know them, is in itself sufficient to initiate and implement changes to provide resources appropriate to their needs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casas-Aznar, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aymerich-Andreu, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planes-Pedra, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gras-Pérez, María Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: en el presente artículo, colectivos vinculados a familias cuidadoras de mayores exponen la valoración que les merecen diversos recursos sociales y sanitarios de apoyo, al tiempo que apuntan propuestas para su mejora. Material y Métodos: se configuran 4 grupos de discusión formados por profesionales del ámbito de la salud expertos en geriatría, profesionales de los servicios sociales, representantes-usuarios de asociaciones de mayores y personas cuidadoras. Resultados: los participantes aprecian especialmente el servicio de ayuda a domicilio, los programas de atención domiciliaria con equipos de soporte, las unidades funcionales interdisciplinarias sociosanitarias, los centros de acogimiento diurno y el programa de descanso familiar, si bien proponen cambios en todos ellos; también solicitan mejoras concretas referidas a la necesidad de ayuda material, económica o emocional para hacer frente a la tarea cuidadora; finalmente reclaman en distinto grado formación, coordinación institucional y divulgación de la información sobre recursos y ayudas disponibles. Conclusiones: respecto al grado de adecuación de los recursos sociales y sanitarios disponibles para hacer frente al cuidado de mayores en el entorno familiar, se aprecia la necesidad de introducir algunos cambios al respecto. De las propuestas de los participantes, muchas resultan razonablemente útiles y aplicables; otras, en cambio, suponen un punto de partida para el debate y la reflexión. En cualquier caso, sólo conociendo y considerando cuáles son las limitaciones percibidas por parte de las familias cuidadoras y de quienes conocen su situación, se puede iniciar e instaurar cambios adecuados a sus necesidades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);40(supl.3): 16-23, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151166</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cuidado de los ancianos en el entorno familiar. Valoración de diversos recursos de apoyo mediante grupos de discusión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
