<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044390</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical and epidemiological study of community-acquired pneumonia in children aged less than 5 years old</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the clinical characteristics of community-acquired pneumonia and associated morbidity in children under 5 years old.                Patients and method: We performed a prospective epidemiological study in 12 primary care clinics and two pediatric emergency departments in Vizcaya, Spain. Demographic, clinical, radiological, laboratory and treatment data were recorded at diagnosis. Different pneumonia groups were established on the basis of radiological images (lobar pattern), total leucocyte count (&gt; 15.000/ml) and C-reactive protein value (&gt; 80 mg/l). These groups ranged from definitive pneumococcal pneumonia (pneumococcus isolated in usually sterile specimens) to pneumonia of probable non-pneumococcal etiology. All patients were followed-up for 7 to 15 days after diagnosis to ascertain outcome.                Results: Between February and April 2003, 412 children with pneumonia were enrolled. The mean age was 33.4 6 15.34 months and 21 % of the patients had received the pneumococcal conjugate vaccine. Overall 20 % had general malaise and 14.6 % required admission, with a mean length of hospital stay of 4.10 ± 2.21 days. The mean length of treatment was 9.51 ± 2.44 days and the mean number of visits to the primary care pediatrician was 2.02 6 1.10. Fifty-three patients (12.9 %) had definitive or highly probable pneumococcal pneumonia and these children had higher temperature (38.74 ± 0.84 vs 38.38 ± 0.94 °C), a higher percentage of general malaise (50.9 % vs 15.3 %) and a higher hospitalization rate (41.5 % vs 10.5 %).                Conclusions: Community-acquired pneumonia in children under 5 years old provokes high morbidity. According to clinical, radiological and laboratory data, suspected pneumococcal pneumonia seems more severe than forms probably caused by other agents</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Díaz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mintegi Raso, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la forma de presentación clínica y morbilidad de la neumonía adquirida en la comunidad, en niños menores de 5 años.                Pacientes y método: Estudio epidemiológico, prospectivo, realizado en 12 centros de atención primaria (CAP) de la provincia de Vizcaya, y en los Servicios de Urgencias Hospitalarias de los Hospitales de Basurto y Cruces (provincia de Vizcaya). En el momento del diagnóstico se recogieron datos demográficos, clínicos, radiológicos y analíticos y del tratamiento. Se estableció una clasificación del tipo de neumonía, desde neumocócica definitiva (aislado del microorganismo en un líquido habitualmente estéril), hasta neumonía de improbable origen neumocócico, basándose en el patrón radiológico de la neumonía (patrón lobular), el número de cifra de leucocitos (&gt; 15.000/&amp;#956;l) y el valor de la proteína C reactiva (PCR &gt; 80 mg/l). Entre los 7 y 15 días del diagnóstico se realizó un control del paciente para comprobar la evolución del proceso.                Resultados: Entre febrero y abril de 2003 se incluyeron en el estudio 412 niños con neumonía. La edad media de los pacientes fue de 33,4 ± 15,34 meses y el 21 % había recibido alguna dosis de la vacuna conjugada neumocócica. El 20 % de los niños presentaba afectación del estado general y el 14,6 % precisó hospitalización, con una estancia media de 4,10 ± 2,21 días. El promedio de visitas a su pediatra de CAP fue de 2,06 ± 1,10 y la duración media del tratamiento fue de 9,51 ± 2,44 días. Un total de 53 pacientes (12,9 %) presentaron una neumonía neumocócica definitiva o muy probable; estos niños mostraron de manera significativa mayor elevación de la temperatura (38,74 ± 0,84 °C frente a 38,38 ± 0,94 °C), un porcentaje mayor de afectación del estado general (50,9 % frente a 15,3 %) y una tasa más elevada de hospitalización (41,5 % frente a 10,5 %).                Conclusiones: La neumonía adquirida en la comunidad, en niños menores de 5 años, presenta una elevada morbilidad. Utilizando parámetros clínicos, analíticos y radiológicos, la neumonía que se sospecha de origen neumocócico, parece más grave que las de otras posibles etiologías</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(2): 131-136, ago. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044390</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio clínico y epidemiológico de la neumonía adquirida en la comunidad en niños menores de 5 años de edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
