<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040070</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8241</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">True refractory hypertension. Study of prevalence at a tertiary care clinic</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Refractory hypertension is defined as the failure to reach goal blood pressure (¾ 140/90 mmHg) in patients who are adhering to full doses of an appropriate three-drug regimen that includes a diuretic. Its prevalence among spanish patients is not well documented. The objective was to determine the true prevalence of refractory hypertension in adult patients from a university hospital hypertension clinic. Material and methods. Patients who fulfilled criteria for refractory hypertension were selected from an initial sample of 281 individuals with suspected resistant hypertension. An exhaustive study was performed on these patients in order to confirm refractory hypertension and to search for causes of secondary hypertension and contributing factors to poor response to treatment. Results. Forty two patients were selected (average age: 60 ± 9 years, 27 women, 15 men). After 3.3 ± 0.5 years of monitoring, 73.8 % of the individuals were diagnosed with secondary hypertension (sleep apnoea as the most frequent cause). Recommended treatment goals were achieved in most patients (61.9 %). Only 4.8 % of the selected patients suffered from true refractory hypertension, as they had essential hypertension and maintained high blood pressure in spite of strict treatment and monitoring. Discussion. Real prevalence of refractory hypertension is very low. An exhaustive study is needed in order to diagnose it. Causes of secondary hypertension and other contributing factors to poor response to treatment can be found in most casesIntroduction. Refractory hypertension is defined as the failure to reach goal blood pressure (¾ 140/90 mmHg) in patients who are adhering to full doses of an appropriate three-drug regimen that includes a diuretic. Its prevalence among spanish patients is not well documented. The objective was to determine the true prevalence of refractory hypertension in adult patients from a university hospital hypertension clinic. Material and methods. Patients who fulfilled criteria for refractory hypertension were selected from an initial sample of 281 individuals with suspected resistant hypertension. An exhaustive study was performed on these patients in order to confirm refractory hypertension and to search for causes of secondary hypertension and contributing factors to poor response to treatment. Results. Forty two patients were selected (average age: 60 ± 9 years, 27 women, 15 men). After 3.3 ± 0.5 years of monitoring, 73.8 % of the individuals were diagnosed with secondary hypertension (sleep apnoea as the most frequent cause). Recommended treatment goals were achieved in most patients (61.9 %). Only 4.8 % of the selected patients suffered from true refractory hypertension, as they had essential hypertension and maintained high blood pressure in spite of strict treatment and monitoring. Discussion. Real prevalence of refractory hypertension is very low. An exhaustive study is needed in order to diagnose it. Causes of secondary hypertension and other contributing factors to poor response to treatment can be found in most cases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Parrilla, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Sánchez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Guerrero, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jarast Olivari, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grilo Reina, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Beníte, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmedo Llanes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Robles, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hipertensión arterial refractaria (HTA-R) puede definirse como la falta de control de las cifras de presión arterial por debajo de 140/90 mmHg a pesar de tratamiento con una combinación adecuada de tres fármacos, siendo uno de ellos un diurético. La prevalencia de HTA-R entre los hipertensos españoles no es bien conocida. El objetivo sería estimar la prevalencia real de HTA-R en una consulta hospitalaria. Material y métodos. A partir de una población inicial de 281 pacientes remitidos por HTA resistente al tratamiento se seleccionó a aquellos individuos que cumplían criterios de HTA-R tras la primera evaluación. Se realizó un estudio exhaustivo de dichos pacientes para confirmar el diagnóstico de HTA-R, buscando causas de HTA secundaria y otros factores contribuyentes a la falta de respuesta al tratamiento. Resultados. Se seleccionó al subgrupo poblacional que cumplía criterios de HTA-R: 42 pacientes de 60 ± 9 años de edad media (27 mujeres y 15 hombres). Tras un seguimiento medio de 3,3 ± 0,5 años, el 73,8 % de los individuos presentaba HTA secundaria, siendo el síndrome de apnea obstructiva del sueño la causa más frecuente. Se obtuvo un control adecuado de la presión arterial en la mayoría de los casos (61,9 %). Sólo en el 4,8 % del subgrupo de 42 pacientes existía HTA-R verdadera, al presentar HTA esencial y mantener cifras elevadas de presión arterial, a pesar del estricto seguimiento y tratamiento. Discusión. La prevalencia real de HTA-R es muy baja, siendo necesario realizar un estudio exhaustivo de los pacientes. En la gran mayoría de los casos se encuentran causas secundarias de HTA y factores contribuyentes a la aparente refractariedad al tratamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Hipertensión (Madr., Ed. impr.);22(5): 189-194, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040070</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipertensión arterial refractaria verdadera. Estudio de prevalencia en una consulta hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4294^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22164</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
