<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138593</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Injuries epidemiology sustained by players during the soccer XXVII South American U-20 championship</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To account the injuries that occurred in the XXVII South American soccer championship U-20. Material and method: Observational surveys submitted by the medical services of all participating teams in the championship. They were young players, all of them under the age of 20. Surveys with parts of incidents were collected and analyzed by the Medical Commission of Conmebol. Results: A total of 109 injuries were registred, 44 of them were caused by contact between players; 18 were the occasion of fouls but 39% of the injuries were not sanctioned by the referees. Of the total, 59 injuries required medical treatment, finding an average of 3.11 injuries per match. The cause of the injuries were, in descending order, 35 bruises, 34 muscle injuries, 10 muscle strains, 9 ankle sprains and 4 concussion without loss of consciousness. The most serious were two fractures and a torn ACL without joint instability. Conclusion: A football World Cup has a high number of injuries, most of them contacts, many of which remain unpunished by the referee's decisions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pangrazio, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forriol, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Contabilizar las lesiones que se produjeron en el XXVII campeonato sudamericano de fútbol sub-20. Material y método: Estudio observacional de las encuestas enviadas por los servicios médicos de todos los equipos participantes en el campeonato. Eran jugadores jóvenes, todos ellos por debajo de los 20 años. Las encuestas con los partes de incidencias fueron recogidas y analizadas por la Comisión Médica de la Conmebol. Resultados: Se recogieron un total de 109 lesiones, de las cuales 44 se produjeron por contacto entre los jugadores y 18 fueron causadas por faltas sancionadas, aunque un 39% de las lesiones no fueron sancionadas por los árbitros. Del total de lesiones, 59 requirieron tratamiento médico, encontrando un promedio de 3,11 lesiones por partido. La causa de las lesiones fueron, por orden decreciente, 35 contusiones, 34 lesiones musculares sin interrecurrencias, 10 distensiones musculares, 9 esguinces de tobillo y 4 concusiones sin pérdida de conocimiento. Las más graves fueron dos fracturas y una rotura del LCA sin inestabilidad articular. Conclusión: Un campeonato mundial de fútbol presenta un número elevado de lesiones, la mayoría por contacto, muchas de las cuales quedan sin sancionar por el árbitro de la contienda (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);26(1): 11-20, ene.-mar. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138593</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de las lesiones sufridas por los jugadores durante el XXVII campeonato sudamericano de fútbol sub-20</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7893^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
