<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77617</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New therapeutic options for the treatment of multiresistant bacteria in the ICU</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The number of new antimicrobial drugs in the healthcare clinical practice has decreased gradually and significantlyin the last 15 years. At the same time, there hasbeen an increase in the appearance of microorganisms withresistance to conventional antibiotics, above all in intensivecare units (ICU). Within this group, Methicillin-resistantStaphylococcus aureus (MSRA) and methicillin-resistant coagulase-negative staphylococci, vancomycin-resistant enterococci,Pseudomonas aeruginosa and Acinetobacter baumaniiresistant to carbapenemics and extended-spectrumß-lactamase-producing (ESBL) Enterobacteria are themost important. These pathogens are frequently also resistantto other groups of antibiotics such as aminoglycosides,fluoroquinolones and macrolides. New recentlyintroduced antimicrobial agents are available to combatthese resistances. These are active mainly against grampositive bacteria resistant strains and in a more timelyway against gram negative ones or both. Among the firstgroup, the following stand out: daptomycin (a lipopeptidebactericide for parenteral use) and linezolid (oxazolidinonewith bacteriostatic activity for parenteral andoral use). On its part, ertapenem (a carbapenem parenteralbactericide) and tigecyclin (a parenteral bacteriostatictetracycline) are active against ESBL enterobacteria, thelatter also being active against non-fermented gram positivesand gram negatives, except for P. aeruginosa.Possibly, the introduction of these new compounds andother futures ones pending introduction will not onlyimprove antimicrobial diversification but also serve tolimit the spreading of these microorganisms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vallverdú Vidal, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellana Perelló, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barcenilla Gaite, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jover Sáenz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El número de nuevos antimicrobianos en la clínica asistencialha descendido de forma gradual y significativa enlos últimos 15 años. Paralelamente se ha producido un incrementoen la aparición de microorganismos con resistenciaa los antibióticos convencionales, sobre todo en las Unidadesde Cuidados Intensivos (UCI). Dentro de este grupo, laresistencia a la meticilina de Staphylococcus aureus (SARM) yde estafilococos coagulasa negativos resistentes a la meticilina,enterococos resistentes a la vancomicina, Pseudomonasaeruginosa y Acinetobacter baumannii resistentes a carbapenémicosy Enterobacterias productoras de betalactamasasde espectro extendido (BLEE) son las más destacables. Estospatógenos con frecuencia son además resistentes a otrosgrupos de antibióticos, como aminoglucósidos, fluorquinolonasy macrólidos. Para hacer frente a estas resistenciasdisponemos de nuevos antimicrobianos de reciente introducción.Éstos son activos principalmente frente a cepas resistentesde bacterias grampositivas, y de manera más puntualfrente a gramnegativos o a ambos. Entre los primerosdestacan: daptomicina (lipopéptido bactericida de uso parenteral)y linezolid (oxazolidinona bacteriostática de usoparenteral y oral). Por su parte, el ertapenem (carbapenembactericida parenteral) y la tigeciclina (tetraciclina bacteriostáticaparenteral) son activos frente a enterobacterias BLEE,siendo esta última además activa frente a grampositivos ygramnegativos no fermentadores, excepto P. aeruginosa. Posiblementela introducción de estos nuevos compuestos yotros futuros pendientes salir, aparte de mejorar la diversificaciónantimicrobiana, sirva para limitar la dispersión de estosmicroorganismos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;21(extr.1): 9-13, jul. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77617</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas opciones terapéuticas para el tratamiento de las bacterias multirresistentes en Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31518^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31518^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31518^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22165^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
