<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043629</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Educating and informing patients in ambulatory surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The benefits of ambulatory surgery are recovery in a familiar environment and independance    in their care. Information and healthcare education    are essential to patient's autonomy and    active responsable postoperative recovery.    Information given by the surgeon and the    anesthesiologist regarding prognosis, surgical    and anesthetic procedures as well as alternative    care is the first step in this educating process. Nevertheless, nursing care is essential in completing this information, as the nurses give emotional support and healthcare education for self care so that the patient can take on responsability  in helping his recovery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pueyo González, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Ferreiro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cereijo Garea, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La cirugía ambulatoria facilita al paciente los  beneficios que proporcionan la recuperación en    el ámbito familiar y la independencia para realizar  sus cuidados. Para potenciar la autonomía    del paciente y que éste se implique de una manera  activa y responsable en su recuperación    postoperatoria son claves la información y la  educación para la salud. La información que proporcionan el cirujano  y anestesiólogo acerca del pronóstico, procedimiento    quirúrgico-anestésico y alternativas asistenciales  constituyen el primer paso del proceso    educativo. No obstante, resulta imprescindible la   atención de enfermería al complementar la información,    proporcionar apoyo emocional e impartir educación para el autocuidado que capacite  al paciente para asumir responsabilidades  que mejoren la recuperación de su salud  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;10(4): 165-174, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043629</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Información y educación del paciente en cirugía ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3243^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10538^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
