<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100239</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A mortal cause of syncope</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anaphylaxis is a generalized reaction produced by the massive release of mediators from mast cells, is rapid in onset and may cause death. The diagnosis is clinical, and the initial symptoms often overlap with those of many other disorders such as, vasovagal reactions, anxiety or asthma, and is often underdiagnosed. A high index of suspicion is necessary for the diagnosis. We report the case of a young woman who presented with syncope in a Primary Care Centre. In spite of the absence of skin lesions, we suspected an anaphylaxis because of the refractory low blood pressure. Thus treatment was started she was transferred to the Hospital. In the Emergency Department, the elevated serum tryptase levels supported our diagnosis. The absence of a clear exposure to a known allergen lead us to suspect a hydatid cysts rupture. The abdominal ultrasound and CT scan confirmed this (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monzón-Ballarín, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo-Díaz de Cerio, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artigas-Montañés, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz-Abad, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anafilaxia es una reacción generalizada debida a la liberación masiva de mediadores de mastocitos y otras células inflamatorias que se instaura rápidamente y puede causar la muerte. Su diagnóstico es clínico y en ocasiones los síntomas con que se presenta pueden simular enfermedades más leves como cuadros vasovagales, ansiedad o asma, por lo que a menudo resulta infradiagnosticada. Es necesario un alto índice de sospecha para su diagnóstico. Presentamos el caso de una mujer joven que acude por síncope al centro de atención primaria. A pesar de la ausencia de lesiones cutáneas, la hipotensión mantenida nos hizo sospechar una anafilaxia, permitiendo la administración precoz de tratamiento y derivación urgente al hospital. en urgencias, nuestra hipótesis se vio reforzada al hallar niveles elevados de triptasa en sangre. La ausencia de exposición a alérgenos comunes nos hizo pensar en una hidatidosis hepática complicada como causa del cuadro, lo que se confirmó mediante ecografía y tomografía computarizada (TC) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(4): 255-257, mayo 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100239</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una causa mortal de síncope</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13955^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13955^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
