<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97281</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutricional assesment in nursing students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of the study was to know dietary habits and nutritional knowledge of women nursing students. Material and methods: Participants of the study were a random sample composed of 180 female students of 1st curse of nursing studies. This sample represented the 95% of total, and the 5% was excluded (men and chronic illness). We studied three-day record study, including a weekend. At the same time, we measured the weight, the height, diameter of hip and diameter of waist. Results: The energy intake was 1720 Kcal/day, and as in similar studies the % energy from fat and proteins was higher than % energy from carbohydrates. Statured fatty acid intake was statistically significant higher than recommendations. Body mass index (BMI) was normal in 81,1% of women (21,3 Kg/m2). The rest was 10% underweight and 8,9% had overweight/obesity. Conclusions: This information provided by this study, should be used in order to improve Nutritional studies in nursing schools (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Mª Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer los hábitos dietéticos y conocimientos nutricionales de estudiantes de primero de enfermería. Material y métodos: Se estudio una muestra de 180 alumnas de 1er curso de enfermería que es el 95% de la población, el 5% restante se excluyó por razón de género o enfermedad crónica. A todas ellas se les realizó una encuesta de hábitos dietéticos y de frecuencia de consumo de alimentos de 3 días, incluyendo fin de semana. Asi mismo se realizó a todas las participantes medición de peso, talla, perímetro de cintura y cadera. Resultados: La ingesta energética media fue de1720 Kcal/día, siendo el aporte calórico proveniente de los hidratos de carbono inferior a las recomendaciones, mientras que el aporte de proteínas y lípidos eran superiores. La ingesta de ácidos grasos saturados (AGS)también era superior a las recomendaciones con significación estadística. En el 80% de las participantes el Índice de masa corporal (IMC) fue normal con un valor de 21,3 Kg/m2. El 11,1% presentaba bajo peso y el 8,9% sobrepeso / obesidad. Conclusiones: La información proporcionada por este estudio podría contribuir para reforzar los programas de formación en el área de Nutrición de las Escuelas de Enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;30(3): 21-26, sept.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97281</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación nutricional en estudiantes de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
