<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052601</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of school-based child sexual abuse prevention program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of the present work is to evaluate the efficacy of a program entitled «Prevention of child sexual abuse» the first structured program in Spain designed to prevent such risks. With this purpose, we carried out a study of 382 minors with ages ranging between 8 and 12 years. The result s show that the program has a very positive impact, increasing the awareness of the minors about this type of risk and improving their skills for coping with a possible event of sexual abuse. The efficacy of the program is also apparent, at the level of secondary prevention, in that it increased the likelihood that the children would reveal such events. Finally, exploration of the possible adverse effects of the program showed that the negative effects observed by parents and educators are negligible</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Sánchez, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo Sánchez, Amaia del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo pretende evaluar la eficacia del programa «Prevención de abusos sexuales a menores», el primer currículo estructurado de nuestro país en la prevención de este riesgo. Con este propósito se realizó un estudio con 382 menores de edades comprendidas entre 8 y 12 años. Los resultados demuestran que el programa tiene un impacto muy positivo, incrementando los conocimientos de los menores sobre este riesgo y mejorando sus habilidades de afrontamiento ante un posible abuso sexual. Asimismo, se pudo constatar la eficacia del mismo, a nivel de prevención secundaria, aumentando la probabilidad de revelación por parte de las víctimas. Finalmente, la exploración de los posibles efectos adversos, asociados a este tipo de programas, reveló que los efectos negativos observados por padres y educadores fueron prácticamente inexistentes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(1): 1-8, feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052601</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa de prefención de abusos sexuales a menores en educación primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
