<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128814</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of Patients With Chlamydia trachomatis Genital Infection in an STD Clinic</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Chlamydia trachomatis genital infection is common in our setting and early treatment can prevent complications. The aim of this study was to report on patients diagnosed with C trachomatis genital infection in a sexually transmitted disease (STD) clinic. Material and methods: This was a descriptive, cross-sectional, observational study of patients diagnosed with C trachomatis infection between 2010 and 2011. We recorded demographic data and information on sexual habits, concomitant sexually transmitted infections (STIs), and various aspects of treatment. Results: In total, 12.3% of the samples analyzed were positive for C trachomatis genital infection. Sixty-two patients (43 men) with a mean age of 31 years were studied; 75% were heterosexual and 87% had had a sexual partner in the previous 2 months. Condom use was inconsistent in 81%, 79%, and 65% of patients who practiced vaginal, oral, and anal sex, respectively. Thirteen percent of the patients had symptoms and anogenital warts were the most common associated STI. The most widely used treatment was doxycycline. Conclusions: A high prevalence of genital C trachomatis infection was detected in our STD clinic, and the majority of cases were found in young men. We observed a high rate of asymptomatic infection in patients who do not engage in high-risk sexual behavior and who had come to the clinic for another reason. Systematic screening of C trachomatis infection should be implemented in STD units to enable the early treatment of patients and their recent sexual partners (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernandez-Morano, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Repiso-Jiménez, J. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas-Ruiz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Troya-Martin, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La infección genital por Chlamydia trachomatis (CT) tiene una alta incidencia en nuestro medio y su tratamiento precoz puede evitar complicaciones. Describimos la población de pacientes diagnosticados en una consulta de enfermedades de transmisión sexual. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo de corte transversal de la población diagnosticada de infección por CT entre 2010 y 2011. Se recogieron datos demográficos, hábitos sexuales, asociación con otras infecciones de transmisión sexual (ITS) y diversos aspectos del tratamiento. Resultados: Encontramos positividad para CT en el 12,3% de las muestras. Se incluyeron 62 pacientes con una media de edad de 31 años. De estos 43 eran hombres y el 75% era heterosexual. El 87% de los pacientes había tenido una pareja sexual en los últimos 2 meses. El uso del preservativo se consideró deficiente en el 81, 79 y 65% de los pacientes en el sexo vaginal, oral y anal respectivamente. Aparecieron síntomas en el 13% y la ITS asociada con más frecuencia fueron las verrugas anogenitales. El tratamiento más usado fue la doxiciclina. Conclusiones: La detección de CT en nuestra consulta es elevada, procediendo en su mayoría las muestras de varones jóvenes. Demostramos una alta incidencia de infección genital asintomática por CT en pacientes sin prácticas sexuales de alto riesgo y que acudieron a la consulta por otros motivos. Es necesario el despistaje sistemático de CT en la consulta de ITS para tratar de forma precoz al paciente y a sus parejas recientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;105(8): 774-779, oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128814</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la población con infección genital por Chlamydia trachomatis en una consulta de enfermedades de transmisión sexual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54470^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54470^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54470^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54470^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54470^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
