<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79118</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Percutaneous treatment of peripheral vascular malformations with a mixture of polidocanol and CO2. Initial experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The percutaneous treatment of peripheral vascular malformations is currently the first treatment option for these processes. We describe our initial experience using a mixture of polidocanol and CO2 as an embolizing agent; we analyze the efficacy and complications of the treatment. Material and methods. Between April 2005 and December 2006, we treated a total of 18 patients, comprising 11 women (61%) and 7 men (39%), with ages ranging from 11 to 80 years. One (5%) vascular malformation was hemodynamically active and the remaining 17 (95%) were hemodynamically inactive. We performed a total of 56 embolizations (mean per patient, 3; range, 1-7) using a mixture of polidocanol and CO2 (mean, 8 cm3; range, 1-28 cm3). The malformations were studied with Doppler ultrasonography, magnetic resonance imaging, and direct puncture angiography and/or arteriography. Specific approaches and treatments were used in each case in function of the location, size, and characteristics of the malformation. Results. Technical success, defined as the possibility of embolizing the malformation, was achieved in all cases. No technical complications occurred. The mean follow-up period was 9 months (range, 1-20). All patients, except one woman who refused to continue treatment, improved objectively and subjectively, and all were able to return to normal daily activities. After embolization, all patients presented edema, pain, and increased functional incapacity that ceased with medical treatment. Conclusion. Percutaneous embolization of vascular malformations using a mixture of polidocanol and CO2 is efficacious and has a low rate of complications. Our initial results are promising but larger studies are necessary to reach definitive conclusions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carreir, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Górriz Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El tratamiento percutáneo de las malformaciones vasculares periféricas es hoy día aceptado como primera opción terapéutica en estos procesos. Describimos nuestra experiencia inicial con una mezcla de polidocanol y CO2 como agente embolizante, analizando su eficacia y complicaciones. Material y métodos. Entre abril de 2005 y diciembre de 2006 se han tratado 18 pacientes, 11 mujeres (61%) y 7 hom bres (39%) con edades comprendidas entre 11 y 80 años. Una malformación vascular era hemodinámicamente activa (5%) y 17 eran hemodinámicamente inactivas (95%). Se realizaron en total 56 embolizaciones (rango: 1-7; media: 3) con una mezcla de polidocanol y CO2 (rango: 1-28 cm3; media 8 cm3). Las malformaciones se estudiaron con ecografía-Doppler, resonancia magnética y angiografía por punción directa o arteriografía. En función de la localización, tamaño y características hemodinámicas, se realizaron abordajes y tratamientos específicos para cada caso. Resultados. Se obtuvo un éxito técnico, entendiendo como tal la posibilidad de embolizar la malformación en el 100% de los casos. No se produjeron complicaciones técnicas. El período medio de seguimiento fue de 9 meses (rango: 1-20). Todos los pacientes, excepto una que rechazó continuar con el tratamiento, mejoraron objetiva y subjetivamente, y todos recuperaron las actividades diarias normales. Todos los pacientes presentaron edema, dolor e incremento de su impotencia funcional tras la embolización, que cedieron con tratamiento médico. Conclusión. La embolización percutánea de malformaciones vasculares con una mezcla de polidocanol y CO2 es un método eficaz y con baja incidencia de complicaciones. Nuestros resultados iniciales son esperanzadores, aunque se precisan estudios más extensos para extraer conclusiones definitivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);50(5): 424-429, sept. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79118</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento percutáneo de las malformaciones vasculares periféricas con una mezcla de polidocanol y CO2. Experiencia inicial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24871^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52606^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12978^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
