<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67958</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-6266</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate the scientific production that the Neumosur journal has had between the years 2002-2006 by means of a bibliometric study of production and impact. Methods. All the editions of the Neumosur journal between the years 2002-2006 were included and were introduced into a data base, with which a descriptive study was made. Later, several bibliometric indicators of production and impact for every year of the journal were calculated: Lotka&#146;s index, cooperation index, reference rate, visibility, influence, half period of the citations and the impact factor. Results. During the period of study, the Neumosur journal has published 102 articles: 14 (13.7%) editorials, 44 (43.1%) originals, 22 (21.6%) review articles, 15 (14.7%) clinical notes and 7 (6.9%) letters to the director. Of those, 81 (79.4%) were citable articles. The cooperation diminished progressively down to 3.04 for the year 2006 with a production similar to previous periods as well as the number of originals. The Neumosur journal has received a total of 5 international citations and 26 national citations. The maximum impact factor reached by the journal was 0.069 in 2004 that rose to 0.207 for the same year when considering citations of the Neumosur journal itself. Conclusions. The evolution of the production and impact indicators of the Neumosur journal reflect a plateau for most of the indicators with respect to the previously studied period</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojano, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Ruiz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Campos, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Riera, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Martín, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrot, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cejudo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar la producción científica que la revista Neumosur ha tenido entre los años 2002-2006 mediante un estudio bibliométrico de producción y repercusión. Métodos. Se recogieron todas las publicaciones de la revista Neumosur entre los años 2002-2006 y se introdujeron en una base de datos, con lo que se realizó un estudio descriptivo. En un segundo tiempo, se calcularon diversos indicadores bibliométricos de producción y repercusión para cada año de la revista como son: índice de Lotka, índice de cooperación, tasa de referencias, visibilidad, influencia, semiperiodo de las citas y el factor de impacto. Resultados. Durante el periodo de estudio, la revista Neumosur ha publicado 102 artículos: 14 (13,7%) editoriales, 44 (43,1%) originales, 22 (21,6%) artículos de revisión, 15 (14,7%) notas clínicas y 7 (6,9%) cartas al director. De ellos, 81 (79,4%) eran artículos citables. La cooperación disminuyó progresivamente hasta 3,04 para el año 2006 con una producción similar a periodos previos así como el número de originales. La revista Neumosur ha recibido un total de 5 citas internacionales y 26 citas de la revista Neumosur. El factor de impacto máximo alcanzado por la revista fue de 0,069 en el año 2004 que ascendió a 0,207 para ese mismo año teniendo en cuenta las citas de la propia revista Neumosur. Conclusiones. La evolución de los indicadores de producción y repercusión de la revista Neumosur reflejan una meseta para la mayoría de los indicadores con respecto al periodo anterior estudiado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neumosur (Sevilla);20(2): 81-87, abr.-jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67958</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
