<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164107</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of glutamine on liver injuries induced by intestinal ischemia-reperfusion in rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Intestinal ischemia-reperfusion (I/R) injury may cause cell and tissue damage, reaching also other organs such as the liver. Because of the involvement of free radicals in I/R injury, treatment options with antioxidants have been studied and tested. Objective: To evaluate the effect of glutamine (Gln) in the liver of animals with intestinal I/R injury. Methods: We used 20 male Wistar rats divided into four groups: sham-operated (SO); glutamine + sham-operated (G+SO); intestinal ischemia-reperfusion (I/R); glutamine + intestinal ischemia-reperfusion (G+I/R). The superior mesenteric artery was clamped for 30 minutes and reperfused for 15 minutes. Gln (25 mg/kg/day) diluted in 1 ml of saline was administered intraperitoneally on the two days before I/R induction. Results: Levels of serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and alkaline phosphatase (ALP), lipid peroxidation (LPO) and expressions of interleukin-6 (IL-6) and nuclear factor kappa B (NF-kB) showed a significant reduction in the G+I/R group as compared with the I/R group. The activity of catalase (CAT), superoxide dismutase (SOD), glutathione peroxidase (GPx), and the levels of glutathione (GSH) showed an increase in the G+I/R group as compared with the I/R group. Conclusion: Pretreatment with Gln reduced oxidative, tissue damage and showed a decrease expression of inflammatory mediators (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Juliana da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabot, Gilmara Pandolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colares, Elizângela Josieli Raskopf</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moura, Rosa Maria Braga Lopes de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Licks, Francielli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Minuzzo Hartmann, Renata</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fillmann, Henrique Sarubbi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marroni, Norma Possa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: las lesiones por isquemia-reperfusión (I/R) intestinales pueden causar daño celular y tisular, llegando incluso a otros órganos, como el hígado. Debido a la participación de radicales libres en la lesión I/R, se han estudiado y probado opciones de tratamiento con antioxidantes. Objetivo: evaluar el efecto de la glutamina (Gln) en el hígado de los animales con lesión intestinal I/R. Métodos: se utilizaron 20 ratas Wistar macho divididas en cuatro grupos: sham-operadas (SO); glutamina + sham-operadas (G+SO); isquemia-reperfusión intestinal (I/R); glutamina + isquemia-reperfusión intestinal (G+I/R). La arteria mesentérica superior se clampó durante 30 minutos y se llevó a cabo la reperfusión durante 15 minutos. Se adminsitró Gln (25 mg/kg/día) diluida en 1 ml de solución salina por vía intraperitoneal en los dos días previos a la inducción de la I/R. Resultados: los niveles de aspartato aminotransferasa (AST), alanina aminotransferasa (ALT) y fosfatasa alcalina (FA), la peroxidación lipídica (POL) y las expresiones de interleucina-6 (IL-6) y factor nuclear kappa B (NF-kB) mostraron una reducción significativa en el grupo G+I/R en comparación con el grupo I/R. La actividad de la catalasa (CAT), la superóxido dismutasa (SOD), glutatión peroxidasa (GPx), y los niveles de glutatión (GSH) mostraron un aumento en el grupo G+I/R en comparación con el grupo I/R. Conclusión: el tratamiento previo con Gln redujo el daño tisular oxidativo y mostró una disminución de los mediadores inflamatorios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(3): 540-547, mayo-jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164107</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la glutamina en las lesiones hepáticas inducidas por isquemia-reperfusión intestinal en ratas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30578</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23743^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23813^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23813^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6117^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6117^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8272^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53500^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53500^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
