<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114694</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vacuum assisted closure (VAC) in the treatment of advanced diabetic foot</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Deep diabetic foot lesions pose an enormous therapeutic problem. The purpose of this study was to present the experience of the use of vacuum assisted closure (VAC) in the treatment of advanced and complicated diabetic foot lesions. Material and methods Five cases of advanced diabetic foot that were treated with VAC were prospectively studied. Three patients were diagnosed with renal failure, including one with renal transplant, who were receiving immunosuppression therapy. Four patients had undergone local foot surgery. The foot lesions were classified as grade 3 or 4 according to the Wagner classification. In all patients extensive debridement was performed that resulted in open minor amputations in four cases and resection of the metatarsophalangeal joint in one case. The VAC was applied during the same procedure. The median follow-up period of the patients was 9 months. Results Foot salvage was achieved in all cases. The median number of changes of VAC was 16 within median period of 8 weeks. Half of the changes were performed as an outpatient procedure. There were no major complications or clinical signs of infection observed. In one case before treatment with VAC began, angioplasty of the iliac artery and superficial femoral artery was performed. Other interventions carried out after the treatment was started were, two distal revascularizations and two partial transmetatarsal amputations. Conclusions VAC appears to be very useful in the treatment of advanced diabetic foot lesions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dzieciuchowicz , Lukasz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grochowicz, Lukasz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa, Gaudencio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Las lesiones profundas del pie diabético constituyen un importante problema terapéutico. El objetivo de este estudio es presentar la experiencia resultante de la utilización del sistema de cierre asistido al vacío (VAC) en el tratamiento del pie diabético avanzado y complicado. Material y métodos Se realizó un estudio prospectivo de 5 casos de pie diabético avanzado tratados mediante VAC. Del total, a 3 pacientes se los diagnosticó de insuficiencia renal, entre ellos uno que recibió tratamiento inmunosupresor debido a un trasplante renal. En 4 de los casos se habían realizado intervenciones quirúrgicas locales sin éxito. Conforme a la clasificación de Wagner, las lesiones se catalogaron como de grado 3 o 4. En todos los casos se realizó un desbridamiento extenso, que en 4 de los pacientes dio lugar a amputaciones menores abiertas a la altura del metatarso, mientras que en uno se tradujo en una resección de la articulación metatarsofalángica. En el mismo acto, en cada uno de los pacientes se colocó VAC. La mediana de seguimiento posprocedimiento fue de 9 meses. Resultados Se consiguió salvar la extremidad en todos los casos. La mediana de cambios de VAC fue de 16 durante un período mediano de 8 semanas. La mitad de los cambios se realizó de modo ambulatorio. No ocurrieron complicaciones mayores. En ningún caso se produjeron signos clínicos de la infección. En uno de los pacientes, antes de comenzar el tratamiento con VAC, se llevó a cabo una angioplastia de arteria ilíaca y femoral superficial. Se necesitaron otros procedimientos adicionales: 2 revascularizaciones distales y 2 amputaciones parciales del antepié, después de que se iniciara el tratamiento con VAC. Conclusione El sistema VAC parece ser muy eficaz en el tratamiento del pie diabético avanzado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);86(4): 213-218, oct. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114694</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El sistema de cierre asistido al vacío en el tratamiento del pie diabético avanzado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31512^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3948^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
