<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69864</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Suprasellar lipomas are uncommon lesions. They are thought to be derived from the abnormal and poorly differentiated persistence of primitive meninx. These tumors are usually diagnosed incidentally, since most are asymptomatic. However, these masses sometimes produce neurological symptoms, such as headache, epileptic seizures, and even pineal malfunction. Diagnosis is given by radiological imaging. The treatment of choice appears to be conservative management. Surgery should only be recommended in patients who do not respond to medical management. We present the case of a 30-year-old woman who was being investigated because of headache; a computed tomography scan revealed an image suggestive of suprasellar lipoma. Apropos of this case, we review the origin, diagnosis and treatment of theses rare tumors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Guardiola, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monereo Megías, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Bolaños, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavón de Paz, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivar Roldán, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya Álvarez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los lipomas supraselares son lesiones muy poco frecuentes. Se cree que derivan de una persistencia anormal y mal diferenciada de la meninge primitiva. Su diagnóstico es generalmente incidental, ya que la mayoría son asintomáticos. Sin embargo, a veces dan lugar a síntomas neurológicos, como cefalea, crisis epilépticas o incluso disfunción hipofisaria. La imagen radiológica permite el diagnóstico. El manejo conservador parece ser el tratamiento de  elección. La cirugía únicamente estaría recomendada para los pacientes que no responden al tratamiento médico. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 30 años a quien se estaba estudiando por cefaleas. En una tomografía computarizada que se le realizó, se encontró una imagen indicativa de lipoma supraselar. A propósito de este caso, hemos revisado el origen, el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de estos raros tumores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(10): 553-555, dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69864</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1958^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
