<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134310</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variables that influence the outcomes of very lengthy temporary disability due to nonoccupational causes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify variables that influence the duration of cases of very lengthy Temporary Disability (TD).Subjects and methods: This was a cross-sectional observational study in a primary care setting. Persons who, as of 1999, had been on TD due to nonoccupational causes for a minimum of 6 months were included in the study. The main variables were: age, gender, treating physician, occupation, diagnosis, number of follow-up visits, duration of TD, number and duration of TD in the previous 5 previous years, resolution of TD and new TD after resolution. Results: There were 164 patients (49.4% men). Mean duration of TD was 376.5 days. The most common pathologies in men were orthopaedic, psychiatric and cardiovascular among women, there was a higher proportion of psychiatric diagnoses and gynaecological problems were third most common. Occupation differed by gender, but was not related to diagnosis. Among older individuals, orthopaedic (56%) and cardiovascular (12%) pathologies prevailed; among the youngest age groups, psychiatric pathologies (40%) were seen most often. Young persons were more likely to be on TD. Family physicians saw a greater number of TD cases and of follow-up visits. TD duration was greatest for those cases seen by General Practitioners Multivariate analysis: psychopathology was associated with a longer duration (R: 0.56, CI 95%: 0.38-0.84), and heart disease with a shorter duration (RR: 1.93, CI 95%: 1,04-3.61) of T as compared to orthopaedic pathology. TD was of shorter duration among persons with a prior history of another TD situation (RR: 1.09, CI 95%: 1.01-1.16). Conclusions: Diagnosis and number of TD in the 5 previous years are associated with TD of greater than 6 month&#146;s duration  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bayona, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jimenez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar las variables que pueden influir en la duración de una Incapacidad Temporal (IT) de muy larga duración. Sujetos y métodos: Éste es un estudio observacional retrospectivo, realizado en el ámbito de la atención primaria de salud, en el que se incluyen todos los pacientes que iniciaron en 1999 un proceso de IT por contingencias comunes, que se prolongó un mínimo de 6 meses. Se seleccionaron como variables principales: edad, sexo, médico prescriptor, ocupación, diagnóstico, número de visitas de control, duración de la IT, número de IT en los 5 años previos, días de IT consumidos en estos 5 años, resolución de la IT y nueva IT tras la resolución. Resultados: 164 pacientes (49,4% hombres). Duración mediana de 376,5 días. Predominio de patología traumatológica, psiquiátrica y cardiológica en los hombres, similar en las mujeres, aunque con mayor proporción de problemas psiquiátricos y siendo tercera la patología ginecológica. La ocupación variaba según el sexo, sin que hubiera relación con el diagnóstico. En los mayores predominaba la patología traumatológica (56%) y cardiológica (12%), mientras que en los jóvenes lo hacía la psiquiátrica (40%). Los jóvenes estuvieron más veces de baja. El número de visitas de control y el número de IT previas era superior en el caso de los médicos de familia. Las IT de los médicos generalistas duraron más. Análisis multivariado: la psicopatología tiene duraciones más largas (RR: 0,56, IC 95%: 0,38-0,84), y más breves en el caso de las cardiopatías (RR: 1,93,IC 95%: 1,04-3,61), que los procesos traumatológicos, y la IT fue más corta si se estuvo más veces de baja previamente (RR:1,09, IC 95%: 1,01-1,16).Conclusiones: el diagnóstico y el número de IT en los 5 años previos están relacionados con la duración de las IT de más de 6 meses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);7(2): 64-69, abr.-jun. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134310</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variable que influyen en la resolución de una incapacidad temporal por contingencias comunes de muy larga duración</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16923^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32711^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
