<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82299</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mesotherapy as a therapeutic option in painful condition of locomotor apparatus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Mesotherapy is a technique that consists in the application of multiple intradermal injections (deep dermis) with different drugs according to the conditions to be treated. It is used in different medical specialties, its use being especially interesting in pain, a prevalent symptom in our specialty. Introduction. This work has aimed to assess the effectiveness and safety of this treatment in patients with chronic painful condition of the locomotor apparatus. Material and methods. We conducted a prospective study of the results obtained with the application of this technique in 59 patients, referred from the Rehabilitation Service, suffering from different conditions. The medications used for pain treatment were a combination of Piroxicam, Lidocaine 1% and Pentoxifylline. The Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), the Health Questionnaire EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D Index score) and the measurement of the painful zone diameter were used to evaluate the results. The statistical analysis was conducted with the SPSS V15.0 computer program and the method consisted in a comparison of means, using the Student's T test for matched data of each of the 3 measurement instruments used. Results and conclusions. None of the patients dropped out of the treatment. Their mean age was 46 years old and 74.5% of the patients were women. Neck pain was the most frequently treated condition. We have demonstrated a statistically significant improvement (p&lt;0.001) of the painful condition of the locomotor apparatus after mesotherapy treatment, with mean decreases of 52.28mm (95% CI: 44.78&#150;59.79) in the VAS, 45.86cm (95% CI: 30.97&#150;60.75) in the lesion diameter and average increase in the EQ-5D Index score of 0.3550 (95% CI: 0.2924&#150;0.4177). As side effects, 26% of the patients had hematomas in the application zone that resolved spontaneously. Results and conclusions. Mesotherapy is a safe and effective method for the treatment of chronic painful condition of the locomotor apparatus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Pastor, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juste Díaz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Fernández, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iñigo Huarte, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calatayud Campos, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Ferrer Sapiña, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La mesoterapia es una técnica que consiste en la aplicación de múltiples inyecciones intradérmicas (dermis profunda) con diferentes fármacos según las patologías a tratar. Es utilizada en distintas especialidades médicas, siendo especialmente interesante su uso en dolor, síntoma prevalente en nuestra especialidad. Introducción. El objetivo de este trabajo es valorar la eficacia y seguridad de este tratamiento en pacientes con patología dolorosa crónica del aparato locomotor. Material y métodos. Realizamos un estudio prospectivo de los resultados obtenidos con la aplicación de esta técnica en 59 pacientes, derivados a la consulta de Rehabilitación y afectos de distintas patologías. Los fármacos utilizados para el tratamiento del dolor fueron una combinación de Piroxicam, Lidocaína al 1% y Pentoxifilina. Para evaluar resultados utilizamos al inicio y final del proceso la Escala Visual Analógica (EVA), el Cuestionario de salud EuroQol-5D (EQ-5D tarifa) y la medición del diámetro de la zona dolorosa. El análisis estadístico se realizó con el programa informático SPSS V15.0 y el método consistió en una comparación de medias utilizando una t de student para datos emparejados de cada uno de las tres instrumentos de medida utilizados. Resultados y conclusiones. Ningún paciente abandonó el tratamiento. Edad media: 46 años. El 74,5% de pacientes fueron mujeres. La cervicalgia fue la patología más frecuentemente tratada. Demostramos una mejoría estadísticamente significativa (p&lt;0,001) de la patología dolorosa del aparato locomotor tras el tratamiento con mesoterapia, con unos descensos medios de 52,28mm (IC 95%: 44,78&#150;59,79) en la EVA y de 45,86cm (IC 95%: 30,97&#150;60,75) en el diámetro de la lesión y un aumento medio en el EQ-5D tarifa de 0,3550 (IC 95%: 0,2924&#150;0,4177). Como únicos efectos secundarios, un 26% de pacientes presentaron hematomas en la zona de aplicación que se resolvieron espontáneamente. Resultados y conclusiones. La mesoterapia es un método de tratamiento eficaz y seguro para el tratamiento de la patología dolorosa crónica del aparato locomotor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);44(4): 311-316, oct.-dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82299</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mesoterapia como opción terapéutica en patología dolorosa del aparato locomotor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27765^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8188^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10625^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
