<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61128</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience with continuous renal replacement  therapy in intensive care. Factors determining the duration of the haemofilter</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Continuous renal replacement therapyis widely used in intensive care units to handle acute renal failure. It is also used in clinical situations with no renal alteration in which its use fullness has been demonstrated, while limiting the complications associated to conventional techniques. The aim of this study is to determine whether the variables analysed have an influence on haemofilterrun times. A descriptive analysis of the data generated in the study of the use of CRRT in our unit is also provided. Material and methods A prospective-descriptive study was carried out on the use of continuous renal replacement therapy in the Intensive Care Unit of the Hospital Comarcal de Melilla. The study included all patients admitted during the period between 04/03/07 and25/09/07 who required such therapy. Results: Of all the variables analysed to determine their relation to filter duration, it was found that there is a positive correlation with blood flow (Spearman&#146;s rho =0.304; p=0.05) and a negative correlation with the number of platelets (Spearman&#146;s rho = -0.469; p= 0.01) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Olert, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Carmona, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sánchez, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles Andujar, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro Nieto, M. Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Bernal, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las técnicas continuas de reemplazo renal son utilizadas ampliamente en las unidades de cuidados intensivos para el manejo del fracaso renal agudo. Se usan también en situaciones clínicas sin alteración renal en las que se ha demostrado su utilidad, limitando al mismo tiempo las complicaciones asociadas a las técnicas convencionales. El objetivo del presente estudio es determinar si las variables analizadas tienen influencia sobre los tiempos de aprovechamiento del hemofiltro. Asimismo se hace un análisis descriptivo de los datos que ha generado el estudio del uso de las TCRR en nuestra unidad. Material y métodos: Se lleva a cabo un estudio prospectivo-descriptivo acerca del uso de las técnicas continuas de reemplazo renal en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos del Hospital Comarcal de Melilla. Se incluyeron en el estudio a todos los pacientes ingresados durante el período comprendido entre el 04/03/07 y el 25/09/07 que precisaron de dichas técnicas. Resultados: De todas las variables analizadas para determinar su relación con la duración del filtro, se encuentra que existe correlación positiva con el flujo de sangre(Rho de Spearman=0.304; p=0.05) y correlación negativa con la cifra de plaquetas (Rho de Spearman= -0.469; p= 0.01) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;11(4): 259-264, oct.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61128</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia con las técnicas continúas de reemplazo renal en cuidados intensivos. Determinantes dela duración del hemofiltro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31085^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29413^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
