<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77857</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Concurrent granulosa tumor and mucinous cystoadenoma in the contralateral ovary</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 57-year-old womanwith mucinous cystoadenoma in one ovary andgranulosa tumor as an incidental finding in theother. The patient reported primary amenorrhea,and clinical presentation consisted of metrorrhagiaand an abdominal mass.Adult granulosa tumors, which belong to thegroup of gonadal stroma neoplasms of the ovary,are more common in postmenopausal women.Clinically, these tumors usually manifest withsymptoms secondary to estrogen secretion, althoughthe proportion of tumors of this kind that secretehormones is difficult to establish (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Eloy-García Carrasco, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán Cantero, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Márquez, Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero Severín, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toro Salas, Antonio de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Justo Moscardó, M. Jesús de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 57 años concistoadenoma mucinoso en un ovario y tumor dela granulosa como hallazgo casual en el anejocontralateral. Clínicamente, la paciente, que referíauna amenorrea primaria, debutó con metrorragia ytumoración abdominal.Los tumores de la granulosa del adulto, quepertenecen a las neoplasias del estroma gonadaldel ovario, son más frecuentes en mujeresposmenopáusicas. En la clínica suelen debutar consíntomas secundarios a la secreción estrogénica,aunque la proporción de tumores de la granulosasecretores de hormonas es difícil de establecer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(9): 533-536, sept. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor de la granulosacoexistente con cistoadenomamucinoso en el ovariocontralateral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31529^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31529^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6257^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
