<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049433</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The aetiopathogenesis of auditory hallucinations in psychosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Auditory hallucinations is one of the core symptoms of psychosis. Two main different approacheshave been made in recent years in order to understand this perceptual abnormality. The psycho-social approaches is trying toexplain auditory hallucinations as a common human phenomenon that only environmental factors cause them to bepathological. It propose psychotherapeutic techniques based on the cognitive model, paying special attention to the emotionalcomponent. The neurobiological approach, specially with neuroimaging techniques, is giving us new information aboutabnormal activation in specific neural networks, particularly in language areas. It propose biological treatments withantipsychotics and transcranial magnetic stimulation. Neither of these approaches are listening to each other. Neither of themlook at the molecular genetic vulnerability to auditory hallucinations in psychosis. Development. From a review of theliterature and our own findings, we present a genetic-environmental model of auditory hallucinations in psychoses. Wehypothesize two types of genetic vulnerability: vulnerability to hearing voices &#150;that could be related with genes that areexpressed in language areas and are related with language abnormalities (FOXP2)&#150;, and vulnerability to abnormal emotionalresponse to voices &#150;that could be related with genes that are involved in the regulation of dopamine in the limbic system (5-HTT,CCK-AR)&#150;. Finally, environmental and cultural factors explain the content and social adjustment to auditory hallucinations.Conclusion. Our model allow the integration of many data from epidemiology and neuroimaging, to psychopharmacology inthe understanding of the aetiology of auditory hallucinations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanjuán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En los últimos años, dos tipos de abordajeshan tratado de avanzar en la comprensión de las alucinacionesauditivas en la psicosis. Desde estudios epidemiológicos en poblacióngeneral se viene defendiendo el &#145;oír voces&#146; como un fenómenohumano común donde los factores ambientales y el ajuste social, yno las alucinaciones en sí, constituirían la verdadera patología.Desde las técnicas de neuroimagen se han descrito las principalesáreas implicadas en la fisiopatología de las alucinaciones auditivas.No hay intentos de integración de estas líneas de investigacióntan diferentes, tanto en sus bases teóricas como en sus propuestasterapéuticas. Además, ninguna de estas aproximaciones aborda elproblema de la vulnerabilidad genética. Desarrollo. A partir de larevisión de la bibliografía y de nuestros propios hallazgos, en estudios genéticos en pacientes psicóticos, planteamos un modelo etiopatogénicointegrador genético-ambiental de las alucinaciones auditivasen la psicosis. Los factores genéticos pertenecen a dos categorías:los que confieren una vulnerabilidad a escuchar voces &#150;estaríanimplicados los genes que se expresan en las áreas del lenguajey se relacionan con trastornos del habla (FOXP2)&#150; y los queconfieren vulnerabilidad a una anormal respuesta emocional alas voces &#150;estarían implicados los genes que regulan, directa oindirectamente, la actividad dopaminérgica en el sistema límbico(5-HTT, CCK-AR)&#150;. Los factores ambientales y culturales modulanel contenido y la repercusión emocional a largo plazo de dichofenómeno alucinatorio. Conclusión. El modelo que se presenta permiteintegrar datos, hasta ahora dispersos, desde la epidemiología,la neuroimagen y la psicofarmacología sobre las alucinaciones auditivas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(5): 280-286, sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049433</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiopatogenia de las alucinaciones auditivas en las psicosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14065^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6365^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
