<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59749</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">European Directive 2004/40/EC on workers' exposure to electromagnetic fields from MRI</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reviews the regulations in force about the exposure of workers to the electromagnetic fields generated by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and evaluates the impact of European Directive 2004/40/EC on the daily use of MRI. We provide a detailed review of the safety criteria stipulated in the International Commission on Non-Ionizing Radiation Protection, in Spanish Royal Decree 1066/2001, and in European Directive 2004/40/EC about exposure to electromagnetic fields. In the case of European Directive 2004/40/EC, the European Union (EU) has introduced a law without adequately evaluating its repercussions. In response to alarms sounded by the radiological and general medical communities, the EU has decided to delay implementation of the Directive. Although the implementation of Directive 2004/40/ EC has been postponed until April 30, 2012, it remains in force. There remains the hope that the Directive will be reconsidered during this interval and that MRI workers will be exempt (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moratal, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí-Bonmatí, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gili, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se revisa la normativa vigente acerca de la exposición de los trabajadores a los campos electromagnéticos presentes en resonancia magnética (RM) y se evalúa el impacto de la Directiva Europea 2004/40/EC acerca del uso diario en la RM. Para ello se revisan en detalle los criterios de seguridad de la International Commission on Non-Ionizing Radiation Protection, el Real Decreto español 1066/2001 y la Directiva Europea 2004/40/EC referentes a la exposición a los campos electromagnéticos. Con la Directiva 2004/40/EC la Unión Europea (UE) introducía una ley sin valorar adecuadamente sus repercusiones. La UE ha decidido su aplazamiento puntual respondiendo a las alertas aportadas por la comunidad radiológica y médica en general. Aunque la normativa Directiva 2004/40/EC se ha pospuesto hasta el 30 de abril de 2012, ésta sigue vigente. Se espera que el replanteamiento de esta normativa produzca una exención del efecto en el ámbito de la RM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);51(1): 30-37, ene. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acerca de la exposición a los campos electromagnéticos presentes en resonancia magnética. Directiva Europea 2004/40/EC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51827^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29758^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31061^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32513</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4646^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
