<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037172</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of stem-cell mobilization with recombinant human granulocyte colony stimulating factor in patients with percutaneously revascularized acute anterior myocardial infarction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. This study reports the findings in a group of 13 patients aged 53±8 years with anterior wall acute myocardial infarction who were revascularized with stents and treated with recombinant human granulocyte colony stimulating factor (G-CSF).Patients and method. Patients were initially treated with intravenous thrombolytics. The first cardiac catheterization was performed between days 0 and 5 after acute myocardial infarction, when the left anterior descending artery was stented. A 10-day course of 10 µg/kg/day G-CSF was started 5 days after acute myocardial infarction. Blood cell counts and immune phenotyping were done to assess the total number of circulating CD34+ cells and their subpopulations in serial fashion. At 3-month follow up, cardiac catheterization was repeated. Functional recovery was defined as an increase in ejection fraction. Results. All patients did well initially, but 1 had spontaneous spleen rupture on day 8 of G-CSF administration, which required emergency splenectomy. The gain in ejection fraction varied among patients from -22 to +18(mean, 6.2%±12%), and correlated directly with the total number of circulating CD34+ CD38- cells/µL on the fifth day of G-CSF treatment (r=0.78; P&lt;.003). The gain in ejection fraction correlated inversely with peak MB fraction creatine kinase (r=-0.82; P&lt;.002). Conclusion. Stem-cell mobilization with G-CSF is a feasible and safe treatment for patients with revascularized acute myocardial infarction. However, because of the possibility of acute splenitis induced by massive cell mobilization, future studies should be designed with due caution to take this eventuality into account</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavlovic, Djordje</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez de Lezo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Rubio, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ojeda, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pan, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. En este estudio se muestran los hallazgos observados en un grupo de 13 pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio (IAM) que fueron revascularizados con stent intracoronario y posteriormente tratados con factor estimulante de colonias granulocíticas recombinado (G-CSF).Pacientes y método. Todos los pacientes recibieron tratamiento trombolítico. El primer cateterismo cardíaco tuvo lugar entre los días 0 y 5 del IAM, y se realizó una revascularización con stent de la arteria descendente anterior. Al quinto día del infarto se empezó tratamiento subcutáneo con G-CSF (10 µg/kg/día durante 10 días).Se efectuaron recuentos sanguíneos e inmunofeno tipificación y se determinó el número total de CD34+ circulantes y de sus subpoblaciones de una forma seriada. A los3 meses de seguimiento se realizó un nuevo cateterismo cardíaco. El grado de recuperación funcional se definió como la ganancia en la fracción de eyección. Resultados. Todos los pacientes evolucionaron favorablemente, sin complicaciones cardíacas. Un paciente presentó una rotura esplénica espontánea al octavo día del tratamiento con G-CSF que precisó una esplenectomía de urgencia. La ganancia en la fracción de eyección osciló entre -22 y +18 (media ± desviación estándar, 6,2± 12%), y se correlacionó de forma directa con el número total de células CD34+ y CD38- circulantes en el quinto día de tratamiento con G-CSF (r = 0,78; p &lt; 0,003) y de forma inversa con el pico de la fracción MB de la creatincinasa (r = -0,82; p &lt; 0,002). Conclusión. La movilización de células madre con GCSF es factible y segura en pacientes con IAM anterior revascularizado. No obstante, la posibilidad de que se produzca una esplenitis aguda inducida por la movilización célular masiva debe ser tratada con cautela en futuros diseños</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;58(3): 253-261, mar. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037172</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la movilización de células madre mediante el uso de factor estimulante de colonias granulocíticas en pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio anterior revascularizado percutáneamente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
