<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110212</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inherited dental abnormalities and dysplasias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alterations of the embryologic development of the dentition cause dental anomalies and dysplasias. The causing factors involved in the disturbances of tooth development are basically two: genetic and environmental factors. Depending on the phase of tooth development when the factors act, they will appear different dental anomalies and dysplasias. Genetic control of tooth development is carried out through two processes: a) control of amelogenesis and dentinogenesis, and b) the specification of the type, size and position of each tooth. Mutation of genes involved in amelogenesis (AMELX, ENAM, MMP20 and KLK4) and dentinogenesis (DSPP) produces non-syndromic alterations of tooth development. On the contrary, mutations in morphogenetic regulatory genes involved in determining the position and the early development of the teeth (homeobox genes), not only alter teeth morpho differentiation, but also have pleiotropic effects affecting other organs, causing hereditary syndromes in which one of its features is the presence of dental abnormalities. Dental anomalies and dysplasias of genetic origin are reviewed in this article (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llamas-Carreras,  J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarilonte-Delgado,  M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Domínguez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura-Egea, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellanos-Cosano,  L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Frías,  F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-González, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las alteraciones del desarrollo embriológico de la dentición provocan anomalías y displasias dentarias. Los factores etiopatogénicos implicados en las alteraciones del desarrollo dentario son básicamente dos: genéticos y ambientales. Según la fase del desarrollo en que afecten al órgano del esmalte y a los tejidos dentarios, aparecerán diferentes anomalías y/o displasias dentales. El control genético del desarrollo dentario se lleva a cabo mediante dos procesos: a) control de la histogénesis del esmalte y la dentina, y b) la especificación del tipo, tamaño y posición de cada diente. La mutación de los genes implicados en la amelogénesis (AMELX, ENAM, MMP20 y KLK4) o en la dentinogénesis (DSPP) produce alteraciones del desarrollo dentario aisladas o no sindrómicas. Por el contrario, las mutaciones de los genes reguladores morfogenéticos involucrados en la determinación de la posición y el desarrollo precoz de los órganos dentarios (genes homeobox), además de alterar la morfodiferenciación dentaria, tienen efectos pleiotrópicos y afectan a otros órganos, provocando síndromes hereditarios en los que uno de sus rasgos es la alteración dentaria. En este artículo se revisan las principales anomalías y displasias dentarias de causa genético-hereditaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;28(6): 287-301, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110212</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anomalías y displasias dentarias de origen genético-hereditario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14461^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37296^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d862^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3759^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31240^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d568^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
