<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90527</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of Nd: YAG capsulotomy on quality of life in pseudophakic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether visual acuity (VA) improvement in patients with posteriorcapsule opacification (PCO), accepted after the capsulotomy, is followed by positive changesin the perception of their quality of life.Method: A total of 130 patients with PCO were examined before and after capsulotomy. In addition to the ophthalmic examination, the EuroQol questionnaire was completed. We analyzed the influence of demographic characteristics on the outcome of the test.                                                             Results: The mean binocular visual acuity (BVA) and the mean scores in the EuroQol dimensionsand EQ-VAS improved significantly after capsulotomy. VA did not have the same effecton dailycommontasks. After treatment, the problems in the usual activities dimension haveseen the largest reduction. Mobility is still the dimension with more problems regardingpatients after capsulotomy.Conclusions: Decreased VA induced by PCO is associated with difficulties performing dailyliving activities. Capsulotomy results in a gain in VA and functional ability of the majorityof patients, improving the perception of their quality of life</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Galilea, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Blanco, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan-Marcos, L. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si la mejoría de agudeza visual (AV) en los pacientes con opacificaciónde cápsula posterior del cristalino (OCP) que se acepta tras la capsulotomía, se traduce encambios positivos en la percepción de su calidad de vida.Método: Se evaluaron 130 pacientes con OCP antes y después de la capsulotomía. Ademásde la exploración oftalmológica se recogieron las respuestas del cuestionario EuroQol y seestudió la influencia de factores demográficos en el resultado del test.Resultados: La agudeza visual binocular (AVB) media y las puntuaciones medias de las cincodimensiones del cuestionario EuroQol y de la EVA mejoraron en el conjunto de pacientesde forma estadísticamente significativa tras la capsulotomía. No todas las tareas de la vidadiaria se afectan en el mismo grado por el estado de la AV. Las limitaciones en la dimensiónde actividades cotidianas son las que más disminuyen con el tratamiento. La dimensión enla que más dificultades continúan relatando los pacientes tras la capsulotomía es en la demovilidad.Conclusiones: La deficiencia visual ocasionada por la OCP conlleva dificultades para realizarlas actividades cotidianas. La capsulotomía supone un incremento en la AV y en lafuncionalidad de la mayoría de los pacientes, mejorando la percepción sobre su estado desalud(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;86(5): 139-144, mayo 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90527</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la capsulotomía Nd: YAG en la calidad de vida de pacientes pseudofáquicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33371^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
