<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049180</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mixed endometrial stromal and smooth muscle tumor: atypical recurrence. Case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mixed endometrial stromal and smooth muscle tumors of the uterus are unusual. For tumors to be classified within this group, at least 30% of each component must be present and diagnosis must be based on light microscopy. Traditionally these tumors were named stromomyomas. Mixed endometrial stromal and smooth muscle tumors are usually benign. In the present case, the tumor recurred in the pelvis 12 months after surgery as a pure smooth muscle tumor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melchor, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silva, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Jiménez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores mixtos de la estroma endometrial y del músculo liso son tumores raros. Para clasificar un tumor dentro de este grupo debe presentar al menos un 30% de cada tipo celular, y diagnosticarse por la evaluación con microscopio óptico. Clásicamente se denominaban «stromomyomas». El comportamiento de los tumores mixtos de la estroma endometrial y del músculo liso suele ser benigno. En este caso la paciente presentó una recurrencia pélvica, con un tumor puro únicamente de músculo liso al año de la primera intervención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);33(6): 230-233, nov. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049180</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor mixto de la estroma endometrial y del músculo liso: recurrencia atípica. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9320^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9406^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9406^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9320^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37266^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
