<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135082</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effects of 16-weeks pilates mat program on anthropometric variables and body composition in active adult women after a short detraining period</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: previous studies have analysed the effect of mat Pilates practice on anthropometric variables and body composition in sedentaries. To date no researches have investigated the benefits of Pilates on these variables after a short detraining period. Objective: to determine the effect of a 16-week mat Pilates program on anthropometric variables, body composition and somatotype of women with previous practice experience after three weeks of detraining period. Method: twenty-one women underwent a complete anthropometric assessment according with ISAK guidelines before and after a 16 week mat Pilates® program (two days, one hour). All women had one to three years of mat Pilates experience and came to three weeks of detraining period (Christmas holiday). Results and discussion: women showed significant decreases for body mass, BMI, upper limb (biceps and triceps) and trunk (subscapular, iliac crest, supraspinale and abdominal) individual skinfolds, 6 and 8 skinfold sums, endomorphy and fat mass; and a significant increases for muscle mass. The mean somatotype was classified as mesomorphic endomorph in the pre- (4.91, 4.01, 1.47) and post-test (4.68, 4.16, 1.69). Eight women changed their somatotype clasification after the intervention program. Conclusions: the practice of mat Pilates for 16 weeks caused changes associated with health state improvements on anthropometric variables, especially on skin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alacid, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Miñarro, Pedro Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero-Cristóbal, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muyor, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza-Ros, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Estudios previos han analizado los efectos de la práctica de Pilates mat sobre las variables antropométricas y la composición corporal en poblaciones sedentarias. No existen estudios sobre los beneficios del Pilates en estas variables tras un corto periodo de desentrenamiento. Objetivo: Determinar el efecto un programa de 16 semanas de Pilates mat sobre las variables antropométricas, la composición coporal y el somatotipo, en mujeres adultas con experiencia previa tras 3 semanas de desentrenamiento. Metodología: A veintiuna mujeres se les realizó una valoración antropométrica completa siguiendo las indicaciones de la ISAK antes y después de un programa de Pilates mat de 16 semanas (2 días a la semana, una hora por día). Todas las mujeres tenían una experiencia previa en la práctica de Pilates® mat de entre 1 y 3 años y venían de un proceso de desentrenamiento de 3 semanas (vacaciones de Navidad). Resultados y discusión: Las mujeres mostraron una reducción significativa del peso corporal, el IMC, los pliegues cutáneos individuales del miembro superior (bíceps y tríceps) y el tronco (subescapular, cresta iliaca, supraespinal y abdominal), el sumatorio de 6 y 8 pliegues, la endomorfia y la masa grasa; y un aumento significativo de la masa muscular. El somatotipo medio se clasificó en meso-endomorfo para el pre- (4,91, 4,01, 1,47) y el post-test (4,68, 4,16, 1,69). Ocho mujeres cambiaron su clasificación del somatotipo tras el programa de intervención. Conclusiones: La práctica de Pilates mat durante 16 semanas provocó cambios asociados a una mejora del estado de salud en las variables antropométricas, sobre todo en los pliegues cutáneos que disminuyeron significativamente, la composición corporal (masa grasa y muscular, que disminuyeron y aumentaron, respectivamente) y el somatotipo (una reducción significativa del componente endomórfico) en mujeres con experiencia previa en la práctica de Pilates después de tres semanas de desentrenamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(4): 1738-1747, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135082</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de un programa de 16 semanas de Pilates mat sobre las variables antropométricas y la composición corporal en mujeres adultas activas tras un corto proceso de desentrenamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13266</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
