<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166441</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of sudden cardiac death</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Despite recent progress in the management of cardiovascular disorders generally, and cardiac arrhythmias in particular, sudden cardiac death remains both a problem for the practising clinician and a major public health issue. An estimate for global annual incidence of sudden cardiac death would be in the range of 4 to 5 million cases per year. Information about the causes and mechanisms of the sudden cardiac death syndrome suggests that a specific reduction will require the development of new and multifaceted approaches, including epidemiologic techniques to address risk characteristics specific to the problem; characterisation of triggering events and identification of specific persons at risk for responding adversely to these events; and methods of evaluating outcomes appropriate to the nature of sudden cardiac death (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Brugada, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asmundis, Carlo de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar de los recientes avances en el tratamiento de los trastornos cardiovasculares en general y de las arritmias en particular, la muerte súbita cardiaca continúa siendo tanto un problema para el médico como un tema de salud pública de gran relevancia. Se estima que la incidencia anual de muerte súbita cardiaca en todo el mundo oscila entre 4 y 5 millones de casos al año. La información disponible sobre las causas y los mecanismos del síndrome de muerte súbita cardiaca revelan que para reducirla será necesario desarrollar nuevos y múltiples enfoques, entre ellos técnicas epidemiológicas para abordar las características de riesgo específicas, la caracterización de los sucesos desencadenantes y la identificación de personas concretas con riesgo de responder mal a estos sucesos, así como métodos adecuados para evaluar la evolución clínica tras un episodio de muerte súbita cardiaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);13(supl.A): 2a-6a, 2013. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166441</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de la muerte súbita cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
