<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27869</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A review of the pharmacologic treatment of migraine in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To describe the efficacy and tolerability of the different medications used to treat migraine in children and adolescents. Development. A literature review of the drug studies involving children and adolescents for the treatment of migraine was conducted. The treatment of migraine is divided in abortive and prophylactic. The different classes of drugs are described in respect to its efficacy and side effects. Few placebo-controlled, double-blind studies are available in children as compared to adults for the treatment of migraine headaches. Only ibuprofen and nasal sumatriptan have been studied and shown to be effective in more than one double blind placebo-controlled study for the abortive treatment of migraine in children. Unlike the adult studies, the oral triptans tested in children have not been effective when compared to placebo. Only flunarizine has shown efficacy in more than one placebo-controlled trial for the prophylactic treatment. Conclusion. Most of the medications used to treat migraine in children and adolescents are well tolerated. The treatment response of migraine in children and adolescent may differ from that of adults. There seems to be a high placebo response rate in the pediatric population. Therefore, further prospective placebo-controlled studies are needed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir la eficacia y tolerabilidad de los distintos fármacos empleados en el tratamiento de la migraña en la infancia y la adolescencia. Desarrollo. Se realizó una revisión de la bibliografía sobre estudios farmacológicos del tratamiento de la migraña llevados a cabo en la infancia y la adolescencia. Hay dos tipos de tratamiento para la migraña: el abortivo y el profiláctico. Se detallan las reacciones adversas y la eficacia de los diferentes tipos de fármaco. Se han publicado pocos estudios controlados por placebo y de doble ciego sobre el tratamiento de las cefaleas migrañosas en niños, comparados con los que se han publicado en adultos. El ibuprofeno y el sumatriptán por vía nasal son los únicos fármacos que se han investigado y que han demostrado ser eficaces en el tratamiento abortivo de la migraña en los niños en más de un estudio de doble ciego controlado por placebo. A diferencia de los estudios en los adultos, los triptanos orales probados en niños no han demostrado ser eficaces con respecto a los placebos. Sólo la flunarizina ha resultado ser eficaz como tratamiento profiláctico en más de una prueba controlada por placebo. Conclusión. La mayor parte de los fármacos que se emplean en el tratamiento de la migraña en los niños y los adolescentes se toleran bien. La respuesta al tratamiento de la migraña en los niños y los adolescentes puede ser distinta a la que se observa en los adultos. Entre la población pediátrica parece haber un alto índice de respuesta a los placebos. Es necesario, por tanto, la realización de más estudios prospectivos controlados por placebo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;37(3): 253-259, ago. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión del tratamiento farmacológico de la migraña en niños</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Vasconcellos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27869</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30516</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23177</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d322</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11350</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
