<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63025</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">According to the European Drug and Drug Addiction Observatory, after Cannabis, Cocaine is the most widely used illegal drug in Europe. Awareness of the damage caused by consuming this substance is clear in some areas, while in others it may be ignored, underestimated or poorly dimensioned. The information systems that do exist almost certainly underestimate the number of deaths connected with cocaine. Apart from the potential the drug has to cause direct damage to different organs of the body, its consumption can lead to serious problems arising from other circumstances that are not always connected with this drug, including murders, traffic accidents and accidents at work, infectious diseases related to high-risk behaviour, and suicides. Cocaine is increasingly present in cases of violence such as fights or aggressions, in many cases accompanied by the use of knives and firearms. Serious behavioural disorders are being seen more and more frequently in the healthcare services, and in clinics we are witnessing a worrying increase on a day-to-day basis of conflictive episodes associated with the use of cocaine amongst our patients. This damage does not only affect a marginal population, but instead all levels of society, and often goes unnoticed or unreported. Coordination between different institutions and healthcare areas is essential in order to obtain this information, and in this way to provide a more precise picture of the consequences of Cocaine consumption, as today we are still far from having quantified its true dimension</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermejo Barrera, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereiro Gómez, César</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Según el Observatorio Europeo de las Drogas y Toxicomanías, la cocaína es, después del cannabis, la droga ilegal más consumida en Europa. La percepción sobre los daños relacionados con el consumo de esta sustancia son claramente percibidos en algunas áreas mientras en otras pueden pasar inadvertidos, infravalorados o mal dimensionados. Los sistemas de información existentes con toda seguridad ofrecen deficiencias al valorar la morbimortalidad relacionada con la cocaína. Además del potencial que la cocaína tiene para producir daños directos en distintos órganos, su consumo puede condicionar graves perjuicios a través de otras circunstancias que no siempre se relacionan con esta droga: homicidios, accidentes de tráfico y laborales, adquisición de enfermedades infecciosas relacionadas con conductas de riesgo, suicidios, etc. La cocaína, está cada vez más presente en episodios de violencia tales como peleas o agresiones, en muchos casos con utilización de armas blancas o de fuego. Las graves alteraciones de conducta se hacen sentir también con fuerza en los servicios asistenciales y los clínicos observamos con gran preocupación como crecen día a día los episodios conflictivos asociados al uso de cocaína entre nuestros enfermos. Los daños no afectan exclusivamente una población marginal, sino a distintos estratos de la sociedad, pasando muchas veces inadvertidos o no registrados. La coordinación entre distintas instituciones y recursos asistenciales es vital para obtener todos estos datos y proporcionar de este modo un acercamiento más riguroso a las consecuencias del consumo de la cocaína, que hoy en día estamos muy lejos de haber cuantificado en su dimensión real</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);20(1): 15-18, ene.-mar. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63025</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3070^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
