<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050513</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5665</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subconjunctival and topic treatment of plasma platelet concentrate in limbal transplantion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It was evaluated the efficiency of the subconjunctival andtopic application of autologous platelet concentrate in oneocular burn after autologous and heterologous limbaltransplant. The eye had a deficit limbal by acid burn and aprevious autotransplant was insuficience.Result: were found a shorter period of time in limbal allographtadaptation; corneal stabilization and better visualacuity in the limbal trasnplants with subconjuctival andtopic plasma platelet concentrates treatment. And acelerationin donnor eye of the healing process with topic plateletconcetrate</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero de Espinosa Escoriaza, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Saez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Leal, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Gutiérrez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez de Aracena del Cid, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha valorado la eficacia del tratamiento subconjuntival ytópico de concentrados plaquetarios plasmáticos tras larealización de un transplante autólogo y otro heterólogohistocompatible de limbo en un ojo con insuficiencia limbartotal tras quemadura por ácido, en que había sidoinsuficiente un injerto previo.Resultado: Se observó un acortamiento en el tiempo deadaptación de los injertos, estabilización corneal y mejorade la agudeza visual en el ojo transplantado. Así mismo,una aceleración de la curación en el ojo donante tras aplicacióntópica de concentrados plaquetarios</dc:description>
<dc:source>MAPFRE med;17(4): 280-285, abr. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050513</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con concentrado plaquetario plasmático subconjuntival y tópico en el transplante de limbo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29361^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29512^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1819</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30006^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28014^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
