<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115708</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Musculoskeletal disorders of the upper and the lumbar region: demographic and occupational characterization, Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Bogotá 2001- 2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to characterize demographic and occupational variables of cases of upper limb and lower back musculoskeletal injuries. Methodology: In a descriptive, cross-sectional study, we searched and reviewed scientific literature to learn about occupational risk factors associated with musculoskeletal injuries of upper limbs, the lower back and to determine relevant variables. The demographic and occupational variables in musculoskeletal injury cases were obtained from records in the database designed by the National Occupational Health Division at Universidad Nacional de Colombia. Results: We identified 99 records of workers with positive diagnosis of upper limb and lower back musculoskeletal injuries. The female gender and age group between 41 to 50 years reported 60% and 43.43% of the cases of musculoskeletal injuries respectively. The percentage of cases by occupational group for teachers and administrative workers showed a similar distribution of 28.28%. We found that repetitive movements of elbow, wrist, fingers for upper limbs and an extended position for lumbar region are the most common risk factors. In workers, wrist and lower back were the most prominent musculoskeletal injuries. Scoliosis and hyperlordosis were spinal disorders more frequent among participants. The improvement and / or disappearance of symptoms with rest and recurrence or worsening during the work time was the more representative criterion for considering the possible cases of occupational origin of musculoskeletal injuries to upper limbs and lower back. Conclusion: The knowledge of these variables associated with musculoskeletal injuries allows for preventive interventions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vargas Porras, P. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Porras, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orjuela Ramírez, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Caracterizar variables demográficas y ocupacionales de casos de lesiones osteomusculares de miembros superiores y región lumbar. Metodología: Estudio descriptivo, corte transversal. Se realizó búsqueda y revisión de literatura científica para conocer factores de riesgo laborales asociados a lesiones osteomusculares de miembros superiores, región lumbar y determinar variables relevantes. Las variables demográficas y ocupacionales en casos de lesiones osteomusculares, se obtuvieron de registros de la base de datos diseñada por la División Nacional de Salud Ocupacional de la Universidad Nacional de Colombia. Resultados: Se identificaron 99 registros de trabajadores con diagnóstico positivo de lesiones osteomusculares de miembros superiores y región lumbar. El género femenino y grupo etáreo entre 41 a 50 años reportó 60% y 43.43% de casos de lesiones osteomusculares respectivamente. El porcentaje de casos según grupo ocupacional para docentes y otros administrativos presentó distribución similar 28.28%. Se encontró que movimientos repetitivos de codo, muñeca, dedos para miembros superiores y postura prolongada para región lumbar son factores de riesgo más frecuentes. En trabajadores los segmentos corporales más comprometidos con lesiones osteomusculares fueron muñeca y zona lumbar. Escoliosis e hiperlordosis fueron las alteraciones de columna vertebral con mayor frecuencia entre la población participante. La mejoría y/o desaparición de los síntomas con descanso y reaparición o agravamiento durante el trabajo fue el criterio más representativo para considerar posible origen laboral de casos de lesiones osteomusculares para miembros superiores y región lumbar. Conclusión: El conocimiento de las variables asociadas a lesiones osteomusculares permite realizar intervenciones preventivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;12(32): 119-146, oct. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115708</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones osteomusculares de miembros superiores y región lumbar: caracterización demográfica y ocupacional. Universidad Nacional de Colombia, Bogotá 2001- 2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54520^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9327^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
