<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153370</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implementation of good quality and safety practices. Descriptive study in a occupational mutual health centre</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To describe the level of implementation of quality and safety good practice elements in a Mutual Society health centre. Method. A Cross-sectional study was conducted to assess the level of implementation of good practices using a questionnaire. Some quality dimensions were also assessed (scale 0 to 10) by a set of 87 quality coordinators of health centres and a random sample of 54 healthcare professionals working in small centres. Results. Seventy quality coordinators and 27 professionals replied (response rates 80% and 50%, respectively. There were no differences in the assessment of quality attributes between both groups. They identified as areas for improvement: use of practice guidelines (7.6/10), scientific and technical skills (7.5/10), and patient satisfaction (7.7/10). Availability and accessibility to clinical reports, informed consent, availability of hydro-alcoholic solution, and to record allergies, were considered of high importance to be implemented, with training and research, improvements in equipment and technology plans, adherence to clinical practice guidelines and the preparation of risk maps, being of less importance. Conclusion. The good practices related to equipment and resources have a higher likelihood to be implemented, meanwhile those related to quality and safety attitudes have more barriers before being implemented. The mutual has a similar behaviour than other healthcare institutions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortner, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzanera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Describir el nivel de implantación de elementos de buena atención sanitaria en una mutua. Método. Estudio descriptivo, transversal. Se encuestó al conjunto de 87 referentes de calidad de MC Mutual y una submuestra aleatoria de 54 sanitarios con destino en centros con entre 4 y 7 profesionales sanitarios. Los 23 elementos del cuestionario fueron seleccionados por su condición de ser identificados como buenas prácticas. Adicionalmente, los sujetos valoraron una serie de atributos que describían el nivel de calidad de los centros (escala de 0 a 10). Resultados. Respondieron 70 referentes y 27 profesionales (tasa respuesta del 80% y 50%, respectivamente). Entre ambos colectivos no hubo diferencias en la valoración de los atributos de calidad. Identificaron como áreas de mejora: uso de guías de práctica (7,6/10), competencia científico-técnica (7,5/10) y satisfacción de los pacientes (7,7/10). Consideraron con alta implantación: disponibilidad y accesibilidad a la historia clínica común, consentimiento informado, disponibilidad de solución hidroalcohólica y sistema de registro de alergias. Con baja implantación: formación e investigación, planes de mejoras en equipamientos y tecnología, adhesión a guías de práctica clínica y mapas de riesgos. Conclusión. Mientras se logra un alto nivel de implantación en elementos de buena práctica relacionados con equipamientos y recursos, otros aspectos relacionados con actitudes hacia la calidad y seguridad requieren de mayor atención, como sucede en otras organizaciones sanitarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;31(3): 168-172, mayo-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153370</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implantación de buenas prácticas en calidad y seguridad. Estudio descriptivo en una mutua laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6435^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
