<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99577</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Environmental biodecontamination with vaporized hydrogen peroxide in the surgical field</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We studied the feasibility of environmental decontamination in the hospital setting with dry steam of hydrogen peroxide produced by VHP-ARD Steris system. It was applied in a general hospital on an Operating Room and an Isolation Room with anteroom, both from the Burn Unit. Exposures were respectively more than 400 ppm for 40 minutes and more than 250 ppm for 89 minutes, being enough for the change of multiple chemical indicators and sterility shown in Geobacillus stearothermophilus biological indicators. In summary, the trial was satisfactory according to the forecasts made (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaquero de la Hoz,  M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Puerta, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fariñas Cabrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se estudió la viabilidad de la descontaminación ambiental en el ámbito hospitalario con vapor seco de peróxido de hidrógeno producido por sistema VHP® ARD de Steris. Se aplicó en un hospital general sobre un quirófano y una habitación de aislamiento con antesala, ambas de la Unidad de Quemados. Las exposiciones fueron respectivamente de más de 400 ppm durante 40 minutos y más de 250 ppm durante 89 minutos, siendo suficientes para el virado de los múltiples indicadores químicos y la esterilidad mostrada en indicadores biológicos de Geobacillus stearothermophilus. En resumen, el ensayo resultó satisfactorio de acuerdo con las previsiones hechas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;14(4): 218-224, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biodescontaminación ambiental con peróxido de hidrógeno vaporizado en el ámbito quirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30037^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28017^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15237</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7015^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27980^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
