<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111396</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characteristics of Asthma Patients Admitted to an Intermediate Respiratory Care Unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Intermediate respiratory care units (IRCU) provide continuous monitoring and non-invasive mechanical ventilation (NIMV) in patients with severe respiratory failure who are usually admitted to intensive care units (ICUs). The usefulness of IRCU in managing severe asthma exacerbations has never been evaluated. Methods: Clinical data were prospectively and systematically compiled from patients admitted to the IRCU with a principal diagnosis of bronchial asthma exacerbation. We assessed therapeutic failure (intubation or exitus) and patient evolution up until 6 months after discharge compared with a group of patients admitted to a conventional hospital ward, paired for age and sex, and with the same principal diagnosis. Results: A total of 74 asthma patients were included (37 admitted to IRCU and 37 to the hospital ward) with a mean age (±SD) of 58±20, who were predominantly women (67%), with previous diagnosis of asthma and persistent asthma treatment. The main cause of admittance to the IRCU was severe respiratory failure. The patients who were admitted to the IRCU presented more radiological affectation (alveolar infiltrates) and had significantly higher pCO2. Ten patients admitted to the IRCU required non-invasive mechanical ventilation (NIMV). There were no differences between the two groups regarding either therapeutic failure or the 6-month follow-up after discharge. Conclusions: Patients with severe asthma exacerbations can be managed in an IRCU while avoiding hospitalization in an ICU and demonstrating a prognosis similar to milder exacerbations treated in conventional hospital wards(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sala, Ernest</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belda, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kersul, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cosío, Borja</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fiorentino, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las unidades de cuidados respiratorios intermedios (UCRI) permiten la monitorización continua y la ventilación mecánica no invasiva (VMNI) en los pacientes con insuficiencia respiratoria grave que habitualmente ingresan en unidades de cuidados intensivos (UCI). La utilidad de las UCRI en el manejo de las agudizaciones graves del asma nunca ha sido evaluada. Métodos: Se recogieron de forma prospectiva y sistemática los datos clínicos de pacientes ingresados en la UCRI con el diagnóstico principal de asma bronquial agudizada, se evaluó el fracaso terapéutico (intubación o fallecimiento) y su evolución hasta 6meses tras el alta, comparada con un grupo de pacientes ingresados en planta de hospitalización convencional pareados por edad y sexo, con el mismo diagnóstico principal. Resultados: Se incluyeron un total de 74 pacientes asmáticos (37 ingresan en la UCRI y 37 en planta) con una edad media (±DE) de 58±20 años, predominantemente mujeres (67%), con diagnóstico previo y tratamiento de asma persistente. La causa principal de ingreso en la UCRI fue insuficiencia respiratoria grave. Los pacientes que ingresaron en la UCRI presentaron más afectación radiológica (infiltrados alveolares) y tenían una pCO2 significativamente mayor. Diez pacientes ingresados en la UCRI precisaron VMNI. No hubo diferencias entre ambos grupos en fracasos terapéuticos, ni en seguimiento a los 6meses del alta. Conclusiones: Los pacientes con agudizaciones graves del asma pueden ser atendidos en una UCRI, evitando ingresos en la UCI y con un pronóstico similar a las agudizaciones más leves que son ingresadas en una planta de hospitalización convencional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;49(4): 146-150, abr. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111396</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de pacientes asmáticos ingresados en una unidad de cuidados respiratorios intermedios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7545^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15097^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7545^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32868^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7545^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27866^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
