<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104340</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Renal length estimation by ultrasound is an important parameter in clinical evaluation of kidney disease and healthy donors. Changes in renal volume may be a sign of kidney disease. Correct interpretation of renal length requires the knowledge of normal limits, these have not been described for Latin American population. Objective: To describe normal renal length (RL) by ultrasonography in a group of Mexican adults. Methods: Ultrasound measure of RL in 153 healthy Mexican adults stratified by age. Describe the association of RL to several anthropometric variables. Results: A total of 77 males and 76 females were scanner. The average age for the group was 44.12 ± 15.44 years. The mean weight, body mass index (BMI) and height were 68.87 ± 11.69 Kg, 26.77 ± 3.82 kg/m2 and 160 ± 8.62 cm respectively. Dividing the population by gender, showed a height of 166 ± 6.15 cm for males and 154.7 ± 5.97 cm for females (p =0.00). Left renal length (LRL) in the whole group was 105.8 ± 7.56 mm and right renal length (RRL) was 104.3 ± 6.45 mm (p = 0.000). The LRL for males was 107.16 ± 6.97 mm and for females was 104.6 ± 7.96 mm. The average RRL for males was 105.74 ± 5.74 mm and for females 102.99 ± 6.85 mm (p = 0.008). We noted that RL decreased with age and the rate of decline accelerates alter 60 years of age. Both lengths correlated significantly and positively with weight, BMI and height. Conclusions: The RL was significantly larger in males than in females in both kidneys (p = 0.036) in this Mexican population. Renal length declines after 60 years of age and specially after 70 years (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oyuela-Carrasco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kimura, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera-Félix,  J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado-Hernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Castellanos, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la estimación del tamaño renal por ultrasonografía es un parámetro importante en la evaluación clínica y en el manejo de pacientes adultos con enfermedad renal y adultos sanos donadores. El cambio en el tamaño renal puede ser una evidencia muy sugerente de enfermedad, por lo que su interpretación requiere de parámetros específicos para la población a estudiar. En el caso de América Latina, no se han descrito parámetros normales. Objetivo: describir parámetros normales de Longitud Renal (LR) por ultrasonografía en una población mexicana adulta. Métodos: medición ultrasonográfica de LR en 153 adultos sanos estratificados por edad. Se investigó la posible asociación de la LR con parámetros antropométricos. Resultados: se estudiaron 77varones y 76 mujeres; la edad promedio fue de 44,12 ± 15,44años. El promedio de peso, Índice de Masa Corporal (IMC) y talla fue de 68,87 ± 11,69 kg, 26,77 ± 3,82 kg/m2y 160 ± 8,62cm, respectivamente. Al dividir a la población estudiada por género, encontramos que la talla fue de 166 ± 6,15 cm para varones y 154,7 ± 5,97 cm para mujeres, (p = 0,00). La Longitud Renal Izquierda (LRI) en el grupo total fue de 105,8 ±7,56 mm, y la Longitud Renal Derecha (LRD), de 104,3 ± 6,45mm (p = 0,000). La LRI en varones fue de 107,16 ± 6,97 mm, y en mujeres, de 104,6 ± 7,96 mm. La media de la LRD en varones fue de 105,74 ± 5,74 mm y en mujeres, de 102,99 ±6,85 mm, (p = 0,008). La LR disminuyó con la edad, y la tasa de disminución parece aumentar después de los 60 años. Las LR se correlacionaron de forma significativa y positiva con el peso, el IMC y la talla. Conclusiones: la LR fue significativamente mayor en varones que en mujeres para ambos riñones (p = 0,036). La LR disminuyó continuamente con la edad, especialmente después de los 60 años y de forma significativa después de los 70 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;29(1): 30-34, ene.-feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104340</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Longitud renal por ultrasonografía en población mexicana adulta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10107</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7840^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
