<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107099</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-4712</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychosocial factors associated with the well-being of colombian immigrants to Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This research is an empirical study with quantitative methodology that studies the relationship of various psychosocial variables usually linked to migration processes, with life satisfaction and self-esteem of immigrants from Colombia in Spain. The sample (N = 281) was obtained through a non probabilistic sampling, using the technique of snowball, carried out with the collaboration of Non Governmental Organizations dedicated to the support of immigrants in several Spanish cities. As was expected, life satisfaction is negatively related with perceived group prejudice and perceived personal discrimination, especially with the first. Life satisfaction is positively related with perceived material well-being. Self-esteem meanwhile is positively correlated with Colombian national identity. Self esteem is also correlated significantly and negatively with perceived group prejudice and perceived personal discrimination, although the latter two variables could not explain statistically the first. These results support in general terms the formulated hypotheses, but with some caveats that are presented and explained. Those results are analyzed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molero Alonso, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo Muñoz, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presente investigación constituye un estudio empírico con metodología cuantitativa que estudia la relación de diversas variables psicosociales generalmente vinculadas a procesos migratorios, con la satisfacción con la vida y la autoestima de inmigrantes de origen colombiano en España. La muestra (N = 281) se obtuvo a través de un muestreo no probabilístico, mediante la técnica de la bola de nieve, realizado con la colaboración de Organizaciones No Gubernamentales dedicadas al apoyo de inmigrantes en varias ciudades españolas. Como se esperaba, la satisfacción con la vida se relaciona negativamente con el prejuicio grupal percibido y la discriminación personal percibida, en especial con el primero. La satisfacción con la vida se relaciona positivamente con el bienestar material percibido. La autoestima por su parte, se correlaciona positivamente con la identidad con la nacionalidad colombiana. La autoestima se correlaciona también en forma significativa y negativa con el prejuicio grupal percibido y la discriminación personal percibida, si bien estas dos últimas variables no pudieron explicar estadísticamente la primera. Estos resultados apoyan en términos generales las hipótesis formuladas, si bien con algunas salvedades que se presentan y explican. Tales resultados son analizados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc. (Internet);21(3): 319-329, sept.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107099</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores psicosociales asociados al bienestar de inmigrantesde origen colombiano en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13330^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
