<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-059022</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proinflammatory cytokine gene overexpression in macrophages of patients with familial hypercholesterolemia and tendon xanthomas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective. Approximately 30%-50% of patients with genetic diagnosis of heterozygous familial hypercholesterolemia (FH) present tendon xanthomas (TX), but the mechanism by which some subjects develop TX and others do not is unknown. Previously, we have shown that macrophages of FH subjects with and without TX develop a different inflammatory response to oxidized LDL (oxLDL). Therefore, the objective of this work was to analyze the gene expression of several inflammatory molecules that could be involved in the onset and development of TX. Material and methods. Ten FH patients were selected, and the antero-posterior Achilles tendon diameter was measured with high resolution sonography. Their monocytes were isolated from 40 ml of peripheral blood. When they were differentiated to macrophages, were supplemented with 50 µg/ml of oxLDL for 1, 3, 6 and 18 hours. The gene expression of PPAR*, IL-8, IL-1ß, CXCL3, tryptase, NF-*BIA and TNF-* was analyzed with real time RT-PCR. Results and conclusion. The FH subjects with TX (FH TX+) showed a tendency to over-express IL-8 gene after 18 h of incubation with oxLDL, while FH subjects without TX (FH TX­) tended to over-express TNF-* gene after 1 h of incubation. CXCL3 gene was significantly over-expressed at all incubation times with oxLDL in FH TX+ group. Furthermore, a positive correlation was found between CXCL3 gene expression and Achilles tendon size, being maximum at 3h of treatment with oxLDL (R = 0.782; p = 0.008). These results would suggest that CXCL3 could play an important role in the ethiology of xanthomas and could be considered as a possible predictor marker of these lipid deposits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cenarro, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Fuentes, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jarauta, Estíbaliz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calmarza, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Otín, Ángel-Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Civeira, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solanas-Barca, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo. Entre el 30 y el 50% de los sujetos con diagnóstico genético de hipercolesterolemia familiar (HF) heterocigota presentan xantomas tendinosos (XT), pero el mecanismo por el cual unos sujetos HF desarrollan XT y otros no se desconoce. Previamente, nuestro grupo de investigación ha demostrado que los macrófagos de sujetos HF con y sin XT desarrollan una respuesta inflamatoria diferente frente a lipoproteínas de baja densidad oxidadas (LDLox). Por ello, el objetivo de este trabajo fue analizar la expresión génica de diversas moléculas inflamatorias que podrían estar involucradas en la aparición y desarrollo de XT. Material y métodos. Se seleccionó a 10 pacientes con diagnóstico genético de HF, en los que se midió el diámetro anteroposterior del tendón de Aquiles mediante ecografía de alta resolución. Se aislaron sus monocitos a partir de 40 ml de sangre periférica. Una vez diferenciados a macrófagos, se suplementaron con 50 µg/ml de LDLox durante 1, 3, 6 y 18 h. Mediante RT-PCR en tiempo real, se analizó la expresión de los genes PPAR*, IL-8, IL-1ß, CXCL3, triptasa, NF-*BIA y TNF-*. Resultados y conclusión. Los sujetos HF con XT (HF XT+) mostraron una tendencia a sobreexpresar el gen IL-8 tras 18 h de incubación con LDLox, mientras que el grupo de sujetos HF sin XT (HF XT­) tendió a sobreexpresar el gen TNF-* tras 1 h de incubación con LDLox. El gen CXCL3 se sobreexpresó significativamente en todos los tiempos de incubación en el grupo HF XT+. Además, se halló una correlación positiva entre la expresión de CXCL3 y el tamaño del tendón de Aquiles, que fue máxima a 3 h del tratamiento con LDLox (R = 0,782; p = 0,008). Estos resultados sugieren que CXCL3 podría desempeñar un papel importante en la etiología de los xantomas, y se puede considerar como un posible marcador predictor de estos depósitos lipídicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);20(1): 14-21, ene. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-059022</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sobreexpresión génica de citocinas proinflamatorias en macrófagos de sujetos con hipercolesterolemia familiar y xantomas tendinosos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28995</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24369^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24369^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d134^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29490</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7118^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24666^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
