<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139967</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to describe symptom control extent in terminally iII patients based on specific diagnostic tools such as the Edmonton Symptom Assessment System (ESAS) and Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). To analyze whether some symptoms are associated with poor survival. Material and methods: this was a longitudinal prospective study in terminally ilI patients fram Badajoz (Spain) who were included in the Regional Palliative Care Program. They were cared for by the Palliative Care Team for a month. Karnofsky Index, first inclusion visit, last visit and demise data, first and last ESAS control, first and last HADS score, and initial assessment with TQSS were collected. Also, to observe improvement in symptomatic control a matched mean comparison test was used. Finally, the Kaplan Meyer procedure was applied for a survival analysis. Results: twenty-five patients were included in the study. Initially, the worst controlled symptoms were asthenia X = 5.3 (3.79-6.82), sadness 7.35 (6.50-8.20) and well-being 6.27 (4.90-7.64). Alter care by a Palliative Care Team symptom severity decreased except for asthenia. We also used the HADS test for measuring clinical anxiety and depression, and obtained the following scores: first meeting X = 23.21 (95% CI: 19.75.26.67) and last visit 19.73 (15.79-23.68). Regarding how survival was affected by dypsnea, we observed that it was longer when dyspnea was not initially present (40 days and 24 days, respectively); log-rank p: 0.0007. Conclusions: there was a statistically significant improvement in symptoms such as depression, anxiety and well-being after a Palliative Care Team intervention. ESAS and HADS are two useful tools for monitoring symptoms. Short survival was associated with the presence of dyspnea and depression (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mota Vargas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Correas, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Jiménez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuervo Pinna, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Moralo, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: describir el grado de control sintomático de enfermos oncológicos terminales, basándonos en herramientas diagnósticas específicas (ESAS y HAD). Analizar si algunos síntomas se asocian con una menor supervivencia. Material y métodos: estudio longitudinal prospectivo de pacientes atendidos por el ESCP de Badajoz durante un mes. Se incluyen: índice de Karnofsky, fechas de primera visita, última visita y éxitus, ESAS inicial y final, HAD inicial y final y TQSS inicial. Para observar el grado de mejoría sintomática, desarrollamos el test apareado de comparación de medias (Stata9). Se utilizaron las tablas de Kaplan Meyer para el análisis de supervivencia. Resultados: se incluyeron 25 pacientes. El nivel de intensidad de los síntomas (ESAS) reveló Que inicialmente los síntomas peor controlados fueron la astenia: X = 5,3 (3,79-6,82), la tristeza: 7,35 (6,50-8,20) y el bienestar, 6,27 (4,90-7,64). Con la intervención del ESCP disminuyó la intensidad de los síntomas excepto la astenia. Cuando empleamos el cuestionario específico HAD para monitorizar la depresión y ansiedad, se comprobó: X = 23.21 (lC 95%,19,75.26,67), en la última visita 19,73 05,79-23,681. En relación a la existencia de disnea la mediana de supervivencia fue de 40 días, si no había disnea inicial, frente a 24, cuando estaba presente (p long. rank: 0,00071. Conclusiones: tras la intervención del ESCP se asistió a una mejoría sintomática, estadísticamente significativa en la depresión, ansiedad y bienestar. El ESAS y el HAD como herramientas diagnósticas fueron útiles para la monitorización de síntomas. La disnea y la depresión se asociaron con una supervivencia inferior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;17(2): 96-102, mar.-abr. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Control de síntomas por un equipo de soporte de cuidados paliativos. Resultados preliminares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24890</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55021^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
