<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-35152</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nogo-A functions during the development of the central nervous system and in the adult</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The myelin-associated inhibitors play a very important role in preventing the regeneration of the adult central nervous system. Among these inhibitors it is Nogo-A, a recently cloned protein expressed by oligodendrocytes. However, after its discovery as a myelin-associated protein, there has been described new functions for Nogo-A far from its role in the oligodendrocytes myelin. Development. After an introduction to the molecular changes that occur after a central nervous system (CNS) injury we focus in the figure of Nogo-A and its family of proteins. Finally, we make a revision of the different functions that have been described to date for Nogo-A, from the development of the CNS to the inhibition of axonal regeneration in the adult, highlighting the therapeutic potential of the selective blockade of Nogo-A. Conclusions. Although Nogo-A was discovered in the context of axonal growth inhibition, in which it is indeed playing a determining role, Nogo-A has turned out to be also a neuronal protein involved in diverse processes that go from axonal fasciculation to apoptosis. As we deepened in our knowledge about the molecular mechanisms that organize the complex functioning of the CNS, it is clearer that the proteins implicated in fasciculation and axonal guidance during development also play equally important roles in mechanisms like the axonal inhibition or the regulation of the synaptic plasticity in the adult CNS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Los inhibidores asociados a la mielina desempeñan un papel muy importante a la hora de impedir la regeneración axonal del sistema nervioso central (SNC) en el animal adulto. Dentro de estos inhibidores destaca Nogo-A, una proteína recientemente identificada con expresión en oligodendrocitos. Sin embargo, tras su descubrimiento como proteína asociada a la mielina, se han empezado a describir nuevas funciones para Nogo-A que distan mucho de su papel en la mielina de los oligodendrocitos. Desarrollo. Tras una introducción a los cambios moleculares que tienen lugar después de una lesión en el SNC, nos centramos en la figura de Nogo-A y su familia de proteínas. Finalmente, hacemos un repaso de las diferentes funciones que hasta la fecha se han descrito para Nogo-A, desde el desarrollo del SNC hasta la inhibición de la regeneración en el adulto, y haremos hincapié en el potencial terapéutico que representa el bloqueo de Nogo-A. Conclusiones. Aunque Nogo-A se descubriera en el contexto de la inhibición del crecimiento axonal, y efectivamente desempeñe un papel determinante en esta inhibición, Nogo-A ha resultado ser también una proteína neuronal implicada en diversos procesos durante el desarrollo y en el adulto, que van desde la fasciculación axonal hasta la apoptosis. A medida que profundizamos en nuestro conocimiento sobre los mecanismos moleculares que organizan el complejo funcionamiento del SNC, resulta más claro que las proteínas que se implican en fasciculación y guía axonal durante el desarrollo llevan a cabo en el SNC adulto funciones igualmente importantes en procesos como la inhibición axonal o la regulación de la plasticidad sináptica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;39(5): 440-446, sept. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Funciones de Nogo-A durante el desarrollo del sistema nervioso central y en el animal adulto</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Del Río, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mingorance, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-35152</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9666</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d916</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9378</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9377</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28186</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9609</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
