<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127035</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiation safety in orthopaedic operating theatres. what is the current situation?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyse the exposure of two Orthopaedic Surgeons to ionizing radiations in their daily work, and to review the main national and international recommendations on this subject. Material and methods. A retrospective study was conducted on the surgical treatments that use fluoroscopy performed by two Orthopaedic Surgeons during a one year period. An evaluation was made of the radiation received, based on measurements of the processes published in the bibliography section. A literature review of international recommendations and regulations is also presented. Results. The radiation received by the two Orthopaedic Surgeons during one year did not exceed the limits of present-day legislation or the new European and international recommendations. The exposure was asymmetrical, with the hands being the most radiated part. The new recommendations reduce the permitted level of radiation on eyes. Discussion. The evaluation of the radiation received demonstrates the need for radiation protection, paying particular attention to the hands and eyes. Good knowledge of operating a fluoroscope and radiation safety measures are also essential (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Barrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas Laso, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Salvador, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mingo-Robinet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Torres, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burón Álvarez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar la exposición a radiaciones ionizantes por parte de dos cirujanos ortopédicos en su práctica diaria y revisar las principales recomendaciones nacionales e internacionales al respecto. Material y método. Se efectúo un estudio retrospectivo de la actividad quirúrgica con uso de fluoroscopia realizado por dos cirujanos ortopédicos en un año. Se calculó la radiación recibida basándose en mediciones por procesos publicados en la bilbliografía. Revisión bibliográfica de recomendaciones y normativas internacionales. Resultado. La radiación recibida en un año por los dos cirujanos ortopédicos no sobrepasó el límite de la legislación actual ni el de las nuevas recomendaciones europeas e internacionales. La exposición fue asimétrica, siendo las manos la zona más radiada. Las nuevas recomendaciones rebajan los niveles permitidos de radiación en ojos. Discusión. La estimación de radiación recibida hace necesario proteger y vigilar especialmente las manos y los ojos. Son necesarios conocimientos del funcionamiento del fluoroscopio y de las medidas de radioprotección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(5): 309-313, sept.-oct. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radioprotección en quirófanos de traumatología: ¿en qué situación estamos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12276^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32403^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10055^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32513</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12276^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12311^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12311^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12311^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12311^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12266</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12276^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12276^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35486</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
