<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145323</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Short, medium and long-term follow-up of living donors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Live-donor kidney transplants are being done since more than fifty years ago. In recent years, a marked increase in live donations is observed, as a result of the limited availability of organs from deceased donors. Also, the use of laparoscopic nephrectomy has contributed to increase live donations. A systematic review of the literature shows that short and long-term risks of morbidity and mortality of the donor are reasonably low. Even so, an increased incidence of high blood pressure and mild proteinuria has been reported. On the contrary, no detrimental effect on renal failure is observed and the incidence of long-term chronic renal failure is lower in the donor population when compared with the incidence observed in the general population. In any case, a regular follow-up of the donors is advisable in order to prevent or early detect those medical conditions that would represent a health risk, in particular those conditions that possibly will affect renal function: hypertension, diabetes, proteinuria and obesity. It would be also necessary to establish a nation-wide scientific registry, with prospective regular data collection, that will make possible a more accurate assessment of the long-term risk of uninephrectomy and early detection of new medical information that would contribute to redefine the risk of kidney donation or to establish new requisites in the donor evaluation protocols (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oppenheimer Salinas, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hace más de 50 años que se vienen practicando trasplantes renales de donante vivo, pero en años recientes el incremento de la demanda y la introducción de la nefrectomía por vía laparoscópica se han traducido en un significativo aumento de este tipo de trasplantes. Aunque la experiencia publicada demuestra que la morbilidad y mortalidad del donante, a corto y a largo plazo, es razonablemente baja, existen evidencias de que algunos donantes pueden presentar un ligero incremento de presión arterial o proteinuria, sin afectar a la función renal remanente. A largo plazo, la incidencia de insuficiencia renal en los donantes renales es inferior a la observada en la población general. Es aconsejable hacer un seguimiento clínico periódico de los donantes para prevenir o tratar los factores de riesgo y/o de complicaciones clínicas intercurrentes que pudieran comprometer su salud en general y en especial la función renal: hipertensión arterial, diabetes, proteinuria y obesidad. También es preciso disponer de un registro científico prospectivo nacional de todos los donantes, con el fin de analizar el impacto a largo plazo de la uninefrectomía y detectar, en su caso, las posibles señales de alarma que ayudarán a modificar los criterios actuales de valoración y aceptación de los candidatos a donación y/o el cuidado clínico de nuestros donantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;30(supl.2): 100-105, feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145323</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento del donante vivo a corto, medio y largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50495^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
