<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139111</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infection with Mycobacterium tuberculosis is highly prevalent and is closely related to migration. It mainly affects lungs, but can also involve other organs such as the central nervous system. This neurologic complication is accompanied by a high morbidity and mortality. Tuberculomas are considered one form of presentation in the brain, and could be diagnosed by needle aspiration or surgical biopsy when they are accessible, or through imaging techniques. In the case of meningeal involvement, study of the cerebrospinal fluid is required for the diagnosis. Anti-tuberculosis drugs and corticosteroids are mainly used for the treatment of tuberculomas, but depending on the clinical situation, surgical procedures could also be performed. To prevent complications, especially in immunocompromised patients, early suspect and diagnosis is important to start immediately the administration of anti-tuberculosis drugs. We report the case of a 41-year-old-man immunocompetent who was diagnosed of pulmonary and cerebral tuberculosis and who was effectively treated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Redondo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez-Sala Walther, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artiles Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carpio Segura, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección por Mycobacterium tuberculosis tiene una alta prevalencia y está en íntima relación con la migración. Afecta fundamentalmente al pulmón, pero también a otros órganos, como el sistema nervioso central, conllevando una alta morbilidad y mortalidad. Se considera a los tuberculomas una forma de presentación a nivel cerebral, diagnosticándose mediante punción-aspiración o biopsia quirúrgica cuando es accesible o a través de técnicas de imagen. En caso de afectación meníngea, es obligado el estudio del líquido cefalorraquídeo. En función de la clínica, el tratamiento de los tuberculomas será quirúrgico o predominantemente farmacológico con cuatro antituberculostáticos y corticoides. Para la prevención de complicaciones, especialmente en inmunocomprometidos, es fundamental el diagnóstico precoz así como el tratamiento inmediato ante la mínima sospecha clínica. Presentamos el caso de un paciente varón de 41 años inmunocompetente que, tras estudio radiológico y microbiológico, se diagnosticó de tuberculosis pulmonar y cerebral y que mejoró satisfactoriamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;18(1): 35-37, ene.-mar. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139111</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tuberculosis pulmonar y cerebral en un paciente inmunocompetente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2526^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2526^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2526^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2526^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
