<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84311</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of emotional intelligence in stress, emotional dissonance and performance of flight attendants</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of work was to design a procedure which allows to simulate, with realism, potentially stressful, frequent and real situations with passengers and analyse the role of emotional intelligence in perceived stress, emotional dissonance, perceived difficulty and performance of flight attendants in the face of disruptive passengers. Every one of the participants, 18 flight attendants, by a role-play, interacted with 2 actors, a man and a woman, acted as passengers, in four scenarios (2 situations, a passenger who has placed his suitcase next to one of the emergency exits and a passenger who has been smoking in the toilette and two types of passenger x 2 types of conflictive passengers, category type I or category type II according to the classification carried out by Federal Aviation Administration). The procedure simulated situations potentially stressful, what have been performed with realism and the conflictive situations caused more perceived stress, emotional dissonance and perceived difficulty. The component clarity of TMMS-24 had positive relationships with perceived stress, emotional dissonance and perceived difficulty and negative relationships with performance, measured by non verbal communication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Castro, Jodi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñar Chelso, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del trabajo ha consistido en diseñar un procedimiento que simule, con realismo, situaciones potencialmente estresantes, frecuentes y verídicas con pasajeros, que permita analizar el papel de la inteligencia emocional en el estrés, la disonancia emocional, la dificultad percibida y el rendimiento de los tripulantes de cabina de pasajeros frente a pasajeros conflictivos. Cada uno de los participantes, 18 tripulantes de cabina de pasajeros, mediante un juego de roles interactuaban con dos actores, un hombre y una mujer que hacían de pasajeros, en cuatro escenarios (2 situaciones, un pasajero que había colocado su equipaje en una ventana de emergencia y un pasajero que había estado fumando en el lavabo x 2 tipos de pasajeros conflictivos, categoría tipo I o tipo II establecida por la Federal Aviation Administration). El procedimiento simuló situaciones potencialmente estresantes que fueron percibidas con realismo y las situaciones conflictivas causaron más estrés percibido, disonancia emocional y dificultad percibida. El componente comprensión del TMMS-24 mostró relaciones positivas con estrés percibido, disonancia emocional y dificultad percibida y negativas con rendimiento, medido a través de la comunicación no verbal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(1): 65-70, ene.-abr. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La influencia de la inteligencia emocional en el estrés, la disonancia emocional y el rendimiento de tripulantes de cabina de pasajeros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9975</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30459^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22322</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
