<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92332</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stauffer syndrome in transitional cell carcinoma of the bladder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To present the case of a woman with the diagnosis of transitional cell carcinoma of the bladder and Stauffer´s syndrome.METHOD: The clinical and radiological files were analyzed, and a bibliographic review was performed.RESULTS: We present an 82 year old female with a four month history of hematuria, presenting in the emergency room where abnormal hepatic profile was documented. The diagnosis of bladder tumor was established and she underwent transurethral bladder resection. The pathological report showed transitional cell bladder cancer, with complete resection. Metastasis and infectious hepatic dysfunction were discarded. The hepatic profile became normal days later, so Stauffer´s syndrome diagnosis was performed.CONCLUSION: This is the first report to our knowledge of this paraneoplastic syndrome in transitional cell carcinoma of the bladder</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo-Belasteguigoitia, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Palacios, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Aranda, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wingartz-Plata, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar el caso clínico de una mujer con cáncer de células transicionales de vejiga y síndrome de Stauffer.MÉTODO: Se realizó revisión del expediente clínico y radiológico así como una revisión de la literatura.RESULTADO: Mujer de 82 años de edad la cual presenta un cuadro de hematuria de cuatro meses de evolución, a su ingreso a urgencias se le encuentra hepatopatía por laboratorio. Se realiza el diagnóstico por imagen de un tumor vesical por lo fue sometida a una resección transuretral de vejiga teniendo como resultado un cáncer de células transicionales de vejiga, se descartó que la hepatopatía se asociara a metástasis o cuadro infeccioso, los parámetros hepáticos mejoraron posterior a la remoción total del tumor, motivo por el cual se concluyó que se debía a un síndrome de Stauffer.CONCLUSIÓN: Este representa el primer reporte de este síndrome paraneoplásico asociado a cáncer de células transicionales de vejiga(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;64(9): 911-913, nov. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Stauffer en cáncer de células transicionales de vejiga</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6566^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2338^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10445^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
