<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83498</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of Scalp Psoriasis: Review of the Evidence and Delphi Consensus of the Psoriasis Group of the Spanish Academy of Dermatology and Venereology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Scalp lesions are common in psoriasis and difficult to treat. Scientific evidence on the topic is scant and fragmentary, especially with respect to long-term treatment. This consensus statement is based on a critical assessment of the results of a MEDLINE search for clinical trials of the efficacy and safety of therapies used to treat scalp psoriasis. The recommendations were developed by an expert panel using the Delphi process to reach a consensus and then ratified by the members of the Psoriasis Group of the Spanish Academy of Dermatology and Venereology. The recommended induction therapy for scalp psoriasis is either a topical corticosteroid or a topical treatment combining calcipotriol and betamethasone. The choice of an appropriate vehicle is crucial in improving effectiveness and patient adherence to treatment. The only formulations that have been studied in the long-term treatment of scalp psoriasis are a combination of calcipotriol and betamethasone in gel and calcipotriol alone in solution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Linares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Juanes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colomé, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernanz, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballé, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Querol, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belinchón, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La afectación del cuero cabelludo resulta frecuente y de difícil tratamiento en los pacientes con psoriasis, siendo escasa y poco sistematizada la evidencia científica al respecto, en particular por lo que se refiere al tratamiento a largo plazo. En el presente documento de consenso, basado en una búsqueda (MEDLINE) de los ensayos clínicos publicados sobre la eficacia y seguridad de los diferentes tratamientos para la psoriasis del cuero cabelludo y su evaluación, se establecen unas recomendaciones, partiendo de un consenso Delphi por parte de un panel de expertos, refrendado por los miembros del Grupo de Psoriasis de la Academia Española de Dermatología y Venereología. El tratamiento de inducción recomendado para la psoriasis del cuero cabelludo son los corticoides tópicos y la combinación de calcipotriol/betametasona. La elección de un vehículo apropiado es decisiva para incrementar la eficacia y el cumplimiento del paciente. Únicamente la combinación de calcipotriol/betametasona en gel y el calcipotriol en solución se han estudiado en el tratamiento de la psoriasis del cuero cabelludo a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;101(10): 827-846, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83498</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la psoriasis del cuero cabelludo. Revisión de la evidencia y Consenso Delphi del Grupo de Psoriasis de la Academia Española de Dermatología y Venereología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12917</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22355^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
