<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83766</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical evolution of breastfeeding. Rights and family conciliation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human milk has been and it is an important means of survival for the human being. The history of the breastfeeding has been linked to the woman's social and cultural situation and it has gone by different vicissitudes. During a long period the breastfeeding was considered as an unsightly, unworthy practice and characteristic of low classes, women that had resources nurses used. In the xix century artificial nursing appears that will be developed significantly starting from half-filled of the following century, relegating, again, to a second plane to the natural nursing. With the beginning of the xx century the first rights of the workers appear and among them it is regulated the right for the first time to the permission for nursing. With the advance of the century diverse norms enlarge their content. Arriving to the current moment in which the right enjoys a wide legal recognition inside the norms that regulate the family reconciliation(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toro Flores, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La leche humana ha sido y es un importante medio de supervivencia para el ser humano. La historia de la lactancia materna ha estado unida a la situación social y cultural de la mujer y ha pasado por distintas vicisitudes. Durante un largo periodo fue considerada como una práctica antiestética, indigna y propia de clases bajas; las mujeres que disponían de recursos utilizaban nodrizas. En el siglo xix aparece la lactancia artificial que se desarrollará de forma importante a partir de mediados del siglo siguiente, relegando, de nuevo, a un segundo plano a la lactancia natural. Con el inicio del siglo xx aparecen los primeros derechos de los trabajadores y entre ellos se regula por primera vez el derecho al permiso para lactancia. Con el avance del siglo diversas normas amplían su contenido. Así se llega al momento actual en el que el derecho goza de un amplio reconocimiento legal dentro de las normas que regulan la conciliación familiar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(12): 840-846, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83766</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución histórica de la lactancia materna. Derechos y conciliación familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13327^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29909^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38404^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38404^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29909^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29038^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29038^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50338</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7952^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13327^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
