<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040160</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">ICU Nursing discharge report is a useful record to guarantee the continuity of cares on the patient's discharge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the ICUs of Spain that fill out nursing discharge report, analyze what information they supply and know how the information on the patients is provided by the ICUs that do not use this record. Material and methods: Observational descriptive study. The nursing discharge reports issued by the ICUs were analyzed. For the units that did not fill them out, it was documented how they provided information on the patient to the ward. Results: A total of 259 ICU (83%) responded and 176 (68%) filled out the nursing discharge report, which was sent with the patient's history in all the units. A total of 99% of the reports included information on the eating and elimination needs and 7% on living according to beliefs in their structure. One hundred percent requested information on the perception/control and nutritional/metabolic patterns; 1% on sexuality/reproduction. Forty three (54%) of the 79 ICU (30%) that did not fill out a nursing discharge report accompanied the patient to the ward and gave an oral report. In all, 242 ICU (93%) provided information to the ward professionals added to that contained in the clinical history. Conclusions: a) the nursing professionals in a significant number of intensive care units filled out a discharge report when the patient was transferred to the ward; b) assessment of basic biological aspects prevailed in these reports over psychological and socioculture aspects; c) the units that did not fill out a discharge report accompany the patient to the ward or give a report by telephone of the patient's situations to the destination ward; and d) most of the ICUs guarantee the continuity of nursing cares when the patient is discharged, either by filling out a nursing discharge report, accompanying the patient to the ward or calling by telephone to the ward's professionals</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Haro Marín, Salvador de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Arnedo, Jesús M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orgiler Uranga, Pedro E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El informe de alta de enfermería de unidad de cuidados intensivos (UCI) es un registro que se utiliza para garantizar la continuidad de los cuidados al alta del paciente. Objetivos: Determinar las UCI de España que cumplimentan informe de alta de enfermería, analizar qué información aportan éstos y conocer cómo las UCI que no utilizan este registro transmiten la información acerca del paciente. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo observacional. Se analizaron los informes de alta de enfermería emitidos por las UCI. Para las unidades que no lo cumplimentaban se documentó cómo facilitaban a planta información acerca del paciente. Resultados: Respondieron 259 (83%) UCI. 176 (68%) cumplimentaban informe de alta de enfermería, que se enviaba con la historia del paciente en todas las unidades. El 99% de los informes recogía en su estructura información acerca de las necesidades de alimentación y eliminación y el 7% acerca de vivir según creencias. El 100% solicitaba información sobre los patrones de percepción/control y nutricional/metabólico; el 1% sobre sexualidad/reproducción. De las 79 (30%) UCI que no cumplimentaban informe de alta de enfermería, en 43 (54%) acompañaban al paciente a planta y daban un relevo oral. En total 242 (93%) UCI transmiten información añadida a la que contiene la historia clínica a los profesionales de planta. Conclusiones: a) en un número importante de unidades de cuidados intensivos los profesionales de enfermería cumplimentan un informe de alta a la salida del paciente a planta; b) en estos informes predomina la valoración de aspectos biológicos básicos sobre los psicológicos y socioculturales; c) en las unidades que no cumplimentan informe de alta, acompañan al paciente a planta o bien informan por teléfono de la situación del paciente a la planta de destino, y d) la mayoría de UCI garantiza la continuidad en los cuidados de enfermería al alta del paciente, bien sea cumplimentando un informe de alta de enfermería, acompañando al paciente a planta o llamando por teléfono a los profesionales de ésta</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;16(2): 62-72, abr. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Informes de alta de enfermería de cuidados intensivos en España: situación actual y análisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37685^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28202^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
