<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133468</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effect of Saccharomyces boulardii in patients eligible for liver transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to evaluate the influence of Saccharomyces boulardii on the intestinal permeability, laboratory parameters and MELD and Child-Pugh severity scores in cirrhotic patients eligible for liver transplantation. Methods: Eighteen patients followed in a Transplant Outpatient Clinic were evaluated immediately before the beginning of treatment, after a 30-day period of treatment period with probiotics and at the end of the second study month (after a thirty-day period without probiotics). Fifteen healthy controls also underwent the intestinal permeability test (lactulose/mannitol). Results: Before the probiotic, the median lactulose/ mannitol ratio was greater in the cirrhotic patients (0.0209, range 0.0012-0.1984) compared to the healthy controls (0.0030, range 0.0020-0.0013) (p &lt; 0.05). Eight of fifteen patients, half of whom had ascites, showed increased intestinal permeability above the higher value observed in the controls. No significant association was found between the severity scores for liver disease, age, presence of ascites and intestinal permeability immediately before the beginning of study. After treatment with S. boulardii, there was no improvement in intestinal permeability or significant differences in the laboratory parameters for the three evaluations. Conclusions: Patients eligible for liver transplants presented with increased intestinal permeability compared to healthy controls. A thirty-day treatment with S boulardii did not improve this intestinal permeability or the severity scores, nor did it impact the laboratory parameters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Correia, Maria Isabel Toulson Davisson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilela, Eduardo Garcia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrari, Maria de Lourdes Abreu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima, Agnaldo Soares</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liboredo, Juliana Costa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la influencia del Saccharomyces boulardii en la permeabilidad intestinal, parámetros bioquímicos, de MELD y de Child-Pugh en pacientes cirróticos candidatos al trasplante de hígado. Métodos: Dieciocho pacientes seguidos en ambulatorio de Transplantes fueron evaluados inmediatamente antes del inicio del tratamento con probióticos, después de período de 30 días con probióticos y al final del segundo mes de estudio (período de treinta días sin probióticos). Quince controles sanos también se sometieron a la prueba de permeabilidad intestinal (lactulosa/manitol).  Resultados: Antes del probiótico, la relación de lactulosa / manitol media fue mayor en los pacientes cirróticos (0,0209; 0,0012-0,1984) en comparación con los controles sanos (0,0030; 0,0020-0,0013) (p &lt; 0,05). Ocho de los quince pacientes, la mitad de los cuales tenía ascitis, presentaron con aumento de la permeabilidad intestinal por encima del valor más alto observado en los controles. No se observó asociación significativa entre los critérios de Meld, Child-Pugh y la edad, la presencia de ascitis y la permeabilidad intestinal inmediatamente antes del inicio del estudio. El tratamiento con S. boulardii, no resultó en mejoría de la permeabilidad intestinal, de los critérios de Meld y Child-Pugh así como de los los parámetros bioquímicos a lo largo de las tres evaluaciones. Conclusiones: Pacientes en lista de espera para transplantes hepático presentan mayor permeabilidad intestinal en comparación con los controles sanos. El tratamiento de treinta días con S. boulardii no resultó en mejoria de la permeabilidad intestinal, del MELD y Child-Pugh, asi como de los parâmetros bioquímicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(2): 778-784, feb. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El efecto de saccharomyces boulardii en pacientes candidatos a trasplante hepático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12814</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10729</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7585^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7585^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33510</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
