<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135160</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-734X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Food allergy in the net</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The fourth consultation reason to the allergy departments in Spain is the food allergy after hay fever, bronchial asthma and adverse drug reaction .This work is intended to asses the quantity and the quality of information related with food allergy in different databases. The objective is to know what has been published from 1998 about food allergy, compared with what is published in Spain. The databases used are Pubmed. EMBASE. BIOSIS, and IME. The data- bases wich offer us more results are Pubmed and EMBASE. The publications more used by the Spanish autor are Allergy (Danish publication), J Allergy Clin Immunol (American publication) and Clin Exp Allergy (British publication). Spanish authors usually publish in English language. Madrid i the Spanish Community wich publishes more articles and Hospital La Paz as institution, followed by Fundación Jiménez Díaz and Escuela Superior de Ingenieros Agrónomo. Comparing the results obtained for Spanish authors with other countries, we can appreciate the number of papers published is quite large (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Huertas Amorós, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arana Arizmendi, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alemán Suárez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mozota Bernad, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echeandía Granda, Mª A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La alergia a lo alimento es el cuarto motivo de consulta en los servicios de alergia en España, detrás de la rinoconjuntivitis, el asma bronquial y la reacciones alérgica a los medicamento. Este análisis bibliométrico intenta valorar la cantidad y la calidad de la información sobre la alergia alimentaria en las distintas bases de datos. Su objetivo es conocer lo que se publica desde 1998 sobre la alergia a los alimentos centrándose en lo publicado en España. Las bases de datos que e van a utilizar son: Pubmed, EMBASE, BIOSIS e IME. Las bases de datos que nos ofrecen más resultados son Pubmed y EMBASE. Las publicaciones más utilizadas por los autores españoles son Allergy (publicación danesa), J Allergy Clin Inmunol (publicación norteamericana) y Clin Exp Allergy (publicación británica). Los autores españoles publican más en inglés. La comunidad autónoma que más publica e Madrid, la institución que más publica es La Paz, seguida de la Fundación Jiménez Díaz y La Escuela Superior de Ingenieros Agrónomos. Al comparar el resultado obtenidos por autores españoles con los de otros países de nuestro entorno podemos apreciar que el número de trabajos publicados por los españoles es bastante elevado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Alergol. inmunol. clín. (Ed. impr.);18(6): 261-266, dic. 2003. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alergia a los alimentos en la red</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12077^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
