<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155449</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diet nursery registrations for patients at semicritics care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: To evaluate nursery records provides information about the activity performed to detect early nutritional problems. Objective: To evaluate and quantify the nursing records regarding the patient&#146;s oral intake. Methodology: Retrospective longitudinal study in a semicrítical unit with 21beds. There were included patients over 18 years old with stays over 24 hours and oral diet. Patients with enteral or parental nutrition were excluded. There were compiled demographics data, medical diagnosis, type of diet, number of data registered linked to weight, size, consciousness, amount of the intake and notes in the graphic. Results: 495 graphics were evaluated (184 patients), the mean age 64.6 (14.1) years. The type of diet were registered in 92.7% and 62.5% had the registrations of weight and size. 84.4% of the records did not include annotations or quantity or intake. There was a higher registration in post surgical patients (p&lt;0,037) and according to the consistency of the diet. It was superior in the liquid intakes (p&lt;.001). Discussion: There is a lack of information regarding to the evaluation of the intake; so as in the quantity as in the problems description, due to the fact that most of the records were taken isolated without describing any planification. Conclusions: The results need to be improved. Nursery needs to review its perform and develop its strategy in order to ensure a correct follow up of the patient&#146;s intake (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valls Matarín, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana Riera, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrico Rodríguez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Evaluar los registros enfermeros, permite conocer la actividad realizada para detectar precozmente problemas nutricionales. Objetivo: Valorar y cuantificar los registros enfermeros respecto a la ingesta oral del paciente. Metodología: Estudio retrospectivo longitudinal en una unidad de semicríticos de 21 camas. Se incluyeron pacientes mayores de 18 años, con estancias superiores a 24 horas y con dieta oral. Se excluyeron pacientes con nutrición enteral o parenteral. Se recogieron datos demográficos, diagnóstico médico, tipo de dieta, número de registros de peso, talla, estado de conciencia, cantidad de ingesta y anotaciones en la gráfica. Resultados: Se valoraron 495 gráficas (184 pacientes), la media de edad fue 64,6 (14,1) años, constaba el tipo de dieta en el 92,7% y en el 62,5% peso y talla. El 84,4% de los registros no incluía ni cantidad ni anotaciones sobre la ingesta. Existió un registro superior en pacientes postquirúrgicos (p&lt;0,037) y según la consistencia de la dieta siendo superior en dietas líquidas (p&lt;0,001). Discusión: Existe una falta de información sobre la evaluación de la ingesta tanto en cantidad como en la descripción de problemas ya que la mayoría de registros son puntuales sin describir ninguna planificación o intervención. Conclusiones: Los resultados son mejorables y enfermería debe revisar su práctica y desarrollar estrategias para asegurar un correcto seguimiento de la ingesta del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;36(3): 14-18, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155449</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registros de enfermería de la dieta administrada a los pacientes ingresados en una unidad de semicríticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28202^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
