<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-059045</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hydraulic dilation (URETEROMAT): effective and safe ureteroscopy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: After the description and standardization of the technique of ureteroscopy in 1979, several methods to obtain a nontraumatic, simple,efficient and fast ureteral acce-ss have been developed.The hydraulic expansion of the ureter was possible in 1986, with the development of ureteromat. We evalua-te the effectiveness of hydraulic ureteral expansion (Ureteromat) for ureteral access and the later endos-copicprocedures.METHOD: The last 100 ureteroscopy carried out from February to October 2006 were evaluated. We used a semi-rigid 9.8 Fr. ureteroscope and hydraulic expansion (Ureteromat) was performed in the same way in all proceduressince 1986.RESULTS: Of the total of cases, 92 were indicated for lithiasicpathology, 7 were exploratory and 1 for ureteral stricture. In 94 patients the procedure was carried out with hydraulic expansion alone, in 2 cases we used a balloon catheter , in 3 patients expansion of the mea-tus was done with forceps and 1 procedure was not possibledue to an ureteral stop.CONCLUSION: The Ureteromat pump guarantees an excellent hydraulic expansion of the ureteral meatus and the passage of the intramural ureter. The visibility is very good at any moment of the procedure, making ureteroscopy a simple, effective, non traumatic and fast method</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orozco Fariñas, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Prieto, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Massarra Halabi, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Castro Ellendt, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cima, Luciano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancebo Gómez, José M. </dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Tras la descripción y estandarizaciónde la técnica de ureteroscopia en 1979, se han desarrollado varios métodos para conseguir un acceso ureteral no traumático, simple, eficiente y rápido. La dilataciónhidráulica del uréter fue posible en 1986, con el desarrollo de Ureteromat. Se evaluó la efectividad de la dilatación ureteral hidráulica (Ureteromat) para el accesoureteral y el procedimiento endoscopico posterior.MÉTODO: Se evaluaron las 100 últimas ureteroscopias llevadas a cabo desde febrero hasta octubre del 2006. En todas las ureteroscopias se utilizo un ureteroscopio semirígido de 9.8 Fr y en todos los procedimientos se realizó dilatación hidráulica (Ureteromat) como se viene realizando desde 1986.RESULTADOS: Del total de los casos, 92 se indicaron por patología litiasica, 7 fueron exploradoras y 1 por estrechez ureteral. En 94 pacientes el procedimiento se llevó a cabo con dilatación hidráulica exclusivamente, en 2 casos se realizó además dilatación con catéter balón, en 3 pacientes dilatación del meato con pinza y sólo en 1 procedimiento no fué posible por un stop ureteral.CONCLUSIÓN: La bomba de irrigación Ureteromat garantiza una excelente dilatación hidráulica del meato ureteral y del trayecto intramural del uréter. La visibilidades muy buena en todo momento, haciendo de la ureteroscopia un método simple, eficaz, no traumático y rápido</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;61(1): 55-60, ene.-feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-059045</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dilatación hidráulica (Ureteromat): ureteroscopia eficaz y segura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24738^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34562^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
