<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140559</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historicity and historiography: contribution of phenomenological interview to Nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Qualitative study grounded in phenomenology in order to highlight the historiography and historicity as an analytical possibilities of the interview based on the theoretical and methodological referential of Martin Heidegger. Scenario was to a hospital in Minas Gerais and as deponents ten women that denoted their understandings about the day to day after cardiac surgery through Phenomenological Interview. It was used the Heideggerian analytical hermeneutics. The results showed the construction of historiography and historicity in motion unveiling of being-there-woman-after-cardiac-surgery, allowing the researcher to understand a way that favors intersubjectivity. We consider the extension of this research to healthcare practice, which in this study turns to women&#146;s health, since intersubjectivity may help guide health professionals to meet the Being, moving the ball ontic ontological to the rescue care-with each other from their multiple and unique needs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amorim, Thaís Vasconselos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza, Ívis Emília de Oliveira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salimena, Anna Maria de Oliveira</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Estudio cualitativo fundamentado en la fenomenología con el fin de mostrar la historiografía y Historicidad como posibilidades analíticas de la entrevista basada en lo referencial teórico y metodológico del Martin Heidegger. Escenario fue a un hospital de Minas Gerais y como deponentes diez mujeres significado que significaban sus entendimientos sobre el día a día después de la cirugía cardíaca a través de la entrevista fenomenológica. Se utilizó la analítica hermenéutica heideggeriana. Los resultados mostraron que la construcción de la historiografía y la historicidad de inauguración movimiento del ser-mujer-después de la cirugía cardíaca, lo que permite al investigador a entender una forma que favorece la intersubjetividad. Consideramos que la extensión de esta investigación a la práctica médica, que en este estudio se dirige a la salud de la mujer, ya que la intersubjetividad puede ayudar a los profesionales de la salud de guía para conocer el Ser, moviendo el balón óntico ontológica al rescate atención-con el otro de sus múltiples y únicos necesidades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;19(41): 71-81, ene.-abr. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140559</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historicidad y historiografía: contribución de la entrevista fenomenológica para Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28202</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6822</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10881</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
