<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90204</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preoperative staging MRI for rectal cancer and pathologic correlation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Our aim is to asses the accuracy of MRIfor preoperative rectal cancer staging and to establisha histopathologic correlation.Material and methods. A retrospective analysis wasperformed on 120 patients aged between 43 and 87 withhistologically proven rectal cancer who underwent MRIfor preoperative staging in our hospital between 2005and 2010. Patients were categorized according to theTNM classification.Results. Eighty of 120 patients underwent adjuvantchemoradiotheraphy because they had advanceddisease (T3-T4), lymph node involvement (N1-N2) orresectable metastases. With 40 patients who didn&#146;tundergo neoadjuvant therapy we performed a correlationbetween MRI and histopathological findings witha diagnostic accuracy in predicting T stage of 72%, Nstage of 60% and distance to the mesorectal fascia of87,5%.Conclusion. Pelvic MRI is a useful technique for locoregionalstaging of rectal cancer with a good radiopathologiccorrelation although the identification of nodaldisease is still a diagnostic problem(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibiricu, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Mendioroz, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabalza, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burguete, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sanchotena, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. El objetivo de este trabajo es revisar lautilidad de la RM pélvica para la estadificación del cáncerde recto y establecer una correlación radiopatológica.Material y métodos. Se realizó un análisis retrospectivode 120 pacientes con una edad comprendida entre 43 y87 años a los que se realizó una RM pélvica para el estadiajede cáncer rectal en nuestro hospital entre los años2005 y 2010. Se catalogaron los pacientes de acuerdo ala clasificación TNM.Resultados. De los 120 pacientes, 80 fueron tratadoscon RT y/o QT neoadyuvante debido a que presentabanenfermedad localmente avanzada (T3-T4), afectaciónganglionar (N1-N2) o metástasis resecables. Con los40 pacientes que no fueron sometidos a tratamientoneoadyuvante se realizó una correlación entre los hallazgosde la RM y de la anatomía patológica con unaprecisión diagnóstica para predecir el estadio T del72%, el estadio N del 60% y la distancia a la FMR del87,5%.Conclusión. La RM pélvica es una técnica útil para laestadificación locorregional del cáncer de recto, obteniendouna buena correlación radiopatológica aunquela identificación de la afectación ganglionar es todavíaun problema diagnóstico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;34(2): 167-174, mayo-ago. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90204</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estadificación prequirúrgica del cáncer de recto mediante RM y correlación radiopatológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
