<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110985</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Implementing a screening programme for distress in cancer settings: science and practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Previous work has addressed the development and diagnostic validity testing of tools for measuring cancer-related distress. Relatively little has been published on the implementation of these tools in clinical  practice. We aimed to review the findingsof randomized and non-randomized trials of  the effect of distress screening to identify the effectiveness and acceptability of screening programmes. Methods. A search was made of the Embase/ Medline and Web of knowledge abstract databases from inception to May 2012. Our inclusion criterion was randomized and non- randomized controlled trials concerning the effect of screening for psychological distress on patient and clinician reported outcomes. We included studies on quality of life. Results. We identified 21 qualifying studies. Twelve were randomized trials and nine were non-randomized trials of the effect of screening for psychological distress. Six randomized trials assigned patients to receive screening or no screening, the remainder randomized patients to receive feedback or  no feedback of screening results. Only 6 of the randomized reported benefits (five as a direct result of screening), although an additional 8 non-randomized studies showed partial benefits. Most benefits were seen in domains of communication, clinician behaviour and patient referral. Acceptability of screening was high during funded screening implementation studies but mixed when incorporated into routine clinical care. Conclusions. Screening for distress has the potential to influence communication, clinician behaviour and patient referral and to a lesser extent recognition of distress and unmet needs. Barriers to implementation  success include low staff confidence, lack of training and support, low acceptability and failure to tie treatment to the screening results. Further work needs to be conducted on the value of screening when incorporated   into routine clinical care and into the most appropriate methods for studying the implementation of screening in clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Waller, Amy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mitchell, Alex J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carlson, Linda E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El trabajo previo ha abordado el  desarrollo y probado la validez diagnóstica de herramientas para medir el malestar emocional asociado al cáncer. Se ha publicado relativamente poco acerca de implementación de estas herramientas en la práctica clínica. Nos propusimos revisar los resultados de los ensayos aleatorios y no aleatorios del efecto del cribado del malestar, para identificar la efectividad y  aceptabilidad de los programas de cribado. Métodos. Se realizó una búsqueda de los abstracts de las bases de datos EMBASE / Medline y Web of Knowledge desde el principio hasta mayo de 2012. Nuestro criterio de inclusión  fueron ensayos controlados aleatorios y no aleatorios concernientes al efecto del cribado de malestr psicológico en los resultados informados por pacientes y médicos. Se incluyeron estudios sobre la calidad de vida. Resultados. Se identificaron 21 estudios cualificados. Los ensayos acerca del efecto del  cribado del malestar psicológico fueron 12 aleatorios y 9 nueve no aleatorios. Seis ensayos aleatorizados asignaron a los pacientes para  recibir cribado o no cribado, el resto aleatorizó a pacientes para recibir feedback o no feedback de los resultados del cribaje. Sólo 6 de los ensayos aleatorizados informaron beneficios (5 como resultado directo cribado),  aunque otros 8 estudios no aleatorios mostraron beneficios parciales. La mayoría de los beneficios se observaron en los dominios de la comunicación, el comportamiento clínico y la derivación de los pacientes. La aceptabilidad del cribado fue alta durante los estudios de implementación del screening financiados  pero mezclados cuando se incorporaron a la atención clínica habitual. Conclusiones. La detección del malestar tiene el potencial de influir en la comunicación, el comportamiento clínico y la derivación de los pacientes y, en menor medida, en el reconocimiento del malestar y de necesidades no satisfechas. Las barreras para su implementación exitosa incluyen baja confianza del  personal, la falta de formación y apoyo, baja aceptabilidad y fracaso para asociar el tratamiento a los resultados del cribado. Se necesita trabajar acerca de la valía del cribado cuando se incorpora a la atención clínica habitual, y de los métodos más apropiados para estudiar  la implementación del cribado en la práctica clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);9(2/3): 259-275, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110985</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implementar un programa de screening del malestar emocional asociado al cáncer: ciencia y práctica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
