<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116742</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subjective quality of sleep in eating disorders patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present research focuses on the analysis of the quality of sleep in eating disorder patients (EDs). For this purpose, scores of 13 EDs patients and 15 controls on the Pittsburg Sleep Quality Inventory (PSQI), the Epworth Somnolence Scale (ESS), the Dysfunctional Beliefs and Attitudes about Sleep Scale (DBAS-18) and a sleep diary were compared. Significant differences were found with regard to subjective quality of sleep, hypnotic medication use, and sleep problems in the PSQI; in addition significant differences were shown on daytime sleepiness levels in the ESS, and in relation to several dysfunctional beliefs about the sleep. In conclusion, EDs patients show less quality of sleep and more sleep problems than controls. These results show the need to be aware into to sleep problems in ED therapeutic interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miró Morales, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Luque, Alejandro de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez narváez, M. Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio se centra en analizar la calidad de sueño de pacientes con trastornos de la conducta alimentaria (TCA). Para ello se compararon las puntuaciones de 13 pacientes con dichos diagnósticos y 15 controles en el Inventario de Calidad de Sueño de Pittsburg (PSQI), la Escala de Somnolencia de Epworth (ESS), la Escala de Creencias y Actitudes Disfuncionales sobre el Sueño (DBAS-18) y un diario de sueño. Se encontraron diferencias significativas con respecto a calidad subjetiva de sueño, consumo de medicación hipnótica y problemas durante el sueño, en los niveles de somnolencia diurna en la ESS y con respecto a creencias disfuncionales sobre el sueño. En conclusión, los pacientes con TCA manifiestan peor calidad de sueño y más problemas de sueño que los controles sanos. Estos resultados ponen de manifiesto la conveniencia de atender a los problemas de sueño en los programas terapéuticos con este tipo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;31(1): 11-20, ene.-abr. 2013. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116742</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad subjetiva de sueño en pacientes con Trastornos de la Conducta Alimentaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
