<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164804</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of mobile technologies in patients with psychosis: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is a growing interest in mobile Health interventions (m-Health) in patients with psychosis. The aim of this study is to conduct a systematic review in order to analysethe current state of research in this area. The search of articles was carried out following the PRISMA criteria, focusing on those studies that used mobile technologies in patients with psychosis during the period from 1990 to 2016. A total of 20 articles were selected from the 431 studies found. Three types of studies are distinguished: 1) Analysis of quality and usability, 2) Improving treatment adherence and reducing hospital admissions, and 3) Analysisof patient symptoms. Conclusions: m-Health interventions are feasible, and are easy to use for patients with psychosis. They evaluate the evolution of psychotic symptoms more efficiently, and improve adherence to treatment, as well as symptoms and hospital admissions. However, a particular strategy does not stand out over the rest, because differences in methodology make them difficult to compare (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sancho, José Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjuan, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet, Lucia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arce, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanquer, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escartí, Maria José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hay un creciente interés en las intervenciones mobile Health (m-Health) en pacientes con psicosis. El objetivo de este estudio es realizar una revisión sistemática para analizar el estado actual de la investigación en este ámbito. La búsqueda de publicaciones se llevó a cabo siguiendo los criterios PRISMA, centrándose en aquellos estudios que utilizan tecnologías móviles en pacientes con psicosis durante el periodo de 1990 a 2016. Se seleccionó un total de 20 artículos de los 431 estudios que se encontraron. Se diferencian 3 tipos de intervenciones: 1) análisis de calidad y usabilidad; 2) mejora de la adherencia, síntomas y reducción de hospitalizaciones, y 3) análisis de la sintomatología del paciente. Conclusión: Las intervenciones m-Health son viables y resultan fáciles de utilizar para los pacientes con psicosis. Evalúan de forma más eficiente la evolución de los síntomas psicóticos y mejoran la adherencia al tratamiento, los síntomas y las hospitalizaciones. No se puede destacar una estrategia sobre las demás debido a que las diferencias en la metodología las hace difícilmente comparables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);10(3): 168-178, jul.-sept. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164804</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de tecnologías móviles en pacientes con psicosis: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37717^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55440^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
