<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158901</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Current practice in regional anaesthesia in South America: an online survey</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. A survey was conducted in order to obtain a profile of the practice of regional anesthesia in South America, and determine the limitations of its use. Methods. After institutional ethics committee approval, a link to an online questionnaire was sent by e-mail to anaesthesiologists in Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Colombia, Panamá, Paraguay, Perú, and Uruguay. The questionnaire was processed anonymously. Results. A total of 1,260 completed questionnaires were received. The results showed that 97.6% of the anaesthesiologists that responded used regional anaesthesia in clinical practice, 66.9% performed peripheral nerve block (PNB) regularly, 21.6% used continuous PNB techniques, and 4.6% used stimulating catheters. The primary source of training was residency programs. As regards PNB, the most common performed were interscalene (52.3%), axillary (45.1%), femoral (43.2%), and ankle block (43%). As regards the localisation technique employed, 16% used paraesthesia, 44.2% used a peripheral nerve stimulator, and 18.1% ultrasound guidance. Conclusions. Regional anaesthesia and PNB are commonly used among South American anaesthesiologists. Considering that each country has its own profile for use, this profile should guide training in clinical practice, especially in residency programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vásquez, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corvetto, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sosa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Folle, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salgueiro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altermatt, FR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crostón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objetivo de este estudio fue describir el perfil de utilización y las limitaciones del uso de la anestesia regional en países de América del Sur. Métodos. Tras la aprobación del comité de ética institucional, se envió un enlace a una encuesta en línea por e-mail a anestesiólogos de Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Colombia, Panamá, Paraguay, Perú y Uruguay. La encuesta se procesó de forma anónima. Resultados. Se recibieron un total de 1.260 cuestionarios completos. El 97,6% de los anestesiólogos encuestados refiere utilizar anestesia regional en su práctica clínica habitual, el 66,9% realiza bloqueos de nervio periférico (BNP) con regularidad, el 21,6% usa técnicas de BNP continuo y un 4,6% usa catéteres estimulantes. La principal fuente de formación fueron los programas de residencia. En cuanto a los BNP más usados, los más comunes son el interescalénico (52,3%), el axilar (45,1%), el femoral (43,2%) y el de tobillo (43%). En cuanto a la técnica de neurolocalización, el 16% utiliza parestesia, el 44,2% estimulador de nervio periférico y un 18,1% ultrasonografía. Conclusiones. La anestesia regional y los BNP son de uso común entre los anestesiólogos de América del Sur. Cada país tiene su propio perfil de utilización y sus propias limitaciones para su uso. Dicho perfil debe ser tomado en cuenta a la hora de planificar las distintas formas de entrenamiento, en especial los programas de residencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;64(1): 27-31, ene. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158901</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Práctica actual de la anestesia regional en América del Sur: encuesta en línea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13403^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10715^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31199^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
