<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140872</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scapula insufficiency fractures after reverse total shoulder arthroplasty in rotator cuff arthropathy: What is their functional impact?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction-objectives. To describe the incidence, etiological factors, functional impairment and therapeutic management of scapular fractures after reverse shoulder arthroplasty (RSA) in rotator cuff arthropathy. Material and method. A retrospective study was conducted on 126 RSA between 2009 and 2011, in which 4 fractures were identified that were compared with a control group of 40 patients. An analysis was performed on the variables related to the surgical technique, functional results, and quality of life (Constant scale, EQ-5D). Results. The fracture incidence was 3.28% with a mean age of 74.7 years. The mean time until diagnosis was 11.9 months. The preoperative Constant score in the control group was 37.3%, and 34.7% in the fracture group (P &gt; .05); postoperative Constant score: 81.2 and 66.5%, respectively (P &gt; .001). Forward elevation and abduction in fracture patients decreased by 39° (P = .02), and 34° (P = .057) respectively. The perceived quality of life (EQ-VAS) was lower in the fracture group (60 vs. 76) (P = .002). There were no instability cases, and no revision surgery was required. The union rate was 50% after a mean follow-up 39.6 months. Conclusions. Scapular fracture after RSA is a rare complication. Despite its presence, the functional outcomes and quality of life of these patients are higher than preoperatively; however, they are lower than that obtained in patients with RSA without this complication. More prospective studies are needed to define guidelines for therapeutic action against this complication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-González, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lópiz, Yaiza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción-objetivos. Describir la incidencia, factores etiológicos, repercusión funcional y actitud terapéutica de las fracturas de acromion y espina de la escápula tras artroplastia invertida por artropatía de manguito rotador. Material y método. Análisis retrospectivo de 126 artroplastias inversas entre los años 2009-2011. Se identificaron 4 fracturas que se compararon con un grupo control de 40 pacientes. Se analizan variables relacionadas con el proceso quirúrgico, funcionales y de calidad de vida (escala Constant, EQ-5D). Resultados. La incidencia de la fractura fue 3,28% (4 pacientes), edad media 74,7 años y tiempo medio hasta el diagnóstico 11,9 meses. El Constant preoperatorio del grupo control fue de 37,3% y de los pacientes con fractura 34,7% (p &gt; 0,05); el postoperatorio 81,2% y 66,5%, respectivamente (p &lt; 0,001). La anteversión y abducción en los pacientes con fractura descendieron en 39° (p = 0,02) y 34° (p = 0,057) respectivamente con respecto al grupo control. La calidad de vida percibida (EQ-VAS) es inferior en el grupo de fractura (60 vs 76) (p = 0,002). En ninguno de los casos de fractura se observó inestabilidad, no precisando cirugías de revisión. La tasa de consolidación fue de un 50% tras un seguimiento medio de 39,6 meses. Conclusiones. La fractura de escápula tras artroplastia invertida es una complicación poco frecuente. A pesar de su aparición los resultados funcionales y de calidad de vida de estos pacientes son superiores a los presentes preoperatoriamente, sin embargo, resultan inferiores a los de los pacientes intervenidos en los que no se encuentra dicha complicación. Son necesarios más estudios prospectivos que nos ayuden a definir las pautas de actuación terapéutica ante esta complicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);59(5): 318-325, sept.-oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140872</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas de estrés de la escápula tras artroplastia invertida en artropatía de manguito: ¿cuál es su repercusión funcional?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d180^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11981^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d180^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d180^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12922^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12922^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
