<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81913</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To evaluate the nutritional state and total body water is fundamental for the evaluation and management of certain patients. Bioimpedanceometry is technology which measures the resistance of tissues and objects to an electric current and converts the data into nutritional and hydration states. In this way we can evaluate the state of a patient at a certain moment in time and monitor their evolution over time during certain pathological states. These measurements, which are collected in a non-invasive and rapid way, have become more precise and sophisticated with the development of better signal capturing systems and analytical algorithms. Thanks to bioelectrical impedance analysis it is possible to innocuously and precisely measure the body composition and state of hydration in both healthy and pathological patients. Data obtained using this system have a prognostic value for nutritional state, and, therefore constitute a validated, precise, noninvasive and simple method for measuring body composition. In this review we analyse the importance of knowing the body composition, the principles of bioimpedance, its applications in daily analysis as well as future fields of development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Diz Gómez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doniz Campos, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padín Barreiro, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orallo Morán, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira Matalobos, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padín Barreiro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conocer el estado nutricional y el agua corporal total es clave en la evaluación y manejo de determinados pacientes. La bioimpedancia es una tecnología que convierte la resistencia que opone el cuerpo al paso de una corriente eléctrica, en datos acerca del estado de nutrición e hidratación del mismo. De esta forma, podemos conocer el estado de los pacientes en un determinado momento así como su evolución en el tiempo en determinados estados patológicos. Estas medidas, que se recogen de forma no invasiva y rápida, se han vuelto más sofisticadas y más precisas con la evolución del tratamiento de la señal y la mejora de los algoritmos matemáticos. Gracias al análisis de la impedancia bioeléctrica es posible valorar de una forma precisa e inocua, la composición corporal y el estado de hidratación tanto en poblaciones sanas como en patológicas. Datos obtenidos por este sistema tienen un valor pronóstico nutricional, constituye por lo tanto un método validado, preciso, no invasivo y fácil de realizar para medir la composición corporal. En esta revisión analizamos la importancia del conocimiento de la composición corporal, los principios de la bioimpedancia, sus aplicaciones en la clínica diaria así como posibles campos de desarrollo futuros (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;20(1): 27-37, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicaciones de la bioimpedanciometría en medicina perioperatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28998^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
