<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106879</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Care in a different culture: experiences of carers of Latin American origin in Pais Vasco</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study is to approach the care of older people in their environment and inquire about the experience of caring in a different culture. Methods: The study houses a qualitative methodology and case study as method of inquiry. Data was collected through in depth interviews with six people in other cultural settings that care for older people in different scenarios. The dynamic was emerging analytical and inductive method applied as categorical content analysis. Results: The results of the study, as in previous studies, we report that culture has a significant influence on the integration of people in our environment. Moreover, it provides data about how that culture shock is affecting the care of people, and therefore, is influencing the locals who come into contact with people from different cultures. Conclusions: This study provides nurses a new understanding of everyday environment, where their actions may be most appropriate and can lead to social-health programs directed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alegre Ruiz de Mendoza, Ania</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo principal: Indagar acerca de la vivencia de cuidar a una persona mayor de una cultura diferente. Metodología: El estudio acoge una metodología cualitativa y el estudio de casos como método de indagación. Los datos se recogieron a través de entrevistas en profundidad a seis personas de otros contextos culturales que cuidan a personas mayores en diferentes escenarios. La dinámica analítica fue emergente e inductiva, aplicando como método el análisis de contenido categorial. Resultados principales: al igual que en otros estudios anteriores, los resultados nos informan que la cultura influye de manera determinante en la integración de las personas en nuestro entorno. Además, aporta datos acerca de cómo ese choque cultural, está influyendo en el cuidado de personas, y por lo tanto, está influyendo en los autóctonos que entran en contacto con personas de diferentes culturas. Conclusión principal: Este estudio proporciona a los profesionales de enfermería conocimientos sobre un nuevo entrono cotidiano, siendo sus actuaciones más apropiadas y pudiendo inducir a programas sociosanitarios dirigidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;20(1/2): 21-25, ene.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106879</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidar en una cultura diferente: vivencias de cuidadoras de origen latinoamericano en el País Vasco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37737^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
