<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125902</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of the catecholaminergic pathway in heart development: beyond neuromodulatory actions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hormones are expressed during development in unexpected locations and stages, and this fact relates to their distinct functional roles in the embryo. In recent work, we found that the expression of Tyrosine Hydroxylase (TH, first enzyme of the catecholamine synthetic pathway) and the presence of catecholamines, antecede neural innervation in some tissues. We focus this overview on the vertebrate developing heart. TH transcripts were present in early cardiogenesis, and adrenergic as well as dopaminergic receptors were found in the cardiac region of chick embryos. We found direct effects of dopamine on cardiac gene expression and we have advanced in revealing the function of catecholamines on cardiac patterning (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Sánchez, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablo, Flora de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las hormonas están expresadas durante el desarrollo en etapas y localizaciones  inesperadas y este hecho se relaciona con sus distintas funciones en el embrión. Recientemente, hemos encontrado que la expresión de la Tirosina Hidroxilasa (TH, el primer enzima de la ruta de síntesis de catecolaminas) y la presencia de catecolaminas, anteceden a la inervación neural en algunos tejidos. Este artículo está centrado en el desarrollo del corazón de vertebrados. Los transcritos de TH se expresan durante la cardiogénesis temprana y se encontraron receptores dopaminérgicos y adrenérgicos en la región cardiaca del embrión de pollo. Hemos demostrado efectos directos de la dopamina sobre la expresión de genes cardiacos y hemos avanzado en caracterizar una función de las catecolaminas sobre la formación del patrón del corazón  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;80(2): 347-361, abr.-jun. 2014. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El papel de las catecolaminas en el desarrollo del corazón: más allá de sus acciones neuromoduladoras</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15118^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14845^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6473^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23962^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6885^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23987^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
