<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89018</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vascualr access in enderly patients, arteriovenous fitula o permanent intravenous catheter</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">During the last few years, the number of elderly patients with end-stage renal disease has been increasing. The native AVF are considered the first choice for vascular access for chronic dialysis in the elderly. Elbow fistulas have higher patency rate in elderly patients compared with radio-cephalic AVF. Age by itself cannot be considered a contraindication for construction of an AV graft. The CVC are a mortality risk factor in the elderly, although are the first choice in patients with limited life expectancy. This review discusses the advantages and disadvantages of the available vascular access modalities (native arteriovenous fistulae, arteriovenous grafts and central venous catheters) in elderly patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saleador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gastambide, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Norberto, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cenizo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Pedrosa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutíerrez, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante los últimos años, el número de pacientes ancianos con enfermedad rena  terminal se ha incrementado. Las FAV nativas se consideran la primera elección de acceso vascular para diálisis crónica en el anciano. La realización de la FAV autóloga a nivel del pliegue del codo obtiene, en ancianos, mejores resultados de permeabilidad que la FAV radio-cefálica. La edad no debe ser considerada por sí misma una contraindicación para la construcción de una FAV protésica. Los CVC en ancianos son un factor de riesgo de mortalidad aunque constituyen la primera elección en pacientes con esperanza de vida  limitada. Esta revisión discute las ventajas y desventajas de las modalidades disponibles de acceso vascular (fístula arteriovenosa nativa, fístula arterio-venosa protésica y catéteres venosos centrales) en los pacientes ancianos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;12(4): 169-173, oct.-dic. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89018</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acceso vascualr en paciente anciano. ¿Fístula arteriovenosa o catéter permanente?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23162^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
