<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053532</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of several illnesses on health related quality of life on workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Foundation and objective: To make a comparative study of the        degree of impact of different diseases in the health related quality of life        (HRQoL) of workers.        Material and methods: A questionnaire including the measure of        HRQoL SF-36, was sent by mail and fulfilled by employees of the Pfizer        company in Spain. Differences in the impact in HRQoL between subjects        with and without several characteristics, with less or more degree of        work productivity and with and without antecedents of several diseases        and current treatment, were assessed by means of statistical tests of U        Mann-Whitney and Kruskal-Wallis.        Results: In a sample of 399 valuable subjects, 35.8±6.5 years        (mean±standard deviation), with a 63.7% of men, worst HRQoL scores        in the Physical Summary Component of SF-36 were observed among        subjects with history of some disease (52.6±5.9 days versus 55.9±2.6),        migraine (46.2±5.9 versus 54.7±4.1), musculoskeletal (49.7±7.2 versus        53.9±5.1) and digestive diseases (51.5±6.6 versus 54.1±4.9), and/or        taking some current treatment (50.2±6.4 versus 55.0±4.4); p&lt;0.05 for all        comparisons. In the Physical Summary Component of SF-36 worst        HRQoL scores were observed among subjects with history of some disease        (51.4±7.1 versus 53.4±5.9), digestive (49.9±8.3 versus 52.5±6.3) and        mental disorders (46.0±8.8 versus 52.4±6.4); p&lt;0.05 for all comparisons.        Conclusions: The impact of the disease in the HRQoL was associated        to the type of pathological antecedents, being migraine that hit more        negatively in the Physical Health, and mental disorders in the Mental        Health</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palacios, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Láinez, M. J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriaza, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rejas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Realizar un estudio comparativo del grado        de impacto de distintas enfermedades en la calidad de vida relacionada        con la salud (CVRS) en el medio laboral.        Material y métodos: Un cuestionario incluyendo el cuestionario de        CVRS SF-36, fue enviado por correo y cumplimentado por empleados de        Pfizer España. Se evaluaron diferencias en el impacto en la CVRS entre        sujetos con/sin distintas características, según grado de productividad        laboral, y según con/sin antecedentes de distintas enfermedades y notoma/        toma actual de tratamiento mediante pruebas estadísticas U Mann-        Whitney y Kruskal-Wallis.        Resultados: En una muestra de 399 sujetos valorables, de 35,8±6,5        años (media±desviación típica), un 63,7% hombres, se observaron peores        puntuaciones en el Índice de Salud Física en sujetos con antecentes        de alguna enfermedad (52,6±5,9 días versus 55,9±2,6), migraña        (46,2±5,9 versus 54,7±4,1), patologías musculoesqueléticas (49,7±7,2        versus 53,9±5,1) y del sistema digestivo (51,5±6,6 versus 54,1±4,9), y        toma de algún tratamiento (50,2±6,4 versus 55,0±4,4); p&lt;0,05 en todas        las comparaciones. En el Índice de Salud Mental se observaron peores        puntuaciones en sujetos con antecedentes de alguna enfermedad        (51,4±7,1 versus 53,4±5,9), enfermedades del sistema digestivo        (49,9±8,3 versus 52,5±6,3) y trastornos mentales (46,0±8,8 versus        52,4±6,4); p&lt;0,05 en todas las comparaciones.        Conclusiones: El impacto de la enfermedad en la CVRS se asoció al        tipo de antecedentes patológicos, siendo la migraña la patología que        impacta más negativamente en la Salud Física, y los trastornos mentales        en la Salud Mental</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;24(1): 3-11, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053532</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de distintas enfermedades en la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) en una población laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15335^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
