<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052110</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bone metastases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bone metastases represent a devastating clinical ;;problem in the most frequent neoplasies, especially ;;in multiple myeloma, tumours breast, prostate ;;and lung. The consequences include pain which is ;;refractory to conventional analgesics, osteolysis ;;often leading to bone-marrow compression and ;;pathological fractures, and metabolic disorders. ;;Recent advances in diagnosis using imaging techniques ;;as well as different biochemical techniques ;;have helped accurate diagnosis and follow-up. The ;;increase in survival has improved through a multimodal ;;approach combining, inhibition of osteolysis, ;;with prophylactic orthopaedic surgery and radiation ;;therapy. Recent advances in basic research have ;;determined the molecular metastatic that can predict ;;its proclivity to metastasize. Basic research will ;;improve understanding of the basic mechanisms and ;;lead to the clarification of molecular targets that will ;;help in the development of medicines capable of preventing, ;;decreasing or blocking the metastatic ;;process</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luis-Ravelo, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicent, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gúrpide, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, J. de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecanda, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las metástasis óseas representan un problema clínicodevastador en las neoplasias más frecuentes,especialmente en el mieloma múltiple, mama, próstata,y pulmón. Las consecuencias incluyen dolores refractariosa analgésicos convencionales, osteolisis queconlleva en ocasiones compresión medular, fracturaspatológicas, y trastornos metabólicos. Recientes avancesen el diagnóstico mediante técnicas de imagen, asícomo diversas técnicas bioquímicas, han favorecidoun certero diagnóstico y seguimiento. El aumento de lasupervivencia se ha mejorado mediante una aproximaciónmultimodal en los tratamientos con la combinaciónde la inhibición de la osteolisis, la cirugía ortopédicaprofiláctica y la radioterapia. Recientes progresosen la investigación básica han determinado la huellamolecular de metástasis de un tumor capaz de predecirsu proclividad metastásica. La investigación básicafavorecerá un conocimiento de los mecanismos básicosy llevará a elucidar dianas moleculares que favoreceránel desarrollo de fármacos capaces de prevenir,amortiguar o bloquear el proceso metastático</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;29(2): 177-188, mayo-ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052110</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las metástasis óseas del cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31996^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10194^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12306^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1884^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
