<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74305</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: In our study we measured the quality of life in agroup of women with mammary hypertrophy who are in surgicalwaiting list to surrender to a reduction mammoplasty,and in another group of patients already operated with reductionmammoplasty in our Service of Surgery between theyears 2000-2005.Patients and methods: We used two validated questionnaireslike the Short Form 36 (SF-36) and Beck Depression Inventory(BDI), as well as an own questionnaire of signs and more specificphysical symptoms of the mammary hypertrophy. These testswere administered to 53 patients submitted to a reduction mammoplastyand to 17 women who were in waiting-list for reductionmammoplasty in the moment to realize the study.Results: The operated on women obtained a major punctuationin the SF-36 that those who were in waiting-list[82,06±21,4 operated on ones vs 72,12 ±13,54 waiting-list].The majority of the operated on patients saw her expectationsfulfilled with regard to the intervention (81,1 %). The physicalsymptoms in the operated on patients are very diminishedwith regard to those who appear in the group of the not operatedon ones with mammary hypertrophy.Conclusions: The operated on women demonstrate to enjoymajor quality of life. The reduction mammoplasty is an interventionthat reports great satisfaction to the patients whosurrender to it. The symptoms resulting from breast hypertrophy,especially physical, were less frequent until almost disappearin the group operated questionnaires of quality of life area very useful tool for our clinical habitual practice(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Correa, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amaya, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Caballero, F. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En nuestro estudio medimos la calidad de vida enun grupo de mujeres con hipertrofia mamaria que se encuentranen lista de espera quirúrgica para someterse a una mamoplastiade reducción, así como en otro grupo de pacientesdonde ya se ha llevado a cabo esta intervención, en nuestroServicio de Cirugía entre los años 2000-2005.Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional de tipo descriptivoy transversal.Utilizamos dos cuestionarios validados como son el ShortForm 36 (SF-36) y Beck Depresión Inventory (BDI), asícomo un cuestionario propio de signos y síntomas físicos másespecíficos de la hipertrofia mamaria. Estas pruebas objetivasfueron administradas a 53 pacientes sometidas a una mamoplastiade reducción y a 17 que se encontraban en lista de esperaen el momento de realizar el estudio.Resultados: Las mujeres intervenidas obtuvieron una puntuaciónmayor en el SF-36 que las que se encontraban en listade espera (82,06 ± 21,4 operadas vs. 72,12 ± 13,54 lista deespera). La mayoría de las pacientes intervenidas vieron cumplidassus expectativas con respecto a la intervención (81,1%).Los síntomas físicos en las pacientes operadas están muy disminuidoscon respecto a los que se presentan en el grupo delas no operadas con hipertrofia mamaria.Conclusiones: Las mujeres operadas demuestran disfrutarde mayor calidad de vida. La mamoplastia de reducción es unaintervención que reporta gran satisfacción a las pacientes quese someten a ella. Los síntomas derivados de la hipertrofiamamaria, sobre todo físicos, fueron menos frecuentes en elgrupo de las pacientes operadas. Los cuestionarios de calidadde vida son una herramienta muy útil para nuestra práctica clínicahabitual(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);21(2): 58-61, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74305</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida en mamoplastia de reducción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7163^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7163^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
