<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161001</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Favipiravir, a new concept of antiviral drug against influenza viruses</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Favipiravir (T-705) is a new antiviral drug with strong inhibitory activity on RNA-dependent RNA polymerase of most RNA virus genome. All the influenza viruses have been shown fully sensitive to this new antiviral, including genetic strains to neuraminidase inhibitors (oseltamivir) resistance. Its mechanism of action lies in blocking viral replication and induction of lethal mutagenesis which determines the loss of infective activity of influenza viruses. Its activity is particularly intense in the respiratory tract, decreasing the viral load to non-infectious levels. Clinical trials in humans have not yet completed but have very favourable results. It seems that the best therapy would be the combination of favipiravir with oseltamivir; both antivirals are synergistic and avoid the emergence of resistance (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reina, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Favipiravir (T-705) es un nuevo fármaco antiviral con intensa actividad inhibitoria sobre la ARN-polimerasa ARN-dependiente de la mayoría de los virus con genoma ARN. Entre ellos los virus gripales se han mostrado totalmente sensibles a este nuevo antiviral, incluso las cepas con resistencia genética a los inhibidores de la neuraminidasa (oseltamivir). Su mecanismo de acción radica en el bloqueo de la replicación viral y en la inducción de una mutagénesis letal que determina la pérdida de la actividad infectiva de los virus gripales. Su actividad es especialmente intensa en el tracto respiratorio, disminuyendo la carga viral hasta niveles no infecciosos. Los ensayos clínicos en humanos todavía no han finalizado pero presentar resultados muy favorables. Parece que la mejor terapia sería la combinación de favipiravir con oseltamivir; ambos antivirales son sinérgicos y evitarían la aparición de resistencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;30(2): 79-83, abr. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Favipiravir, un nuevo concepto de fármaco antiviral frente a los virus gripales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21079^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21079^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7274^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d630^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7274^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10155^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1002^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
