<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150165</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between learning and motivation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The traditional idea that learning depends just on child intelligence has been changed. Now days, it is accepted that variables like attention and motivation are basic in order to get assimilation and not only memory. The present communication tries to analyse the relationship existent between the attitude towards learning foreign languages and the level pupils show in them. Tests batteries were created to evaluate Verbal Intelligence, giving importance to aspects like Fluidity and Verbal Comprehension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallo Álvaro, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Fernández, Luis Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cueto, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La idea de que el aprendizaje sólo depende de la inteligencia del alumno ha pasado a la historia. Actualmente se defiende que variables como la atención y la motivación son imprescindibles para que el aprendizaje no sea exclusivamente memorístico e implique un proceso de asimilación. En la comunicación se trata de analizar la relación que existe entre la actitud hacia el aprendizaje de lenguas extranjeras y el nivel de los diferentes alumnos en esas lenguas. Se crearon baterías de tests para evaluar la Inteligencia Verbal considerándose aspectos como la Fluidez y la Comprensión Verbal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(supl.2): 344-347, 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150165</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre motivación y aprendizaje</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33194</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
