<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81945</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Course of alcohol withdrawal syndrome in a general hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: There is little information available regarding the course of alcohol withdrawal syndrome in a general hospital. The aim of this study was to analyse the timing of the most important clinical features attributed to alcohol withdrawal, as well as their prognostic implications. Material and method: A cohort study of patients with a diagnosis of alcohol withdrawal syndrome was carried out at the Xeral Hospital in Lugo (Spain) between 1987 and 2003, in accordance with DSM IV-TR criteria. Data on clinical characteristics and course were collected, with special attention to the timing of significant events. Results: A total of 539 episodes were studied in 436 patients: 156 cases of alcohol withdrawal syndrome and 383 of alcohol withdrawal delirium. Mean time of abstinence until the diagnosis of alcohol withdrawal syndrome was 54 hours (D.T. = 31.1). Seizures occurred at 35 hours (D.T. =23.3) after abstinence. The alcohol withdrawal syndrome lasted for 46.4 hours (D.T. = 23.1) after diagnosis. In cases in which delirium tremens developed, this occurred at 46.4 hours (D.T. = 23.1), and lasted 73.9 hours (D.T. = 41.5). Patients needing intensive care were admitted to the ICU40.8 hours (D.T. = 60) after the diagnosis of alcohol withdrawal syndrome. The clinical features of alcohol withdrawal syndrome tended to be more prolonged in patients admitted with a medical or surgical diagnosis other than withdrawal syndrome than in those admitted because of withdrawal syndrome itself. Conclusions: The natural history of alcohol withdrawal syndrome in a general hospital setting and the timings of its principal events follow a clearly recognizable pattern. This knowledge can help to provide better assessment in relation to the monitoring and treatment of these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bal Alvaredo, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabuñal Rey, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pazos Ferro, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casariego Vales, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz Fuentes, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monte Secades, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pértega Díaz, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: Existe poca información sobre el curso temporal del síndrome de abstinencia alcohólica en el ámbito de un hospital general. El objetivo de este estudio es saber qué manifestaciones son atribuibles a la abstinencia y en qué momento de su evolución, así como sus implicaciones pronósticas. Material y método: estudio de cohortes sobre los enfermos diagnosticados de síndrome de abstinencia alcohólica en el Hospital Xeral de Lugo entre 1987 y 2003, según criterios del manual DSM IV-TR. Para cada caso se registraron datos clínicos y de seguimiento, con especial atención a los intervalos temporales de aparición y duración de sus manifestaciones. Resultados: Se estudiaron 539 episodios en 436 pacientes: 156 casos de síndrome de abstinencia no complicado y 383 casos de delirium tremens. El tiempo medio de abstinencia hasta el diagnóstico de síndrome de abstinencia alcohólica fue 54,4 horas (D.T. = 31,1). Las crisis comiciales aparecieron 35 horas (D.T. = 23,3) desde el cese de la ingesta. La duración del síndrome de abstinencia no complicado desde el diagnóstico fue 46,4 horas (D.T. = 23,1). Cuando evolucionaron a delirium tremens, estese diagnosticó a las 40,2 horas (D.T. = 29,4), y se prolongó durante 73,9 horas (D.T. = 41,5). Cuando fue preciso el traslado a la UCI, éste se produjo a las 40,8 horas (D.T. = 60) desde el diagnóstico de síndrome de abstinencia. Los enfermos en los que el síndrome de abstinencia alcohólica complicó un ingreso por otro motivo, presentaron manifestaciones clínicas más prolongadas que los que ingresaron por abstinencia. Conclusiones: las manifestaciones clínicas del síndrome de abstinencia alcohólica siguen una pauta evolutiva claramente reconocible. Su conocimiento puede ayudar a una mejor planificación de su atención y tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);22(2): 141-146, abr.-jun. 2010. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81945</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Curso temporal del síndrome de abstinencia alcohólica en un hospital general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6925^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
