<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98060</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Left ventricular mass, diastolic function and collagen metabolism biomarkers in essential hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To evaluate the association between circulating biomarkers of collagen metabolism in serum, left ventricular mass index (LVMI) and diastolic dysfunction in patients with resistant hypertension.Patients and methods: Fifty-two patients with resistant hypertension and 24 healthy individuals were included. The following biomarkers of collagen metabolism were analyzed by ELISA: carboxy-terminal propeptide of procollagen type I (PICP) and transforming growth factor beta1 (TGF&amp;#946;1). The biomarker C-terminal telopeptide of collagen type-I (ICTP) was assayed by electrochemiluminescence immunoassay. In the patient's group a record of 24-h blood pressure monitoring was obtained and an echocardiography was performed. Left ventricular mass was measured according to the formula of Devereux and the diastolic function according to the relation of E and A waves and mitral propagation velocity. Results:Hypertensive patients showed higher levels of PICP and lower levels of ICTP than controls: 83.7 (24.7) vs. 55.0 (8.7), P&lt;.0001; and 175.0 (136.4) vs. 323.3 (121.3), P&lt;.0001). Hypertensive patients showed a significant relationship between PICP and LVMI (r=0.631, P&lt;.0001) and between PICP and diastolic dysfunction (r=&#150;0.519, P&lt;.0001). The groups with and without hypertrophy, and with or without diastolic dysfunction, differed in the mentioned peptides but not in BP values. Conclusions:Our findings suggest that the analyzed markers of synthesis and degradation of collagen may be related to myocardial hypertrophy and diastolic dysfunction independent of blood pressure values (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Doblas Delgado, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Luna, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stiefel, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Jiménez, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Aguilar, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fatela-Cantillo, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías Blanco, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Evaluar la asociación entre biomarcadores del metabolismo del colágeno, índice de masa ventricular izquierda (IMVI) y función diastólica en pacientes con hipertensión arterial (HTA) refractaria. Pacientes y método:Se estudiaron 52 pacientes diagnosticados de HTA refractaria y se compararon con 24 individuos sanos. Se midió en suero el propéptido C-terminal de la molécula de procolágeno tipo I (PICP) y el factor de crecimiento transformante beta 1 (TGF&amp;#946;1) por métodos de enzimoinmunoanálisis, y el telopéptido C-terminal del colágeno tipo I (ICTP) por inmunoensayo electroquimioluminiscente. A los pacientes se les practicó una ecocardiografía donde se calculó el IMVI por la fórmula de Devereux y se valoró la función diastólica a partir de la relación entre las ondas E y A (E/A) y la velocidad de propagación mitral. También se les practicó un registro de monitorización de la presión arterial (PA) de 24h. Resultados:Los hipertensos mostraron valores (media ±DE) superiores de PICP e inferiores de ICPT que los controles: 83,7 (24,7) frente a 55,0 (8,7), p&lt;0,0001, y 175,0 (136,4) frente a 323,3 (121,3), p&lt;0,0001. En los hipertensos existió una relación significativa entre el PICP y el IMVI (r=0,631, p&lt;0,0001) y disfunción diastólica (r=&#150;0,519, p&lt;0,0001). Los grupos con y sin hipertrofia, y con o sin función diastólica, diferían en los citados péptidos pero no en las cifras de PA. Conclusiones: Nuestros hallazgos sugieren que diferentes marcadores de la síntesis y de la degradación del colágeno pueden relacionarse con la presencia de hipertrofia miocárdica o disfunción diastólica con independencia de las cifras de PA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);138(4): 139-144, feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98060</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Masa ventricular izquierda, función diastólica y marcadores de metabolismo del colágeno en la hipertensión arterial refractaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36240^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30693^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29340^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3998^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2130^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
