<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168321</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Safety and efficacy of prasugrel and ticagrelor in acute coronary syndrome. Results of a 'real world' multicenter registry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The incorporation of the new antiplatelet agents (NAA) prasugrel and ticagrelor into routine clinical practice is irregular and data from the 'real world' remain scarce. We aimed to assess the time trend of NAA use and the clinical safety and efficacy of these drugs compared with those of clopidogrel in a contemporary cohort of patients with acute coronary syndromes (ACS). Methods: A multicenter retrospective observational study was conducted in patients with ACS admitted to coronary care units and prospectively included in the ARIAM-Andalusia registry between 2013 and 2015. In-hospital rates of major cardiovascular events and bleeding with NAA vs clopidogrel were analyzed using propensity score matching and multivariate regression models. Results: The study included 2906 patients: 55% received clopidogrel and 45% NAA. A total of 60% had ST-segment elevation ACS. Use of NAA significantly increased throughout the study. Patients receiving clopidogrel were older and were more likely to have comorbidities. Total mortality, ischemic stroke, and stent thrombosis were lower with NAA (2% vs 9%, P &lt; .0001; 0.1% vs 0.5%, P = .025; 0.07% vs 0.5%, P = .025, respectively). There were no differences in the rate of total bleeding (3% vs 4%; P = NS). After propensity score matching, the mortality reduction with NAA persisted (OR, 0.37; 95%CI, 0.13 to 0.60; P &lt; .0001) with no increase in total bleeding (OR, 1.07; 95%CI, 0.18 to 2.37; P = .094). Conclusions: In a 'real world' setting, NAA are selectively used in younger patients with less comorbidity and are associated with a reduction in major cardiac events, including mortality, without increasing bleeding compared with clopidogrel (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almendro-Delia, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chica-Ruiz Ruano, Rafael de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Alcántara, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Rubira, Juan C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre-Prados, M Victoria de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Butrón-Calderón, Michel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina-Toral, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arboleda-Sánchez, José Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo-Urbano, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Guerrero, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La incorporación de los nuevos antiagregantes (NAA) prasugrel y ticagrelor a la práctica clínica está siendo errática. Los datos del mundo real todavía son escasos. Se analizó la tendencia temporal de uso de NAA, su seguridad y eficacia clínica frente a clopidogrel en una cohorte actual de pacientes con síndrome coronario agudo (SCA). Métodos: Estudio multicéntrico observacional retrospectivo de pacientes con SCA ingresados en unidades coronarias incluidos de forma prospectiva en el registro ARIAM-Andalucía entre 2013 y 2015. Se analizaron las tasas de eventos cardiovasculares mayores y hemorragias intrahospitalarias mediante modelos de propensión y regresión multivariante. Resultados: Se incluyó a 2.906 pacientes: el 55% recibió clopidogrel y el 45% NAA. Un 60% presentó SCA con elevación del segmento ST. El uso de NAA se incrementó de forma significativa a lo largo del estudio. El grupo de clopidogrel presentó mayor edad y comorbilidad. La tasa de mortalidad total, el ictus isquémico y la trombosis del stent fue menor con NAA (2 frente a 9%, p &lt; 0,0001; 0,1 frente a 0,5%, p = 0,025; 0,07 frente a 0,5%, p = 0,025, respectivamente). No hubo diferencias en la tasa de hemorragias totales (3 frente a 4%; p = NS). Tras el análisis de propensión, se mantuvo la reducción de mortalidad con NAA (OR = 0,37; IC95%, 0,13-0,60; p&lt; 0,0001) sin incremento en las hemorragias totales (OR = 1,07; IC95%, 0,18-2,37; p = 0,094). Conclusiones: En el mundo real, los NAA se usan de forma selectiva en sujetos más jóvenes y con menor comorbilidad. Su uso se asocia con una reducción de eventos cardiacos mayores, incluida mortalidad, sin aumentar las hemorragias en comparación con clopidogrel (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;70(11): 952-959, nov. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168321</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad y eficacia clínica con prasugrel y ticagrelor en síndrome coronario agudo. Resultados de un registro multicéntrico en el mundo real</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55910^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53718</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19367^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54169^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d249^s22003</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
