<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150997</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology and neurological complications of infection by the Zika virus: a new emerging neurotropic virus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The current epidemic outbreak due to Zika virus began in 2015 and since then it has been reported in 31 countries and territories in America. The epidemiological and clinical aspects related to infection by Zika virus are reviewed. Development. Since 2007, 55 countries in America, Asia, Africa and Oceania have detected local transmission of the virus. This epidemic has aff ected almost 1.5 million people in Brazil. 80% of the cases are asymptomatic. The symptoms of Zika virus disease include fever, maculopapular rash, arthralgia and non-purulent conjunctivitis. The symptoms are usually selflimiting and last one week. An increase in the incidence of cases of microcephaly, retinal lesions and Guillain-Barré syndrome associated with the Zika virus has been reported. Zika-associated Guillain-Barré syndrome in Polynesia is a pure motor axonal variant. The RNA of the Zika virus has been identifi ed in samples of brain tissue, placenta and amniotic liquid of children with microcephaly and in the still-born infants of women infected by Zika during pregnancy. The reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction test is recommended to detect viral RNA, and serological tests (IgM ELISA and neutralising antibodies) should be conducted to confi rm infection by Zika. The diff erential diagnosis includes infection by the dengue and chikungunya viruses. Conclusions. Knowledge about the pathogenic mechanisms involved in infection due to Zika virus and its long-term consequences in adults and newborn infants is still limited ((AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carod Artal, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El actual brote epidémico por virus Zika se inició en 2015 y en la actualidad afecta a 31 países y territorios en América. Se revisan los aspectos epidemiológicos y clínicos asociados con la infección por virus Zika. Desarrollo. Desde 2007, 55 países de América, Asia, África y Oceanía han detectado transmisión local del virus. La actual epidemia ha afectado a casi 1,5 millones de personas en Brasil. El 80% de los casos son asintomáticos. La enfermedad por virus Zika cursa con fi ebre, exantema maculopapular, artralgias y conjuntivitis no purulenta. Los síntomas suelen ser autolimitados y duran una semana. Se ha descrito un aumento de la incidencia de los casos de microcefalia, lesiones retinianas y síndrome de Guillain-Barré asociados con el virus Zika. El síndrome de Guillain-Barré asociado al Zika en la Polinesia es una variante axonal motora pura. El ARN del virus Zika se ha identifi cado en muestras de tejido cerebral, placenta y líquido amniótico de niños con microcefalia y en pérdidas fetales de mujeres infectadas por Zika durante el embarazo. Se recomienda realizar la prueba de reacción en cadena de la polimerasa mediante transcriptasa inversa para detectar ARN vírico y pruebas serológicas (IgM ELISA y anticuerpos neutralizantes) para confi rmar una infección por Zika. El diagnóstico diferencial incluye la infección por virus dengue y chikungunya. Conclusiones. Existe un conocimiento limitado sobre los mecanismos patogénicos implicados y las consecuencias a largo plazo de la infección por virus Zika en adultos y recién nacidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;62(7): 317-328, 1 abr., 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150997</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología y complicaciones neurológicas de la infección por el virus del Zika: un nuevo virus neurotropo emergente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9020^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4742^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33353^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56233^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56233^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56233^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56233^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34211^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31464^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56233^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56233^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37255^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9636^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
