<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97934</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic non-compliance with insulin in the treatment of diabetes mellitus 2</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the percentage of therapeutic noncompliance among type 2 diabetes patients on treatment with insulin.                                             Design: Prospective multicentre study. Setting: Nine Primary Care Health Centre in Huelva (Spain).                          Participants: A total of 121 type 2 diabetics, who, in the opinion of their doctor, need to start treatment with insulin or have their insulin treatment modified.                                                    Main measurements: Five visits were made (enrolment, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months). The variables analysed were, fasting blood glucose, glycosylated haemoglobin, compliance with insulin treatment, measured by counting insulin units. The percentage compliance (PC) was calculated by (PC = Total No. of insulin units expected to be consumed / Total No. of insulin units that should have been taken x 100). A complier was considered as one who achieved a PC between 80 and 100%.                            Results: There were 103 evaluable subjects (85.8%) with a mean age of 66.4 (SD 11.6) years, and 45 were male (42.8%). The mean percentage compliance with insulin was 90.9% (95% CI, 84.2-97.6%). At the 6, 12, 18 and 24 months visits it was 92.1% (95% CI, 85.6-98.6%), 92.3, 90.1 and 89.2% (95% CI, 81.7-96.7%), respectively.                                           Overall patient compliance was 74.75% (95% CI, 64.3-85.2%). For the visits, compliance was 82.5% (95% CI, 73.3-91.7%), 77.7%, 73.8% and 71.8% (95% CI, 60.9-82.7%), respectively (P&lt;.05 initial-final).                                  Conclusions: A quarter of the diabetic patients did not comply with their insulin treatment(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chaves González, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Guillén, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martell Claros, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín de Pablos, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Martínez, José Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferraro García, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Contreras, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ortega, Amalia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la magnitud del incumplimiento del tratamiento farmacológico con insulina, en pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2). Diseño: Estudio prospectivo, longitudinal y multicéntrico. Emplazamiento: 9 centros de salud. Distrito Huelva-Costa. España.                                                    Participantes: 121 diabéticos tipo 2 que precisaron según criterio de su médico inicio o modificación del tratamiento con insulina, con un seguimiento de 2 años. Mediciones principales: Se efectuaron 5 visitas (inclusión, 6, 12, 18 y 24 meses).                                                       Variables analizadas: glucemia basal, hemoglobina glucosilada, cumplimiento del tratamiento con insulina, medido mediante recuento de unidades de insulina. Se calculó el tanto por ciento de cumplimiento (PC) (PC=N.° total de unidades de insulina presumiblemente consumida/N.° total de unidades de insulina que debiera haber sido administrada x 100). Se consideró cumplidor aquel cuyo PC estaba entre 80 y 100%.                                             Resultados: Concluyeron 103 pacientes (85,1%) (edad 66,4, DE 11,6 años). Fueron 45 varones (42,8%).                    El porcentaje de cumplimiento medio fue de 90,9% (IC 84,2-97,6%). Por visitas (6, 12, 18 y 24 meses, respectivamente) fue de 92,1% (IC 85,6-98,6%), 92,3, 90,1 y 89,2% (IC 81,7-96,7%).                                            El porcentaje de cumplidores fue del 74,75% (IC 64,3-85,2%). Por visitas fue respectivamente 82,5 (IC 73,3-91,7%), 77,7, 73,8 y 71,8 (IC 60,9-82,7%) (p&lt;0,05 entre inicio y final). El porcentaje de control final de glucemias basales y hemoglobina glucosilada fueron del 22,33% (IC 12,17-32,49%) y del 11,65% (IC 3,83-19,47%). Conclusiones: Una cuarta parte de los diabéticos fueron incumplidores del tratamiento con insulina(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;44(2): 74-81, feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97934</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El cumplimiento terapéutico con insulina en el tratamiento de la diabetes mellitus tipo 2: estudio CUMINDIAB</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
