<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89177</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutricional inquiry workers form a health area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sanitary staff working in different shifts could lead into anomalous life habits. Through this inquiry we will evaluate food habits comparing different sections workers, so we can determine if a healthy diet is being followed considering SENC&#146;s advice on food portions in  adult diets. Total cholesterol figures established in the analytical profiles of health tests are also analyzed. It&#146;s crucial that the Occupational Health Department asks the employees about their eating habits and provides advice on health promotion and illness prevention related to eating disorders. Occupational Health doctors can identify early risk factors and, if necessary, transfer the patient to an endocrinologist or nutritionist (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ligero López, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu Celdrán, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Ortiz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trabajo a turnos en personal sanitario puede inducir a hábitos de vida anómalos. Mediante una encuesta se valoran los hábitos alimentarios en trabajadores del centro de diferentes secciones, para determinar si se sigue una alimentación sana según las raciones recomendadas para adultos por la SENC. También se analizan las cifras de  colesterol total determinadas en los perfiles analíticos de sus exámenes de salud. Es importante que en los servicios de medicina laboral se pregunte al trabajador sobre sus hábitos alimentarios y se le proporcionen consejos para la promoción de su salud y prevención de enfermedades ocasionadas por trastornos alimentarios. El médico del trabajo puede detectar de manera precoz factores de riesgo, y realizar un abordaje terapéutico y remitir al trabajador al endocrinólogo o nutricionista si fuera preciso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;17(2): 34-37, oct. 2008. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89177</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta nutricional en trabajadores de un área de salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
