<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103822</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Corneal toxicity due to amantadine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 64 year-old female with Parkinson disease treated with amantadine for two years who suddenly suffered bilateral corneal oedema. It was initially treated as herpetic endotheliitis without improvement as we lacked information on her chronic treatment. The corneal oedema finally resolved after withdrawing the drug. Discussion: Amantadine hydrochloride may produce endothelial dysfunction. Once the amantadine treatment is stopped, the corneal oedema may be reversible but endothelial density remains low. An ophthalmologist examination should be performed before the initiation of amantadine treatment in order to establish a risk: benefit ratio, especially in those patients with low endothelial density or any endothelial anomaly (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mesa-Varona, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Arroquia, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Celis-Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avendaño-Cantos, EM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González del Valle, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez-Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Mujer de 64 años en tratamiento con amantadina durante 2 años por enfermedad de Parkinson, que presentó edema corneal bilateral de inicio brusco. Inicialmente se trató como una endotelitis herpética sin mejoría, al desconocer la medicación empleada por la enferma. Finalmente el edema se resolvió tras la suspensión del fármaco. Discusión: El hidrocloruro de amantadina puede producir disfunción endotelial. El edema corneal puede ser reversible tras su suspensión, pero la densidad endotelial permanece baja. Sería necesario realizar un control oftalmológico previo al inicio del tratamiento para valorar el riesgo/beneficio del mismo, sobre todo en los pacientes que presenten baja densidad endotelial o un endotelio alterado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;87(9): 290-293, sept. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103822</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Toxicidad corneal por amantadina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23941^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23941^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23941^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
