<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127151</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital varicella syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vertical transmission of the varicella virus is estimated to occur in 8% to 25% of cases. Among these, congenital varicella syndrome develops in only 1% or 2% of transmissions, especially if the infection occurs between weeks 12 and 20 of pregnancy. The detection of DNA from the virus in the amniotic fluid, combined with the presence of ultrasonographic markers of fetal involvement, leads to a highly likely diagnosis. We present the case of a gravida 3 who contracted varicella at week 14 of gestation, with fetal involvement (hepatic and myocardial calcifications detected on ultrasonography) and newborn death at 1 month of life. Currently, passive immunization is the only active strategy to prevent the serious consequences of congenital varicella syndrome if a non-immune pregnant woman is exposed to the varicella zoster virus before week 20 of pregnancy, since neither the use of antiviral prophylaxis or treatment, nor the use of anti-varicella zoster virus immunoglobulin have been proved to give significant results. Thus, it is of the utmost importance to provide information to parents and adequate management of this type of pregnancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Uriarte, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente Fernández, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloreda García, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jódar Pérez, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Pérez, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Izquierdo, Olivia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rivero, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Remezal Solano, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se estima que la transmisión vertical del virus de la varicela ocurre entre un 8 y un 25% de los casos. De estos, solo en un 1-2% de las ocasiones se producirá el síndrome de varicela congénita (SVC), sobre todo si la infección ocurre entre las semanas 12-20 de gestación. La detección del DNA del virus en líquido amniótico, junto con la presencia de marcadores ecográficos de afectación fetal, hacen el diagnóstico altamente probable. Presentamos el caso de una tercigesta que en la semana 14.ª de gestación contrajo varicela, ocurriendo afectación fetal (calcificaciones hepáticas y miocárdicas en ecografía) y muerte del neonato al mes de vida. Actualmente, la inmunización pasiva representa la única estrategia activa para prevenir las graves consecuencias del SVC si una gestante no inmune se expone al VVZ antes de la semana 20 de gestación, ya que, tanto el uso de antivirales como profilaxis o como tratamiento como el uso de inmunoglobulina anti VVZ tras un contacto, no han mostrado resultados concluyentes. Por todo esto, consideramos capital la correcta información a los padres y el adecuado control de este tipo de gestaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);57(9): 432-435, nov. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127151</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de varicela congénita</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11691^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d668</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2689^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11691^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
