<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138590</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the eHealth Literacy Scale (eHEALS) in Spanish University Students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: One of the scales most used to measure quickly and easily eHealth Literacy is the eHealth Literacy Scale (eHEALS); however, there was no validation of this scale in Spanish. Therefore, the aim of this study was to adapt and validate the eHealth Literacy Scale (eHEALS) to the Spanish context. Methods: Spanish translation of the scale eHEALS was administered along with other scales to measure some indicators of psychological well-being (self-esteem, subjective vitality and life satisfaction). A sample of 447 university students aged between 18 and 45 years was selected. An exploratory factor analysis, confirmatory factor analysis, analysis of invariance, reliability, temporal stability and bivariate correlations were performed. Results: Exploratory factor analysis revealed a monofactorial structure that explained 52.55% of variance, with high factor loadings of the items. Reliability of 0.87 and test-retest correlation of 0.78 was obtained. The confirmatory factor analysis showed appropriate adjustments indices: &amp;#967;2=66.60; p=0.00; &amp;#967;2/ df=4.44; comparative fit index=0.97; incremental fit index=0.97; tucker lewis index=0.94; root mean square of approximattion =0.08; standardized root mean square residual=0.05. The questionnaire was invariant by gender. Regarding the criterion validity, a statistically significant and positive correlations between 0.12 and 0.16 with three indicators of psychological wellbeing was obtained (self-esteem, subjective vitality and life satisfaction). Conclusions: The spanish version of the eHEALS tested in this work has shown to be a valid and reliable scale to measure eHealth competence in university students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernando Gómez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jesús Almagro, Bartolomé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguaded Gómez, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paramio Pérez, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Una de las escalas más empleadas para medir de forma rápida y sencilla la competencia en eSalud es la eHealth Literacy Scale (eHEALS), sin embargo, no existe su validación en castellano. Por ello, el objetivo de este estudio fue adaptar y validar al contexto español la escala eHEALS. Métodos: Se administró la traducción al español de la escala eHEALS, junto a otras escalas para medir algunos indicadores del bienestar psicológico (autoestima, vitalidad subjetiva y satisfacción con la vida). Se utilizó una muestra de 447 estudiantes universitarios de edades entre los 18 y los 45 años. Se realizó un análisis factorial exploratorio, un análisis factorial confirmatorio, análisis de invarianza, de fiabilidad, de estabilidad temporal y de correlaciones bivariadas. Resultados: El análisis factorial exploratorio mostró una estructura monofactorial que explicó el 52,55% de la varianza, con elevados pesos factoriales de sus ítems. Se obtuvo una fiabilidad de 0,87 y una correlación test-retest de 0,78. El análisis factorial confirmatorio mostró unos índices de ajustes adecuados: &amp;#967;2 = 66,60; p=0,00; &amp;#967;2/gl=4,44; índice de ajuste comparativo =0,97); índice de ajuste incremental =0,97; índice tucker-lewis =0,94; error de aproximación cuadrático medio=0,08; residuo cuadrático medio estandarizado=0,05. No hubo diferencias por sexo. En cuanto a la validez de criterio, se obtuvieron correlaciones estadísticamente significativas y positivas e entre 0,12 y 0,16 con tres indicadores del bienestar psicológico (autoestima, vitalidad subjetiva y satisfacción con la vida). Conclusiones: La versión española de la eHEALS testada ha mostrado ser una escala válida y fiable para medir la competencia en eSalud en el alumnado universitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(3): 329-338, mayo-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la Escala Ehealth Literacy (Eheals) en población universitaria española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3009^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28417</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55787^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55787^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55787^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54383</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53793^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35223</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
