<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057050</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">2nd National Study of Pressure Ulcers Prevalence in Spain, 2005. Epidemiology and defining variables of lesions and patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since 1999, GNEAUPP considered it vital to create a permanent observatory of the epidemiological evolution of these processes, in order to rescue and maintain the real value of the problem of Pressure Ulcers, which has given way to the next step, the 2nd National Prevalence Study we now present.        The objectives set forth in this study were to obtain epidemiological indicators that would allow us to find the extent of the pressure ulcer problem in Spain, as well as some aspects related to the prevention of such in primary care centers, hospitals and socio-sanitary institutions.         We sent out a questionnaire in order to estimate the punctual and average prevalence of PU (initials UPP in Spanish) using non-random sampling. Primary Care professionals were asked to give information about their patients who were over 14 years of age (General Practitioner Surgeries) and professionals from Hospital Units and socio-sanitary centers were asked about their patients respectively. Prevalence was defined as &#145;punctual prevalence&#146; (information in a specific moment in time). The crude prevalence (initials PC in Spanish) and average prevalence (PM) were calculated. The questionnaires only included questions on patients with PU (numerator of the indicator) over the total of patients of the unit being studied (denominator of the indicator) about the wounds caused as well as information on PU prevention in the institutions where each respondant worked. 1,791 patients were reported to have pressure ulcers (39% in hospital, 27% in primary care centers and 34% in socio-sanitary centers). In Primary Care, the PC was 3.73% and the PM was 9.11% ± 10.9% for patients over 14 years who were included in the home care program. In the hospital units, the PC was 8.24% and the PM was 8.91% ± 12.20% and in the socio-sanitary centers, the PC was 6.10% and the PM was 10.9% ± 11.9%. The group most affected of each health care level was the one over 65 years of age (84.7%). The completed questionnaires provided information about 2,837 wounds: 23.2% were stage I, 37.5% stage II, 27.0% stage III, 11.8% stage IV and 0.5% did not state the stage. PU most frequently affected the sacral region, followed by the heels, in all health care levels.         It can be concluded that PU are still an important public health problem that affect mainly elderly people</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Verdú Soriano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Cuervo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torra i Bou, J. E </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Casanova, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayán Santos, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soldevilla Agreda, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rueda López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde el año 1999 el GNEAUPP consideró de vital interés para rescatar y mantener el valor real del problema de las úlceras por presión (UPP), la constitución de un observatorio permanente de la evolución epidemiológica de estos procesos, cuyo siguiente paso ha sido el desarrollo de este 2º Estudio Nacional de Prevalencia que presentamos. Se definieron como objetivos de la investigación obtener indicadores epidemiológicos que permitiesen dimensionar el problema de las UPPen España, así como algunos aspectos relacionados con las tendencias de prevención de las mismas en instituciones de Atención Primaria, atención hospitalaria y asistencia sociosanitaria. Elaboramos un cuestionario postal para estimar la prevalencia puntual y media de UPP a partir de una muestra no aleatoria. En estos cuestionarios se solicitaba a los profesionales de Atención Primaria que informasen acerca de su lista de usuarios mayores de 14 años (Unidades básicas asistenciales de Medicina General) y a los profesionales de unidades de hospitalización o de centros sociosanitarios que informasen acerca de los pacientes de sus respectivas unidades. Se definió la prevalencia como &#147;prevalencia puntual&#148; (información en un solo momento del tiempo). Se calculó la prevalencia cruda (PC) y media (PM). Los cuestionarios contenían preguntas para obtener datos sobre los pacientes con UPP (numerador del indicador), sobre el total de pacientes de esa unidad a estudio (denominador del indicador), sobre las lesiones mismas, así como información de las tendencias de prevención de UPP en las instituciones de los receptores de los cuestionarios. Se reportaron 1.791 pacientes con UPP (39% en hospital, 27% en Atención Primaria y 34% en centros sociosanitarios). En Atención Primaria la PC fue de 3,73% y la PM de 9,11% ± 10,9% para los pacientes mayores de 14 años incluidos en el programa de atención domiciliaria; en las unidades de hospital, la PC fue de 8,24% y la PM de 8,91% ± 12,20%, y en los centros sociosanitarios la PC fue de 6,10% y la PM de 10,9% ± 11,9%. En todos los niveles asistenciales, el grupo de población mayoritariamente afecto era el de los mayores de 65 años (84,7%). Los cuestionarios recibidos proporcionaron información sobre 2.837 lesiones: 23,2% de estadio I, 37,5% de estadio II, 27,0% de estadio III, 11,8% de estadio IV y un 0,5% sin estadiar. La localización más frecuente fue el sacro seguido de los talones, en todos los niveles asistenciales.         Puede concluirse que las UPP siguen constituyendo, todavía, un importante problema de salud pública que afecta de manera primordial a personas mayores</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);17(3): 154-172, jul.-sep.2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057050</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">2º Estudio Nacional de Prevalencia de Úlceras por Presión en España, 2005. Epidemiología y variables definitorias de las lesiones y pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
