<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88681</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of new information and communication methodologies (ICT) for laboratory teaching in applied physics and physical chemistry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this innovative teaching work is the improvement in the learning process of laboratorypractical sessions of the subject &#145;Applied Physics and Physical Chemistry&#146; of the Pharmacy degreesyllabuses at the University of Granada. The laboratory practical sessions of several subjects in thisFaculty have been traditionally carried out with the collaboration of &#145;laboratory demonstrators&#146;, whohelp to their classmates in the performance of the experiments, being always coordinated andsupervised by a senior professor. This system has however some handicaps and limitations. With thisproject, we expect on one hand the figure of &#145;laboratory demonstrators&#146; to disappear, and on the otherhand to achieve that the student is more receptive and shows a higher interest in the practical sessions.Our experience proves that it is very important for the student to visualize the manipulation andmethodology needed for the performance of the experiments in the laboratory. The new audiovisualInformation and Communication Technologies (ICT) provide very didactic tools, which make thelearning more attractive. With this purpose, we have prepared a DVD movie of each experimentplanned in the practical sessions of the subject. These movies show the manipulation of the materialand reagents, the use of specific instrumentation, good behaviour in the laboratory, and dataacquisition and analysis, with the aim of guiding the student in the experimental work. The studentwill perform the experiments simultaneously to the movie projection, with the possibility ofinteracting with the movie itself and the senior professor present during the session. In short, weexpect to enhance the motivation and own-initiative of the students, facilitating their self-learning, bymeans of an innovative teaching methodology that contributes to promote the adaptation to theEuropean Space for Higher Education(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Talavera Rodríguez, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruedas Rama, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle Ribes, M. C. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orte Gutiérrez, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Pez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crovetto González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Con tal fin, se ha elaborado para la asignatura antesmencionada un vídeo de cada práctica en formato DVD, en los que, con objeto de guiar al alumno enel trabajo experimental, se muestra la manipulación del material y reactivos empleados en cadapráctica, uso de la instrumentación específica, buenas prácticas en un laboratorio y adquisición yanálisis de datos. El objetivo que se persigue es que el alumno realice la práctica simultáneamente aldesarrollo del vídeo, con la opción de interactuar con el vídeo y con el propio profesor presente en lasesión. En definitiva, mediante esta metodología de prácticas innovadora se pretende la captación de laatención del alumno, su motivación, promoción del trabajo autónomo y capacidad de iniciativafacilitando de esta forma su capacidad de autoaprendizaje. Todo lo comentado, contribuye a potenciarla adaptación de los actuales estudios universitarios al Espacio Europeo de Educación Superior(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.2): 543-550, mayo 2010. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88681</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de nuevas metodologías de la información y la comunicación (TIC) a la enseñanza práctica de física aplicada y físicoquímica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2673^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22519^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54404^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29580^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11257^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
