<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92773</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Continuing education and teaching plans in a comprehensive cancer centre: strategy and implementation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The Oncology Catalonian Institute (ICO) launched the training and education unit (UFiD) in 2006, in order to enhance professional development, dissemination of knowledge and quality of the oncology care. Here are described the tune-up of this process and the results of the training needs survey carried out among the professionals and collectives of the centre. Materials and methods. Training and educational actions deployed during 2008 and 2009 and its evaluation results are presented. A total of 60 training activities were carried out in which 719 students of all professional categories participated, and with a score of participant&#146;s satisfaction of 7.8 out of 10. In the area of education, the paths of the different services were reorganized and new initiatives were supported. A total of 3 masters, 3 post-graduate degrees, 59 update courses with semi-presential (blended learning) methodology and 19 on-line methodology courses, all of them with academicaccreditation were imparted with a satisfaction average score of 8 out of 10.Results and conclusions. The activity carried out by the UFiD during this period, has made possible to articulate the continuing training based on the study of the professionals needs. This has allowed promoting the professional development and the quality of the care. Supporting existing training activities and promoting new initiatives encourage the dissemination of knowledge in the area of oncology and has positioned us as a centre committed to oncology training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Batiste, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esperalba, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toro, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boqué, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guanter, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feliu, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moliner, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alburquerque, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El Institut Català d&#146;Oncologia (ICO) puso en marcha la Unidad de Formación y Docencia (UFiD), en el año2006, con el objetivo de potenciar el desarrollo profesional, la difusión del conocimiento y la calidad de la atención oncológica. En el presente artículo se describe el proceso de puesta en marcha de la UFiD, los resultados del estudio de las necesidades formativas realizada por los profesionales y colectivos de la institución, las acciones formativas organizadas, y en el área de docencia, los resultados de la reorganización de las trayectorias docentes de los diferentes servicios, así como el apoyo de nuevas iniciativas. Materiales y métodos. Durante el periodo 2008-2009, se implantaron acciones formativas y docentes en concordancia con los resultados del estudio de necesidades y con las líneas estratégicas de la institución. Se realizaron un total de 71actividades formativas, con 898 participantes de todas las categorías profesionales, con una tasa de satisfacción de los participantes de 7,8 sobre 10. En el apartado de docencia, durante el mismo periodo se realizaron 3 másteres, 3 posgrados,59 cursos de actualización con metodología semipresencial y 19 cursos con metodología online, todos ellos con acreditación académica. La satisfacción media fue de 8 sobre 10.Resultados y conclusiones. La actividad llevada a cabo por la UFiD ha permitido, por una parte, articular la formación continuada en base al estudio de las necesidades de los profesionales, lo que ha contribuido a promover el desarrollo profesional y la calidad asistencial de éstos, y por otra parte, dar soporte a las actividades docentes ya existentes y promover nuevas iniciativas para favorecer la difusión de conocimientos en el área oncológica, lo que ha posicionado al ICO como un centro absolutamente comprometido con la formación oncológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);14(1): 57-68, mayo 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92773</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plan de formación y docencia en un centro integral de cáncer: estrategia e implementación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2205^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17571</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
