<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120584</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intestinal permeability measurements: general aspects and possible pitfalls</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Disturbances of the gut barrier function have been related to a variety of diseases, including intestinal and extra-intestinal diseases. The intestinal permeability tests are considered useful tools for evaluating disease severity and to follow-up patients after a therapeutic intervention and indirectly assess barrier function. Objective: The aims of this review were to highlight the possible factors underlying higher intestinal permeability and the clinical conditions that have been associated with this in different age range; and also provide some insight into methodological aspects. Results and discussion: Abnormal regulation of tight junction function is the main cause of altered intestinal barrier. The impaired barrier function results in higher permeation rates of administered probes through the intestinal mucosa. Lactulose and mannitol are one of the most commonly used probes. The innocuousness and easiness of intestinal permeability tests can be explored to expand the knowledge about the clinical situations in which intestinal barrier dysfunction can be an important feature. Many factors may influence the results of the test. Researchers and healthcare professionals should try to circumvent the possible pitfalls of the intestinal permeability tests to produce consistent evidences. The use of others markers of intestinal physiology may also contribute to understand the role of barrier function in different diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Souza, Nilian Carla Silva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreira, Ana Paula Boroni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frias, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teixeira, Tatiana Fiche Salle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peluzio, Maria do Carmo Gouveia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Alteraciones funcionales de la barrera intestinal se han relacionado con una variedad de enfermedades intestinales y también con enfermedades no intestinales. Las pruebas de permeabilidad intestinal son consideradas herramientas útiles para evaluar la gravedad de la enfermedad para el posterior seguimiento de los pacientes después de una intervención terapéutica. Objetivo: El objeto de esta revisión ha sido destacar los posibles factores que pueden estar asociados a una mayor permeabilidad intestinal y revisar condiciones clínicas que han sido asociadas en individuos de diferentes edades. También revisar ciertos aspectos metodológicos de las pruebas de permeabilidad intestinal. Resultados y discusión: Las uniones estrechas entre los enterocitos son las principales estructuras encargadas de la regulación de la barrera intestinal. Una alteración de éstas, resulta en una deficiencia en la permeabilidad intestinal y una mayor penetración de las sustancias marcadoras de permeabilidad intestinal. La lactulosa y el manitol son las sustancias marcadoras más utilizadas. La inocuidad y facilidad de los test de permeabilidad han sido de ayuda para explorar y ampliar el conocimiento de muchas condiciones clínicas en las que la disfunción de la barrera intestinal ha sido un sello distintivo. Muchos factores pueden influir en los resultados de los test de permeabilidad. Sin embargo, los investigadores y los clínicos han de tratar de eludir los posibles inconvenientes de las pruebas de permeabilidad intestinal para poder producir evidencias más consistentes. El uso de otras sustancias marcadoras de la fisiología intestinal también puede contribuir a comprender mejor el papel de la barrera intestinal en diferentes enfermedades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(2): 269-281, 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mediciones de permeabilidad intestinal: aspectos generales y posibles riesgos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7970</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7585^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10729</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
