<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138857</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Magnetic resonance for noninvasive detection of microcirculatory disease associated with allograft vasculopathy: intracoronary measurement validation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Cardiac allograft vasculopathy affects both epicardial and microcirculatory coronary compartments. Magnetic resonance perfusion imaging has been proposed as a useful tool to assess microcirculation mostly outside the heart transplantation setting. Instantaneous hyperemic diastolic flow velocity-pressure slope, an intracoronary physiology index, has demonstrated a better correlation with microcirculatory remodelling in cardiac allograft vasculopathy than other indices such as coronary flow velocity reserve. To investigate the potential of magnetic resonance perfusion imaging to detect the presence of microcirculatory remodeling in cardiac allograft vasculopathy, we compared magnetic resonance perfusion data with invasive intracoronary physiological indices to study microcirculation in a population of heart transplantation recipients with macrovascular nonobstructive disease demonstrated with intravascular ultrasound. Methods. We studied 8 heart transplantation recipients (mean age, 61 [12] years, 100% male) with epicardial allograft vasculopathy defined by intravascular ultrasound, nonsignificant coronary stenoses and negative visually-assessed wall-motion/perfusion dobutamine stress magnetic resonance. Quantitative stress and rest magnetic resonance perfusion data to build myocardial perfusion reserve index, noninvasively, and 4 invasive intracoronary physiological indices were determined. Results. Postprocessed data showed a mean (standard deviation) myocardial perfusion reserve index of 1.22 (0.27), while fractional flow reserve, coronary flow velocity reserve, hyperemic microvascular resistance and instantaneous hyperemic diastolic flow velocity-pressure slope were 0.98 (0.02), cm/s/mmHg, 2.34 (0.55) cm/s/mmHg, 2.00 (0.69) cm/s/mmHg and 0.91 (0.65) cm/s/mmHg, respectively. The myocardial perfusion reserve index correlated strongly only with the instantaneous hyperemic diastolic flow velocity-pressure slope (r = 0.75; P = .033). Conclusions. Myocardial perfusion reserve index derived from a comprehensive dobutamine stress magnetic resonance appears to be a reliable technique for noninvasive detection of microcirculatory coronary disease associated with cardiac allograft vasculopathy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Pulpón, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segovia, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escaned, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-López, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastrana, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pavía, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oteo, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirelis, Jesús G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cavero, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echavarria-Pinto, Mauro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La vasculopatía del aloinjerto cardiaco afecta tanto al compartimento coronario epicárdico como al de la microcirculación. Se ha propuesto el uso de las técnicas de imagen de perfusión de la resonancia magnética como instrumento útil para la evaluación de la microcirculación, principalmente fuera del contexto del trasplante de corazón. La pendiente de velocidad del flujo-presión diastólica hiperémica instantánea, que es un índice de la fisiología intracoronaria, ha mostrado mejor correlación con el remodelado microcirculatorio en la vasculopatía del aloinjerto cardiaco que la de otros índices como la reserva de velocidad del flujo coronario. Con objeto de investigar el potencial de las técnicas de imagen de perfusión de resonancia magnética para detectar la presencia de remodelado microcirculatorio en la vasculopatía de aloinjerto cardiaco, se ha comparado los datos de perfusión de resonancia magnética con los índices fisiológicos intracoronarios invasivos, para estudiar la microcirculación en una población de pacientes con trasplante de corazón que presentaban una enfermedad macrovascular no obstructiva demostrada por la ecografía intravascular. Métodos. Se estudió a 8 pacientes con trasplante de corazón (media de edad, 61 ± 12 años; el 100% varones) que presentaban una vasculopatía del aloinjerto epicárdica definida por ecografía intravascular, estenosis coronarias no significativas y una resonancia magnética de estrés con dobutamina con evaluación visual del movimiento de la pared/perfusión negativa. Se determinaron los datos de perfusión de resonancia magnética cuantitativa en estrés y en reposo para establecer el índice de reserva de perfusión miocárdica, de manera no invasiva, y se determinaron cuatro índices fisiológicos intracoronarios evaluados de manera invasiva. Resultados. Los datos posprocesados mostraron una media del índice de reserva de perfusión miocárdica de 1,22 ± 0,27, mientras que la reserva de flujo fraccional, la reserva de velocidad del flujo coronario, la resistencia microvascular hiperémica y la pendiente de velocidad del flujo-presión diastólica hiperémica instantánea fueron de 0,98 ± 0,02, 2,34 ± 0,55, 2,00 ± 0,69 y 0,91 ± 0,65 cm/s/mmHg respectivamente. El índice de reserva de perfusión miocárdica presentó una correlación intensa tan solo con la pendiente de velocidad del flujo-presión diastólica hiperémica instantánea (r = 0,75; p = 0,033). Conclusiones. El índice de reserva de perfusión miocárdica obtenido a partir de la resonancia magnética de estrés con dobutamina completa resulta una técnica fiable para la detección no invasiva de la enfermedad coronaria microcirculatoria asociada a la vasculopatía de aloinjerto cardiaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;68(7): 571-578, jul. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resonancia magnética para la detección no invasiva de la enfermedad microcirculatoria asociada a la vasculopatía de alotrasplante: validación de la determinación intracoronaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55171^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36271^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9022^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10669^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36271^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36271^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36271^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
