<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036883</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">First trimester screening for trisomy 21 with the use of the biochemistry-ultrasound combined test. A prospective intervention trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To assess the efectiveness of the Combined Test (first-trimester biochemistry and ultrasound) in the prenatal detection of Down syndrome in the general pregnant population.        Material and methods: First-trimester biochemical markers (pregnancy associated plasma protein-A and free &amp;#61666;&amp;#61472;-hCG) were determined in maternal serum at 7-12 weeks. Nuchal translucency and the gestational age were assessed in a 10-14 weeks scan. The estimated combined risk was delivered the same day of the scan, and when it was 1:250 or above, cytogentic diagnosis was offered by means of chorion villus sampling.         Results: The mean gestational age at biochemistry was 9.5 weeks and 12.1 for ultrasound. In the 4,447 studied pregnancies with a complete follow-up, detection rate for trisomy 21 was 91% (10/11), 83% (5/6) for trisomies 18-13, with a 3.8% (167/4423) false-positive rate.        Conclusion: The Combined Test, with the assessment of biochemical markers and nuchal translucency in their optimal gestational periods during the first trimester, showed a 91% detection rate for trisomy 21 with a reduced false-positive rate of 3.8%</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borrell, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goncé, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cararach, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanrell, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casals, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortuny, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercadé, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la efectividad del Test Combinado (bioquímica y ecografía en el primer trimestre) para la detección prenatal del síndrome de Down en la población general.        Material y métodos: Se determinaron los marcadores bioquímicos de primer trimestre (proteína plasmática A asociada al embarazo y fracción &amp;#61666;&amp;#61472;libre de la gonadotropina coriónica) en suero materno a las 7-12 semanas. La translucencia nucal fetal y la edad gestacional se determinaron mediante ecografía a las 10-14 semanas. Se estimó el riesgo combinado el mismo día de la ecografía y se ofreció el diagnóstico citogenético mediante biopsia de corion si el riesgo era de 1:250 o superior.        Resultados: La edad gestacional media en la determinación bioquímica fue de 9,5 semanas y de 12,1 para la ecografía. En las 4.447 gestaciones estudiadas con seguimiento completo, los índices de detección fueron del 91% (10/11) para la trisomía 21 y del 83% (5/6) para la trisomía 18 o 13, con una tasa de falsos positivos del 3,8% (167/4.423).        Conclusión: El Test Combinado, al determinar los valores de marcadores bioquímicos y de translucencia nucal en intervalos gestacionales óptimos durante el primer trimestre, mostró una tasa de detección del 91% para la trisomía 21 con una reducción en la tasa de falsos positivos al 3,8%</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);48(5): 223-230, mayo 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036883</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado de trisomía 21 en el primer trimestre mediante test combinado de bioquímica y ecografía. Estudio prospective de intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14715^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
