<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59394</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of a schoolbased intervention to promote smokefree areas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the effect of an intervention in secondary schools on visible tobacco use, the prevalence and intensity of smoking, and the attitudes and behaviors of teachers and students. Methods: We performed a quasiexperimental study in 18 public secondary schools that carried out the program and in 18 that did not (control group). Information was obtained on visible tobacco use and the number of ashtrays and smokefree posters through direct observation. Data were collected on tobacco use, the number of heavy smokers, smoking in schools, opinions on smokefree schools, smoking in front of the students, and attempts to quit smoking through questionnaires to teachers and students in the third year of compulsory secondary education (15-year-olds) and in the final year of secondary school (18-year-olds). Results: Visible tobacco use was lower in the intervention group (27.9 vs. 45.6%) and twice as many posters were displayed. No differences were found in the prevalence of daily tobacco use, but the percentage of heavy smokers was lower in teachers and students in the intervention group. Smoking was lower in students in the third year of compulsory secondary education in schools carrying out the program. Opinions about smokefree schools were favorable in both groups. Conclusions: The program contributed to reducing visible tobacco use and in decreasing the number of heavy smokers among teachers and students(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Iglesias, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arbesú Fernández, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Tenreiro, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Vigil, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rodríguez, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Vázquez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer el efecto de un programa sobre el consumo visible de tabaco en los institutos de enseñanza secundaria (IES), la prevalencia y la intensidad del consumo del alumnado y el profesorado, y sus actitudes y conductas respecto al consumo en el centro. Métodos: Estudio casi experimental en 18 IES que realizaron el programa y en 18 que no lo realizaron (grupo control). Por observación directa se registró el consumo visible, la existencia de ceniceros y de carteles de «espacio libre de humo». Por encuesta al profesorado y al alumnado de 3.o de ESO y 2.o de Bachillerato, se recogieron datos de consumo de tabaco, grandes fumadores, consumo en el recinto escolar y opinión sobre la prohibición de fumar; a los profesores también se les preguntó sobre el consumo delante de los alumnos y sobre los intentos de dejar de fumar. Resultados: En el grupo de intervención había menor consumo en las zonas observadas (el 27,9 frente al 45,6%) y el doble de carteles. No hubo diferencias en la prevalencia de consumo diario, pero sí en el porcentaje de grandes fumadores, que fue menor en el profesorado y el alumnado del grupo de intervención; también eran menos los alumnos de 3.o de ESO que fumaban en el centro. La opinión sobre la prohibición de fumar en el centro era favorable en los dos grupos. Conclusiones: El programa contribuyó a la reducción del consumo visible y del número de cigarrillos/día consumidos por profesorado y alumnado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(1): 23-28, ene.-feb. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59394</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de una intervención de promoción de espacios sin humo en el ámbito educativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
