<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055071</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Newborn neurometabolic diseases as a cause os neurodevelopmental disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Foetal distress and hypoxic-ischaemic encephalopathy are two of the most frequent causes of neonatal    morbidity and mortality. They can be caused by a number of factors. Uterine and intrapartum asphyxia are the two most    common causes; nevertheless, there are also other causing factors that are not usually considered, such as inborn errors of    metabolism (IEM), for example. Manifestations can be very different, not particularly specific and easily mistaken for the first    two situations. The neonatologist and, later, the neuropaediatrician must be familiar with the initial clinical-biochemical    presenting symptoms, as they can often mimic the clinical picture of hypoxic-ischaemic encephalopathy or the foetal distress.    Once the most common causes have been ruled out and working in collaboration with the clinical biochemist and neuropaediatrician,    they will be able to offer guidance on the complex diagnostic and therapeutic approach. In recent years, the    combination of the wider experience held by departments and modern laboratory techniques has made it possible to establish    much earlier diagnoses and treatments that are of greater benefit to the affected patients. Development. In this review we analyse    the clinical presenting symptoms in a consecutive series of 51 newborn infants with neurological manifestations and who were    finally diagnosed with IEM. Conclusions. The diagnostic approach and prognosis will vary considerably, while genetic    counselling can be offered and prenatal diagnosis can sometimes be performed. Unfortunately, the prognosis of IEM with    inborn neurological manifestations is still uncertain and the morbidity and mortality rates remain high (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campistol, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La pérdida del bienestar fetal y la encefalopatía hipoxicoisquémica son dos de las causas más frecuentes    de morbimortalidad neonatal. Obedecen a múltiples causas. La asfixia uterina e intraparto son las dos causas más    habituales; sin embargo, existen otros factores causales que habitualmente no se plantean, como los errores congénitos del    metabolismo (ECM), entre otros. Las manifestaciones pueden ser muy variadas, poco específicas y confundirse fácilmente con    las dos primeras situaciones. El neonatólogo y posteriormente el neuropediatra deben conocer los síntomas clinicobioquímicos    iniciales de presentación, que con frecuencia pueden remedar la clínica de la encefalopatía hipoxicoisquémica o de la pérdida    del bienestar fetal. Una vez descartadas las causas más comunes y trabajando conjuntamente con el bioquímico clínico y    el neuropediatra, podrán orientar el complejo abordaje diagnóstico y terapéutico. En los últimos años, la mayor experiencia    de las unidades y las modernas técnicas de laboratorio han permitido diagnósticos mucho más precoces y tratamientos más    beneficiosos para los pacientes afectados. Desarrollo. Se analizan en esta revisión los síntomas clínicos de presentación en una    serie consecutiva de 51 neonatos con manifestaciones neurológicas y diagnosticados finalmente de un ECM. Conclusiones. La    orientación diagnóstica y el pronóstico variarán considerablemente, a la vez que se puede ofrecer un consejo genético y en    ocasiones proceder al diagnóstico prenatal. Desgraciadamente, el pronóstico de los ECM con manifestaciones neurológicas    de inicio neonatal sigue siendo reservado y la morbimortalidad elevada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(supl.3): s19-s25, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055071</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedades neurometabólicas de presentación neonatal como causantes de trastornos del neurodesarrollo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1954^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1954^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
