<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74905</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0367</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multidisciplinary Team of Specialized support (EMSE): A mobile outreach Project for psychiatric emergency home visits in the city of Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: our group has set up a program for psychiatric emergency home interventions. It is composed of a multidisciplinary mobile outreach team (EMSE) that attends to spychicatic emergency units called for on the local emergency number (061). Objective: to describe the program, the phses of development and a preliminary evaluation. Methods: a descriptive analysis of home interventions from January 2004 to December 2004. During 2004 teher were 196 calls, of which 109 required home intervention. Results: 55,5% were severe mental disorders that were not being treated at the time. The most frequent motives for consultation were delusions, behavior associated with isolation and agitation-aggression. The diagnoses were classified in the spectrum of schizophrenic disorders. The results from intervention indicate that 48,4% are admitted involuntarily and 22,6% are referred to mental health community centres. The evaluation is positive and results in a 80% follow-up and adherence to treatment by patients. Conclusions: This program is proving both satisfactory and necessary. The adherence to treatment reflects the success of the interventions. The program will also be useful in predicting and detecting further needs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Leal Leturia, Itziar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córcoles Martínez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín López, Luis Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bulbena Vilarrasa, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellsolà Gonzàlez, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coletas Juanico, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arcega Felipe, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: se presenta la implantación de un nuevo dispositivo asistencias, el Equipo Multidisciplinar de Soporte Especializado (EMSE). Este es resultado de un programa de soporte y atención a las urgencias psiquiátricas extrahospitalarias en la ciudad de Barcelona (061). Se describen las características del programa, las fases de desarrollo y se realiza una evaluación. Métodos: se analiza la fase 2, se estudian los pacientes valorados en el domicilio en el periodo del 1 de enero del 2004 al 31 de diciembre de 2004. Las alertas son 196, de las cuales se generan 109 casos que serán tributarios de intervención domiciliaria. Resultados: el 55,5% son trastornos mentales graves desvinculados de la red, y el 22,6% son trastornos mentales vinculados pero que han sido atendidos hace más de cuatro semanas. La historia de trastorno psiquiátrico se caracteriza por tener un tiempo medio sin recibir tratamiento de 40 meses (DS ± 59,2 meses). El delirio, conductas de aislamiento y la agitación-agresividad son las razones de consulta principales. Los diagnósticos se agrupan en el espectro del trastorno esquizofrénico. Las recomendaciones-disposiciones de la consulta, el 48,4% se resuelven en ingresos involuntarios y el 22,6% finalizan en el Centro de Salud Mental. En la evaluación a los cuatro meses, se obtiene un 80% de vinculación en los casos gestionados por EMSE. Conclusiones: la utilidad del programa se constata al comprobar la adherencia al tratamiento. Además este dispositivo puede ser predictor y observatorio de detección de necesidades(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. psiquiatr;70(3): 225-234, jul.-sept. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74905</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las urgencias psiquiátricas: oportunidades para la adherencia terapéutica. El programa E.M.S.E. Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
