<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117311</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outpatient treatment of uncomplicated acute diverticulitis: Impact on healthcare costs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background Outpatient treatment of uncomplicated acute diverticulitis is safe and effective. The aim of this study was to determine the impact of outpatient treatment on the reduction of healthcare costs. Patients and methods A retrospective cohort study comparing 2 groups was performed. In the outpatient treatment group, patients diagnosed with uncomplicated acute diverticulitis were treated with oral antibiotics at home. In the hospital treatment group, patients met the criteria for outpatient treatment but were admitted to hospital and received intravenous antibiotic therapy. Cost estimates have been made using the hospital cost accounting system based on total costs, the sum of all variable costs (direct costs) plus overhead expenses divided by activity (indirect costs).Results A total of 136 patients were included, 90 in the outpatient treatment group and 46 in the hospital group. There were no differences in the characteristics of the patients in both groups. There were also no differences in the treatment failure rate in both groups (5.5% vs. 4.3%; P=.7). The total cost per episode was significantly lower in the outpatient treatment group (882 ± 462 vs. 2.376 ± 830 euros; P=.0001).Conclusions Outpatient treatment of acute diverticulitis is not only safe and effective but also reduces healthcare costs by more than 60% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pera, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Courtier, Ricard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cots, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente, Leyre</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvans, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El tratamiento ambulatorio de la diverticulitis aguda no complicada es seguro y eficaz. El objetivo de este estudio es cuantificar el impacto que el tratamiento ambulatorio tiene en la reducción de costes sanitarios. Pacientes y métodos Estudio comparativo de cohortes retrospectivo. Grupo ambulatorio: pacientes diagnosticados de diverticulitis aguda no complicada tratados con antibióticos vía oral de forma ambulatoria. Grupo de tratamiento hospitalario: pacientes que cumplían criterios de tratamiento ambulatorio pero que fueron ingresados con tratamiento antibiótico intravenoso. La valoración de costes se ha realizado a través del sistema de contabilidad analítica del hospital, basado en costes totales: suma de todos los costes variables (costes directos) más el conjunto de costes generales repartidos por actividad (costes indirectos).Resultados Se incluyó a 136 pacientes, 90 en el grupo ambulatorio y 46 en el grupo de ingreso. No hubo diferencias en las características de los pacientes entre los 2 grupos. No hubo diferencias en el porcentaje de fracaso del tratamiento entre los 2 grupos (5,5 vs. 4,3%; p = 0,7). El coste global por episodio fue de 882 ± 462 euros en el grupo ambulatorio frente a 2.376 ± 830 euros en el grupo hospitalario (p = 0,0001).Conclusiones El tratamiento ambulatorio de la diverticulitis aguda no solo es seguro y eficaz sino que también reduce más de un 60% los costes sanitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);91(8): 504-509, oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento ambulatorio de la diverticulitis aguda no complicada: impacto sobre los costes sanitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4301^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
