<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140870</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hamate fractures</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The purpose of this paper is to present our experience in the treatment of the fractures of the hamate and to make a review of the literature on this topic. Material and method. We retrospectively reviewed 10 patients treated in our clinic between 2005-2012 suffering from fractures of the hamate. Six cases were fractures of the body and four were fractures of the hamate. Five cases were of associated injuries. Diagnostic delay ranged from 30 days to 2 years. Patient follow-up ranged from 1 to 10 years. Patient satisfaction was evaluated using the DASH questionnaire. Five patients with a fracture of the body underwent surgery, and one was treated conservatively. Two patients with fracture of the hook of the hamate were treated with immobilization, and two more patients had the fragment removed. Results. The grip strength and the digital clip were reduced in 2 cases. Flexion and extension of the wrist was limited in 3 cases. The mobility of the fingers was normal in all the cases, except in one. The results obtained from the DASH questionnaire were normal in all the cases, except in one case of fracture of the hamate, and in two cases of fracture of the body. Conclusions. The surgical treatment should reduce the dislocation and stabilize the injuries with osteosynthesis. The fractures of the hamate are usually diagnosed late, and the most recommended treatment is removal of the fragment, although it cannot be deduced from this study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibañez Martínez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarabia Condés, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Carrasco, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmerón Martínez, EL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Julia, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objeto de este trabajo es presentar nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento de las fracturas del ganchoso y hacer una revisión bibliográfica. Material y método. Hemos revisado de forma retrospectiva 10 pacientes tratados en nuestro centro entre 2005-2012 que presentaban fractura del ganchoso. Seis casos eran fracturas del cuerpo y 4 fracturas del gancho. Cinco presentan otras lesiones asociadas. El retraso diagnóstico osciló entre los 30 días y los 2 años. El tiempo de seguimiento oscilaba entre 1 y 9 años. Se valoró la calidad de vida del paciente con el cuestionario DASH. Cinco pacientes con fractura del cuerpo fueron intervenidos y uno fue tratado conservadoramente. Dos pacientes con fractura del gancho fueron tratados con inmovilización y otros dos tratados con exéresis del fragmento. Resultados. La fuerza de prensión y de la pinza digital estaba disminuida en 2 casos. La flexoextensión de la muñeca estaba limitada en 3 casos. La movilidad de los dedos era normal en todos los casos excepto en uno. La puntuación obtenida en el DASH estaba en los límites de la normalidad en todos los casos excepto en un caso de fractura del gancho y en 2 casos de fractura del cuerpo. Conclusiones. El tratamiento quirúrgico deberá reducir la luxación y estabilizar las lesiones con osteosíntesis. Las fracturas del gancho suelen diagnosticarse tardíamente y su tratamiento más aconsejable es la exéresis, aunque no es deducible de este estudio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);59(5): 299-306, sept.-oct. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140870</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas del ganchoso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15352^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50357^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7285^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15352^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50357^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50357^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50357^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
