<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154839</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-7606</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">DSM-5. Substance use disorders. Are the new changes problematic in the forensic field?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The recently released Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th edition (DSM-5) by the American Psychiatric Association has supposed several and significant changes and it has raised heated debates and criticisms. This paper focus on substance use disorders. One of the principal changes regarding this disorder is the dimensional approach. The abuse and dependence categories have been merged into one disorder applied to each substance and requiring two or more out of eleven specified symptoms. Craving criterion is included and «legal problems» had disappeared beacause they have showed poor discrimination for diagnosis. The disappearance of abuse and dependence categories might cause some confusion between judicial workers. From now on the forensic experts will have to make an effort to explain to the court the specific features according to items endorsed in DSM-5 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portero Lazcano, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La reciente publicación del Manual Diagnóstico y Estadístico de los Trastornos Mentales en su 5a edición (DSM-5) por la American Psychiatric Association ha supuesto varios y significativos cambios, así como encendidos debates y críticas. Este artículo se centra en el trastorno por consumo de sustancias. Uno de los principales cambios en relación a este trastorno es el enfoque dimensional. Las categorías de abuso y dependencia se incluyen dentro de un trastorno, y se aplica a cada una de las sustancias requiriendo dos o más de los once síntomas especificados. Se incluye el craving y han desaparecido los «problemas legales» porque han mostrado una pobre discriminación para el diagnóstico. La desaparición de las categorías del abuso y la dependencia puede causar cierta confusión entre los operadores judiciales. A partir de ahora, los peritos tendrán que hacer un esfuerzo para explicar a los tribunales las características específicas de acuerdo a los ítems aprobados en el DSM-5 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. med. forense;21(3/4): 96-104, jul.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154839</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">DSM-5. Trastornos por consumo de sustancias. ¿Son problemáticos los nuevos cambios en el ámbito forense?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5688^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12528^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
