<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125171</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Allergic Contact Dermatitis due to Nickel: Descriptive Study in a Tertiary Hospital, 2000-2010</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study based on the records of the dermatology department of a tertiary referral hospital was to describe patients treated for allergic contact dermatitis induced by nickel between 2000 and 2010. Materials and methods: From records of the skin allergy section of the dermatology department we extracted and analyzed information for patients who underwent patch testing with the standard series of the Spanish Contact Dermatitis Research Group (GEIDAC), which includes a patch with 5% nickel sulfate in petroleum jelly. The possibility that nickel release from various objects might have triggered the patient's dermatitis was assessed with the dimethylglyoxime spot test, which reveals a reddish precipitate if the metal is present. Results: A total of 3,404 patients underwent GEIDAC patch testing during the study period; 24.2% had positive reactions to the patch containing 5% nickel sulfate in petroleum jelly. However, the contact dermatitis could be attributed to nickel in only 57 of the 824 patients (6.9%) who showed sensitization to nickel. Conclusions: Patch-test evidence of sensitization was found to be clinically relevant in only a small percentage of patients. We emphasize the usefulness of the dimethylglyoxime test to help establish the relevance of a positive nickel patch test. This test is even useful for identifying the specific object responsible for a patient's dermatitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuadra-Oyanguren, J. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zaragozá-Ninet, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Rabasco, A. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ruíz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este trabajo es el estudio descriptivo de los pacientes con dermatitis alérgica de contacto por níquel que han sido atendidos en un hospital de referencia en dermatología en un periodo de 10 años. Material y métodos: Se han analizado los datos de todos los pacientes parchados con la batería estándar del Grupo Español de Investigación en Dermatitis de Contacto y Alérgica Cutánea (GEIDAC) que incluye un parche con sulfato de níquel en vaselina al 5%, a partir de la base de datos informatizada de la sección de alergia cutánea de nuestro servicio. Para conocer la implicación de diferentes objetos metálicos en el origen de la dermatitis utilizamos un método colorimétrico llamado test de dimetilglioxima (DMGO). Resultados: Durante el periodo de estudio se ha explorado mediante pruebas epicutáneas con la batería estándar del GEIDAC a 3.404 pacientes. Del total de pacientes parchados un 24,2% presentaron un parche positivo para sulfato de níquel al 5% en vaselina. Sin embargo, de los 824 pacientes sensibilizados al níquel solo en 57 de ellos (6,9%) se pudo demostrar una asociación de la sensibilización con la dermatitis por la que consultaban. Conclusiones: Solo se identificó relevancia presente en un pequeño porcentaje de pacientes con positividad al níquel en las pruebas epicutáneas. Destacamos la utilidad del test de DMGO como método de ayuda para establecer la relevancia de la positividad del parche con níquel, e incluso para conocer el objeto causante de dicha dermatitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;105(6): 590-596, jul.-ago. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatitis alérgica de contacto a níquel. Estudio descriptivo en un hospital terciario en la década del 2000 al 2010</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9717^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22604^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
