<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61990</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Drug treatment of dyslipidemia in type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Type 2 diabetes carries an elevated cardiovascular risk. A significant component of this risk can be attributed to diabeticdyslipidemia, a cluster of plasma lipid and lipoprotein abnormalities that are metabolically interrelated. The main characteristics of diabetic dyslipidemia are elevated triglycerides, lowered high-densitylipoproteins (HDL) and raised small, denselow-density lipoproteins (LDL). These alterations are also known as the &#147;atherogenic lipid triad&#148;. Other components of the atherogenic lipid profile are elevatedapo B levels, prolonged postprandial lipemia and accumulation of triglyceride-richremnant particles in the circulation. In the last few years, several prospective trials have proven the effectiveness of statins in improving diabetic dyslipidemia and in reducing cardiovascular risk. These drugs are therefore considered the initial drug ofchoice for diabetic dyslipidemia. Fibrates can be used in a subset of patients, mostlyin combination with statins. Future trials with new lipid-lowering and antidiabetic agents will hopefully allow more targeted treatment of lipid disorders and postprandiallipemia in type 2 diabetics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carmena, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Real, J. T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La diabetes mellitus tipo 2 conlleva un elevado riesgo cardiovascular. Un componente significativo de este riesgo puede atribuirse a ladislipemia diabética, un agrupamiento de anomalías de los lípidos y las lipoproteínas en el plasma íntimamente relacionadas. Sus principales características son hipertrigliceridemia, descenso del colesterol ligado a lipoproteínas de alta densidad (cHDL) y aumento de las lipoproteínas de baja densidad (LDL) pequeñas y densas. Estas alteraciones se conocen también como la tríada aterogénica. Otros componentes son la elevación de la apolipoproteína (apo) B, la prolongación de la lipemia posprandialy el aumento de las partículas remanentes, ricas en triglicéridos. En los últimos años, numerosos estudios prospectivos han demostrado los beneficios de las estatinas para mejorar el perfil lipídico de la dislipemiadiabética y también para reducir el riesgo cardiovascular de estos pacientes. Las estatinas se consideran el tratamiento fundamental y básico de la dislipemia diabética. Los fibratos pueden usarse en algunos grupos reducidos de pacientes y, generalmente, siempre en combinación con las estatinas. Estudios futuros con nuevos fármacos hipolipemiantesy antidiabéticos permitirán un tratamiento más eficaz de la dislipemiadiabética (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;55(supl.2): 78-82, ene. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61990</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento farmacológico de la dislipemia en la diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
