<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161408</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An unexpected complication: glans ischemia after circumcision. Review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Circumcision is a frequent and common surgical procedure in children; nevertheless it is not completely hassle-free. Post circumcision ischemic complications are even rare and they are generally due to administration of local vasoconstrictor anesthetics. There are few cases reported in the literature. We report the management and treatment of post- circumcision penile ischemia (PCI). Case report. A 10 years old patient who underwent circumcision and a dorsal penile nerve block DPNB presents signs of penile ischemia two hours after surgery without any other symptoms. Ultrasonography shows weak flow of the penile artery, with progressive worsening. 24 hours later we start treatment with pentoxifylline (PTX) that is maintained for 6 days, topical testosterone and a caudal blocking (for 48 hours). The patient evolved favorably within a few hours and there was complete resolution in 6 days. Discussion. We analyze 9 cases of pediatric patients which were described in the literature. 7 cases (77.7 %) received DPNB. The PCI is an unusual complication of circumcision, and DPNB seems to be the most frequent cause. Several therapeutic options are available for its management, but none is protocolised (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Siu Uribe, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Rueda, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betancourth Alvarenga, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Crespo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas Elías, MÁ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes Esteban, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murcia Pascual, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La circuncisión, aunque es el procedimiento quirúrgico más común en niños, no está totalmente libre de complicaciones. Las complicaciones isquémicas post-circuncisión, son muy raras, y generalmente debidas a la administración de anestésicos locales vasoconstrictores. Se presenta el manejo y tratamiento con éxito de una isquemia peneana post-circuncisión (IPC) en un niño y se realiza una revisión de los casos descritos en la literatura. Caso clínico. Paciente de 10 años de edad sometido a circuncisión y bloqueo del nervio dorsal peneano (BNDP), que presenta a los 2 horas de la intervención, signos de isquemia peneana, sin otra sintomatología. La ecografía objetiva flujo débil de la arteria peneana, con empeoramiento progresivo. A las 24 horas, se inicia tratamiento con pentoxifilina (PTX) durante 6 días, testosterona tópica y un bloqueo caudal que se mantuvo durante 48 horas. Se observa mejoría de la isquemia a las pocas horas de instaurado el tratamiento y resolución total a los 6 días. Discusión. Existen 9 casos de pacientes con edad pediátrica de IPC descritos en la literatura en los últimos 10 años, 7 de los cuales (77,7%) recibieron BNDP. La IPC es una complicación inusual y el BNDP parece ser la causa más frecuente. Se dispone de diferentes opciones terapéuticas para el manejo de la IPC, pero ninguna protocolizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;29(3): 127-130, jul. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Isquemia postcircuncisión: una complicación inesperada. Revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2970^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
