<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107931</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Budgetary impact for the National Health System of Apixaban prophylaxis of venous thromboembolism in patients undergoing total knee or hip replacement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BacKground: Due to high health care costs of venous thromboembolism (VTE), economic analyses are needed to determine the efficiency of different drug treatments. Consequently, a study was conducted to estimate the budgetary impact for the National Health System (NHS) with apixaban for prevention of venous thromboembolism (VTE) in total hip (THR) or knee (TKR) replacement. Methods: Cost considered: the drugs for the prevention of VTE (apixaban, dabigatran, enoxaparin, fondaparinux, other heparins, rivaroxaban and warfarin) and the complications of VTE in the short term and in 5 years (deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism, bleedings and the post-thrombotic syndrome). The effectiveness of prophylaxis was estimated using a meta-analysis. The VTE rates and death with apixaban are lower in THR and TKR than enoxaparin (-3.5% and -10.0%, respectively) with less bleeding events (-0.7% and -1.6%, respectively). Population data and unit costs were obtained from Spanish sources. Time horizon: 5 years. All costs were discounted by 3.5% annually. Five years after commercialization, the use of apixaban was estimated to account for 23% of the prophylaxis of VTE and the use of enoxaparin decrease from the 60% to 33%. Results: Apixaban´s introduction for the prophylaxis of VTE would have a significant impact for the NHS, resulting in a saving of euros 547,422 over a period of 5 years. In the case of outpatient administration of heparin did not have a cost, the savings for the NHS five years amount to euros 270,068. Conclusions: According to this study, the introduction of apixaban may reduce the rate of VTE and bleeding compared with enoxaparin, decreasing the expenditure of NHS in VTE prophylaxis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio-Terrés, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Cerezo, Jorge F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Arrayas, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Fernández, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betegón Nicolás, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas-Cansado, Marina de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Debido al elevado coste sanitario del tromboembolismo venoso (TEV) es necesario realizar análisis económicos que determinen la eficiencia de sus diferentes tratamientos farmacológicos. El objetivo del trabajo es estimar el impacto presupuestario para el Sistema Nacional de Salud (SNS) de la prevención del tromboembolismo venoso (TEV) con apixaban en artroplastia total de cadera (ATC) o rodilla (ATR). Métodos: Se consideraron los costes de los diferentes fármacos para la prevención del TEV (apixaban, dabigatrán, enoxaparina, fondaparinux, otras heparinas, rivaroxaban y warfarina) y los de las complicaciones del TEV a corto plazo (90 días) y a 5 años (trombosis venosa profunda, embolismo pulmonar, sangrados y síndrome postrombótico). La eficacia de la prevención se estimó mediante un metaanálisis. Las tasas de TEV y muerte con apixaban fueron inferiores en ATC y ATR a las observadas con enoxaparina (-3,5% y -10,0%, respectivamente) y tuvo menos acontecimientos hemorrágicos (-0,7% y -1,6%, respectivamente). Los datos poblacionales y los costes se obtuvieron de fuentes españolas. Horizonte temporal: 5 años. Todos los costes se descontaron anualmente un 3,5%. Se estimó que a los cinco años de su comercialización el consumo de apixaban supondría el 23% de la prevención del TEV y el de enoxaparina descendería del 60% hasta el 33%. Resultados: La introducción de apixaban para la prevención del TEV produciría un ahorro para el SNS de 547.422 euros en un periodo de 5 años. En el caso de considerar sin coste la administración ambulatoria de las heparinas, el ahorro quinquenal para el SNS ascendería a 270.068 euros. Conclusiones: La introducción de apixaban podría reducir la tasa de TEV y sangrados en comparación con enoxaparina, reduciéndose el gasto del SNS en la prevención del TEV(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;86(6): 601-612, nov.-dic.2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto presupuestario para el Sistema Nacional de Salud de la prevención del tromboembolismo venoso con Apixaban en pacientes sometidos a artroplastia total de rodilla o cadera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28214</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31485^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52618^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1185^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55153</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31485^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
