<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80949</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Material and method: We have performed a systematic reviewof breast cancer with the following key words: Boneevents and zoledronic acid, bone-mineral density and zoledronicacid, antitumoral activity and zoledronic acid (preclinicaland clinical trials).Results: Treatment with zoledronic acid decreased the incidenceof bone metastases and micro metastases in the bonemarrow of women with advanced breast cancer. In premenopausalwomen with adjuvant endocrine therapy with concomitantzoledronic acid bone loss of bone-mineral density wasprevented during therapy and it was improved at 5 years.There are preliminary that support a sinergistic effect aboutzoledronic acid and neoadjuvant treatment on recurrence anddisease-free survival.Conclusions: There are evidence from zoledronic acid andthe treatment of bone tumors and bone metastases. The treatmentwith zoledronic acid would improve bone-mineral densityin the adjuvant treatment in women with endocrine-responsivebreast cancer. Zoledronic acid with good preliminary results inthe neoadjuvant chemotherapy would be a promise in thestandard management of these patients. There are promisingdifferent therapeutic clinical models studies in this way(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roman, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merchán, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidart, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brenes, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Material y método: Se realizó una estrategia de búsquedade cáncer de mama con los siguientes descriptores: ácido zoledrónicoy eventos óseos, ácido zoledrónico y mineralizaciónósea, ácido zoledrónico y efecto antitumoral (estudios preclínicosy clínicos).Resultados: La administración de ácido zoledrónico disminuyóde forma significativa el número de metástasis óseas enmujeres con cáncer de mama avanzado.En mujeres premenopáusicas con cáncer de mama y tratamientohormonal adyuvante en un seguimiento a 5 años, ladensitometría ósea de las mujeres que recibieron tratamientocon hormonoterapia y ácido zoledrónico se mantuvo establedurante los tres primeros años y aumentó a los cinco años.Los resultados preliminares de últimos estudios hablan deun efecto sinérgico del tratamiento neoadyuvante y el ácidozoledrónico y de su probable influencia sobre la recidiva y lasupervivencia libre de enfermedad.Conclusiones: Existe evidencia científica acumulada deltratamiento de tumores óseos y metástasis óseas con ácido zoledrónico.La administración de ácido zoledrónico en el tratamientoadyuvante de hormonoterapia parece aumentar la mineralizaciónósea. El ácido zoledrónico con buenos resultadospreliminares en la quimioterapia neoadyuvante promete serun buen candidato junto al tratamiento estándar de las pacientescon cáncer de mama y es un campo en el que se está investigandoampliamente, en espera de resultados definitivos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);23(3): 98-106, 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80949</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de mama y ácido zoledrónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33861^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1887^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2147^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14010^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4220^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
