<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92293</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sexual abuse: symptoms and consequences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sexual abuse like crime framed inside the contexts of violence sociopolítica, admits in terms of a traumatic event that it leaves serious alterations in the health of the survivors. The generated sequels, they have devastating scopes in the course of lavida of lasvíctimas, compromising his mental, physical, and sexual integrity. This article, it does a review of the principal consequences that leaves the sexual abuse in the women, to level sintomatológico. contexts are exposed also of revictimización and general positions with regard to the topic in the panorama investigativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Córdoba Arévalo, Martha Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo Samudio, Álvaro Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El abuso sexual como delito enmarcado dentro de los contextos de violencia sociopolítica, se reconoce en términos de un evento traumático que deja graves alteraciones en la salud de los sobrevivientes. Las secuelas generadas, tienen alcances devastadores en el curso de lavida de lasvíctimas, comprometiendo su integridad mental, física, y sexual. este artículo, hace una revisión de las principales consecuencias que deja el abuso sexual en las mujeres, a nivel sintomatológico. se exponen también contextos de revictimización y posturas generales respecto al tema en el panorama investigativo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;29(1): 161-175, ene.-abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92293</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abuso sexual: síntomas y consecuencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12338^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13122^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
