<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050391</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-4723</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The results of a 25-year study of 180 patients with the ulcerative colitis is presented. This entity was found to be predominant in females. Most patients were between 20and 40 years, white and belonged to urban areas. The most frequent chief complaints were diarrhea and hematochezia. The predominant symptoms and signs were diarrhea with mucus and blood, asthenia, loss of weight, psychiatric disorders and abdominal pain with tenesmus. Arthropathy was the most common extraintestinal manifestation. Patients were classified according to the clinical course, anatomic involvement and endoscopic features. Pseudopolyps, hemorrhages and modifications of the bowel diameter were the most common complications.T he most frequent medical therapy was salicylazosulfapyridine, followed by steroids in different route administrations. Other medicines were used such as azathioprine and methotrexate. Surgical therapy was instituted in 41patients. The most important causes of death were: sepsis, massive hemorrhage and malignant lesions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Holguín, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pila Pérez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alzate, Luis F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el resultado del estudio de 180 pacientes concolitis ulcerosa en nuestro hospital durante 25 años. Se informa que la enfermedad predominó en el sexo femenino, que la mayoría de los pacientes se encontraban entre20 y 40 años, pertenecían la mayoría al color de la piel blanca y de procedencia urbana. Se indica que los motivos de consulta más frecuentes fueron la diarrea y la enterorragia. Se destaca que los síntomas y los signos predominantes fueron la diarrea con flemas y sangre, la astenia, la pérdida de peso, los trastornos psíquicos y el dolor abdominal con pujo y tenesmo. Se expresa que las artropatías ocupan el primer lugar como manifestación extracólica. Se clasificó a los pacientes atendiendo a su curso clínico evolutivo, anatómico y endoscópico. Se comprobó que los pseudopólipos, las hemorragias y las modificaciones del calibre del intestino fueron las complicaciones halladas con mayor frecuencia. La terapéutica médica se efectuó con mayor frecuencia con salicilazosulfapiridina, seguida por los esteroides en diferentes vías de administración, otros medicamentos empleados fueron el imuran y el metotrexate, la terapéutica quirúrgica se practicó en 41 enfermos (22,8%). La mortalidad se encontró en 15,8% de los pacientes, siendo las causas más frecuentes la sepsis, la hemorragia y la malignización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. emerg;8(1): 27-33, ene.-mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colitis ulcerosa. Estudio de 25 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23971^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12835^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
