<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73419</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Obsessive-Compulsive Inventory &#150; Revised (OCI-R): Applicability to general population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Obsessive-Compulsive Inventory - Revised (OCI-R; Foa et al., 2002) has became the measure of election for the assessment of obsessive-compulsive behaviors, given its validity and the short time that its administration requires. Nevertheless, the OCI-R not yet has been studied on samples from the general population. In the present study the psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the OCI-R in two groups of subjects have been analyzed: university students (n = 247), which will allow comparing the results with those of previous studies, and general population (n = 395), which will allow generalizing these results to people without known clinical pathology or with subclinical symptoms. The factorial structure, the reliability and the convergent, divergent and criterion validity of the OCI-R were analyzed. The results show a factorial structure and psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the OCI-R similar to the ones found on the original version and, as expected, moderate relationship between the OCI-R scores and related variables: intrusions, dysfunctional beliefs, worry, and perfectionism. It is concluded that the Spanish version of the OCI-R is applicable to the general population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Godoy, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Malpica, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Víctor M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavino, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Obsessive-Compulsive Inventory - Revised (OCI-R; Foa et al., 2002) se ha convertido en instrumento de elección para la evaluación de los comportamientos obsesivo-compulsivos, dada su validez y el corto tiempo que requiere su administración. Sin embargo, el OCI-R aún no ha sido estudiado sobre muestras de la población general. En el presente estudio se analizan las propiedades psicométricas de la versión española del OCI-R en dos grupos de sujetos: estudiantes universitarios (n = 247), lo que permitirá comparar los resultados obtenidos con los de estudios previos, y población general (n = 395), lo que permitirá generalizar dichos resultados a personas sin patología clínica conocida o con sintomatología subclínica. Se ha analizado la estructura factorial, la fiabilidad y la validez convergente, divergente y de criterio del OCI-R. Los resultados muestran una estructura factorial y unas propiedades psicométricas similares a las halladas con la versión original y, tal y como se esperaba, un grado medio de relación entre el OCI-R y otras variables con las que se hipotetizó que estaría relacionado: intrusiones, creencias disfuncionales, preocupaciones y perfeccionismo. Se concluye que la versión española del OCI-R es aplicable a la población general(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;25(2): 217-226, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73419</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inventario de Obsesiones y Compulsiones-Revisado (OCI-R): Aplicabilidad a la población general</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9955^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
