<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118591</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tranexamic acid in orthopedic surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Perioperative bleeding may require blood transfusions, which are sometimes not without complications and risks, with the subsequent increase in health care costs. Among other prevention methods, treatment with tranexamic acid (ATX) has shown to be effective in reducing surgical blood loss, especially in the immediate postoperative period. In this regard, studies evaluating ATX in orthopedic surgery show that it is effective and safe when administered intravenously or intra-articularly. The usual evaluated intravenous doses range between 10 mg/Kg and 20 mg/kg or a fixed dose of 1 g to 2 g; while intra-articularly, it varies between 250 mg and 3 g. ATX, as an anti-fibrinolytic has a potential thrombotic effect, thus it is contraindicated in those patients at risk or with a history of thrombosis. Its topical administration may be safer, but studies are needed to confirm this (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Zapata, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Natera-Cisneros, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monllau-García, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera-Roigg, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jordán-Sales, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sangrado perioperatorio en ocasiones conduce a transfusiones sanguíneas no exentas de complicaciones y riesgos, con un alto gasto sanitario. Entre otros métodos de prevención, el tratamiento con ácido tranexámico (TXA) ha mostrado ser efectivo en la disminución de las pérdidas sanguíneas quirúrgicas y especialmente en el postoperatorio inmediato. Al respecto, los estudios que lo han evaluado en cirugía ortopédica muestran su eficacia y seguridad, administrado por vía tanto intravenosa como intraarticular. Las dosis habituales por vía intravenosa evaluadas oscilan entre 10 y 20 mg/kg, o en dosis fijas de 1 a 2 g, mientras por vía intraarticular varía entre 250 mg y 3 g. El TXA como antifibrinolítico tiene un potencial efecto trombótico y está contraindicado en aquellos pacientes con riesgo o antecedentes de trombosis. Su administración por vía tópica podría ser más segura aunque se precisan estudios que lo confirmen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(1): 52-56, ene.-feb. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118591</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ácido tranexámico en cirugía ortopédica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1831^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14540^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27231^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14540^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14540^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27231^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
