<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048653</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypersensitivity reaction to systemic corticosteroids in a hemodialysis patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypersensitivity reactions are a feared complication of hemodialysis consideringtheir potential for a serious and eventually fatal course. This association could reflecta number of different exposures, including concomitant medications. Like this,systemic steroid-induced hypersensitivity reactions do occur, althought their incidenceis extremely rare. A few reactions related to metylprednisolone have beenreported in renal transplantation. The diagnosis could be confirmed by the patient history and performing skin testing, oral or parenteral challenge or by the evienceof specific IgE. We report on a 39-year-old woman undergoing dialysis therapyin whom severe bronchospasm was induced by corticosteroids. She has a positivesystemic reaction on the oral steroid challenge test. A successful desensitizationregimen for safe administration was achieved. The recognition of high-risk subjectsand alternative therapeutic approach are critical, mainly in the managementof patients while receiving corticosteroids or a renal allograft</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Enríquez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sirvent, A. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samper, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Calle, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, J. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenas, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las reacciones de hipersensibilidad que ocurren durante la hemodiálisis son unacomplicación de curso potencialmente fatal. Se describen asociadas a una seriede factores que incluyen la administración concomitante de medicación. Por otraparte y aunque se consideran raras, se han comunicado reacciones de hipersensibilidada corticoides sistémicos. Algunos casos, en relación a metilprednisolona,se han evidenciado en la inducción del trasplante renal. El diagnóstico se confirmaen base a la historia clínica y a tests cutáneos y de provocación oral o parenteral,o incluso por la identificación de IgE específicas. Describimos el caso deuna mujer de 39 años en hemodiálisis de mantenimiento que presentaba reaccionesde hipersensibilidad inducidas por esteroides demostradas por la pruebade provocación oral. En la enferma se logró inducir tolerancia a metilprednisolonamediante un régimen de desensibilización. La identificación de hipersensibilidada esteroides sistémicos es necesaria en pacientes que los precisen como terapiade mantenimiento o para un futuro trasplante renal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;26(1): 128-131, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048653</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reacción de hipersensibilidad por corticoides sistémicos en una paciente en hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29373</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30024^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7202^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7450</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2016^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
