<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148341</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">On the therapeutic action of psychoanalysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Advances in the understanding of the therapeutic action of psychoanalysis should be based on a deeper insight into the psychoanalytic process: the significant interactions between patient and analyst which lead to structural changes in the patient's personality. Interaction with the environment plays an important role in the formation, development, and inte. rity of the psychic apparatus and means to deal with the central problem of the relationship between the development of psychic structures and nteraction with other psychic structures, and of the connection between ego-formation and object-relations. Ego-development is resumed in the therapeutic psychoanalytic process in the relationship with a new object, the analyst. Attempts are made to correlate the understanding that the significance of object-relations has the formation and development of the psychic apparatus with the dyamics of the therapeutic process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Loewald, Hans W</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Avanzar en la comprensión de la acción terapéutica del psicoanálisis requiere de la comprensión del proceso psicoanalítico, específicamente de las interacciones significativas entre paciente y analista que producen cambios estructurales en la personalidad del paciente. Apreciar el rol de la interacción con el entorno en la formación, desarrollo e integridad del aparato psíquico supone ocuparse de su interacción con otros, y de la conexión entre la formación del yo y las relaciones de objeto. El desarrollo del yo se continúa en el proceso terapéutico psicoanalítico en la relación con el nuevo objeto, el analista. El trabajo intenta correlacionar la comprensión de la importancia de las relaciones de objeto en la formación y el desarrollo del aparato psíquico con las dinámicas del proceso terapéutico. Para desarrollar ese tema el autor encara problemas de la teoría psicoanalítica y de la tradición concerniente a las relaciones objetales, el fenómeno de la transferencia, las relaciones entre las pulsiones y el yo, tanto como lo que concierne a la función del analista en la situación analítica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(75): 51-86, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148341</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sobre la acción terapéutica del psicoanálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4389</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14230^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14230^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27466^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12491</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33143</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27466^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
