<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101642</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subtypes of adolescents with substance use disorders and psychiatric comorbidity using cluster and discriminant analysis of MMPI-A profiles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main aim of this study was to replicate and extend previous results on subtypes of adolescents with substance use disorders (SUD), according to their Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory for adolescents (MMPI-A) profiles. Sixty patients with SUD and psychiatric comorbidity (41.7% male, mean age = 15.9 years old) completed the MMPI-A, the Teen Addiction Severity Index (T-ASI), the Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL), and were interviewed in order to determine DSMIV diagnoses and level of substance use. Mean MMPI-A personality profile showed moderate peaks in Psychopathic Deviate, Depression and Hysteria scales. Hierarchical cluster analysis revealed four profiles (acting-out, 35% of the sample; disorganized-conflictive, 15%; normative-impulsive, 15%; and deceptive-concealed, 35%). External correlates were found between cluster 1, CBCL externalizing symptoms at a clinical level and conduct disorders, and between cluster 2 and mixed CBCL internalized/externalized symptoms at a clinical level. Discriminant analysis showed that Depression, Psychopathic Deviate and Psychasthenia MMPI-A scales correctly classified 90% of the patients into the clusters obtained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forns, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canalda, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro-Fornieles, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magallón-Neri, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goti, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo principal de este estudio fue replicar y ampliar los resultados de estudios previos sobre subtipos de adolescentes con trastorno por uso de sustancias (TUS), de acuerdo con sus perfiles de personalidad en el Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory for adolescents (MMPI-A). Sesenta pacientes con TUS y comorbilidad psiquiátrica (41.7% hombres, edad media = 15.9 años) completaron el MMPI-A, el Teen Addiction Severity Index (T-ASI), el Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL), y entrevistas para obtener diagnósticos DSM-IV y medidas del nivel de uso de sustancias. El perfil general de personalidad MMPI-A mostró elevaciones moderadas en las escalas de Desviación Psicopática, Depresión e Histeria. El análisis de cluster jerárquico reveló cuatro perfiles (acting-out, 35% de la muestra; disorganized-conflictive, 15%; normative-impulsive, 15%; y deceptive-concealed, 35%). Se encontraron asociaciones entre el cluster 1, la sintomatología externalizante a nivel clínico del CBCL y los trastornos de conducta, así como entre el cluster 2 y un nivel clínico de síntomas internalizantes y externalizantes del CBCL. El análisis discriminante mostró que las escalas del MMPI-A Depresión, Desviación Psicopática y Psicastenia, clasificaron correctamente el 90% de los pacientes dentro de los subgrupos obtenidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);24(3): 219-228, jul.-sept. 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101642</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Subtipos de adolescentes con trastornos por uso de sustancias y comorbilidad psiquiátrica utilizando los análisis de cluster y discriminante de perfiles MMPI-A</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9140^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
