<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047751</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9626</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Report of the III workshop on immunochemistry of the spanish society of immunology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The III workshop in immunochemistry supported by the&#147;Sociedad Española de Inmunología&#148; (SEI), consisted in a inter-laboratorycomparative study to evaluate the homogeneity of the analytic methodsin immunochemistry. The objective was to create quality control toolsto standardise analytic procedures (1-4).Methods: 21 centres have participated in the workshop. It comprisedthe quantification of IgG, IgA, IgM, total IgE, &amp;#954; and &amp;#955; light chains, IgG subclasses,C3, C4, RF, CRP and ASL in serum samples. Monoclonal proteinspresent in serum and urine samples have been also characterised. Thestudy was performed using standard routine methods (5,6). Each laboratorysent its results to the workshop coordinators that proceeded toanalyse and present them in the Congress of the SEI.Results: Analytical parameters standardised by the International Federationof Clinical Chemistry (IFCC) showed a good homogeneity, exceptC4, that exhibited an important dispersion associated to punctual differencesin standardisation between different manufacturers. Analyticalparameters not standardised by IFCC showed higher heterogeneity.The identification of the monoclonal proteins in serum and urine washighly homogeneous. Quantitative results of monoclonal isotypes wasmore heterogeneous than that of polyclonal immunoglobulins.Conclusions: Inter-comparative studies are very useful to investigatethe homogeneity among different laboratories. These results demonstratethe need of: quality controls, evaluation of suppliers, and elaborationof consensus working procedures</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sequí Navarro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar Guimerans, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Molina, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El III Taller de Inmunoquímica (IQ) auspiciado por la SociedadEspañola de Inmunología (SEI), consistió en un estudio de comparacióninterlaboratorios para evaluar la homogeneidad de los métodosanalíticos en IQ. El objetivo es la creación de herramientas de control decalidad que permitan estandarizar los procedimientos analíticos (1-4).Métodos: En el ejercicio han participado 21 centros y ha consistido enla cuantificación de IgG, IgA, IgM, IgE total, cadenas ligeras &amp;#954; y &amp;#955;, subclasesde IgG, C3, C4, FR, PCR y ASLO en muestras de suero. También se hancaracterizado los Componentes Monoclonales (CM) en muestras de sueroy orina. El estudio se realizó mediante los métodos de trabajo habituales(5,6). Los laboratorios remitieron los resultados a los coordinadores del Taller,que procedieron a su análisis y presentación en el Congreso de la SEI.Resultados: Los parámetros analíticos estandarizados por la InternationalFederation of Clinical Chemistry (IFCC) mostraron una buenahomogeneidad, exceptuando el C4, que presentaba una importante dispersiónde los resultados asociada a diferencias puntuales de estandarizaciónentre distintos fabricantes. La heterogeneidad fue mayor en losparámetros no estandarizados por la IFCC.La identificación de los CM en sangre y orina demostró una alta homogeneidad.Los resultados cuantitativos de los isotipos de los CM es másheterogénea que en las inmunoglobulinas policlónales . Conclusiones: Losestudios intercomparativos son de gran utilidad para conocer el estadode homogeneidad entre los laboratorios. Se constata la necesidad de reforzarla calidad, la evaluación de proveedores y elaborar protocolos de trabajoconsensuados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inmunología (1987);25(1): 57-66, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047751</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de parámetros inmunoquímicos y paraproteínas. Informe del III Taller de Inmunoquímica de la Sociedad Española de Inmunología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23289^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22253^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23132^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
