<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112743</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A method for detect Ig M monoclonal gammopathies in an autoanalyzer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Most patients with multiple myeloma have a previous monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance. This study analyzes the possible clinical usefulness of a false positive lipemia as a routine, inexpensive screening tool for IgM monoclonal gammopathies. Material and methods. Serum samples from 244 consecutive patients with a false positive (n=34) or negative lipemia test (n=210), with triglycerides &lt;1.7mmol/L were studied. Immunoglobulin levels were quantified in an AU-5430 autoanalyzer. Lipemia tests were performed in a final saline concentration of 0,038M, and proteins by capillary-zone electrophoresis. Results. Sensitivity for monoclonal band detection was 97% (95% CI 91-100) for false lipemia, with 94% (95% CI: 91-97) specificity. The positive and negative predictive values were 72% (95% CI: 59-85) and 99% (95% CI: 99-100), respectively. Its sensitivity for elevated IgM detection was 71% (95% CI: 55-86) and 99% (95% CI: 98-100) specificity, positive and negative predictive values of 92% (95% CI: 82-100) and 95% (95% CI: 93-98), respectively. Age and sex-adjusted odds ratio of elevated IgM for false lipemic serum patients was 768.0 (95% CI: 75.8-7799.3), and 219.4 (95% CI: 42.9-1120.5) for the monoclonal band. Conclusions. A false positive lipemic test was associated with elevated IgM, and particularly with monoclonal gammopathy. This finding offers an inexpensive, sensitive and specific screening tool to detect IgM monoclonal gammopathy processes in routine autoanalyzer interference tests (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baena-Díez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Sarmiento, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrugat de la Iglesia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esquerdo Merlos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fitóe Colomer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Frecuentemente el mieloma múltiple es precedido de una gammapatía monoclonal de significado incierto. Este estudio analiza la utilidad de una lipidemia falsamente positiva como un método rutinario y barato de detección de gammapatías monoclonales de IgM. Material y métodos. Se examinaron los sueros de 244 pacientes consecutivos con un índice lipidémico falso positivo (n=34) o negativo (n=210) y triglicéridos &lt; 1,7mmol/L. Las concentraciones de inmunoglobulinas se estudiaron mediante un autoanalizador AU-5430. Los test de lipidemia fueron realizados con una concentración salina de 0,038M y los proteinogramas mediante una electroforesis capilar de la zona. Resultados. Con el diagnóstico de banda monoclonal la lipidemia falsa positiva tuvo una sensibilidad del 97% (95% CI: 91-100) y especificidad del 94% (95% CI: 91-97). El valor predictivo positivo y negativo fue de 72% (95% CI: 59-85) y 99% (95% CI: 99-100), respectivamente. Para el diagnóstico de IgM elevada la sensibilidad fue del 71% (95% CI: 55-86), la especificidad del 99% (95% CI: 98-100) y el valor predictivo positivo y negativo del 92% (95% CI: 82-103) y 95% (95% CI: 93-98), respectivamente. El OR ajustado por edad y sexo de la lipidemia falso positivo fue de 768,0 (95% CI: 75,8-7.799,3) para la IgM elevada y de 219,4 (95% CI: 42,9-1.120,5) para la banda monoclonal. Conclusiones. La lipidemia falsamente positiva se asoció a la IgM elevada y particularmente a la gammapatía monoclonal. Es una herramienta barata, sensible y específica para detectar una gammapatía monoclonal de IgM en los índices de interferencia rutinarios en analizadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;6(2): 55-59, abr.-jun. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112743</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un método de detección de gammapatías monoclonales de IgM en un analizador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10454^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22207^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32762^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32762^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32762^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32762^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32762^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
