<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61501</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychosocial and psychopathological characteristics of Spanish adolescents sample throw Youth Self-Report/11-18</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study we analyzed the psychosocial competences and psychopathological characteristics assessed by the YSR/11-18 in a sample of 961 Spanish adolescents from 13-18 years. The results indicated that men scored high in various social activities and externalized psychopa-thologies, while women have high scores for performance in different tasks and internalized symptoms. Younger adolescents showed higher scores than older ones in participation in groups and organizations, as well as in most of the YSR/11-18 syndromic scales, while older adolescent&#146;s preferred no sports activities and works or tasks. Students at Compulsory Secondary Education and Non-Compulsory Secondary Education showed more activity than those in Vocational Training Cycles in all psychosocial competencies, but the latter overcame the first in most of the syndromic scales. Adolescents without romantic relation scored higher in the psycho-social competencies than those who enjoyed romantic relation, although the second ones showed more psychopathology than the first ones. Fi-nally, working (in addition to studying) did not seem to be relevant in determining differences regarding the psychosocial competencies and syndromic scales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Parra, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zubeidat, Ihab</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analizan las competencias psicosociales y características psicopatológicas evaluadas por el YSR/11-18 (Achenbach y Rescorla, 2000, 2001) en una muestra de 961 adolescentes españoles de 13-18 años de edad. Los resultados encontrados indicaron que los varones puntúan de forma elevada en distintas actividades sociales y psicopatología externalizante, mientras que las mujeres presentan mayores puntuaciones en rendimiento en diferentes tareas y sintomatología internalizante. Los adolescentes de menor edad presentan puntuaciones más altas que los mayores en la participación en grupos y organizaciones, así como en la mayoría de las escalas sindrómicas del YSR/11-18, mientras que los segundos prefieren realizar actividades no deportivas y trabajos o tareas. Los alumnos de ESO y Bachillerato presentan más actividad en todas las competencias psicosociales que los de Ciclos Formativos, aunque éstos últimos superan a los primeros en la mayoría de las escalas sindrómicas. Los adolescentes sin relación de pareja puntuaron más alto en las competencias psicosociales que los que disfrutan de la misma, aunque éstos muestran más psicopatología que los primeros. Por último, realizar una actividad laboral (además de estudiar) no parece ser relevante a la hora de establecer diferencias respecto a las competencias psicosociales y a las escalas sindrómicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;25(1): 60-69, ene.-jun. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61501</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características psicosociales y psicopatológicas en una muestra de adolescentes españoles a partir del Youth Self-Report/11-18</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
