<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112267</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fully covered self-expanding metal stents in the management of difficult common bile duct stones</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: plastic biliary stents are often used after an ERCP session without complete common bile duct stones (CBDS) extraction. Sometimes, the volume of biliary drainage with these stents may be insufficient. We present our experience with the use of fully covered self-expanding metal stents (FCSEMS) in the setting of incomplete CBDS extraction. Patients and methods: after an ERCP session with difficult CBDS not completely removed, biliary FCSEMS (Wallflex) were inserted in some patients when it was deemed that biliary sphincterotomy and a single plastic stent would not provide an adequate drainage. Results: a retrospective study was performed. Biliary FCSEMS were inserted in 29 patients, mean age 81 years. CBDS could not be extracted through a biliary sphincterotomy due to its large size (n = 18) or because of the presence of inflammatory distal strictures (n = 11). The greatest biliary drainage with shortest ERCP time was considered mandatory due to clinical instability of patients and/or poor tolerance to conscious sedation administered by the endoscopist. Successful biliary drainage was obtained in all cases. FCSEMS were removed after a median of 199.5 days in 16 patients with a complete CBDS extraction in 15 (93.7%). FCSEMS were not removed in the remaining 13 patients due to their clinical condition, and a wait-and-see strategy was undertaken. Conclusions: in selected cases, utilization of removable FCSEMS can be a good option for a quick and adequate biliary drainage in the setting of difficult CBDS. Because of the higher cost of these stents its use needs to be individualized(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Karolina Reyes Guevara, Amanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morillas Ariño, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Sola, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valiente González, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viñuelas Chicano, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Vigara, Gracia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pérez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cano, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Ruiz, Carmen Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Fernández, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: las prótesis biliares plásticas suelen emplearse tras una sesión de CPRE sin extracción completa de coledocolitiasis. En ocasiones, el calibre de drenaje con estas prótesis puede ser insuficiente. Presentamos nuestra experiencia en la utilización de prótesis metálicas autoexpandibles totalmente recubiertas (PMATR) en coledocolitiasis no extraídas. Pacientes y métodos: se insertó una PMATR (Wallflex biliar) en algunos pacientes con coledocolitiasis difíciles no extraídas tras una sesión de CPRE cuando se consideró que la esfinterotomía biliar y una prótesis plástica no aportaban un calibre de drenaje adecuado. Resultados: estudio retrospectivo en el que se utilizó una PMATR en 29 pacientes, edad media 81 años. Las coledocolitiasis no pudieron extraerse por la esfinterotomía biliar debido a su gran tamaño (n = 18) o por la presencia de estenosis distal inflamatoria (n = 11). Se consideró que era preciso el mayor drenaje biliar con el menor tiempo posible de CPRE debido a la situación de inestabilidad clínica de los pacientes y/o a la mala tolerancia a la sedación consciente administrada por el endoscopista. Se obtuvo un drenaje biliar adecuado en todos los casos. Las PMATR se retiraron tras una mediana de 199,5 días en 16 pacientes, obteniéndose una extracción completa de las coledocolitiasis en 15 (93,7%). No se extrajeron las PMATR en los 13 restantes debido a su situación clínica, manteniéndose una conducta expectante. Conclusiones: en casos seleccionados, la utilización de PMATR extraíbles es una buena opción para obtener un drenaje biliar adecuado y rápido en coledocolitiasis difíciles. El mayor coste de estas prótesis precisa que se individualice su utilización(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(1): 7-12, ene. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112267</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prótesis metálicas autoexpandibles totalmente recubiertas en el tratamiento de coledocolitiasis difíciles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29813^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29813^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29813^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
