<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040572</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Indolent infectious mononucleosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The authors report the case of a 14-year-old girl. diagnosed as having infectious mononucleosis. She presented severe hypertrophy of the reticuloendothelial system, with hepatosplenomegaly of more than 16 cm, marked changes in liver enzymes and hypertrophy of the cervical Iymph nodes. Despite these signs, she presented practically no clinical symptomatology. Four weeks later, the clinical and analytical findings were normal; however, the reticuloendothelial system involvement persisted, with adenoid hypertrophy and hepatomegaly that lasted for 10 months</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cidoncha, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Campderá, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de una paciente de 14 años, diagnosticada de mononucleosis infecciosa, con una importante hipertrofia del sistema reticuloendotelial, con hepatosplenomegalia de más de 16 cm, una importante afectación de las enzimas hepáticas e hipertrofia de los ganglios cervicales. A pesar de estas manifestaciones, prácticamente no presentó ningún tipo de sintomatología clínica. La paciente evolucionó clínica yanalíticamente a la normalidad en cuatro semanas; sin embargo, persistió la afectación del sistema reticuloendotelial con hipertrofia adenoidea y hepatomegalia durante 10 meses</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;63(9): 389-393, oct. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mononucleosis infecciosa de evolución tórpida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33755^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33755^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33755^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6686^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13546^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7421^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
