<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77549</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Synovial chondromatosis. A study of 39 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the clinical manifestations, use of diagnostic imaging techniques and outcome of patients with synovial chondromatosis in our health area. Patients and methods: POVISA Hospital provides health services to a population of 127,000 inhabitants. The clinical histories of all the patients in this area who were histologically diagnosed with synovial chondromatosis between January 1992 and December 2003 were reviewed. Results: There were 38 cases of joint chondromatosis, all monoarticular, and one case of extra-articular chondromatosis in 20 men and 19 women aged 56.5 ± 12.7 years (mean ± SD) at diagnosis (range: 16-79 years). The main joint affected was the knee (15; 39.5%), followed by the hip (8; 21%) and the temporomandibular joint and elbow, both of these in three patients (7.9%). Previous arthropathy was recorded in 18 patients (18/38, 47.4%). Symptom duration prior to diagnosis was 25.4 ± 34 months. The most frequent clinical manifestations were joint pain (100%), restricted movement (77%) and swelling (57%). Plain radiographs were carried out in all patients and suggested the diagnosis in 20 (51.3%). Magnetic resonance imaging findings led to a diagnosis in 12 out of 15 patients in whom this procedure was required (80%). In all patients loose bodies were removed and synovectomy was performed by arthroscopic procedures in six. In 16 patients (42%) total joint replacement was required. The mean postoperative follow-up was 23.7 ± 5.3 months. No cases of chondrosarcoma were identified and the recurrence rate was low (7.9%). Conclusions: In our setting, almost half (47.4%) of the cases of synovial chondromatosis occurred in a previously damaged joint: the correct diagnosis was delayed by more than 2 years and total arthroplasty was required in 42% of the patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Penelas-Cortés, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón-Badiola, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Lorenzo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Rodríguez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez-Ruán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puente, M. C. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);2(2): 58-63, mar.-abr. 2006. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condromatosis sinovial. Estudio de 39 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24563^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31223^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33576^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32350^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
