<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116587</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patterns of Visceral Metastasis in Cutaneous Melanoma: A Descriptive Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objectives: Some types of cancer tend to spread to certain organs. In the case of melanoma, uveal melanoma spreads almost exclusively to the liver, while cutaneous melanoma spreads to the liver and other organs. Although important advances have been made in our understanding of the molecular mechanisms underlying melanoma, few recent studies have focused on the patterns of visceral metastasis in cutaneous melanoma. The aim of this study was to retrospectively investigate whether clinicopathologic variants of cutaneous melanoma and primary tumor site might be associated with pattern and time of onset of metastasis to visceral sites, including the central nervous system (CNS). Materials and methods: We included patients diagnosed with cutaneous melanoma between 1988 and 2009 with at least 2 years&#146; follow-up. Results: Of the 1083 patients studied, 92 developed visceral metastasis. The CNS was affected in 21 cases, the lungs in 24, the liver in 17, the digestive tract in 7, and multiple organs simultaneously in 23. Metastasis to the lungs, the liver, and the digestive tract occurred within 5 years in most cases, while metastasis to the CNS and multiple organs occurred later (&gt; 5 years in 38% and 43% of cases, respectively). Conclusions: Unlike uveal melanoma, cutaneous melanoma spreads to different organs without any particular predilection. We observed no significant associations between the site of visceral metastasis and either clinicopathologic variant or location of the primary tumor. Metastasis occurred within 5 years of diagnosis in most cases, but it can occur after 10 years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcoval, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Penín, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferreres, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa de Olza, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Algunas formas de cáncer tienden a producir metástasis en determinados órganos. En cuanto al melanoma, el melanoma uveal produce metástasis casi exclusivamente en el hígado, mientras que el melanoma cutáneo se disemina también a otros órganos. A pesar de importantes avances en el conocimiento de las bases moleculares del melanoma, hay pocos estudios recientes sobre el patrón de diseminación visceral del melanoma cutáneo. Nuestro objetivo fue analizar retrospectivamente una posible asociación entre tipo clinicopatológico y localización del melanoma cutáneo con el patrón de diseminación visceral y su cronología. Material y métodos: Se incluyeron en el estudio los pacientes diagnosticados de melanoma cutáneo entre 1988-2009 con más de 2 años de seguimiento. Resultados: De un total de 1.083 pacientes 92 desarrollaron metástasis viscerales: 21 en el sistema nervioso central (SNC), 24 en los pulmones, 17 en el hígado, 7 en el tubo digestivo y 23 en múltiples órganos simultáneamente. Las recidivas en el pulmón, el hígado y el tubo digestivo se produjeron mayoritariamente antes de los 5 años, mientras que las metástasis al SNC y a múltiples órganos simultáneamente fueron más tardías (38 y 43% después de los 5 años respectivamente). Conclusiones: A diferencia del melanoma ocular, el melanoma cutáneo se disemina por igual a múltiples órganos. No hemos detectado asociación significativa respecto al órgano diana de las metástasis según el tipo histológico y tampoco según la localización del tumor primario. A pesar de que la mayoría de metástasis viscerales se producen antes de los 5 años, también pueden producirse metástasis viscerales más allá de los 10 años de seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;104(7): 593-597, sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116587</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo del patrón de diseminación visceral del melanoma cutáneo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19377^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
