<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156916</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use and perceived usefulness of the Nursing Blog «Looking after newborns»</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to describe the demographical groups which are currently reading the &#147;«Looking after newborns» blog and its social networks, as well as learning their opinion about whether the information provided through its entries, both in the blog and in its social networks, has increased their knowledge about Neonatology. Method: a descriptive transversal study through an anonymous online survey conducted through the «Looking after newborns» blog and social networks, with a total population of 3,474 readers. The survey included 17 questions associated with the profile of connection to the network by its followers, and their interaction with the blog and social networks. Results: in total, 353 questionnaires were collected. The profile of «Looking after newborns» followers was varied; the highest proportions were for nurses (59.5%) and parents (19.3%). Users accessed it the first time through social networks or by recommendation of another healthcare professional. A 91.4% of parents and 80.4% of healthcare professionals followed the entries through Facebook. The blog section considered more interesting was «Care focused on development», with 57.9% for healthcare professionals, and «Information for parents», with 84.3% for parents. A 94.3-100% claims that reading this blog increased their knowledge, or allowed them to be more updated regarding Neonatology. Conclusions: reading the «Looking after newborns» blog and its social networks has become an important source for spreading knowledge on Neonatology among its readers, encouraging communication between healthcare professionals and parents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ros Navarret, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: describir los grupos demográficos que conforman actualmente los lectores del blog «Cuidando neonatos» y sus redes sociales, así como conocer su opinión acerca de si la información aportada a través de sus publicaciones, tanto en el blog como en sus redes sociales, aumenta sus conocimientos sobre Neonatología. Método: estudio descriptivo transversal mediante encuesta anónima online distribuida a través del blog y redes sociales de «Cuidando neonatos» con una población total de 3.474 lectores. La encuesta constaba de 17 preguntas relacionadas con el perfil de conectividad a la red de sus seguidores y su interacción con el blog y redes sociales. Resultados: se recogieron 353 cuestionarios. El perfil de seguidores de «Cuidando neonatos» fue variado, destacando por su número: enfermeras (59,5%) y padres (19,3%). Los usuarios accedieron por primera vez a través de las redes sociales o por consejo de otro profesional sanitario. El 91,4% de los padres y el 80,4% de los sanitarios seguían las publicaciones vía Facebook. La sección del blog con mayor interés fue «Cuidados centrados en el desarrollo» (57,9%) para los profesionales de salud e «Información para padres» para los padres (84,3%). El 94,3-100% afirma que su lectura aumentó sus conocimientos o les permitió estar más al día sobre Neonatología. Conclusiones: la lectura del blog «Cuidando neonatos» y sus redes sociales se ha convertido en una importante fuente de difusión de conocimientos sobre Neonatología para sus lectores, facilitando la comunicación entre profesionales sanitarios y padres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(8): 49-56, oct. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156916</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso y utilidad percibida del blog de Enfermería «Cuidando neonatos»</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53807^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54836^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53806^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
