<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134019</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience with pulse carbon monoxide oximetry for prehospital assessment of patients exposed to smoke from fires in closed spaces in Catalonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To describe the clinical characteristics of fire smoke inhalation victims and carboxyhemoglobin values (Sp- CO) recorded with a portable pulse carbon monoxide (CO) oximeter at rescue sites in Catalonia. To assess the contribution of SpCO information to decision-making during emergency transfers. Methods. Retrospective observational study. We included records for patients exposed to smoke in closed spaces at fires. The patients had been attended by the Catalan Emergency Medical Group (GEM) from January 2010 to December 2012. A logistic regression model included the following independent variables: sex, age, smoking status, known medical history, signs and symptoms of intoxication, burns, SpCO, and oxygen saturation. The dependent variable was the decision to transfer the patient to a hospital. Results. The GEM attended 331 victims; 6 died at the scene of the fire and 43.8 % (135/308) were transferred to a hospital. The cohort included 178 men (57.8% of 308), and 73.0% were between the ages of 18 and 65 years (216/296). SpCO levels were over 10% in 11.4% (35/308); the mean SpCO was 4.33% (95% CI, 3.65%-5.12%). The regression model identified the following variables associated with the decision to transfer the patient to a hospital: presence of burns (P=.014), signs (P&lt;.001) and symptoms (P=.011) of intoxication, and SpCO value (P&lt;.001). The odds ratio for SpCO &amp;#8805;  10% was 12.59 (95% CI, 4.32-36.69) in relation to transfer to a hospital. Conclusion. Pulse CO-oximetry contributed to the prehospital emergency care of these patients by influencing the decision to transfer the patient to a hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trilla, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sequera, Víctor-Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilajeliu, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrés-Padró, Vicenç</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El estudio describe las características clínicas y los valores de carboxihemoglobina por pulsicooximetría portátil (SpCO) in situ que presentaron víctimas de incendios y valora su aporte en la decisión de traslado hospitalario. Método. Estudio observacional retrospectivo. Se incluyeron víctimas expuestas a humo de incendios en ambientes cerrados que recibieron asistencia prehospitalaria por el Grup d&#146;Emergències Mèdiques (GEM) desde enero del 2010 a diciembre 2012. Se construyó un modelo explicativo de regresión logística con las variables independientes: sexo, edad, hábito tabáquico, antecedentes patológicos, síntomas y signos de intoxicación, presencia de quemaduras, valor de SpCO y saturación de oxígeno. La variable respuesta fue la decisión de traslado hospitalario. Resultados. Se atendieron a 331 de víctimas, seis de ellas fallecieron in situ. El 43,8% (135/308) fueron trasladadas a un hospital. El 57,8% (178/308) eran hombres, con edades comprendidas entre 18 y 65 años el 73,0% (216/296). El 11,4% (35/308) presentó valores de SpCO &amp;#8805; 10%, y la media global fue de 4,33% (IC95% 3,65-5,12). Las variables del modelo multivariante que mostraron asociación con la decisión de traslado hospitalario fueron: presencia de que- maduras (p = 0,014), signos (p &lt; 0,001) y síntomas (p = 0,011) de intoxicación y los valores de SpCO (p &lt; 0,001). En el caso de valores de SpCO &amp;#8805; 10%, la OR para traslado hospitalario fue 12,59 (IC 95% 4,32-36,69). Conclusión. El uso del pulsicooxímetro en la asistencia prehospitalaria aportó un valor añadido independiente para la toma de decisión de traslado hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(1): 23-26, feb. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134019</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia del uso del pulsicooxímetro en la evaluación prehospitalaria de las víctimas expuestas al humo de incendios en ambientes cerrados en Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30272^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22594^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2288^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22126^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35473</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13287^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
