<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96855</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interleucin 1 beta concentrations in preeclamptic patients and healthy normotensive pregnant women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To compare concentrations of interleukin-1 beta in patients with preeclampsia and healthy normotensive pregnant women. Material and methods One hundred patients were selected. Fifty preeclamptic patients were selected as cases (group A) and 50 healthy pregnant women with a similar age and body mass index to those in the study group were selected as controls (group B). Blood samples for interleukin-1 beta determination were collected in all patients before labor and immediately after diagnosis in the study group. Results No significant differences were found in maternal age, gestational age or body mass index at sample collection (p=ns). Significant differences were observed between groups in mean values of systolic and diastolic blood pressure (p&lt;0.05). Interleukin-1 beta concentrations were significantly higher in group A than in group B (18.2±7.3pg/ml compared with 13.6±5.4pg/ml; p&lt;0.05) and showed a slight, positive and significant correlation with values of systolic blood pressure and diastolic blood pressure (p&lt;0.05). Conclusions Concentrations of interleukin-1 beta were significantly higher in preeclamptic patients than in healthy normotensive pregnant women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reyna, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perozo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Comparar las concentraciones de interleucina 1 beta en pacientes con preeclampsia y embarazadas normotensas sanas. Material y métodos Se seleccionó un total de 100 pacientes. Se incluyeron a 50 pacientes preeclámpticas como los casos (grupo A) y un grupo control que fue seleccionado por tener una edad y un índice de masa corporal similares al grupo de estudio, y consistió en 50 embarazadas sanas (grupo B). Las muestras de sangre para la determinación de interleucina 1 beta se recolectaron en todas las pacientes antes del parto e inmediatamente después del diagnóstico en el grupo de casos. Resultados No se encontraron diferencias significativas con relación a la edad materna, edad gestacional e Índice de masa corporal al momento de la toma de la muestra (p=ns). Se observaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los grupos en los valores promedio de presión arterial sistólica y diastólica (p&lt;0,05). Las concentraciones de IL-1 beta fueron significativamente superiores en el grupo de estudio comparado con el grupo de controles (18,2±7,3pg/ml comparado con 13,6±5,4pg/ml, p&lt;0,05) y se observó una correlación leve, positiva y significativa con los valores de presión arterial sistólica y con los valores de presión arterial diastólica (p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones Las pacientes preeclámpticas presentaron concentraciones significativamente mas altas de concentraciones de interleucina 1 beta al compararlo con embarazadas normotensas sanas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);38(4): 128-132, jul. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96855</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Concentraciones de interleucina 1 beta en pacientes con preeclampsia y embarazadas normotensas sanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52277^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11662^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
