<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054157</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Delivery room cardiopulmonary resucitation of very preterm infants is associated with adverse shoirt and long term outcomes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective         To assess the short- and long-term outcome of infants &lt;= 1250 grams who have received delivery room cardiopulmonary resuscitation (DR-CPR). Methods         In a cohort of infants &lt;=1250 grams born between 01/2000 and 12/2003, we compared the rates of death, severe intraventricular hemorrhage (S-IVH), periventricular leukomalacia and combined poor short-term outcome (CO). At 18 months post- conception age (PCA) we compared DR-CPR and non-DR-CPR groups on the Bayley II Mental and Psychomotor Developmental Indices (MDI and PDI). Results         Of 397 infants who met enrollment criteria, the 53 (13%) who received DR-CPR had a higher risk for mortality, S-IVH, PVL and CO. At 18 months PCA, MDI and PDI scores were lower in the DR-CPR group (67.7 ± 18.3 vs. 81.3 ± 17.7; p = 0.006) and (74.4 ± 19.9 vs. 85.1 ± 17.2; p = 0.027), respectively. Conclusion         DR-CPR in infants &lt; 1250 grams is associated with higher mortality and greater short- and long-term morbidity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sola, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lee, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deulofeut, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rogido, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Evaluar los resultados a corto y largo plazo de la reanimación cardiopulmonar en sala de partos (RCP-SP) en neonatos 1.250 g o menos.         Métodos En una cohorte de neonatos con y sin RCP-SP con peso de 1.250 g o inferior nacidos entre enero de 2000 y diciembre de 2003, comparamos las tasas de mortalidad, hemorragia intracraneana severa (HIC-S), leucomalacia periventricular (LPV) y las variables combinadas (VC) adversas a corto plazo; a los 18 meses de edad posconcepcional (EPC) comparamos los índices del desarrollo mental (IDM) y psicomotor (IDP) según la escala de Bayley-II.         Resultados En 397 niños, los 53 (13 %) que habían recibido RCP-SP tuvieron mayor riesgo de mortalidad, HIC-S, LPV y VC adversas. A los 18 meses de edad posconcepcional la puntuación de IDM e IDP fue más baja en el grupo con RCP-SP (67,7 ± 18,3 frente a 81,3 ± 17,7; p = 0,006) y (74,4 ± 19,9 frente a 85,1 ± 17,2; p = 0,027), respectivamente.         Conclusión La RCP-SP en recién nacidos de 1.250 g o menos está asociada con mayor mortalidad y con peores tasas de morbilidad, en el corto plazo y en el seguimiento a largo plazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);66(1): 31-37, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054157</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La reanimación cardiopulmonar en sala de partos del recién nacido muy prematuro está asociada con resultados adversos a corto y a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23234^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19229^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19229^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19229^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19229^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1748^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
