<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137493</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metabolic syndrome in canarian working population (prospective study by an occupational medicine basic health unit)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Metabolic Syndrome (MS) is known to be a set of complex clinical pathological events with multiple causes: genetic, social, cultural, economic and occupational issues. According to global data MS prevalence ranges from 20 to 40% of the population. In Spanish occupational population, this &amp;#64257;gure reaches 7.8 to 12.1% (average 1/10 workers). Nevertheless, Occupational Medicine has been sidelined due to the fact that MS has no causal relationship and is not considered an occupational disease and / or work related illness, therefore it is not a research topic for work related issues. However, the paradox appears when once MS and its consequences are diagnosed, it is up to the medical services within the Occupational Medicine Basic Health Unit (BHU) to advise on the employee&#146;s suitability to perform usual tasks. MS pathophysiological factors, insulin resistance and obesity, come from a series of risk factors. Therefore, primary prevention is the most economical, affordable, effective and sustainable action to detect these factors. In this investigation, we show a 134 healthy workers&#146; sample who have  had periodical medical examinations by the Basic Health Unit (BHU)  of a Prevention Service (PS) (at present  PREMAP, Seguridad y Salud). An overall prevalence of 18% (24 workers) was obtained according to the de&amp;#64257;nition of MS by the NCEP-ATP III (Panel of Experts for detection, evaluation and treatment of High Cholesterol in Adults amended in 2005).According to the results obtained, Occupational Medicine has numerous everyday tools to diagnose, monitor and prevent the consequences of Metabolic Syndrome in workers and ultimately in general population. Moreover, according the Law of Prevention of Occupational Risks (LPOR) seeks not only the management of duties and responsibilities if subjects in regards to work issues, aiming also to promote a new culture in the &amp;#64257;eld of prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martel Martín, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Cruz, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se conoce al Síndrome metabólico (SM) como el conjunto de eventos clínico-patológicos complejos con una multicausalidad: genética, social, cultural, económica y laboral en el individuo. Según datos mundiales la prevalencia de SM oscila entre el 20-40 % de la población. En España, centrándonos en población laboral, ronda el 7,8 %- 12,1 % (de media 1/10 trabajadores). Sin embargo, la Medicina del Trabajo se ha mantenido al margen, ya que el SM no tiene una relación causa-efecto para ser considerada enfermedad profesional y/o enfermedad relacionada con el trabajo, por lo que no es tema de investigación en el campo laboral. Sin embargo, la paradoja se da cuando establecido el síndrome y sus consecuencias son los servicios médicos dentro de la Unidad Básica de Salud (UBS) de Medicina del Trabajo los que han de evaluar la aptitud del trabajador en las tareas habituales que realiza. Tanto la resistencia a la insulina como la obesidad, factores &amp;#64257;siopatológicos del SM, parten de una serie de factores  de riesgo  siendo la prevención primaria la acción más económica, barata, asequible y sostenible para detectar estos factores. En el estudio que presentamos de una muestra de 134 trabajadores sanos que han realizado reconocimiento médico periódico en una UBS de la Sociedad  Prevención (SP) de FREMAP (actualmente PREMAP Seguridad y Salud),  se obtuvo una prevalencia global del 18 % (24 trabajadores) siguiendo la de&amp;#64257;nición de SM según los criterios NCEP-ATP III (Panel de Expertos para la Detección, Evaluación y Tratamiento de la Hipercolesterolemia en adultos) modi&amp;#64257;cado en 2005. A partir de los resultados obtenidos, los médicos del trabajo cuentan con numerosas herramientas de uso diario para diagnosticar, controlar y prevenir las consecuencias del SM para los trabajadores y en de&amp;#64257;nitiva, para la población general. Es más, según la Ley de Prevención de Riesgos Laborales (LPRL) no sólo se persigue la ordenación de obligaciones y responsabilidades de los sujetos relacionados con el hecho laboral, sino que se  pretende fomentar una nueva cultura en el campo de la prevención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;24(2): 68-75, jun. 2015. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137493</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome metabólico en población laboral canaria (Estudio prospectivo en una Unidad Básica de Salud de Medicina del Trabajo)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51562</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
