<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041083</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurologic complications following hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Study of 14 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The frequency and cause of neurologic complications (NC) following hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) have changed over time. We have analyzed the NC in 185 consecutive patients who underwent HSCT in a period of 5 years in a single HSCT Unit. Patients and method: 185 consecutive patients underwent HSCT (44 allogeneic) between February 2000 and March 2005 to treat hematologic malignancies. Most frequent diagnoses were multiple myeloma (41 patients) and acute myeloblastic leukemia (n = 35). Demographic and clinical data, HSCT characteristics and procedure-related events with special attention to neurological findings were recorded. Imaging studies (magnetic resonance imaging and/or computerized tomography scan), cerebro-spinal fluid analyses and microbiological studies were performed in all patients developing NC. Results: After a median follow-up of 27 months, 14 patients (7.5%) developed NC, 6 of them after an allogeneic HSCT. The most common conditioning regimen in these patients was BEAM (5/14); 6 patients submitted to allogenic-HSCT received methotrexate and cyclosporin as graft-versus-host disease prophylaxis, and intrathecal prophylaxis of relapse was administered to 3 patients. The median time to the appearance of a NC was 13 days from HSCT (range: -4 to + 135 days). Seizures (8 cases) and encephalopathy (n = 2) were the most frequent clinical manifestations. In 12 cases the cause of the NC was related to drugs, there was one case of virical encephalytis and in the remaning case was caused by hemorrhage. Two patients died, one due to thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura attributed to cyclosporin and the other due to viral encephalytis. Conclusions: In our series drug toxicity was the main cause of NC (particularly seizures) following HSCT. Our results contrast with previous studies in which infections, especially of fungal origin, were the main cause of NC. These changes over time should be taken into account during diagnostic procedures</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oriol, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrà, Christelle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xicoy, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, Josep-Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batlle, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Feliu, Evarist</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La frecuencia y la causa de las complicaciones neurológicas (CN) después de un trasplante de progenitores hemopoyéticos (TPH) son muy variables y han ido cambiando con el tiempo. Se analizan las CN en una serie de 185 TPH consecutivos efectuados en un solo centro durante un período de 5 años. Pacientes y método: Entre febrero de 2000 y marzo de 2005 se realizaron 185 TPH (44 alogénicos), por diferentes hemopatías malignas, de las cuales las más frecuentes fueron el mieloma múltiple (41 casos) y la leucemia mieloblástica aguda (n = 35). De cada paciente con CN se recogieron las variables demográficas, las características del TPH y las características clínicas, etiología, tratamiento y evolución de las CN. En todos los casos con CN se llevó a cabo una prueba de imagen (tomografía computarizada y/o resonancia magnética), así como un estudio microbiológico del líquido cefalorraquídeo. Resultados: Tras una mediana de seguimiento de 27 meses, un 14 de los pacientes (7,5%) sufrieron CN (6 tras un TPH alogénico). La pauta de acondicionamiento más utilizada fue BEAM (carmustina, etopósido, citarabina y mefalán) (5/14), y en 6 pacientes la profilaxis de la enfermedad del injerto contra el huésped se realizó con ciclosporina y metotrexato. Recibieron metotrexato intratecal 3 pacientes. La mediana de aparición de la CN fue de 13 días desde el TPH (extremos: ­4 y + 135) y la manifestación clínica más frecuente fue la convulsión (8 casos), seguida de la encefalopatía (3 casos). En 12 pacientes la causa de la CN fue farmacológica, en uno una encefalitis viral y en el restante una hemorragia. Fallecieron 2 pacientes, uno por púrpura trombótica trombocitopénica atribuida a ciclosporina y el segundo por encefalitis viral. Conclusiones: En esta serie la mayoría de las CN del TPH fueron inducidas por fármacos, lo que contrasta con otras series históricas en las que la infección, sobre todo fúngica, fue la principal causa. Este hecho debe tenerse en cuenta a la hora de efectuar el diagnóstico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);125(18): 697-699, nov. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041083</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones neurológicas después de un trasplante de progenitores hemopoyéticos. Estudio de 14 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32203^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
