<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042570</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of pressure sores in primary care in two areas of Catalonia (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the prevalence of and risk factors for skin breakdown due to pressure ulcers. Method. We performed an observational, cross sectional study between April 1 and April 15, 2003 in all community nurses in the areas of Bages and Berguedà (Barcelona, Spain) and the head nurses of all nursing homes. Information (patient and caregiver characteristics and preventive measures) was gathered on all patients previously diagnosed with skin breakdown or risk of skin breakdown. Results. A total of 810 patients were studied (209 with skin breakdown and 601 at risk for skin breakdown). The prevalence of patients with skin breakdown due to pressure ulcers was 0.11% among the adult population, 0.42% in individuals aged more than 64 years old, 7.3% in patients receiving home care, and 4.8% in nursing home residents. Each community nurse attended a mean of 3.7 patients (SD = 2.5) at risk of skin breakdown and a mean of 1.8 patients (SD = 1.1) with pressure ulcers. Conclusions. Given the prevalence of pressure ulcers in patients receiving home care, detection of risk should be increased to prevent ulcer progression. When risk is detected, preventive measures should be increased. Health education should be improved in family caregivers, who play a major role in the process</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morros-Torné, Concepció</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Carrera, Assumpció</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santaeulàlia-Potrony, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heras-Fortuny, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moix-Manubens, Immaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabria-MartÍnez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la prevalencia de deterioro de la integridad cutánea por úlceras por presión, y su riesgo. Método. Se presenta un estudio observacional transversal, realizado entre el 1 y el 15 de abril de 2003, que comprende a todas las enfermeras comunitarias de las comarcas del Bages y del Berguedà (Barcelona) y a una enfermera responsable de cada residencia geriátrica. Se recogió información (características del paciente, cuidador y medidas preventivas) de los casos diagnosticados previamente de deterioro de la integridad cutánea y de riesgo de deterioro de la integridad cutánea. Resultados. Se estudiaron 810 casos: 209 de deterioro de la integridad cutánea y 601 de riesgo de deterioro de la integridad cutánea. La prevalencia del deterioro de la integridad cutánea por úlceras por presión fue del 0,11% entre la población adulta y del 0,42% en mayores de 64 años, y del 7,3% en pacientes de atención domiciliaria y del 4,8% en residentes de residencias geriátricas. A cada enfermera comunitaria le correspondieron, de media, 3,7 pacientes (desviación estándar [DE] = 2,5) con riesgo de deterioro de la integridad cutánea y 1,8 (DE = 1,1) con presencia de úlceras por presión. Conclusiones. Dada la prevalencia de úlceras por presión en los pacientes de atención domiciliaria, es necesario aumentar la detección del riesgo para evitar el proceso ulceroso, aumentar las medidas preventivas en las situaciones de riesgo detectadas, y mejorar la educación sanitaria a familiares cuidadores que tanto intervienen en el proceso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(1): 35-38, ene. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042570</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de úlceras por presión en atención primaria en dos comarcas catalanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
