<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043983</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Superficial cervicovaginal myofibroblastoma. A report of one case and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Superficial cervicovaginal myofibroblastomais a recently described tumour that characteristicallyoccurs in the distal female genital tract. It is abenign lesion probably arising from superficial subepithelialzone of the stroma extending from cervix to vulva.The lesion is characteristically found in women with agesranging from 40 to 74 years (median, 58 years) with a historyof pregnancy and/or exogenous hormone administration.Patients and methods: We describe a case of avaginal tumor in a 62 years old woman, who was on hormonetherapy as part of management for breast cancer.The lesion presented as a polypoid mass. Microscopically,it was moderately cellular and composed of blandmesenchymal cells embedded in a collagenous stroma.The tumor was immunoreactive for vimentin, desmin,CD34 and estrogen and progesterone receptors. No mitosiswas found and follow-up data showed no recurrence ometastasis. Conclusions: It is interesting to bear in mindthis entity because it could be mistaken with other tumorsin this location having different prognosis and treatmentas the aggressive angiomyxoma</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Anglada Pérez, José Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Alonso, María Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Díaz, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martínez, María Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El miofibroblastoma cérvico-vaginalsuperficial es una entidad tumoral específica del tractogenital femenino inferior descrita recientemente. Se trata deun tumor benigno, que se origina probablemente en las célulasdel estroma subepitelial que se extiende desde el cérvixa la vulva, y que se presenta en mujeres con una edad queoscila entre 40 y 74 años (mediana 58 años), en las que puedehaber una historia de embarazo o de administración exógenade hormonas. Descripción del caso: Presentamos uncaso de localización vaginal, en una mujer de 62 años queestaba siguiendo un tratamiento hormonal por carcinoma demama. El tumor tenía un crecimiento polipoide y microscópicamentese trataba de una lesión con densidad celularmoderada, bastante colagenizada y constituída por célulasmesenquimales de núcleos pequeños, con cromatina fina ypequeño nucleolo, e inmunorreactivas con la vimentina, ladesmina , el CD34, y los receptores de estrógenos y progesterona.No se encontraron mitosis y tras dos años de seguimiento,no ha habido recidiva o metástasis. Conclusiones:El interés en su conocimiento radica en que puede confundirsecon otras lesiones de esta localización, algunas de lascuales, como el angiomixoma agresivo, tiene otras connotacionesterapéuticas y pronósticas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;38(3): 183-187, jul.-sep. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Miofibroblastoma cérvico-vaginal superficial. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8986^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15027^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9573^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
