<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94876</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebral polymicrogyria and 22q11 deletion syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Summary. Introduction. Chromosome 22q11 microdeletion syndrome, DiGeorge syndrome or CATCH 22 spectrum, is characterised by conotruncal heart malformations, facial dysmorphisms, cleft palate, velopharyngeal insufficiency, transient hypocalcemia and T cell disorders. Furthermore, a significant number of patients may present autism-type developmental disorders, learning disabilities, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder or schizophrenia-like psychiatric problems. Case report. A girl with congenital heart disease that had been treated surgically in the neonatal period, who presented psychomotor  retardation, dysmorphic features and microcephaly. The conventional karyotype study that was performed at birth was normal. The physical examination revealed subtle signs of left hemiparesis. A neuroimaging study showed polymicrogyriatype cortical dysplasia that involved the right frontotemporal cortex. A chromosomal study was conducted and findings showed a 22q11.2 chromosome deletion. Conclusions. Brain malformations in children with deletion of the 22q11.2 chromosome have been reported previously, but their real prevalence and the most frequent type of malformation have not been properly determined. The authors conclude that brain malformations should be studied in all patients with 22q11.2 deletion and it should be borne in mind that all patients with cortical dysplasias may present this deletion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Verdú Pérez, a</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro De Castro, P. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriola Pereda, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Introducción. El síndrome de microdeleción del cromosoma 22q11, síndrome de DiGeorge o espectro CATCH 22, se caracteriza por malformaciones cardíacas conotruncales, dismorfismos faciales, paladar hendido, insuficiencia velofaríngea, hipocalcemia transitoria y alteraciones de las células T. Además, un significativo número de pacientes puede presentar alteraciones del desarrollo de tipo autismo, problemas de aprendizaje, trastorno por déficit de atención/hiperactividad o problemas psiquiátricos de tipo esquizofrenia. Caso clínico. Niña con una cardiopatía congénita intervenida en el período neonatal que presentó retraso psicomotor, rasgos dismórficos y microcefalia. El cariotipo convencional que se le realizó al nacer fue normal. En la exploración física presentaba signos sutiles de hemiparesia izquierda. El estudio por neuroimagen demostró una displasia cortical de tipo polimicrogiria que afectaba al córtex frontotemporal derecho. Se realizó un estudio cromosómico que mostró una deleción cromosómica 22q11.2. Conclusiones. Hay comunicaciones previas de malformaciones cerebrales en niños con deleción del cromosoma 22q11.2, pero su prevalencia real y el tipo de malformación más frecuente no están bien establecidos. Los autores concluyen que las malformaciones cerebrales deberían estudiarse en todos los pacientes con una deleción 22q11.2 y la posibilidad de presentar esta deleción debería considerarse en todos los pacientes con displasias corticales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;48(4): 188-190, feb. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polimicrogiria cerebral y síndrome de deleción 22q11</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2579^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4100^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32938^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12033^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
