<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151516</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-1637</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of self-etching adhesives in orthodontics: Theoretical bases and practical applications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Advances in adhesive technology have led to create new self-etching adhesives which combine acid and primer, simplify the bonding procedure, reduce chair time, avoid the side-effects of acid etching and minimize technique sensitivity. However, although these sell-etching adhesive systems are commonly used in bonding brackets to enamel, little is known about their action's mechanisms, properties, inconvenient and advantages which are widely revised in this article. Additionally, the most recently advances introduced are studied such as the use of antibacterial self-etching adhesives, the performance of the self-etching adhesives with a Jayer of saliva on the enamel surface, the additional etching with phosphorie acid before self-etching adhesive application and the efficacy of the new sell-etching adhesive cements (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albaladejo, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Morente, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los avances en la tecnología adhesiva han permitido la creación de sistemas autograbantes que combinan el ácido y el primer en un solo paso, simplificando el proceso de adhesión, reduciendo el tiempo de trabajo, evitando los efectos adversos provocados por el tratamiento previo con ácido y minimizando la sensibilidad a la técnica. Sin embargo, aunque estos adhesivos comienzan a usarse rutinariamente en la adhesión esmalte-bracket, se sabe muy poco por parte de los clínicos de su mecanismo de acción, propiedades, así como de las ventajas e inconvenientes que poseen, los cuales se revisan ampliamente en este artículo. Además se estudian las propuestas más recientes aplicadas a la adhesión en Ortodoncia, como el uso de adhesivos autograbantes antibacterianos, el comportamiento de los sistemas autograbantes en presencia de saliva, el grabado ácido previo a la aplicación del adhesivo autograbante y el comportamiento de los cementos resinosos autograbadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ortod. esp. (Ed. impr.);47(3): 217-230, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151516</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de adhesivos autograbantes en ortodoncia: bases teóricas y aplicaciones prácticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38352^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33084^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3752^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
