<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155749</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Age discrimination. Point of view of the professionals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. It is generally believed that legislation is an essential resource in the prevention of discriminatory behaviour against older people. This study first examines the Spanish legislation for potential age discrimination and then uses the C-EVE-D questionnaire to ask professionals in social work and health care settings the extent to what certain ageist behaviours described in the questionnaire are observed in practice. Methods. The field study was carried out with professionals in geriatrics and gerontology, who are members of Spanish Society for Geriatrics and Gerontology (SEGG). The EVE discrimination questionnaire consists of 28 items which investigate the existence of age discrimination in medical and social care contexts. Results. A total of 174 people (63% women; mean age: 45.6 years) took part in the study, with a mean professional experience of 17.2 years. Doctors made up 59% of the sample, psychologists 19%, with the rest coming from other professions. The first 20 discrimination items of the EVE-D questionnaire were significantly positively reported by more than 60% of the sample. Conclusions. Although Spanish legislation, from the constitution down to the rules that govern social and health care settings, clearly prohibits any kind of discrimination with regard to age, our results show that Spanish professionals most closely involved in the care of older people perceive both direct and indirect age discrimination. Furthermore, evidence was found of prejudice in the treatment of older people as a phenomenon in day-to-day health and social services care, both when analysing medical cases and, to a greater extent, cases of a more general nature and/or relating to co-existence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerra Vaquero, Ana Ilenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Ballesteros, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huici Casal, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera Casado, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustillos, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Existe una consideración general de que la legislación es el recurso definitivo a la hora de velar por comportamientos que no discriminen en función de la edad a las personas mayores. En este estudio, tras indagar en la legislación española sobre la potencial existencia de discriminación en función de la edad, preguntamos a profesionales sociosanitarios (socios de la SEGG) en qué medida observaban determinados comportamientos edadistas descritos en un cuestionario ad hoc. Métodos. El estudio de campo se lleva a cabo entre profesionales de la Geriatría y la Gerontología miembros de la SEGG mediante el Cuestionario EVE de Discriminación (EVE-D), elaborado por los autores, con 28 ítems y en el que se pregunta sobre la existencia de discriminación en razón de la edad en contextos médicos y sociales. Resultados. Respondieron 174 profesionales (63% mujeres), con un tiempo medio de ejercicio profesional de 17,2 años. El 59% eran médicos, el 19% psicólogos y el resto otros profesionales. Las primeras 20 situaciones de discriminación son informadas positivamente por más del 60% de la muestra, todas significativas en comparación con la media. Conclusiones. A pesar de que la legislación española (desde la Carta Magna hasta las normas que rigen contextos sanitarios y sociales) claramente prohíbe cualquier forma de discriminación por edad, los profesionales españoles más directamente implicados en el cuidado de las personas mayores perciben esta discriminación tanto directa como indirecta, así como un trato desigual a las personas mayores. Esto es así tanto cuando el análisis se establece sobre supuestos relacionados con la salud como, en mayor medida, cuando se hace sobre supuestos de carácter general y/o vinculados a la convivencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);51(5): 270-275, sept.-oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Se discrimina a los mayores en función de su edad? Visión del profesional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50334^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55084^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55088^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5993^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
