<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89315</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Idiopathic short stature (ISS): current status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The diagnosis of idiopathic short stature (ISS) indicates that the cause of the child or adolescent´s short stature is unknown. This is a nosologically heterogeneous condition that is fundamentally diagnosed by excluding all known circumstances that affect lineal growth. It is an arbitrary and descriptive term that can only he employed when the child presents with short stature for age and sex for their population of origin and the cal history, physical exam and complementary studies do not demonstrate any plausible cause. More specifically, in a patient cataloged as having ISS, GH secretion is normal, there is no indication of having been small is not organic pathology present, all syndromes that are associated with short stature have been discarded, and there is no underlying psychiatric pathology. Hence, the term idiopathic short stature is not based on any positive finding, only the exclusion of known organic, syndromic, mental and molecular pathologies. Therefore, we are confronted with a complex diagnosis that requires the study of multiple organic, syndromic and molecular causes, an authentic textbook of internal medicine, in order to confirm that the etiology of the short stature is really idiopathic based on our current knowledge. The progress made in the molecular diagnosis of new monogenic diseases, in patients with harmonic short stature as well as disharmonic, has been extraordinary in recent years. This has made a very important contribution to the understanding of the molecular basis of idiopathic short stature. The progress in international consensus has also been very fruitful, including the analysis of the requirements for diagnosis and therapy. Treatment with biosynthetic growth hormone of patients with idiopathic short stature, although approved by the FDA, remains to be clarified, especially in cases requiring treatment with recombinant growth hormone of patients with idiopathic short stature, although approved by the FDA, remains to be clarified, especially in cases requiring treatment with recombinant growth hormone or insulin-like growth factor I, or will require auxological observation without therapy. Aromatase inhibitors could be of interest for some boys. Treatment with GnRH analogues in combination with GH at the start of puberty could benefit some patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Argente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico de talla baja idiopática (TBI) se fundamenta en el desconocimiento de la causa que origina el que un niño o adolescente presente talla baja inferior a -2 DE para su edad y sexo, referido a su población. Se trata de una entidad nosológica heterogénea, cuyo diagnóstico se debe a la exclusión de las causas conocidas que determinara una afectación del crecimiento físico. En un término descriptivo, y arbitrario que únicamente puede emplearse cuando un niño presenta talla baja para la población y sexo del que procede y, la historia clínica, el examen físico y los estudios complementarios no demuestran ninguna causa responsable. Más específicamente, podría afirmarse que en un paciente catalogado de talla baja idiopática, la secreción de GH es normal, no existen antecedentes de haber sido pequeño para la edad gestacional, las proporciones  corporales son normales, no existe patología orgánica, se han descartado entidades sindrómicas que cursan con talla baja y no se detecta ninguna patología psiquiátrica de base. Por consiguiente, el término TBI no se basa en ningún hallazgo positivo, sino en la exclusión de la patología orgánica, sindrómica, mental y molecular conocidas. Asistimos, por tanto aun complejo diagnóstico que requiere investigar múltiples causas, un auténtico tratado de medicina interna de la infancia, para poder afirmar que la etiología de la talla baja es realmente idiopática para nuestros conocimientos actuales. Los progresos efectuados en el diagnóstico molecular de nuevas enfermedades monogénicas, tanto en pacientes con talla baja armónica como disarmónica, están siendo extraordinarios en los últimos años y su contribución al esclarecimiento de las bases moleculares de la talla baja idiopática, está siendo ciertamente relevante. Los progresos en los consensos internacionales están siendo fructíferos, analizando las bases diagnósticas y terapéuticas. El tratamiento con hormona de crecimiento biosintética de los pacientes con talla baja idiopática, aunque aprobado por la FDA, resta por dilucidarse; muy en particular, los casos que pudieran requerir tratamiento con hormona de crecimiento o con factor de crecimiento semejante a la insulina tipo I, o simplemente observación de su evolución auxológica sin terapia. El empleo de inhibidores de aromatasa, puede ser de utilidad para algunos niños, El tratamiento con análogos de GnRH en combinación con GH al inicio de la pubertad puede, asimismo, ser beneficioso para el paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(3): 167-179, mayo-jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Talla baja idiopática (TBI): estado actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38789^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29311^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6280^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33003^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33003^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22294^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
