<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108708</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypertensive women: a silent experience in family and society</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction:  Hypertension has implications for public health indicators and quality of life of people and taking as a principle of autonomy of adults in making decisions against their health, this research seeks to understand the meaning that a group of hypertensive elderly women gave hypertension and their social environment. Methodology: This is a phenomenological study in the perspective of Merleau Ponti. Six women were interviewed who was volunteered to participate signed the informed consent record. Each one was conducted at home, in three depth-interviews. Results: Two thematic areas were identified for understanding the phenomenon, meaning «living with a silent disease but serious consequences» and «social environment: coadjuvant or limiting health care». Hypertension was living with anxiety and concern. The social environment was a horizon of uncertainty, indifference, family, disrespect and abuse, and overload voltage generator, offset in part by support from neighbors and friends. Physical disability, coupled with long waits, alienated women from health institutions. We identified a lack of clarity on the continuing needs for monitoring and control of health. Conclusions: Social environment and the meaning given the same involved in the lack of adherence to treatment as well as the silent disease, meaning that as the participants gave to it. The connotation of women as caregivers, the social role ascribed and socially acceptable representations of what is a woman represented a very important role in the low self of the participants. Recommendations: Transcending  the  attention of healing attention towards health that provided the specific conditions and social environment is needed to improve health care of people.  Develop  programs  hypertension  with home care programs, emerges as an important alternative nursing care to these people (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soto Chaquir, Mercy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barón Castro, Mónica Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La hipertensión arterial tiene consecuencias en los indicadores de salud pública y en la calidad de vida de las personas, y teniendo como principio la autonomía de los adultos en la toma de decisiones frente a su salud, esta investigación busca comprender el significado que un grupo de mujeres adultas mayores hipertensas le dio a la hipertensión y a su medio social. Métodos: Estudio fenomenológico en la perspectiva de Merleau Ponti. Se entrevistaron seis mujeres que aceptaron voluntariamente participar firmando acta de consentimiento informado. A cada una se le realizaron tres entrevistas a profundidad en el domicilio. Resultados: Se identificaron 2 áreas temáticas que permitieron comprender el fenómeno: significado de «vivir con una enfermedad silenciosa pero de graves consecuencias» y «medio social: coadyuvante o limitante para el cuidado de la salud». La hipertensión fue vivida con angustia y preocupación. El medio social mostró un horizonte de incertidumbre, indiferencia familiar, desconsideración y abuso, generador de tensión y sobrecarga, compensado en parte por el apoyo de vecinos y amigos. La incapacidad física, aunada a largas esperas, alejaron a las mujeres de las instituciones de salud. Se identificó falta de claridad en la necesidad permanente del seguimiento y control de la salud. Conclusiones: El medio social y el significado dado al mismo intervinieron en la falta de adherencia al tratamiento así como el significado que como enfermedad silenciosa dieron las participantes a la misma. La connotación social de la mujer como cuidadora, el rol social atribuido y las representaciones socialmente aceptadas de lo que es ser mujer; representaron un papel muy importante en el bajo autocuidado de las participantes. Recomendaciones: Trascender la atención del curar a una atención en pro de la salud en la que se contemple las condiciones particulares y del medio social es necesario para mejorar el cuidado de la salud de las personas. Desarrollar los programas de hipertensión arterial con programas de cuidado en casa, surge como una alternativa importante en el cuidado de enfermería a estas personas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;16(34): 32-43, sept.-dic. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108708</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ser mujer hipertensa: una experiencia silenciosa en la familia y en la sociedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29154</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
