<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115120</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Discourses on sexual responsibility in a group of HIV-positive MSM in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: High rates of sexual risk behaviours are being reported among HIV-positive MSM which raises the question about the ideas of sexual responsibility that exist in this population to prevent the transmission and/or re-infection of HIV and other STIs. This study sought to understand the discourses on sexual care and responsibility in men living with HIV who have sex with men. Methods: A qualitative study was carried out with 78 men (aged 27-65): 35 individual interviews and 43 in five discussion groups, in the cities of Barcelona, Madrid and Palma de Mallorca, between 2007 and 2008. The selection criterion was that eighteen months had passed after a HIV diagnosis was established. The grounded theory approach was used to analyze the data. Results: Three distinct discourses about sexual responsibility were observed: (1) sole responsibility: it is the HIV-positive man who should protect himself in order to protect others. This discourse is based on an ethical position (altruistic), in which the duty and obligation to protect others is a priority; (2) shared responsibility: both parties agree and/or consent to high risk sexual practices although those who tend to use this discourse, in practice, ultimately assume full responsibility, and (3) individual responsibility: each person is responsible for himself, although the type of emotional bond with others may affect the decision to protect only oneself (there is some commitment to protect a sexual partner when something is felt for that person). Conclusions: The sexual care behaviour among HIV-positive MSM was determined by three discourses. Those discourses were influenced by various factors: moral conscience, sexual context, type of sexual partner and disclosure of HIV status(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Dávila, Percy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Carmona, Adriana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Entre los hombres VIH-positivos que tienen sexo con hombres (HSH VIH-positivos) se vienen reportando elevadas tasas de prácticas sexuales de riesgo, lo que lleva a preguntarnos sobre las ideas del cuidado sexual que existen en este colectivo para evitar la transmisión y/o reinfección del VIH y otras ITS. Este estudio buscó comprender los discursos que sobre la responsabilidad sexual tienen estos hombres. Método: Se realizó un estudio cualitativo. Participaron 78 hombres (27-65 años), 35 en entrevistas individuales y 43 en cinco grupos de discusión, en las ciudades de Barcelona, Madrid y Palma de Mallorca, entre 2007 y 2008. Se estableció como criterio de selección que hubieran transcurrido 18 meses desde el diagnóstico del VIH. El enfoque utilizado para analizar los datos fue la Teoría Fundamentada. Resultados: Entre los participantes se diferenciaron tres tipos de discurso respecto a la responsabilidad sexual: (1) Responsabilidad única: el sujeto seropositivo es el que debe cuidarse para cuidar a otros. Se fundamenta en un posicionamiento ético (altruista) en el que el deber y la obligación por proteger a los otros está por encima de todo. (2) Responsabilidad compartida: ambas partes deciden y/o consienten tener una relación sexual de riesgo aunque los que esgrimen este discurso en la práctica terminen asumiendo toda la carga de la responsabilidad. Y (3) Responsabilidad individual: cada uno vela por el cuidado de sí mismo, aunque el tipo de vínculo emocional con otras personas podría afectar la decisión de cuidarse o no (existe algún tipo de compromiso de proteger a alguien cuando se siente algo por esa persona). Conclusiones: La conducta de cuidado sexual de los HSH VIH-positivos estuvo orientaba en base a los tres discursos sobre la responsabilidad. Estos discursos estuvieron influenciados por diversos factores: conciencia moral, el contexto sexual, el tipo de pareja sexual y el revelamiento del seroestatus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;87(4): 367-382, jul.-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115120</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discursos sobre la responsabilidad sexual en hombres Vih-positivos que tienen sexo con hombres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23027^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23027^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
