<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99155</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of central catheters in hemodialysis patients as a permanent vascular access has increased during the last years, reaching numbers of around 7% of prevalent patients and between 25% of incident patients. Although the current catheters allow higher sanguineous flows with smaller incidence of infectious complications and dysfunction, the dose of dialysis that is reached is still inferior to that obtained with native arterio-venous fistula (AVF) and grafts. The aim of the present study was to evaluate the possible additional time supposed by dialysis using central venous catheters with respect to habitual vascular access as a consequence of the lesser blood flow (Qb) and the irregularity of its function (frequent lowering of the Qb and necessity of inverting the lines on many occasions). A total of 48 patients (31 men/17 women) with an average age of 61.6 ± 14 years old (rank: 28-83), 20 with tunnelled catheter and the remaining with AVF, were included in the study. All the patients were dialyzed in the modality of high flux hemodialysis with a polisulphone of 1.9 m2 dialyzer, dialysis time of 240 minutes, dialysate flow 500 ml/min and monitors equipped with ionic dialysance (ID) with the objective of obtaining a Kt of 45 litres with each one of the different vascular accesses. The patients with AVF received 3 sessions, with variations of Qb to 300, 350 and 400 ml/min. The patients with tunnelled catheter received two sessions, to the maximum Qb, one with normal connection and other with inverted one. In the results obtained it is possible to emphasize that only the patients with AVF and 400 ml/min reached the objective of 45 L of Kt. The patients with AVF needed to increase 12 minutes of hemodialysis with a Qb of 350 ml/min and 28 minutes with a Qb of 300 ml/min; the catheters on normal position needed to increase 24 minutes and finally in the inverted catheters an increase of 59 minutes was necessary to reach the same Kt objective. We concluded that the patients dialyzed with central catheters on average needed to increase by 30 minutes the time of dialysis if the catheter worked in a normal position but 60 minutes if the arterio-venous lines were inverted so as to reach the minimum dose of dialysis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maduell, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cases, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontseré, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campistol, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bergadá, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años hemos observado un aumento progresivo en el porcentaje de pacientes de hemodiálisis que utilizan catéteres centrales tunelizados como acceso vascular permanente, situándose las tasas de prevalencia e incidencia entorno al 7 y 25%, respectivamente. A pesar de que los catéteres actuales permiten la obtención de mayores flujos sanguíneos y menores complicaciones infecciosas, las dosis de diálisis obtenidas resultan inferiores a las alcanzadas mediante la utilización de fístulas arterio-venosas nativas (FAV) y prótesis vasculares. El objetivo principal del presente estudio fue valorar el tiempo adicional para obtener una dosis óptima de diálisis mediante la utilización de catéteres centrales venosos tunelizados. Dicha premisa se basa en la obtención de menores flujos sanguíneos (Qb) así como de posibles disfunciones vasculares que en diferentes ocasiones obligan a invertir las líneas arterio-venosas. Se analizaron un total de 48 pacientes (31 varones/17 mujeres) con una edad media de 61,6 ± 14 años (rango: 28-83); 20 con catéteres centrales tunelizados y 28 con FAV nativas. Todos los pacientes incluidos en el estudio se dializaron con la modalidad de hemodiálisis de alto flujo, con polisulfona de 1,9 m2, con una duración de 240 minutos, con flujo baño a 500 ml/min y monitores equipados con dialisancia iónica (DI). El objetivo principal de análisis fue la obtención de un Kt de 45 litros con cada uno de los diferentes accesos vasculares. Los pacientes portadores de una FAV recibieron 3 sesiones con variaciones de Qb a 300, 350 y 400 ml/min. Los pacientes con catéteres tunelizados recibieron dos sesiones de diálisis al máximo Qb, una con conexión de líneas normales y otra con líneas invertidas. Entre los resultados obtenidos cabe destacar que sólo los pacientes portadores de una FAV con un Qb de 400 ml/min alcanzaron el objetivo de Kt de 45 litros. Los sujetos con FAV precisaron incrementar 12 minutos de hemodiálisis con Qb de 350 ml/min y 28 minutos con Qb de 300 ml/min; los catéteres tunelizados en posición normal 24 minutos y los invertidos un total de 59 minutos. Concluimos que los pacientes dializados con catéteres centrales venosos tunelizados necesitan para alcanzar una dosis mínima de diálisis (Kt de 45 litros), incrementar por término medio 30 minutos el tiempo de la sesión si funciona en posición normal y 60 minutos en posición invertida de líneas arterio-venosas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(6): 633-636, nov.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cuánto tiempo es necesario aumentar la prescripción de hemodiálisis con la utilización de catéteres?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54279^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23606^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
