<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154298</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">assessment and intervention of anxiety and depression disorders in primary care: an unsolved problem</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The mental health problems, especially anxiety and depression, represent approximately one in every four visits received by primary care physicians. In this paper we present a review that aims to answer two interrelated questions. First, how primary care physicians diagnose and treat anxiety and depression? And secondly, how can we solve the problem? To answer the second question we will discuss the following aspects: the training needs of primary care physicians, the development of specific assessment tools for being used in this context, the development of psychotherapeutic techniques adapted to the characteristics of the primary care setting as well as the increasing number of health professionals dedicated to mental health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antonio Cano Vindel, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro Bravo, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latorre Postigo, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Salguero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mae Wood, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra Delgado, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los problemas de salud mental, especialmente los de ansiedad y depresión, suponen aproximadamente una de cada cuatro consultas que reciben los médicos de atención primaria. En este trabajo se presenta una revisión que pretende responder a dos preguntas interrelacionadas. En primer lugar, ¿cómo abordan los médicos de atención primaria el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de la ansiedad y depresión? Y en segundo lugar, ¿cómo se puede solucionar el problema? Para responder a la segunda pregunta vamos a tratar los siguientes aspectos: las necesidades de formación de los médicos de atención primaria, el desarrollo de instrumentos de evaluación específicos para su uso en ese contexto, el desarrollo de técnicas psicoterapéuticas adaptadas a las características de la atención primaria, así como el incremento del número de profesionales sanitarios dedicados a la salud mental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;5(1): 37-45, feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación e intervención de los problemas de ansiedad y depresión en atención primaria: un problema sin resolver</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
