<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161343</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contribution of women on Armed Forces&#146; international missions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Until just a decade, women have been largely excluded from participating in war as active subjects. After the 1325 Resolution of the UN Security Council in October 2000, incorporation of women to armies in peace-keeping missions and post-conflict reconstruction has been generalized, being the main objective of the «Action Plan of Government of Spain» approved in 2007 to «Enhance Women´s Participation in Missions and Decision-Making Bodies». Objective: To determine the level of compliance in relation to the participation of women in the Spanish army in peace-keeping processes and post-conflict reconstruction. Materials and methods: Design: It is an observational, retrospective, descriptive and longitudinal study. Ambit: Spanish army, during the period between January 1993 and December 2015. Population: women who have joined the Spanish army during the studied period and have participated in international tours of duty. Results: During the studied period, an increase of women in the different armies that participated in international missions has been observed, being 2014 the year with maximum participation of women, 12.5%. Conclusions: An increase in the proportion of women participating in international missions (FAS), as well as their access to positions of greater responsibility has been observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escrivá Ortuño, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Hasta hace apenas una década, las mujeres han estado generalmente excluidas para participar en la guerra como sujetos activos. Después de la Resolución 1325 del Consejo de Seguridad de las Naciones Unidas (UN) de Octubre del 2000, se ha generalizado su incorporación a los ejércitos en procesos de paz y reconstrucción posconflicto; siendo el principal objetivo del Plan de Acción del Gobierno de España aprobado en 2007 «Potenciar la participación de mujeres en misiones y órganos de toma de decisiones». Objetivo: Determinar el nivel de cumplimiento con respecto a la participación de las mujeres del ejército español en procesos de paz y reconstrucción posconflicto. Material y método: Diseño: se trata de un estudio observacional descriptivo longitudinal retrospectivo. Ámbito: Fuerzas Armadas Españolas, durante el periodo comprendido entre enero de 1993 y diciembre de 2015. Población: Mujeres que han ingresado en las Fuerzas Armadas Españolas durante el periodo de estudio y que han participado en misiones internacionales. Resultados: durante el periodo de estudio se observó un incremento de mujeres en los diferentes ejércitos que participaron en misiones internacionales, siendo el año 2014 el de máxima participación con un 12,5% de mujeres. Conclusiones: Se observó un incremento en la proporción de mujeres participantes en misiones internacionales (FAS), así como su acceso a los cargos de mayor responsabilidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;73(1): 40-45, ene.-mar. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161343</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribución de la mujer en misiones internacionales de las Fuerzas Armadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3489</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8660^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9110^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9110^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14879^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8660^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14879^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
