<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79482</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">FlowSecureTMartificial urinary sphincter for the treatment of stress urinary incontinence after radical prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To diffuse the concept and implantation surgical technique of a new prosthesis for the treatment of stress urinary incontinence, the Flow Secure artificial urinary sphincter.METHODS: The prosthesis is a single silicone piece filled with saline solution which has the following parts: (1) Pressure regulation reservoir, (2) assistance reservoir for stress situations, (3) control pump with self-sealant port and (4) a cuff. One of the main characteristics is the self-sealant port enables pressure adjustment depending of the clinical needs of the patient as many times as necessary.RESULTS: The surgical technique is simple and the level of continence achieved excellent. The only complication inherent to the Flow Secure design is perforation of the cuff during the act of pressurization, but it has been coArchrrected by designing a new control pump which can not be punctured. Self limited scrotal edema/hematoma are frequent; they can be avoided minimizing the time of trocar use. The remainder complications are common with the AMS 800 and other implantable prosthesis.CONCLUSIONS: Despite midterm good results, we need to wait for a greater number of patients with the Flow Secure sphincter and longer follow up to determine the definitive role of this prosthesis for the treatment of urinary incontinence(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Montes, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Difundir el concepto y técnica quirúrgica de implantación de una nueva prótesis para el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo, el esfínter urinario artificial FlowSecureTM.MÉTODOS: La prótesis consiste en una sola pieza de silicona llena de suero salino que consta de: (1) Un reservorio regulador de presión, (2) un reservorio de asistencia al estrés, (3) una bomba de control con un puerto autosellable y (4) un manguito. Una de su principales características es que el puerto autosellable permite ajustar la presión del sistema dependiendo de las necesidades clínicas del paciente cuantas veces sea necesario.RESULTADOS: La técnica quirúrgica es simple y el nivel de continencia obtenido excelente. La única complicación inherente al diseño del FlowSecureTM es la perforación del manguito durante el acto de presurización, pero ya se ha corregido diseñando una nueva bomba de control que no se puede pinchar. Es frecuente el edema/hematoma escrotal autolimitado que se evita minimizando el tiempo de utilización del trocar. El resto de complicaciones son comunes al AMS-800TM y a cualquier prótesis implantable.CONCLUSIONES: A pesar de los buenos resultados a medio plazo, es necesario esperar a que exista un mayor número de pacientes con el esfínter FlowSecureTM y un mayor seguimiento para determinar el papel definitivo que esta prótesis desempeña en el tratamiento de la incontinencia de esfuerzo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;62(10): 845-850, dic. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79482</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El esfínter urinario FlowSecureTM en el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo post prostatectomia radical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29753^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33582^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14954^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
