<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120017</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measles outbreak in 2011. An analysis of cases identified at an emergency department in a Spanish hospital (Madrid)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Measles is a highly contagious infectious dis­ease, associated with an important morbidity and mortality. An effective and safe vaccine is available and its eradication is possible. However, since 2009 measles outbreaks are occur­ring in Europe, with an important number of cases in Spain. Methods: Retrospective study conducted in an emergency department of a tertiary hospital. We included pediatric patients diagnosed of possible measles during the period January-December of 2011. Results: We diagnosed 67 suspected measles cases, the 76% of which had typical symptoms like coryza, cough or exanthema. There had been contact with confirmed measles cases in 50% of suspected cases, mainly familiar. The diagnostic was confirmed by laboratory tests in 25 patients, like serology or PCR of nasopharyngeal secretions. Another 25 patients were compatible with measles by clinic or epidemiological vinculum. 90% of confirmed cases took place in unvaccinated patients.12% of possible measles cases were admitted to hospital. Pneumonia was diagnosed in 2 patients. Conclusions: Our study shows an elevated incidence of measles in a sanitary area and confirms the existence of susceptible population due to a fail in vaccine coverage. To reach the objective of WHO of eradicating measles in 2015 in the European region, an early communication and investigation of suspected cases of measles is necessary. Sanitary professionals must be informed of the existence of an outbreak, because it is an infrequent infection in the daily clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sobrino Baladrón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vierge Hernán, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Lafever, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>País Roldán, p</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marañón Pardillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El sarampión es una infección altamente contagiosa y con una elevada morbilidad, para la que se dispone de una vacuna eficaz y segura y cuya erradicación es posible. Sin embargo, desde 2009 se han registrado brotes en Europa, con un aumento de casos en 2011 en España. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de pacientes diagnosticados por sospecha de sarampión en el servicio de urgencias de un hospital terciario, en el periodo comprendido entre enero y diciembre de 2011. Resultados: Se diagnosticaron 67 pacientes por sospecha de sarampión. El 76% de los casos sospechosos presentaban clínica típica de tos, coriza y exantema, y se refería contacto en el 50% de los casos, principalmente familiar. La infección se confirmó en 25 pacientes mediante serología o reacción en cadena de la polimerasa de exudado nasofaríngeo. Otros 25 pacientes fueron compatibles por clínica o vínculo epidemiológico. El 91% de los casos confirmados o compatibles no estaban vacunados. Ingresaron el 12% del total de pacientes por sospecha de sarampión. Se diagnosticó neumonía en 2 pacientes. Conclusiones: Este estudio demuestra una incidencia elevada de sarampión en un área sanitaria, lo que confirma la existencia de población susceptible por fallo en la cobertura vacunal. Para alcanzar el objetivo de la Organización Mundial de la Salud de erradicar el sarampión en el año 2015 en Europa, es preciso la comunicación y la investigación temprana de las sospechas. Los profesionales sanitarios deben estar informados de la situación del sarampión, al tratarse de una infección poco frecuente en la práctica clínica habitual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;72(2): e36-e39, feb. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de sarampión en 2011. Análisis de casos identificados en urgencias en un hospital de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23113^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
