<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101160</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hormonal treatment in biochemical recurrence after radical prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To date, the role of hormonal therapy (HT) after biochemical failure, when to initiate it, the therapeutic scheme and duration remains controversial due to the absence of well designed randomized trials analyzing the overall survival of patients. In clinical practice, the most widely spread treatment in this scenario is hormonal therapy with LH-RH analogues. However, the scientific support for this issue is very weak. We are extrapolating the benefits proven for early vs delayed HT in advanced prostate cancer, to asymptomatic patients presenting just an increase in PSA. These patients usually have a long time disease-history until development of metastasis. It should also be noticed the harmful secondary effects acquired with the time of employment of hormotherapy. Probably patients suffering a Gleason score &gt;8 and PSA doubling time &lt;12 months could obtain a benefit from an early castration treatment, even more if they are young (grade 2c). Except in selected cases of local treatment as radiotherapy, the decision for early or delayed hormonal therapy should be taken carefully with patient consensus. The alternatives for hormonal treatment to preserve sexual function, as intermittent treatment, antiandrogen monotherapy, or antiandrogen plus 5 alpha reductase inhibitors, are very attractive in this scenario. However due to the short time experience with these modalities of treatment should be evaluated with caution(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díez Sicilia, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Antolín, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castellano, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Otero, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Esteban, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz González, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duarte Ojeda, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabeza Rodríguez, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hasta la fecha el papel de la HT en la recidiva bioquímica, su inicio, esquema y duración permanecen en controversia dada la ausencia de ensayos randomizados que analicen la supervivencia del paciente sometido a esta terapia tras fracaso bioquímico. La hormonoterapia mediante el empleo de análogos LH-RH resulta en este escenario la medida más frecuentemente empleada en la práctica clínica. Sin embargo el sustento científico de la misma es bastante endeble. Implica extrapolar los beneficios de la HT precoz vs diferida, vista en otros estadios de la enfermedad (generalmente avanzada), a un paciente asintomático con exclusivo aumento del PSA, que tendría en muchos casos una larga historia natural hasta el desarrollo de metástasis y con el impuesto añadido de los efectos secundarios bien conocidos actualmente. Probablemente los pacientes con Gleason &gt;8 y TDPSA &lt; 12 meses sí pudieran beneficiarse de un tratamiento hormonal precoz, sobre todo si son jóvenes (grado 2c). En muchos otros casos donde no se contemple un tratamiento local como RT, la decisión de HT precoz o tardía debe ser cuidadosamente valorada y comentada con el paciente. Las alternativas de tratamiento hormonal con preservación de función sexual, como el bloqueo intermitente, monoterapia con antiandrógenos o la suma de un 5- ARI con antiandrógeno, deben ser valoradas con cautela ante la escasez de información a largo plazo aunque éste parece un atractivo escenario para su empleo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(1): 111-121, ene.-feb. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101160</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento hormonal en la recidiva bioquimica tras prostatectomía radical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29311^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6885^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d738^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
