<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79144</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review about clinical control trials of respiratory rehabilitation in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective Compare the effectiveness various exercises training programmes in the rehabilitation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) patients. DESIGN: A systematic literature review of random control trials. Search strategy  We conducted a systematic search to identify relevant studies published between 1999 and 2009 in Medline database. Selection of studies  The search limits were randomised controlled trial. The selection criteria were trials using exercise training in patients with COPD on dryland or water and included the following clinical and functional outcomes: lung function, oxygen uptake and quality of life questionnaire, respectively. Methodological quality of randomized controlled trials was assessed using the Delphi list. The literature search delivered a total of 38 studies, however only nine reach eligibility selection. Results  Most trials used incremental aerobic resistance exercises at an intensity ranging from 90 to 50% of VO2max. Frequency was two or four days a weeks, in sessions of 30 to 60min over a period of 8 to 12 weeks. All studies include persons with severe COPD who had stopped smoking before beginning the intervention. The effect of exercise training in CRQ and VO2max was not significant. In summary, the systematic review shows a clear tendency toward the use of incremental physical workload as the most effective in the treatment of patients with COPD(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuesta-Vargas, A. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labajos-Manzanares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Valero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo  Comparar los tipos de entrenamiento físico para pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) y analizar cuál es el más efectivo. Diseño  Revisión sistemática de la literatura médica sobre el tema. Estrategia de búsqueda  Se realizó una búsqueda sistemática de los estudios relevantes publicados desde 1999 hasta 2009 en la base de datos de Medline. Selección de estudios: los límites de búsqueda son ensayos clínicos aleatorios. Los criterios de selección son artículos que muestran tipos de entrenamiento en seco o agua para pacientes con EPOC y que incluían las variables funcionales y clínicas siguientes: datos espirométricos, consumo de oxígeno y cuestionarios de calidad de vida, respectivamente. La calidad metodológica fue medida con la lista Delphi. Un total de 38 artículos fueron incluidos en la revisión sistemática y solo 9 superaron los criterios de selección. Resultados  La mayoría de los artículos defienden el ejercicio físico aeróbico resistido incremental, con una intensidad que va del 90&#150;50% de la VO2máx, con una frecuencia entre 2&#150;4 días a la semana, la sesión desde 30&#150;60min y un periodo de tratamiento desde 8&#150;12 semanas de duración. Todos los artículos incluyen pacientes con EPOC grave y que habían dejado de fumar antes de comenzar la intervención de ejercicio físico. Los valores del tamaño del efecto en el cuestionario respiratorio y el VO2máx no mostraron diferencias significativas. Conclusión  Existe una clara tendencia de los autores a presentar el trabajo de ejercicio físico aeróbico incremental como el de mayor efectividad en el tratamiento de los pacientes con EPOC(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);44(2): 158-166, abr.-jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de ensayos clínicos sobre rehabilitación respiratoria en enfermos pulmonares obstructivos crónicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1970</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
