<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037759</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tracheoesophageal fistula in an intubated patient. Treatment through exclusion and esophageal patch</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Currently, acquired benign tracheoesophageal fistulas are mainly iatrogenic lesions produced by prolonged    tracheal intubation. Their occurrence in intubated patients is infrequent but devastating and their therapeutic resolution is highly complex. We present the case of a patient with an extensive tracheoesophageal fistula following tracheal intubation  that was surgically treated through esophageal exclusion (cervical esophagostomy and suture-sta-pling of the distal esophagus) and closure of the tracheal   defect using the posterior esophageal wall (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iribarren, Mauricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañizares, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nóvoa, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meléndez, Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, Gonzalo de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivo, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad, las fístulas traqueoesofágicas adquiridas, de etiología benigna, son principalmente lesiones    iatrogénicas, producidas por una intubación traqueal prolongada. Su formación en pacientes intubados es infrecuente,  pero suele comportar consecuencias devastado-ras, y su solución terapéutica es de gran complejidad.    Presentamos el caso de un paciente con una amplia    fístula traqueoesofágica postintubación traqueal, que se trató quirúrgicamente mediante exclusión esofágica (esofagostomía cervical y sutura-grapado de esófago distal) y cierre del defecto traqueal, utilizando    la pared posterior del esófago (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);77(4): 230-232, abr. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037759</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fístula traqueoesofágica en paciente intubado: tratamiento mediante exclusión y patch esofágico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22894^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5036^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29567^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5025^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29567^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5036^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
