<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90048</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Viral load is not a prognostic factor in LSIL</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To study the HPV viral load (VL) in the prediction of the persistence and/or progression in LSIL cases. Study design. Prospective study. 102 consecutive cases diagnosed as LSIL in 2006 with follow-ups at 6, 12 and 24 months subsequent to diagnosis. Method. Liquid based cytology (ThinPrep®, Hologic, Malborough, MA, USA), for the cytological study. Hybrid Captute II Test (HCII-HR, Quiagen, Hilden, Germany), for the determination of the presence or absence of High-Risk HPV. Results. 87 of the 102 cases studied were HR-HPV positive (85.3%). The presence or progression was detected in 54%, 42% and 33.35% of the cases in the first, second and third controls respectively. No lesion was demonstrated in 46%, 57% and 66.7% of the cases at first, second and third controls respectively. 19 cases progressed to HSIL; 11 of which were detected on the first control, 6 on the second and 2 on the third. The sensitivity of the VL for detecting HSIL never exceeded 89%, with a specificity always inferior to 40%. Conclusion. The VL determined by the HC2 method is not a useful indicator of prognosis in the follow-up of LSIL cases(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mancebo, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrazabal, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pijuan, Lara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreras, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mojal, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiñonero, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alameda, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloveras, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estudiar el valor de la carga viral para predecir la persistencia y/o la progresión en LSIL. Diseño del estudio. Estudio prospectivo. Todos los casos diagnosticados como LSIL en el año 2006, y seguidos a los 6, 12 y 24 meses después del diagnóstico. Método. Citología líquida (ThinPrep®, Hologic, Malborough, MA, EE. UU.) para realizar el estudio citológico. Test de captura de híbridos (HCII-HR, Quiagen, Hilden, Alemania), utilizando el test para determinar la presencia de VPH de alto riesgo. Resultados. De los 102 casos, 87 fueron HPV positivos (85,3%). La persistencia o progresión se observó en el 54% de los casos en el primer control, en el 42,4% en el segundo control y en el 33,3% en el tercer control. No se demostró lesión en el seguimiento en el 46% de los casos en el primer control, en el 57% de los casos en el segundo control y en el 66,7% de los casos en el tercer control. Diecinueve casos progresaron a HSIL: 11 detectados en el primer control, 6 en el segundo y 2 en el tercero. La sensibilidad para HSIL nunca superó el 89%, con una especificidad siempre menor del 40%. Conclusiones. La determinación de la carga viral mediante HC2 en LSIL no es útil para predecir su comportamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;44(3): 139-144, jul.-sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90048</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La carga viral no es un factor pronóstico en LSIL</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34541^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2330^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33123^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50448^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50448^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
