<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136389</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of GLP-1 receptor agonists on carbohydrate metabolism control</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonists are a new group of drugs for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus (DM2). In the present article, we review the available evidence on the efficacy of GLP-1 receptor agonists as glucose-lowering agents, their place in therapeutic algorithms, and the clinical factors associated with a favorable treatment response. Finally, we describe the clinical characteristics of patients who may benefit from these drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-García, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tinahones, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colomo, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los agonistas del receptor del péptido similar al glucagón-1 (arGLP-1) son un nuevo grupo de fármacos desarrollados para el tratamiento de la diabetes mellitus tipo 2 (DM2). En el presente artículo revisamos la evidencia disponible sobre la eficacia de los arGLP-1 como agentes hipoglucemiantes, el lugar que ocupan este nuevo grupo de fármacos en los algoritmos terapéuticos, los factores clínicos asociados a una mejor respuesta y, por último, perfilamos las características clínicas del paciente que sería candidato a este tipo de terapias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(supl.2): 18-22, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136389</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de los agonistas del receptor de GLP-1 sobre el control del metabolismo hidrocarbonado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50567^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52846^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23100^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4208^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
