<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101436</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Splenic Marginal Zone B-Cell Lymphoma With Epidermotropic Skin Involvement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Marginal zone B-cell lymphoma (MZL) is subclassified into extranodal MZL of mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue (including cutaneous lymphomas), splenic MZL, and nodal MZL. We report the case of a 68-year-old man with erythematous-violaceous plaques and nodules. Skin biopsy showed an epidermotropic lymphocytic infiltration and cytology and immunohistochemistry were consistent with MZL. The workup revealed disease in the peripheral blood and bone marrow and massive splenomegaly. Splenectomy confirmed the diagnosis of splenic MZL and led to resolution of the skin lesions. Cutaneous recurrence was treated successfully with chemotherapy and rituximab but caused fatal hepatitis due to hepatitis B virus reactivation. Skin involvement by splenic MZL is uncommon; this form of the disease can present epidermotropism, a very rare finding in primary cutaneous MZL. Treatment consists of splenectomy, which may be associated with chemotherapy and/or rituximab; this treatment may lead to reactivation of latent hepatitis B infection and screening for hepatitis should therefore be performed prior to starting therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Estebaranz, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-de la Fuente, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalón, L. B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calzado-Villarreal, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinedo-Moraleda, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El linfoma B de la zona marginal (LZM) se subdivide en LZM extraganglionar tipo MALT (incluye los cutáneos), esplénico y ganglionar. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 68 años con placas y nódulos eritematovioláceos. La biopsia cutánea mostró una infiltración linfocitaria epidermotropa con citología e inmunohistoquímica compatibles con LZM. El estudio de extensión mostró afectación de sangre periférica, médula ósea y esplenomegalia masiva. La esplenectomía confirmó el diagnóstico de LZM esplénico con desaparición de las lesiones cutáneas. Tras la recidiva cutánea se instauró quimioterapia/rituximab con desaparición de la misma, pero produciéndose una hepatitis letal por reactivación de virus de hepatitis B. La afectación cutánea por un LZM esplénico es un hallazgo infrecuente. Dicha afectación puede presentar epidermotropismo, hallazgo excepcional en los LZM cutáneos primarios. El tratamiento consiste en esplenectomía y/o quimioterapia y/o rituximab que pueden reactivar una hepatitis B inactiva, por lo que es preciso el screening de hepatitis antes de iniciarlos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;103(5): 427-431, jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfoma B esplénico de la zona marginal con afectación cutánea epidermotropa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13539^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29014^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29014^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29014^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6665^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35559^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30684^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
