<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97744</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">ERCP during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and aims: ERCP during pregnancy is always challenging for the entire team performing the endoscopic intervention. In this study techniques and different interventional aspects used at several centres about the clinical experience on ERCP in pregnant women are analyzed. Patients and methods: the practice on ERCP in pregnant women in six centers during a period of ten years is reported. Results: eleven patients were included in the study. Mean age was 30.6 years. Indication for ERCP was always symptomatic common bile duct stone (CBDS) disease. Before the procedure abdominal ultrasound was performed at all times and magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography in four occasions. Conscious sedation by means of midazolam and fentanyl or meperidine was applied. Sphincterotomes and guidewires were used for bilary cannulation. Sometimes, rapid exchange platforms with short-length guidewires controlled by the same endoscopist were employed. Biliary cannulation was confirmed in 9 occasions by bile aspiration. In five procedures, a mean of 30 seconds of fluoroscopy was used, both to verify cannulation and to corroborate complete CBDS clearance. These patients had the pelvic zone protected with a lead shield and radiation dose was measured. Ten biliary sphincterotomies were performed followed by CBDS extraction. Two plastic stents were inserted. Relief of biliary obstruction was attained in all circumstances. Only one patient had hyperamylasemia after ERCP. All pregnant women had healthy foetuses with normal deliveries. Conclusions: with experience, ERCP appears to be a safe technique during pregnancy. With simple measures fluoroscopic time can be diminished or even abolished. It seems that ERCP during pregnancy is underused in our working areas, although it has shown to be a useful technique for relieving biliary obstruction(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Naranjo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Huix, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serna, Carlos de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martín, Juan Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Miranda, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cano, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Roldán, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Carro, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ramos, Claudio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: la CPRE realizada durante el embarazo constituye siempre un reto para todo el equipo que participa en la intervención endoscópica. En este estudio se analizan los diferentes aspectos y técnicas en varios centros sobre la experiencia clínica de la CPRE realizada en mujeres gestantes. Pacientes y métodos: experiencia en seis centros sobre las CPRE en embarazadas durante 10 años. Resultados: se incluyeron 11 pacientes con edad media de 30,6 años. La indicación fue siempre coledocolitiasis sintomática. Antes de la CPRE se realizó ecografía abdominal en todos los casos y colangiorresonancia en 4. Se utilizó sedación consciente con midazolam y fentanilo o meperidina. Para la canulación biliar se utilizaron esfinterotomos y guías. A veces con sistemas de intercambio rápido y guías cortas manejadas por el endoscopista. En 9 ocasiones la confirmación de canulación biliar fue por aspiración de bilis. Se utilizó fluoroscopia (media de 30 segundos) en 5 procedimientos, para confirmar la canulación biliar y asegurar la extracción completa de coledocolitiasis. En estos casos se protegió la zona pélvica con un mandil de plomo y se midió la radiación. Se realizaron 10 esfinterotomías biliares con extracción de las coledocolitiasis y se insertaron dos prótesis plásticas resolviéndose en todos los casos la obstrucción biliar. Tras la CPRE solo hubo hiperamilasemia en una paciente. Todas las gestantes dieron a luz fetos sanos con partos normales. Conclusiones: con experiencia, la CPRE es una técnica segura durante el embarazo. El tiempo de fluoroscopia puede reducirse incluso suprimirse con medidas sencillas. Parece que, en nuestro medio, la CPRE es poco utilizada en la gestación, aunque es una forma útil para desobstruir la vía biliar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;104(2): 53-58, feb. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97744</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">CPRE durante el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3166^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19248^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3166^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38038^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
