<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149770</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Labor productivity losses attributable to premature deaths due to traffic injuries between 2002 and 2012</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To estimate the years of potential life lost, years of potential productive life lost and the labor productivity losses attributable to premature deaths due to traffic injuries between 2002 and 2012 in Spain. Method: Several statistical sources were combined (Spanish Registry of Deaths, Labor Force Survey and Wage Structure Survey) to develop a simulation model based on the human capital approach. This model allowed us to estimate the loss of labor productivity caused by premature deaths following traffic injuries from 2002 to 2012. In addition, mortality tables with life expectancy estimates were used to compute years of potential life lost and years of potential productive life lost. Results: The estimated loss of labour productivity caused by fatal traffic injuries between 2002 and 2012 in Spain amounted to 9,521 million euros (baseline year 2012). The aggregate number of years of potential life lost in the period amounted to 1,433,103, whereas the years of potential productive life lost amounted to 875,729. Throughout the period analyzed, labor productivity losses and years of life lost diminished substantially. Conclusions: Labor productivity losses due to fatal traffic injuries decreased throughout the period analyzed. Nevertheless, the cumulative loss was alarmingly high. Estimation of the economic impact of health problems can complement conventional indicators of distinct dimensions and be used to support public policy making (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Berta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña-Longobardo, Luz María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casal, Bruno</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubí-Mollá, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva-Moreno, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estimar los años potenciales de vida perdidos (APVP), los años potenciales de vida laboral perdidos (APVLP) y la pérdida de productividad laboral asociados a los fallecimientos prematuros ocasionados por lesiones de tránsito durante el periodo 2002-2012 en España. Método: Se combinaron varias fuentes estadísticas (Registro de defunciones, Encuesta de población activa y Encuesta de estructura salarial) para desarrollar un modelo de simulación basado en el enfoque de capital humano, que permitió estimar las pérdidas de productividad laboral ocasionadas por las muertes prematuras por lesiones de tránsito durante el periodo 2002-2012. Se utilizaron las tablas de mortalidad de la población de España para el cálculo de los APVP y los APVLP. Resultados: La pérdida de productividad laboral causada por lesiones de tránsito en España entre 2002 y 2012 se estimó en 9521,2 millones de euros (año base: 2012). El número de APVP acumulados durante el periodo ascendió a 1.433.103, mientras que los APVLP alcanzaron la cifra de 875.729. A lo largo del periodo analizado, las pérdidas y los años de vida perdidos disminuyeron sustancialmente. Conclusiones: Las pérdidas laborales asociada a muertes prematuras por lesiones de tránsito disminuyeron en el periodo analizado. Pese a ello, la cifra acumulada es de una enorme magnitud. La estimación del impacto económico de los problemas de salud puede complementar a indicadores de otras dimensiones y servir de herramienta de apoyo en la planificación de políticas públicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;29(supl.1): 79-84, sept. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149770</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pérdidas laborales atribuibles a la mortalidad prematura por lesiones de tránsito entre 2002 y 2012</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d44</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54724^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
