<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158209</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Needs of patients hospitalized at the intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to describe the needs reported by patients during their stay at the Intensive Care Unit (ICU), and to analyze the environmental stressors they perceived. Methodology: a narrative review of literature. The databases used were: Cuiden Plus, PubMed, CINAHL, SciELO, i-cercador, IME and Cochrane. The inclusion criteria for the articles were: published in Spanish or English, between 2005 and 2014, about adult patients, and with a score in the methodological scale The SQUIRE &amp;#8805; 10 scores. Grey literature was excluded, as well as those studies assessing the needs of the family.  Results: thirteen (13) articles were included. The most common needs detected were: being informed about their process and being able to make decisions about it, being able to communicate with their family and the professionals, being able to rest well without frequent awakenings, and staying in contact with their family, due to the high level of loneliness they felt.  Conclusions: ICU stays generate a high level of stress for patients. The unmet needs reported by patients were: feeling informed, making decisions, resting, and feeling safe, due to the loneliness, concern and feeling of imminent death experienced. Patients and their relatives demanded being together as long as possible, and claimed that this would be very beneficial in order to promote their wellbeing and comfort in the ICU (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Toquero, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llauradó Serra, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: describir las necesidades que reconocen tener los pacientes durante su estancia en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI) y analizar los factores ambientales estresantes percibidos por ellos. Metodología: revisión narrativa de la literatura. Las bases de datos utilizadas fueron Cuiden Plus, PubMed, CINAHL, SciELO, i-cercador, IME y Cochrane. Los criterios de inclusión de los artículos fueron: publicados en castellano o inglés, entre 2005 y 2014, pacientes adultos y puntuación de la escala metodológica The SQUIRE &amp;#8805; 10 puntos. Se excluyeron la literatura gris y los estudios que evaluaran las necesidades de la familia. Resultados: se incluyeron 13 artículos. Las necesidades más detectadas han sido: estar informados sobre su proceso y poder decidir sobre él, poder comunicarse con su familia y los profesionales, tener un buen descanso disminuyendo los despertares frecuentes y mantenerse en contacto con su familia debido a la gran soledad que sienten. Conclusiones: la estancia en la UCI genera un alto grado de estrés para los pacientes. Las necesidades que el paciente manifiesta como no cubiertas son sentirse informados, tomar decisiones, descansar y sentirse seguro por la soledad, preocupación y sensación de muerte inminente que padecen. Los propios pacientes y sus familiares reclaman pasar el mayor tiempo juntos, afirmando que sería muy beneficioso para promocionar el bienestar y el confort de ambos en la UCI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(10): 63-70, dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158209</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Necesidades de los pacientes ingresados en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
