<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106664</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alternative biological materials to detect prenatal exposure to drugs of abuse in the third trimester of pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Detection of prenatal drug abuse exposure is essential to ensure an appropriate monitoring of affected children. A maternal questionnaire is not an efficient screening tool. The usefulness of maternal hair and meconium as biological materials to assess this exposure has been described in last few years. The aim of this study was to compare both these alternative biological materials for prenatal drug exposure detection in the third trimester of pregnancy, in order to assess its use as a screening tool. Patients and methods: Between January and March 2010, samples of maternal hair and meconium from 107 mother-infant dyads were collected in Can Misses Hospital, Ibiza. The presence of opiates, cocaine, cannabis, and amphetamines, was determined in both materials, using standard chromatographic techniques. Results: Maternal hair analysis showed a 15.9% positivity for drugs of abuse (17 cases): 11 cannabis, 7 cocaine, 1 cannabis and ecstasy, and 1 cannabis and cocaine. Only one mother reported cannabis consumption and another one, cocaine. Of the 7 cocaine positive cases in hair, 6 were confirmed in meconium analysis, while of 11 cannabis positive cases, only 3 were confirmed in meconium. Two different consumer profiles were defined: cocaine consumers and cannabis consumers (with only 2 cases of multiple drug use). The highest level of cocaine ever published was detected (1.582ng/g) in one case. Discussion: This study reveals a high prevalence of drug abuse in this cohort during pregnancy. Improved screening methods may optimize prevention and monitoring of exposed infants. Maternal hair seems to be more sensitive than meconium to detect prenatal exposure to cannabis during the third trimester, so it might become a good screening tool(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vall, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Serra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simó, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pichini, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramis, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Joya, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Algar, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La detección de la exposición prenatal a drogas de abuso es fundamental para asegurar un adecuado seguimiento de los niños afectados. El cuestionario materno no es una herramienta de cribado eficiente. En los últimos años, se ha descrito la utilidad del cabello materno y del meconio como matrices biológicas para valorar esta exposición. El objetivo de este estudio es comparar ambas matrices alternativas en la detección de la exposición prenatal a drogas en el tercer trimestre del embarazo, con la finalidad de valorar su uso como herramienta de cribado. Pacientes y métodos: Entre enero y marzo de 2010 se recogieron muestras de cabello materno y meconio de 107 parejas madre-recién nacido del Hospital Can Misses de Ibiza. Se determinó en ambas matrices la presencia de opiáceos, cocaína, cannabis y anfetaminas, utilizando técnicas cromatográficas estandarizadas. Resultados: El análisis del cabello materno fue positivo para drogas de abuso en 17 casos (15,9%): 11 a cannabis, 7 a cocaína, uno a cannabis y éxtasis, y uno a cannabis y cocaína. Solo una madre había declarado consumo de cannabis y otra de cocaína. De los 7 casos positivos para cocaína en cabello, 6 se confirmaron en el estudio de meconio, mientras que de los 11 casos positivos para cannabis, solo 3 fueron confirmados en meconio. Se definieron 2 perfiles diferenciados de consumidoras: cocaína y cannabis (solo se detectaron 2 casos de policonsumo). Se detectó un caso con los valores de cocaína en meconio más altos publicados (1.582ng/g). Discusión: Este estudio revela una elevada prevalencia del consumo de drogas de abuso durante el embarazo en esta cohorte. La mejora en los métodos de cribado podría optimizar la prevención y el seguimiento de los recién nacidos expuestos. El cabello materno parece ser más sensible que el meconio para detectar la exposición prenatal a cannabis durante el tercer trimestre, por lo que podría convertirse en una buena herramienta de cribado(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);77(5): 323-328, nov. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106664</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Matrices biológicas alternativas para detectar la exposición prenatal a drogas de abuso en el tercer trimestre de la gestación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8597^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2894^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2894^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37617^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6350^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8640^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
