<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81662</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Essential thrombocythemia and retinal vein thrombosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case Report: Essential thrombocytosis is a disorder of the hematopoietic stem cell that causes proliferation of platelets. We report two cases: a 72-year-old woman with ischemic retina and tortuous and white veins in the superior retina and diffuse hemorrhages in the inferior retina with blot hemorrhages scattered throughout the equatorial region in the left eye; and a 62-year-old man with a central retinal vein occlusion in the left eye as signs of essential thrombocythemia. Discusion: These cases are examples of potential complications of essential thrombocytosis. Vulnerable patients should be monitored for retinal vascular occlusions, especially when platelet counts do not exceed 106/mm3(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Asensio Sánchez, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Navarro, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manteca Jiménez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Casos Clínicos: La trombocitosis esencial es una enfermedad de las células madres hematopoyéticas que se caracteriza por un exceso de plaquetas. Se presentan dos casos, una mujer de 72 años con retina isquémica, venas tortuosas y convertidas en cordones blanquecinos en la retina superior y hemorragias difusas en la retina inferior con hemorragias puntiformes en la región ecuatorial en el ojo izquierdo y un varón de 62 años con oclusión de la vena central de la retina en el ojo izquierdo, como manifestaciones de trombocitemia esencial. Discusión: Estos casos clínicos son ejemplos de las posibles complicaciones de la trombocitosis esencial. Estos pacientes deberían ser controlados ante posibles complicaciones oclusivas retinianas, especialmente al reducir el recuento plaquetario por debajo de 106/mm3(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;79(12): 629-632, dic. 2004. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombocitemia esencial y trombosis venosa retiniana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22492</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19336^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
