<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141438</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the psychometric properties of the Gambling Motives Questionnaire in Argentinian young people and adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of the present study was to evaluate, in a sample of young people and adults from the general community, the psychometric properties of two models developed for assessing gambling motives (Gambling Motives Questionnaire and Gambling Motives Questionnaire-Financial; GMQ and GMQ-F). Specifically, a confirmatory factor analysis was carried out to assess the fit of the two models to the data. Internal consistency of the scales was then analyzed. A multiple regression analysis was conducted to analyze the utility of gambling motives for predicting levels of gambling problem severity. The final sample was made up of 341 young people and adults, aged 18 to 60, who reported any gambling activity during the last six months. The maximum likelihood (ML) method with robust Satorra-Bentler correction was used to evaluate the fit of the models to the data. The results indicated that both the GMQ and the GMQ-F models show a reasonable fit to the data. All scales have adequate internal consistency values. Enhancement, coping and financial gambling motives were associated with greater severity of gambling problems. Overall, the results indicate that both models have adequate psychometric properties, though the GMQ-F appears to provide a more comprehensive alternative for assessing gambling motives in the general community (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pilatti, Angelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tuzinkievich, Francisco Benjamín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo tuvo como objetivo evaluar, en una muestra de apostadores jóvenes y adultos de la comunidad general, las propiedades psicométricas de estructura y consistencia interna del Cuestionario de Motivos de Apuestas en sus dos versiones: original (GMQ) y revisada (GMQ-F). Específicamente, se efectuó un análisis factorial confirmatorio para evaluar el ajuste de ambos modelos. Luego se analizó la consistencia interna de las escalas y se analizó la utilidad de las escalas para predecir un mayor nivel de severidad en los juegos de apuestas. Participaron 341 jóvenes y adultos, con edades entre 18 y 60 años, que reportaron realizar apuestas en los últimos seis meses. Para evaluar el ajuste de los modelos propuestos se utilizó el método de estimación máxima verosimilitud (ML) con la corrección robusta de Satorra-Bentler. Los resultados indicaron que los modelos GMQ y GMQ-F presentan un ajuste razonable a los datos. Todas las escalas presentan adecuados valores de consistencia interna. Los motivos de mejora, afrontamiento y financieros se relacionan con una mayor severidad de problemas con las apuestas. En general, los resultados indican que ambos modelos cuentan con adecuadas propiedades psicométricas, sin embargo, el GMQ-F se ofrece como una alternativa más completa para la medición de los motivos de apuestas en la comunidad general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);27(1): 17-26, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141438</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de las propiedades psicométricas del Cuestionario de Motivos de Apuestas en jóvenes y adultos argentinos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
