<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111278</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and annual risk of tuberculosis infection in the school population aged 7 years old in Ceuta (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To determine the prevalence of tuberculosis infection and annual risk of infection in the school population of Ceuta. Method A cross-sectional study was conducted. A tuberculin test (2UT RT-23 Tween 80) was given to 7-year-old schoolchildren in Ceuta in 2008. A positive result was considered as an induration of &amp;#8805;5mm at 72hours in unvaccinated children. Results A total of 612 children were studied. The prevalence of tuberculosis infection was 0.98% (95% confidence interval with a 2.5% margin of error). The distribution showed differences among three health areas, and was greatest in the most deprived area (2.07%). The annual risk of infection was 0.15%.ConclusionsAccording to the most recent studies, the prevalence of tuberculosis infection in Ceuta is one of the highest of Spain. Our results do not agree with the epidemiological data for tuberculosis in Ceuta, which also includes imported cases(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Marín, María Violeta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantón Gálvez, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Romero, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Fernández, José Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Fernández, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Conocer la prevalencia de la infección tuberculosa y el riesgo anual de infección en la población escolar de Ceuta. Método Estudio transversal. Se realizó la prueba de la tuberculina (2UT RT-23 Tween 80) a los niños de 7 años de edad escolarizados en Ceuta en 2008. Se consideraron positivos los niños no vacunados con una induración &amp;#8805;5mm a las 72 horas. Resultados Se estudiaron 612 niños. La prevalencia de la infección fue del 0,98% (intervalo de confianza del 95%, margen de error del 2,5%). Su distribución mostró diferencias entre las tres zonas de salud, y fue mayor en las zonas más deprimidas, donde llegó al 2,07%. El riesgo anual de infección fue del 0,15%.ConclusionesLa prevalencia de la infección es de las más altas de España, según los últimos estudios realizados. Los resultados no se corresponden con los datos epidemiológicos de tuberculosis de Ceuta, al tener en cuenta los casos importados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(3): 274-276, mayo-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111278</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y riesgo anual de infeccion por tuberculosis en la población escolar de 7 años de edad de Ceuta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22710^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
