<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137584</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of nontumoral portal vein thrombosis in cirrhosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Portal vein thrombosis in cirrhosis is a relatively common complication associated with the presence of an accompanying prothrombotic phenotype of advanced cirrhosis. The consequences of portal vein thrombosis are relevant because it can be associated with impaired hepatic function, might contraindicate hepatic transplantation and could increase morbidity in the surgical procedure. There is controversy concerning the most effective treatment of portal vein thrombosis, which is based on information that is seldom robust and whose primary objective is to achieve a return to vessel patency. Various studies have suggested that starting anticoagulation therapy early is associated with portal vein repatency more frequently than without treatment and has a low rate of complications. There are no proven data on the type of anticoagulant (low-molecular-weight heparins or dicoumarin agents) and the treatment duration. The implementation of TIPS is technically feasible in thrombosis without cavernous transformation and is associated with portal vein recanalization in a significant proportion of cases. Thrombolytic therapy does not appear to present an adequate balance between efficacy and safety; its use is therefore not supported for this indication. The proper definition of treatment for portal vein thrombosis requires properly designed studies to delimit the efficacy and safety of the various alternatives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catalina, María-Vega</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bañares, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La trombosis portal en la cirrosis es una complicación relativamente frecuente asociada a la presencia de un fenotipo protrombótico acompañante de la enfermedad hepática avanzada. Las consecuencias de la trombosis portal son relevantes porque se puede asociar a deterioro de la función hepática, puede contraindicar la realización de trasplante hepático y aumentar la morbilidad en torno al procedimiento quirúrgico. Existe controversia acerca del tratamiento más eficaz de la trombosis portal que además se sustenta en información poco robusta y cuyo objetivo primario es obtener la repermeabilización del vaso. Diversos estudios sugieren que la anticoagulación instaurada precozmente se asocia a repermeabilización portal de forma más frecuente que la ausencia de tratamiento, con una tasa baja de complicaciones; no existe información contrastada acerca del tipo de anticoagulante (heparinas de bajo peso molecular o dicumarínicos) y de la duración del tratamiento. La realización de derivación portosistémica percutánea intrahepática es técnicamente posible en la trombosis sin transformación cavernomatosa y se asocia a recanalización portal en una proporción significativa de casos. El tratamiento trombolítico no parece presentar un adecuado balance entre eficacia y seguridad, lo que no avala su uso en esta indicación. La correcta definición del tratamiento de la trombosis portal requiere de estudios adecuadamente diseñados para delimitar la eficacia y seguridad de las diferentes alternativas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;37(supl.2): 62-67, jul. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de la trombosis portal no tumoral en la cirrosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
