<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77931</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infancy and Vulnerability for the mental illness in child and adult: a vision from the genes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The relative effect of life events on the origin of mental illness, on the one hand, and certain endogenous bioligcal processes considered as relatively independent from the environment, in the other hand, continue to be theme of debate in the understanding of the aetiology of mental illness. However, recent scientiic evidences suggest that the genetic profile of and individual could constitute and element in continuous interaction with the environment, especially during childhood and adolescence, and determine, at least in part, the differential exposition of the individual to environmental risk factors form mental illness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fañanás Saura, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fatjó- Vilas Mestre, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El peso relativo en el orgen de la enfermedad mental de las experiencias vitales, por un lado y de ciertos procesos biológicos endógenos relativamente independientes del ambiente, por otro, sigue siendo un tema de debate en la comprensión de la etiología de la enfermedad mental. Sin embargo, las evidencias científicas más recientes ponen de manifiesto que el perfil genético de un individuo podría constituir unelemento en continua interacción con el ambiente, especialmene durante la infancia y adolescencia y determinar, al menos en parte, la exposición diferencial de la persona a factores de riesgo ambiental para la enfermedad mental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(7): 23-32, ene.-jun. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77931</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infancia y vulerabilidad para la enfermedad mental de niño y del adulto: una visión desde los genes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4858</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
