<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119965</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rare problem with the insertion of a Supreme&#153; laryngeal mask airway device. Case of the trimester</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A breast tumor was resected under general anesthesia. After the induction the airway was managed whit a Supreme &#153; laryngeal mask airway device. The insertion of the laryngeal mask airway device, the introduction of a probe of aspiration across the pipe of gastric drainage and the mechanical ventilation were very difficult from the beginning. On having withdrawn completely the mask to correct the problem was observed a break of the pipe of gastric drainage by exit of the probe of aspiration to his slant, towards the previous or laryngeal zone of the mask. Later there was verified that this mask and all those of the same lot of manufacture had suffered a change in his design: the muff was of a softer material and without reinforcement in the top, and the pipe of gastric drainage there was presenting a fault of head-sealing that facilitated the break. It was contacted by the local distributor and the manufacturer to communicate to them the incident, withdrawing from him the defective lot from which the above mentioned mask was coming. Likewise the incident spread across SENSAR to other hospitals, allowing to alert rapidly other users of the possible secondary problems at the rate of design of the laryngeal mask Supreme &#153; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sistema Español de Notificación en Seguridad en Anestesia y Reanimación (SENSAR), España</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente a la que se realizó una anestesia general para realizarle una tumorectomía de mama. Tras la inducción se procedió a insertar una mascarilla laríngea Supreme&#153; para control de la vía aérea. La inserción de la mascarilla, la introducción de una sonda de aspiración a través del tubo de drenaje gástrico y la ventilación mecánica fueron muy dificultosos desde el inicio. Al retirar completamente la mascarilla para subsanar el problema se observó una rotura del tubo de drenaje gástrico con salida de la sonda de aspiración a su través, hacia la zona anterior o laríngea de la mascarilla. Posteriormente se comprobó que esa mascarilla y todas las del mismo lote de fabricación habían sufrido un cambio en su diseño: el manguito era de un material más blando y sin refuerzo en la punta, y el tubo de drenaje gástrico presentaba un defecto de termosellado que facilitó la rotura. Se contactó con el distribuidor local y el fabricante para comunicarles el incidente, retirándose el lote defectuoso del que procedía dicha mascarilla. Asimismo se difundió el incidente a través de SENSAR a otros hospitales, permitiendo alertar rápidamente a otros usuarios de los posibles problemas secundarios al cambio de diseño de la mascarilla laríngea Supreme&#153; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;61(3): e20-e22, mar. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119965</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Problema inusual con la mascarilla laríngea Supreme&#153;. Caso del trimestre</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54205^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4947</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
