<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152272</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Eczema coxsackium and another atypical presentation of hand, foot and mouth disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hand, foot and mouth disease (HFMD) is one of the most frequent exanthematic disease in children younger than five years. It is usually caused by Coxsackievirus A16 and enterovirus 71. Last years, other different skin presentations are observed and they are produced by less common serotypes of enterovirus such as Coxsackievirus A6. Patients with Coxsackievirus A6 HFMD present with fever and systemic symptoms as in typical HFMD, but usually have a more severe cutaneous involvement, being able to pretend a Giannotti Crosti-like symptoms, or even, an eczema herpeticum. In this cases, we recommend to analyze coxsackievirus A6 HFMD to prevent unnecessary diagnostic tests and inappropriate antiviral treatment. We report two cases of atypical hand, foot and mouth disease in children younger of five years. Both of them referred atopic dermatitis as precedent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Gutiérrez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Bertolín, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Orta, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López García, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad de mano-pie-boca (EMPB) es una de las enfermedades exantemáticas más frecuentes en niños menores de cinco años, generalmente producida por los virus Coxsackie A16 y enterovirus 71. En los últimos años se están observando manifestaciones dérmicas diferentes a la habitual causadas por serotipos menos frecuentes como el Coxsackievirus A6. Los pacientes con la EMPB por Coxsakievirus A6 presentan fiebre y síntomas sistémicos como la EMPB típica, pero tienen una manifestación cutánea más grave, pudiendo simular un cuadro Gianotti Crosti-like, o, incluso, un eccema herpeticum. En estos casos, recomendamos analizar el serotipo de enterovirus para prevenir pruebas diagnósticas innecesarias o tratamientos antivirales inapropiados. Presentamos dos casos en niños menores de cinco años, de presentación atípica de EMPB, atendidos en nuestro Servicio de Urgencias. Ambos referían como antecedente padecer dermatitis atópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;18(69): 45-48, ene.-mar. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152272</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eccema coxsackium y otra presentación atípica de la enfermedad de mano-pie-boca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5175^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13668^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13668^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3400^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3400^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3400^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5175^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7785^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3400^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4849^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
