<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165140</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Resin infiltration: An effective and minimally invasive treatment for the treatment of non-cavitated white lesions. Narrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Caries is a process in which the mineral gain of the dental tissue is less than the loss of them, which leads to the initial formation of an opaque and white lesion, which in the beginning will not cavitate and if the process Will continue to cavitate. There are several treatments to treat these non-cavitated white lesions among which there are infiltrating resins. ICON trade name is indicated for D1 or R3 lesions according to radiographic detection criteria (radiolucency up to the external third of the dentin) and white spot lesions on free vestibular surfaces. There is a variety of scientific evidence that supports its use, both in interproximal treatment and in the treatment of free surfaces.  Conclusions: The use of infiltrating resin therapy for the management of interproximal incipient lesions as well as treatment of free vestibular lesions (post orthodontic treatment) is supported by scientific evidence. Studies have shown that the use of RI to stop the progression of non cavitated carious lesions is encouraging. This suggests that IR is a promising non invasive technique. Available scientific evidence also shows that resin infiltration significantly improves the clinical appearance of vestibular LBNCs and reduces their size. However, high-quality, long-term clinical trials are needed to confirm the efficacy of IR in arresting non-cavitated lesions in both temporal and permanent teeth. In particular, in order to determine the long-term benefits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nahuelhuaique Fuentealba, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Meléndez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sandoval Vidal, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La caries es un proceso en el que la ganancia de minerales del tejido dentario es menor que la pérdida de ellos, lo que conlleva a la formación inicial de una lesión opaca y blanca, que en un comienzo será no cavitada y si el proceso continua se cavitará. Existen variados tratamientos para tratar estas lesiones blancas no cavitadas entre los que existen las resinas infiltrantes. Con nombre comercial ICON este tratamiento está indicado para lesiones D1 o R3 según criterio de detección radiográfico (radiolucidez hasta el tercio externo de la dentina) y lesiones de mancha blanca en superficies libres vestibulares. Existe variada evidencia científica que respalda su uso, tanto en tratamiento interproximal como para tratamiento de superficies libres. Conclusiones: El uso de la terapia con resinas infiltrantes tanto para detención de lesiones incipientes interproximales como para tratamiento de lesiones libres vestibulares (post tratamiento de ortodoncia) está respaldada por la evidencia científica.  Los estudios revelaron que el uso de RI para detener la progresión de lesiones de caries no cavitadas es alentador. Esto sugiere que RI es una prometedora técnica no invasiva.  La evidencia científica disponible nos muestra también que la infiltración de resina mejora significativamente la apariencia clínica de LBNC vestibulares y reduce su tamaño.  Sin embargo, ensayos clínicos de alta calidad y a largo plazo, son necesarios para confirmar la eficacia de RI en la detención de lesiones no cavitadas tanto en dientes temporales como permanentes. En particular, con el fin de determinar los beneficios a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;33(3): 121-126, mayo-jun. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resinas infiltrantes: Un tratamiento eficaz y mínimamente invasivo para el tratamiento de lesiones blancas no cavitadas. Revisión narrativa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12538^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23439^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3758^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
