<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96009</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Delayed Right Hepatic Artery Haemorrhage After Iatrogenic Gallbladder by Laparoscopic Cholecystectomy that Required a Liver Transplant Due to Acute Liver Failure: Clinical Case and Review of the Literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Right hepatic artery (RHA) injury after laparoscopic cholecystectomy (LC) may go unnoticed clinically, but can sometimes cause necrosis of the right lobe. Exceptionally, when the necrosis spreads to segment IV, fulminant liver failure (FLF) may occur, and an urgent liver transplantation (LT) may be required. Patients and method We provide a review of the literature on patients with indication for an LT due to vascular damage caused by bile duct injury following LC. The case reported herein is the fourth described in the specialized literature of LT due to RHA injury after LC and the second of FLF after RHA injury. Results LT due to RHA injury was performed in 3 of 13 patients reported in the literature: one LT was performed at 3 months due to FLF, after an extended right hepatectomy was performed, and the remaining two were performed due to secondary biliary cirrhosis. Our patient was transplanted due to FLF 15 days after the injury. Conclusions RHA injury after LC may require LT due to FLF. Although exceptional, this possibility should be considered when there are RHA complications that may require occlusion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marín Hernández, Caridad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla Paricio, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Hernández, Juan Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor Perez, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez Bueno, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramirez Romero, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles Campos, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción La lesión de la arteria hepática derecha (AHD) tras colecistectomía laparoscópica (CL) puede pasar desapercibida clínicamente, aunque a veces ocasiona una necrosis del lóbulo derecho. En situaciones excepcionales, cuando la necrosis se extiende al segmento IV, podría ocurrir un fallo hepático fulminante (FHF) y requerir un trasplante hepático urgente (TH).Pacientes y método Presentamos una revisión de la literatura médica de los pacientes en los que se indicó TH debido a una lesión vascular secundaria a lesión biliar por CL. También presentamos el cuarto paciente descrito en la literatura especializada que precisó TH secundario a lesión de la AHD tras CL, el segundo por FHF. Resultados El TH debido a la lesión de la AHD se realizó en 3 de 13 pacientes recogidos en la literatura médica: uno se realizó a los 3 meses de la lesión por FHF, tras realizar una hepatectomía derecha ampliada y los otros 2 debido a cirrosis biliar secundaria. Nuestro paciente se trasplantó a los 15 días de la lesión por FHF. Conclusiones La lesión de la AHD tras CL puede requerir TH por FHF, aunque es excepcional, es necesario pensar en esta posibilidad ante complicaciones de la AHD que requieran su oclusión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);89(10): 670-676, dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia diferida de la arteria hepática derecha tras iatrogenia biliar por colecistectomía laparoscópica que precisó trasplante hepático por insuficiencia hepática aguda: caso clínico y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30788^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30667^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6652^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
