<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90190</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge of gender-based violence in the population seen in Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the knowledge and attitudes towards gender-based violence in the Primary Care patient population and their relationship with sociodemographic factors and personal experience.DesignA descriptive, cross-sectional study.SettingUrban Health Centres.ParticipantsPatients &amp;#8805;18 years-old who were seen in a Primary Care clinic.Materials and methodA questionnaire was used that included questions associated with knowledge, attitudes and experience of gender-based violence in the domestic environment. Variables such as, age, sex, education level, marital state were recorded, as well as the detection of personal experiences of Gender-Based Violence using the short Woman Abuse Screening Tool (WAST).ResultsA total of 673 people, from 18- 86 years, responded, of which 68% were women. Only 18.2% had sufficient knowledge on who is considered to exercise gender-based violence. Half of the participants believed that gender-based violence included physical and psychological injuries, inhibition of freedom and rape. In the logistic regression analysis an independent relationship was found with the knowledge of the correct response on what is gender-based violence by marital state, being less likely in married people as regards widowers (OR: 0.28; CI 95%: 0.11-0.72), to consider that gender-based violence involves physical injury (OR: 2.55; CI 95%: 1.28-5.08), but not psychological injury (OR: 0.52; CI 95%: 0.28-0.96), and not giving the correct response on what is domestic violence (OR:0.06; CI 95%: 0.03-0.12).ConclusionsThere is a wide variation in the results as regards what patients believe gender-based violence is and what aspects it covers(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>del Campo Giménez, María del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya Fernández, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Martínez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Téllez Lapeira, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Lozoya, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escobar Rabadán, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Ruiz, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Lozoya, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar conocimientos y actitudes hacia la violencia de género de la población consultante en Atención Primaria y su relación con factores sociodemográficos y experiencias personales.DiseñoEstudio descriptivo transversal.EmplazamientoCentros de Salud urbanos.ParticipantesPacientes &amp;#8805; 18 años que acuden a consulta de Atención Primaria.Mediciones principalesSe utilizó un cuestionario que incluía preguntas relativas a conocimientos, actitudes y experiencias vividas en relación con la violencia de género y en el ámbito doméstico, y que también recogía edad, sexo, nivel de estudios, estado civil y detección de experiencias personales de violencia de género mediante la versión corta del Woman Abuse Screening Tool (WAST).ResultadosRespondieron 673 personas, de 18-86 años, con un 68% de mujeres. Solo un 18,2% tenía un adecuado conocimiento sobre quién se considera que ejerce la violencia de género. La mitad de los participantes consideraban que la violencia de género incluía lesiones físicas, psicológicas, cohibición de libertad y violación. A través de un análisis de regresión logística se encontró una asociación independiente con el conocimiento de la respuesta correcta sobre qué es la violencia de género del estado civil, siendo menos probable en los casados con respecto a los viudos (OR: 0,28; IC 95%: 0,11-0,72) considerar que la violencia de género implica lesión física (OR: 2,55; IC 95%: 1,28-5,08), pero no lesiones psicológicas (OR: 0,52; IC 95%: 0,28-0,96), y no dar la respuesta correcta sobre qué es la violencia doméstica (OR: 0,06; IC 95%: 0,03-0,12).ConclusionesExiste una gran dispersión en las respuestas con relación a qué consideran los pacientes que es la violencia de género y qué aspectos abarca(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;43(9): 459-464, sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90190</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimientos sobre violencia de género de la población que consulta en Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16855^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16855^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16855^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
