<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128971</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Support for the development of narrative abilities in children with specific language impairment in inclusive contexts</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article evaluates the effect of an intervention on thBe narrative abilities of children with specific language impairment (SLI) in inclusive contexts. The research was carried out in three children attending three different preschool classrooms. Our intervention program, which was implemented jointly by speech therapists and preschool teachers, consisted of 48 sessions that focused on scripts and narrative abilities. The results showed some improvement in script acquisition and some narrative skills but the children did not reach the required level for their age. We conclude that, while group work inside the classroom helps to improve narrative skills in children with SLI, a more individually tailored and functional intervention is needed when these children have to manage more complex linguistic structures(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Axpe, Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acosta, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo analiza el impacto de una intervención sobre habilidades narrativas en sujetos con trastorno específico del lenguaje (TEL) en contextos inclusivos. Para ello, se ha llevado a cabo un estudio con tres casos distribuidos en tres aulas diferentes de educación infantil. El programa de intervención, implementado de manera colaborativa entre logopedas y profesoras de este nivel educativo, constó de 48 sesiones, en las que se trabajó sobre los guiones y las categorías básicas de la narración. Los resultados de la primera fase de aplicación indicaron, entre otras cosas, un avance en la adquisición de guiones y de ciertas habilidades narrativas, pero sin llegar a una eficiencia cercana a su edad cronológica. Las conclusiones revelan que el trabajo en grupo en el contexto del aula puede resultar beneficioso para incrementar la narrativa en los TEL, pero que se debe recurrir conjuntamente a una intervención más individualizada y funcional para el manejo de estructuras lingüísticas más complejas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);30(4): 196-205, oct.-dic.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128971</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apoyo al desarrollo de habilidades narrativas en niños con trastorno específico del lenguaje dentro de contextos inclusivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29323^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7983^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6472^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13448^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1307^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37586</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
