<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117151</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life of diabetic patients with medical or surgical treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In general, most of the studies agree in that the quality of life (QoL) of patients with diabetes is worse than that of the general population. Furthermore, these same studies have also described very positive effects on quality of life after bariatric surgery. The aim of this study was to analyze whether the impact on quality of life of diabetic patients after being submitted to bariatric surgery is the one supposed to be. Methods: We prospectively analyzed our data on 524 diabetic patients submitted to bariatric surgery between 2001 and 2005. All the patients filled up three QoL questionnaires before the surgery and at 1, 3, 6, and 12 months after the surgery. The answers were gathered from an annual database. All patients were submitted to adjustable gastric band surgery, Y-Roux gastric bypass, or BPD-Scopinaro. Results: We obtained complete data on 89 patients that were included into the study. One year after the surgery, the QoL had significantly improved independent of disease remission and weight loss. Diabetes got improved in all the cases. The improvement on the quality of life was higher in the patients with total remission of the disease than in those only improving their health status, although it was lower than that of those patients without diabetes before the surgery. Conclusions: After a literature review and with our own prospective data, we may conclude that the benefits obtained by diabetic patients from bariatric surgery are mainly due to improvement of their diabetes, irrespective of their initial BMI and the BMI decrease after the intervention. Further studies are needed to investigate the results of the QoL test in diabetics with low BMI after bariatric surgery and in the long run (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Weiner, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Neugehauer, EAM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En general, la mayoría de los estudios coinciden en que la calidad de vida de las personas con diabetes es peor que la calidad de vida de la población general (QoL). Además, estos mismos estudios también han descrito efectos muy positivos sobre la calidad de vida tras cirugía bariátrica. El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar si el impacto sobre la calidad de vida de los pacientes diabéticos después de ser sometidos a cirugía bariátrica según el test (QoL) es el que se supone debería ser. Métodos: Analizamos nuestra colección de datos prospectivos de 524 pacientes diabéticos que se sometieron a cirugía bariátrica entre 2001 y 2005. Todos los pacientes realizaron 3 cuestionarios de calidad de vida antes de la cirugía y después de 1, 3, 6 y 12 meses. Las respuestas se recogieron en una base de datos anual. Todos los pacientes se sometieron a una intervención de banda gástrica ajustable, Bypass Gástrico en-Y-Roux o BPD-Scopinaro. Resultados: En total se obtuvieron los datos completos de 89 pacientes que fueron incluidos en el estudio. 1 año después de la cirugía, la calidad de vida mejoró de manera significativa e independientemente de la remisión de la enfermedad y de la pérdida de peso. La diabetes mejoró en todos los casos. La mejora en la calidad de vida fue superior en los pacientes con remisión de la enfermedad que en los que únicamente mejoraron su estado, pero inferior que en los pacientes que no tenían diabetes antes de la operación. Conclusiones: Tras el análisis de la literatura y de nuestros propios datos prospectivos, podemos concluir que los beneficios que obtienen los pacientes diabéticos tras la cirugía bariátrica son debidos principalmente a la mejora de su diabetes, independientemente del IMC inicial y de la disminución del IMC tras la intervención. Se necesitan más estudios para investigar los resultados del test QoL en diabéticos con bajo índice de masa corporal tras la cirugía bariátrica y a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(supl.2): 66-77, 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117151</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida de pacientes diabéticos; tratamiento médico vs cirugía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
