<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045956</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cockayne&#146;s Syndrome: A case report. Literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cockayne&#146;s syndrome is a genetic disorder with a recessive autosomal inheritance, described first by Cockayne in 1936. Patients with this syndrome present failure to thrive, short stature, premature aging, neurological alterations, photosensitivity,    delayed eruption of the primary teeth, congenitally absent of some permanent teeth, partial macrodontia, atrophy of the alveolar process and caries. It could be caused by two gene mutations, CNK1 (ERCC8) and ERCC6, located on the 5 and 10 chromosomes respectively, causing two variations of Cockayne&#146;s syndrome, CS-A, secondary to a ERCC8 mutation and CS-B with ERCC6 mutation, the last one causes hypersensitivity to the ultraviolet light secondary to a DNA repair defect. The syndrome is also associated with mutations of the XPB, XPD and XPG genes.    In this report we present a 9 year and 4 month old patient. He had a height of 94 cm, weight of 8.6 Kg, head circumference    of 42 cm. and blood pressure of 120/80. Cachectic habitus, kyphosis, microcephaly, oval face, sunken eyes, a thin and beaklike nose, lack of subcutaneous facial fat (especially in the middle of the face), and large ears give the patient a birdlike appearance. It is notorious the photosensitivity in all the sun-exposed skin. The patient also displays delayed psychomotor skills and mental retardation.    In the oral cavity we found deficient hygiene, gingivitis, cervical caries, enamel hipoplasia, abnormal position of the upper and inferior lateral incisors, macrodontia of the upper central teeth, the left one presented a caries. In the x-ray we observed congenital absence of 14, 23 and 24 teeth and mandibular hipoplasia.    The aim of this review is to show the dentistry community the characteristics of the Cockayne&#146;s syndrome by means of a clinical case</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arenas Sordo, María de la Luz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldape Barrios, Beatriz Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Zamora, Edgar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya Pérez, Luis Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Síndrome de Cockayne (CS) es un desorden genético con un patrón de herencia autosómico recesivo que fue descrito    por primera vez en 1936 por Cockayne. Los pacientes con este síndrome presentan detención del crecimiento, talla baja, envejecimiento prematuro, anormalidades neurológicas, fotosensibilidad, retraso en la erupción de los dientes primarios, ausencia congénita de dientes permanentes, macrodoncia parcial, atrofia de los procesos alveolares y caries dental. Puede ser causado por mutación en dos genes, el CKN1 (ERCC8) y el ERCC6, localizados en los cromosomas 5 y 10 respectivamente; originando dos tipos: CS-A que tienen mutación en ERCC8 y CS-B con mutación en ERCC6, este último provoca sensibilidad a la luz ultravioleta, secundaria a una deficiencia en la reparación de DNA. También se ha asociado el síndrome a mutaciones de los genes XPB, XPD y XPG.    En el presente reporte se informa de un paciente de 9 años con cuatro meses de edad. En la exploración física se registró talla de 94 cm, peso de 8.6 kg y perímetro cefálico de 42 cm. TA 120/80. Hábito caquéctico, problemas posturales con encorvamiento, así como microcefalia, cara ovalada, ojos hundidos, nariz delgada y afilada, falta de grasa en la cara, más notorio en el tercio medio y orejas grandes que le confieren una apariencia de &#147;pajarito&#148;. Se observa marcada fotosensibilidad en toda la piel expuesta al sol. Presenta retraso psicomotor y mental.    Intrabucalmente se aprecia higiene deficiente, gingivitis, caries cervical, hipoplasia del esmalte, mala posición dentaria de los incisivos laterales superiores e inferiores, y macrodoncia de los dientes centrales superiores, el izquierdo presenta una lesión por caries. Radiográficamente se observa ausencia congénita de los dientes 14, 23, 24 e hipoplasia mandibular.    El objetivo de este trabajo es dar a conocer a la comunidad odontológica las características del síndrome de Cockayne a través de un caso clínico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(3): E236-E238, mayo 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045956</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Cockayne: Informe de un caso. Revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9248^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3087^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3087^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9248^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
