<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153254</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autosomal recessive polycystic kidney disease with neonatal: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Autosomal recessive polycystic kidney disease (ARPKD) is a rare hereditary disease caused by PKHD1, gene mutation, characterized by the appearance of multiple small cysts kidney, liver involvement and development of hypertension. Neonatal debut is the most common presentation which generally associates serious nephromegaly, oligoamnios and secondary pulmonary hypoplasia. We present a case of ARPKD diagnosed at 16 days of age by abdominal ultrasound performed by abdominal distension and bilateral palpation of mass; later it was con&amp;#64257;rmed by genetic study. Initially the baby had asymptomatic hyponatremia with normal renal function and hypertension with left ventricular hypertrophy which disappeared after hypertension treatment. Currently the patient who is 22 months old has had several urinary tract infections; he continues under antihypertensive treatment with multiple therapy because of his dif&amp;#64257;cult control hypertension and he has developed chronic renal failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Justa Roldan, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Odriozola Grijalba, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustillo Alonso, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Salas, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Congost Marin, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perales Martinez, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lalaguna Mallada, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vara Callau, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larena Fernandez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad poliquistica renal autosomica recesiva (PQRAR) es una enfermedad hereditaria rara, debida a una mutación del gen PKHD1, caracterizada por la aparición de múltiples quistes renales de peque&amp;#64257;o tamaño, afectación hepática y desarrollo de hipertensión arterial. Su forma de presentación más frecuente es la neonatal que, generalmente, cursa con nefromegalia grave, oligoamnios e hipoplasia pulmonar secundaria. Presentamos un caso de PQRAR diagnosticado a los 16 dias de vida al realizarse ecografía abdominal por distensión abdominal y palpación de masa bilateral, siendo con&amp;#64257;rmado, posteriormente, con estudio genético. Inicialmente se constató la existencia de hiponatremia asintomática con función renal normal y la presencia de hipertensión arterial (HTA) con repercusión cardíaca en forma de hipertro&amp;#64257;a del ventrículo izquierdo que se normalizó tras inicio tratamiento hipertensivo. Actualmente el paciente, que tiene 22 meses de edad y ha presentado varias infecciones del tracto urinario, continua tratamiento antihipertensivo con terapia múltiple y ha desarrollado enfermedad renal crónica (ERC) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;72(1): 46-51, ene.-feb. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153254</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Poliquistosis renal autosomica recesiva: un caso de debut neonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7859^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7859^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7859^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7189^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7189^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29056^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
