<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106616</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relationship between nutritional status and the risk of having pressure ulcers in patients included in a home care program</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The objective of the present study was to evaluate the relationship between the nutritional status and the risk of pressure ulcers (PU) in patients within home care programs (ATDOM). We also evaluated the relationship between the level of cognitive impairment, physical dependence, underlying diseases and the nutritional status. Scope: Patients in home care program in Primary Health Care.Patients100 home care patients. Main variables: age, sex, caregiver, illness, BMI, haemoglobin, haematocrit, lymphocyte count, albumin, cholesterol, Barthel index, Pfeiffer, nutritional assessment (MNA) and Braden scale. Results: Fourteen percent of the ATDOM patients had malnutrition and 46% a high risk of malnutrition. The degree of dependency, and the level of cognitive impairment increased (P&lt;001) the risk of pressure ulcers. Furthermore, the nutritional status affected the risk of pressure ulcers (P&lt;001) with OR 3.73 higher in malnourished patients. Values of 3.76±0.05g/dL albumin and cholesterol of 176.43±6.38 were associated with an increased risk of ulceration. There was a significant relationship between nutritional status (P&lt;01) and the degree of dependence. In malnourished patients albumin levels decreased to 3.46±0.098, with averages of 11.41±154.95mg/dL cholesterol. Finally, a lower BMI was significantly related to malnutrition. Conclusions: The present study demonstrates that 14% of the ATDOM patients showed malnutrition, and 46% a high risk of malnutrition. Malnutrition, the degree of physical dependence and severity of cognitive impairment is associated with an increased risk of ulceration, which justify the need for carrying out some personalised measurements on ATDOM patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mach, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho, Àngela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albiol, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Se evaluó el grado de relación entre estado nutricional y riesgo de presentar úlceras por presión (UPP) en pacientes de atención domiciliaria (ATDOM). Secundariamente, se valoró la relación entre el grado de deterioro cognitivo, dependencia física, patologías de base y estado nutricional. Ámbito: Pacientes de atención domiciliaria (ATDOM) en atención primaria.Pacientes100 pacientes ATDOM. Variables principales: Edad, sexo, cuidador, enfermedades, IMC, hemoglobina, hematocrito, linfocito S, albúmina, colesterol, Barthel, Pfeiffer, valoración nutricional (MNA) y Braden. Resultados: Un 14% de los pacientes ATDOM presentaron malnutrición y un 46% riesgo de desnutrición. El incremento del grado de dependencia y el deterioro cognitivo aumentó (p&lt;0,001) el riesgo UPP. Además, el estado nutricional afectó al riesgo de UPP (p&lt;0,001) con una OR 3,73 superior en aquellos pacientes malnutridos. Valores de albúmina de 3,76±0,05g/dL y de colesterol de 176,43±6,38 se relacionaron con un mayor riesgo de ulceración. En cuanto al estado nutricional existió una relación significativa (p&lt;0,01) con el grado de dependencia. En pacientes malnutridos los niveles de albúmina disminuyeron a 3,46±0,098, con medias de colesterol de 154,95mg/dL±11,41. Finalmente, IMC menores se relacionaron significativamente con malnutrición. Conclusiones: El presente estudio demuestra que el 14% de pacientes ATDOM presentaron malnutrición y un 46% riesgo de desnutrición. La malnutrición, el grado de dependencia física, el deterioro cognitivo severo y los parámetros sanguíneos básicos se relacionan significativamente con un aumento del riesgo de ulceración, justificando la necesidad de llevar a cabo medidas de corrección y mejoría personalizada en los pacientes ATDOM(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;44(10): 586-594, oct. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre el estado nutricional y el riesgo de presentar úlceras por presión en pacientes incluidos en el programa de atención domiciliaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30376^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
