<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88508</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Innovation vs. tradition: the election of an european way toward pharmaceutical industrialisation, 19th-20th centuries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper discusses the scientific and technological factors that coincided in the beginning and in the initial development of the pharmaceutical industry in Europe. Having pointed out the reasons that favoured the initial success of the German chemical pharmaceutical industry, we evaluate the efforts of other countries to occupy the leadershipof this industrial sector: from the British trials of business concentration to all the strength of the Swiss as a neutral nation in conflicts of war; a special tractor will be dedicated to the study of the penetration of German industry in France, in particular, in the systems invented by German manufacturers to violate the French protectionist legislation. In concluding, we describe the two industrialization models followed by the pharmaceutical industry during the decades of change of the 19th-20th centuries. We evaluate and explain the social, economic, cultural and, above all, scientific-technical reasons that defined both and discuss the motives that led to the current situation of leadership of the central European model in the pharmaceutical sector (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Bueno, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Nozal, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Analizamos los factores científicos y tecnológicos que confluyeron en el inicio y primer desarrollo de la industria europea del medicamento. Tras señalar las razones que favorecieron el auge inicial de la industria químico-farmacéutica alemana, pasamos a valorar los esfuerzos de otros países por ocupar el liderazgo de este sector industrial: desde los ensayos británicos de concentración empresarial hasta la potencialidad de Suiza como nación neutral en los conflictos bélicos; un capítulo especial queda dedicado al estudio de la penetración de la industria alemana en Francia, en particular, a los sistemas ideados por los fabricantes alemanes para violar la legislación proteccionista gala. Para concluir, caracterizamos los dos modelos de industrialización seguidos por la industria farmacéutica durante el gozne de los siglos XIX y XX; se valoran y explican las razones sociales, económicas, culturales y, sobre todo, científico-técnicas que les definen y se discuten los motivos que condujeron a la actual situación de liderazgo del modelo centroeuropeo en el sector farmacéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;76(4): 459-478, oct.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88508</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Innovación vs. tradición: la elección de un modelo de industrialización farmacéutica en la Europa de los siglos XIX y XX</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2672^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24459</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4407^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
