<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046965</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Natural therapies for the treatment of erectile dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Erectile dysfunction is a disorder with a high prevalence that affectsthe individual not only through the organic consequences itentails but also for the social and relational impact it has. Alternativemedicine has a great number of remedies derived from plantsincluded in its pharmacopoeia to treat this problem. Most of theseremedies have been extracted from the traditional medicine ofother cultures. Clinical trials developed so far to support their useare very scarce, however, and despite the existence of effectivedrugs, the consumption of these natural remedies is really important</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Sanguino, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Ruiz, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disfunción eréctil es una alteración con una alta prevalencia yque afecta al individuo que la sufre no sólo por sus consecuenciasorgánicas, sino también por las de índole relacional y social. Lamedicina alternativa cuenta entre su farmacopea con una ingentecantidad de remedios derivados de plantas para tratar este problema,la mayor parte de los cuales han sido extraídos de la medicinatradicional de otros pueblos. Los ensayos clínicos desarrolladoshasta el momento para respaldar su uso son escasos, sin embargoy a pesar de la existencia de fármacos eficaces, el consumo de estosremedios naturales es realmente importante</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(4): 22-24, mayo 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046965</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapias naturales para el tratamiento de la disfunción eréctil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33751</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15412^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
