<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87063</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biofilms, scenarios of biodiversity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bacterial biofilms are stratified microbial communities imbibed in an extracellular polymer and adhered to a solid surface in an aquatic environment. They might be integrated by one or several species and are organized in complex communities selfregulated by an efficient communication system. They protect themselves against hostile agents assembling with their own materials a peculiar architecture with an interior network of channels guaranteeing the supply of water, nutrients and gases to the majority of its components. Moreover, through the modulation of these chemical signals, individual cells or small groups detach themselves and occupy new grounds initiating the slow but inexorable invasion of a habitat. The damage to the warships&#146; hull; biocorrosion of the  weaponry and other alloy materials &#150;or non metallic ones&#150; susceptible to moisture; biodegradation of excess of trinitrotoluene; foodborne diseases due to cross contaminations; oral pathologies; persistent infections in chronic wounds; contamination of the water supply in military barracks; development of slime on the walls of the water tanks, in cisterns or fountains of the military barracks  dining-halls; persistence of Legionella spp in the cooling towers or the antibiotic resistance in infections after implantation of joint prosthesis or any other clinical device; these are frequent situations in which biofilm-producing microorganisms participate in their emergence and evolution. In this article the different phases leading to their development are described, the regulation mechanisms and the strategies that allow their survival in a hostile environment against the action of the biocides or the immune response of the host (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zamora, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guijaro, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosoo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa, M. A de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los biofilmes bacterianos o biopelículas son comunidades estratificadas de células embebidas en un polímero extracelular y adheridas a una superficie sólida en un medio acuático; están constituidos por una única especie o por especies diferentes. Se organizan en comunidades complejas autorreguladas gracias a un eficaz sistema de comunicación, protegiéndose frente a los agentes hostiles mediante la construcción con materiales propios, de una estructura de arquitectura particular y dotada de una red interior de canalizaciones, que garantiza el abastecimiento de agua, nutrientes y gases a la mayoría de los integrantes. Además, a través de modificaciones de estas señales químicas, células individuales o pequeños grupos se destacan en avanzadas sobre el terreno y, tras afianzarse sobre la posición, retoman la pausada pero  inexorable invasión de un hábitat. El deterioro de los cascos de los buques de guerra; la biocorrosión del armamento y de otros materiales de aleación &amp;#8722;o no metálicos&amp;#8722; susceptibles de humedecerse; la biodegradación de excedentes de trinitrotolueno; la presentación de infecciones alimentarias por contaminaciones cruzadas; la incidencia de patologías bucodentales; las infecciones pertinaces en las heridas crónicas; la contaminación de las redes de distribución de agua de los acuartelamientos; la aparición de limos en las paredes de los depósitos de instalaciones interiores, en los aljibes o en las fuentes de los comedores colectivos militares; la persistencia de Legionella spp. en las torres de refrigeración o la antibiorresistencia de infecciones surgidas tras la implantación de prótesis articulares o de cualquier otro dispositivo de  uso clínico, son situaciones frecuentes en cuya gestación y evolución posterior, intervienen microorganismos formando biofilmes. En este trabajo se describen las distintas etapas que conducen a su desarrollo, los mecanismos de regulación y las estrategias que les permiten sobrevivir en un medio desfavorable, venciendo la acción de los biocidas o la respuesta inmunitaria del hospedador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;65(4): 246-258, oct.-dic. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biofilmes, escenarios de biodiversidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32342^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10764^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19083^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
