<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68488</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retrospective analysis of 6 cases of elastofibroma dorsi</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Elastofibroma dorsi is a benign lesion of fibroelastic tissue. It often presents bilaterally, is frequently localized to the subscapular region, and is more common in middle-aged and elderly women. The pathogenesis is still unclear but it has been suggested to involve reactive, degenerative, or neoplastic processes. We present a retrospective study of the findings from 6 patients with elastofibroma dorsi. Elastofibroma should be included in the differential diagnosis of subcutaneous scapular tumors, as it is a benign lesion that only requires surgery when associated with symptoms or the lesion is extensive. Noninvasive techniques such as ultrasonography, computed tomography, and, above all, magnetic resonance imaging, may be sufficient to guide diagnosis. The results of histology and imaging are closely correlated, so the need for unnecessary biopsy and surgery may beavoided (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echevarría, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yáñez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landeras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Val-Bernal, JF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El elastofibroma dorsi es una lesión benigna de tejido fibroelástico, a menudo bilateral, localizada frecuentemente en la región subescapular, más común en mujeres de edad media y ancianas. La patogénesis es desconocida, y se ha sugerido que se trate de un proceso reactivo, degenerativo o neoplásico. Presentamos un estudio retrospectivo de los hallazgos observados en seis pacientes con elastofibroma dorsi. El elastofibroma debe plantearse en el diagnóstico diferencial de tumoraciones subcutáneas de localización escapular, ya que es una lesión benigna que sólo requiere tratamiento quirúrgico cuando es sintomático o muy grande. Técnicas no invasivas, como la ecografía, tomografía computarizada y especialmente la resonancia magnética pueden ser suficientes para orientar el diagnóstico, con estrecha correlación entre el cuadro histológico y las imágenes radiológicas específicas evitando biopsias y cirugías innecesarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;99(8): 644-647, oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68488</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Elastofibroma dorsi: estudio retrospectivo de seis casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4621^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5486^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13369^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13369^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4621^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4621^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
