<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057978</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptive cell immune response against the hepatitis C virus infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hepatitis C virus (HCV) infects around 175 million people worldwide and is one of the leading causes of chronic liver disease. Less than one third of patients infected with HCV are able to spontaneously clear the virus during acute infection, while most patients evolve to chronic infection. Control of viral replication has been associated to the cellular component of the host immune response. It is not fully understood what distinguish a successful cellular immune response. An integral interpretation of the numerous experimental findings may allow a better understanding of the immune mechanisms involved in the inability of the immune system to successfully control chronic HCV infection</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibón Rallón, Norma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El virus de la hepatitis C (VHC) infecta alrededor de 175 millones de personas en el mundo y es una de las principales causas de enfermedad hepática crónica. Menos de una tercera parte de las personas expuestas controlan el virus espontáneamente después de la infección aguda, mientras que el resto evoluciona a la cronicidad. La resolución de la infección se ha asociado al componente celular de la respuesta inmunitaria del huésped. No se conoce bien qué distingue una respuesta inmunitaria celular exitosa frente al VHC. Una interpretación integral de los diversos hallazgos experimentales permite una mejor comprensión del porqué del fracaso inmunitario en la infección crónica por el VHC</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);129(12): 468-474, oct. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057978</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta inmunitaria celular adaptativa frente a la infección por el virus de la hepatitis C</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30260^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31852^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24525^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23473^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
