<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043587</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endometrial cancer with unfavorable clinical course in a patient treated with tamoxifen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endometrial cancer is the most common gynecological malignancy and accounts for 6% of all cancers in women. An increased incidence has also been found in association with tamoxifen treatment, as in the case described herein. We present the case of a 54-year-old woman who was treated with tamoxifen for breast cancer. The patient was subsequently diagnosed with endometrial cancer. The clinical course was unfavorable with abdominopelvic disease recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escudero, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de endometrio es la malignidad ginecológica más común y representa el 6% de todos los cánceres que se presentan en la mujer. Existe un aumento de la incidencia concomitante con el tratamiento con tamoxifeno, presente en el caso descrito. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 54 años controlada y tratada con tamoxifeno por cáncer de mama, que presenta un cáncer de endometrio con mala evolución posterior y recurrencia abdominopélvica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);33(1): 22-24, ene.-feb. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043587</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de endometrio con evolución desfavorable en paciente tratada con tamoxifeno</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14010^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32835^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30131^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14010^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30131^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32835^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30131^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
