<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79593</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measurement of the quality of life in the residents doctors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. During specialty studies, the resident doctor faces higher stress levels than the normal population, affecting him/her professionally and personally, hence we ask the question: do the residency studies modify the quality of life of the resident doctors who are taking the specialty? Subjects and methods. A descriptive, comparative study was carried out in February 2006 and in February 2007. We applied the PECVEC questionnaire central module to two resident&#146;s groups: the first one, initiating their medical specialty and one year later; and the second one, residents with more than one year of specialty studies. We included residents from medical and surgical specialties that agreed to participate in this study. All data was captured on SPSS v. 15 for analysis descriptive statistics were used for socio-demographic variables, the Student&#146;s t for comparing the quality of life among residents and specialty. The quality of life was classified as &#145;very good&#146; between 3.1 and 4,&#145;good&#146; between 2.1 and 3, &#145;regular&#146; between 1.1 and 2 and &#145;bad &#145;between 0 and 1. Results. 54 residents were included in the FirstGroup, from which only 45 completed the questionnaires at the beginning and one year later. We excluded 9 residents because they didn&#146;t complete the second questionnaire. In the second group, we included 62 second and third year residents that had more than a year of specialty studies. We found that after one year of specialty, the 6 evaluation scales showed a decline in the quality of life, falling from a level considered as &#145;very good&#146;(3.18) to &#145;good&#146; (2.73) p &lt; 0.001. However, when we compared these results with the second group, this one didn&#146;t have a decline in the quality of life; the most affected parameters were: physical function and negative state of mind, with respect to (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Bernardino, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Benítez, W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Miranda, S. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Durante los estudios de especialidad el médico residente afronta niveles de estrés superiores a la población general afectándolo profesional y personalmente, por lo que cuestionamos por qué los estudios de residencia modifican la calidad de vida de los médicos residentes que los cursan. Sujetos y métodos. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo, comparativo, entre febrero de 2006y febrero de 2007. Se aplicó el módulo central del cuestionario PECVEC a dos grupos de residentes: un grupo de residentes que iniciaba su especialidad y un año después, y a otro grupo que ya tenía más de un año realizando estudios de especialidad; se incluyeron residentes tanto de especialidades medicas como quirúrgicas que aceptaron participar. Los datos se capturaron en el programa SPSSv. 15. Se utilizó estadística descriptiva para variables sociodemográficas de Student para comparar la calidad de vida entre residentes y especialidad cursada. La calidad de vida se clasificó como &#145;muy buena&#146; de 3,1 a 4, &#145;buena &#145;de 2,1 a 3, &#145;regular&#146; de 1,1 a 2 y &#145;mala&#146; entre 0 y 1. Resultados. En el primer grupo se incluyeron 54 residentes, sólo45 residentes completaron las encuestas al ingreso y un año después, y se excluyó a 9 por no completar la segunda evaluación; el segundo grupo incluyó a 62 residentes de segundo y tercer año que tenían más de un año realizando estudios de especialidad. Se encontró que después de un año de especialidad en las seis  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);12(3): 169-177, sept. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79593</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medición de la calidad de vida en médicos residentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22941^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
