<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040875</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2760</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anatomy of the lower limb lymphatic system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From the anatomical functional point of view, the lymphatic system is divided into: the lymphatic currents, lymphatic    nodes and lymph.    At the lower limb level, as happens in the veins, are    differentiated two lymphatic currents: the superficial and    the deep. A third system, of the perforant lymphatic vessels,    links both currents.    The principal node groups of the lower extremities are    represented by the popliteal nodes and the inguinal nodes;    there also exist secondary nodes such as the anterior    tibial nodes, peroneal nodes, posterior tibial nodes,    femoral nodes and iliopelvic nodes.    The lymphatic system of the abdomen is formed by the    lymphatic trunks, the parietal nodes (of the anteriolateral    abdominal wall and the retroperitoneals) and the visceral    nodes. The lymph proceeding from the entire retroperitoneal    plexus is collected by the lumbar trunks, which are the principal origin of the thoracic duct (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosendo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Latorre, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciucci, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde el punto de vista anátomo funcional, el sistema linfático se divide en: corrientes linfáticas, ganglios    linfáticos y linfa.    A nivel del miembro inferior, al igual que ocurre en las    venas, se diferencian dos corrientes linfáticas: superficiales    y profundas. Un tercer sistema, el de los vasos    linfáticos perforantes, comunicaría ambas corrientes.    Los grupos ganglionares principales de la extremidad    inferior están representados por los ganglios poplíteos y    los ganglios inguinales; existiendo además ganglios secundarios    tales como los tibiales anteriores, peroneos,    tibiales posteriores, femorales e iliopélvicos.    El sistema linfático del abdomen esta formado por los    troncos linfáticos, los ganglios parietales (de la pared    abdominal anterolateral y los retroperitoneales) y los    ganglios viscerales. La linfa procedente de los miembros    inferiores y de todo el plexo retroperitoneal es recogida    por los troncos lumbares, que son el origen principal del conducto torácico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. cir. card. cir. vasc;11(3): 147-156, mayo-jun. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040875</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anatomía del sistema linfático del miembro inferior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8383^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8385^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31210^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37781^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37781^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14294^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14294^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1168^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1168^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8385^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14294^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
