<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126629</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">European Union Health Strategy: Public Health for european people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The member States have exclusive authority over health, but the European Union has the responsibility, pursuant to the provisions of Article 152 of the Treaty, of rounding out the policies of the member Status in order to enhance public health, prevent diseases and avoid sources of hazards to human health, which includes the fight against the most serious, widespread diseases (by supporting the research of their aetiology, their transmission and prevention), as well as health information and education and the surveillance of serious transborder threats to health, alerting in the event of such threats and combating the same. In order to fulfil these obligations, the European Commission presented the White Paper "Together for Health: A Strategic Approach for the EU 2008-2013" on October 23, 2007. But the community-based health strategy has been being taking shape for some time now by means of different documents which have progressively been prefiguring it, thus being the result of long years of continuous work which has been being done since the early nineties. Throughout this time, the Directorate General of Public Health has been taking part in the process of preparing these documents and thus in what is now being presented as the EU health strategy. The main idea around which this work revolves is that there is a patent continuity and clear public health content in both the White Paper and in the documents which preceded it in time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvete Oliva, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La salud es competencia exclusiva de los Estados miembros (EEMM) pero la Unión Europea (UE) tiene la responsabilidad, de acuerdo con lo establecido en el artículo 152 del Tratado, de complementar las políticas de los EEMM para mejorar la salud pública, prevenir las enfermedades y evitar las fuentes de peligro para la salud humana; eso incluye la lucha contra las enfermedades más graves y ampliamente difundidas (apoyando la investigación de su etiología, de su transmisión y de su prevención), así como la información y la educación sanitarias y la vigilancia de las amenazas transfronterizas graves para la salud, la alerta en caso de tales amenazas y la lucha contra ellas. Para dar cumplimiento a estas obligaciones, la Comisión Europea (CE) presentó el día 23 de octubre de 2007 el Libro Blanco "Juntos por la salud: un planteamiento estratégico para la UE (2008-2013)". Pero la estrategia sanitaria comunitaria se viene gestando desde hace bastante tiempo mediante diversos documentos que han ido prefigurándola, de manera que es fruto de un trabajo largo y continuado desarrollado desde los primeros años noventa. A lo largo de ese tiempo la Dirección General de Salud Pública ha venido participando en el proceso de elaboración de esos documentos y, por ende, en lo que hoy se presenta como estrategia sanitaria de la Unión Europea. La idea central de este trabajo es que existe una línea de continuidad evidente y un claro contenido de salud pública, tanto en el Libro Blanco como en los documentos que le precedieron (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;82(3): 273-281, mayo.-jun. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126629</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategia de salud de la Unión Europea: Salud Pública para las personas europeas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16835^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7555^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5160^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16835^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16835^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
