<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128017</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Naso-orogastric tube in paediatric patients. Review of methods of confirmation of placement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nasogastric tube (NGT) placement is a frequent procedure in the paediatric population. Nasogastric and orogastric tubes are commonly used in hospitalized children, in the paediatric emergency departments and in critical care departments. They have diagnostic, therapeutic, descompression or evacuation of gastric aspirates objectives. Making a blind placement of nasogastric tubes, involve that nasogastric tube could be misplaced in 4.7 % to 69 % of cases. An accurate method for confirmation of nasogastric tube positioning is therefore needed. Chest X-ray remains the only hundred per cent reliable method (gold standard), but it only confirms tube positioning at the exact time of the X-ray. Non-radiologic verification methods provide an accurate alternative and contribute to decrease radiation exposure for pediatric patients. Non-radiologic methods to verify appropiate placement of tubes are many and are supported by different degrees of evidence in the literature: measurement of tube length from point of entry; auscultation; placing the tube in water to assess bubbling; aspiration of stomach or intestinal contents for visual inspection; pH testing; use of CO2 monitoring devices, or combinations of these methods. In this article we thoroughly review the reliability and safety of these non radiologic methods for the verification of nasogastric tube placement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerrero-Márquez, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Míguez-Navarro, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Serrano, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La colocación de la sonda gástrica (SG) es un procedimiento no infrecuente en la población pediátrica. Las SG se utilizan con asiduidad en los servicios de Hospitalización, de Urgencias Pediátricas y en los de Cuidados Críticos. Sus objetivos son diagnósticos, terapéuticos y la descompresión y evacuación del contenido aspirado. La colocación a ciegas de la SG conlleva tasas de colocación incorrecta de entre un 4.7 % y un 69 % de los casos. Se necesita por lo tanto la utilización de un método fiable de determinación de la colocación de la misma. La radiografía (Rx) de tórax es el único método fiable al cien por cien (gold standard), pero solo confirma la colocación en el momento exacto de realización de la Rx. Los métodos no radiológicos son una alternativa fiable que contribuyen a reducir la exposición a radiaciones en los pacientes pediátricos. Hay diversos métodos alternativos a la Rx para verificar la colocación apropiada de la SG y que están respaldados por distintos grados de evidencia científica. Algunos son: medida de la sonda desde el punto de entrada; auscultación, aspiración del contenido estomacal o intestinal para inspeccionarlo visualmente; medición del pH; capnografía, o la combinación de varios de estos métodos. En este artículo se revisa a fondo la validez y la seguridad de algunos de estos métodos no radiológicos como métodos de comprobación de la ubicación de la SG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(9): 575-580, sept. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sondaje naso/orogástrico en el paciente pediátrico. Revisión de métodos de comprobación de la ubicación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33095^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7602^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7602^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35089</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
