<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056615</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Publications on primary care evaluation in Spain after twenty years of reform (1984-2004): thematic and bibliometric analysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In view of the widespread opinion as to the lack of data for        evaluating the results of the Primary Care reform which began        in Spain in 1984, the conducting of a thematic and bibliometric        analysis for the published evaluation studies is posed. The        documents published within the 1984-2004 time period,        located by means of systematic bibliographic search both in        biomedical journals and in theses, reports or books on any of        the components of Primary Care included within the proposed        thematic classification and referred to scopes broader than one        single healthcare center. Three complimentary search strategies        were used: electronic databases, manual review of indexes and        reference work quote-based searches. A total of 684 documents        met the criteria for inclusion: 85% having been taken from        biomedical journals, 12.3% having been doctoral theses, and        2.6% reports or books. Documents were located in 49 different        journals (29 foreign), Atención Primaria (52.7%) being the        journal having provided the largest number of articles. A total        12.7% of the articles were published in journals indexed in the        SCI, and 8.6% in foreign journals. In 32% of the studies, the        first author was working at a reformed healthcare center. Twothirds        of the evaluations revolved around the analysis of the        process; the topics most often evaluated having been related to        healthcare spending (pharmacy), the system organization        (emergencies) and professional satisfaction. Broad-based        documentation is provided with evaluations of primary care in        Spain. Studies have been focused more on the evaluation of the        process than on that of the results. Research in this field        requires including studies not published in journals (theses and        reports)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Otero Puime, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo-Cáceres Ascanio, Antonio de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ante la extendida opinión sobre la falta de datos para evaluar        los resultados de la reforma de la Atención Primaria iniciada        en España en 1984, se plantea realizar un análisis temático y        bibliométrico de los trabajos de evaluación publicados. Se estudiaron        los documentos publicados entre 1984 y 2004, localizados        mediante búsqueda bibliográfica sistemática tanto en revistas        biomédicas como en tesis, informes o libros, sobre        cualquiera de los componentes de la Atención Primaria recogidos        en la clasificación temática propuesta y referidos a ámbitos        superiores a un solo centro de salud. Se utilizaron tres estrategias        de búsqueda complementarias: bases de datos electrónicas,        revisión manual de índices y búsqueda a partir de citas bibliográficas.        684 documentos cumplieron los criterios de        inclusión. 85% procedían de revistas biomédicas, 12,3% eran        tesis doctorales y 2,6% informes o libros. Se localizaron documentos        en 49 revistas diferentes (29 extranjeras), siendo Atención        Primaria (52,7 %) la que proporcionó más artículos. El        12,7% de los artículos fueron publicados en revistas indexadas        en el SCI y un 8,6% en revistas extranjeras. En el 32% de los        estudios el primer autor trabajaba en un centro de salud reformado.        Dos tercios de las evaluaciones se centraron en el análisis        del proceso. Los temas más frecuentemente evaluados se        relacionaban con el gasto sanitario (farmacia), organización        del sistema (urgencias) y satisfacción de los profesionales.        Existe una amplia base documental con evaluaciones de la        atención primaria española. Los estudios se han dirigido más        hacia la evaluación del proceso que a la de resultados. La investigación        en este campo requiere incluir trabajos no publicados        en revistas (tesis e informes)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;81(2): 131-145, mar.-abr.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056615</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Publicaciones sobre evaluación de la atención primaria en España tras veinte años de reforma (1984-2004): análisis temático y bibliométrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
