<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040825</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of the theory of mind: its involvement in distinct autistic spectrum disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malfunction of the ability to ascribe mental states to others, that is, possession of a Theory of Mind (ToM), was proposed by CD Frith as a necessary, sufficient and specific condition of schizophrenia. The present article reviews the evidence for and against this assumption, bearing in mind its putative relationship with other cognitive variables, whether the lack of a ToM is trait marker or rather a state marker and whether its causal role involves the underlying psychotic disorder or only some psychotic symptoms. Equally, whether the recent findings of ToM dysfunction in bipolar disorder and frontotemporal dementia could modify basic theoretical assumptions about ToM, schizophrenia and related conditions is also discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rejón Altable, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Santín, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disfunción de la habilidad para adscribir estados mentales a otros, esto es, la posesión de una teoría de la mente, ha sido propuesta por Frith como condición necesaria, suficiente y específica de la esquizofrenia. Este artículo revisa los datos a favor y en contra de tal asunción, teniendo en cuenta su relación hipotética con otras variables cognitivas, si la falta de una teoría de la mente es un marcador de rasgo o de estado y si su rol causal implica el trastorno psicótico básico o sólo algunos síntomas psicóticos. Igualmente se considera si los recientes hallazgos de disfunción de la teoría de la mente en el trastorno bipolar y en la demencia frontotemporal podrían modificar las asunciones teóricas básicas sobre la teoría de la mente, la esquizofrenia y los trastornos relacionados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);12(5): 206-213, sept. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Origen y destino de la teoría de la mente: su afectación en trastornos distintos del espectro autista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d346^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
