<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051201</identifier>
<setSpec>0482-5985</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Supracondylar stress fractures of the femur</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Description of a clinical case report of a stress fracture in the supracondylar femur  an extremely rare fracture site. We wish to highlight the importance of early diagnosis of these fractures to prevent complications. Their existence must be considered when there is persistent pain in the anterior knee, not only in the case of athletes or military personnel, but in any person who does a lot of physical activity. The main differential diagnosis must be a femoropatellar syndrome. We consider surgical, and not conservative, treatment advisable in young persons, since it allows a rapid return to work and prevents complications due to displacement</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Durán Stern, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Úbeda, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lópiz Morales, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe un caso clínico de una fractura de estrés en la región supracondílea del fémur, una localización extremadamente rara. Pretendemos llamar la atención sobre la importancia del diagnóstico precoz de estas fracturas para evitar el desarrollo de complicaciones, debiendo tenerlas presentes ante un dolor persistente en la región anterior de la rodilla, no sólo en atletas y militares, sino en cualquier persona que realice una actividad física importante. El diagnóstico diferencial principal se hace con el síndrome femoropatelar. En personas jóvenes nos inclinamos por el tratamiento quirúrgico de estas fracturas frente al conservador, ya que permite una rápida reincorporación a la actividad laboral previa y evita las complicaciones derivadas de su desplazamiento</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. ortop. traumatol. (Madr., Ed. impr.);50(5): 386-389, sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051201</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fractura de estrés en región supracondílea de fémur</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24657^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24657^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
