<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111062</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the clinical features and course of 10 cases of Kawasaki disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To report our experience in Kawasaki disease, describing the clinical characteristics, course, treatment and cardiological complications of patients diagnosed in our center. Material and method: Clinical, analytical and cardiological evaluation of 10 cases of Kawasaki disease diagnosed in our hospital from 1988 to 2000. Results: The mean patient age was 2 years 8 months (range: 4 months to 10 years). The male-to-female ratio was 1.5 to 1. All the patients met 5 of the 6 criteria considered fundamental, with fever, oropharyngeal injuries, exanthema, conjunctival injection and desquamation of hands and feet. Some also presented indurated rash on hands and feet, cervical lymphadenopathy and cracked lips (80%), diffuse oral rash (60%) and perineal desquamation (30%). Diagnosis was delayed in a patient who presented with marked cervical lymphadenopathy. Cardiac symptoms appeared in the acute phase; they were mild and transient in 40% of patients, and one child had a coronary aneurysm which increased in size after an untreated bout of fever. All were treated with acetylsalicylic acid, accompanied by intravenous gammaglobulin in 7. There were no cases of myocardial infarct and no deaths. Conclusion: All the cases were typical, with patients meeting 5 diagnostics criteria. Diagnosis was delayed in those in whom the presentation was unusual. One patient had a relapse, which produce a negative effect on his aneurysm. Treatment was delayed in 80% of cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moruno Tirado, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Hinojosa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Boné Montero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pichi Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Torrado, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mier Palacios, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal Romero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir nuestra experiencia en la enfermedad de Kawasaki, así como características clínicas, evolución, tratamiento y complicaciones cardiológicas de los pacientes diagnosticados en nuestro Centro. Material y método: Valoración clínica, analítica y cardiológica  de 10 casos de enfermedad de Kawasaki diagnosticados en nuestro hospital desde 1988 a 2000. Resultados: Edad media de 2 años y 8 meses (rango: de 4 meses a 10 años). Relación hombre-mujer: 1,5/1. En todos ellos se cumplieron 5 de los 6 criterios considerados fundamentales, estando siempre presentes: fiebre, lesiones orofaríngeas, exantema, inyección conjuntival y descamación de manos y pies. En menor medida hubo: eritema indurado de manos y pies, adenopatías cervicales y fisuras labiales (80%), eritema oral difuso (60%) y descamación perineal (30%). Existió retraso diagnóstico en el paciente que debutó con una gran adenopatía cervical. Se presentaron alteraciones cardíacas en la fase aguda, leves y transitorias en el 40% de pacientes, y un paciente manifestó un aneurisma coronario cuyo tamaño aumentó tras un nuevo brote febril no tratado. El tratamiento se realizó en todos con ácido acetilsalicílico, y en siete de ellos, con gammaglobulina intravenosa. No hubo ningún caso de infarto de miocardio ni de fallecimiento. Conclusión: Todos los casos fueron típicos, presentando cinco criterios diagnósticos. Existió retraso diagnóstico en los de presentación no habitual. Hubo recaída de la enfermedad en un paciente, en el que empeoró el aneurisma que previamente sufría. Existió retraso diagnóstico en los de presentación no habitual. Hubo recaída de la enfermedad en un paciente, en el que empeoró el aneurisma que previamente sufría. Existió retraso del tratamiento en el 80% de los casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;61(10): 531-535, nov. 2003. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111062</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio clínico y evolutivo de 10 casos de enfermedad de Kawasaki</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9272^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9272^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9272^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19138^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19138^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19138^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
