<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76451</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of osteoid osteoma by means of CT-guided radiofrequency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To present the results obtained in the treatment of osteoid osteoma by percutaneous resection using computerized tomography-guided radiofrequency. We discuss the technique used and report on the economic advantages of the procedure, as compared with the traditional surgical technique. Patients and methodology: Between October 2001 and July 2007, twenty-one patients were analyzed who presented with an osteoid osteoma located in the femur (11 cases), tibia (7 cases), pelvis (1 case), talus (1 case) and hand (1 case). A CT-guided cool-tip electrode was introduced into the center of the nidus, connecting it to a radiofrequency generator. Patients stayed in hospital for 10h and immediately afterwards returned to their usual activities. A study was carried out to compare the cost/effectiveness of the CT-guided RF technique as compared with the conventional technique, whereby open surgery is performed to remove the bone fragment contained by the tumor. Results: The results obtained show complete remission of symptoms in 20 cases; the remaining case improved when the procedure was repeated. The cost/effectiveness study revealed hospital cost savings for the RF procedure. Conclusions: This is a simple percutaneous technique that can be carried out on an outpatient basis. It is indicated in nearly all locations. No significant complications have been reported and the results obtained have been satisfactory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarabia Condes, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Barrio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villamor Redondo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Presentar los resultados obtenidos en el tratamiento del osteoma osteoide mediante resección percutánea con radiofrecuencia guiada por tomografía computarizada (TC), exponer la técnica utilizada y mostrar las ventajas económicas del procedimiento, comparado con la técnica quirúrgica tradicional. Pacientes y metodología: Se estudiaron 21 pacientes que presentaban un osteoma osteoide localizado en el fémur (11 casos), la tibia (7 casos), la pelvis (un caso), el astrágalo (un caso) y la mano (un caso), entre octubre de 2001 y julio de 2007. Se introdujo un electrodo de punta fría guiado por TC en el centro del nidus y se conectó a un generador de radiofrecuencia. Los pacientes permanecieron ingresados 10h y volvieron a su actividad habitual de forma inmediata. Se realizó un estudio económico comparativo con la técnica convencional que elimina el fragmento óseo que contiene el tumor a cielo abierto y la descrita en este trabajo. Resultados: Los resultados obtenidos muestran la desaparición completa de la sintomatología en 20 casos y el caso restante mejoró al repetir el procedimiento. El estudio económico revela un ahorro de costes hospitalarios para el procedimiento realizado con radiofrecuencia. Conclusiones: Es una técnica fácil, percutánea y ambulatoria. Está indicada en casi todas las localizaciones. No se han descrito complicaciones importantes y proporciona buenos resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);54(1): 20-26, ene.-feb. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76451</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del osteoma osteoide mediante radiofrecuencia guiada por tomografía computarizada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4636^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10197^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10197^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
