<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60915</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5187</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Onychopathy with parakeratosis determined by direct examination with</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">20 cases are reported of patients with onychopathy in hands and feet, who were referred for mycological examination to confirm a diagnosis of onychoycosis.Clinically they exhibited onycholysis, color changes and trophic disorders in one or more nails. When subjected to direct examination of thenail bed with Clorazol Black E, all showed nucleated cells (parakeratosis) with positive results for fungi in 4 patients (20%).Electroencephalograms were performed on 7 patients (35%) showing symptoms of depression (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arreaza, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presento 20 casos de pacientes con onicopatía en manos y pies, quienes fueron referidos a la consulta de micología para hacer diagnóstico confirmatoriode onicomicosis. Clínicamente presentaban onicolisis, cambios de coloración y trastornos tróficos en una o varias uñas.Al practicarle examen directo del lecho ungueal con Negro de Clorazol, todos presentaban células nucleadas (paraqueratosis) con examen directopositivo para hongos en 4 pacientes (20%).Se le practicó electroencefalograma (mapa tac cerebral) y test psicométrico en 7 pacientes (35%) encontrándose cuatro de depresión endógena. Elresto de pacientes no colaboraron para la evaluación psicológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. cután. ibero-lat-am;36(2): 72-75, mar.-abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60915</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Onicopatías con paraqueratosis determinada por examen directo con Negro de Clorazol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6380^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10430^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6380^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5669^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30899^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5669^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
