<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119286</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transcultural adaptation and validation of the Celiac Disease Quality of Life (CD-QOL) survey, a specific questionnaire to measure quality of life in patients with celiac disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: celiac disease is a chronic condition that requires continued treatment, with the resultant impact on health-related quality of life (HRQOL) of people who suffer it. Most studies in this field have used generic questionnaires to measure HRQOL in celiac patients. It was therefore decided to conduct a study to translate into Spanish and validate a specific questionnaire for celiac disease, the Celiac Disease Quality Of Life Survey (CD-QOL). Objectives: to translate and validate in Spanish the specific celiac disease questionnaire CD-QOL. Methods: a multicenter, prospective, observational study was designed consisting of two phases: In the first phase, the questionnaire was translated and adapted into Spanish using the translation/back translation procedure and an understandability study. In the second phase, internal consistency of the translated questionnaire was analyzed. For this, results of the CD-QOL were compared to those of EuroQol and the Daily Fatigue Impact Scale (D-FIS). Understandability of the translated and adapted questionnaire was tested in six patients, and the validation study was done in 298 celiac patients (201 treated with a gluten-free diet and 97 at diagnosis). Results: in both celiac groups, Cronbach&#146;s alpha coefficient was high (0.90), feasibility was excellent (99.2 % of patients completed all questions), and there were no ceiling and floor effects. Spearman correlation to EuroQol and D-FIS was statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05). CD-QOL score was different depending on whether state of health was good, fair, or poor based on the EuroQol score. Conclusion: the Spanish version of the CD-QOL is a valid tool for measuring HRQOL in celiac patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Vivancos, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucendo, Alfredo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina-Infante, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casellas, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Bañares, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivas, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosinach, Mercé</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la enfermedad celiaca es una enfermedad crónica que requiere de un tratamiento continuado, lo que conlleva un impacto sobre la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) de las personas que la padecen. La mayoría de estudios en nuestro medio han utilizado cuestionarios genéricos para medir la CVRS en los pacientes celiacos, lo que ha motivado el presente estudio para traducir y validar al castellano un cuestionario específico para la enfermedad celiaca, el &#147;Celiac Disease Quality Of Life Survey&#148; (CD-QOL). Objetivos: traducir y validar al castellano el cuestionario específico para la enfermedad celiaca CD-QOL. Métodos: se ha diseñado un estudio multicéntrico, prospectivo y observacional desarrollado en dos fases: la primera de traducción/adaptación al idioma castellano mediante el procedimiento de traducción/retrotraducción y estudio de comprensibilidad. A continuación se desarrolló la segunda fase de análisis de la consistencia interna del cuestionario traducido. Para ello se han comparado los resultados del CD-QOL con los del EuroQol y la escala de impacto diario de la fatiga (EIDF). El estudio de comprensibilidad del cuestionario traducido y adaptado se realizó en 6 pacientes, y el estudio de validación en 298 celiacos (201 tratados con dieta sin gluten y 97 al momento del diagnóstico). Resultados: en ambos grupos de celiacos el coeficiente alfa de Cronbach fue elevado (0,90), la factibilidad fue excelente (99,2 % de pacientes completaron todas las preguntas) y el efecto techo y suelo fue nulo. La correlación de Spearman con el EuroQol y el EIDF fue estadísticamente significativa (p &lt; 0,05). El CD-QOL puntuó diferente según el estado de salud fuera bueno, regular o malo en función de la puntuación del EuroQol. Conclusión: la versión en castellano del CD-QOL es un instrumento válido de medida de la CVRS de los pacientes celiacos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;105(10): 585-593, nov.-dic. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119286</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación transcultural y validación del &#147;Celiac Disease Quality of Life (CD-QOL) survey&#148;, un cuestionario específico de medida de la calidad de vida en pacientes con enfermedad celiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
