<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99784</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Euthanasia in Belgium</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The experience of the Netherlands in relation with the legalization and practice of euthanasia is better known in Spain than the Belgian experience in this matter. But the historical process of social debate in Belgium has many specific details which should be known by Spanish healthcare professionals, bioethicists, politicians and lawyers. This paper begins with a comparative analysis of both countries: Spain and Belgium and follows with a description of the milestones of the historical process of debating and, finally, passing the Belgian Law on Euthanasia in 2002. The next chapter consists of a description of themain contents of this important Law. The paper continues then with an approach to the epidemiology of the practice of euthanasia in Belgium and finishes with a description of the different positions of the actors of the process. Two positions are described more in depth: the opinion of the specialists in palliative care, and the opinion of the Catholic Church. The paper ends underlining the reason for the incorporation of the Belgian experience on euthanasia to the debate about the possibility of legalizing euthanasia in Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón Lorda, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Cantalejo, Inés M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La experiencia holandesa en relación con la legalización y la práctica de la eutanasia es más conocida en España que la experiencia belga. Sin embargo, el proceso histórico de debate social en Bélgica en torno a la eutanasia tiene una riqueza en matices que debería ser conocida por los profesionales sanitarios, bioeticistas, políticos y juristas. El presente trabajo se inaugura con un análisis sobre las similitudes y diferencias que existen entre España y Bélgica, lo que permite encuadrar el desarrollo posterior. Después se describe la historia del proceso de debate realizado en Bélgica que tiene su punto álgido en la aprobación de la ley de eutanasia en el año 2002. En el apartado siguiente se analiza de forma detallada el contenido de esta disposición legislativa, señalando los aspectos más relevantes. A continuación se exponen algunos datos epidemiológicos sobre la práctica de la eutanasia en Bélgica y se finaliza con un relato sobre la manera en que diversos grupos de población han afrontado el tema de la eutanasia. En este último apartado el trabajo se detiene en las posiciones de dos grupos especialmente relevantes: los especialistas en Cuidados Paliativos y la Iglesia Católica. Se finaliza con una exposición de los motivos por los que resulta conveniente incorporar la perspectiva y experiencia belga en futuros debates sobre la posible legalización de la eutanasia en España(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;86(1): 5-19, ene.-mar.2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La eutanasia en Bélgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30490^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9619^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30490^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30490^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28008^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
