<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132095</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-7347</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pneumocystis jirovecii colonization in COPD patients and relationship to the stage of disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: factors that determine which smokers will develop COPD and the severity of the disease are unknown at present, but have attracted interest the possible role that infectious agents could play inducing inflammatory response, accelerating progression of the disease or perpetuating its progression. The aim of our study was to determine the rate of colonization with Pneumocystis jirovecii in subjects with COPD and view their relationship with the various disease stages. Methods: We performed a cross sectional study in patients treated in these clinics for smoking, with or without COPD, at any stage of their disease. Each patient underwent a detailed medical history, besides making induced sputum samples and lung function tests. The molecular diagnosis of Pneumocystis jirovecii colonization was performed by PCR in induced sputum samples. Statistical analysis was performed comparing colonization Pneumocystis jirovecii in different groups of smokers without COPD and COPD in its various stages, using SPSS, version 18. Results: 42.6% of the 101 patients studied had Pneumocystis jirovecii colonization. No differences were found in the presence of the microorganism, depending the stage of the disease as well as in relation to the suffered symptoms or exacerbations in the previous year. Conclusions: There is a high prevalence of colonization Pneumocystis jirovecii in smokers with or without COPD. No statistically significant differences we obtain in the presence of the pathogen, as disease states (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega Ruiz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Martín, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón Sandubete, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campano Cuevas, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Horra Padilla, C. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los factores que determinan qué fumadores desarrollarán EPOC y gravedad de la enfermedad se desconocen en la actualidad, pero ha suscitado interés el posible papel que los agentes infecciosos pudieran desempeñar a través de la respuesta inflamatoria que inducen, acelerando la progresión de la enfermedad o perpetuando su progresión. El objetivo de nuestro estudio es conocer la tasa de colonización por Pneumocystis jirovecii en sujetos con EPOC y ver su relación con los distintos estadios de la enfermedad. Método: realizamos un estudio transversal en pacientes atendidos en las consultas de neumología por tabaquismo, con o sin EPOC, en cualquier estadio de su enfermedad. A cada paciente se le realizó una historia clínica detallada, además de la toma de muestras de esputo inducido y pruebas de función respiratoria. El diagnóstico molecular de la colonización por Pneumocystis jirovecii se efectuó mediante PCR en las muestras de esputo inducido. Se realizó un análisis estadístico, comparando la colonización por Pneumocystis jirovecii en los distintos grupos de fumadores sin EPOC y con EPOC en sus distintos estadios, utilizando el paquete estadístico SPSS, versión 18. Resultados: el 42,6% de los 101 pacientes estudiados presentó colonización por Pneumocystis jirovecii. No se hallaron diferencias en cuanto a la presencia del microorganismo, dependiendo del estadio de la enfermedad, así como en relación a los síntomas o exacerbaciones sufridas en el año anterior. Conclusiones: existe una elevada prevalencia de colonización por Pneumocystis jirovecii en sujetos fumadores, con o sin EPOC. No obtenemos diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la presencia de este patógeno, según estadios de enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol. torac;26(4): 244-249, oct.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132095</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colonización por pneumocystis jirovecii en pacientes con epoc y relación con el estadio de enfermedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37992^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19278^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
