<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137428</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of the multiple births recorded in Complejo Hospitalario  Universitario of Vigo (Spain) in the years 1994 and 2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether there were differences between the numbers, characteristics and  complications of the multiple births that took place in the Complejo Hospitalario Universitario of Vigo (Spain) in 1994 and 2004. Participants and Methods: We performed an observational, descriptive, cross-sectional study of the multiple births recorded in the Complejo Hospitalario Universitario of Vigo in 1994 and 2004. Results: The incidence of multiple births was 0.91% in 1994 (35 of 3840) and 1.38% in 2004 (59 of 4266). In 1994, 2.9% of the multiple pregnancies were the result of assisted reproductive technologies, compared with 42.4% in 2004 (p&lt;0.05). The average maternal age at the time of the delivery was 29.66 years in 1994 (95% CI [confidence interval]: 27.91- 31.40) and 32.15 years in 2004 (95% CI: 30.91-33.99) (p=0.19). The percentage of primigravidas over 35 years age was 5.7% in 1994 and 15.3% in 2004 (p=0.016). The percentage of primiparas over 35 years of age was 18.6% in 2004 and 5.7% in 1994 (p=0.039). The incidence of caesarean section performed in cases of multiple births was 54.3% in 1994 and 84.5% in 2004 (p=0.001). Conclusions: We recorded an increase in the number of multiple pregnancies, while significant increases were also observed in the number of  multiple pregnancies occurring after the use of assisted reproductive technologies, in the mean age of the women with multiple pregnancies, in the  percentage of women that became pregnant and gave birth for the first time past the age of 35 years, and in the incidence of caesarean section (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Boubeta, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cid-González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Gómez, M J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer si existen diferencias en el número, las características y las complicaciones de los partos múltiples atendidos en el Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Vigo en los años 1994 y 2004. Personas y método: Estudio observacional, descriptivo y transversal de todos los partos múltiples atendidos en el Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Vigo en 1994 y 2004. Resultados: En 1994, el porcentaje de partos múltiples fue del 0,91% (35 de 3.840) y, en 2004, de 1,38% (59 de 4.266). En 1994, el 2,9% de las gestaciones múltiples fueron resultado de técnicas de reproducción asistida, frente al 42,4% de 2004 (p &lt;0,05). La media de la edad materna en el momento del parto fue de 29,66 años en 1994 (Intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%: 27,91-31,40), y de 32,15 años en 2004 (IC del 95%: 30,91-33,99) (p= 0,19). El porcentaje de primigestas mayores de 35 años fue del 5,7% en 1994 y del 15,3% en 2004 (p= 0,016). El porcentaje de primíparas mayores de 35 años en 2004 fue del 18,6% y en 1994 del 5,7% (p= 0,039). Un 54,3% de todas las gestaciones múltiples finalizaron por cesárea en 1994, frente al 84,5% en 2004 (p= 0,001). Conclusiones: Hemos encontrado un aumento en el número de gestaciones múltiples. También ha aumentado de manera significativa el número de gestaciones múltiples que son resultado de técnicas de reproducción asistida, así como la edad media de las mujeres y el porcentaje de mujeres que se quedan embarazadas y tienen su primer hijo con más de 35 años, y el porcentaje de cesáreas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;9(2): 17-20, abr.-jun. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137428</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparativa de partos múltiples en el Complejo Hospitalario Universitario de Vigo en los años 1994 y 2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36295^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
