<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053223</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Technical features of interest in lymphatic basin localization in breast cancer sentinel lymph node biopsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. The sentinel node is defined as the node with the highest probability of being involved in the case of lymphatic spread from a tumor. Accurate identification and biopsy of this node can avoid unnecessary lymphadenectomies. The aim of this study was to determine if there are differences in the number of isolated sentinel lymph nodes in breast cancer according to whether a mixed technique (vital dye plus isotopic tracer) or radiotracer alone is used and if there are differences in the detection of more than one lymphatic basin and in the number of lymphatic nodes depending on the site of tracer injection.  Patients and method. A total of 173 sentinel lymph node biopsies in 173 women with breast cancer were studied taking into account the technique (mixed [n = 109] or radiotracer alone [n = 64]) and the location of tracer injection (periareolar [n = 81], intra and/or peritumoral [n = 92]). The number of lymphatic basins and the number of sentinel nodes were compared among the distinct groups resulting from the combination of the 2 parameters.  Results. Simultaneous drainage to both the axilla and internal mammary chain was more frequent with the intra-periareolar technique. The number of identified nodes was significantly higher when mixed techniques were compared, and was higher with periareolar injection than with the intra-peritumoral route. Conclusions. In breast cancer sentinel lymph node biopsy, the number of identified nodes is not influenced by the use of a mixed technique or radiotracer alone. However, the number of identified nodes is higher with the periareolar route than with the intra-peritumoral route. Intra-peritumoral injection of the tracer shows a higher frequency of internal mammary chain drainage than periareolar injection, although this difference was not statistically significant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galindo-Fernández, Pedro José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canteras-Jordana, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñero-Madrona, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicolás-Ruiz, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Illana-Moreno, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla-Paricio, Pascual</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. El ganglio centinela es el que tiene más probabilidad de afectarse en caso de extensión linfática de un tumor. Su identificación y biopsia correctas pueden evitar linfadenectomías innecesarias. El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar si hay diferencias en el número de ganglios centinelas aislados en el cáncer de mama dependiendo de que se utilice la técnica mixta (colorante más trazador isotópico) o únicamente isótopo como trazador, y si las hay en la aparición de más de un drenaje linfático y en el número de ganglios centinela, dependiendo de la localización de la inyección del trazador. Pacientes y método. Se han estudiado de forma prospectiva 173 biopsias selectivas del ganglio centinela en 173 mujeres con carcinoma de mama, considerando la técnica usada (mixta, 109; isótopo, 64) y la localización de la inyección del trazador (periareolar [n = 81], intratumoral y/o peritumoral [n = 92]). Se comparó el número de drenajes y el número de ganglios centinela entre los distintos grupos resultantes de combinar los dos parámetros. Resultados. El drenaje simultáneo a axila y a cadena mamaria interna fue más frecuente en los casos de inyección intratumoral y peritumoral. Con relación al número de ganglios identificados, encontramos que fue significativamente mayor al comparar las técnicas mixtas entre sí, y fue mayor el número de ganglios con la técnica de inyección periareolar que con la intratumoral y peritumoral.         Conclusiones. En la biopsia selectiva del ganglio centinela para el cáncer de mama, el número de ganglios centinelas identificados no depende de usar una técnica mixta o sólo isótopo como trazador; sin embargo, es mayor cuando se usa la vía periareolar que la intratumoral y peritumoral. La inyección intratumoral y peritumoral muestra una mayor frecuencia de drenajes hacia la cadena mamaria interna que la periareolar, aunque esta diferencia no es estadísticamente significativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);81(5): 264-268, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos técnicos de interés en la localización de drenajes linfáticos en la biopsia del ganglio centinela del cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12288</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
