<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162673</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-3703</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Polarity and totipotency during preimplantational development</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For a long time, it has been tried to find the first differences between cells taking place during preimplantational development of the mammalian embryo, arising different cell fates. Instead of differential divisions of maternal determinants as occurs in other species. It has been shown that this process is regulated by differences in cell to cell interactions, gene expression and individual cell microenvironment. However, how this differences at first appear and how molecular and cellular factors involved in differentiation are regulated, is still unknown. Material shortage and ethical limitations complicate the study on human embryos. Gradually the new advances in imaging techniques and transcriptome analysis of a single cell provide new insights that will help to solve questions that arise today (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Corral Castroviejo, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matorras Weining, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante mucho tiempo se ha intentado hallar las primeras diferencias entre células que ocurren durante el desarrollo preimplantacional en el embrión de mamífero, y que posteriormente darán lugar a diferentes destinos celulares. En los últimos años los estudios han demostrado que este proceso está regulado por diferencias en interacciones célula-célula, expresión génica y el microambiente de cada célula, en vez de por la división diferencial de determinantes maternos como pasa en otras especies. Sin embargo como aparecen estas diferencias en un primer momento y como regulan los factores moleculares y celulares implicados en la diferenciación celular es una pregunta por resolver. La escasez de material y las limitaciones éticas complican el estudio en embriones humanos. Poco a poco los nuevos avances en técnicas de imagen y análisis de transcriptómica de una única célula proveen nuevos conocimientos que ayudarán a resolver las dudas que se plantean hoy en día (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. iberoam. fertil. reprod. hum;34(1): 34-43, ene.-mar. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162673</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polaridad y totipotencia durante el desarrollo preimplantatorio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33166^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36531^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2995^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2489^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33558^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30203^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24666^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38858^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
