<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138367</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of vaginal cones int he treatment of pelvic floor rehabilitation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The pelvic floor (PF) is a sheet of muscles and other tissues that support the pelvic organs in their physiological positions. Throughout women&#146;s lives, these structures can become weak or be injured by events such as pregnancy, childbirth, surgery, overweight or constipation. PF dysfunction includes a group of disorders causing urinary incontinence, as well as genital prolapse or pelvic pain, and can significantly deteriorate women&#146;s quality of life. Vaginal cones (VC) represent a non-pharmacological, economical, safe and non-invasive method for the treatment of PF dysfunction; they allow the patient to increase the physiological consciousness of the musculature of the PF while promoting an increase in the muscle tone. The midwife, as a professional intimately connected with women&#146;s health care, works with the multidisciplinary team which treats pelvic dysfunctions; therefore, they need to provide updated information about the different methods for improving perineal function, including VC, and providing advice on their use and management, and establishing individualized exercise programs and tracking information for each case. The available scientific evidence on the effectiveness of the VC is limited and there may be other methods to treat PF dysfunctions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Onandia Garate, Maialen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Pan, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luces Lago, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tizón Bouza, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El suelo pélvico (SP) es el conjunto de músculos encargados del soporte y mantenimiento de los órganos pélvicos en sus posiciones fisiológicas. A lo largo de la vida, esta estructura puede alterarse por situaciones como la gestación, el tipo de parto, las intervenciones quirúrgicas realizadas sobre la zona perineal, la obesidad o el estreñimiento, entre otras. La alteración de la funcionalidad del SP puede dar lugar a la aparición de patologías como los prolapsos genitales, las incontinencias urinarias o el dolor pélvico, que pueden ocasionar una importante alteración en la calidad de vida de la persona que las padece. Los conos vaginales (CV) suponen un método no farmacológico, económico, seguro y no invasivo para el tratamiento efectivo de la disfunción de la musculatura del SP, puesto que permite a la paciente aumentar la conciencia fisiológica de la musculatura de su SP al tiempo que promueve el aumento de la fuerza muscular. La matrona, como profesional íntimamente ligado a la atención de la mujer, forma parte del equipo multidisciplinar encargado del abordaje activo de las disfunciones pélvicas; por ello, debe ofrecer a la mujer información actualizada sobre los CV, asesorando sobre su uso y manejo y estableciendo programas de ejercicios y seguimiento individualizados para cada caso. La evidencia científica disponible acerca de la eficacia de los CV es limitada y señala que pueden existir otros métodos o tratamientos de eficacia semejante para el tratamiento rehabilitador del SP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;38(7/8): 488-494, jul.-ago. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de los conos vaginales en el tratamiento rehabilitador del suelo pélvico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31202^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31203^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
