<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044947</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Low glycemic index lunch on satiety in overweight and obese people with type 2 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several studies have shown that isocaloric diets have different effects on satiety. The aim of the present study was to compare the effect of lunches with different glycemic indexes (GI) in type 2 diabetics. Ten men and women with type 2 diabetes participated in the study. Subjects were given two experimental lunches with glycemic indexes of 43 and 88. Visual analogue rating scales were completed before and after each experimental meal periodically to record subjective feelings of satiety. Satiety Area Under the Curve was 1024 ± 160 mm after the low GI diet and 711 ± 190 mm after the high GI diet. Eating a lunch with a low GI index resulted in higher satiety perception. These results suggest the need to promote culturally based combined foods with high fiber and low GI. This approach might contribute to the prevention of obesity by increasing the perception of satiety while also improving metabolic control of diabetics. In addition, this is a low cost approach for people with limited financial resources (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bacardi-Gascon, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Cruz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noriki Gutiérrez-González, Aaron</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diversos estudios han demostrado que las dietas hipocalóricas tienen diferentes efectos sobre la saciedad. El objetivo de este estudio fue comparar el efecto de comidas con diferentes índices glucémicos (IG) en diabéticos de tipo 2. Diez hombres y mujeres con diabetes de tipo 2 participaron en el estudio. Se administró a los individuos dos comidas experimentales con índices glucémicos de 43 y 88. Se completaron periódicamente escalas analógicas visuales de gradación antes y después de cada comida experimental para registrar los síntomas subjetivos de saciedad. El área bajo la curva de saciedad fue 1.024 ± 160 mm tras la dieta con IG bajo y 711 ± 190 mm tras la dieta con IG alto. La ingestión de una comida con un IG bajo produjo una mayor sensación de saciedad. Estos resultados sugieren la necesidad de promocionar los alimentos combinados, con una base cultural, con un contenido elevado en fibra y un IG bajo. Este abordaje podría contribuir a la prevención de la obesidad aumentando la percepción de saciedad a la vez que aumenta el control metabólico de los diabéticos. Además, este abordaje tiene un coste bajo en gente con recursos económicos limitados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;20(5): 348-350, sept.-oct. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044947</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comida con índice glucémico bajo y saciedad en gente obesa y con sobrepeso con diabetes mellitus de tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12909</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3950</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12910</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
