<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125376</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Post-surgical conventional dressing versus interactive moist wound healing dressing: Comparative evaluation in oncological surgical patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To compare the clinical performance of a surgical interactive transparent moist environment dressing versus a surgical gauze and tape conventional dressing in oncological abdominal surgical patients. Method: A prospective cohort study conducted at the MD Anderson Hospital (Madrid). Pilot assessment of 24 surgical oncology patients who underwent major abdominal surgery of gastrointestinal and gynecological specialities. Twelve were treated by the conventional dressing (Cosmopor®) and twelve by interactive dressing (Opsite® Post Op Visible). The sample is collected in the second half of the year 2011. Results: The interactive dressing remains at least 7 days over the wound without being changed, compared with traditional dressing that requires daily change what it means a difference of costs of 0.70&#128; in material resources and 24 min less in nursing time. Under the clinical point of view with the interactive dressing there are less surgical site infection episodes (8.31% vs 33.3%), less other adverse events (0 vs 8.3%) and improved satisfaction amongst patients and healthcare professionals adhesiveness, tolerance in shower and visibility of the wound. Conclusions: The systematic use of interactive postoperative dressings in surgical oncology increases the time of permanence of the dressings on wounds with a reduction of the 75% of surgical site infections and other adverse events reduction, as well as a cost reduction, estimated on a basis of 282 possible admissions per year of 193.17&#128; in materials, 282 hours in nursing time, and 71 episodes of surgical site infection with an extra bed occupancy of 558 days (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nieto Alonso, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz López, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz García, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torra i Bou, Joan-Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garnica Goyanes, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Lorenzo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: comparar las prestaciones clínicas de un apósito quirúrgico interactivo transparente de cura en ambiente húmedo frente al apósito quirúrgico convencional de gasa y esparadrapo en pacientes quirúrgicos oncológicos de cirugía abdominal. Método: estudio de cohortes prospectivo, realizado en el MD Anderson Cancer Center (Madrid). Se evalúan, de forma piloto, 24 pacientes quirúrgicos oncológicos, intervenidos de cirugía mayor abdominal de las especialidades digestiva y ginecológica. Doce de los pacientes son tratados con el apósito tradicional (Cosmopor®) y doce con el apósito interactivo (Opsite® Post Op Visible). La muestra se recoge en el segundo semestre del año 2011. Resultados: el apósito interactivo permanece al menos 7 días sobre la herida sin despegarse, frente al apósito convencional que precisa cambios diarios. Esto supone una diferencia en costes de 0,70 &#128; en materiales y 24 min menos de enfermería por paciente. Desde el punto de vista clínico, con el apósito interactivo se presentan menos casos de infección de herida quirúrgica (8,3% frente a 33,3%) y de efectos adversos (0 frente a 8,3%), y una mejor valoración por parte de los pacientes y profesionales ante la adhesividad, tolerancia en la ducha y visibilidad de la herida. Conclusiones: la utilización sistemática de apósitos interactivos en heridas quirúrgicas oncológicas permite que aumente la permanencia del apósito sobre éstas, con una reducción de un 75% tanto de las infecciones como de otras complicaciones, y una disminución de costes estimada, basándose en 282 posibles pacientes al año, de 193,17 &#128; en materiales, 282 horas de tiempo de enfermería y 71 episodios de infección de herida quirúrgica (IHQ) con una estancia extra de 558 días (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);25(1): 34-40, mar. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125376</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Apósito posquirúrgico convencional frente a apósito interactivo transparente de cura en ambiente húmedo: evaluación comparativa piloto en pacientes quirúrgicos oncológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15343</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9964^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
