<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99851</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">When to suspect seronegative spondyloarthropathy on MRI?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe the magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) findings for the spine in patients with seronegative spondyloarthropathy (SNS) and discuss the indications for MRI in the diagnosis and follow-up of this type of patients. We describe the pathological aspects of four patients diagnosed with SNS (Crohn's disease, ankylosing spondylitis, and psoriasis) with spinal involvement. The MRI findings in SNS vary in function of the type and stage of disease. Osteitis of the anterior vertebral bodies is a very early sign of spinal involvement in this group of diseases. Inflammatory involvement of the discovertebral complex that involves the adjacent vertebral bodies to a greater or lesser extent occurs later. MRI of the spine makes it possible to evaluate incipient signs of disease that are characteristic of these patients, so it is a useful tool for the diagnosis of SNS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Squarcia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pomés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oleaga, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olondo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berenguer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Templado, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Describir los hallazgos en columna de la resonancia magnética (RM) en las espondiloartropatías seronegativas (ESN) y valorar la indicación de esta modalidad de imagen en el diagnóstico y seguimiento de este tipo de pacientes. Se describen los aspectos patológicos en 4 casos diagnosticados de ESN (Crohn, espondilitis anquilopoyética y psoriasis) con afectación espinal. Los hallazgos en RM en las ESN varían en función del tipo de enfermedad y del estadio en el que se encuentre. La osteítis anterior de los cuerpos vertebrales es el signo más precoz de la afectación espinal en este grupo de enfermedades. La afectación inflamatoria del complejo discovertebral con mayor o menor grado de afectación de los cuerpos vertebrales adyacentes se produce más tardíamente. La RM de columna vertebral permite valorar signos patológicos incipientes característicos por lo que representa una herramienta útil para el diagnóstico en las ESN (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);54(2): 165-171, mar.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99851</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Espondiloartropatía seronegativa en RM: ¿cuándo pensar en ella?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36005^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13515^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
