<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047084</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sleeping difficulties among the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sleeping difficulties affect individuals at all ages, but the number of those affected increases in direct proportion to age. Frequently, the elderly manifest their difficulties in achieving a satisfactory degree of sleep. This circumstance, which has a negative effect on their physical and psychological well-being, is a common reason to consult a doctor. However, treatment with pharmaceuticals should not be considered a definitive solution. Health Education workshops make it possible to deal with sleep related difficulties in an integrated manner with a group of patients. These workshopsenable health professionals to work with the elderly toanalyze positive and negative factors which condition sleep, to know the changes which age produces in sleep patterns, to facilitate adapting to the afore mentioned changes, to reeducate inadequate habits and to promote healthy life styles which make an improvement possible. Furthermore, in these sleep workshops, participants receive trainingin techniques to control stimuli and induce relaxation, developing skills which the elderly can daily employ</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aparicio Alonso, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos de sueño afectan a individuos de todas lasedades, pero su número aumenta en proporción directa a laedad. Las personas mayores manifiestan con frecuencia susdificultades para lograr un sueño satisfactorio. Esta circunstancia, que incide negativamente en su bienestar físico y psicológico, constituye un motivo usual de consulta médica. Sin embargo, el tratamiento farmacológico no debe considerarse una solución definitiva. Los talleres de Educación para laSalud hacen posible el abordaje en grupo de los problemasde sueño con un enfoque integral. Permiten analizar los factores positivos y negativos que condicionan el sueño, conocer los cambios que produce la edad en los patrones desueño, facilitar la adaptación a dichos cambios, reeducarhábitos inadecuados y fomentar estilos de vida saludablesque posibiliten una mejora. En los talleres de sueño, además, se entrena a los participantes en técnicas de control de estímulos y de relajación, desarrollando habilidades para su práctica diaria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;29(3): 208-212, mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dificultades de sueño en las personas mayores. Abordaje</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
