<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106633</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exposure to Residential Radon and Lung Cancer in Never-Smokers: the Preliminary Results of the LCRINS Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: Residential radon is the second most important risk factor for lung cancer and the first among never-smokers. The objective of this study is to report the concentrations of residential radon in a series of never-smoker cases recruited in a multicenter study of cases and controls in northwestern Spain. In this study, all the hospitals in the Spanish province of Galicia and one from Asturias participated. Patients and methods: The present article includes a series of cases with residential radon measurements. All the subjects were personally interviewed, 3ml of blood were taken from each, and they were each given instructions about how to place a residential radon detector in their homes. Results: Sixty-nine case subjects were recruited, 84% of whom were women with a mean age of 71, and 81% of whom had adenocarcinoma. The average concentration of residential radon in the cases was 237Bq/m3, while the average concentration in the Galician population is 79Bq/m3. No relationship was observed between the concentration of residential radon and either sex or age at the time of diagnosis of the cases, but there was a tendency towards having a greater concentration in those diagnosed with small-cell and large-cell carcinoma. Conclusions: The concentrations of residential radon in the cases included are very high at about three times the average concentration of residential radon to which the general population of Galicia is exposed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruano-Ravina, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mejuto-Martí, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Silva, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Barcala, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leiro-Fernández, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veres-Racamonde, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pena, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prini-Guadalupe, Luciana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abal-Arca, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Golpe-Gómez, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-González, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barros-Dios, Juan Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero-Martínez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: El radón residencial es el segundo factor de riesgo del cáncer de pulmón y el primero en nunca fumadores. El objetivo de este estudio es describir la concentración de radón residencial en una serie de casos nunca fumadores reclutados en un estudio multicéntrico de casos y controles en el noroeste de España. En este estudio participan todos los hospitales gallegos y uno asturiano. Pacientes y métodos: En el presente artículo se incluye la serie de casos con mediciones de radón residencial. A todos los casos se les realiza una entrevista personal, se les extraen 3ml de sangre total y se les dan instrucciones para la colocación de un detector de radón residencial en su domicilio. Resultados: Se han incluido 69 casos (el 84% mujeres), con una edad media de 71 años y el 81% con adenocarcinoma. La concentración mediana de radón residencial en los casos ha sido de 237Bq/m3, mientras que la concentración mediana en la población gallega es de 79Bq/m3. No se ha observado relación entre la concentración de radón residencial y el sexo o la edad al diagnóstico de los casos, pero sí hay una tendencia a tener mayor concentración en los diagnosticados de carcinoma de células pequeñas y de células grandes. Conclusiones: Las concentraciones de radón residencial en los casos incluidos son muy elevadas, del orden de 3 veces la concentración mediana de radón residencial a la que está expuesta la población general gallega(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;48(11): 405-409, nov. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106633</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exposición a radón residencial y cáncer de pulmón en nunca fumadores. Resultados preliminares del estudio LCRINS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
