<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87041</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the Assistances of Nursing in a Base</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This work presents a descriptive, retrospective and longitudinal analysis of assistance and nursing cares records obtained during four years (2003 to 2006) in the Base «El Empecinado», taking into account the monthly count of people, the ages rank, and the percentage of sexes. Instruments: The records book of diary assistance is used and data are treated with the program Microsoft Excel. Results: Both demographic and nursing assistance data are taken into account, observing that the unit which contributes with a major number of people has a mean age of 27,53 years, the percentage of women is 15 %, the daily average number of assistance during the four years period is 3,07  and they are fundamentally dedicated to vaccination, vital constants surveillance and PAEF. Conclusion: In view of the major part of nursing staff assistance work is dedicated to prevention and promotion of health more than urgencies and emergencies, it would be important to take this data into account in the moment of nursing staff deployment in operation zones or as a support for other units (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zarzuela Regueiro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Se muestra un análisis descriptivo, retrospectivo y longitudinal de los registros obtenidos durante cuatro años (2003 a 2006, a. i.) de las asistencias y cuidados de enfermería en la Base Militar «El Empecinado», teniendo en cuenta la fuerza en revista media, el rango de edades y el porcentaje de personal por sexos. Instrumentos: Se utiliza un libro de registros de las asistencias diarias y se tratan los datos  mediante el programa Excel de Microsoft Office. Resultados: Se tienen en cuenta tanto los datos demográficos como los puramente asistenciales, observando que la unidad que aporta mayor número de personal tiene una edad media de 27,53 años, el porcentaje de mujeres es del 15 %, el número de asistencias de enfermería medio diario en el cuatrienio es de 3,07 dedicándose fundamentalmente a las variables  vacunas, toma de constantes y PAEF. Conclusión: A la vista de que la mayor parte del tiempo de trabajo asistencial del personal de enfermería está dedicado a labores de prevención y promoción de la salud más que al específico de urgencias y emergencias, sería importante tener estos datos en cuenta a la hora de desplegar a este personal a ZO (Zona de Operaciones) o para prestar apoyo a unidades con diferentes cargas de trabajo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;65(2): 79-82, abr.-jun. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87041</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las Asistencias de Enfermería en una Base</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28202^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6928^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9076^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8660^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
