<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87876</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contribution of the Faculty of Pharmacy of Santiago de Compostela to the development of the Spanish scientific research in the first third of the 20th century (1900-1936)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Faculty of Pharmacy of Santiago de Compostela was founded in 1857, but research activities did not start until the beginning of the 20th century. The new Spanish regulations promoting the experimentation at universities and the stages of professors and recently graduated students outside Spain contributed to generate a remarkable research group in a provincial university. The excessive university centralism at that time in Spain and the characteristics of the headquarters of the faculty &#151;a 16th century Renaissance palace&#151; hindered, in general, the research development. However, the scientific spirit of professors and students, and their work were imposed and they achieved an estimable status in pharmacy research in Galicia. The facilities were the staff's highest priority and it raised more than a protest. A remarkable investment in apparat uses and laboratory materials was carried out and researchers started to publish original research papers in local journals, such as the «Revista de farmacia», published by their own University.In the previous years to the Spanish Civil War (1936) the research status in drug development and the background of the staff and students were important, allowing them to join the military laboratory that Franco&#146;s army created at the faculty of pharmacy. The research work continued in a small scale and was specially focused on the production of «copy drugs» copying European specific drugs which were scarce at that time. The first third of the 20th century was the germ of the great research prestige that the Faculty of Pharmacy of Santiago de Compostela enjoys at present (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Landín, Mariana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brasa Arias, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanmartín Míguez, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Facultad de Farmacia de Santiago de Compostela se fundó en 1857, pero no fue hasta comienzos del siglo XX cuando comenzó a desarrollar una labor de investigación en medicamentos.Las nuevas reglamentaciones que fomentaban la experimentación en los laboratorios universitarios y la formación de profesores y recién licenciados en el extranjero, contribuyeron a generar un grupo investigador notable dentro de una Facultad de provincias. La excesiva centralización en materia universitaria de la época y las características de la sede de la Facultad &#151;un palacio renacentista del siglo XVI&#151; dificultaron, en general, el desarrollo de la investigación. Sin embargo, el espíritu científico de profesores y alumnos, y su trabajo se impusieron y lograron un estatus digno en investigación de medicamentos en Galicia. En estos años comenzaron a publicarse trabajos originales principalmente en la «Revista de Farmacia», publicada por la propia Universidad compostelana. En los años precedentes a la guerra civil española (1936) el nivel alcanzado en investigación y desarrollo de medicamentos era importante, favoreciendo el hecho de que, una vez comenzada la contienda, el personal de la Facultad trabajó en el laboratorio de farmacia militar en el que fue transformada por el ejército franquista. Durante este período la labor investigadora continuó, aunquea menor escala, y orientada a la obtención de «medicamentos copia» de otros específicos que escaseaban en tiempos de guerra. Durante el primer tercio del siglo XX se desarrolló el germen del prestigio investigador del que goza en la actualidad la Facultad de Farmacia compostelana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;62(1): 93-118, ene.-jun. 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contribución de la Facultad de Farmacia de Santiago de Compostela al desarrollo de la investigación científica española en el primer tercio del siglo XX (1900-1936)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9018^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9018^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
