<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055994</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">William Cheselden: singular lithotomist and great ilustrator of the XVIII</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a brief historic reference of who probably was the most famous English urologist-surgeon of the 18th century, and who, following the chronicle writers, holds the record for extraction of a bladder stone (between 24 and 54 seconds). He also was an example of humanism related to the medical profession: he was an extraordinary illustrator of his own books with the help of the &#147;dark chamber&#148;, so frequently used by Renaissance artists, contributed to the design and performance of civil architectonic work, had relationships    with the literature world through poetry, and decisively influenced the reformation and separation of barbers and surgeons, which ultimately lead to the creation    of the Royal College of Surgeons</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros Sampol, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta una breve referencia histórica del que fue, probablemente, el más famoso cirujano-urólogo    inglés del s. XVIII y que, según, los cronistas posee el &#147;record&#148; en la extracción de un cálculo vesical: entre 24 y 54 segundos, según las fuentes. Es, además, un ejemplo de humanismo tan frecuentemente relacionado con la profesión médica: fue un extraordinario ilustrador de sus propias obras ayudado de la &#147;cámara oscura&#148; tan utilizada por los artistas del Renacimiento, contribuyó    al diseño y realización de obra arquitectónica civil, se relacionó con el mundo literario a través de la poesía e influyó decisivamente, merced a sus influencias,en la reforma y separación entre &#147;barberos&#148; y &#147;cirujanos&#148; que ulteriormente concluyó en la creación del Royal College of Surgeons</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(7): 723-729, sept. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055994</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">William Cheselden, singular litotomista y gran ilustrador inglés del Siglo XVIII</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24010^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14972^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
