<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132390</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anthocyanins: potential for the prevention of neurodegenerative diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anthocyans are polyphenolic compounds widely distributed in nature, found both in food and in medicinal plants. They are responsible for the red-blue colors of different fruits, leaves, roots or bulbs. Many scientific studies have confirmed its healthy properties, mainly related to their anti-inflammatory and antioxidant activities. For these reasons, they could be proposed as agents for the prevention and treatment of neurodegenerative diseases. In the present paper, the latest scientific knowledge on the effects of these compounds on central nervous system functions has been reviewed. Despite what was thought until recently, several studies, both in animal and in humans, seem to confirm their ability to pass the blood-brain barrier (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carretero, M Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los antocianos son compuestos polifenólicos, de origen vegetal, ampliamente distribuidos en la naturaleza, tanto en plantas medicinales como en alimentos, responsables de los colores rojizos, azulados y violáceos de diferentes frutos, hojas, raíces o bulbos. Numerosos estudios científicos han constatado sus propiedades saludables, principalmente relacionadas con sus actividades antiinflamatorias y antioxidantes. En base a ello han sido propuestos como candidatos para la prevención y tratamiento de enfermedades neurodegenerativas. En este artículo se revisan los últimos conocimientos científicos publicados sobre sus efectos beneficiosos sobre las funciones del SNC. Es interesante señalar que dichos estudios parecen confirmar, tanto en animales como en el hombre, su capacidad de atravesar la barrera hematoencefálica, cuestionada hasta hace poco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;14(2): 101-113, dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132390</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antocianos: su potencial en la prevención de enfermedades neurodegenerativas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d906^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d887^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d887^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d887^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54550^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d887^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
