<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79782</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of the EFQM Red Threads in the Health Public Health System</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyse the use of transversal axes (TA) of the EFQM Model in the self- assessment of the service organisations in an Autonomous Community and to describe the self assessment results for the health care system (HCS) as a whole. Material and methods: Descriptive study divided in two phases: 1) evaluation of the use of the EFQM model in the HCS, and 2) analysis of the methodology using TA. All (37) of the self-assessment reports corresponding to Primary Care and Hospitals in 2007 were analysed. A quantitative analysis was performed on the strengths (S) and areas of improvement (AI) identified, stratifying them according to level of care, centre and EFQM criteria and TA. Results: The use of the EFQM in the HCS reaches 84% of the organizations (32/37), and 94% deploy improvement plans (30/32). A total of 3543 S and 3573 AI were described for the HCS as a whole. From the total identified S, enablers reach 67.66%. Results: Results according to TA the organization management axes are the dominant ones: people, clients, process and communication. Results: Application difficulties derive from the organizations&#146; leadership in quality management, the training strategies for deployment, the innovation character of the model in certain settings and the potential workload generated. Conclusions: TA are perceived as a feasible work method to gather and synthesize AI. However it requires appropriate training to optimize its use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Morón-Merchante, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo-Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo-Martínez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alguacil-Pau, AI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Royo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrándiz-Santos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la utilización de los ejes transversales (EETT) del modelo EFQM en la autoevaluación de las organizaciones de servicios en una comunidad autónoma, y describir el resultado de la autoevaluación para el conjunto del sistema sanitario público (SSP). Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo en dos etapas: 1) evaluación del uso del modelo EFQM en el SSP, y 2) análisis de la metodología de trabajo mediante EETT. En la primera fase se analizó el 100% de los informes de autoevaluación (37 gerencias) de Atención Primaria (AP) y Especializada (AE) (2007). Se realizó un análisis cuantitativo de la distribución de puntos fuertes (PF) y áreas de mejora (AM), según nivel asistencial, centro sanitario y su agrupación en criterios y EETT del Modelo. Resultados: La utilización del modelo EFQM en el conjunto del SSP alcanza el 84% de las gerencias (32/37) y el 94% despliegan planes de mejora (30/32). Se describen 3.543 PF y 3.573 AM, para el SSP. Del total de PF, los criterios agentes suponen un 67,6%.ResultadosLos resultados por EETT resaltan la dominancia de los ejes de gestión de la organización, personas, clientes, proceso y comunicación. Resultados: Las dificultades para su aplicación derivan del liderazgo de la organización en gestión de la calidad, de las estrategias formativas para su despliegue, del carácter novedoso que supone la herramienta en determinados entornos, y de la potencial carga de trabajo generada. Conclusiones: Los EETT se perciben como un método de trabajo factible para la agrupación y síntesis de las AM, precisando una formación adecuada para optimizar su utilización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;25(3): 120-128, mayo-jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79782</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de los ejes transversales del modelo EFQM en el ámbito sanitario público</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
