<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147759</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Could the moderate consumption of beer be included within a healthy diet?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Beer is a beverage that has been usually included in our habitual diet from immemorial time. However, beer consumption depends on food habits and lifestyle in different populations. In Mediterranean countries, fermented beverages like beer, takes up a key space in the Mediterranean diet that has been declared in 2010 as Cultural Immaterial World Heritage by UNESCO. Objectives: The positioning where the Spanish Society of Primary Care Medicine and the Beer and Health Information Centre have conjointly worked on has the following beer consumption-related aims: a) to update its knowledge based on the scientific evidence; b) to evaluate the possibility to include it within a healthy diet for healthy adults; c) to inform health professionals and the general population about its possible health benefits. Methodology: A panel of experts, represented by clinicians and researchers in the field of nutrition held a meeting with the purpose to review the scientific literature related to the effects of the moderate consumption of fermented beverages, particularly beer, and to reach a consensus on the results, conclusions and recommendations suggested and established by other experts at an international level. Results: The current scientific evidence reflects that moderate consumption of beer does not affect anthropometry related variables. Although energy supply from beer is very low, its nutrients and bioactive compound contents are interesting, since its potential antioxidant effect together with the fact that anti-carcinogenic, anti-inflammatory and anti-viral effects have been demonstrated, as well as its beneficial effect on cardiovascular health, leading to a greater protection than even in the abstemious population. Conclusions: In view of the results obtained from the literature consulted by the expert panel, we can conclude that the moderate consumption of beer can be considered within a healthy diet. Nevertheless, the general recommendation is addressed only to healthy adults, never to children, adolescents or pregnant women. In the case of elderly people, any beverage containing alcohol should not be recommended for those who are treated with drugs in order to avoid possible interactions with alcohol consumption (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Fuster, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Díaz-Ufano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La cerveza es una bebida que lleva formando parte de nuestra vida habitual desde tiempos inmemoriales. Sin embargo, su consumo depende de los hábitos alimentarios y del estilo de vida de las distintas poblaciones. En los países europeos situados en la cuenca mediterránea, las bebidas fermentadas como la cerveza ocupan un lugar clave en la dieta mediterránea, declarada en 2010 como Patrimonio Cultural Inmaterial de la Humanidad por la UNESCO. Objetivos: El posicionamiento en el que colaboran de forma conjunta un grupo de expertos de la Sociedad Española de Médicos de Atención Primaria (SEMERGEN) y el Centro de Información Cerveza y Salud (CICS) tiene como objetivos, en relación con el consumo moderado de cerveza: a) actualizar el conocimiento basado en la evidencia científica; b) valorar la posibilidad de incluirlo dentro de una alimentación saludable para adultos sanos; c) informar sobre sus posibles beneficios a los profesionales de la salud y a la población en general. Metodología: Un panel de expertos, representado por clínicos e investigadores en el campo de la nutrición, se reunió para revisar la literatura científica relacionada con los efectos del consumo moderado de bebidas fermentadas, en particular de la cerveza, y consensuar resultados, conclusiones y recomendaciones emitidas por distintos autores en el ámbito internacional. Resultados: La evidencia científica actual refleja que el consumo moderado de cerveza no modifica los parámetros relacionados con la antropometría, tanto los pliegues cutáneos como el peso se mantienen. Su aporte energético es bajo, aunque el contenido en nutrientes y compuestos bioactivos es muy interesante, ya que se ha demostrado su potencial efecto antioxidante, anticarcinogénico, antiinflamatorio y antiviral, así como su efecto beneficioso sobre la salud cardiovascular, obteniéndose con ingestas moderadas una protección mayor que en población abstemia. Conclusiones: A la vista de los resultados obtenidos tras la consulta bibliográfica realizada por el panel de expertos, se puede concluir que el consumo moderado de cerveza puede considerarse como parte de una alimentación saludable. No obstante, el consumo moderado de cerveza tradicional está contemplado en adultos sanos, nunca en menores de edad, mujeres gestantes o personas mayores con medicación susceptible de interaccionar con la ingesta de alcohol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);41(supl.1): 1-12, mayo 2015. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147759</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿El consumo moderado de cerveza podría incluirse dentro e una alimentación saludable?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1534</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1534^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
