<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121960</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The legitimization of psychiatric semeiology and its conjunction with the concepts of &#147;normal&#148; and &#147;pathological&#148;: a vision during the Age of Revolution (18th-19th centuries)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper will address an essential question: What is it that will give validity and legitimacy to the psychiatric semeiology? To answer this, initially we analyze the characteristics, rules and some of the issues for configuring semiological signs and clinical elements; next we take a look to what is understood by &#147;normality&#148; from the perspectiveof Georges Canguilehm. We then examinethe history, and the philosophical and medical psychiatric origins of semeiology during what is called the Age of Revolution. To continue, we leave the psychiatric field in order to take a glance of the field of rhetoric and oratory, and the categorizing and normalizing function of certain clinical signs related to language; then we come back to psychiatry and discuss how Michel Foucault conceivedin an original way symptomatology and semeiology as a result of the concept of &#147;instinct&#148;, the voluntary-involuntary axis and the influence of neurology in the mid 19th century. Finally, we analyze how the statistics and the eugenics played also an important role in the conceptualization of the norm and therefore the scientific discourse behind the established clinical signs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Enrique Londoño, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo tratará una pregunta esencial: ¿Qué es lo que le va dar validez y legitimidad dentro del ámbito psiquiátrico a la semiología? Para responder, inicialmente se analizan las características,las reglas y algunas de las problemáticas para la configuración de signos como elementos semiológicos y clínicos; enseguida se da una mirada a lo que se entiende por normalidad desde la perspectiva de Georges Canguilehm. Se examinará entonces la historia y los orígenes filosóficos y médico-psiquiátricos de la semiología en lo que se llamó la Era de la revolución. Se sale de la esfera psiquiátrica para tocarel ámbito de la retórica y la oratoria, y su función normalizadora y categorizadora de ciertos signos clínicos relativos al lenguaje, para regresar a la psiquiatría y analizar cómo Michel Foucault de una manera original concibió la sintomatología y la semiología a partir del concepto de &#147;instinto&#148;, el eje voluntario involuntario, y la influencia de la neurología en la mitad del siglo XIX. Finalmente, se ve como la estadística y la eugenesia jugarán un papel igualmente importante en la conceptualización de la norma y por ende del discurso científico detrás de los signos clínicos establecidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;34(122): 337-351, abr.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La legitimización de la semiología psiquiátrica y su conjunción con los conceptos de &#147;normal&#148; y &#147;patológico&#148;: una visión en la Era de la revolución (siglos XVIII-XIX)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7496</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5149^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54306^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54306^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10878^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38882</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1546^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27466^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
