<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84258</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life after deep venous thrombosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Little is known about the impact of the posthrombotic syndrome (PTS) on thequality of life (QoL) of patients after deep vein thrombosis (DVT).Objective. The aims of this study were to analyze the long-term QoL after DVT and to examinewhether QoL correlates with the severity of PTS.Material and methods. Patients with previous symptomatic, unilateral, and a fi rst episode ofDVT were enrolled in this study. After 5 years of follow-up, the venous disease was related topathological severity of PTS according to the scale of Villalta. All patients then completed ageneric (EuroQol) and a disease-specifi c one for venous insuffi ciency (CIVIQ) questionnaires. Theanalysis of results was blinded to clinical details of the patients.Results. Of the 165 patients initially recruited, 100 patients completed the follow-up andcompleted the QoL assessment at 5 years. Despite the regular use of compression stockings theincidence of PTS was 65 %: 35 asymptomatic, 41 with moderate-PTS, and 24 with severe-PTS.The mean QoL with the EuroQol and the CIVIQ was 91.5 % and 89.46 % in absent-PTS; 85.9 % and74.43 % in moderate-PTS; and 58.2 % and 49.82 % in severe-PTS, respectively. The EuroQol onlyshowed signifi cant differences when the PTS was severe, while the CIVIQ was useful to detectdifferences among the different subgroups. These scores worsened signifi cantly with increasingseverity of PTS (r = 0.601).Conclusions. Patients with DVT in whom PTS develops have a worse QoL than those without PTS.Patient-based QoL measures correlated well with the severity of PTS(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mengibar Fuente, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Pedrosa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almaraz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvador Calvo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Fajardo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Poco se conoce sobre el impacto del síndrome postrombótico (SPT) en la calidadde vida (CV) de los pacientes.Objetivos. Evaluar la CV a largo plazo en pacientes con trombosis venosa profunda (TVP) de losmiembros inferiores y examinar si ésta se correlaciona con el nivel de gravedad del SPT.Material y métodos. Todos los pacientes incluidos fueron consecutivos, con síntomas unilateralesy primer episodio de TVP. Tras 5 años de seguimiento, el grado de secuela postrombótica fuevalorado mediante la escala de Villalta. Al fi nalizar todos realizaron un cuestionario genérico(EuroQol) y otro específi co de insufi ciencia venosa (CIVIQ). Los resultados fueron analizados demanera ciega.Resultados. De 165 pacientes inicialmente reclutados, tan sólo 100 completaron el seguimientode 5 años y cumplimentaron los cuestionarios. A pesar del uso regular de medias elásticas (75 %),la incidencia de SPT fue del 65 %: 35 pacientes asintomáticos, 41 pacientes con SPT moderado y24 pacientes con SPT grave. La CV media con el EuroQol y el CIVIQ fue, respectivamente, de91,5 % y 89,46 % en SPT ausente; 85,9 % y 74,43 % en SPT moderado; 58,2 % y 49,82 % en SPT grave.El EuroQol tan sólo mostró diferencias signifi cativas cuando el SPT fue grave, mientras queel CIVIQ se reveló muy útil para detectar diferencias entre los distintos subgrupos, mostrando undeterioro progresivo en relación con el nivel de gravedad del SPT (r = 0,601).Conclusiones. Los pacientes con TVP que desarrollan SPT presentan un importante deterioro dela CV, tanto peor cuanto más grave sea la secuela postrombótica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;62(4): 140-145, jul.-ago. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84258</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la calidad de vida en pacientes con síndrome postrombótico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52619^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
