<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136498</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Safety in the diagnosis and treatment of inflammatory bowel disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The presentations at Digestive Disease Week 2013 emphasized treatment safety. Anti-tumor necrosis factor (TNF) agents and thiopurines are reasonably safe in breastfeeding and pregnancy. Several studies indicate that controlling the risk of tuberculosis when anti-TNF agents are planned presents several problems, both in the initial diagnosis of latent tuberculosis and in subsequent patient follow-up, given that cases of tuberculosis continue to occur, despite recommendations. Thiopurines increase the risk of lymphoma, but there is no residual risk when these drugs are withdrawn. Despite increasing knowledge of the risks and recommendations on how to avoid them, there remain considerable shortfalls in the application of preventive measures and, more specifically, in vaccinations. Infliximab and cyclosporin produce similar results when used to treat severe outbreaks of ulcerative colitis. Thromboembolism prevention continues to be deficient, and the barriers to effective prevention concern not only physicians but can also involve nursing staff, for example. There is still a wide margin for improvement in safety. New drugs under study (vedolizumab, golimumab) have not shown any hitherto unknown signs of significant toxicity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gomollón, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las comunicaciones presentadas en la Digestive Disease Week 2013 han hecho especial énfasis sobre la seguridad de los tratamientos. Se confirma que los anti-TNF (antifactor de crecimiento tumoral) y las tiopurinas son razonablemente seguros en la lactancia y el embarazo. En varios estudios se señala que el control del riesgo de tuberculosis cuando se van a emplear anti-TNF presenta varios problemas, tanto en lo referente al diagnóstico inicial de la tuberculosis latente como en el seguimiento posterior de los pacientes, puesto que, a pesar de las recomendaciones, se siguen produciendo algunos casos. Las tiopurinas aumentan el riesgo de linfoma, pero no suponen un riesgo residual cuando se retiran. A pesar de un conocimiento cada vez mayor de los riesgos y de las recomendaciones para evitarlos, todavía se detectan lagunas considerables en la aplicación de las medidas preventivas y más concretamente de las vacunaciones. El infliximab y la ciclosporina muestran riesgos similares cuando se utilizan en el tratamiento del brote grave de colitis ulcerosa. La prevención de la tromboembolia sigue siendo deficiente en muchas áreas, y las barreras no son estrictamente médicas, sino que pueden afectar también a enfermería, por ejemplo. El margen de mejora en seguridad es todavía amplio. Los nuevos fármacos en estudio (vedolizumab, golimumab) no han mostrado señales de toxicidades relevantes previamente no conocidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;36(supl.2): 15-20, oct. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136498</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad en el diagnóstico y tratamiento de la enfermedad inflamatoria intestinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
