<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142550</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of classical oral glucose-lowering medications in current treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Classical oral glucose were discovered in the mid twentieth century. Despite the time elapsed since then and the lack of large studies to support the use of some of these drugs, they continue to be employed, are indicated in all clinical practice guidelines and consensus documents and, overall, remain among the most widely prescribed drugs in the national health system. The main arguments for their continued use are their widespread and prolonged prescription, their effectiveness, and cost. Their main disadvantages have always beenand continue to betheir adverse gastrointestinal effects, weight gain, the risk of hypoglycemia and other adverse effects, which have encouraged the development of new glucose-lowering drugs with an improved pharmacological profile that would cover the various mechanisms of hyperglycemia. Currently, deep knowledge of glucose-lowering drugs is required in the patient-centered management of diabetes. Furthermore, this knowledge should be adapted to each individual patient to acquire the experience necessary to achieve effective metabolic control, delay the development of chronic complications, and improve the quality of life and life expectancy of patients with diabetes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carramiñana Barrera, F. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A pesar del tiempo trascurrido desde su descubrimiento, a mediados del siglo pasado, de estar inmersos de pleno en la segunda década del siglo XXI, de que algunos no tengan grandes estudios propios que avalen suficientemente su evidencia, los hipoglucemiantes orales clásicos siguen manteniendo su vigencia, aparecen indicados en todas las guías y consensos y, globalmente, continúan en los primeros puestos de prescripción en el Sistema Nacional de Salud. Los principales argumentos para mantener el uso actual son el amplio y prolongado uso, la eficacia y el coste, mientras que sus principales inconvenientes siempre han sido y son los efectos gastrointestinales, la ganancia ponderal, el riesgo de hipoglucemia u otros efectos secundarios, motivos que han promovido el desarrollo de nuevos hipoglucemiantes que mejorasen el perfil farmacológico y cubriesen los diferentes mecanismos de la hiperglucemia. Actualmente, en el manejo centrado del paciente con diabetes resulta necesario tener un conocimiento profundo de los hipoglucemiantes y aplicarlo a las peculiaridades de cada individuo para adquirir la experiencia necesaria que logre un control metabólico efectivo, retrasar las complicaciones crónicas y el objetivo final de mejora en la calidad y expectativa de vida del paciente con diabetes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);40(supl.2): 9-15, jul. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142550</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de los hipoglucemiantes orales clásicos en el tratamiento actual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55659^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d286</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13841^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38089^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8862^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
