<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125480</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic accompainment: practice and clinic in a psychiatric hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article one case is going to be addressed from the theory, technique and practice of the Therapeutic Accompaniment. The program has been established within a plant of long stay of a psychiatric hospital, inside a more wide strategy of multidisciplinary work. The target population of the program are patients with a severe chronic mentally illness, particularly with psychotic and affective disorders. In the Case M the work has been made in coordination with he family in order to be able to return the autonomy and be discharged from the hospital. After a year of Therapeutic Accompaniments an improvement can be appreciated at functional and social levels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosique, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Vega, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Partiendo de la teoría, técnica y práctica del Acompañamiento Terapéutico en el presente artículo se va a abordar un caso de la planta de larga estancia de un hospital psiquiátrico. Allí se instaura, dentro de una estrategia más amplia de trabajo multidisciplinar y psicosocial, un programa de Acompañamientos para pacientes con trastorno mental grave, concretamente para trastornos psicóticos y afectivos. En el Caso M se trabaja en coordinación con su familia con el objetivo último de que pueda retomar su autonomía y ser dada el alta. Tras un año de Acompañamiento Terapéutico se aprecia una pronunciada mejoría, tanto a nivel funcional como social (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;34(123): 583-587, jul.-sept. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acompañamiento terapéutico: práctica y clínica en un hospital psiquiátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10548</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6934</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
