<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89762</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience with posterior interosseous flaps: a cases series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To describe 10 patients treated for traumatic wounds or scar tissue retraction with reversed pedicled posterior interosseous flaps. Material and methods. Ten consecutive patients, operated on for wound coverage between March 2007 and April 2010, were retrospectively reviewed in terms of demographic factors, etiology, wound location, flap dimensions, final outcome, and complications. Results. One patient was excluded due to anatomical variations. From the remaining nine patients, full flap survival was achieved in seven; partial survival (10% flap loss at the distal end opposite to the pedicle) was achieved in two. Slight to moderate venous congestion was observed in the three first patients of this series, but this did not affect the final outcome. Discussion. It is our preference to avoid the use of free flaps in order to decrease the operation time and to avoid complications related to the anastomosis technique. The addition of a large subcutaneous vein dissected with subcutaneous tissue, which we started in the fourth case, solved the problems related to edemas and venous congestion. Split thickness skin grafts on the donor area can lead to aesthetic complaints. Conclusion. Posterior interosseous flap was shown to be a reliable and effective alternative for wound coverage within the range of its pedicle, unless there are anatomical variations, which is not common (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanmartín-Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Couceiro-Otero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melo-Pabón, J. N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Se describen diez pacientes intervenidos para coberturas de heridas traumáticas y retracciones cicatriciales las cuales se realizaron con un colgajo interóseo posterior. Material y método. Diez pacientes consecutivos, que fueron programados para coberturas de heridas entre marzo de 2007 y abril de 2010, se revisaron retrospectivamente en cuanto a factores demográficos, etiología, localización de las heridas, dimensiones del colgajo, resultado final y complicaciones. Resultados. Se descartó un paciente por encontrarse variaciones anatómicas. De los nueve restantes, la supervivencia fue total en siete y parcial (pérdida del 10% de la extremidad opuesta al pedículo) en dos. En los tres primeros casos de la serie se apreció una congestión venosa leve a moderada que no comprometió el resultado final. Discusión. Es nuestra preferencia prescindir del uso de colgajos libres para disminuir el tiempo de intervención y evitar complicaciones derivadas de la realización de anastomosis. La incorporación de una vena subcutánea de gran calibre disecada con tejido subcutáneo realizada a partir del cuarto caso solucionó los problemas de edemas por congestión venosa. El injerto de piel parcial en la zona donante puede llevar a quejas estéticas. Conclusión. El colgajo interóseo posterior demostró ser una alternativa fiable y efectiva para cobertura de heridas que se localicen en el rango de alcance de su pedículo, a menos que se encuentren variaciones anatómicas, lo cual ocurre en pocos casos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);55(4): 248-256, jul.-ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia con el colgajo interóseo posterior: serie de casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6382^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6378^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
