<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049578</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of the nursing process in primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: In recent years, primary care nurses have acquired grea ter responsibility in providing health services, becoming authentic nursing care managers. This new integral concept of care has been aided by the use of the nursing process. The present study aims to describe the implantation and development of the nursing process in a primary care area in the Autonomous Community of Madrid. Methods: We performed a longitudinal descriptive study to analyze the strategies employed to introduce utilization of the nursing process and to evaluate the key indicators defined to monitor nursing care in 42 primary care teams of Area 11 in Madrid between 2001 and 2004. Results: The number of nurses using the nursing process and nursing diagnoses increased by 167%. The frequency of nursing diagnoses made since 2001 was 50,815. The indicator of overall quality showed a continuous increase since 2001 and was 90.5% in 2004. In the last two years of the study, the indicator of resolution of nursing diagnosis was achieved in approximately 75% of the problems attended. The synthetic indicator of nursing care increased by 350%. Conclusions: Primary care nurses in Area 11 of Madrid have integrated the nursing process as a working methodology into their clinical practice, thus contributing to the organization's model of excellence through their specific discipline and integrating the nursing care of the population as a key process in the organization</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santamaría García, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Ramos, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil de Pareja Palmero, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Rivas, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochandorena Juanena, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beamud Lagos, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Las enfermeras de atención primaria (AP) han adquirido en los últimos años una mayor responsabilidad en la provisión de servicios sanitarios, y se han convertido en auténticos gestores de cuidados. La utilización de la metodología de enfermería ha facilitado esta nueva concepción integral de la atención. El objetivo de este estudio es dar a conocer la experiencia de implantación y desarrollo de la metodología de enfermería en un área sanitaria de AP de la Comunidad de Madrid. Métodos: Estudio descriptivo longitudinal, realizado en los 42 equipos de AP del Área 11 de Madrid, acerca de las estrategias de implantación de la metodología y la evaluación de los indicadores clave definidos para la monitorización del proceso del cuidado en el período 2001-2004. Resultados: El número de enfermeras que utiliza la metodología y los diagnósticos de enfermería ha aumentado un 167%. La frecuencia de diagnósticos de enfermería identificados desde el año 2001 ha sido de 50.815. El indicador de calidad global mantiene desde el año 2001 un incremento continuado, y en 2004 se situó en el 90,5%. El indicador de capacidad de resolución se ha situado en los 2 últimos años en torno al 75% de los problemas atendidos. El ICE (indicador sintético de cuidados enfermeros) se ha incrementado un 350%. Conclusiones: Las enfermeras/os de AP del Área 11 de Madrid han integrado el proceso de atención de enfermería como metodología de trabajo en su práctica asistencial, participando del modelo de excelencia de la organización con su aportación disciplinar específica e integrando como proceso clave de la organización el cuidado de la población</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;21(5): 247-254, sep. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de la metodología enfermera en atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12072^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
