<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86338</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term changes in left ventricular function following intracoronary stem cell transplantation for acute myocardial infarction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Controversy surrounds the long-term effects of intracoronary bone marrow stem cell transplantation after ST-elevation acute myocardial infarction (STEAMI). We report on the long-term changes in left ventricular function observed in 29 patients with STEAMI who were treated using this technique. Cardiac magnetic resonance imaging was performed at baseline, 6 months after transplantation, and long-term follow-up (median 27 months, interquartile range 24&#150;35 months). The left ventricular ejection fraction had improved significantly by 6 months (from 47.6±8.9% to 52.7±11.6%; P=.001) and this improvement was maintained long-term, at 52.4±11.8% (P=.01 vs. baseline and P=.999 vs. 6 months). There was no significant change from baseline in end-diastolic or end-systolic ventricular volume. Our findings indicate the improvement in injection fraction occurs soon after stem cell transplantation, within the first 6 months, and remains unchanged at long-term follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Avilés, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Román, José Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnold, Román</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Pedro Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villa, Adolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Revilla, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinedo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El efecto a largo plazo del trasplante intracoronario de células madre de médula ósea tras un síndrome coronario agudo con elevación del ST (SCACEST) es controvertido. Exponemos la evolución a largo plazo de los parámetros relacionados con la función ventricular izquierda en 29 pacientes con SCACEST sometidos a esta técnica. Se realizó resonancia magnética cardiaca basal, al sexto mes y a largo plazo (27 [24-35] meses). La fracción de eyección del ventrículo izquierdo mejoró significativamente al sexto mes (47,6±8,9% frente a 52,7±11,6%; p=0,001), mejora que se mantuvo en el seguimiento a largo plazo (52,4±11,8%; p=0,01 frente a basal, y p=0,999 frente a sexto mes). No se produjeron cambios significativos en los parámetros basales de volumen telediastólico o telesistólico ventricular izquierdo. Nuestro análisis indica que la mejora de la fracción de eyección tras el trasplante celular ocurre tempranamente, dentro de los primeros 6 meses y no se modifica a largo plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(4): 334-337, abr. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86338</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución a largo plazo de la función ventricular tras la terapia celular intracoronaria en el infarto agudo de miocardio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29149^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29149^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13620^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6487^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6487^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32388</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
