<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143537</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Polydipsia, intermittent hyponatraemia and psychosis (PIP syndrome): A severe and possibly under-diagnosed clinical condition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Electrolyte disorders in schizophrenic patients can be caused either by osmotic dysregulation, intrinsic to disease itself, or by adverse effects associated with both typical and atypical antipsychotics. The so-called polydipsia-intermittent hyponatraemia-psychosis (PIP) syndrome is clinically characterized by confusional acute confusional symptoms, which are the pathophysiological translation of symptomatic hyponatraemia and water intoxication, and could compromise the patient&#146;s survival. Serum sodium serum levels must be corrected progressively in order to prevent the osmotic demyelination syndrome, which could cause permanent neurological deficits. The prevalence of PIP syndrome is usually underestimated, and there should be preventive measures such as avoiding antipsychotic polypharmacy; routinely determining the water intake patterns in chronic schizophrenic patients; routinely measuring the serum sodium levels &#151; particularly when treatment is adjusted or modified &#151;; and evaluating acute confusional symptoms associated with water toxicity and hyponatraemia when another medical condition is not the origin of the confusional state (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrión-Expósito, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hans-Chacón, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Doblado, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quirós-López, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presencia de alteraciones hidroelectrolíticas en pacientes esquizofrénicos puede derivarse tanto de trastornos en la regulación osmótica inherentes a la propia enfermedad como de efectos indeseables de los antipsicóticos (típicos y atípicos). El denominado síndrome polidipsia-hiponatremia intermitente-psicosis (PIP) cursa con clínica confusional aguda, que es la traducción fisiopatológica de la hiponatremia sintomática y la intoxicación hídrica, pudiendo comprometer la vida del enfermo. La corrección de los valores de Na debe hacerse progresivamente para evitar el llamado síndrome de desmielinización osmótica, que puede ocasionar secuelas neurológicas permanentes. Dado que la prevalencia del síndrome PIP podría encontrarse infraestimada, la prevención debe realizarse evitando la polifarmacia antipsicótica, explorando sistemáticamente los patrones de ingesta de agua en los pacientes con esquizofrenia crónica, determinando periódicamente la natremia (sobre todo ante cambios de tratamiento) y dando valor diagnóstico a los síntomas confusionales como resultado de la intoxicación hídrica y la hiponatremia en ausencia de otra condición médica que los justifique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);19(supl.1): 68-71, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143537</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Polidipsia, hiponatremia intermitente y psicosis (síndrome PIP): una condición clínica grave y posiblemente infradiagnosticada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54544^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7189^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
