<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048205</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate whether the concomitant administrationof ibuprofen or indomethacin plus amikacin may alter the latterdrug's pharmacokinetic parameters, and hence amikacin plasmalevels.Method: Retrospective cohort study performed by reviewingthe medical records of premature children with persistent ductusarteriosus receiving amikacin and ibuprofen, or amikacin andindomethacin. They were divided up into three groups: group 1:treatment with amikacin went before indomethacin or ibuprofen;group 2: simultaneously treated with amikacin and indomethacin;group 3: simultaneously treated with amikacin and ibuprofen.Pharmacokinetic parameters, distribution volume, and amikacinclearance were measured using the PKS program (a non-linearregression method). Half life was determined from previous parameters.Results: Twenty-eight patients were included. No statisticallysignificant differences were found among pharmacokinetic parameterscorresponding to each study group.Conclusions: Further studies are needed with a greater numberof patients and currently recommended doses to assess theinfluence of indomethacin and ibuprofen in the pharmacokineticsof amikacin in premature children with persistent ductus arteriosus</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poveda Andrés,  J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta Grueso, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morcillo Sopena, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peris Ribera,  J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno Navarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marqués Miñana, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar si la administración concomitante de ibuprofenoo indometacina puede alterar los parámetros farmacocinéticosde amikacina y, por lo tanto, los niveles plasmáticos de lamisma.Método: Estudio de cohortes retrospectivo mediante revisiónde historias clínicas correspondientes a niños prematuros con ductusarterioso persistente tratados con amikacina e ibuprofeno, obien amikacina e indometacina. Se ditribuyen en tres grupos: grupo1: el tratamiento con amikacina fue previo a la administraciónde indometacina o ibuprofeno; grupo 2: tratados simultáneamentecon amikacina e indometacina; grupo 3: tratados simultáneamenteamikacina e ibuprofeno. Los parámetros farmacocinéticos,volumen de distribución y aclaramiento de amikacina se determinaronmediante el programa PKS (método de regresión no lineal).La semivida se determinó a partir de los parámetros anteriores.Resultados: Se incluyen 28 pacientes. No se hallan diferenciasestadísticamente significativas entre los parámetros farmacocinéticoscorrespondientes a cada grupo del estudio.Conclusiones: Serían necesarios estudios con mayor númerode pacientes y con las dosis recomendadas actualmente, en losque se evalúe la influencia de indometacina e ibuprofeno en la farmacocinéticade amikacina en niños prematuros con ductus arteriosopersistente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;30(3): 149-153, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048205</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la administración concomitante de indometacina o ibuprofeno en la farmacocinética de amikacina en neonatos prematuros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23152^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23152^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4435^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28146^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28145^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
