<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053616</identifier>
<setSpec>0303-8874</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cutaneous melanoma of the head and neck</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The clinical records of 20 patients with the diagnosis of cutaneous melanoma of the head and neck treated between 1991 and 2005 were retrospectively reviewed. Advances in diagnostic techniques and treatment have had obvious impact on outcomes in cutaneous melanoma. Cutaneous melanoma of the head of neck is treated with complete surgical resection in early stage disease. Resection margins are determined by the size and depth. Evaluation for regional and distant metastatic disease is necessary in advanced stage disease. Adjuvant therapy may be indicated in regional nodal disease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tapia Risueño, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouso Montero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Villares, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pomar Blanco, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Román Carbajo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pello, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se realiza una revisión retrospectiva de 20 pacientes diagnosticados de melanomas cutáneos de cabeza y cuello tratados entre 1991 y 2005. Los avances en las técnicas diagnósticas y en el tratamiento han tenido un impacto obvio en los resultados de los melanomas cutáneos. En estadios tempranos se realiza una resección quirúrgica completa. Los márgenes de resección están determinados por la extensión superficial y en profundidad. Cuando la enfermedad se diagnostica en un estadio avanzado es necesario el estudio de las metástasis regionales y a distancia. El tratamiento complementario podría estar indicado cuando existe afectación regional</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Otorrinolaringol Ibero Am;34(2): 151-162, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Melanomas cutáneos de cabeza y cuello</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8714^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
