<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134936</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiomodifying effect of organic grape juice supplementation on hematological parameters and organ weight in whole-body X-irradiation in rats</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is testing black grape juice as a radiomodifier against whole body X-irradiation using an animal model. Sixteen male Wistar rats were divided into four groups where two were irradiated by X-rays from a 200 kV machine specially designed to biological samples. Animals were fed ad libitum and drank voluntarily 2-10 ml a day of grape juice or placebo (isocaloric glucose and fructose solution) for one week before and two weeks after 6 Gy X-irradiation when they were sacrificed. Results have shown a significant liver weight loss in irradiated placebo group only while grape juice one has presented no losses. Hematological analysis showed typical abnormalities for ionizing radiation exposure, including early leucopenia and anemia. The intake of grape juice induced an increase in granulocyte percent count (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teixeira Rocha, JB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garzo,  E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marina, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauriz, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Da Costa Escobar Piccoli, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio, JP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manica da Cruz, IB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos de Andrade, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este estudio fue comprobar el efecto radiomodificador del mosto tinto de uva frente a irradiación de cuerpo entero con rayos X usando un modelo animal. Dieciséis ratas macho de raza Wistar fueron irradiadas mediante un aparato de 200 kV diseñado específicamente para muestras biológicas. Los animales fueron alimentados ad libitum y bebieron cada dia voluntariamente entre 2 y 10 ml de mosto de uva o placebo (solución isocalórica de glucosa y fructosa) durante una semana antes y dos semanas después de irradiación con rayos X a una dosis de 6 Gy, momento en que fueron sacrificadas. Los resultados mostraron una pérdida significativa de peso hepático en los animales irradiados tratados con placebo, mientras que los tratados con mosto presentaron valores similares a los controles no irradiados. El análisis hematológico presentó las anomalías típicas de la exposición a radiación ionizante, con disminución leucocitaria temprana y anemia. La ingestión de mosto de uva indujo un aumento del porcentaje de granulocitos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;24(3): 297-303, mayo-jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134936</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto radiomodificador de la suplementación con mosto de uva de cultivo ecológico sobre parámetros hematológicos y peso de órganos en ratas sometidas a irradiación de cuerpo entero con rayos X</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35969</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12271^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10107^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51396</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
