<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88011</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spontaneous internal carotid artery dissection: a diagnostic challenge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Extracranial internal carotid artery dissection is a rare occurrence with a difficult diagnosis that requires a high level of suspicion. We present the case study of a 55 year old male with migraines and partial Horner's syndrome in which a magnetic resonance angiography gave us a clear diagnosis. This technique offers good results and is currently replacing angiography. The patient was treated with acenocoumarol and then later with clopidogrel. Although, there are no randomised trials that support this action, this combination is the most used. The patient progressed favourably, as in the majority of cases. However, it is important to remember that some patients can suffer devastating consequences, such as cerebral infarction. Therefore it is important for primary care doctors to recognise this pathology in order to diagnose it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Henares García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La disección extracraneal de la arteria carótida interna es una entidad poco frecuente y de difícil diagnóstico que requiere un alto índice de sospecha. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 55 años con cefalea y síndrome de Horner incompleto, en el que la angiografía por resonancia magnética (angio-RM) nos dio el diagnóstico definitivo. Esta técnica obtiene muy buenos resultados y actualmente está desplazando a la angiografía. El paciente fue tratado con acenocumarol y posteriormente con clopidogrel, pues a pesar de la falta de ensayos clínicos que apoyen esta actuación, es la más extendida. Evolucionó favorablemente, como suele ocurrir en la mayoría de los casos, no obstante es importante recordar que en algunos pacientes puede originar consecuencias devastadoras, como un infarto cerebral, por tanto es importante que el médico de atención primaria conozca esta enfermedad para poder diagnosticarla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(4): 219-221, abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88011</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disección espontánea de la arteria carótida interna: un reto diagnóstico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34245^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34245^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32158^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32158^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32158^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2381^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2381^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34245^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2381^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34245^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
