<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161683</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of tuberculosis, human immunodeficiency virus, and hepatitis C VIRUS in homeless population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of tuberculosis, AIDS and Hepatitis C in a representative sample of homeless people in Girona, and set the connections with the main factors related to sociodemographic and health habit aspects. Methods: Transversal, observational and analytic study, CHI square, and multivariate regressive logistics. Results: There is a prevalence of tuberculosis infection of 40.2% and tuberculosis of 5.2%, both factors related to socioeconomic factors. The rate of VIH was 7.2% and VHC was 11.7%. Those people who had consumed drugs through parenteral ways were the ones with the highest infection risk of both VIH (p=0.002) and VHC (p&lt;0.001). Conclusions: Since the time of permanence on the street is not a main factor associated to the contagion of the analysed diseases, it is necessary to carry out an intense follow up and specific programmers to prevent the disease risk factors in homeless people (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo, Fran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giralt, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turró, Oriol</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo principal: Determinar la prevalencia de tuberculosis, Virus de la Inmunodeficiencia Humana y Virus de la Hepatitis C en una muestra representativa de personas sin-hogar de Girona y establecer relaciones con los principales factores sociodemográficos y hábitos de salud. Metodología: Estudio transversal, observacional y analítico, Chi cuadrado y regresiones logísticas multivariadas. Resultados principales: Se establece una prevalencia de infección tuberculosa del 40&#146;2% y de tuberculosis del 5,2%, relacionándose ambas con factores socioeconómicos. La tasa de VIH fue del 7,2% y del VHC del 11,7%, siendo las personas que se han consumido drogas por vía parenteral el principal factor de riesgo de infección tanto de VIH (p=0&#146;002) como de VHC (p&lt;0,001). Conclusión principal: No siendo el tiempo de permanencia en la calle el principal factor asociado al contagio de las enfermedades analizadas, se requiere de un seguimiento intenso y programas específicos para prevenir los factores de riesgo de enfermedad de las personas sin-hogar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;25(4): 248-252, oct.-dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161683</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tuberculosis, virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana y virus de la Hepatitis-C en población sin-hogar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33344^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19640^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
