<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134543</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screeners and brief assessment methods</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last two decades easy-to-use simple instruments have been developed and validated to assess specific aspects of the diet or a general profile that can be compared with a reference dietary pattern as the Mediterranean Diet or with the recommendations of the Dietary Guidelines. Brief instruments are rapid, simple and easy to use tools that can be implemented by unskilled personnel without specific training. These tools are useful both in clinical settings and in Primary Health Care or in the community as a tool for triage, as a screening tool to identify individuals or groups of people at risk who require further care or even they have been used in studies to investigate associations between specific aspects of the diet and health outcomes. They are also used in interventions focused on changing eating behaviors as a diagnostic tool, for self-evaluation purposes, or to provide tailored advice in web based interventions or mobile apps. There are some specific instruments for use in children, adults, elderly or specific population groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riobó Serván, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morán Fagúndez, Luis Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aranceta Bartrina, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Rodrigo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En las dos últimas décadas se han desarrollado y validado instrumentos sencillos que permiten valorar aspectos concretos de la ingesta dietética o bien un perfil general que puede compararse con patrones dietéticos de referencia como la Dieta Mediterránea o bien con las recomendaciones de las Guías Alimentarias. Son instrumentos rápidos, sencillos y fáciles de utilizar por personal no especializado sin necesidad de un entrenamiento específico. Estas herramientas son de utilidad tanto en el ámbito clínico como en Atención Primaria o en la comunidad como instrumento de triage, como herramienta de cribado con el fin de identificar individuos o grupos de población con riesgo que requieran mayor atención o incluso se han utilizado en estudios para investigar entre aspectos concretos de la dieta y resultados de salud. También se utilizan en intervenciones sobre cambio de conductas alimentarias como herramienta diagnóstica o de autoevaluación, o para facilitar consejo personalizado en intervenciones a través de páginas web o de aplicaciones móviles. Existen algunos instrumentos específicos para su utilización en niños, en adultos, en ancianos o en grupos específicos de población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(supl.3): 91-98, mar. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Métodos de cribado y métodos de evaluación rápida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4080^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4080^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4080^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16541</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
