<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111845</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioral types in relation to burnout, mobbing, personality, and adaptation of self-conduct in health care workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To define the different patterns of behavior among workers in health care in Ceuta. Design: Cross-sectional and descriptive. Sites and participants: 200 randomly selected workers in the Ceuta Health Care Area using a stratified sampling of workplace, job and sex. Measurements: The instruments used were the MBI, the LIPT by Leymann, a reduced version of the Pinillos CEP, Musitu self concept and adaptation behavior, all adapted in the context of occupational health examinations. Results: Principal components analysis allowed us to define 5 components, one strictly related to the scale of mobbing with 85% of weight; another for burnout with 70% weight; a third to adaptation and family satisfaction with a weight of 64%; a fourth with adaptation, control, emotional self, professional achievement and occupational self-weight of 52%; and a fifth component defined by social evaluations in the levels of extraversion and social adjustment with 73%. Conclusions: Highlights five different behavioral characteristics peculiar interest for clinical work are highlighted: burnout, mobbing, family work satisfaction; individual occupational and sociable satisfaction(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Fernández, Julián Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla Segura, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Padilla, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Fernández, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Definir la existencia de diferentes patrones de comportamiento en los trabajadores de atención a la salud en Ceuta. Diseño: Transversal y descriptivo. Emplazamientos y participantes: Doscientos trabajadores del área sanitaria de Ceuta seleccionados aleatoriamente mediante muestreo estratificado por centro de trabajo, puesto de trabajo y sexo. Mediciones principales: Los instrumentos utilizados fueron el MBI, el LIPT de Leymann, una versión reducida del C.E.P. de Pinillos, Autoconcepto de Musitu y Adaptación de conducta, todos adaptados, en el contexto de los exámenes de salud laborales. Resultados: El análisis de componentes principales permitió definir 5 componentes, uno estrictamente relacionado con la escala de acoso laboral con un 85% de peso; otro claramente con el desgaste profesional con un 70% de peso; un tercero con la adaptación y autoconcepto familiar con un peso de un 64%; un cuarto con la adaptación, control, autoconcepto emocional, logro profesional y autoconcepto laborales con peso del 52%; y un quinto componente definido por las valoraciones sociales en los niveles de extroversión y adaptación social con un 73%. Conclusiones: Se destacan 5 tipos comportamentales de características peculiares y de interés para la clínica laboral: quemado (desgaste profesional), acosado, satisfecho laboral familiar, satisfecho laboral individual y sociable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;45(4): 199-207, abr. 2013. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tipologías comportamentales en relación con el burnout, mobbing, personalidad, autoconcepto y adaptación de conducta en trabajadores sanitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10742^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
