<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158862</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spontaneous pneumothorax and delivery: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The onset of spontaneous pneumothorax during pregnancy is uncommon. However, due to the physiological changes of the respiratory system during pregnancy, any entity that causes an alteration in the ventilation, seriously affects both the pregnant woman and fetus. Pneumothorax should be excluded when presented with a pregnant woman with dyspnea and chest pain. We report the case of a multiparous woman with 39 weeks of amenorrhea who presented spontaneous pneumothorax. After admission to the ICU and placement of a pleural tube with a Heimlich valve, labour began. Epidural analgesia was used, and a healthy child was born after instrumental delivery. Postpartum had a normal evolution; Two days later, the Thoracic tube was removed and the mother referred for definitive surgical treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero Martínez, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Remesal Prieto, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Ferrón, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de un neumotórax espontáneo durante la gestación es infrecuente. Sin embargo, debido a los cambios fisiológicos del sistema respiratorio durante el embarazo, cualquier entidad que provoque una alteración en la ventilación afecta gravemente tanto a la gestante como al feto, por lo que ante una gestante que presente disnea y dolor torácico debería excluirse el diagnóstico de neumotórax. Se expone el caso de una mujer multípara con 39 semanas de amenorrea que presentó un neumotórax espontáneo; tras su ingreso en la UCI y la colocación de tubo pleural con válvula de Heimlich, se inicia trabajo de parto, con nacimiento de un niño sano tras parto instrumentado con analgesia epidural. Posparto de evolución normal; a los dos días se retira el tubo torácico y se remite para tratamiento quirúrgico definitivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;17(4): e1-e5, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158862</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumotórax espontáneo y parto: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11460^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
