<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97656</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Double J catheter migrated to the bladder and encrusted. Case report and bibliographic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: Urinary tract obstruction is one of the most prevalent diseases in urology. The handling of it includes conservative (analgesia and fluid therapy) and invasive (urinary diversion) measures. Ureteral stent is the method currently employed for urinary tract diversion. Complications of urinary tract stents maintenance have already been studied and are well known. We report a case of ureteral stent migrated to the bladder, calcified and embedded and we review the existing literature.                                   METHODS: A 28 year-old man with the diagnosis of ureteral stent coiled in bladder and calcified. The patient was successfully operated of suprapubic cystolithotomy.We conducted a Medline search using the terms &#147;ureteral stent &#147;+&#148; embedded stent, &#147;&#148; bladder ureteral stent, &#147;incrusted bladder stent&#148; and &#147;ureteral stent complicactions&#148;.      RESULTS: He is currently free of disease. We found a total of 45 articles that responded to the search criteria, from which we select the highest citation index.                                         CONCLUSIONS: The use of ureteral stents for urinary diversion of the upper urinary tract is safe and well tolerated but not without complications, that is why we have to raise awareness among patients of the need to undergo periodic inspections and instruct them to possible symptoms and / or signs that may indicate changes in position and / or state of the stent(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Persiva, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garau Perelló, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Mestre, Mateo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Povo Martin, Ivan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francia Valero, José Antonio de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosquet Sanz, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles Aguado, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno Argente, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: La obstrucción de vía urinaria es una de las patologías de mayor prevalencia en Urología. El manejo de la misma incluye medidas conservadoras (analgesia y fluidoterapia) e invasivas (derivación de vía urinaria). El método más empleado en la actualidad para derivar la vía es la utilización de catéter ureterales de tipo doble J. Las complicaciones del mantenimiento en vía urinaria de los stents doble J han sido ya estudiadas y son bien conocidas. Presentamos un caso clínico de un catéter doble J migrado a vejida, calcificado e incrustado y hacemos una revisión de la literatura existente.                                             MÉTODOS: Hombre de 28 años de edad al que se le diagnostica de catéter doble J enrollado en vejiga y calcificado. El paciente es intervenido de cistolitotomía suprapúbica satisfactoriamente. Realizamos una búsqueda bibliográfica en Medline mediante los términos &#147;ureteral stent&#148;+&#148;incrusted stent&#148;, &#147;bladder ureteral stent&#148;, &#147;bladder incrusted stent&#148; y &#147;ureteral stent complicactions&#148;        RESULTADOS: En la actualidad se encuentra libre de enfermedad. Encontramos un total de 45 artículos que respondieron a los criterios de búsqueda, de los que seleccionamos los de mayor índice de citación.               CONCLUSIONES: EL empleo de catéter doble J para derivar la vía urinaria es un método seguro y bien tolerado aunque no exento de complicaciones, es por ello por lo que hemos de concienciar a los pacientes de la necesidad de someterse a controles periódicos e instruirlos ante posibles síntomas y/o signos que puedan indicar alteraciones de la posición y/o estado del stent(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;65(2): 251-255, mar. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97656</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cateter doble J migrado e incrustado en vejiga. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1773^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23500^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29242^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
