<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75779</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A comparative study of the effect of applying polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon, 7,12-dimethyl-1,2-benzanthracene (DMBA), to the oral mucosa of hamsters and guinea-pigs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Oral squamous cell carcinoma is a malignantneoplasm with a bad prognosis and low survival rate.Tobacco and alcohol are among the most important causativefactors. In 1954, Salley described an experimental modelof carcinogenesis, applying the agent DMBA to the jugalmucosa of hamsters. Methods: we have developed two differentexperimental models based on the application ofDMBA to guinea pigs and hamsters. Results: No carcinogenesiswas seen in the guinea pigs at the administereddoses of DMBA, only areas of epithelial dysplasia, whichwere more severe in the animals that were also given alcohol.Malignant neoplasias developed in the hamsters andwere more numerous and more aggressive when DMBAwas administered together with ethanol. Conclusions: Inthe present study, ethanol acted as an enhancer of carcinogenesis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez García, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Jornet, Pía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Ortega, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Sánchez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El carcinoma oral de células escamosases una neoplasia maligna con mal pronóstico y baja tasa desupervivencia, en cuya etiología están fuertemente implicadosel tabaco y el alcohol, entre otros factores. En 1954,Salley describió un modelo experimental de carcinogénesisen la mucosa yugal del hámster mediante la aplicación delagente DMBA. Métodos: Hemos desarrollado dos modelosexperimentales diferenciados, basados en la aplicación delDMBA sobre cobayas y hámster respectivamente. Resultados:En el primer modelo (cobayas) no ocurrió el fenómenode la carcinogénesis con el tiempo y las dosis administradas.Solamente observamos áreas de displasia epitelial,que era más severa en los animales que, además del tratamientocon DMBA, ingerían etanol. En el segundo modelo(hámster), se desarrollaron neoplasias malignas, que eranmás numerosas y con un comportamiento biológico másagresivo cuando se administraba el DMBA combinado conel etanol. Conclusiones: El etanol se ha comportado comoagente promotor de la carcinogénesis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;42(4): 287-295, oct.-dic.2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75779</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de la aplicación del hidrocarburo aromático policíclico 7, 12-dimetil-1, 2-benzatraceno (DMBA) sobre la mucosa oral del hámster y del cobaya</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4173^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6320^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4173^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4173^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11518^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11518^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11518^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11518^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9255^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11518^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
