<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88203</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of processes and pathologies dealt with by the prehospital emergency medical services in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study was carried out by contacting 26 MedicalEmergency Services (MES), through survey,with final data obtained from 22. Population covered:42,538,730. Total number of calls: 7,656,768, with711,228 interventions. Number of operational forces:intensive care units (mobile-ICUs): 329, rapid interventionvehicles (RIV) 20, health ambulances 39 andmedical helicopters 39 (5 of them 24 hour: Canary andBalearic Islands and Castille-La Mancha) and 3 airplanes.Interventions: mobile-ICUs: 94.3%, medical helicopters:1.4% and health ambulances: 4.3%. Numberof A&amp;E doctors/day: 388, nursing personnel 427. Pathologiesdealt with, grouped according to ICE-9-MC:V-psychiatry group: 3.7%, VI-neurological group: 2.7%,VII-cardiovascular group: 9.3%, VIII-respiratory group:3.2%, XVII-lesions poisonings group: 23.1%, IX-digestivegroup: 1.3%, X-XI-genital-urinary and gynaecologyobstetricsgroups: 1.4%, XVI-group of other ill-definedpathologies: 40.1%. Specifically studied groups (fromthe MESs that provided them) were: thoracic paindyspnea:3.7%, ictus/acute cerebrovascular accident:0.9%, alteration in consciousness: 7.7%, syncope-blackout:2.5%, self-inflicted lesions: 2,654 (0.4%). Total ofpathological and syndrome groups: 59.9% and total ofother ill-defined pathologies: 40.1%. Of the pathologiesconsidered to be of greater relevance in A&amp;E: acutecoronary syndrome: 3.1%, arrhythmias: 3.2%, cardiacarrest: 1.7%, respiratory stoppage: 0.16%, total traumatisms:34.9%, traumatisms: 1.16%, cranioencephalictraumatism: 1.77%, intoxications: 5.1%, aggressions:6.9%, burns: 0.26%(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Senosiáin, M. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burusco, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio se ha realizado contactando con 26Servicios de Emergencia Médica (SEMEx), vía encuestatabulada, obteniendo datos finales de 22. La poblaciónde cobertura atendida: 42.538.730 habitantes. El númerototal de llamadas: 7.656.768, con 711.228 intervenciones.El número de dispositivos operativos al día: unidadde vigilancia intensiva (UVI-móviles): 329, vehículos deintervención rápida (VIR) 20, ambulancias sanitarias39 y helicópteros medicalizados 39 (5 de ellos 24 horas:Islas Canarias y Baleares, y Castilla-LaMancha) y 3aviones. Intervenciones: UVI-móvil: 94,3%, helicópterosmedicalizados: 1,4% y ambulancias sanitarias: 4,3%. Elnúmero de médicos de emergencias/día: 388, personalenfermería 427. Las patologías atendidas, agrupadassegún clasificación CIE-9-MC: grupo V-psiquiatría: 3,7%,grupo VI-neurológico: 2,7%, grupo VII-cardiovascular:9,3%, grupo VIII-respiratorio: 3,2%, grupo XVII-lesionesenvenenamientos: 23,1%, grupo IX-digestivo: 1,3%,grupos X-XI-genito-urinario y gineco-obstetricia: 1,4%,grupo XVI-otros mal definidos: 40,1%. Los datos delos grupos específicos estudiados (de los SEMEx quelos aportaron) fueron: dolor torácico-disnea: 3,7%, ictus/accidente cerebrovascular agudo: 0,9%, alteraciónconciencia: 7,7%, síncope-lipotimia: 2,5%, autolesiones:2.654 (0,4%). Total grupos patológicos y sindrómicos:59,9% y total de otros mal definidos: 40,1%. De las patologíasconsideradas de mayor relevancia en urgencias-emergencias: síndrome coronario agudo: 3,1%,arritmias: 3,2%, paro cardiaco: 1,7%, paro respiratorio:0,16%, traumatismos totales: 34,9%, politraumatismos:1,16%, traumatismo cráneo encefálico: 1,77%, intoxicaciones:5,1%, agresiones: 6,9%, quemados: 0,26%(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;33(supl.1): 37-46, ene.-abr. 2010. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88203</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de procesos y patologías atendidos por los servicios de emergencia médica extrahospitalaria en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50246</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
