<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61796</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Update on the Treatment of Alopecia Areata</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alopecia areata is nonscarring telogenic alopecia of autoimmune etiology. It is estimated to be the presenting complaint in 2 % of dermatologic consultations, and can appear at any age although it is more common in young patients. Treatment depends on several factors, such as extent of the disease and age, and may be local or systemic. Local treatments aim to achieve hair regrowth, but do not alter the underlying condition, whereas systemic treatments can modify the course of the disease. In neither case does treatment provide a cure. In this article, we review most of the therapeutic options described in the literature for alopecia areata (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Giménez, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Bujaldón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán-Gutiérrez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La alopecia areata es una alopecia no cicatricial telogénica de base autoinmune. Se estima que origina un 2 % de las consultas dermatológicas y puede aparecer a cualquier edad, aunque es más frecuente en pacientes jóvenes. Su tratamiento va a depender de varios factores, fundamentalmente de la extensión de la enfermedad, de la edad del paciente, así como de medidas locales y sistémicas. Mientras que los tratamientos locales tienen como objetivo conseguir el recrecimiento piloso, sin influir en la evolución de la enfermedad, los tratamientos sistémicos pueden interferir en la evolución de la misma, siendo ambos medidas paliativas. En este trabajo revisamos la mayoría de las opciones terapéuticas descritas en la literatura para la alopecia areata (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;100(4): 266-276, mayo 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61796</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización terapéutica en alopecia areata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7676^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27774^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30103^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22708^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22356^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12137^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27948^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d509^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30164^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9103^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12835^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d509^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200905</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
