<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166390</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life and psychological state of patients with implantable cardioverter&#150;defibrillators</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients with an implantable cardioverter-defibrillator (ICD) form a population that is at an increased risk of presenting with a psychological disorder or a poor quality of life. However, most large randomized clinical studies demonstrate that ICD use leads to a normal or improved quality of life. The main predictor of a poor quality of life and of psychological disturbance after ICD implantation is the frequency of device firing. Other predictors are young age, a history of anxiety or depression, and poor family or social support. The majority of studies have evaluated quality of life over only the short term, and it is not known whether it could change over the long term. In addition, few data are available on the quality of life of patients using an ICD for primary prevention. A range of resources are available for helping patients adapt to life with an ICD. Accurate programming of the parameters for tachycardia detection and antitachycardia pacing therapy significantly reduces the number of ICD discharges and makes a deterioration in quality of life less likely. A range of psychological therapies, involving drugs as well as psychotherapeutic interventions, have proven effective in improving the quality of life of patients who have experienced a decline after device implantation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merino-Llorens, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macía-Palafox, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintero-Henson, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peinado-Peinado, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernán Roa-Rad, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes con desfibrilador automático implantable (DAI) constituyen una población en riesgo de presentar alteraciones psicológicas y una peor calidad de vida. Sin embargo, datos derivados de la mayoría de los grandes ensayos clínicos aleatorios con DAI ponen de manifiesto que el efecto del dispositivo sobre la calidad de vida es beneficioso o neutro. El principal predictor de empeoramiento de la calidad de vida y ajuste psicológico al DAI, tras el implante, es el número de descargas del dispositivo. Otros predictores son la juventud, los antecedentes de trastornos de ansiedad o depresión, y el escaso apoyo social o familiar. En la mayor parte de los estudios se han realizado evaluaciones de la calidad de vida a corto plazo y se desconoce si ésta puede cambiar a más largo plazo. Además, hay menos información sobre la calidad de vida en pacientes con indicación de DAI como prevención primaria. Disponemos de diversos recursos para ayudar al paciente en el proceso de adaptación a la vida con DAI. Una adecuada programación de los criterios de detección y las terapias de estimulación antitaquicardia reducirá significativamente el número de descargas y hará menos probable el deterioro de la calidad de vida. En pacientes que han experimentado una reducción en ésta tras el implante de DAI, diversas terapias psicológicas, tanto farmacológicas como de intervención psicoterapéutica, han demostrado ser eficaces en la mejoría de la calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);8(supl.A): 40a-50a, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166390</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida y estado psicológico de los pacientes portadores de desfibrilador automático implantable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8076^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d902^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53393^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
