<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95871</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the attributes of patient-based health outcomes instruments</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Study of the quality and use of patient-based outcomes instruments has been and still is an area of growing interest inmany health disciplines, including nursing. In the last 30 years, the number of measures has greatly increased. However, there is enormous disparity in their contents, hampering selection of one or other of these instruments for use in clinical medicine or research. The aim of this article was to describe the quality attributes that patient-basedhealth instruments should meet before being used. For that purpose, we provide a detailed description of the attributes on which there is both national and international consensus. These instruments are grouped in 3 main axes: conceptual adequacy, applicability, and psychometric properties (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabañero-Martínez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrero-García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Richart-Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Mendoza, C. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio de la calidad y uso de instrumentos de medición de resultados de salud basados en el paciente ha sido y es un campo de interés incipiente para muchas disciplinas sanitarias, entre ellas la enfermería. En los últimos 30 años se ha multiplicado el número de instrumentos de medición, y se ha observado una enorme disparidad en sus contenidos, lo que dificulta la selección de uno de ellos para su uso en la clínica o en la investigación. El objetivo de este artículo es presentar los atributos que deben reunir los instrumentos de salud basados en el paciente antes de ser utilizados. Para ello, se presentan con detalle los atributos que, al respecto, se han consensuado, tanto en el ámbito nacional como internacional, agrupándolos en 3 grandes ejes: adecuación conceptual, aplicabilidad y propiedades psicométricas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);18(2): 84-90, mar. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95871</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de los atributos de las medidas de resultados de salud basados en el paciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28085</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
