<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94459</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of the birth ball in the birthing room</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to identify the benefits of using a birth ball during the dilation and pushing phases of labour, in women who were admitted while in labour or for induction of labour.Material and method: cross-sectional descriptive study conducted at the Parc Tauli Health Care Corporation of Sabadell in 2008. The sample consisted of women admitted while in labour or in order to induce labour in CSPT (Parc Tauli Health CareCorporation) who accepted the use of the birth ball. A self-elaborated questionnaire on the use of the ball was administered,containing the following: demographic data, data related with the use of the ball, peridural analgesia matters, positions adopted during the process and degree of satisfaction. Results: of the 1.285 births attended over the course of the study the ball was offered to 102 women, three of whom refused to use it because they preferred to stand or lay on the bed. When comparing the ball with the bed, the majority of women (96,7%)found the ball to be very comfortable, their pain improved (79,6%), as did the sensation of movement (97,0%). The experience of feeling accompanied by their partner improved in73,5%. 94,9% of women reported that the ball helped them manage their pain better during contractions.Conclusions: the results indicate the clear benefits of using the ball during labour, but further analytical studies are needed to confirm its efficacy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Madrigal, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Santin, Assumpta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Quiroga, Coloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cots Paltor, M. Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Barragán, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castán Enseñat, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: identificar los beneficios del uso de la pelota de partos durante el proceso de dilatación y expulsivo, en mujeres que ingresaban en curso de parto o para inducción al parto.Material y método: estudio descriptivo transversal, en la Corporació Sanitària Parc Taulí (CSPT) de Sabadell en 2008. Se incluyeron mujeres que ingresaban en curso de parto o para inducción al parto en CSPT y que aceptaban el uso de la pelota.Se utilizó un cuestionario de elaboración propia sobre el uso de la pelota que contenía: datos demográficos relacionados con el empleo de la pelota, cuestiones que hacían referencia a la analgesia peridural, posiciones adoptadas durante el proceso y el grado de satisfacción.Resultados: de 1.285 partos asistidos en el período de estudio, la pelota se ofreció a 102 mujeres, tres de las cuales la rechazaron porque querían estar de pie o en la cama. Comparando la pelota con la cama, la gran mayoría de mujeres (96,7%) encontraron la pelota muy confortable, la sensación de dolor mejoró(79,6%) así como la sensación de movimiento (97,0%).La vivencia de acompañamiento por parte de la pareja mejoró en un 73,5%. En un 94,9% las mujeres refirieron que la pelota les ayudaba a controlar mejor el dolor de la contracción.Conclusiones: los resultados apuntan claros beneficios con la utilización de la pelota durante el proceso de parto, si bien son necesarios estudios analíticos para confirmar su eficacia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;13(9): 62-65, nov. 2010. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94459</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios de la pelota de partos (birth ball) en la sala de partos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37660</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38636^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23043</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201011</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
