<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88140</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary laparoscopic retroperitoneal lymph node dissection for clinical stage I nonseminomatous germ-cell testis tumor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: this report is intended to retrospectively assess cancer control and morbidity of primary laparoscopic reproperitoneal lymphadenectomy (L-RPLND) in patients with clinical Stage I non seminomatous germ cell tumour (NSGCT). Materials and methods: one hundred and sixty-four patients with clinical Stage I NSGCT underwent primary diagnostic LRPLND between 1993 and 2006. Patients were operated unilaterally limiting the dissection to templates. Kaplan Meier curves were generated estimating time to recurrence. Results: of the 164 patients, 82 (48%) had embryonal components and 35 (20%) lymphovascular invasion in the orchiectomy specimen. The median (IQR) age, operative time, length of hospital stay, blood loss and number of lymph nodes retrieved was 28 years (24-33), 135 minutes. (120- 180), 48 hours (24-48), 50 cc (20-100) and 14 (10-18) nodes, respectively. All patients had negative serum markers preoperatively. Presence of lymph node metastasis was identified in 32 (19.5%) patients. Follow-up was available in 15 of these. Fourteen received adjuvant chemotherapy and 2 of them had recurrence at 3 and 64 months. Absence of lymph node metastasis was diagnosed in 132 (80.5%) patients. Follow-up was available in 80 of these. Among them 7 recurred (5 retroperitoneum, 2 lung), one of them 33 months after L-RPLND. Median follow-up for patients without recurrence was 14 months (IQR:4-35). The cumulative 3-year recurrence free rate was 82% (95%CI: 64-91). Seventeen (10%) of 164 patients had intra or perioperative complications. Conclusions: this is the largest series of L-RPLND performed in a single institution. Both morbidity and oncologic safety of this technique needs to be prospectively evaluated in randomized trials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Foneron, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, O. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal-Mora, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campero, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Secin, F. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Salas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el propósito de este informe es evaluar retrospectivamente el seguimiento de cáncer y la mortalidad en linfadenectomía retroperitoneal laparoscópica (LRL) primaria en pacientes con tumor de células germinales no seminomatoso (TCGNS) es estadio clínico I. Materiales y métodos: ciento sesenta y cuatro pacientes con TCGNS en estadio clínico I se sometieron a LRL diagnóstica primaria entre 1993 y 2006. Los pacientes fueron operados unilateralmente limitando la disección a áreas. Se generaron curvas Kaplan Meier estimando el período de recurrencia. Resultados: de los 164 pacientes 82 (48%) tenían componentes embrionarios y 35 (20%) invasión linfovascular en la muestra de orquiectomía. La edad media (RI), tiempo operatorio, estancia en el hospital, pérdida de sangre y número de ganglios linfáticos recuperados fueron 28 años (24-33), 135 minutos (120-180), 48 horas (24-48), 50 cc (20-100) y 14 (10-18) ganglios linfáticos, respectivamente. Todos los pacientes tenían marcador sérico negativo antes de la intervención. La presencia de metástasis en ganglios linfáticos se identificó en 32 (19,5%) pacientes. Se hizo un seguimiento en 15 de ellos. Catorce recibieron quimioterapia adyuvante y dos de ellos sufrieron recurrencia a los 3 y 64 meses. La ausencia de metástasis en ganglios linfáticos se diagnosticó en 132 (80,5%) pacientes. Se hizo un seguimiento en 80 de ellos. Entre ellos 7 sufrieron recurrencia (5 retroperitoneo, 2 pulmonar), uno de ellos a los 33 meses de la LRL. El seguimiento medio de los pacientes sin recurrencia fue de 14 meses (RI: 4-35). La tasa acumulada de supervivencia libre de enfermedad a los tres años fue del 82% (IC 95%: 64-91). Diecisiete de 164 (10%) padecieron complicaciones intra o perioperatorias. Conclusiones: ésta es la serie más larga de LRL llevada a cabo en una única institución. Tanto la mortalidad como la seguridad oncológica de esta técnica deben ser evaluadas prospectivamente en ensayos aleatorios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;35(1): 22-28, ene. 2011. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88140</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfadenectomía retroperitoneal laparoscópica primaria para el tumor testicular de células germinales no seminomatoso en estadio clínico I</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31880^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12604^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
