<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038567</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primitive neuroectodermal tumor. Ewing´s sarcoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Primitive neuroectodermal tumor is an extraordinarily rare primary tumor in the kidney and can be mistaken for a variety of other round cell tumors. It is important to recognize each of these entities, because each carries unique therapeutic and prognostic implications. However, accurate diagnosis of these tumors is hindered by their significant morphologic overlap and complicated by their rarity. These neplasm are highly aggressive that tend to recurence and to metastatize. Standard therapy combining surgery, chemotherapy, radiation and genetic therapy. We report a case of primitive neuroectodermal tumor of the kidney in a 50 year old female patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mallén Mateo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Sanz, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Jalón Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rioja Sanz, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Serrano, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Regueiro, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalvo Ibarra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores neuroectodérmicos primitivos de riñón son neoplasias extremadamente raras, pudiendo ser confundidas con toda la variedad de tumores de células redondas de riñón. Es importante hacer diagnóstico diferencial entre estas entidades por sus implicaciones terapéuticas y pronosticas, aunque no deja de ser difícil debido a su infrecuencia. Estos tumores son extremadamente agresivos, con tendencia a la recurrencia y a la diseminación temprana a distancia. El tratamiento combina cirugía, quimioterapia y radioterapia, apoyándose en la terapia génica. Aportamos un caso de tumor neuroectodérmico primitivo de riñón en una paciente de 50 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;29(3): 311-313, mar. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038567</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor neuroectodérmico primitivo renal/Sarcoma de Swing</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12891^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31257^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31583^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
