<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130113</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Practical considerations for high resolution anoscopy in patients infected with human immunodeficiency virus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anal cancer is uncommon in the general population, however its incidence is increasing significantly in certain risk groups, mainly in men who have sex with men, and particularly those infected with human immunodeficiency virus. High resolution anoscopy technique is currently considered the standard in the diagnosis of anal intraepithelial neoplasia, but at present there is no agreed standard method between health areas. High resolution anoscopy is an affordable technique that can be critical in the screening of anal carcinoma and its precursor lesions, but is not without difficulties. We are currently studying the most effective strategy for managing premalignant anal lesions, and with this article we attempt to encourage other groups interested in reducing the incidence of an increasing neoplasia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Carreró Fojón, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ocampo Hermida, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Parada, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Girondo, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iribarren-Díaz, Mauricio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de ano, una enfermedad infrecuente en la población general, presenta una incidencia elevada y progresiva en ciertos grupos de riesgo, fundamentalmente en hombres que tienen sexo con hombres, y particularmente en aquellos con infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana. La anoscopia de alta resolución se considera actualmente la técnica estándar en el diagnóstico de la neoplasia intraepitelial anal, pero su uso protocolizado aún está por consensuar en los sistemas sanitarios. Aunque no está exenta de dificultades, es una técnica asequible que puede llegar a ser fundamental en el cribado del cáncer de ano y sus lesiones precursoras. Actualmente estamos estudiando la estrategia más efectiva para el manejo de las lesiones premalignas anales, y con esta publicación intentamos animar a otros grupos interesados en la reducción de una neoplasia epidemiológicamente en progresión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(10): 676-680, dic. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consideraciones prácticas de la anoscopia de alta resolución en pacientes infectados por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1011^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1011^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1008^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10399^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1008^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24015^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1011^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24015^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1008^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
