<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158383</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence, knowledge and attitudes towards smoking among SEPAR members</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of this study were to estimate the prevalence of smoking among SEPAR members, and their approach to smoking cessation in their patients. An online survey was completed by 640 members (496 pulmonologists, 45 nurses, 34 thoracic surgeons, 37 physiotherapists, and 28 other specialists). Of the members interviewed, 5% confessed that they were smokers: 3.5% pulmonologists; 8.9% nurses; 8.8% thoracic surgeons, and 13.5% physiotherapists. A total of 96% of members assign a lot or quite a lot of importance to setting an example; 98% of members always or often ask their patients about their smoking habit. The most effective anti-smoking intervention, according to 77% of members, is a combination of drugs and psychological support. These results are an indicator of the awareness and commitment of SEPAR members to smoking and its cessation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Granda Orive, José I de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Higes Martinez, Eva de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solano Reina, Segismundo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Rueda, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfageme Michavila, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Lozano, Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas Ramos, Pilar de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Ruiz, Carlos A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Callejas González, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos del estudio son estimar la prevalencia del hábito tabáquico entre los socios y las actitudes e intervenciones sobre tabaquismo que realizan los miembros SEPAR ante sus pacientes. Se realizó una encuesta on line, a la que respondieron 640 socios (496 neumólogos, 45 enfermeras, 34 cirujanos torácicos, 37 fisioterapeutas y 28 profesionales de otras especialidades). El 5% de los socios encuestados confiesan ser fumadores: neumólogos 3,4%; enfermería 8,9%; cirujanos torácicos 8,8%; fisioterapeutas 13,5%. El 96% de los socios dan mucha o bastante importancia a la función modélica. El 98% de los socios preguntan siempre o a menudo a sus pacientes sobre el consumo de tabaco. La intervención más eficaz para tratar el tabaquismo para un 77% de los socios es el uso de fármacos, combinado con soporte psicológico. Estos resultados son un exponente de la firme sensibilización e implicación que los miembros SEPAR tienen frente al tabaquismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;52(12): 605-610, dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158383</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia, conocimiento y actitudes acerca del consumo de tabaco en los miembros de SEPAR</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
