<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95419</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the teamwork in six intensive care units of two university hospitals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction It has been demonstrated that teamwork has a direct positive effect on the quality and the efficiency of patient's care and consequently on hospital costs.Objectives1.To assess attitudes toward the teamwork of nurses and physicians of 6 ICUs in two teaching hospitals. 2.To analyze if there are any relationships between attitudes toward teamwork and socio-demographic variables. 3.To study if there are differences in the attitudes toward teamwork among professionals of the different units. Method This prospective study evaluated the attitudes of teamwork of 136 professionals with the scale development by Heinemann et al. in 1999. This scale is made up of three subscales that measure the value of being in a team, the efficiency of the team and the function of collaboration of the physician within the team.Results The majority of professionals had a positive attitude towards teamwork. They obtained a mean score of 97.01 for a maximum of 120 points. In regards to sociodemographic variables, statistically significant differences were only found in gender and professional category, as women and female nurses had better attitudes toward teamwork. There were no differences in attitudes towards teamwork in the different units studied.Conclusion Attitude toward teamwork by physicians and nurses of the 6 ICUs studied was good. No differences were found between attitudes toward teamwork among the professionals of the different units (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Del Barrio Linares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reverte Sanchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El trabajar en equipo ha demostrado tener una repercusión directa en la calidad y en la eficacia del cuidado proporcionado al paciente y en consecuencia en el coste hospitalario. Objetivos 1) Evaluar las actitudes hacia el trabajo en equipo de las enfermeras y médicos de 6 UCI en 2 hospitales universitarios. 2) Analizar si existen relaciones entre las actitudes hacia el trabajo en equipo y las variables sociodemográficas. 3) Analizar si existen diferencias en las actitudes hacia el trabajo en equipo entre los profesionales de las distintas unidades.Método Este estudio prospectivo descriptivo evaluó en 136 profesionales las actitudes hacia el trabajo en equipo mediante la escala desarrollada por Heinemann et al, en 1999. Consta de 3 subescalas que miden el valor de ser equipo, la eficiencia del equipo y la función de colaboración del médico dentro del equipo.Resultados La mayoría de los profesionales tenían una actitud positiva hacia el trabajo en equipo, la puntuación media que obtuvieron para el total de la escala fue de 97,01 para un máximo de 120 puntos. Con relación a las variables sociodemográficas solo se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el sexo y en la categoría profesional, al tener unas mejores actitudes hacia el trabajo en equipo las mujeres y las enfermeras. No ha habido diferencias en las actitudes hacia el trabajo en equipo en las diferentes unidades.Conclusión La actitud hacia el trabajo en equipo de los médicos y enfermeras de las 6 UCI ha sido buena no encontrándose diferencias en las actitudes entre los profesionales de las distintas unidades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;21(4): 150-160, Oct. - Dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95419</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del trabajo en equipo en seis unidades de cuidados intensivos de dos hospitales universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
