<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145521</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effects of the Pilates method on hamstring extensibility, pelvic tilt and trunk flexion</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Pilates includes a high volume of hamstring stretching and maximal trunk flexion with knees extended exercises. Objective: to perform a systematic review about Pilates practice effects and a detraining period on hamstring extensibility, pelvic tilt and trunk flexion in maximal trunk flexion with knees extended. Method: it was analysed all the experimental or quasi-experimental designs written in English, Spanish or Portuguese and included in the following databases: Pubmed, Sports Discus, ISI Web of Knowledge, Dialnet and Research Gate. Results and discussion: twenty-one papers were analysed. Most of them used a pre-test-post-test design with control group. The intervention programs applied were heterogeneous. Samples were composed mainly of women, both young and old. It was found that the Pilates practice, with different volume, significantly increased hamstring muscle extensibility and pelvic tilt in maximal trunk flexion. At least three training sessions peer week during six weeks were necessary in order to obtain a high trunk inclination. Studies which involved athletes showed contradictory results. By inducing a detraining period it was noticed a decrease in hamstring extensibility and trunk flexion from the second week. Conclusions: there is a moderate evidence that Pilates is an effective method to increase hamstring extensibility, pelvic tilt and the degree of trunk flexion in maximal flexion positions in sedentary and recreational active people and also to increase hamstring extensibility in athletes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Cristóbal, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alacid Cárceles, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Miñarro, Pedro A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esparza Ros, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el Pilates engloba un gran volumen de ejercicios de estiramiento de la musculatura isquiosural y de flexión máxima del tronco con rodillas extendidas. Objetivo: realizar una revisión sistemática sobre los efectos de la práctica de Pilates y de un período de desentrenamiento sobre la flexibilidad isquiosural, la inclinación pélvica y la flexión del tronco en flexión máxima del tronco con rodillas extendidas. Metodología: se analizaron todos los diseños experimentales o cuasi-experimentales redactados en inglés, español o portugués incluidos en las siguientes bases de datos: Pubmed, Sports Discus, ISI Web of Knowledge, Dialnet y Research Gate. Resultados y discusión: fueron analizados veintiún artículos. La mayoría utilizó un diseño de pre-testpost-test con grupo control, siendo heterogéneos los programas de intervención aplicados. La muestra estaba compuesta principalmente por mujeres, jóvenes y mayores. Se encontró que la práctica de Pilates, con diferente volumen, incrementaba significativamente la extensibilidad isquiosural y la inclinación pélvica en flexión máxima del tronco. Para obtener una mayor inclinación del tronco fueron necesarios, al menos, tres días de entrenamiento semanal durante seis semanas. En los estudios que incluyen poblaciones de deportistas los resultados son contradictorios. Con el desentrenamiento se produce una disminución de la extensibilidad isquiosural y la flexión del tronco a partir de la segunda semana. Conclusiones: existen moderadas evidencias de que el Pilates es efectivo para aumentar la extensibilidad isquiosural, la inclinación pélvica y el grado de flexión del tronco en posiciones de flexión máxima en poblaciones sedentarias y activas recreacionales, así como para incrementar la flexibilidad isquiosural en deportistas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(5): 1967-1986, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145521</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del método Pilates sobre la extensibilidad isquiosural, la inclinación pélvica y la flexión del tronco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
