<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110462</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with edentulousness in an elderly population in Valencia (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the prevalence of edentulism and its association with various socioeconomic factors and oral health habits in the population aged 65-74 years old in the region of Valencia. Methods: A cross sectional study was designed. Thirty-four primary health centers and five nursing homes were chosen at random in the region of Valencia (10-15 voluntary participants per sampling point). Clinical examinations were carried out by three calibrated dentists (kappa&gt;0.85) in the same centers. The total sample consisted of 531 individuals (235 men and 296 women). Results: The percentage of toothlessness was 20.7% and the mean number of natural teeth present was 14.92. The prevalence of edentulism was significantly higher (p &lt;0.05) in men, institutionalized persons, those with no schooling, those with poor oral hygiene, those who visited the dentist regularly and those living in peri-urban/rural areas. In a multivariate logistic regression model with edentulism as the dependent variable, the following factors were identified as significant independent variables: institutionalization (odds ratio [OR]=2.88), poor oral hygiene (OR=2.35), regular visits to the dentist (OR=2.34) and age (OR=1.19). Conclusion: Edentulousness is a complex phenomenon that involves distinct social and economic factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Eustaquio-Raga, María Vicenta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montiel-Company, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almerich-Silla, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia del edentulismo y su asociación con diferentes factores socioeconómicos y de hábitos de salud oral en la población valenciana de 65 a 74 años de edad. Métodos: Se diseñó un estudio transversal. Se seleccionaron aleatoriamente 34 centros de salud de atención primaria y cinco residencias geriátricas de la Comunidad Valenciana (10 a 15 individuos voluntarios por punto de muestreo). Las exploraciones clínicas las realizaron tres odontólogos previamente calibrados (kappa&gt;0.85) en los mismos centros. La muestra total fue de 531 personas, 235 hombres y 296 mujeres. Resultados: El porcentaje de desdentados totales fue de 20,7, y la media de dientes naturales presente de 14,92. La prevalencia de edentulismo fue significativamente mayor (p &lt;0.05) en los hombres, en las personas institucionalizadas, que no tienen estudios, con pobre higiene oral, que visitan regularmente al odontólogo y en las que viven en zonas periurbanas o rurales. En un modelo de regresión logística multivariada con el edentulismo como variable dependiente se han hallado como variables significativas la institucionalización (odds ratio [OR]=2,88), la pobre higiene oral (OR=2,35), las visitas regulares al odontólogo (OR=2,34) y la edad (OR=1,19).  Conclusión: El edentulismo es un fenómeno complejo, con diversos factores sociales y económicos implicados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;27(2): 123-127, mar.-abr. 2013. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores asociados con el edentulismo en población anciana de Valencia (España)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29447^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29447^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10090^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
