<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91974</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Memory Bias in Anxiety Disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There are currently a large number of theoretical models that defend the importance of cognitive appraisal in the onset and maintenance of anxiety response. Research into the cognitive processes underlying anxiety response have clearly shown that, in comparison to normal subjects, anxious subjects display a tendency to selectively pay attention and catastrophically interpret information that is congruent with their emotional state. However, there is a third bias about which the data from the various investigations have yielded diffuse results in the different disorders and experimental tasks. This is the case of memory bias, which can be defined as the tendency to preferentially recall previously presented negative stimulation in comparison to neutral stimulation. Atheoretical review is presented with the main goal of determining the existence of memory bias across diverse anxiety disorders and the different experimental tasks used to assess this bias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz Blasco, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel-Tobal, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Morales, M. ª Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad existen un gran número de modelos teóricos que defienden la importancia de la valoración cognitiva en el inicio y mantenimiento de la respuesta de ansiedad. La investigación acerca de los procesos cognitivos que subyacen a la respuesta de ansiedad ha puesto de manifiesto de manera bastante sólida cómo los sujetos ansiosos en comparación con sujetos normales muestran una tendencia a atender de manera selectiva y a interpretar de un modo catastrofista información congruente con su estado emocional. Sin embargo, existiría un tercer sesgo para el cual los datos de las distintas investigaciones han arrojado resultados difusos en los distintos trastornos y tareas experimentales. Nos referimos al sesgo de memoria, que puede definirse como la tendencia a recordar preferentemente estimulación negativa presentada previamente en comparación con estimulación neutra. Se presenta un trabajo de revisión teórica sistemática que tiene como objetivo fundamental determinar la existencia del sesgo de memoria a lo largo de los diferentes trastornos de ansiedad y de las diferentes tareas experimentales utilizadas en la evaluación de dicho sesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;22(2): 187-197, jul. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91974</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sesgos de Memoria en los Trastornos de Ansiedad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
