<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76785</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-811X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Combined screening in the detection of Down syndrome in the first trimester</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">First-trimester screening for Down¡¯s syndrome, combiningtwo biochemical markers ¨CPregnancy associatedplasma protein-A (PAPP-A) and free ¦Â human chorionicgonadotropin (f¦ÂhCG)-, and an ultrasound marker -nuchaltranslucency (NT)¨C, allows a higher detection rate(96.55% in our series) assuming a false positive rate of 5%. These results increase significantly those obtainedwith the second trimester screening.The incorporation of biochemical markers impliesmainly a reduction in the false positive rate, and consequentlya reduction of invasive methods to perform.Detection rate in this study is higher to detection ratepublished in other series. This fact can be due to the ageof pregnant women included in the present paper.The lower false positive rate, the higher detectionrate an the early diagnosis make this screening, actually,a good method to apply to general population.. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borrell, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casamitjana, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercade, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gratacos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casals, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cribado del sindrome de Down, en el primer trimestrede gestaci¨®n, incorporando dos parsmetros bioquimicos¡ªproteina plasmstica asociada al embarazo (PAPP-A) y fracciona libre de la hormona gonadotrofina cori¨®nica (f¦ÂhCG)¡ª,y un parametro ecografico ¡ªtranslucencia nucal (TN)¡ª, permiteuna mayor tasa de deteccion (96,55 % en esta serie),asumiendo una tasa de falsos positivos del 5 %. Estos resultadosmejoran de forma significativa los resultados obtenidoscon el cribado ya establecido de segundo trimestre.La incorporacion de los parsmetros bioquimicos se traduceprincipalmente en una disminuci¨®n de los falsos positivos,con la consecuente disminuci¨®n de pruebas invasivas a realizar.La tasa de detecci¨®n en este estudio es algo superior alas mostradas en otras series, hecho atribuible a la edad delas gestantes incluidas en el mismo.Debido al menor porcentaje de falsos positivos, a la mayortasa de deteccion y a la precocidad diagnostica, esta modalidadde cribado es, hoy por hoy, el metodo de eleccion pararealizar un cribado poblacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. diagn. trat. prenat. (Ed. impr.);21(1): 15-19, ene.-mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76785</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado combinado para la deteccion del sindrome de Down en el primertrimestre de gestacion</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28087^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11707</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
