<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044559</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical collection of scientific instruments from Spanish Pharmacy Museum of the Faculty of Pharmacy of Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The collection has 453 pieces grouped on 349 instrumental units or stand alone instruments plus 74 accessories or instrument parts sorted on 27 chapters; and belonge to the University Complutense. All of them are settled now on Faculty of Pharmacy, Complutense University, Madrid: some come from its preceding Central University and others from San Fernando College. On the collection we have verify 74 instruments given by different institutions or individuals. On this paper are described scientific instruments from passed branch of study «Physical Instruments Applied to Pharmacy» («Cátedra de aparatos de Física aplicada a la Farmacia») born at 1892. Therefore this Pharmacy, Physic-Chemistry and Pharmaceutical Instrumental Analysis instrument collection is singular and has an outstanding, scientific, teaching and museum value. Optical instruments domain over electrical instruments, having whole collection enough apparatus to can sure the high level of Pharmacy studies on the past. Indeed, this collection preservation results a valuable tool for historical purposes. On collection are more research physical equipments over teaching equipments. There is 13,9% of electrical equipments versus 28,1% of optical equipments, all of them used by several Pharmacy students generations, pharmaceutical and other professionals. The collection is based on Technical Physics and explains very well this discipline level. Work approach has been to contribute to Spanish Pharmacy Museum Catalogue. Included instruments have been described and indeed studied y catalogued</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García de Marina Bayo, Adrián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La colección histórica de instrumentos científicos del Museo de la Farmacia Hispana de la Facultad de Farmacia de Madrid (Universidad Complutense de Madrid) consta de 453 ejemplares, agrupados en 349 conjuntos instrumentaleso instrumentos y 74 accesorios o partes de los mismos, conjunto ordenado en 27 secciones.Todos ellos se encuentran en la actualidad en la Facultad de Farmacia de la Universidad Complutense de Madrid: algunos proceden de su precursora, la UniversidadCentral, y otros del Colegio de San Fernando. En la colección hemos podido constatar que existen asimismo instrumentos donados por distintas institucionesy particulares. En el trabajo se recogen los instrumentos científicos desde la creación, en 1892, de la Cátedra de Aparatos de Física aplicada a la Farmacia. Por ello, esta colección de instrumentos de Farmacia, Físico-Química y Análisis Instrumental Farmacéutico es singular y de enorme valor científico, didáctico y museístico.Predominan entre todos, los instrumentos ópticos sobre los eléctricos, englobando la colección un número de aparatos suficientemente importante como paraaseverar el alto nivel que tenían los estudios de Farmacia de la época. Por otra parte, la conservación de dicha colección resulta una herramienta de inmensurableutilidad con fines históricos. En la colección dominan los equipos físicos para investigación sobre los de docencia, con un 13,9 por 100 de equipos eléctricos, frente a un 28,1 por 100 de equipos ópticos, todos ellos utilizados por varias generaciones de estudiantes de Farmacia y por profesionales farmacéuticos y de otras ramas. La colección se basa en Técnica Física y explica el nivel de esta disciplina. El objetivo del trabajo ha sido contribuir al catálogo del Museo de la Farmacia Hispana; los instrumentos expuestos, no sólo se han descrito, sino que se han estudiado y catalogado</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;70(4): 813-838, oct. 2004. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044559</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colección histórica de instrumentos científicos del Museo de la Farmacia Hispana de la Facultad de Farmacia de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38880</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29007^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9336^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29007^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29007^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38875</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10796^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
