<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049468</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of the spanish version of the Bladder control self-assessment questionnarie (B-SAQ). A new concept screening instrument for lower urinary tract dysfunction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Taking into account the high prevalence in our country of Overactive Bladder Syndrome (OAB) ('urgency', with or without incontinence, sometimes associated to an increase in frequency and/or nocturia) and the difficulty to identify it, it would be interesting to have a short patient self assessment screening questionnarie for the evaluation of lower urinary tract symptoms. The objective of the study is to evaluate the psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the Bladder control Self-Assessment Questionnaire (B-SAQ). Patients and methods: 133 women consulting due to lower urinary tract symptoms in a health care centre specialised on uroginecology. The subjects filled the B-SAQ (scales 'symptoms' and 'discomfort') and the ICIQ-UI SF, and underwent the usual protocol: uroginecologic history, pelvic examination and urodynamic study. Feasibility, validity, and reliability of the B-SAQ were assessed, as well as the ROC curve for the scores of both BCSEQ scales regarding the urodynamic diagnosis of Detrusor Overactivity (DO). Results: Feasibility: Average administration time, 3.5 (1.5) minutes; 2 women did not answer any of the questionnaires. Validity: the scores for 'symptoms' and 'discomfort' were higher in those women with a DO diagnosis: 'symptoms' = 7.8 (2.6) vs 6.2 (2.3) (p=0.0002); 'discomfort' = 9.1 (3) vs 7.8 (3.6) (p=0.03); the Spearman&#146;s correlation coefficient between 'discomfort' scale and item 3 of the ICIQ-UI SF (affection) was 0.65 (p&lt;0.001). Feasibility: Cronbach&#146;s alpha for 'symptoms' was 0.722 and 0,889 for 'discomfort'. According to the COR curve for both scales, a score greater than or equal to 6 showed adequate sensibility and specificity for the DO diagnosis. Conclusions: The B-SAQ is an easy-use instrument which shows adequate feasibility, validity and reliability for its use in clinical practice as screening instrument for OAB</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puig Clota, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebollo Álvarez, </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espuña Pons, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Teniendo en cuenta la elevada prevalencia del síndrome de Vejiga Hiperactiva-VH ('urgencia', con o sin incontinencia, a menudo asociada a aumento de frecuencia y/o nocturia) en nuestro país y la dificultad de identificarlo, sería interesante tener un instrumento en forma de cuestionario corto autocontestado para detectar y evaluar los pacientes con síntomas del tracto urinario inferior. El objetivo del estudio fue evaluar las propiedades psicométricas de la versión española del Cuestionario de Autoevaluación del Control de la Vejiga (CACV). Pacientes y método. Se incluyeron consecutivamente a 133 mujeres que consultaron por síntomas urinarios en una unidad especializada, para la realización de un estudio urodinámico. Las pacientes cumplimentaron el CACV (escalas 'síntomas' y 'molestias') y el ICIQ-UI SF y fueron sometidas al protocolo habitual: historia uroginecológica, exploración pélvica y estudio urodinámico. Se calcularon factibilidad, validez y fiabilidad del CACV, así como la curva COR para la puntuación de las dos escalas del CACV respecto al diagnóstico urodinámico de Hiperactividad del Detrusor (HD). Resultados. Factibilidad: tiempo medio de administración, 3,5 (1,5) minutos; 2 mujeres no contestaron ninguno de los cuestionarios. Validez: las puntuaciones de 'síntomas' y 'molestias' fueron superiores en las mujeres diagnosticadas de HD: 'síntomas'= 7,8(2,6) vs 6,2(2,3) (p=0,0002); 'molestias'=9,1(3) vs 7,8(3,6) (p=0,03); el coeficiente de correlación de Spearman entre la escala 'molestia' y el ítem 3 del ICIQ-UI SF (afectación) fue de 0,65(p&lt;0,001). Fiabilidad: el alfa de Cronbach para 'síntomas' fue 0,722 y para 'molestias' 0,889. Según la curva COR, para ambas escalas, la puntuación igual o superior a 6 puntos mostró adecuada sensibilidad y especificidad en el diagnóstico de HD. Conclusiones: El Cuestionario de Autoevaluación del Control de la Vejiga-CACV es un instrumento de sencillo uso que muestra adecuadas factibilidad, validez y fiabilidad para ser empleado en la práctica clínica como instrumento de cribado para VH</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(10): 1017-1024, nov.-dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión en español del &#147;Cuestionario de Autoevaluación del Control de la Vejiga (CACV). Un nuevo instrumento para detectar pacientes con disfunción del tracto urinario inferior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52134^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14949^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
