<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-117192</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasound-guided peripheral nerve block at wrist level for the treatment of idiopathic palmar hyperhidrosis with botulinum toxin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveEvaluation of pain and degree of satisfaction in patients undergoing ultrasound-assisted peripheral regional block for the treatment of idiopathic palmar hyperhidrosis with botulinum toxin.Patients and methodsA descriptive, observational study of patients with palmar hyperhidrosis treated with botulinum toxin A, who underwent ultrasound-guided peripheral regional block of the median and ulnar nerves with 3 ml of mepivacaine 1% in each one. The radial nerve block was injected in the anatomical snuffbox. After establishing blocking, the dermatologist performed a mapping and injected around 100 IU of botulinum toxin across the whole palm. The pain experienced during the injection of botulinum toxin was evaluated by verbal numerical scale (from 0 to 10), along with the degree of satisfaction with the anesthetic technique, and the post-anesthetic complications.ResultsA total of 40 patients were enrolled in the study, 11 men and 29 women with no significant differences. The pain intensity assessed with verbal numerical scale was 1.03 (standard deviation of 1.37). No patients had a value greater than 5. The degree of patient satisfaction with the anesthetic technique was very good for 85% of the patients, and good for 7.5%. There were no complications related to type of anesthesia.ConclusionsThe ultrasound-assisted peripheral regional block could be a simple, effective and safe technique for patients undergoing palmar injection of botulinum toxin. Pain intensity was very low, and it provided a very good level of satisfaction in most patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fondarella, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olea, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez de Salinas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iriarte, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluación del dolor y el grado de satisfacción en pacientes sometidos a bloqueo regional periférico guiado por ultrasonidos para el tratamiento de la hiperhidrosis palmar idiopática con toxina botulínica. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio descriptivo, observacional, de pacientes con hiperhidrosis palmar tratados con toxina botulínica A, a los que se les realizó un bloqueo regional periférico guiado por ecografía de los nervios mediano y cubital con 3 ml de mepivacaína al 1% en cada uno. El bloqueo del nervio radial se llevó a cabo con infiltración en abanico a nivel de la tabaquera anatómica. Tras establecer el bloqueo, el dermatólogo realizó un mapeo e inyectó alrededor de 100 UI de toxina botulínica distribuidas en toda la palma de la mano. Fueron evaluados el dolor experimentado en la inyección de toxina botulínica mediante la escala verbal numérica (de 0 a 10), el grado de satisfacción con la técnica anestésica y las posibles complicaciones postanestésicas. Resultados. Se incluyeron 40 pacientes, 11 hombres y 29 mujeres. La intensidad del dolor evaluado con la escala numérica verbal fue de 1,03 (desviación típica 1,37). Ninguno de los pacientes presentó un valor superior a 5. El grado de satisfacción de los pacientes con la técnica anestésica fue muy bueno para el 85% de los pacientes, y bueno para el 7,5%. No hubo complicaciones derivadas del procedimiento anestésico. Conclusiones. El bloqueo de los troncos nerviosos distales guiado por ultrasonidos puede ser una técnica sencilla, eficaz y segura para los pacientes sometidos a inyección palmar de toxina botulínica. La intensidad del dolor fue muy baja y proporcionó un grado de satisfacción muy bueno en la mayoría de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;60(10): 571-575, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-117192</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueo de los nervios periféricos a nivel de la muñeca guiado por ecografía para el tratamiento de la hiperhidrosis idiopática palmar con toxina botulínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7126^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7126^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33081^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8791^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
