<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040125</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cockayne syndrome: treatment and rehabilitation. Based on one case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cockayne syndrome is a rare autosomal recessive disease characterized by physical and psychomotor retardation, progressive neurological disfunction, photosensitivity, ophthalmological abnormalities, neurosensorial deafness and other pathologic features such as leucodistrophy and calcifications in the central nervous system with segmental demyelination in the peripheral nervous system. In this work we report a clinical case of an eleven years old patient with Cockayne syndrome. This patient presents a mixed picture with growth and psychomotor retardation, ataxia, muscle tone alterations, orthopedic problems, sensorial disfunctions and speech problems. We describe the therapies used, including an individualized complete Rehabilitation program in order to improve the patient quality of life</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bayón Calatayud, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morante del Blanco, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urdiales Urdiales, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atienza Delgado, R. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Cockayne es una extraña enfermedad autosómica recesiva caracterizada por retraso psicomotor y del crecimiento, deterioro neurológico progresivo, fotosensibilidad, alteraciones oftalmológicas, sordera neurosensorial, imágenes patológicas de calcificaciones y leucodistrofia en el sistema nervioso central, con desmielinización segmentaria en el sistema nervioso periférico. Presentamos el caso clínico de un paciente con síndrome de Cockayne de 11 años de edad, en el que se aprecia un cuadro abigarrado con retraso psicomotor y del crecimiento, ataxia, alteraciones del tono muscular, ortopédicas, sensoriales y del lenguaje. Describimos los tratamientos empleados, incluido un programa de rehabilitación integral individualizado, cuyo objetivo es mejorar la calidad de vida del paciente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(4): 171-175, jul. 2005. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Cockayne: tratamiento y rehabilitación. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3087^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9322^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3087^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3087^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
