<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047202</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Trends in socioeconomic inequalities and self-perceived health in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the evolution of sociaoeconomic inequalities and socioeconomic inequalities in self-perceived health in Spain between from 1987 to 2001. Methods: We estimated the distributions of educational level and per capita provincial income and the differences of less-than-good self-assessed health according education level and per capita provincial in both periods. Results: The percentage of the population that had completed secondary education was greater, and inequality in per capita provincial income was lower, in 2001 than in 1987. In general terms, the differences in suboptimal (less-than-good) self-perceived health by education and by provincial income were greater in 2001 than in 1987, in both absolute and relative terms. However, when the potential within-province correlation in outcomes was taken into account, the differences according provincial income were lower in 1987 than in 2001. Conclusions: The redistribution of socioeconomic resources achieves greater social justice, but probably does not lead to reduced health inequalities in all cases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Astasio, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regidor, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle, María E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la evolución de las desigualdades socioeconómicas y las desigualdades socioeconómicas en la percepción subjetiva de la salud en España entre 1987 y 2001. Métodos: Se han estimado la distribución del nivel de estudios y de la renta per cápita provincial, así como las diferencias en la percepción de la salud según el nivel de estudios y según la renta per cápita provincial en cada período. Resultados: El porcentaje de población que había completado estudios de segundo grado o superiores fue mayor, y la desigualdad en la renta per cápita provincial fue menor en el año 2001 que en 1987. En líneas generales, las diferencias en la percepción de la salud como según el nivel de estudios y la renta per cápita provincial fueron mayores en 2001que en 1987, en términos relativos y absolutos. En cambio, cuando se tuvo en cuenta el efecto de la correlación residual dentro de las provincias en el resultado, las diferencias según la renta per cápita provincial fueron menores en 2001 que en 1987. Conclusión: La redistribución de los recursos socioeconómicos básicos consigue una mayor justicia social, pero probablemente no siempre consigan reducir las desigualdades en salud</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;20(3): 178-182, may. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047202</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de las desigualdades socioeconómicas y las desigualdades en la percepción de la salud en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20187</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
