<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052831</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early mother-infant interaction and factors negatively affecting parenting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The social information-processing model contributes to identifying the psychological processes underlying the construct «sensitivity» in early mother-child interaction. Negative emotional states associated with inadequate self-regulation in coping with stressors affect the mother&#146;s attention skills and the processing of the baby&#146;s signals. This leads to less synchronous parental practices, particularly unsatisfactory when the baby is unhappy, or crying because the required self-regulation is not provided. This micro-social research studies the sequential profile of maternal reactions to the baby&#146;s positive/neutral vs. difficult behaviours and compares them in two groups of dyads, one with mothers who reported high levels of distress and other negative factors for parenting and another group with low levels. The unfavourable circumstances of the high stress group and their negative effects on interaction were observed in some indiscriminate maternal responses and particularly as they reacted to their baby&#146;s difficult behaviour, when the mother&#146;s regulatory role is more necessary</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pons-Salvador, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trenado, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerezo, M Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El modelo del procesamiento de información social contribuye a identificar los procesos psicológicos subyacentes al constructo de «sensibilidad» en interacción madre-hijo. Los estados emocionales negativos por inadecuada autorregulación materna ante los estresores afectan sus habilidades atencionales y estadios del procesamiento de las señales infantiles llevándola a actuaciones menos sensibles: respuestas inoportunas, asincrónicas, particularmente insatisfactorias cuando el bebé manifiesta quejas/ llanto porque no le proporcionan la autorregulación emocional necesaria. Este estudio microsocial explora perfiles interaccionales secuenciales de reacciones maternas a conductas infantiles positivas/neutras vs. difíciles y los compara en dos grupos de díadas, uno con madres con alto nivel de factores negativos para la parentalidad y otro con bajo nivel. Las circunstancias desfavorables de madres del grupo alto y sus efectos negativos sobre la interacción se observaron en ciertas reacciones que no discriminaban el antecedente infantil y particularmente tras los estados de arousal negativo del bebé cuando el papel regulador materno es más necesario</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(3): 544-550, ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052831</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interacción temprana madre-hijo y factores que afectan negativamente a la parentalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8594^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32176^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
