<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036906</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mucocele-like breast tumors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Mucocele-like breast tumors (MLT) are uncommon lesions histologically defined as cysts or dilated ducts that contain mucin. We describe the clinical, mammographic, and echographic findings for MLT. Material and methods: Retrospective study of the four cases of MLT found in our archives; all diagnoses were confirmed at histological study of excisional biopsies. We review the clinical presentation (age and palpation), as well as the mammographic and echographic findings. Results: Mean patient age was 42 years (range: 35-48 years). In one case MLT presented as a soft, low-suspicion, palpable lesion. At mammography, two cases showed a set of suspicious polymorphic micro-calcifications and the other two had normal findings. Echography showed cysts with diffuse internal echoes in the two cases with normal findings at mammography. Conclusions: Breast MLT can present as a low-suspicion palpable nodule at physical examination, as suspicious microcalcifications at mammography, or as cysts with diffuse internal at echography</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zornoza, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cosín, Octavio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pina, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Regueira, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Marculeta, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sola, Jesús J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Los tumores mucocele-like (TML) de mama son lesiones infrecuentes que se definen anatomo-patológicamente como quistes o conductos dilatados que contienen mucina. Nuestro objetivo es describir los hallazgos clínicos, mamográficos y ecográficos de los TML de mama. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo. En los archivos de nuestro centro se encontraron cuatro casos de TML, todos ellos confirmados mediante biopsia escisional. Se revisó la presentación clínica (edad y palpación), así como los hallazgos mamográficos y ecográficos. Resultados: La edad media de las pacientes fue de 42 años (rango: 35-48). Uno de los casos resultó palpable, se trataba de un nódulo blando de baja sospecha. Los hallazgos mamográficos consistieron en dos casos en una agrupación de microcalcificaciones polimórficas sospechosas, mientras que en los otros dos las mamografías fueron normales. La ecografía mostró la presencia de quistes con ecos internos difusos en los dos casos con mamografías normales. Conclusiones: Los TML son lesiones mamarias que pueden manifestarse como un nódulo palpable de baja sospecha en la exploración física, como microcalcificaciones sospechosas en mamografía o como quistes con ecos internos difusos en ecografía</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);47(1): 23-25, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036906</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores mucocele-like de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31271^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9271^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
