<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10852</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ustekinumab to treat Crohn's disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ustekinumab is a monoclonal antibody directed against the p40 subunit, which is part of interleukins IL-12 and IL-23. The efficacy of ustekinumab versus placebo in terms of clinical response and remission of induction has been shown in phase3 clinical trials. When used as subcutaneous maintenance therapy, the therapeutic benefit of ustekinumab over placebo has been confirmed in both clinical response and remission in patients who have responded clinically to induction therapy. In addition, ustekinumab has demonstrated an improvement in mucosal healing parameters. The safety profile of the drug has been good, with low infection rates (without reactivation of tuberculosis) and absence of tumour reporting. The development of drug immunogenicity appears to be rare. In summary, ustekinumab is a promising treatment option in patients with Crohn's disease, as an alternative to anti-TNF&amp;#945; drugs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chaparro, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gisbert, Javier P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ustekinumab es un anticuerpo monoclonal dirigido frente a la subunidad p40, que forma parte de las interleucinas IL-12 y IL-23. En los ensayos clínicos fase3, ustekinumab ha demostrado su eficacia frente a placebo, en términos de respuesta clínica y remisión de la inducción. Cuando se ha empleado como terapia de mantenimiento por vía subcutánea, ustekinumab ha confirmado su beneficio terapéutico (sobre placebo) tanto en la respuesta clínica como en la remisión, en pacientes que habían respondido clínicamente a la terapia de inducción. Adicionalmente, ustekinumab ha demostrado una mejoría de los parámetros de curación mucosa. El perfil de seguridad del fármaco ha sido bueno, con tasas de infecciones infrecuentes (sin reactivación de tuberculosis) y ausencia de descripción de tumores. El desarrollo de inmunogenicidad frente al fármaco parece ser infrecuente. En resumen, ustekinumab representa una prometedora opción de tratamiento en pacientes con enfermedad de Crohn, como alternativa a los fármacos anti-TNF&amp;#945; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;40(10): 688-698, dic. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ustekinumab en el tratamiento de la enfermedad de Crohn</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
