<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90284</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">To what extent is child-to-parent violence bidirectional?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Child-to-parent violence is a family problem that has remained obscured for decades. The main purpose of this study was to explore gender differences in victims and perpetrators of child-to-parent violence. The importance of intra-family violence in the development of this type of violent behavior was also studied. The sample comprised 485 adolescents from the province of Gipuzkoa (Spain), of both sexes, taken from 9 schools and aged 12 to 18. As found in many previous studies, sons were more likely to be perpetrators of physical abuse than daughters. Although mothers suffered more psychological and emotional abuse than fathers, there were no differences between mothers and fathers with regard to physical abuse from their children. The hypothesis of the bidirectionality of violence was confirmed for physical violence in the male group that battered their parents. Similarly, marital violence (violence between parents) was a predictor of the three types of child-to-parent abusive behaviours (physical, psychological and emotional) for the male group. Moreover, we found three psychological variables in adolescents (drug abuse, self-esteem and anxiety) that emerged as predictors of child-to-parent violence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ibabe, Izaskun</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaureguizar, Joana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La violencia filio-parental es un problema familiar que ha permanecido en la oscuridad durante décadas. El objetivo principal de este estudio fue comprobar las diferencias de género respecto a las víctimas y a los perpetradores de violencia filio-parental. Se estudió también la importancia de la violencia intra-familiar en el desarrollo de las conductas violen-tas de hijos contra sus progenitores. La muestra estuvo compuesta de 485 adolescentes de la provincia de Gipuzkoa (España), de ambos sexos, de edades comprendidas entre 12 y 18 años y procedentes de 9 centros escolares. Al igual que en muchos estudios previos, los hijos varones ejercían más violencia física contra sus padres que las hijas. Aunque las madres sufrían más abuso psicológico y emocional que los padres, no había diferencias en cuanto a la violencia física. Se verificó la hipótesis de la bidireccionalidad de la violencia física para el grupo de hijos varones que agreden a sus padres. Del mismo modo, la violencia entre los padres predecía los tres tipos de violencia filio-parental (físico, psicológico y emocional) en el grupo de hijos varones. Por otra parte, se encontraron tres variables psicológicas de los adolescentes (consumo de drogas, autoestima y ansiedad) predictoras de las conductas violentas de éstos contra sus progenitores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(2): 265-277, mayo-ago. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90284</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Hasta qué punto la violencia filio-parental es bidireccional?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
