<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-32934</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intratympanic gentamicin in patients with Ménière's disease: analysis of our protocol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: The aim of this paper is to analyze the peculiarities of a protocol for treatment with intratympanic gentamicin in patients with Ménière's disease. MATERIAL AND METHODS: 71 patients with unilateral disabling Ménière's disease were followed for a period longer than two years after concluding the treatment. AAO-HNS criteria for reporting treatment results was followed. Gentamicin was applied weekly until of symptoms or signs of vestibular hypofunction were noticed. RESULTS: Control of vertigo was obtained in 83% of the patients while in 24% a second course was needed beacuse of vertigo recurrence. 66% of the patients developed a typical syndrome of unilateral vestibular hypofunction in the ear treated. CONCLUSIONS: Ending weekly injections of gentamicin for the treatment of patients with Ménière's disease when signs of vestibular hypofunction appear warrants a control of vertigo similar to that obtained in other series (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar las características y los resultados de un protocolo de tratamiento con gentamicina intratimpánica para la Enfermedad de Ménière. Material y métodos: Se estudiaron 71 con enfermedad de Ménière unilateral seguidos por un período superior a 2 años después de finalizado el tratamiento. Se utilizaron los criterios de la AAO-HNS para el diagnóstico y seguimiento de estos pacientes. La gentamicina se aplicó hasta la aparición de síntomas o signos de hipofunción vestibular unilateral. Resultados: Se obtuvo un control del vértigo en el 83 por ciento de los enfermos si bien en un 24 por ciento fue necesario repetir el tratamiento por recurrencia de los síntomas. El 66 por ciento de los pacientes presentaron un cuadro clínico, vestíbulo-espinal y oculomotor típico de la desaferentización periférica unilateral aguda. Conclusiones: El protocolo de tratamiento con gentamicina intratimpánica resulta eficaz en el control de los síntomas siendo comparable a otras series de tratamiento a dosis única o semanales también (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;55(6): 270-276, jun. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gentamicina intratimpánica para la enfermedad de Ménière: análisis de la técnica</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Martín Sanz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-32934</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d287</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24913</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8745^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14832^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
