<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162792</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A case report: Nursing interventions on a patient with anaphylactic shock in ICU</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The care plan of a 42-year-old woman with anaphylactic shock, secondary to ingestion of amoxicillin/clavulanic acid, with upper airway involvement due to laryngeal angioedema, is presented. Previously she had had two episodes of angioedema of unknown origin. The incidence of this phenomenon is between 3.2 and 10 cases/100,000 people/year. Clinical observation: An evaluation was made and three altered necessities stood out: breathing and circulation (she needed mechanical ventilation and noradrenalin perfusion), elimination (she required furosemide to keep an acceptable diuresis time), and hygiene and skin protection (she presented generalised hyperaemia, lip, lingual and oropharyngeal oedema). The hospital's Clinical Research Ethics Committee requested the patient's informed consent to access her clinical history. Interventions: According to the altered necessities, seven diagnoses were prioritised according to NANDA taxonomy: risk of allergic response, risk of infection, risk of ineffective renal perfusion, decreased cardiac output, impaired spontaneous ventilation, risk of unstable blood glucose level, and risk of dysfunctional gastrointestinal motility. Discussion and conclusions: Scores of outcome criteria showed a favourable evolution after 24 hours. The development of a standardised NANDA-NOC-NIC language in the clinical case presented allowed us to organise the nursing work, facilitating recording and normalising clinical practice. As a limitation of this case, we didn&#146;t have serial plasma levels of histamine and tryptase to assess the evolution of anaphylactic symptoms. Highlight the importance of health education in a patient with a history of angioedema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zariquiey-Esteva, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santa Candela, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Se presenta el plan de cuidados de una señora de 42 años con shock anafiláctico secundario a la ingesta de amoxiclavulánico, con compromiso de la vía aérea superior por angioedema de laringe. Previamente tuvo 2 episodios de angioedema. La incidencia de este fenómeno oscila entre 3,2 y 10 casos/100.000 personas/año. Observación clínica: Se realizó una valoración donde destacaron tres necesidades alteradas: respiración y circulación (precisó ventilación mecánica invasiva y perfusión de noradrenalina), eliminación (requirió furosemida para mantener diuresis horarias aceptables) e higiene y protección de la piel (presentó hiperemia generalizada, edema labial, lingual y orofaríngeo). El Comité de Ética de Investigación Clínica del Hospital solicitó el consentimiento informado de la paciente para el acceso a la historia clínica. Intervenciones: De acuerdo con las necesidades destacadas, se priorizaron siete diagnósticos según la taxonomía NANDA: riesgo de respuesta alérgica, riesgo de infección, riesgo de perfusión renal ineficaz, disminución del gasto cardíaco, deterioro de la ventilación espontánea, riesgo de nivel de glucemia inestable y riesgo de motilidad gastrointestinal disfuncional. Discusión y conclusiones: Los criterios de resultados evidenciaron una evolución favorable pasadas 24h. El desarrollo del lenguaje estandarizado NANDA-NOC-NIC en el caso clínico presentado nos permitió organizar metodológicamente el trabajo enfermero, facilitando el registro y normalizando la práctica. Como limitación, no se dispuso de niveles plasmáticos de histamina y triptasa para valorar la evolución del cuadro anafiláctico. Destacar la importancia de la educación sanitaria en una paciente con antecedentes de angioedema (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;28(2): 80-91, abr.-jun. 2017. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162792</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">A propósito de un caso: intervenciones enfermeras a una paciente con shock anafiláctico en la UCI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d721^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23500^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9916^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
