<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036790</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Value of the diagnosis of malabsorption of lactose in patients with syndrome or irritable intestine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Basis: In occasions one advises to suppressthe lacteal products to patients with Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS) without evidence of malabsorption.The aim is to study the frequency of malabsorption of lactose in patients diagnosed of IBS. Method: The frequency is studied of malabsorption of lactose to 50 patients with IBS and25 healthy controls, test of hydrogen is realized exhaled to evaluate malabsorption. Results: It was observed malabsorption of lactose in 12/50 (24%) patients with IBS and5/25 (20%) controls. After removing the milk for six months in those patients diagnosed of IBSand that gave alone positive, 1/12 (8,33%) patients improved of his symptomatology of partialform. Conclusions: The identification of the malabsorption of lactose in patients with diagnosis of syndrome of irritable intestine not presents advantages. A significantly major frequency does not estimate of malabsorption in patients with IBS that in healthy controls, in addition in our study the cases with malabsorption diagnosed of IBS, the improvement is low when the milk of the diet is suppressed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baños, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salama, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morán, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medranda, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercader, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: En ocasiones se aconseja suprimirlos lácteos a pacientes con Síndrome de Intestino Irritable (SII) sin evidencia de malabsorción. El objetivo es estudiar la frecuencia de malabsorción de lactosa en pacientes diagnosticados de SII. Método: Se estudia la frecuencia de malabsorción de lactosa a 50 pacientes con SII y 25controles sanos, se realiza test de hidrógeno espirado para evaluar dicha malabsorción. Resultados: Se observó malabsorción de lactosa en 12/50 (24%) pacientes con SII y 5/25(20%) sujetos control. Tras retirar la leche durante seis meses en aquellos pacientes diagnosticados de SII y que dieron positivo para malabsorción de lactosa, sólo mejoraron su sintomatología1/12 (8,33%) pacientes. Conclusiones: La identificación de malabsorción de lactosa en pacientes con diagnóstico de SII presenta escasas ventajas. No se aprecia una frecuencia significativamente mayor de malabsorción en pacientes con SII que en controles sanos, además en nuestro estudio los casos con malabsorción diagnosticados de SII, mejoran en una pequeña proporción cuando se suprime la leche de la dieta</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;25(2): 10-13, mar.-abr. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036790</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor del diagnóstico de malabsorción de lactosa en pacientes con síndrome de intestino irritable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7964^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7964^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23695^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
