<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049521</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">History of the chronic pain treatment: the spanish experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It was at the beginning of the twentieth century when a rational and efficient chronic pain treatment was first used. The practice of neurotomies, neurolisis and therapeutic blockades of peripheral, cranial and even intracranial nervous structures were initiated at the same time. A little bit later was the beginning ofthe sympathetic nervous system blockades with chemical substances with the intention of interrupt the afferent nervous current that transmit the pain sensation.This treatments and clinical essays were first employed in Germany, France, United States of America and Great Britain where many doctors were famous due to their good practice. Otherwise, the labour done by the Spanish doctors was practically unknown.The aim of this study is to know and evaluate the implantation of these treatments against chronic pain in Spain. Our investigation includes a 75 years period, between 1900 and 1975, and it is based on the search, analysis and interpretation of an important documental material that we could find in the libraries of our country. Even though it does not try to be exhaustive &#150;it would exceed this study limits&#150; it turns out to be a good representation of the chronic pain treatment topic. A chronological register of the treatment techniques was done as these were being introduced in clinic and they were classified in based of its actuation over central, peripheral or sympathetic nervous system. After the analysis of this documentation we deduce that the chronic pain, rebel to usual treatment, had an early an strong implantation in Spain, simultaneously to other countries of our environment. It was also possible to verify that in many cases were our doctors who overcame with their investigations the doctors of the countries that leaded the studies about pain</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Luis, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un tratamiento racional y eficaz del dolor crónico no comenzó a ser utilizado en la clínica hasta los primeros años del pasado siglo XX. De manera paralela, se iniciaron las prácticas de las neurotomías, neurólisis y bloqueos terapéuticos de las estructuras nerviosas periféricas, craneales y aun intracraneales, y, algo más adelante, del sistema nervioso simpático, con el propósito de interrumpir la corriente nerviosa aferente transmisora de la sensación dolorosa. Estos tratamientos y ensayos clínicos comenzaron en Alemania, Francia, EE.UU. e Inglaterra y están bien documentados, al contrario de lo que ocurre en nuestro país donde la labor realizada por los médicos españoles es prácticamente desconocida. El propósito de este estudio es conocer y valorar adecuadamente qué implantación tuvieron, en España, los distintos procedimientos terapéuticos. Nuestra investigación abarca un periodo de 75 años &#150;entre 1900 y 1975&#150;, y está basada en la búsqueda, análisis e interpretación de un importante conjunto documental que hemos logrado reunir en bibliotecas y hemerotecas del estado. Aunque no pretende ser del todo exhaustiva &#150;lo que se escaparía de los límites de este trabajo-, representa un segmento importante de la misma. Se hizo un ordenamiento cronológico de las técnicas de tratamiento a medida que estas iban introduciéndose en la clínica, y a efectos metodológicos fueron clasificadas según se actuase sobre el sistema nervioso central y periférico o sobre el simpático. Del análisis de esta documentación se deduce que el tratamiento del dolor crónico, rebelde al tratamiento habitual, tuvo en España una implantación temprana e importante, paralelamente a lo que acontecía en países de nuestro entorno. También se pudo constatar que, en muchos casos, nuestros médicos se anticiparon con sus investigaciones a los de países que, en aquellos tiempos, lideraban los más importantes estudios sobre el tratamiento del dolor</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;16(3): 125-139, jul.-sept. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049521</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historia del tratamiento del dolor crónico. La experiencia española (1900-1970)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13942^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6825</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14676^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9600^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
