<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049367</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interrelationship among "NANDA, NOC y NIC". A pilot study and an evaluation of a nursing document</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: a) to determine the effectiveness of a nursing document which integrates nursing diagnoses, nursing treatments/actions (N/C), and results(NOC); b) to verify the application of the a forementioned document in a hospitalization unit. Materials and Methods: A descriptive, transversal and observational study. Materials: nursing documents (NANOA, NIC and NOC taxonomies). Phases: 1st: analysis of the content in the nursing documentation for 23 pneumonic patients:    Selection of nursing diagnoses and the most frequent interdependent problems. 2nd: Selection of results and nursing treatment/actions. 3rd: Elaboration of the document and a description of the Likert sea les to define the state of the indicators for each result. 4th: A pilot study of the document applied to 12 patients.    Conclusions: the application of the document permits one to identify the real status of a patient; to establish specific objectives; to improve the recording of data; to observe the effectiveness of treatment; to include educational activities; to give greater continuity and quality to a treatment plan</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tina Majuelo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Perea, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomez de Segura Navarro, Carlota</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guembe Ibáñez, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esain Larrambe, Ainhoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Narvaiza Solls, M. Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: a) determinar la eficacia de un documento de enfermería que integre diagnósticos de Enfermería (DE), intervenciones (NIC) y resultados (NOC); b) comprobar la aplicación de dicho documento en una unidad de hospitalización.    Material y métodos: estudio descriptivo, transversal y observacional. Material: documento de enfermería (taxonomías NANDA, NIC y NOC). Fases: I: análisis de contenido de la documentación de enfermería de 23 pacientes neumológicos: selección de diagnósticos de enfermería y problemas interdependientes más frecuentes. II: selección de resultados e intervenciones. III: elaboración del documento y descripción de las escalas de Likert para definir el estado de los indicadores de cada resultado. IV: estudio piloto del documento aplicándolo a 12 pacientes.    Conclusiones: la aplicación del documento permite identificar el estado real del paciente; establecer objetivos específicos; mejorar el registro de datos; evidenciar la eficacia de las intervenciones; incluir actividades educativas; dar mayor continuidad y calidad al plan de cuidados</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;29(7/8): 501-506, jul.-ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interrelación entre NANDA, NOC y NIC. Estudio piloto, valoración de un documento de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29491^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13340</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
