<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113843</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic containment and satisfaction of nursing staff after the change of infusion sets at hospital santa caterina of salt (Girona)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In situations such as the current economic crisis it is very important to consider the quality-price of healthcare materials. One of the most commonly used by nurses are the intravenous infusion sets. It is described the features of a new intravenous infusion set, that increases patient safety and improves the nursing care workload. Objectives: We suggested an analysis of the economic containment, as well as an appraisal of the nursing staff satisfaction, after the change of the intravenous infusion sets by new sets with different performances. Methodology: The study was conducted in the four hospital units at Hospital Santa Caterina of Salt (Girona): unit A (obstetrics and pediatrics), unit B (traumatology-surgery), unit F (internal medicine) and unit D (convalescence-palliative care). A cost study was developed comparing the costs in 2010 for the old intravenous infusion set with costs in 2011 for the new infusion set. A survey to assess the nursing staff satisfaction on the new infusion set was carried out in 2012 with 91 nurses (75.8% of nurses working in the four units) . Results: It has obtained an average decrease of 41.44% in consumption of infusion sets with Y and a 41.09% in infusion sets without Y. This change of infusion sets has represented a financial saving of 8.003 &#128; on sets with Y and 2.017 &#128; on sets without Y. And regarding the nursing satisfaction survey the results have mostly shown a high level of satisfaction in their management. In addition nurses surveyed considered that makes their task easier and improves the patient safety in hospital. Conclusions: The change by the new infusion set has reduced the consumption of infusion sets and meant considerable savings in costs of infusion sets, both sets with Y as in without Y. Nurses mostly manifest a high level of satisfaction(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boix Llebot, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilalta Altés, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batlle Joher, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jurado Pérez, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En situaciones de crisis económica como la actual es muy importante considerar la relación calidad-precio de los materiales sanitarios. Uno de los más utilizados por el personal de enfermería se trata de los equipos de infusión endovenosa. Se describe un nuevo equipo de infusión endovenosa con prestaciones nuevas que aumenta la seguridad del paciente y ayuda en el trabajo asistencial de enfermería. Objetivos. Se plantea un análisis de la contención económica, así como una valoración de la satisfacción del personal de enfermería, al efectuar el cambio de los equipos de infusión endovenosa por equipos nuevos con prestaciones diferentes. Metodología. El estudio se realizó en las cuatro unidades de hospitalización del Hospital Santa Caterina de Salt (Girona): hospitalización A (materno-infantil), hospitalización B (cirugía ortopédica traumatológica), hospitalización F (medicina interna) y hospitalización D (convalecencia-paliativos).Se elaboró un estudio de costes de los gastos con el equipo antiguo de infusión endovenosa en el año 2010, y los del año 2011 con el nuevo equipo. Para valorar la satisfacción del personal de enfermería sobre el nuevo equipo de infusión se realizó una encuesta durante el año 2012 con 91 enfermeras (75,8% del total que trabajan en las cuatro unidades). Resultados. Se ha obtenido una disminución media del consumo de los equipos de un 41,44% con los equipos con Y y un 41,09% con los equipos sin Y. Este cambio de equipo de infusión ha representado un ahorro económico de 8.003 &#128; en los equipos con Y y de 2.017 &#128; en los equipos sin Y. Con relación a la encuesta de satisfacción del personal de enfermería, los resultados han mostrado mayoritariamente un nivel alto de la misma en su manejo. Además las enfermeras encuestadas han considerado que facilita su trabajo y mejora la seguridad del paciente hospitalizado. Conclusiones. El cambio por el nuevo equipo ha supuesto una reducción en el consumo de los equipos de infusión y un ahorro considerable en los costes de fungible, tanto en los equipos con Y como en los sin Y. El personal de enfermería manifiesta mayoritariamente un nivel alto de satisfacción(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;36(3): 180-184, mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contención económica y satisfacción del personal de enfermería en el cambio de los equipos de infusión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19210^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3376^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
