<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147449</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of chronic kidney disease in the occurrence of loss of tissue integrity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Calciphylaxis is characterized by calcification of arterioles, fibrosis and thrombosis which leads to the onset of ischemic skin ulcers and necrosis, and most often affects in patients with end stage renal disease. Treatment of calciphylaxis is varied, without effective therapeutic modality and poor prognosis, mainly due to sepsis secondary to infection of the skin lesions. Objective: To know the scientific production on calciphylaxis related to chronic kidney disease. Methodology: A literature review was conducted with a literature search in the following databases: PubMed / Medline, Scielo, Cuiden, ProQuest / Health and Medical Complete, IME and Google Scholar. Results: Sixty-one articles were selected for the study: 19 review articles, 13 originals and 29 clinical cases. The variables studied were: alterations in the metabolism of phosphorus, calcium and parathyroid hormone, several risk factors, distribution of injuries, death due to sepsis, medical treatment and nursing care. The most influential factors in the development of calciphylaxis are alterations in metabolism, obesity, diabetes, hypertension, low serum albumin and taking anticoagulants. Treatment involves multiple therapeutic measures aimed at controlling the metabolic disorders and cure of cutaneous manifestations. Conclusion: Calciphylaxis is an uncommon event with high mortality. The pathogenesis is unknown and from a therapeutic point of view, there is no specific treatment, so that a multidisciplinary approach is essential for its prevention and early detection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Blancas, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Montero, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moyano Espadero, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estepa del Árbol, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La calcifilaxis se caracteriza por calcificación de arteriolas, fibrosis y trombosis que conduce a la aparición de úlceras cutáneas isquémicas y necrosis, y afecta con mayor frecuencia a pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica terminal. El tratamiento de la calcifilaxis es variado, sin existir una modalidad terapéutica eficaz, y presenta mal pronóstico, principalmente por la sepsis secundaria a infección de las lesiones cutáneas. Objetivo: Conocer la producción científica sobre la calcifilaxis relacionada con la enfermedad renal crónica. Metodología: Se ha llevado a cabo una revisión bibliográfica con una búsqueda de bibliografía en las principales bases de datos PubMed/Medline, Scielo, Cuiden, ProQuest/Health and Medical Complete, IME y Google Académico. Resultados: Se seleccionaron 61 artículos para la realización del estudio: 19 artículos de revisión, 13 originales y 29 casos clínicos. Las variables estudiadas han sido las alteraciones en el metabolismo del fósforo, calcio y hormona paratiroidea, varios factores de riesgo, distribución de las lesiones, fallecimiento por sepsis, tratamiento médico y cuidados de enfermería. Los factores más influyentes en la aparición de calcifilaxis son las alteraciones en el metabolismo, obesidad, diabetes, hipertensión, baja albúmina sérica y toma de anticoagulantes. El tratamiento implica múltiples medidas terapéuticas, dirigidas al control de las alteraciones del metabolismo y la cura de las manifestaciones cutáneas.  Conclusiones: La calcifilaxis es una entidad poco frecuente y con una elevada mortalidad. La patogénesis es desconocida y desde el punto de vista terapéutico, no existe un tratamiento específico, por lo que es fundamental un enfoque multidisciplinar, para su prevención y detección precoz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;18(4): 290-302, oct.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147449</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la enfermedad renal crónica terminal en la aparición de pérdida de la integridad tisular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22298^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22298^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22298^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
