<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040137</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Primary hypothyroidism after radiotherapy in patients with head and neck cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Radiotherapy in the treatment of cancer of the head and neck can cause hypothyroidism. Our aim was to study the development of thyroid hypofunction in these patients. Patients and methods: We performed a retrospective analysis of 194 patients who underwent radiotherapy for head and neck cancer. Thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) and free thyroxine (FT4) levels were determined at 3, 6 and 12 months after radiotherapy and then annually during follow-up. Hypothyroidism was classified as subclinical (SHT) (an increase of TSG and normal FT4 levels) and clinical (CHT) (an increase of TSH and a decrease of FT4). The association between hypothyroidism and age, sex, histological type of the tumor, radiation dose and use of chemotherapy was analyzed. Results: With a mean follow-up of 4.2 years, 56 patients showed elevated TSH levels (SHT in 39 patients and CHT in 17). The mean time to diagnosis was 3.0 ± 1.8 years (SHT 2.6 ± 1.5 years, CHT 4 ± 1.9 years; p &lt; 0.05). Eighty percent of the patients were diagnosed between the second and the sixth year after radiotherapy. Age, histological type, radiation dose and use of chemotherapy did not affect the probability of developing hypothyroidism. Sex had a predictive value (66.6% in women versus 25.8% in men; p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions: The incidence rate of hypothyroidism after radiotherapy in patients with cancer of the head and neck is high. Prolonged follow-up of TSH levels should be performed in these patients after radiotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Massó, M. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alba, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basterra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapater, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El tratamiento con radioterapia en el cáncer de cabeza y cuello es una causa de hipotiroidismo. Nos proponemos estudiar el desarrollo de hipofunción tiroidea en estos pacientes. Pacientes y métodos: Se realizó un análisis retrospectivo de 194 pacientes tratados con radioterapia por cáncer de cabeza y cuello. Se determinó la tirotropina (TSH) y la tiroxina (T4) libre a los 3, los 6 y los 12 meses después de la radioterapia y anualmente durante el seguimiento. El hipotiroidismo se clasificó como subclínico (aumento de la TSH y la T4 libre normal) y clínico (aumento de la TSH y disminución de la T4 libre). Se analizó la relación del hipotiroidismo con edad, sexo, estirpe histológica del tumor, dosis de radiación y el uso de quimioterapia. Resultados: Con una media de seguimiento de 4,2 años, 56 pacientes presentaron elevación de la TSH (39 pacientes subclínico y 17 clínico). El tiempo medio para el diagnóstico fue de 3,0 ± 1,8 años (subclínico 2,6 ± 1,5 años, clínico 4 ± 1,9 años; p &lt; 0,05). El 80% de los pacientes fueron diagnosticados entre el segundo y el sexto año desde la radioterapia. La edad, la histología del tumor, la dosis de radiación y el uso de quimioterapia no modificaron la probabilidad de desarrollar hipotiroidismo. El sexo demostró un valor predictor (un 66,6 frente a un 25,8% en mujeres y varones, respectivamente; p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: La tasa de incidencia de hipotiroidismo después de radioterapia en pacientes con cáncer de cabeza y cuello es elevada. Es importante determinar la TSH durante un largo período de tiempo después de la radioterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(8): 387-390, oct. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040137</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipotiroidismo primario posradioterapia en pacientes con cáncer de cabeza y cuello</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14349^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7217^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
