<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041533</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of AZF regions of Y chromosome in males with idiopathic infertility. Analysis of two methods of molecular diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: It is well known that both azoospermia and oligozoospermia are associated to microdeletions of single tagged sites (STS) in the long arm of the Y chromosome. Characterization of deletions is carried out by polimerase chain reaction, although the number and regions included in the analysis varies between laboratories. The aim of this study was to analyze the presence of chromosome Y microdeletions using 2 different sets of STSs. Patients and Method: We analysed the presence of microdeletions in the Yq chromosome in 30 patients with idiopathic male infertility, using 2 sets of STSs, those proposed by the European Molecular Genetics Quality Network (EMQN) as first choice and those of the Y Chromosome Deletion Detection System® (Promega). Results: AZF microdeletions were detected in 4 patients (13%). Only one case was detected simultaneously with both sets. Conclusion: In patients with idiopathic male infertility detection of AZF microdeletion in Y chromosome has important methodological problems. Further studies are needed to achieve a more reliable method to be used by clinical laboratories</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Macías, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miralles-García, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Sarmiento, Rogelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Isidoro-García, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corrales-Hernández, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La azoospermia y la oligospermia causantes de infertilidad masculina se asocian con deleciones en regiones que contienen secuencias no repetitivas en el brazo largo del cromosoma Y. La caracterización de estas deleciones se realiza mediante reacción en cadena de la polimerasa, aunque varían el número y la localización de las regiones estudiadas dependiendo de los laboratorios. En este estudio nos planteamos analizar la presencia de deleciones en el cromosoma Y de pacientes infértiles empleando dos métodos diferentes. Pacientes y método: Se ha estudiado a 30 pacientes con infertilidad idiopática masculina, siguiendo las recomendaciones de la EMQN (European Molecular Genetics Quality Network) y, en paralelo, con el test Y Chromosome Deletion Detection System® (Promega). Resultados: Hemos detectado deleciones en la región AZF en 4 pacientes (13%). En sólo un caso ambos sistemas la detectaron simultáneamente. Conclusiones: La detección de microdeleciones de las regiones AZF del cromosoma Y presenta problemas metodológicos. Se necesitan más estudios para conseguir un consenso sobre el método más fiable para aplicar este tipo de estudios a los laboratorios clínicos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);125(19): 731-733, nov. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041533</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de las regiones AZF del cromosoma Y en varones con infertilidad idiopática. Comparación de dos métodos de diagnóstico molecular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10031^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36519^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
