<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74312</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the clinical-biological features of infiltratingbreast carcinomas in women aged &lt; 40 years and tocompare then with those observed in women aged 40-45years with the same malignant tumours.Material and methods: The study group included two subgroups:a) 11 women aged &lt; 40 years; and b) 26 womenaged between 40 and 45 years. We assayed the levels of epidermalgrowth factor receptor in cell surfaces, as well as thecytosolic concentrations of estrogen receptor, progesteronereceptor, pS2 and cathepsin D. Tumor size, axillary involvement,distant metastasis, histological grade and cellular Sphase(SP) were taken account.Results: The breast carcinomas of patients aged &lt; 40 yrs.had higher concentrations of EGFR (p &lt; 0,05) and were moreoften EGFR positive (&gt; 5 fmol/mg prot.; p &lt; 0,01) and FS&gt; 7% (p &lt; 0,01). We did not observed any statistically differencesin the number of recurrences and deaths in both subgroupsof patients. The ER-negative/EGFR-positive pattern associatedsignificantly with the tumors of women aged between40 and 45 years, whereas the RE-negative/EGFR-negative associatedwith the tumors of patients aged less than 40 years.Conclusions: Our results suggest that the breast carcinomasin women aged &lt; 40 yrs. show a greater proliferation andEGFR expression than those of women aged between 40 and45 yrs., being associated with ER-negative/EGFR-negativepattern. Further studies are necessary to know the EGFR rolein breast carcinomas in young women(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruibal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pombo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar las características clínico-biológicas delos carcinomas mamarios de pacientes con edad &lt; 40 años ycompararlas con las de mujeres de edad comprendida entre40 y 45 años.Pacientes y método: Incluyen dos subgrupos: a) 11 mujerescon una edad &lt; 40 años; y b) 26 con edades comprendidasentre 40 y 45 años. Hemos determinado las concentracionesde EGFR en las membranas celulares, así como las delreceptor de estrógenos, de progesterona, pS2, y catepsina Dcitosólicas. Se consideró, además, el tamaño, afectación axilar,metástasis a distancia, grado y subtipo histológico, asícomo la fase de síntesis celular (FS).Resultados: Los tumores de mujeres &lt; 40 años mostraronmayores concentraciones de EGFR (p &lt; 0,05) y fueron másfrecuentemente EGFR positivo (&gt; 5 fmol/mg prot. &#150;p &lt;0,01&#150; y FS &gt; 7% &#150;p &lt; 0,01&#150;). No se constataron diferenciasen el número de recidivas y muertes observadas durante el seguimiento.El patrón tisular RE negativo/EGFR-negativo seasoció significativamente a tumores en mujeres entre los 40 y45 años, mientras que el patrón RE-negativo/EGFR-positivolo hizo con los de mujeres &lt; 40 años.Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados, sugieren que los carcinomasmamarios en mujeres &lt; 40 años parecen cursarcon una mayor proliferación y expresión de EGFR que losde mujeres con edad comprendida entre los 40 y 45 años,asociándose a un patrón tisular RE-negativo/EGFR-positivo;son necesarios más estudios para poder precisar el valordel EGFR en la biología de los carcinomas mamarios de mujeresjóvenes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);21(3): 96-99, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74312</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinomas infiltrantes mamarios en mujeres menores de 40 años: posible interés fisiopatológico del receptor del factor de crecimiento epidérmico (EGFR)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
