<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129974</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of two root canals in mandibular incisors: an experience with undergraduate students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The purpose of this ex vivo study was to evaluate, in mandibular incisors treated by undergraduate students of the pre-clinic area of USAL/AOA, the percentage of teeth with two canals and the comparison between the frequency of untreated root canals and the amount of root canals present. Material and methods. 76 human extracted mandibular incisors, endodontically treated by students, were radiographed in buccolingual and mesiodistal directions. Afterward, the teeth were transversally sectioned at different levels of the roots obtaining three sections: coronal, middle and apical. Then, the sections and the radiographs obtained were evaluated taking into consideration the number of root canals and those who were instrumented and filled in each specimen. The results of the percentage of root canals found were evaluated with a 95% confidence intervals (CI) calculated with the binomial distribution. In order to compare the frequency of untreated root canals and the amount of root canals present the Fisher exact probability test was used. Results. From the 76 mandibular incisors, 18 (23.7%) (CI 14.7%-34.8%) showed two canals, only in 1 (5.6%) of them both root canals were instrumented and filled. In the other 17 (94.4%) (CI 72.7%-99.9%) one of the canals was missed. Statistical significant differences were observed between the frequency of untreated root canals and the amount of root canals present (P&lt;0.001). Conclusions. In consideration with this experience, it was pointed out that it is necessary to insist, in the undergraduate training, on the importance of the anatomical complexity of the mandibular incisors and that the proper clinical procedures for its treatment are to be enhanced (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Goldberg, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miraglia Cantarini, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantarini, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El propósito de este estudio fue evaluar, ex vivo, en incisivos inferiores tratados por alumnos de grado en el área preclínica de la USAL/AOA, el porcentaje de dientes que presentaban dos conductos y comparar la frecuencia de conductos no tratados según la cantidad de conductos presentes. Material y métodos. Setenta y seis incisivos mandibulares humanos extraídos fueron tratados endodónticamente por alumnos de grado y luego radiografiados en sentido vestibulolingual y mesiodistal. Las raíces de las piezas dentarias fueron seccionadas transversalmente a diferentes niveles obteniendo tres cortes transversales: coronario, medio y apical. A continuación se examinaron los cortes y las radiografías, y se evaluaron la cantidad de conductos radiculares presentes y los instrumentados y obturados de cada especimen. Los resultados obtenidos a partir del porcentaje de conductos encontrados fueron evaluados con un intervalo de confianza del 95% (IC) a partir de la distribución binomial. Para comparar la frecuencia de conductos no tratados según la cantidad de conductos presentes se empleó la prueba de probabilidad exacta de Fisher. Resultados. De los 76 incisivos inferiores, 18 (23,7%) (IC 14,7%-34,8%) presentaban dos conductos radiculares, de los cuales solo en 1 (5,6%) ambos conductos fueron instrumentados y obturados. En los 17 (94,4%) (IC 72,7%-99,9%) incisivos restantes uno de los conductos fue ignorado. La evaluación comparativa entre la frecuencia de conductos no tratados y la cantidad de conductos presentes mostró diferencias estadísticas significativas (p&lt; 0,001). Conclusiones. En consideración de la experiencia expuesta, se destaca la necesidad de insistir en la docencia de grado, en la importancia de la complejidad anatómica de los incisivos inferiores y resaltar los procedimientos clínicos apropiados para su tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);31(3): 117-121, jul.-sept. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129974</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de dos conductos radiculares en incisivos inferiores: una experiencia con alumnos de grado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55116</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14485^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13722^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
