<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166463</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The pharmacology and clinical management of dabigatran</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dabigatran etexilate is an oral anticoagulant that is effective in preventing embolism in patients with nonvalvular atrial fibrillation. It is a prodrug that is rapidly converted to dabigatran, a potent, reversible direct thrombin inhibitor. The plasma concentration of dabigatran reaches a peak 2 hours after administration and the drug&#146;s half-life is 14 hours. The anticoagulant activity of dabigatran is predictable and it is not necessary to monitor the clotting time. The drug is primarily eliminated by the kidneys, largely in an unaltered form. Renal failure predisposes to its accumulation. Dabigatran is not metabolized by cytochrome P450 isoenzymes and has few drug interactions. Dabigatran dose-adjustment should be considered in elderly patients and in those who have a low body weight, who are at a high risk of bleeding or who are receiving concomitant treatment with verapamil or antiplatelet agents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Armenta, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugada, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dabigatrán etexilato es un anticoagulante oral eficaz en la prevención de embolias en pacientes con fibrilación auricular no valvular. Es un profármaco que se transforma rápidamente en dabigatrán, un inhibidor potente, directo y reversible de la trombina. Tras su administración alcanza el pico plasmático a las 2h y tiene una vida media de 14h. Su actividad anticoagulante es predecible y no precisa monitorización de los tiempos de coagulación. El fármaco se elimina fundamentalmente por los riñones, mayormente sin alteraciones. La insuficiencia renal favorece su acumulación. El dabigatrán no se metaboliza por las isoenzimas del citocromo P450 y presenta escasas interacciones farmacológicas. Debe considerarse ajustar la dosis de dabigatrán en pacientes con edad avanzada, bajo peso corporal, alto riesgo hemorrágico o en tratamiento concomitante con verapamilo o antiagregantes plaquetarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);12(supl.B): 18b-24b, 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166463</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Farmacología de dabigatrán y su manejo clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55927^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34262^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4409</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23506^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23521^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
