<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047867</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Up-date in Intensive Medicine: ARDS Inflammatory response and apoptosis in acute pulmonary injury</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the principal mechanisms of pulmonary injury in acute respiratory distress is due to the effects of the precipitated inflammatory response. The damage produced to the alveolar epithelium and underlying endothelium depends on the sequestration and activation of inflammatory cells, which in turn exert their actions through mediators. On the other hand, apoptosis is a mechanism responsible for epithelial damage and regulation of inflammation. Response of the lung tissue subjected to mechanical ventilation stimulus is added to the previous mechanisms. All these processes flow into a series of common pathways of cellular activation. Knowledge of these mechanisms could serve to identify which patients would benefit from a specific treatment before applying therapies that act indiscriminately in the inflammatory response</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Albaiceta, G. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taboada, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedreira, P. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Prieto, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Uno de los principales mecanismos de lesión pulmonar en el distrés respiratorio agudo se debe a los efectos de la respuesta inflamatoria desencadenada. El daño producido al epitelio alveolar y al endotelio subyacente depende del secuestro y activación de células inflamatorias, que a su vez ejercen sus acciones a través de mediadores. Por otro lado, la apoptosis es un mecanismo responsable de daño epitelial y de regulación de la inflamación. A los anteriores mecanismos se añade la respuesta del tejido pulmonar sometido al estímulo de la ventilación mecánica. Todos estos procesos desembocan en una serie de vías comunes de activación celular. El conocimiento de estos mecanismos podría servir para identificar qué pacientes se beneficiarían de un tratamiento concreto, antes que aplicar terapias que actúan de manera indiscriminada en la respuesta inflamatoria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);30(6): 268-275, ago. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047867</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta inflamatoria y apoptosis en la lesión pulmonar aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8345^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8345^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
