<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038303</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in the surgical indications for posttraumatic intradural lesions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The surgical treatment of focal intradural lesions is still a matter of considerable debate. This is especially important in the decision to evacuate brain contusions. We present the results of a prospective observational study in which the main goal was to analyze intracenter variability in the indication for surgery in focal posttraumatic intradural lesions in a department of Neurosurgery of a University Hospital with a specialized neurotrauma unit.  Clinical material and methods. Between May 1 and December 31, 2001, 32 patients with a closed traumatic brain injury and an intradural posttraumatic focal lesion were included. The patients studied were a subgroup included in the European multicenter observational study of the management of intradural lesions conducted under the aegis of the European Brain Injury Consortium (EBIC).  Results. Intradural lesions &gt; 25cc were immediately evacuated. Nine out of thirteen patients with lesions &lt; 25cc also underwent surgery due to intracranial hypertension or neuroworsening. In all patients in whom lesions were surgically evacuated, the postoperative CT-scan showed neuroradiological improvement of the signs of mass effect or midline shift.  Conclusions. In our center, we found no evidence of significant variability in the indications for surgery in intradural lesions of more than 25 cc. However, significant differences were detected among neurosurgeons in the surgical indications for lesions below 25cc. The small sample analyzed precludes generalization of these conclusions. The definitive results of the EBIC study will provide the neurosurgical community with a better understanding of variability in the management of these lesions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sahuquillo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mena, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arikan, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilalta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riveiro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garnacho, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poca, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El tratamiento de las lesiones focales intradurales continúa siendo motivo de controversia. Esto es especialmente importante en la decisión de evacuar contusiones cerebrales. Presentamos los resultados de un estudio prospectivo y observacional, cuyo objetivo ha sido analizar la variabilidad en las indicaciones quirúrgicas de lesiones focales intradurales postraumáticas en un servicio de neurocirugía perteneciente a un hospital universitario, dotado de una unidad especializada en neurotraumatología.  Material y métodos. Entre el 1 de mayo y el 31 de diciembre de 2001, se incluyeron 32 pacientes con un traumatismo craneoencefálico (TCE) cerrado, con lesiones focales intradurales. Estos pacientes constituyen la aportación que nuestro centro realizó en el estudio multicéntrico y observacional sobre el manejo de lesiones intradurales dirigido por el European Brain Injury Consortium (EBIC).  Resultados. Las lesiones intradurales de volumen &gt; 25 cc. se evacuaron de forma inmediata al diagnóstico. Nueve de los 13 pacientes con lesiones  25 cc. Sin embargo, existen discrepancias en las indicaciones quirúrgicas de las lesiones con volumen &lt; 25 cc. Los resultados definitivos del estudio del EBIC permitirán conocer mejor la variabilidad existente en el manejo de este tipo de pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);16(2): 108-116, abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038303</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad en las indicaciones quirúrgicas de las lesiones intradurales postraumáticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2585^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3264^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6558</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6410^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24697</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34241</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1956^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
