<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043952</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Palisading dermatofibroma: an unusual histologic variant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report a new case of an unusual variant of dermatofibromaof a 38-year-old man in which nuclear palisading isa prominent feature. Histopathologically, the lesions werecharacterized by areas of nuclear palisading with formationof Verocay-like bodies in addition to the more typical featuresof the «fibrous» variant of dermatofibroma. This neoplasmshould be differentiated from benign and malignantskin tumors with a palisading pattern. Pathologists and cliniciansshould know of the existence of this type of dermatofibromaand should avoid overdiagnosis and overtreatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Solís García, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Sánchez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles Frías, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro Gabalón, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Sánchez-Vizcaíno, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta un caso de esta infrecuente variedad de dermatofibromaen un varón de 38 años cuya principal característicaes la disposición en empalizada de los núcleos. Histopatológicamente,la lesión estaba caracterizada por áreasde empalizada nuclear con formación de cuerpos de tipoVerocay, junto a áreas clásicas de dermatofibroma tipofibroso. Esta neoplasia debería ser diferenciada de otrostumores benignos y malignos cutáneos con patrón en empalizada.Patólogos y clínicos deberían conocer la existenciade este tipo de dermatofibroma, que no comporta peor pronósticoni tratamiento adicional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;38(1): 42-44, ene.-mar. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dermatofibroma con empalizadas. Una variante histológica singular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32848^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24250^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32639^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31407^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13259^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
