<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146315</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical evaluation of the Baska Mask ® laryngeal mask in adult patients in ambulatory surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the clinical performance of the Baska Mask®, a new second-generation supraglottic airway device with a self-inflating cuff and two side suction channels for continuous aspiration. Material and methods. Eighty adult patients without difficult airways were prospectively included. Ease of insertion and number of attempts needed, quality of ventilation, airway seal pressure, fibreoptic view, ease of gastric access, and complications were assessed. Sizes 3, 4, 5 were analyzed and compared. Results. First attempt insertion success rate was 88% and the overall rate was 100%, although additional maneuvers were necessary in 44% of the cases. The ventilation was adequate in 96%, with 39% of them requiring adjusting maneuvers. Size 3 needed significantly less adjustments, and achieved a higher seal pressure than sizes 4 and 5 combined. The airway seal pressure was 33 ± 7 cmH2O. Complete or partial vocal cords were visible in 90% of the 66 cases assessed. Partial obstruction, caused by distortion of the cuff-free border, was seen in 5%, and no glottic structures were identified in 5%. Gastric access was easy in all cases. Complications were mild and transient. Conclusions. The Baska Mask achieves a high seal pressure, effective ventilation, and a quick access to drain gastric contents. However, additional adjustment maneuvers are frequently required to insert the mask and to optimize ventilation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontanals, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San José, I de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Rojas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermoso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar el comportamiento clínico de la Baska Mask®, un nuevo dispositivo supraglótico de ventilación que incorpora un balón autoinflable y doble canal de aspiración. Material y métodos. Se incluyeron prospectivamente 80 pacientes sin criterios de vía aérea difícil. Se evaluaron el número de intentos y la facilidad de inserción, la ventilación, la presión de sellado de la vía aérea, la visión fibrobroncoscópica, el acceso gástrico y las complicaciones observadas. Se analizaron y compararon los tamaños 3, 4 y 5. Resultados. La tasa de éxito de inserción al primer intento fue del 88%, y la global, del 100%, aunque en el 44% de los casos fue necesario rotar o curvar el dispositivo. La ventilación fue eficaz en el 96%, requiriendo maniobras de ajuste en el 39%. La presión de sellado fue de 33 ± 7 cmH2O. El tamaño 3 requirió significativamente menos ajustes y obtuvo una presión de sellado más alta. La visión total o parcial de las cuerdas vocales se obtuvo en el 90% de los 66 casos evaluados, en el 5% se observó obstrucción parcial por distorsión del borde libre del balón, y en el 5% restante no se identificaron estructuras glóticas. La inserción de la sonda gástrica fue fácil en todos los casos. Las complicaciones fueron leves y transitorias. Conclusiones. La Baska Mask consiguió una presión de sellado elevada, una ventilación adecuada y un acceso gástrico rápido. Sin embargo, requirió con frecuencia aplicar maniobras de ajuste para la inserción y para obtener una ventilación adecuada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;62(10): 551-556, dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación clínica de la mascarilla laríngea Baska Mask ® en pacientes adultos en cirugía mayor ambulatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15097^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15228^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32868^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4905^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30112^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30675^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
