<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116664</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient with testosterone deficit syndrome and erectile dysfunction non-responder to PDE-5 inhibitors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Androgens play an essential role in the corporo-venous occlusive mechanism that provokes erection. Accordingly to various studies based on animal models, testosterone deficit syndrome causes an endothelial disorder in the corpora cavernosa with diminished secretion of NO, alteration of penile smooth muscle and tunica albuginea structure, and increase of the number of adipocytes within the erectile tissue, which favors fibrosis and impairs erection. All these alterations are reversible with the exogenous administration of androgens. There are not enough studies to get definitive conclusions about androgen supply improving erectile dysfunction in patients with hypogonadism. Studies have been published in which seems that exogenous testosterone could be useful in the treatment of this type of patients. Never screetheless, in most published randomized double blind studies comparing with placebo, testosterone supply does not provide greater benefit on erectile dysfunction than PDE-5 Inhibitors exclusively. All studies coincide in the need to optimize the treatment with PDE-5 Inhibitors since they do have proven to be effective for the treatment of erectile dysfunction in patients with testosterone deficit syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Portillo, Luis del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carballido, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Salamanca, Juan I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares Espinós, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Areche, Jennifer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Izquierdo, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moncada, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los andrógenos juegan un papel fundamental en el mecanismo corporo-venooclusivo que provoca la erección. Según diversos estudios basados en modelos animales, el déficit de testosterona provoca una alteración del endotelio de los cuerpos cavernosos con disminución de secreción de NO, alteración en la estructura del músculo liso y la túnica albugínea del pene y aumento de la cantidad de adipocitos en el tejido eréctil lo que favorece la fibrosis y dificulta la erección. Todas estas alteraciones son reversibles con la administración exógena de andrógenos. No existen estudios suficientes que permitan extraer conclusiones definitivas sobre que el aporte de andrógenos en pacientes con hipogonadismo mejore la función eréctil. Se han publicado estudios en los que parece que la testosterona exógena podría ser útil en el tratamiento de este tipo de pacientes. Sin embargo en la mayoría de estudios aleatorizados doble ciego y comparados con placebo publicados, la administración de testosterona no aporta mayor beneficio sobre la función eréctil que el tratamiento con inhibidores de la fosfodiesterasa 5 (PDE5) exclusivamente. En lo que coinciden todos los estudios es en la necesidad de optimizar el tratamiento con inhibidores de la PDE5 ya que éstos sí han demostrado ser efectivos para el tratamiento de la disfunción eréctil en pacientes con síndrome de déficit de testosterona (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(7): 723-728, sept. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116664</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paciente con SDT y DE no respondedor a 5IPDE</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54134^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
