<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64165</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Starting in the 1970s with valproate and carbamazepine several anticonvulsant drugs have been established as treatment option in bipolar disorder. Level I of evidence based medicine confirm the efficacy of valproate and carbamazepine in the treatment of mania but their role in maintenance therapy is less clear than of lithium. Level I of evidence based medicine also confirm the efficacy of lamotrigine in the treatment of depression and in the maintenance therapy of bipolar disorder. Oxcarbazepine is a chemical keto-derivative of carbamazepina with a similar structure and antiepileptic profile. Oxcarbazepine has less severe adverse effects and less pharmacological interactions than carbamazepine and valproate. The available evidence suggest that oxcarbazepine may be effective in the treatment of mania and in the maintenance treatment of bipolar disorder. Further double-blind placebo controlled studies are needed for confirm this statement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nieto, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde la década de 1970 con el valproato y la carbamazepina varios fármacos antiepilépticos se han establecido como opciones terapéuticas en el trastorno bipolar. Según el nivel I de la medicina basada en la evidencia se ha confirmado la eficacia del valproato y la carbamazepina en el tratamiento de la manía, si bien su papel en el tratamiento de mantenimiento es menos evidente que el del litio. La lamotrigina ha demostrado también con un nivel I de evidencia su eficacia en el tratamiento de la depresión y el mantenimiento del trastorno bipolar. La oxcarbazepina es un cetoanálogo de la carbamazepina con similar estructura y perfil antiepiléptico. La oxcarbazepina tiene menos efectos secundarios importantes y menos interacciones farmacológicas que la carbamazepina y el valproato. La evidencia disponible sugiere que la oxcarbazepina puede ser efectiva en el tratamiento de la manía y en el tratamiento de mantenimiento del trastorno bipolar. Son necesarios nuevos estudios doble-ciego controlados con placebo que lo confirmen definitivamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;36(supl.3): 28-38, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64165</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2256^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
