<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84973</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Coccygeal dermal sinus: Clinical relevance and management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The presence of a dermal sinus on a child's back is a common cause for paediatric neurosurgical consultation. The relative frequency of these lesions and fears on their possible clinical consequences enhances the importance of early diagnosis and treatment. With this work we aimed to search for the most relevant clinical features that might indicate an intradural penetration of the lesions and that may advise performing neuroimaging studies and a paediatric neurosurgical consultation. Patients and methods: The records pertaining to children diagnosed with sacro-coccygeal pits seen at our institution during the years 2005&#150;2009 were reviewed. A Pub Med search of the most relevant articles on the subject was also performed. Results: Thirty-two children diagnosed with sacro-coccygeal pits were seen at our institution in the study period. Most cases had been sent for neurosurgical consultation by their paediatricians, paediatric surgeons or paediatricians of the emergency services in our region. Seventeen patients were submitted to some neuroimaging study and 15 were evaluated only by physical examination. In no patient was an intradural penetration of the lesion observed. The lack of reports on coccygeal sinuses probably reflects the unimportance given to these lesions in the absence of neurological involvement. Conclusions: A detailed physical examination can reduce the number of neuroimaging studies, an intergluteal localization of the sinus being the most important diagnostic clue. Doubtful cases of an intradural penetration of the lesion can be further evaluated by ultrasound as a preliminary screening tool and by magnetic resonance and neurosurgical consultation if deemed necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Lage, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarejo Ortega, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galarza, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Felipe-Murcia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almagro, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La presencia de un seno dérmico en la región dorsal de los niños constituye un motivo habitual de consulta en los servicios de neurocirugía pediátrica. Su frecuencia y posibles complicaciones hacen que su diagnóstico y tratamiento precoces sean importantes. En este trabajo revisamos los criterios sobre el tratamiento de los senos sacrocoxígeos para sugerir un manejo racional de acuerdo con los datos publicados para evitar, en lo posible, derivaciones y exploraciones costosas e innecesarias. Material y métodos: Se revisaron las historias de niños diagnosticados de sinus dérmico sacrocoxígeo vistos en nuestro hospital durante el período 2005&#150;2009. Asimismo se realizó una búsqueda bibliográfica de los artículos más relevantes sobre el tema. Resultados: Durante estos años se vieron 32 pacientes con fosita coxígea. La mayoría de niños fueron remitidos por cirujanos pediátricos, pediatras de zona o pediatras de los servicios de urgencia de los hospitales de nuestra región. Diecisiete niños fueron estudiados con pruebas de neuroimagen y 15 fueron evaluados exclusivamente mediante exploración física. En ninguno de los pacientes se apreció penetración intraraquídea. Conclusiones: De acuerdo a nuestra experiencia y a la bibliografía consultada pensamos que la exploración clínica es suficiente para un diagnóstico y manejo correcto de estos senos, siendo el dato más importante la situación de la fosita coxígea dentro de los límites del repliegue interglúteo. En casos dudosos de conexión del seno con la duramadre se deberá realizar una ecografía como prueba de primera línea y, si es necesario, una resonancia magnética y consulta con Neurocirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);73(6): 352-356, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sinus dérmico sacrocoxígeo: importancia clínica y manejo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12821</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29126^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
