<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113632</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">N-terminal Pro-brain Natriuretic Peptide and High-sensitivity Troponin in the Evaluation of Acute Chest Pain of Uncertain Etiology. A PITAGORAS Substudy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. High-sensitivity troponin assays have improved the diagnosis of acute coronary syndrome in patients presenting with chest pain and normal troponin levels as measured by conventional assays. Our aim was to investigate whether N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide provides additional information to troponin determination in these patients. Methods. A total of 398 patients, included in the PITAGORAS study, presenting to the emergency department with chest pain and normal troponin levels as measured by conventional assay in 2 serial samples (on arrival and 6 h to 8 h later) were studied. The samples were also analyzed in a central laboratory for high-sensitivity troponin T (both samples) and for N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide (second sample). The endpoints were diagnosis of acute coronary syndrome and the composite endpoint of in-hospital revascularization or a 30-day cardiac event. Results. Acute coronary syndrome was adjudicated to 79 patients (20%) and the composite endpoint to 59 (15%). When the N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide quartile increased, the diagnosis of acute coronary syndrome also increased (12%, 16%, 23% and 29%; P=.01), as did the risk of the composite endpoint (6%, 13%, 16% and 24%; P=.004). N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide elevation (&gt;125 ng/L) was associated with both endpoints (relative risk= 2.0; 95% confidence interval, 1.2-3.3; P=.02; relative risk=2.4; 95% confidence interval, 1.4-4.2; P=.004). However, in the multivariable models adjusted by clinical and electrocardiographic data, a predictive value was found for high-sensitivity T troponin but not for N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide. Conclusions. In low-risk patients with chest pain of uncertain etiology evaluated using high-sensitivity T troponin, N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide does not contribute additional predictive value to diagnosis or the prediction of short-term outcomes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Pedro L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avanzas, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrabés, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carratalá, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchis, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loma-Osorio, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bardají, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La troponina ultrasensible ha mejorado el diagnóstico del síndrome coronario agudo en los pacientes que se presentan con dolor torácico y troponina convencional normal. Nuestro objetivo es analizar si la fracción aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético cerebral aporta información adicional. Métodos. Se estudió a 398 pacientes, incluidos en el estudio PITAGORAS, que acudieron a urgencias por dolor torácico con troponina convencional normal en dos muestras seriadas (a la llegada y a las 6-8 h). Se midió de forma centralizada la troponina T ultrasensible en las dos muestras y la fracción aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético cerebral en la segunda. Los objetivos fueron diagnóstico de síndrome coronario agudo y evento compuesto de revascularización o evento cardiaco a los 30 días. Resultados. Se diagnosticó síndrome coronario agudo a 79 pacientes (20%), y 59 (15%) presentaron el evento compuesto. A superior cuartil de la fracción aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético cerebral se incrementan las frecuencias de diagnóstico de síndrome coronario agudo (el 12, el 16, el 23 y el 29%; p  =  0,01) y del evento compuesto (el 6, el 13, el 16 y el 24%; p  =  0,004). La elevación de la fracción aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético cerebral (&gt; 125 ng/l) se asoció con ambos objetivos (riesgo relativo = 2,0; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,2-3,3; p  =  0,02; riesgo relativo = 2,4; intervalo de confianza del 95%, 1,4-4,2; p  =  0,004). Sin embargo, en los modelos multivariables ajustados por datos clínicos y el electrocardiograma, la troponina T ultrasensible mostró valor predictivo, pero no la fracción aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético cerebral. Conclusiones. En el dolor torácico de origen incierto y bajo riesgo evaluado mediante troponina T ultrasensible, la fracción aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético cerebral carece de valor predictivo adicional para el diagnóstico o el pronóstico a corto plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;66(7): 532-538, jul. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113632</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracción aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético cerebral y troponina ultrasensible en el dolor torácico agudo de origen incierto. Un subestudio del estudio PITAGORAS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14739</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38110</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38330</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28938^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14739^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38110^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28938^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
