<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040468</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outcome replacement of two patients with Hurler´s syndrome under enzyme replacement therapy with human recombinant &amp;#945; -L-iduronidase</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We performed a prospective study of two patients with Hurler's syndrome (aged 4.8 years and 17 months at the beginning of the intervention) under enzyme replacement therapy with human recombinant &amp;#945; -L-iduronidase for 452 and 28 weeks respectively. The aim of this study was to analyze the safety and efficacy of the intervention during the treatment periods. Several diagnostic imaging tests, clinical examinations, and serial laboratory determinations were performed to demonstrate the effectiveness of the therapy in both patients. In patient 1 (a boy aged 4.8 years, homozygote W402X), the treatment was always intended to be palliative because of the advanced stage of the disease. In patient 2 (a 17-month-old girl, heterozygote W402X) the treatment was initiated early with subsequent clinical stabilization without acquisition of regressive factors. Bone marrow transplantation from an unrelated donor was successful. Currently, because of the lack of histocompatible bone marrow donors, transplantation of hematopoietic stem cells from umbilical cord blood or peripheral blood are being performed with satisfactory results. In the future, gene therapy may be able to prevent the diseases associated with Hurler's syndrome and halt the neurocognitive deterioration characteristic of these patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ruiz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pardos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivé, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chabás, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Benito, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coll, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mintegui, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sardón, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Estudio prospectivo de 2 pacientes con enfermedad de Hurler (de 4,8 años y 17 meses de edad al inicio de la intervención) en tratamiento enzimático sustitutivo con enzima recombinante humana &amp;#945; -L-iduronidasa durante 52 y 28 semanas, respectivamente, con el objetivo de analizar la eficacia y seguridad de la intervención durante dicho período de tiempo. Se realizaron para ello diversas pruebas diagnósticas por imagen, exámenes clínicos y analíticos seriados que demostraron en ambos casos ser una terapia efectiva. En el caso 1 (varón de 4,8 años, homocigoto W402X) la intervención se planteó con fines paliativos desde el comienzo debido a su estado clínico muy evolucionado. En el caso 2 (mujer de 17 meses, heterocigota para W402X) la intervención se realizó de forma precoz y se observó una estabilización clínica posterior sin la adquisición de factores regresivos. Posteriormente se realizó con éxito un trasplante de médula ósea de donante no emparentado. Actualmente, ante la carencia de donantes de médula ósea histocompatibles, se está realizando trasplante de células madre hematopoyéticas procedentes de cordón o de sangre periférica con resultados satisfactorios. La terapia génica se considera el tratamiento futuro capaz de prevenir la enfermedad asociada al síndrome de Hurler y detener el deterioro neurocognitivo característico de estos pacientes.</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);63(1): 61-67, jul. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de dos pacientes con síndrome de Hurler en tratamiento con enzima recombinante humana &amp;#945; -L-iduronidasa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30379^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7251^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
