<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-22592</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Modified technique for transurethral prostatic resection using a suprapubic tube and local anaesthesia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">PURPOSE: To establish a technique for transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP), combining the use of local anaesthesia with an Amplatz suprapubic tube, in patients at high surgical risk. MATERIALS AND METHOD: A study was carried out in 32 patients who underwent TURP with a 30 F Amplatz suprapubic tube following local anaesthesia. This technique was indicated where surgery presented a general risk, in ederly patients, and for patients refusing to undergo spinal intradural or general anaesthesia. The mean age of the patients was 70 years (61-82 years). The risk of surgery was assessed according to the ASA classification. RESULTS: According to the ASA classification, 7 patients were ASA III (21,9%), and 25 patients were ASA IV (78,1%). In 31 of the 32 patients the operation was completed in one session. When questioned about the pain they felt, 11 patients reported no pain, 12 slight discomfort and 3 ocassional pain. In the latter three patients, intravenous sedation was enhanced with 0,1 mg etomidate per kg body weight. The volume of the resected fragments ranged from 18 to 120 ml, with a mean of 47 ml, except in one patient with 205 ml who required two treatment sessions. CONCLUSIONS: Large prostate resection in patients at high surgical risk was performed comfortably using a combination of local anaesthesia and an Amplatz suprapubic tube. This procedure is one possible option to be considered as an alternative to other treatments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Ene Ediciones, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: Describimos una técnica para la resección transuretral (RTU) de próstata combinando el uso de anestesia local con un tubo de Amplatz suprapúbico en pacientes con alto riesgo quirúrgico. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS: Nuestro estudio comprende 32 pacientes sometidos a RTU de próstata con un tubo de Amplatz suprapúbico de 30 Fr bajo anestesia local. Esta técnica se indicó en aquellos casos con alto riesgo quirúrgico. La edad media fue de 70 años (61-82 años). Evaluamos el riesgo quirúrgico de acuerdo a la clasificación ASA.RESULTADOS: De acuerdo con la clasificación ASA del riesgo quirúrgico, se agrupó a los pacientes en los siguientes grupos: 7 pacientes (21,9 por ciento) presentaban ASA III y 25 pacientes (78,1 por ciento) ASA IV. En 31 de 32 pacientes la cirugía se completó en una sesión. Interrogados acerca del dolor percibido, 11 pacientes refirieron no haber sentido dolor, 12 pacientes refirieron una molestia leve, y 3 pacientes un dolor esporádico. En los últimos tres pacientes se incrementó la dosis de sedación intravenosa con 0,1 mg/kg de peso corporal de Etomidato. El volumen medio de los fragmentos resecados fue de 47 ml, con un rango ente 18 y 120 ml, excepto en un paciente con un volumen de 205 ml que precisó dos sesiones quirúrgicas. CONCLUSIONES: La resección de próstatas de gran volumen en pacientes con riesgo quirúrgico se puede realizar con un mínimo de confort para el paciente utilizando una combinación de anestesia local y tubo de Amplatz suprapúbico. Este procedimiento es una opción a tener en cuenta como tratamiento alternativo a otros métodos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;27(3): 216-220, mar. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnica modificada para la resección trnsuretral de próstata con drenaje suprapúbico y anestesia local</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Elizalde Benito, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Zalabardo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdivia Uría, J. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle Gerhold, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López López, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regojo Zapata, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Elipe, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-22592</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2077</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34537</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22873</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23500</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8188</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8791</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
