<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055392</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mixed transitional cell and small cell carcinoma of the bladder with metastases with neuroendocrine histology only. Case report and bibliography review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To report one case of transitional cell carcinoma with areas of small cell carcinoma presenting in its evolution an adrenal metastasis with the neuroendocrine component only. We perform a bibliography review for the cases of small cell carcinoma of the bladder, its epidemiology, prognosis and treatment. ;;METHODS: We describe the clinical case and perform a Medline review. ;;RESULTS: Small cell carcinoma of the bladder is a rare entity, ;;with a more aggressive behaviour and poorer prognosis than transitional cell carcinoma. The pathologic characteristics allow differentiation of primary tumor and metastatic disease. In the bibliographic search we did not find any previous ;;report of exclusive dissemination of the neuroendocrine ;;histological component in cases of mixed tumors. ;;CONCLUSIONS: There is no standard treatment for small cell carcinoma of the bladder. For metastatic disease the most commonly used combination is cisplatin and etoposide</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Capdevila, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algaba, Ferran</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maroto, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lerma, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villavicencio, Humberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Comunicación de un caso clínico de carcinoma urotelial con áreas de carcinoma de célula pequeña, que presentó en su evolución una metástasis suprarrenaldel componente neuroendocrino exclusivo. Revisiónen la literatura de los casos de carcinoma de célula pequeña de vejiga urinaria, epidemiología, pronóstico y tratamiento.MÉTODOS: Descripción del caso clínico y revisión Medline.RESULTADOS: El carcinoma de célula pequeña vesical es una entidad poco frecuente, con un comportamiento más agresivo y con peor pronóstico que el carcinoma urotelial de vejiga. Las características patológicas permiten el diagnósticodel tumor primario y de la enfermedad metastásica. No se encuentran comunicaciones en la literatura de diseminaciónexclusiva del componente histológico neuroendocrinoen casos de tumores mixtos.CONCLUSIONES: No existe un tratamiento estándar del carcinoma de células pequeñas de vejiga. En enfermedad metastásica la combinación más utilizada es con cisplatino y etopósido</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(3): 306-309, abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055392</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma mixto de urotelio y célula pequeña de vejiga urinaria: metástasis de la histología neuroendocrina sola. Comunicación del caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3576^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28884^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32875^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5143^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7114^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2971^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31587^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32875^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
