<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166876</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Heart failure and arrhythmias: a complex interaction requiring a multidisciplinary approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Today heart failure has a greater impact on public health in developed countries than the majority of diseases and its impact is likely to become even more significant in the future. Clearly, rhythm disturbances associated with heart failure have serious clinical implications. Recent years have seen dramatic scientific and technological developments in the way we approach this type of arrhythmia, and current treatment options, and those expected in the near future, are highly promising. However, it is important to remember that the success of any therapeutic approach depends on a good level of cooperation between the different cardiology subspecialties and other disciplines involved. A multidisciplinary approach to this condition is essential (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Violeta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Cano, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Mansilla, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia cardiaca es ya, y es previsible que lo sea aún más, una de las enfermedades de mayor impacto sociosanitario en los países desarrollados. Sin duda, los trastornos del ritmo asociados a insuficiencia cardiaca tienen un impacto clínico de elevada magnitud. El desarrollo científico y técnico en el abordaje de este tipo de arritmias ha sido espectacular en los últimos años y las oportunidades presentes y, previsiblemente, de futuro son muy esperanzadoras, pero es importante tener en cuenta que el éxito de cualquier abordaje terapéutico pasa por una adecuada interacción de las distintas subespecialidades cardiológicas y no cardiológicas implicadas. El abordaje multidisciplinario para esta patología es una exigencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.A): 60a-68a, 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166876</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Insuficiencia cardiaca y arritmias: una interacción compleja que requiere un abordaje multidisciplinario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54223^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
