<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038132</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Periodontal diseases in schizophrenic patients. A case-control study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to assess the periodontal conditions in schizophrenic patients compared with control patients. Patients and methods. 50 schizophrenic patients attended in the Psychiatric Unit at the Virgen Macarena Universitary Hospital of Seville were compared with 50 control patients (without systemic diseases, and drugs) attended in the School of Dentistry of Seville. Periodontal conditions were assessed according to the WHO criteria (CPITN). Results and Discussion. Schizophrenic patients showed more significative extended excluded sextants (1,64 vs 0,42) and prevalence of shallow pockets (25,6% vs 22,4%) while control patients showed more calculus (69,4% vs 60,5%) and deep pockets (6,1% vs 4,7%). Periodontal conditions showed an increased tendency with age. Males (schizophrenics and controls) (32,4% and 31,3%; respectively) showed a higher prevalence of periodontal pockets than females (22,2% and 23,5%). Also, this study showed a higher prevalence and extension of periodontal pockets among smoker patients (schizophrenics and controls). Conclusions. Relationship between periodontal and psychiatric disturbances must be constitute a field of epidemiological and clinical research for knowledge of natural history of periodontal diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velasco Ponferrada, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco Ortega, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monsalve Guil, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medel Soteras, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Barquero, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo era valorar las condiciones periodontales en pacientes esquizofrénicos comparados con pacientes control. Pacientes y Métodos. El estudio se realizó en 50 pacientes esquizofrénicos ingresados en la Unidad de Psiquiatría del Hospital Universitario Virgen Macarena de Sevilla y se compararon con 50 pacientes adultos de los que acuden a recepción de la Facultad de Odontología de la Universidad de Sevilla, excluyendo de este último grupo aquellos pacientes que presentaban alguna patología sistémica en el momento de la exploración o en los seis meses previos a ésta. En ambos grupos se valoró el estado periodontal según el protocolo de la OMS (CPITN). Resultados y Discusión. Los pacientes esquizofrénicos presentaron una significativa mayor extensión de sextantes excluídos (1,64 vs 0,42) y una mayor prevalencia de bolsas moderadas (25,6% vs 22,4%) mientras que los pacientes controles presentaron una mayor prevalencia de cálculo (69,4% vs 60,5%) y bolsas profundas (6,1% vs 4,7%). Las condiciones periodontales presentaban una tendencia ascendente con la edad. Los hombres (esquizofrénicos y controles) (32,4% y 31,3%, respectivamente) tenían mayor prevalencia de bolsas periodontales que las mujeres (22,2% y 23,5%). Además este estudio muestra una mayor prevalencia y extensión de las bolsas periodontales entre los pacientes fumadores (esquizofrénicos y controles). Conclusiones. La relación entre los problemas periodontales y mentales debe constituir un campo de investigación epidemiológica y clínica para el conocimiento de la historia natural de las enfermedades periodontales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;17(1): 31-39, abr. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038132</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades periodontales en pacientes esquizofrénicos. Un estudio de casos-controles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10090^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6030^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6030^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6030^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14415^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
