<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038563</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results and complications of TVT procedure for surgical treatment of female stress incontinence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives: To evaluate the efficacy and safety of Tension-free vaginal tape (TVT) for treatment of female stress urinary incontinence(SUI).To determine the mid-term outcome of TVT performed during other pelvic floor reconstructive procedures. Patients and methods: 100 women with SUI undergoing TVT procedure under spinal anesthesia from January 2000 to November 2002 were studied.76 women were treated with TVT alone. 24 patients were treated with TVT and pelvic floor reconstruction: we repaired 24cystoceles grade II-III, 3 rectoceles and 4 concomitant vaginal histerectomies. Results: Mean age was 49,3 years (range 35-78). Mean parity: 2 (range 0-6) and mean operative time was 38 minutes (range20 to 50). The postoperative hospital stay was 24 hours for women treated with TVT alone. Only 1 patient (1%) need bladder catheterization during 7 days due to urinary retention. Mean follow up was 18 months (range 12-48). Objetive: cure rate was 95%. In our study the rate of de novo post-operative urge symptoms (16%) was the most frequent complication. Bladder injury was the most grave problem and it happened in 1patient (1%). Conclusion: The results confirm the feasibility and safety of TVT for treatment of SUI. Moreover, TVT procedure is economical and efectiveness. Pelvic floor defects, benign uterine disorders and SUI can be safely treated with TVT and vaginal procedures during the same surgical time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Placer Santos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bielsa Galí, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortadellas Ángel, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gelabert-Mas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arango Toro, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar la eficacia y seguridad de la cinta vaginal sin tensión (TVT) en el tratamiento de la incontinencia urinaria de esfuerzo femenina (IUE).Analizar los resultados a medio plazo de la asociación de la TVT con la corrección quirúrgica de prolapsos genitales. Pacientes y método: Se estudian 100 pacientes con IUE intervenidas de forma consecutiva en nuestro centro bajo anestesia regional. A todas ellas se les implantó la TVT y en 24 casos además, se corrigió un cistocele grado II-III. Fue necesario en 3de estas 24 pacientes reparar un rectocele y se practicaron 4 histerectomías vaginales en el mismo acto quirúrgico. Resultados: La edad media de las mujeres fue de 49,3 años (35-78), el número promedio de partos de 2 (0-6), la duración media de la intervención de 38 minutos (20-50) y todas las pacientes a las que se colocó la TVT sin otras correcciones quirúrgicas obtuvieron el alta hospitalaria a las 24 horas de la intervención. Tan sólo una paciente precisó de sonda varios días por retención urinaria. El tiempo medio de seguimiento fue de 18 meses (12-48) y la IUE se solucionó en el 95% de los casos. Como complicación más frecuente observamos la aparición de hiperactividad detrusorial sintomática &#147;de novo&#148; en el 16% de la serie; la perforación vesical en una de las pacientes fue el problema más grave. Conclusiones: La TVT es una técnica sencilla, segura, eficaz y relativamente económica para el tratamiento de la IUE. La TVT puede asociarse con éxito a la corrección quirúrgica de prolapsos genitales. Este hecho prolonga la estancia hospitalaria en 48 horas sin incrementar la morbilidad de la cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;29(3): 287-291, mar. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038563</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados y complicaciones de la técnica TVT en el tratamiento de la incontinencia de esfuerzo femenina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7226^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1770^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14950^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33761^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29576^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
