<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147011</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Silicosis in Workers Exposed to Artificial Quartz Conglomerates: Does It Differ From Chronic Simple Silicosis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recently, a number of reports have been published on silicosis in workers exposed to artificial quartz conglomerates containing high levels of crystalline silica particles (70-90%) used in the construction of kitchen and bathroom surfaces. Three cases of silicosis in workers exposed to artificial quartz conglomerates are reported. The diagnosis was derived from both the International Labour Office and the International Classification of HRCT for Occupational and Environmental Respiratory Diseases (ICOERD) classifications and cytological analysis of bronchoalveolar lavage fluid. In 2 cases, levels of respirable silica greatly in excess of recommended standards were measured in the workplace, and cytological analysis of bronchoalveolar lavage fluid highlighted a prevalence of lymphocytes, meeting criteria for the diagnosis of accelerated silicosis. The prevention of pneumoconiosis caused by the use of innovative materials, such as artificial conglomerates with high crystalline silica content must be addressed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sartorelli, Pietro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bartoli, Dusca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gerardina Sisinni, Antonietta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazzei, Maria Antonietta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romeo, Riccardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paolucci, Valentina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la bibliografía, hay una serie de estudios recientes sobre silicosis en trabajadores expuestos a conglomerados artificiales de cuarzo con un alto porcentaje de partículas de sílice cristalina (70-90%) empleado para elaborar superficies de cocinas y baños. Se analizan tres casos de silicosis en trabajadores expuestos a conglomerados artificiales de cuarzo. El diagnóstico se realizó conforme a las clasificaciones de la Organización Internacional del Trabajo y la ICOERD (clasificación internacional de TAC de alta resolución para enfermedades respiratorias ocupacionales y ambientales) y mediante análisis citológico del líquido del lavado broncoalveolar. En dos casos, se midieron en el lugar de trabajo niveles de sílice respirable que superaban en gran medida los umbrales recomendados y el análisis citológico del líquido del lavado broncoalveolar mostró la prevalencia de linfocitos indicativos de diagnóstico de silicosis acelerada. Es preciso reestudiar esta neumoconiosis, sobre todo para evitar el uso de materiales innovadores como los conglomerados artificiales con alto contenido en sílice cristalina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;51(12): e57-e60, dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147011</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Silicosis en trabajadores expuestos a conglomerados artificiales de cuarzo: ¿es distinta a la silicosis crónica simple?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13209^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12228^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13209^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11438^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13209^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11438^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11438^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13209^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32824^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
