<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136933</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oct parameters as predictive factors for the visual outcome after ranibizumab therapy in neovascular age related macular degeneration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate macular morphological parameters measured by spectral domain optical coherence tomography (SD-OCT) as predictive factors of visual outcome in patients with exudative age-related macular degeneration (AMD) treated with ranibizumab. Methods: A retrospective study was conducted on 47 patients diagnosed with exudative AMD and treated with intravitreal ranibizumab for twelve months. Central retinal thickness (CRT), extension and thickness of modifications secondary to neovascular process, and status of the bands corresponding to the external limiting membrane (ELM) and to the ellipsoid region of the photoreceptors (ISe) were evaluated by means of SD-OCT. The relationship between these variables and visual acuity was analyzed by statistical methods. Results: At the time of the diagnosis, preservation of ELM and ISe bands, and CRT were correlated with initial visual acuity. Twelve months later, CRT and visual acuity were independent parameters. Bivariate relationship analysis showed a correlation between final visual acuity and the following parameters: initial CRT, initial ISe and ELM status, and ISe and ELM integrity after loading dose. Multiple regression analysis indicated that initial visual acuity and ISe band status after loading dose have a predictive value for final visual acuity. Conclusions: The status of ISe and ELM bands after twelve months of treatment with ranibizumab was associated with visual outcome. Initial visual acuity and status of the ISe band after loading dose are prognostic factors of final visual acuity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valverde-Megías, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Feijoo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Gil-de-Bernabé, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Megías-Fresno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Donate-López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar parámetros morfológicos maculares determinados mediante tomografía de coherencia óptica de dominio espectral (SD-OCT) como factores predictivos de la respuesta funcional en pacientes con degeneración macular asociada a la edad (DMAE) de tipo exudativo tratados con ranibizumab. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de 47 pacientes diagnosticados de DMAE exudativa y tratados con ranibizumab intravítreo durante 12 meses. Mediante SD-OCT se evaluaron el grosor retiniano central (CRT), la extensión y el grosor de las alteraciones secundarias al proceso neovascular, y el estado de las bandas correspondientes a la membrana limitante externa (MLE) y a la región elipsoide de los fotorreceptores (ISe), analizándose por métodos estadísticos la relación entre estas variables y la agudeza visual. Resultados: Al diagnóstico, la conservación de las bandas MLE e ISe y el CRT se correlaciona con la visión inicial. Doce meses después, el CRT y la visión final son parámetros independientes. Los análisis bivariante mostraron correlación entre la agudeza visual final y los siguientes parámetros: CRT inicial, estado inicial de las bandas ISe y MLE, y estado de estas tras la dosis de carga. El análisis de regresión lineal múltiple indica que la visión inicial y el estado de la banda ISe tras la fase de carga tienen valor predictivo de la visión final. Conclusiones: El estado de conservación de las bandas ISe y MLE tras 12 meses de tratamiento con ranibizumab se correlaciona con el resultado visual. La agudeza visual inicial y el estado de la banda ISe tras la fase de carga son factores pronóstico de la agudeza visual final (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;90(4): 156-163, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136933</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parámetros tomográficos como factores pronóstico del resultado visual tras terapia con ranibizumab en degeneración macular neovascular asociada a la edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38334^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38334^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31066^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31066^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31066^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31066^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38334^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38334^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
