<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85117</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Upper Lobectomy for Lung Cancer with True Tracheal Bronchus: A Unique Presentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tracheal bronchus is an aberrant bronchus usually originating from the right lateral wall of the trachea, with an incidence ranging from 0.1% to 5% and usually within 2.0cm above the carina. The incidence of lung cancer with bronchial anomaly is very rare. There are only nine cases of lung cancer developing from the tracheal bronchus reported in the literature. Histological examination showed squamous cell carcinoma in only three of them, and we present a fourth case who was a 57-year-old man. Interestingly our patient's anomaly included both an absence of the normal right upper bronchus as well as right upper lobe ventilated from the true tracheal bronchus. This is the first documented case in the world of a squamous carcinoma arising from the true tracheal bronchus. Post-surgical histological stage was T2aN0M0 (stage IB). The patient is well 48 months after the operation and has no evidence of recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>ªentürk, Ekrem</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>ªen, Selda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pabuºçu, Engin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>ªen, Serdar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El bronquio traqueal es un bronquio aberrante que se origina generalmente en la pared lateral derecha de la tráquea, a menos de 2cm por encima de la carina, y su incidencia oscila entre el 0,1 y el 5%. La incidencia de cáncer de pulmón con anomalías bronquiales es poco común. En la bibliografía especializada sólo se recogen 9 casos de este tipo de cáncer desarrollado en un bronquio traqueal. El examen anatomopatológico mostraba carcinoma epidermoide en sólo 3 de ellos, y aquí presentamos un cuarto caso que corresponde a un varón de 57 años de edad. Curiosamente, la anomalía de nuestro paciente incluía la ausencia de un bronquio superior derecho normal, además de que el lóbulo superior derecho ventilaba a través del bronquio traqueal. Éste es el primer caso documentado en todo el mundo de carcinoma escamoso con origen en el bronquio traqueal. El estadio anatomopatológico posquirúrgico fue T2aN0M0 (estadio IB). El paciente se encuentra en buen estado de salud 48 meses después de la operación y no presenta indicios de recurrencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;46(6): 332-334, jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lobectomía superior por cáncer de pulmón con bronquio traqueal verdadero: una presentación inusual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11442^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
