<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62603</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to evaluate the effectiveness of "Primary BereavementCare&#148; (PBC), a bereavement intervention specifically designed for primaryhealth care (PHC).Design: a cluster (family physicians)-randomized controlled trial.Location: 19 Basque Health Service (Osakidetza) Centers in Biscay. Participants: 104 women selected within 3 months of their partners&#146;demise, and 31 collaborating family physicians.Interventions: experimental group: 7 sessions of 45 minutes each, performed at 4, 4½, 5, 6, 8, 10 and 13 months after partner death, applying PBC general techniques (REFINO: relationship, "ear", facilitation, information,normalization, and orientation) and PBC specific techniques(date anticipation, decision taking, etc.). Control group: 7 sessions withthe same frequency, but without specific content and duration. Principal measurements: "improvements" are analyzed according tothe Texas Revised Inventory of Grief, Grief Experiences Inventory, qualityof life (SF-36) and mental health (GHQ-28), at 3, 9, 15 and 21 monthsfollowing the partner's death; via a covariance analysis adjusted by predictedand confounding variables, using a mixed linear model. All analyseswill be performed on an intention-to-treat basis. Discussion: the project is very complex and full of difficulties, but theconclusions obtained will provide useful scientific evidence for the definitionof the most appropriate care for the bereaved in PHC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mauriz Etxabe, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pombo Ramos, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andollo Hervás, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grandes, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landa Petralanda, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar la eficacia de los "Cuidados Primarios de Duelo" (CPD), una intervención biopsicosocial en duelo diseñada específicamentepara la atención primaria (AP). Diseño: ensayo clínico aleatorizado por médicos, distribuidos en dosgrupos paralelos: control (GC) e intervención (GI). Emplazamiento: 19 Centros de Salud de Vizcaya del Servicio Vasco deSalud/Osakidetza. Participantes: 104 mujeres captadas antes de transcurridos 3 meses del fallecimiento de su pareja y 31 médicos de AP colaboradores. Intervenciones: GI: 7 sesiones de CPD, de 45 minutos cada una, realizadasa los 4, 4½, 5, 6, 8, 10 y 13 meses de la muerte del cónyuge y en lasque se aplicarán las técnicas generales (REFINO: relación, escucha, facilitación,información, normalización y orientación) y específicas (anticipaciónde fechas, toma de decisiones,&#133;) de los CPD. GC: 7 sesiones realizadascon la misma periodicidad que el GI, pero libres en duración ycontenido. Mediciones principales: se analizarán las "mejorías" en el InventarioTexas Revisado de Duelo, Inventario de Experiencias en Duelo, calidad devida (SF-36) y salud mental (GHQ-28), a los 3, 9, 15 y 21 meses del fallecimientodel cónyuge; mediante análisis de la covarianza ajustado por lasvariables predictoras y confusoras que se consideren, y con un modelo lineal mixto. Todos los análisis se harán por intención de tratar. Discusión: el proyecto es muy complejo y está lleno de dificultades, perolas conclusiones que se deriven del mismo aportarán evidencias científicas útiles para definir la atención más apropiada a las personas en duelo en AP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;14(3): 174-178, jul.-sept. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62603</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proyecto de investigación para evaluar la eficacia de los "Cuidados Primarios de Duelo" (CPD) en viudas: un ensayo clínico aleatorizado por médicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d17140^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30973^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
