<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056027</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diabetic mastopathy in a woman with long-standing type 1 diabetes: a description of a poorly characterized entity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Diabetic mastopathy is an uncommon form of lymphocytic mastitis    that typically occurs in women with long-standing type 1 diabetes.    This entity, which presents with a characteristic stromal fibrosis, is a    benign fibrous lesion, but may clinically mimic a malignant lesion.    The authors report a case involving the development of diabetic    mastopathy, diagnosed in a woman with long-standing type 1 diabetes    and known controlled chronic microvascular complications. After    the detection of a breast lump in a routine ultrasound scan, she was    referred to a breast surgeon for evaluation. The diagnosis of diabetic    mastopathy was confirmed by biopsy, which ruled out the presence    of malignant lesions. The management was conservative</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Agulló, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmena, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ampudia-Blasco, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mastopatía diabética es una forma poco frecuente de mastitis    linfocitaria que aparece preferentemente en mujeres con una diabetes    mellitus tipo 1 (DM1) de larga evolución. Esta entidad, con una    característica proliferación fibrosa del estroma, se encuadra dentro    de las lesiones mamarias fibrosas benignas, pero clínicamente puede    confundirse con lesiones malignas. En este caso clínico se describe un    proceso de mastopatía diabética en una paciente con DM1 de larga    duración y complicaciones crónicas microvasculares conocidas,    aunque controladas. Tras la detección de la lesión en una ecografía    de control, fue remitida al cirujano de mama para su valoración. El diagnóstico    se realizó mediante biopsia, y se descartó la presencia de    lesiones malignas. El tratamiento de la mastopatía diabética fue conservador</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;23(3): 237-240, mayo-jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056027</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mastopatía diabética en una mujer con diabetes mellitus tipo 1 de larga evolución: descripción de una entidad poco conocida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5484^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
