<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056512</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of inguinal graft infections by means of a cryopreserved arterial allograft, rotational muscular flap and partial skin graft</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Inguinal graft infections constitute a severe complication that puts the revascularised limb at risk    and they are often difficult to resolve, even in the best situations. Case report. A 56-year-old male who had previously    undergone several revascularisation operations in both lower limbs and had no autologous veins. The patient had    previously suffered early infection of a femoral-popliteal graft which was treated by means of partial withdrawal. He    visited because of an inguinal infection with a compound (polytetrafluoroethylene-great saphenous vein) below-theknee    femoral-popliteal bypass that was seen to be patent. The procedure consisted in wide debridement of the area, with    removal of the residual graft, and an anatomic bypass was implanted with a cryopreserved arterial allograft and later    covered with a rotational muscular (rectus femoris-sartorius) flap and partial skin graft. In a control visit at three    months, the bypass was seen to be patent and the graft was well integrated. Conclusions. In cases of infection of a    prosthetic graft, associated with widespread tissue involvement, and the absence of autologous material with which to    replace it, use of a cryopreserved arterial allograft that is later covered with a muscle and skin flap has proved to be a    valid management option</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peñafiel-Marfil, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros-Díe, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sellés-Galiana, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara-Villaoslada, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca-Manteca, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros-Vidal, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La infección protésica inguinal es una complicación grave que pone en riesgo la extremidad revascularizada,    y su solución resulta compleja en muchas ocasiones, incluso en las mejores situaciones. Caso clínico. Varón    de 56 años con varias cirugías revascularizadoras en ambos miembros inferiores y ausencia de vena autóloga. Presenta    antecedente de infección precoz en una prótesis femoropoplítea tratada con retirada parcial. Acude por infección    inguinal con bypass femoropoplíteo infragenicular compuesto (politetrafluoroetileno-vena safena interna) permeable.    Se realizó un amplio desbridamiento de la zona, con la retirada de la prótesis residual, y se implantó un bypass ortoanatómico    con aloinjerto arterial criopreservado y posterior cobertura con flap muscular rotacional (recto anterior-sartorio)    e injerto cutáneo parcial. Visto en una revisión a los tres meses con permeabilidad del bypass y buena integración del    injerto. Conclusión. En caso de infección protésica, asociada a gran afectación tisular, y ausencia de material autólogo    para su sustitución, el empleo de un aloinjerto arterial criopreservado con posterior cobertura con un flap muscular y    cutáneo se presenta como una opción válida en su manejo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;59(5): 399-405, sept.-oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056512</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la infección protésica inguinal mediante aloinjerto arterial criopreservado, flap muscular rotacional e injerto cutáneo parcial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23504^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37257^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28157^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7439^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24593^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24593^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7439^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14575^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12878^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37257^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12878^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
