<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125784</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Working with families of children and adolescents in a Children Mental Health Unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A short reflection about the current divorce between Psychiatry and Psychoanalysis id offered. Four clinical vignettes of three boys and an adolescent girl are presented; they were treated in the Children Mental Health Unit of Jerez de la Frontera and Virgen Macarena Hospital at Seville. One question is put forward: what tells apart a more or less well trained psychoanalyst from his/her colleagues in a public mental health network? The analyst´s listening is the author´s answer. The author also points out that both Bion´s concept of containment and Winnicott´s use os an object have always been very important in his everyday work (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jarast, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se hace una breve reflexión sobre el divorcio actual entre la psiquiatría y el psicoanálisis. Se presentan cuatro viñetas clínicas de tres niños y una adolescente, tratados en la Unidad de Salud Mental Infantil de Jerez de la Frontera y en la Unidad de Salud Mental Infantil del Hospital "Virgen Macarena" de Sevilla. Se plantea la pregunta: ¿qué diferencia a un psicoanalista más o menos bien formado de sus compañeros de trabajo en una red pública? La escucha del analista es la respuesta del autor. El autor también plantea que los conceptos de "contención" de Bion y "uso del objeto" de Winnicott, han sido siempre muy importantes en su trabajo cotidiano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(67): 199-208, nov. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125784</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trabajando con familias de niños y adolescentes en una unidad de salud mental infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28462</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
