<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057547</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioural activation and de-medicalization of depression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Behavioural activation (BA) emerges as the most effective therapy for treating depression. It has shown to be more effective than cognitive    therapy, and similarly effective but with more effectiveness than medications used to treat major depression. BA therapy considers    depression in contextual terms, trying to help depressed persons to get their lives back. BA represents an alternative view to the    deficit model of depression that prevails among clinical settings in terms or brain chemistry or psychological mechanisms</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Álvarez, Marino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Activación Conductual (AC) emerge como la terapia más eficaz para la depresión. Ha mostrado ser más eficaz que la Terapia    Cognitiva y tan eficaz pero más eficiente que la medicación para la depresión mayor. La AC entiende la depresión en términos contextuales    y trata de ayudar a las personas deprimidas a reengancharse en sus vidas. La AC representa una alternativa a los modelos    del déficit de la depresión que dominan el discurso clínico, sea en términos de química cerebral o de mecanismos psicológicos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;28(2): 97-110, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057547</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La activación conductual y la desmedicalización de la depresión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
