<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95015</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological coping with invasive and painful medical procedures in the treatment of childhood and adolescent cancer: The cognitive-behavioural approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Psychological coping with childhood cancer involves the use of strategies and resources that help children and their families undergo the disease with the fewest possible emotional and behavioural problems. In the field of Psychology, techniques and programs have been developed and adapted with the aim of minimizing the psychological impact of the diagnosis and treatment of childhood and adolescent cancer. The present paper reviews psychological procedures based on the cognitive-behavioural paradigm, such as transmission of information, coping skills training, the use of audiovisual materials, games, bibliotherapy, and humour. It considers the use of such procedures in children and adolescents and the role of parents in the preparation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riquelme, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortigosa, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez, Francisco Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El afrontamiento psicológico del cáncer infantil implica el uso de estrategias y recursos que ayuden al niño y a su familia a vivenciar la enfermedad con la menor afectación emocional y comportamental posible. En este sentido, desde la Psicología se han desarrollado y adaptado técnicas  y programas con el objetivo de minimizar el impacto psicológico que implica el diagnóstico y tratamiento del cáncer en la infancia y la adolescencia. En el presente artículo se revisan los procedimientos psicológicos fundamentados en el paradigma cognitivo-conductual como la transmisión de información, el entrenamiento en habilidades de afrontamiento, el audiovisual, el juego, la biblioterapia y el humor, considerando su aplicación en niños y adolescentes, y el papel de los padres en la preparación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);6(2/3): 413-428, dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95015</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Afrontamiento psicológico de los procedimientos médicos invasivos y dolorosos aplicados para el tratamiento del cáncer infantil y adolescente: la perspectiva cognitiva conductual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
