<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113080</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parenting styles and stress in students of compulsory secondary education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The main purpose of this study was to examine any possible existing connection between parenting style, as perceived by a group of teenagers, and the level of concern shown at a group of daily stressors among this stage in development. In addition, it was studied whether the reported level of stress was subjected to change related to gender. 495 students of compulsory secondary education ranging between 12 and 16 participated in the study. The results obtained revealed that those adolescents with parents exhibiting a permissive style showed a lower level of stress compared to those belonging to authoritarian homes. Furthermore, gender-related differences were only found in one of the stressor categories. The results are discussed appealing to an ecological model of human development</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carpio, Mª Villa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Mª Cruz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova, Pedro F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerezo, Mª Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, Manuel J de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tuvo como objetivo principal examinar las posibles relaciones existentes entre el estilo educativo familiar percibido por un grupo de adolescentes y el nivel de inquietud expresada ante un conjunto de eventos estresantes cotidianos propios de esta etapa evolutiva. Adicionalmente, se exploró si el grado de estrés informado difería en función del sexo. Participaron 495 estudiantes de educación secundaria obligatoria, con edades comprendidas entre los 12 y los 16 años. Los resultados obtenidos revelan que los adolescentes que perciben en sus hogares el desempeño de un estilo educativo permisivo manifiestan menores índices de estrés que los jóvenes pertenecientes a hogares autoritarios. Asimismo, se obtienen diferencias en función del sexo en tan solo una de las categorías de eventos estresantes evaluadas. Los resultados se discuten apelando a un modelo ecológico de desarrollo humano (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;19(3): 577-590, sept.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113080</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos educativos paternos y estrés en estudiantes de educación secundaria obligatoria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2719^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10479^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
