<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100680</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parenting style in Spanish parents with children aged 6 to 14</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper was to establish which parenting style of Spanish families is associated with optimum children&#146;s outcomes. A random Spanish sample of 1,103 parents of children and teenagers from 6 to 14 years of age, of whom 47% were females, reported on their child-rearing practices. Families were classified into 1 of 4 groups (authoritative, authoritarian, indulgent, or neglectful) based on the parents&#146; answers. Socialization outcomes were 6 indicators of interpersonal relationship quality, 9 indicators of psychological adjustment, 7 indicators of personal competence, and 12 indicators of behavior problems. Results showed that indulgent and authoritative parenting styles were associated with better outcomes than authoritarian and neglectful parenting. Overall, our results supported the idea that, in Spain, the optimum parenting style is the indulgent one, as scores in the four sets of socialization outcomes among children and teenagers from indulgent families were always equal to, or even better than, the authoritative parenting style (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Alonso-Geta, Petra María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de esta investigación fue analizar los estilos de socialización parental buscando determinar cuál es el estilo de socialización más idóneo en España, midiendo múltiples indicadores de ajuste en los hijos. Se utilizó una muestra representativa nacional de 1.103 padres con hijos de 6 a 14 años (47% hijas) que indicaron las prácticas de socialización que utilizaban. Las familias se clasificaron a partir de las respuestas de los padres en una de las cuatro tipologías clásicas (autorizativa, autoritaria, indulgente o negligente). Se usaron como criterios seis indicadores de la calidad de la relación interpersonal, nueve indicadores de ajuste psicológico, siete indicadores de competencia personal y doce de problemas conductuales. Los estilos familiares autorizativo e indulgente se correspondieron generalmente con mejores puntuaciones que los autoritarios y negligentes. Los resultados mostraron que el estilo familiar más idóneo en España es el indulgente, ya que las puntuaciones de los hijos de familias indulgentes siempre fueron equivalentes, o mejores, que los de las familias autorizativas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(3): 371-376, jul.-sept. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100680</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La socialización parental en padres españoles con hijos de 6 a 14 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5323</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30184</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
