<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104271</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The «Projecte Pont» (or Bridge Project) started in year 2004. At present, in 2008, we have had 89 patients admitted to the Subacute Inpatient Unit, of which the 64,04 % have been linked to «Projecte Pont». This project is the result of the cooperation among the teenagers unit of CASM Benito Menni, mainly the subacute inpatient unit, and the Marianao Foundation, across the «Casa Infantil y Juvenil de Marianao». This is an neighborhood entity with social initiative, promoting several socio-educational projects aimed at children, teenagers, young people, adults and community in general. It is a program of socialization and normalization through activities carried out in a community centre, which purpose is to promote the participation of these teenagers admitted in the subacute unit in areas and spaces of community relation, along their process of personal rehabilitation and transition towards the social, educational and labour world placement. The target population are the patients admitted to the subacute unit, in those we want have a special effect, letting them know the existing resources in the community, so they can get linked to their own community resources when they return to their town of origin, what would serve as support and integration into the normalization process. This project is part of the Individualized Therapeutic Program (PTI) and complements the groups program and therapeutic activities developed at the of subacute in patient unit itself (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Eulalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledo, Encarna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrico, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Mercè</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Projecte Pont comenzó en el año2004, actualmente en el 2008 hemos tenido89 pacientes ingresados en subagudos de los que el 64,04 % han sido vinculados a Projecte Pont. Este proyecto es fruto de la cooperación entre la Unidad de Adolescentes de CASM Benito Menni, principalmente la Unidad de Subagudos, y la Fundación Marianao, a través del «Casal Infantil y Juvenil de Marianao» que es una entidad de barrio con iniciativa social que promueve diversos proyectos socioeducativos dirigidos a niños y adolescentes, jóvenes, adultos y a la comunidad en general. Es un Programa de socialización y normalización a través de actividades realizadas en un «casal comunitario» cuya finalidades potenciar la participación de los adolescentes ingresados en la unidad de subagudos en los ámbitos y espacios de relación comunitaria, dentro de su proceso de rehabilitación personal y en la transición hacia la inserción social, escolar y laboral. La población diana son pacientes ingresados en la Unidad de Subagudos, en los que se quiere incidir de manera especial, en que conozcan los recursos que hay en la comunidad y al regreso a su municipio de origen, se vinculen en sus propios recursos comunitarios, para que sirvan de sostén e integración en el proceso de normalización. Este proyecto forma parte del Programa terapéutico individualizado (PTI) y complementa el programa de grupos y actividades terapéuticas que se desarrollan en la propia unidad de subagudos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(201): 325-330, jul.-sept. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104271</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Projecte Pont</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29316</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3187^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
