<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98292</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this research was to study school violence and exclusion across different educational levels in the Madrid Region, Spain. Participants were 1,635 students (aged 14-18 years) with different education levels ?compulsory secondary education, specific/ initial training courses and vocational training. Students filled out a questionnaire that included measures of school satisfaction, type of violence (e.g., exclusion, verbal violence, physical violence, vandalism), violence roles (i.e., aggressors, victims and spectators), and attitudes towards violence (e.g., intolerance, sexism and violence justification). Results indicated that a) social exclusion and verbal violence are the most prevalent types of violence, b) school violence decreased when the educational level increased, and c) special vulnerability was higher among specific groups. Implications and interventions are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pulido Valero, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Seoane, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera Gómez, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente estudio ha sido analizar las situaciones de violencia escolar y exclusión, a través de los diferentes niveles educativos en la Comunidad de Madrid, España. Los participantes han sido 1.635 estudiantes (con edades comprendidas entre 14-18 años), de distintos niveles educativos (Educación Secundaria Obligatoria, Bachillerato, Grado Medio y Garantía Social). Los estudiantes tuvieron que rellenar un cuestionario que incluía medidas de satisfacción escolar, distintas situaciones de violencia escolar (exclusión, violencia verbal, violencia física, vandalismo), desde el punto de vista de los tres roles implicados (agresores, víctimas y observadores), y actitudes (intolerancia, sexismo y justificación del comportamiento violento). Los resultados obtenidos indicaron que las situaciones de violencia escolar más frecuentes se relacionan con la exclusión social y la violencia verbal, que las manifestaciones de violencia escolar decrecen cuando aumenta el nivel educativo, y que existen grupos de especial vulnerabilidad. Se analizarán las posibles implicaciones e intervenciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);14(2): 103-113, jul.-dic. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98292</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Maltrato entre iguales y exclusión social en la Comunidad de Madrid. Análisis y posibilidades de intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34658</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
