<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165376</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of the novelties from the 32nd ECTRIMS Congress, 2016, presented at the 9th Post-ECTRIMS Meeting (II)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For the ninth year in a row the Post-ECTRIMS Meeting has been held in Madrid (Spain) with the aim of presenting and discussing the hottest issues debated at the ECTRIMS Congress by renowned specialists in multiple sclerosis in our country. One outcome of this scientific activity, endorsed by the Spanish Neurology Society, is this review article, which is published in two parts. This second part reflects the current controversy over the management of multiple sclerosis, especially as regards the progressive forms and their differential diagnosis. The work presents the latest advances in remyelination, where the use of the micropillar technique in laboratory stands out, and in neuroprotection, which is reviewed through a study of the optic nerve. Anti-CD20 antibodies are a very promising development and we find ourselves before a new mechanism of action and therapeutic target in cells to which little attention has been paid to date. Another notable fact is the high correlation between the levels of neurofilaments in cerebrospinal fluid and in serum, which could make it possible to avoid the use of cerebrospinal fluid as a biological sample in future studies of biomarkers. The review also provides a preview of the advances in clinical research, which will converge in clinical practice in the future, thereby conditioning the steps that should be taken in the therapeutic management of multiple sclerosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ginés, M Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramió-Torrentà, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saiz, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginestal, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva-Nacarino, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brieva, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Merino, Juan A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calles-Hernández, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oreja-Guevara, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comabella, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meca-Lallana, José E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Antigüedad, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oterino, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Delicias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Pinel, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendibe-Bilbao, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova-Estruch, Bonaventura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Por noveno año consecutivo se ha celebrado en Madrid (España) la Reunión Post-ECTRIMS con el objetivo de presentar y discutir los temas más debatidos en el congreso ECTRIMS de la mano de reconocidos especialistas en esclerosis múltiple de nuestro país. Fruto de esta reunión científica, avalada por la Sociedad Española de Neurología, se genera este artículo de revisión que sale publicado en dos partes. En esta segunda parte se pone de manifiesto la controversia actual en el manejo de la esclerosis múltiple, especialmente en cuanto a formas progresivas y diagnóstico diferencial se refiere. Se presentan los últimos avances en remielinización, donde destaca el uso de la técnica con micropilares en el laboratorio, y en neuroprotección, la cual se revisa a través del estudio del nervio óptico. Los anticuerpos anti-CD20 ofrecen grandes expectativas, y estamos ante un nuevo mecanismo de acción y diana terapéutica en unas células a las que les habíamos prestado poca atención hasta la fecha. Otro hecho destacable es la elevada correlación entre los niveles de neurofilamentos en el líquido cefalorraquídeo y el suero, que podría evitar el uso del líquido cefalorraquídeo como muestra biológica en futuros estudios de biomarcadores. También se anticipan los avances en investigación clínica que en el futuro acabarán convergiendo en la práctica clínica, condicionando los pasos que se deberán seguir en el abordaje terapéutico de la esclerosis múltiple (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;65(2): 75-84, 16 jul., 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165376</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de las novedades del XXXII Congreso ECTRIMS 2016, presentadas en la IX Reunión Post-ECTRIMS (II)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29431</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56136</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
