<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153467</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Appropriate use of methotrexate in juvenile idiopathic arthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to its safety and effectiveness, methotrexate (MTX) is the most widely used disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drug (DMARD) in children and adolescents with juvenile idiopathic arthritis (JIA). It is considered the drug of choice to initiate remission-induction therapy. The use of MTX depends on the clinical form of JIA. The usual starting dose is 10-15 mg/m2/week. Subcutaneous administration is recommended due to its better bioavailability and tolerability, especially at doses of  15 mg/m2/week. The child´s vaccination status is important and should be taken into account before and during MTX therapy. Monitoring mainly consists of periodic analytic tests. Severe adverse effects are exceptional, but gastrointestinal intolerance is relatively frequent. Toxicity is reduced by folic acid supplementation. The effectiveness of biological therapy can be enhanced when biological agents are combined with MTX. Treatment can be withdrawn at least 6 months after the achievement of remission (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Robledillo, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El metotrexato es el fármaco modificador de la enfermedad más empleado en niños y adolescentes con artritis idiopática juvenil por su eficacia y seguridad. Se considera de elección para iniciar el tratamiento inductor de remisión. El metotrexato debe utilizarse según la forma clínica de artritis idiopática juvenil. La posología de inicio habitual es 10-15 mg/m2/semana. La forma de administración subcutánea es la recomendable por su mejor biodisponibilidad y tolerabilidad, sobre todo con dosis   15 mg/m2/semana. El estado vacunal del niño es importante y se debe considerar antes y durante el tratamiento con metotrexato. La monitorización consiste fundamentalmente en la realización de analítica periódicamente. Los efectos secundarios graves son excepcionales, pero la intolerancia digestiva es relativamente frecuente. La suplementación de ácido fólico reduce la toxicidad. La eficacia del tratamiento biológico puede ser mayor cuando se combina con metotrexato. La retirada del tratamiento puede realizarse al menos 6 meses después de alcanzada la remisión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);11(supl.1): 42-47, ene. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso adecuado del metotrexato en artritis idiopática juvenil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34546</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27231^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1177^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32355^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19333^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5629^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
