<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136837</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Global nightlife: recreational drug use and harm minimisation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">International tourism associated with dance music is now responsible for millions of young people travelling abroad each year to sample nightlife in different countries. We consider three public health issues associated with this recent phenomenon: changes in young people&#146;s substance use while abroad, international variations in nightlife health and safety standards and, the status of systems for communicating health and nightlife information on an international basis. Individuals travelling abroad continue to spread new trends in recreational drug use. However, international networks for sharing intelligence on trends in recreational drug use and on interventions to deal with the associated health consequences remain poorly developed. The development of an international nightlife continues to play a vital role in the economic development of cities and resorts worldwide. However, more investment is urgently needed into the international exchange of harm reduction and nightlife health and safety intelligence and into the development of interventions specifically aimed at young people partying abroad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hughes, Karen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellis, Mark A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El turismo internacional vinculado a la música dance es responsable de que millones de jóvenes viajen al extranjero cada año para disfrutar de la vida nocturna en diferentes países. Debemos considerar tres problemas de salud asociadas a este reciente fenómeno: cambios en las drogas que consumen durante su estancia en el extranjero, variación de los estándares de salud y seguridad de la vida nocturna en un plano internacional, y la situación relativa de los sistemas que suministran información sobre la salud y la vida nocturna a nivel internacional. Las personas que viajan al extranjero continúan extendiendo nuevas tendencias en el consumo de las drogas recreativas. Sin embargo, las redes internacionales para cooperar en la recogida de información de las nuevas tendencias en el consumo de drogas recreativas y en las intervenciones para enfrentarse a las consecuencias asociadas a problemas de la salud, siguen estando muy poco desarrolladas. El desarrollo de la vida nocturna internacional continúa jugando un papel importante en el desarrollo económico de las ciudades y centros de ocio mundiales. No obstante, urge una mayor inversión en el plano internacional que atienda a la reducción de daños, a la información que incumbe a la seguridad y salud, y a la promoción de intervenciones especialmente dirigidas a jóvenes que salen fuera de sus países (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);15(supl.2): 289-305, 2003. ilus, tab, mapas, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136837</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo recreativo de drogas y reducción de daños en la vida nocturna global</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23605</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24318</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50218</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8076</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
