<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152938</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in a rural area of Guadalajara, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a global health problem due its elevated prevalence, high morbimortality, and substantial socioeconomic cost. In Spain its prevalence varies considerably among the different geographical areas studied. The aim of this study was to establish the prevalence of COPD in a rural area health and its stratification according different risk factors. Methods: A cross-sectional, observational study was perfomed in Yunquera de Henares (Guadalajara, Spain) in the year 2014. A questionnaire on sociodemographic, consumption tobacco age and profession was used to a randomized, stratified sample in different stages. The sample was proportional in age, sex and population centers. A total of 749 persons were included. Data were analyzed using descriptive, analytical, and multivariant statistical procedures and logistical regression. Results: The prevalence of COPD was 15.8% (CI 95%: 13.2-18.4) and was statistically significantly higher in elderly (64.6±11 years vs 58.9±11,7 years); males (83.2%; CI95%: 85.9-80.5), smokers (40.3%, CI95%: 43.8-36.8) and people with primary education (66.4% ; CI95%: 69.7-63). People with COPD had higher BMI (28.2%; IC95%: 29.5-26.9). People working in the field was 28.6% (IC95%: 20,5-36,7%). Conclusions: High prevalence of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease was found. Occupational exposure may be an important factor in rural areas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vasquez Marín, Carlos Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Zapata, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pérez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: La enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica es un problema sanitario mundial debido a su elevada prevalencia, alta morbilidad y cuantioso coste económico. En España su prevalencia varía considerablemente entre las diferentes áreas geográfica estudiadas. El objetivo de este estudio fue establecer la prevalencia de enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica en una zona básica de salud de ámbito rural y el análisis según diferentes factores de riesgo. Métodos: Estudio transversal realizado en Yunquera de Henares (Guadalajara) durante 2014. Para la recogida de información se utilizó un cuestionario que recogió datos sociodemograficos, consumo de tabaco, edad y profesión a una muestra de sujetos seleccionada de manera aleatoria y estratificada según edad, sexo y núcleos de población. El tamaño muestral fue de 749 personas. Se realizó análisis estadístico descriptivo con medias y porcentajes, analítico: chi2, t de Student, ANOVA y multivariante por regresión logística. Resultados: La prevalencia de enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica fue del 15,8% (IC 95%: 13,2-18,4). Las personas con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica tenían una edad media de 64,6±11años vs 58,9±11,7 de quienes no la padecían (p&lt;0,05), eran hombres el 83,2% (IC95%: 85,9-80,5; p&lt;0,001), fue más frecuente en personas con estudios primarios: 66,4% (IC95%: 69,7-63; p&lt;0,01) y entre quienes consumían tabaco: 40,3% (IC 95%: 43,8-36,8 ; p&lt;0,001). De manera no estadísticamente significativa, también presentaban mayor índice de masa corporal:28,2% (IC95%: 29,5-26,9). Trabajababan en el campo el 28,6% (IC95%: 20,5-36,7). Conclusiones: La prevalencia de enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica encontrada fue alta. La exposición laboral puede ser un factor importante en el medio rural (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;90: 0-0, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152938</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica en una zona rural de Guadalajara</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12797^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
