<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136943</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Screening with angiographic images prior to 99mTc-HMPAO labelled leukocyte scintigraphy in the diagnosis of periprosthetic infection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To evaluate the impact of the angioscintigrapy of the three phase bone scan as screening method to rule out infection of the hip and knee prosthesis prior to performing the 99mTc-HMPAO leukocyte scintigraphy. Material and methods. A total of 120 (70 women, 50 men; mean age 71 ± 11 years) with clinical suspicion of hip (n = 63) or knee (n = 57) infection of the prosthesis and clinical suspicion of infection were evaluated prospectively. All patients underwent three-phase bone scan (angioscintigraphy, vascular and bone phase) and 99mTc-HMPAO-labelled white blood cell scintigraphy. Final diagnosis of infection was made by microbiological documentation or clinical follow-up for at least 12 months. Results. Eighteen out of 120 patients were diagnosed of infection of hip prosthesis (n = 10) or knee prosthesis (n = 8). The angioscintigraphy was positive in 15/18 infected cases and in 21/102 of the non-infected cases with a sensitivity of 83%, specificity of 79% and negative predictive value of 97%. Sensitivity and specificity of 99mTc-HMPAO leukocyte scintigraphy were 72% and 95%, respectively. If the leukocyte labeled scintigraphies had been used exclusively for patients with positive angioscintigraphy, this would have saved up to 70% of the 99mTc-HMPAO leukocyte scintigraphies performed. There were no cases of infection with positive labeled leukocyte scintigraphy and negative angioscintigraphy. Conclusion. Angioscintigraphy (blood flow phase of bone scan) is a useful technique for screening for hip and knee joint prosthesis infection, significantly reducing the need for 99mTc-HMPAO leukocyte scintigraphy without affecting the sensitivity of the technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Granados, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuster, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bori, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perlaza, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar la utilidad de la fase angiogammagráfica de la gammagrafía ósea en 3 fases como posible método de cribado en el diagnóstico de infección de prótesis de cadera y de rodilla, previa a la realización de la gammagrafía con leucocitos marcados. Material y métodos. Se analizaron prospectivamente 120 pacientes (70 mujeres y 50 hombres) con edad media de 71 ± 11 años y sospecha clínica de infección de prótesis de cadera (n = 63) o rodilla (n = 57), a los que se realizó gammagrafía ósea en 3 fases (angiogammagrafía, fase vascular y fase ósea) y gammagrafía con leucocitos marcados con 99mTc-HMPAO. El diagnóstico definitivo se realizó mediante estudio microbiológico o seguimiento clínico mínimo de 12 meses. Resultados. Se estableció el diagnóstico de infección de la prótesis articular en 18/120 pacientes: 10 pacientes con prótesis de cadera y 8 pacientes con prótesis de rodilla. La angiogammagrafía fue positiva en 15/18 pacientes infectados y en 21/102 pacientes no infectados, mostrando una sensibilidad del 83%, una especificidad del 79% y un valor predictivo negativo del 97%. La gammagrafía con leucocitos marcados mostró una sensibilidad y una especificidad del 72 y del 95%, respectivamente. Si se realizara la gammagrafía con leucocitos marcados exclusivamente a los pacientes con angiogammagrafía positiva, se reduciría un 70% de gammagrafías con leucocitos practicadas. No hubo ningún caso de infección con gammagrafía con leucocitos marcados positiva y angiogammagrafía negativa. Conclusiones. La angiogammagrafía es una buena técnica de cribado de infección de prótesis articulares de cadera y rodilla, disminuyendo significativamente el número de gammagrafías con leucocitos marcados, sin afectar la sensibilidad de la técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);34(4): 219-224, jul.-ago. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado mediante angiogammagrafía previo a la realización de gammagrafía con leucocitos 99mTc-HMPAO en el diagnóstico de infección de prótesis articulares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8140^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7763^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24665^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33627^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8140^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8138^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7763^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
