<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128612</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The surgical treatment of hemorrhoids</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Surgery is the most effective treatment in patients with symptomatic grade III-IV hemorrhoids who have not responded to outpatient treatment, when there is associated abnormalities (anal fissure, anal fistula, skin tags) and in thrombosed hemorrhoids. Hemorrhoidectomy is currently the "gold standard" treatment. Randomized controlled trials comparing open with closed hemorrhoidectomy show no significant differences in pain scores. Stapled hemorrhoidectomy produces less postoperative pain than hemorrhoidectomy but is less effective in terms of symptom control. No treatment is superior to others in reducing postoperative pain except the use of drugs and anesthetic techniques. In patients with prolapsed internal hemorrhoids and thrombosed hemorrhoids, treatment may initially consist of an urgent hemorrhoidectomy with the same results as those obtained with elective surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oteiza, Fabiola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciga, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel, Mario de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento quirúrgico de las hemorroides está indicado en aquellas de grados III-IV, sintomáticas, que no han respondido al tratamiento conservador, ante una enfermedad asociada (fisura, fístula, colgajos cutáneos grandes) y en la trombosis hemorroidal. La hemorroidectomía sigue siendo el patrón oro. Los estudios aleatorizados no muestran ventajas de la técnica cerrada con relación a la abierta para reducir el dolor. La hemorroidopexia grapada produce menos dolor postoperatorio con relación a la hemorroidectomía, pero es menos eficaz para resolver los síntomas asociados a las hemorroides. Ningún procedimiento ha demostrado ventajas en reducir el dolor postoperatorio, salvo el uso de fármacos o técnicas anestésicas. En las hemorroides internas prolapsadas y trombosadas se puede realizar una hemorroidectomía de urgencia con los mismos resultados que con la cirugía electiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);78(supl.3): 15-23, dic. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128612</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento quirúrgico de las hemorroides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31020^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6638^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55038^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
