<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131682</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Immunisation schedule of the Spanish Association of Paediatrics: 2015 Recommendations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Advisory Committee on Vaccines of the Spanish Association of Paediatrics updates the immunisation schedule every year, taking into account epidemiological data as well as evidence on the safety, effectiveness and efficiency of current vaccines, including levels of recommendation. In our opinion, this is the optimal vaccination calendar for all children resident in Spain. Regarding the vaccines included in the official unified immunization schedule, the Committee emphasizes the administration of the first dose of hepatitis B either at birth or at 2 months of life; the recommendation of the first dose of MMR and varicella vaccine at the age of 12 months, with the second dose at the age of 2-3 years; DTaP or Tdap vaccine at the age of 6 years, followed by another Tdap booster dose at 11-12 years old; Tdap strategies for pregnant women and household contacts of the newborn, and immunization against human papillomavirus in girls aged 11-12 years old with a 2 dose scheme (0, 6 months).  The Committee reasserts its recommendation to include vaccination against pneumococcal disease in the routine immunisation schedule, the same as it is being conducted in Western European countries. The recently authorised meningococcal B vaccine, currently blocked in Spain, exhibits the profile of a universal vaccine. The Committe insists on the need of having the vaccine available in communitary pharmacies. It has also proposed the free availability of varicella vaccines. Their efectiveness and safety have been confirmed when they are administred from the second year of life. Vaccination against rotavirus is recommended in all infants. The Committee stresses the need to vaccinate population groups considered at risk against influenza and hepatitis A (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Pérez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Merino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>gar´cia Sánchez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortigosa del Castillo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arístegui Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cilleruelo Ortega, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sampelayo Matos, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corretger Rauet, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino Moína, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Contreras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez García, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Comité Asesor de Vacunas de la Asociación Española de Pediatría actualiza anualmente su calendario de vacunaciones, tras un análisis tanto epidemiológico como de la seguridad, efectividad y eficiencia de las vacunas actuales, incluyendo grados de recomendación. Es el calendario que se estima idóneo actualmente para los niños residentes en España. En cuanto a las vacunas oficiales incluidas en el calendario común, se recalca la posibilidad de vacunar indistintamente frente a hepatitis B desde el nacimiento o desde los 2 meses; la recomendación de la primera dosis de triple vírica y de varicela a los 12 meses y la segunda a los 2-3 años; la administración de la vacuna DTPa o Tdpa a los 6 años, con refuerzo en la adolescencia; estrategias con Tdpa en embarazadas y convivientes del recién nacido, y la inmunización frente al papilomavirus en niñas a los 11-12 años con pauta de 2 dosis (0, 6 meses). Este comité insiste en la vacunación antineumocócica universal, tal y como se está llevando a cabo en todos los países de Europa Occidental. La vacuna frente al meningococo B, autorizada pero bloqueada actualmente en España, presenta un perfil de vacuna sistemática y se reivindica que, al menos, esté disponible en las farmacias comunitarias. Se propone, igualmente, la disponibilidad pública de las vacunas frente a la varicela, ya que han demostrado ser efectivas y seguras a partir del segundo año de vida. La vacunación frente al rotavirus es recomendable en todos los lactantes. La vacunación antigripal anual y la inmunización frente a la hepatitis A están indicadas en grupos de riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): 44.e1-44.e2, ene. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131682</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calendario de vacunaciones de la Asociación Española de Pediatría: recomendaciones 2015</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35386^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35386^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11801^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31393^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6658^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6658^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11801^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
