<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131391</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The demand for health care services in the gender identity units of Andalusia and Catalonia during the period of 2000 to 2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the demand for public health services in two gender identity disorder units (Andalusia and Catalonia) during the period of 2000-2009. Method. A descriptive and comparative study was made of the demand for health services, the demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients, and the sex reassignment surgeries performed. Results. A total of 828 subjects in Andalusia and 549 in Catalonia requested clinical assistance. In both communities, the percentages of cases diagnosed of transsexualism (88 vs 89.7%), the percentages excluded in the sex reassignment program (16.7 vs 15.3%), the male/female ratio (1.6:1 vs 2.1:1), and the mean age (28 vs 29years) were similar. A total of 284 sex-reassignment surgeries were performed in Andalusia and 50 in Catalonia. Conclusions. The demand has been maintained in Andalusia and has increased in Catalonia in recent years. The basic demographic (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Godás Sieso, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Halperin Rabinovich, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Gil, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteva de Antonio, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almaraz, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriguer Escofet, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar de forma comparada la demanda de atención sanitaria pública en dos unidades de trastornos de la identidad de género (Andalucía y Cataluña) durante la década 2000-2009. Método. Estudio descriptivo y comparativo de la demanda sanitaria, características de los solicitantes y cirugías realizadas. Resultados. Han solicitado asistencia sanitaria 828 pacientes en Andalucía y 549 en Cataluña. En ambas comunidades es similar el porcentaje de casos que cumplen criterios de transexualismo (88 vs. 89,8%), la frecuencia de casos excluidos del programa de reasignación sexual (16,7 vs. 15,3%), la razón de sexos hombre/mujer (1,6:1 vs. 2,1:1), y la edad media (28 vs. 29 años). Se han realizado 284 cirugías de reasignación sexual en Andalucía y 50 en Cataluña. Conclusiones. La demanda en Andalucía se ha mantenido estable y en Cataluña se ha incrementado en los últimos años. Las características demográficas y clínicas de los pacientes transexuales son similares y acordes con la mayoría de estudios realizados en otros países(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;211(5): 233-239, mayo 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demanda de atención sanitaria en las unidades de identidad de género de Andalucía y Cataluña durante la década 2000 a 2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6454^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6454^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
