<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90807</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-4723</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Human African Trypanosomiasis (HAT) is currently treated with medicines introduced more than80 years ago. Despite clinical trials carried out within the last 10 years, no new medicine has-been added to the current ones available for stage I, suramine and pentamidine, or stage II, melarsoprol,eflornithine and nifurtimox. The main progress in HAT treatment over the last 10 years has consisted in establishing new protocols with the existent medicines. Recently, compounds like fexinidazole have been identified and it could represent, within the next decade, new alternatives for the treatment of this fatal disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Postigo, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Tripanosomiasis Humana Africana (THA) se trata actualmente con medicamentos que fueron introducidos hace más de 80 años. A pesar de los ensayos clínicos realizados en los últimos 10años ningún medicamento nuevo se ha podido añadir a los ya conocidos para tratar el estadioI, suramina y pentamidina, o el estadio II, melarsoprol, eflornitina y nifurtimox. Los principales avances en el tratamiento de la THA en los últimos 10 años han consistido en el establecimiento de nuevas pautas terapéuticas con los medicamentos existentes. Recientemente se han identificado compuestos como el fexinidazol que podrían representar, dentro de la próxima década, nuevas alternativas para el tratamiento de esta mortal enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. emerg;11(2): 71-80, abr.-jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avances en el tratamiento de la Tripanosomiasis Humana Africana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14751^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13879^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9733^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8717^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10613^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14748^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14755^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
