<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165334</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Incidence of hypophosphatemia in not critically ill patients with enteral feeding</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Up to 30-40% of the patients starting artificial nutritional support develop hypophosphatemia. In general, patients with mild and moderate hypophosphatemia do not have symptoms, but severe hypophosphatemia is the hallmark of refeeding syndrome. Aim: To determine the incidence of hypophosphatemia in not critically ill patients receiving enteral feeding. Material and methods: Prospective study. We assessed during seven days 181 not critically ill patients started on enteral artificial nutrition support during seven days. Results: 51.9% of the patients were considered to be at risk of developing refeeding syndrome (United Kingdom National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence criteria). The incidence of hypophosphatemia was 31.5%, but only 1.1% of the patients developed severe hypophosphatemia. Older age and lower plasma proteins were significantly associated with hypophosphatemia. Conclusion: The incidence of severe hypophosphatemia in our study is low, so we can&#146;t offer robust conclusions about the risk of hypophosphatemia in the type of patients receiving enteral nutrition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Pérez, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Márquez, Áurea María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bardasco Alonso, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mato Mato, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivero Luis, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alves Pérez, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández López, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Urrutia, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casado Vázquez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiros Blanco, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: se ha descrito una incidencia de hipofosfatemia en pacientes con soporte nutricional especializado (SNE) de hasta el 30-40%. La hipofosfatemia leve y la moderada son generalmente asintomáticas, mientras que la severa es el hecho fundamental del síndrome de realimentación. Objetivo: evaluar la incidencia y gravedad de la hipofosfatemia en pacientes hospitalizados no críticos con nutrición enteral (NE). Material y métodos: se diseñó un estudio observacional y prospectivo en condiciones de práctica clínica habitual. Se recogieron datos clínicos, antropométricos y analíticos de 181 pacientes a los que se les inició nutrición enteral. El seguimiento fue de siete días. Resultados: el 51,9% de los pacientes estaban en riesgo de desarrollar síndrome de realimentación según las guías del United Kingdom National Institute for Health and Clinical Excellence (NICE). La incidencia de hipofosfatemia fue del 31,5% y la de la hipofosfatemia severa, del 1,1%. De todos los parámetros clínicos, antropométricos y analíticos analizados, solo la edad y unas proteínas séricas más bajas se correlacionaron de forma estadísticamente significativa con el aumento en la incidencia de hipofosfatemia. Conclusión: la incidencia de hipofosfatemia grave en nuestra serie es muy baja, lo que hace imposible extraer conclusiones específicas para este grupo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(4): 761-766, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165334</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia de hipofosfatemia en pacientes ingresados no críticos con nutrición enteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31395^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53105^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
