<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042066</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nucleotide P2Y receptors reduce depolarization-evoked calcium entry into rat midbrain synaptic terminals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Studies were carried out to determine the presence and function of P2Yreceptors in synaptic terminals from rat midbrain. Immunochemical essays haveshown the expression of the nucleotide P2Y2 and P2Y4 receptors. Activation ofthese receptors induces a reduction of the calcium entrance into the terminals,when stimulated with depolarising agents. A similar effect is produced by agonistsof metabotropic receptors, such as the adenosine A1 or GABAB receptors, whichare well known for its role in the presynaptic control or transmitter release.Activation of the P2Y receptors also triggers a reduction in the intrasynaptosomalcAMP concentration. Thus, these receptors seem to be negativelycoupled to adenylate cyclase activity. However, we postulate that P2Y receptors areable to reduce calcium entrance into the terminals by the activation of thecorresponding G protein, dissociation of the trimer and action of the âã subunitson voltage activated calcium channels</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gualix, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Villafuertes, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín García, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se han llevado a cabo estudios para determinar la presencia y función de receptoresP2Y en terminales sinápticas de cerebro medio. Ensayos imnunoquímicoshan mostrado la expresión, en dichas terminales, de los receptores P2Y2 y P2Y4. Laactivación de estos receptores por sus agonistas selectivos lleva a una reducción enla entrada de calcio en las terminales, inducida por agentes despolarizantes. Esteefecto es similar al que producen agonistas de otros receptores metabotrópicos,como los A1 de adenosina o los GABAB, conocidos por su papel en el controlpresináptico de la liberación de neurotransmisores.La activación de los receptores P2Y conduce asimismo a una disminución enlos niveles intrasinaptosomales de AMPc, por lo que estos receptores parecen estaracoplados negativamente a la actividad de la adenilato ciclasa. Sin embargo, seplantea como hipótesis que los receptores P2Y pudiesen actuar reduciendo laentrada de calcio en las terminales a través de la disociación de la proteína G ala que están acoplados, y la posterior acción del dímero âã sobre canales de calciodependientes de voltaje</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;71(3): 659-672, jul. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042066</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los receptores de nucleótidos P2Y reducen la entrada de calcio inducida por despolarización en terminales sinápticos de cerebro medio de rata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23571^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d269^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33043^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31156^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
