<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-22489</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rosai-Dorfman Disease (Sinus Histiocytosis with Massive Lymphadenopathy). A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The entity known as sinus histiocytosis with massive lymphadenopathy (SHML), or Rosai-Dorfman disease, is an uncommon benign proliferation of hematopoietic and fibrous tissue is that often present in the head and neck region. Its initial manifestations include bilateral cervical adenopathies, and in a high percentage it has an extranodal affectation. Its cause is unknown and it usually resolves satisfactorily. We present a case and we revise the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad conocida como Histiocitosis Sinusal con Linfadenopatías Masivas (SHML) o enfermedad de Rosai-Dorfman es una patología histiocítica proliferativa que afecta a los ganglios linfáticos principalmente, sobre todo los cervicales, y en un alto porcentaje tiene afectación extraganglionar. Su causa y patogenia son desconocidas y suele evolucionar favorablemente. Presentamos un caso y revisamos la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;54(5): 384-387, mayo 2003. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad de Rosai-Dorfman (Histiocitosis Sinusal con Linfadenopatías Masivas): a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agut Fuster, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viel Martínez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Martínez, , MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agulles Fornés, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo  Biosca, MJ del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-22489</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d13596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9524</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13590</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
