<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053061</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Research line: nursing care and practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article shows the development of the research line and the accomplished projects concerning the care phenomenon executed by the investigation group "Conceptualization and Practice" -of the Nursing Faculty of the Pontificia Universidad Javeriana of Bogotá-, Colombia. The results are presented as part of a systematic methodological process whose range and projections from an academic and research function contribute to the care phenomenon construction in the Nursing world</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Daza de Caballero, Rosita</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo muestra el desarrollo de la línea de investigación y los proyectos realizados alrededor del fenómeno de Cuidado, por parte del grupo de investigación Conceptualización y Práctica de la Facultad de Enfermería de la Pontificia Javeriana de Bogotá, Colombia. Los resultados se presentan como parte de un proceso metodológico sistemático, cuyos alcances y proyecciones, desde la función académica e investigativa, contribuyen a la construcción del fenómeno del Cuidado en el mundo de la Enfermería</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;14(50): 57-60, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053061</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidado y práctica de enfermería. Línea de Investigación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4574</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
