<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149479</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A decade of reflection on health plans in Spain. SESPAS report 2010</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article reports the experience of the Working Group of the SESPAS-SCSP (Spanish Society of Public Health and Healthcare Administration-Canary Islands Society of Public Health) in health policy and planning during the first decade of the 21st century and its possible impact on the design of health planning. We review the conclusions reached from 2000 to 2008 in the first five Biannual Planning and Health Policy meetings that took place during that period. The workshops were designed with two speakers who presented different views of the subject under discussion, a moderator, who led the debate on the findings, and a narrator who served as a notary and also took responsibility for the text summary of each table. Two general narrators were responsible for the final wording of the conclusions of each workshop or biannual meeting. From 2000 to 2008, there were 25 round tables with 121 conclusions and 160 participants. We believe that the SESPAS working groups provide multidisciplinary professional values within a context of debate in a professional environment, and create spaces for reflection, thus helping to improve the health planning system in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguiar Rodríguez, Juan Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fiuza Pérez, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monzón Batista, Nayra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo se presenta la experiencia acumulada por el Grupo de Trabajo SESPAS-SCSP (Sociedad Española de Salud Pública y Administración Sanitaria-Sociedad Canaria de Salud Pública) sobre Planificación y Política Sanitaria durante la primera década del siglo XXI y su posible repercusión en el diseño de la planificación sanitaria. Repasamos las conclusiones obtenidas del periodo 2000&#150;2008 en las cinco primeras Bienales de Planificación y Política Sanitaria. Las mesas de trabajo se diseñaron con un ponente y un replicante que expusieron los diferentes puntos de vista del tema debatido, un moderador que dirigía el debate hacia las conclusiones y un relator que ejercía de notario y asumía la responsabilidad del texto de síntesis de cada mesa. Para la redacción final de las conclusiones de cada taller o bienal contamos con dos relatores generales. Entre los años 2000 y 2008 se realizaron 25 mesas, con 121 conclusiones y con 160 participantes. Creemos que los grupos de trabajo de SESPAS aportan como valor la multidisciplinariedad profesional dentro de un contexto de debate en una sociedad profesional; crean espacios propicios para la reflexión y contribuyen a aumentar la masa crítica sobre la planificación sanitaria en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;24(supl.1): 37-41, dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149479</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una década de reflexión sobre los planes de salud en España. Informe SESPAS 2010</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28455</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
