<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162965</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiac autonomic responses of trained cyclists at different training amplitudes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: The aim of this study was to evaluate the effect of different training amplitudes on the autonomic nervous system  (ANS) responses and recovery through heart rate (HR), heart rate variability (HRV ) and rate of perceived effort (RPE).  Methods: In a counterbalanced design, male trained cyclists (24.8 ± 6.9 years old) performed three training sessions matched  by total duration (20 min) and by mean power (55% of maximal power output, ), but with different effort:pause ratio and  different amplitudes. Continuous training (CT ) was composed by efforts of 55% of maximal power (Pmax). The low amplitude  training (LAT ) was composed by efforts with 80% of Pmax and pauses of 30% of Pmax, and high amplitude training (HAT ) with efforts of 110% of Pmax and passive pauses (0% of Pmax). Data were analyzed using a two-way ANOVA with repeated  measures or non parametric correspondent.  Results:  HAT promoted superior RPE (9.0 ± 1.0 au) in comparison to the LAT (3.8 ±2.8 au), and CT (2.8 ± 1.5 au) with p &lt;.01,  and higher increments in the maximal HR (172.8 ± 11.8 bpm) in comparison to the CT (140.8 ± 14.2 bpm, p = .001). Regarding  HRV, the three protocols had similar results, except by the CT, which did not return to baseline levels after 24h of rest.  Conclusions: The HAT showed higher impact on the RPE and in maximum HR at the end of the session and the HRV variables  showed similar responses despite the difference in the training protocols (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Del Vecchio, Fabriíio B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picanço, Luan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cavalheiro, Gilberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaz, Marcelo S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar el efecto de diferentes amplitudes de entrenamiento sobre las respuestas  y recuperación del sistema nervioso autónomo (SNA) por medio de la frecuencia cardíaca (FC), variabilidad de la frecuencia  cardíaca (VFC) y tasa de esfuerzo percibido (RPE).  Métodos: En diseño contrabalanceado, ciclistas masculinos entrenados (24.8± 6.9 años de edad) realizaron tres sesiones de entrenamiento emparejados con duración total (20 min) y promedio de potencia (55% de la potencia máxima), pero con diferentes tasas de esfuerzo-pausa y diferentes amplitudes. El entrenamiento continuo (EC) fue compuesto por esfuerzos de 55% de la máxima potencia (Pmax). El ejercicio con baja amplitud de entrenamiento (EBA) fue compuesto por esfuerzos de 80% de la Pmax con pausas de 30% de la Pmax, y en entrenamiento en alta amplitud (EAA) con esfuerzos de 110% de la Pmax y pausas passivas (0% de la Pmax. Los datos fueron analizados mediante ANOVA de dos vías con medidas repetidas o su correspondiente no paramétrico. Resultados:  EAA promovió RPE superiores (9.0 ± 1.0 u.a) en comparación con EBA (3.8 ± 2.8 au), y EC (2.8 ± 1.5 u.a) con p&lt;.01, con elevados incrementos en la FC máxima (172.8 ± 11.8 bpm) en comparación con EC (140.8 ± 14.2 bpm, p=.001).  Considerándose la VFC, los tres protocolos tuvieron resultados similares, excepto por el EC, pues no volvió a los niveles basales después de 24h de descanso.  Conclusiones: El EAA presentó mayor impacto en la RPE y en la FC máxima al final de la sesión y las variables de VFC mostraron respuestas similares a pesar de la diferencia en los protocolos de entrenamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;34(177): 15-20, ene.-feb. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162965</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuesta del sistema cardiaco autónomo en ciclistas entrenados con diferentes amplitudes de entrenamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d38384</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29097^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1667^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1349^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
