<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045722</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of Helicobacter pylori in stomach cancer after partial gastrectomy for benign ulcer disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to determine the prevalence of Helicobacter pylori infection in patients having undergone gastrectomy for nonneoplastic disease who later developed gastric stump cancer. Material and methods: retrospective study of all patients with partial gastrectomy for non-malignant peptic disease who were submitted to an endoscopic exploration between 1995 and 2001. A comparison was made of major clinical and histological characteristics, and the presence of Helicobacter pylori among patients with and without gastric cancer in the stomach remnant. Results: a total of 73 patients were studied in this period. Fifteen patients (20.5%) had remnant-stump gastric cancer. All but one were adenocarcinomas (71% intestinal and 29% diffuse, respectively). The average time between diagnosis of gastric cancer and previous gastrectomy was 32 (14-48) years. There was a higher detection rate of Helicobacter pylori in patients with cancer in the gastric remnant (100 vs. 81.5%, respectively, p &lt;0.07). No relationship was seen between type of gastric reconstruction (Billroth I or II) and rate of Helicobacter pylori detection. Conclusions: Helicobacter pylori infection is frequent in patients with previous gastrectomy for non-neoplastic disease. The results of the study suggest that Helicobacter pylori infection may play a role in gastric stump cancer</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andreu, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alameda, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>O&#146;Callaghan, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bessa, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Munné, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallen, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bory, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seoane, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Panadès, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar la prevalencia de la infección por Helicobacter pylori en pacientes gastrectomizados por enfermedad no neoplásica, y que han desarrollado posteriormente cáncer gástrico. Material y métodos: estudio retrospectivo con reclutamiento de todos los pacientes con gastrectomía parcial por enfermedad péptica benigna que han sido sometidos a una exploración endoscópica entre 1995-2001. Se ha realizado una comparación de las principales características clínicas e histológicas y de la presencia de Helicobacter pylori en los pacientes con y sin cáncer del remanente gástrico. Resultados: se han estudiado un total de 73 pacientes en este periodo. Se han encontrado 15 pacientes (20,5%) con cáncer en el remanente gástrico, 14 adenocarcinomas (71% tipo intestinal y 29% tipo difuso) y un linfoma. El tiempo transcurrido entre el diagnóstico de cáncer gástrico y la gastrectomía previa ha sido de 32 (14-48) años. Se ha detectado un alto porcentaje de infecciónpor Helicobacter pylori (100% en los pacientes con cáncervs. 81,5% en los pacientes sin cáncer, p &lt; 0,07). No se ha observado relación entre el tipo de reconstrucción gástrica (Billroth I o II) y el porcentaje de infección por Helicobacter pylori. Conclusiones: la infección por Helicobacter pylori es frecuente en pacientes gastrectomizados por patología benigna. Los resultados de este estudio sugieren que la infección por Helicobacter pylori podría jugar un papel en el cáncer gástrico</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;97(11): 778-785, nov. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045722</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel del Helicobacter pylori en el cáncer gástrico tras gastrectomía parcial por úlcera benigna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5884</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13666^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32236^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13666^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5894^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5894^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
