<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86110</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consensus statement of the Spanish Society of Rheumatology on the management of biologic therapies in spondyloarthritis except for psoriatic arthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Due to the amount and variability in quality regarding the use of biologic therapy (BT) in patients with spondyloarthritis (SpA), except for psoriatic arthritis (PsA) patients, the Spanish Society of Rheumatology has promoted the generation of recommendations based on the best evidence available. These recommendations should be a reference for rheumatologists and those involved in the treatment of patients with spondyloarthritis (SpA), except for psoriatic arthritis (PsA), who are using, or about to use BT. Methods. Recommendations were developed following a nominal group methodology and based on systematic reviews. The level of evidence and grade of recommendation were classified according to the model proposed by the Center for Evidence Based Medicine at Oxford. The level of agreement was established through Delphi technique. Results. We have produced recommendations on the use of BT currently available for SpA (but not PsA) in our country. These recommendations include disease assessment, treatment objectives, therapeutic scheme and switching. Conclusions. We present an update on the SER recommendations for the use of BT in patients with SpA, except for PsA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juanola Roura, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarco Montejo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mulero Mendoza, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares Ferrando, Luis Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batlle Gualda, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collantes Estevez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Fernández, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariza Ariza, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Vicuña, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Sanz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gratacós Masmitja, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loza Santamaría, Estíbaliz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez Carballido, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Dada la gran cantidad de información sobre las terapias biológicas (TB) en las espondiloartritis (EspA), excepto la artritis psoriásica (APs), y la variabilidad en cuanto a su calidad, desde la Sociedad Española de Reumatología (SER) se ha impulsado la generación de recomendaciones basadas en la mejor evidencia posible. Estas deben de servir de referencia para reumatólogos e implicados en el tratamiento de estos pacientes. Métodos. Las recomendaciones se emitieron siguiendo la metodología de grupos nominales. El nivel de evidencia y el grado de recomendación se clasificaron según el modelo del Center for Evidence Based Medicine de Oxford y el grado de acuerdo se extrajo por técnica Delphi. Resultados. Se realizan recomendaciones sobre el uso de las TB para el tratamiento de las EspA (excepto la APs). Incluyen la evaluación de la enfermedad, objetivos del tratamiento, esquema terapéutico y cambios en éste. Conclusiones. Se presentan las actualizaciones a las recomendaciones SER para el uso de TB en pacientes con EsA, excepto la APs(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);7(2): 113-123, mar.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86110</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Documento SER de consenso sobre el uso de terapias biológicas en la espondilitis anquilosante y otras espondiloartritis, excepto la artritis psoriásica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36004^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22870</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
