<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18151</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A preliminary report on distribution and demography of primates in Eritrea</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At least three diurnal primate taxa are still present in Eritrea, NE Africa: hamadryas baboons (Papio h. hamadryas), olive baboons (Papio h. anubis) and grivet monkeys (Cercopithecus a. aethiops). During a survey, focusing on hamadryas baboons, we achieved information about their geographical distribution and abundance, their altitudinal range, the habitat quality of their home-ranges, and aggregation sizes at sleeping cliffs. We also collected detailed demographic data on six bands of hamadryas baboons at four sites in different eco-geographical zones. Opportunistically, we gathered information about the situation of olive baboons and grivet monkeys. Both baboon taxa are still present in Eritrea in good numbers. An estimated 15,000 Papio h. hamadryas live in the 25,000 Km2 area of survey (0.58 baboons/Km2). Preliminary comparative information on habitat quality and demography are given with other studies in Ethiopia and Saudi Arabia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zinner, Dietmar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peláez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En Eritrea, nordeste de África, se encuentran todavía tres taxones de primates: papiones hamadryas (Papio h. hamadryas), papiones anubis (Papio h. anubis) y monos grivet (Cercopithecus a. aethiops). En una expedición centrada en los papiones hamadryas, hemos recogido información sobre la distribución geográfica, su rango altitudinal, calidad del hábitat en sus territorios y tamaño de las agregaciones en los roquedos donde duermen. También hemos recogido datos demográficos de seis bandas de hamadryas en cuatro puntos de distintas ecozonas de Eritrea central. De manera oportunista reunimos información de papiones anubis y de monos grivet allí donde los encontramos. Ambos taxones de Papio son todavía muy numerosos en Eritrea. Hemos estimado una población de 15.000 papiones hamadryas en los 25.000 Km' recorridos (0,58 papiones/Km2).En este trabajo hacemos una estimación comparativa preliminar sobre la calidad del hábitat y demografía de los papiones hamadryas de Eritrea y los de otros estudios en Etiopía y Arabia Saudita (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(2): 239-246, mayo 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18151</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un estudio preliminar sobre la distribución y demografía de los primates de Eritrea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28576</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11759</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d357</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10402</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2558</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
