<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146762</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical profile, level of affection and therapeutic management of patients with osteoarthritis in primary care: the Spanish multicenter study EVALÚA</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the clinical profile, degree of involvement and management in patients with knee, hip or hand osteoarthritis. Material and method. Observational study (health centers from 14 autonomous regions, n=363 primary care physicians), involving patients with clinical and/or radiological criteria for osteoarthritis from the American College of Rheumatology, consecutively selected (n=1,258). Sociodemographic variables, clinical and radiological findings, comorbidity and therapeutic management were analyzed. Results. Mean age was 68.0±9.5 years old; 77.8% were women and 47.6% obese. Distribution by location was: 84.3% knee, 23.4% hip, 14.7% hands. All patients reported pain. The most frequent radiographic Kellgren-Lawrence grade was stage 3 for knee and hip (42.9% and 51.9%, respectively), and 3 (37.2%) and 2 (34.5%) for hip. Time since onset of osteoarthritis symptoms was 9.4±7.5 years, with a mean age at onset of around 60 years old and a family history of osteoarthritis in 66.0%. The most frequent comorbidities were: hypertension (55.1%), depression/anxiety (24.7%) and gastroduodenal diseases (22.9%). A total of 97.6% of the patients received pharmacological treatment, with oral analgesics (paracetamol) (70.5%) and oral NSAIDs (67.9%) being the most frequent drugs. Bilateral osteoarthritis was present in 76.9% of patients with knee osteoarthritis, 59.3% in hip and 94.7% in hands. Female gender and time since onset were associated with bilateral knee and hip osteoarthritis. onclusions. The profile of the osteoarthritis patient is female, &gt;65 years old, overweight/obese, with comorbidity, frequent symptoms and moderate radiologic involvement. Most of patients had bilateral osteoarthritis, associated with female gender and time since onset of disease. Paracetamol was the most common pharmacological treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toro Santos, Francisco Javier de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Carou, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pita Fernández, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pértega Díaz, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar el perfil clínico, afectación y tratamiento en pacientes con artrosis de rodilla, cadera y manos. Material y método. Estudio observacional (Centros de Salud de 14 comunidades autónomas, n=363 médicos). Se incluye a pacientes con criterios clínicos/radiológicos de artrosis del American College of Rheumatology, seleccionados consecutivamente (n=1.258). Se analizan variables sociodemográficas, los hallazgos clínico-radiológicos, la comorbilidad y el tratamiento. Resultados. La media ± desviación estándar de edad fue 68,0±9,5 años, 77,8% eran mujeres y 47,6% tenían obesidad. Un 84,3% tenía artrosis de rodilla, un 23,4% de cadera y un 14,7% de manos. Todos los pacientes referían dolor. El grado radiológico de Kellgren-Lawrence más frecuente en rodilla y mano fue el 3 (42,9% y 51,9%, respectivamente), y en cadera grado 3 (37,2%) y 2 (34,5%). El tiempo de evolución de los síntomas de artrosis fue 9,4±7,5 años, con edad de inicio alrededor de 60 años. El 66% de los pacientes tenían antecedentes de artrosis. Las comorbilidades más frecuentes son: hipertensión (55,1%), depresión/ansiedad (24,7%) y patología gastroduodenal (22,9%). Un 97,6% recibía tratamiento farmacológico, los más utilizados son: analgésicos orales (paracetamol) (70,5%) y AINE orales (67,9%). Presentaban afectación bilateral el 76,9% de los pacientes con artrosis de rodilla, el 59,3% en cadera y el 94,7% en manos. El sexo femenino y mayor tiempo de evolución se asocian a afectación bilateral en rodilla y cadera. onclusiones. El perfil del paciente artrósico es de mujer &gt; 65 años, con sobrepeso-obesidad, comorbilidad, clínica frecuente y afectación radiológica moderada. La mayoría presenta afectación bilateral, asociada al sexo femenino y el tiempo de evolución. El paracetamol es el fármaco más utilizado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);11(6): 353-360, nov.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil clínico, grado de afectación y manejo terapéutico de pacientes con artrosis en atención primaria: estudio multicéntrico nacional EVALÚA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33759^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55021^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
