<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155456</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analisis of the quality of parenteral nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Parenteral nutrition is an important frame in the treatment of inpatients. It helps with the outcomes in the diseases. The big problem with it is their use, there are a lot of complications around the use of inappropriate nutrition. The nutrition support team is made by hospital pharmacist, their aim is to have a good use of the central and peripheral parenteral nutrition. Objective: In this study our aim is to measure the quality of the parenteral nutrition administration in the nutrition unit in our hospital Pharmacy in a private general hospital. Methods: We review the inpatients who have received parenteral nutrition during a period of 4,5months, by our nutrition support team, and we compare it with another group of inpatients with parenteral nutrition before the beginning of this team. Results: We have decreased from 41.4% to 17.2% the percentage of inappropriate indications of parenteral nutrition in compliance with mandatory European guidelines nutrition in control group and in the study group respectively, and we have a decreased of 50% in the number of the short administration of the parenteral nutrition too, but still do not accomplish quality standard. The rest of quality indicators are meet standards in all of them, good caloric intake, progressive suspension of the nutrition, and monitoring of patients. Conclusions: The nutrition support team in a Pharmacy Service has reduced inappropriate use of parenteral nutrition, as well as the use of short-term parenteral nutrition. Meet the target of quality standards in terms of energy requirements administered and patient monitoring (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berisa Prado, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La nutrición parenteral, forma parte del tratamiento farmacológico de los pacientes hospitalizados, mejorando su evolución clínica. Sin embargo, se encuentra como gran inconveniente, las complicaciones derivadas de su uso inadecuado. Con esto motivo, se crearon las unidades de nutrición, formadas por farmacéuticos hospitalarios, cuyo objetivo es el uso apropiado de la nutrición parenteral tanto central como periférica. Objetivos: Estimar la calidad de la administración de la nutrición parenteral desde una unidad de nutrición clínica dentro del Servicio de Farmacia en un Hospital general privado. Métodos: Revisión de los pacientes con nutrición parenteral en el área de hospitalización durante un periodo de 4 meses y medio, por el equipo de la unidad de nutrición (grupo estudio), comparados con un grupo de pacientes, con nutrición parenteral previo a la implantación de dicha unidad de nutrición (grupo control). Resultados: Se observa una disminución del 24,2% del número de nutriciones que no cumplen con la indicación según las guías europeas en el grupo de estudio respecto al control, no llegando a cumplir los estándares de calidad establecidos; se ha obtenido una reducción del 50% de la nutrición parenteral de corta duración, el resto de los indicadores de calidad en el grupo de estudio sí que se cumplen en cuanto a aporte calórico recibido calculado adecuadamente, suspensión progresiva de la nutrición y monitorización de los pacientes. Conclusiones: La unidad de nutrición dentro del Servicio de Farmacia ha logrado reducir el uso inapropiado de la nutrición parenteral, así como el uso de la nutrición parenteral de corta duración. Cumpliendo los estándares de calidad en cuanto a requerimientos energéticos administrados y monitorización de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;36(3): 59-67, 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155456</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Analisis de la calidad de la nutricion parenteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5661^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
