<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145253</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Blunted erythropoietic response in the anemia of anorexia nervosa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The cause of the anemia in anorexia nervosa (AN) has not been fully ascertained. Ferritin, folate and cobalamin values are usually within normal ranges. Anemia does not have a relationship with bone marrow changes and erythropoietin (EPO) levels have not been investigated. The objective of this study was to evaluate the EPO response in a small group of AN patients. Patients and methods: EPO levels were measured in serum samples of 41 female AN patients (11 with anemia, and 30 with normal blood cell count). The adequacy of EPO response was assessed by comparing the increase observed in a group of normal weight patients with anemia. Results: EPO concentrations in anemic AN patients were higher than in non-anemic: 20.63 mU/mL (4.04-28.46) vs 8.7 mU/mL (3.9-20.93), P = .0088, but the increase in EPO was lower than expected (27.85 mU/mL [17.7-118.9]), P = .014. BMI and the difference between actual and expected EPO were inversely correlated. Conclusions: Inadequate EPO response may partly explain anemia in AN, but further studies are necessary (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sorigué, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldea, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Planell, Lluis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Hernández, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granada, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juncà, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: La causa o causas de la anemia que acompaña a la anorexia nerviosa (AN) no ha sido establecida, pero no parece relacionarse con deficiencias nutricionales ni cambios medulares. El objetivo de este trabajo fue evaluar la producción de eritropoyetina (EPO) en respuesta a la anemia en un pequeño grupo de pacientes con AN y anemia. Pacientes y métodos: Los niveles de EPO en muestras de suero de 41 mujeres con AN (11 con anemia y 30 sin alteraciones en los parámetros de la serie eritroide) se compararon con la respuesta observada en un grupo de pacientes de peso normal con  anemia. Resultados: Las concentraciones de EPO en pacientes con AN anémicas fueron mayores que en las no anémicas: 20,63 mU/ml (4,04 a 28,46) frente a 8,7 mU/ml (3,9 a 20,93), p = 0,0088, pero el aumento de EPO fue menor de lo esperado (27,85 mU/ml [17,7 a 118,9]), p = 0,014. La correlación entre el IMC y la diferencia entre la EPO y la EPO esperada es inversa. Conclusiones: Una producción inadecuada de EPO puede explicar en parte la anemia en la AN. Son necesarios más estudios para investigar la causa de esta respuesta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);145(10): 433-435, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145253</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disminución de la respuesta eritropoyética en pacientes con anorexia nerviosa y anemia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6555^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33527^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30606^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30606^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24194^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
