<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90040</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New therapeutic strategies for stroke prevention in patients with atrial fibrillation: a perspective from Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the most common sustained arrhythmia, which leads to a higher number of hospital admissions and is the main cause of stroke of cardioembolic origin. According to the recommendations of the clinical practice guidelines, therapeutic strategy in AF has as its priority objectives, among others, the correction of the rhythm disorder with reversion, control of the heart rate, and prevention of thromboembolism. Anticoagulant treatment with warfarin or acenocoumarol is the keystone to the prevention of stroke in patients with AF, and has been the standard treatment for more than half a century. Their use in clinical practice, although it is widely unknown, requires regular monitoring to maintain the correct dose, which makes it difficult to be accepted by patients and doctors. The new oral synthetic anticoagulants are an important advance in the prevention of stroke and systemic embolism in patients with FA. Some of them, such as dabigatran, have recently been approved in the USA and Canada in the indication of arterial thromboembolic complications in patients with AF. If this indication, as is expected, is approved in our country, the importance of the role of coumarin derivatives (Sintrom®) will not last much longer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llisterri Caro, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Canales, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios Alonso, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrilación auricular (FA) es la arritmia sostenida más frecuente, la que produce mayor número de ingresos hospitalarios y la principal causa de ictus de origen cardioembólico. Según recomiendan las guías de práctica clínica la estrategia terapéutica en la FA tiene como objetivos prioritarios, y no excluyentes, la corrección del trastorno del ritmo con reversión a ritmo sinusal, el control de la frecuencia cardiaca y la prevención de la tromboembolia. El tratamiento anticoagulante oral con warfarina o acenocumarol constituye la piedra angular para prevenir el ictus en pacientes con FA y ha sido el tratamiento de referencia durante más de medio siglo. Su uso en la práctica clínica, aunque está ampliamente reconocido, precisa una monitorización regular para mantener la dosis correcta, lo cual dificulta su aceptación por parte de pacientes y médicos. Los nuevos antitrombóticos orales sintéticos suponen un avance importante en la prevención del ictus y embolia sistémica de los pacientes con FA. Alguno de ellos, como es el caso de dabigatran, ha sido recientemente aprobado en EE.UU. y Canadá en la indicación de prevención de complicaciones tromboembólicas arteriales en pacientes con FA. Si se aprueba esta indicación en nuestro país, como es de esperar, el protagonismo del Sintrom® no durará mucho tiempo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);37(7): 352-359, ago.-sept. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90040</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas estrategias terapéuticas para la prevención del ictus en pacientes con fibrilación auricular: perspectiva desde atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15261^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
