<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112564</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654x</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of hepatic metabolic activity in non-alcoholic fatty livers on 18FDG PET/CT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The liver has been used as a reference organ for the assessment of abnormal 18F-fluoro-2-deoxy- d -glucose (18FDG) in the body. Some researchers found that hepatosteatosis significantly changed the hepatic 18FDG uptake, while others did not. This study investigated whether the liver's 18FDG uptake was affected by the diffuse fatty infiltration of the liver. Material and methods. A total of 156 cases were included in this study. Different patient groups were defined according to the liver Hounsfield unit (HU). The HU was calculated from an unenhanced CT, for all patients, and we calculated the mean standardized uptake value (SUVmean) and maximum standardized uptake value (SUVmax) on an 18FDG PET scan. For this purpose, we placed regions of interest (ROIs) on the liver image. We statistically compared the SUVmean and SUVmax measured in the fatty liver patients and the control group. Results. The average SUVmean and SUVmax values were calculated as 2.58±0.66 and 3.94±1, respectively, in the patient group and 2.54±0.57 and 3.7±0.88, respectively, in the control group. We found the average SUVmean and SUVmax values in the fatty liver group and its subsets were not significantly different from the values in the control group (p&gt;0.05). We also did not find any statistically significant correlation between average liver density (HU) and the average SUV values (p&gt;0.05). Conclusion. Fatty infiltration may not have a significant effect on the liver's 18FDG uptake. Thus, the liver may be used as a reference or comparator on 18FDG PET scans in patients with fatty liver disease(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dostbil, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sari, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serdengeçti, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varoðlu, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Önder, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kaya, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El hígado se ha usado como órgano de referencia para evaluar la captación anormal de la 18F-fluoro-2-deoxi- d -glucosa (18FDG). Algunos trabajos publicados muestran que la esteatosis hepática modifica la captación hepática de 18FDG, mientras que otros no encuentran modificaciones. Este trabajo ha estudiado si la captación hepática de 18FDG se ve afectada por la infiltración grasa difusa del hígado. Material y métodos. En este estudio se incluyeron 156 casos. Se definieron diferentes grupos de pacientes de acuerdo a las unidades Hounsfield (HU) del hígado. En todos los pacientes, las HU se calcularon a partir de la TAC sin contraste. Además se calculó el SUVmedio y el SUVmáx en el estudio PET con 18FDG. Para ello se dibujaron regiones de interés (ROI) sobre el área hepática. Se realizó una comparación estadística del SUVmedio y SUVmáx medidos en los pacientes con hígado graso y en un grupo control. Resultados. En el grupo de pacientes, los promedios de SUVmedio y SUVmáx fueron 2,58±0,66 y 3,94±1, respectivamente; en el grupo control fueron 2,54±0,57 y 3,7±0,88, respectivamente. Encontramos que los promedios del SUVmedio y SUVmáx en los pacientes con hígado graso no fueron significativamente diferentes a los valores del grupo control (p&gt;0,05). Asimismo, no detectamos correlación estadísticamente significativa entre los valores de la densidad media del hígado, medida en HU, y el promedio de los SUV (p&gt;0,05). Conclusión. La infiltración grasa no parece tener un efecto significativo sobre la captación hepática de 18FDG. Por ello, el hígado se puede usar como órgano de referencia en los estudios PET con 18FDG realizados en pacientes con enfermedad grasa hepática(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);32(3): 156-161, mayo-jun.2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112564</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación mediante PET/TAC con 18FDG de la actividad metabólica hepática en pacientes con hígado graso de origen no alcohólico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54666^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
