<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143682</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Food patterns associated with a healty body weight in Chilean students of nutrition and dietetics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: to determine food patterns and its association with the consumption of various foods with nutritional status of Chilean university students of Nutrition and Dietetics. Material and methods: cross-sectional study, 634 students were evaluated Nutrition and Dietetics at the Universidad San Sebastián, of Santiago, Concepción, Valdivia and Puerto Montt. Each student a food survey was applied and an anthropometric assessment. Results: 68% of students eat breakfast daily, 36.1% and 37.1% consume the recommended servings of fruits and vegetables, 64.9% consume soft drinks frequently. A positive association was observed between an adecuated weight and the fact of eat vegetables (&amp;#8805; 2 servings/day) OR = 0.662 (0.440 to 0.996), whole grains OR = 0.474 (0.224 to 1.002), low consumption of fried and sweet snack OR = 0.643 (0.406 to 1.019) and OR = 0.545 (0.360 to 0.825) respectively. Conclusions: students have an insufficient intake of healthy foods and a high intake of unhealthy foods, also shows that the intake of vegetables, whole grains, low consumption of fried foods and sweet snacks are associated with a normal nutritional status among students evaluated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fehrmann Rosas, Pamela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Godoy, Eloina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Sánchez, Claudia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Fernández, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yunge Hidalgo, Wilma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Fuentes, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintana Muñoz, Carol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán Agüero, Samuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar los patrones de alimentación y asociar el consumo de diversos alimentos con el estado nutricional de estudiantes universitarios chilenos de Nutrición y Dietética. Material y métodos: estudio transversal. Se evaluaron 634 estudiantes de Nutrición y Dietética de la Universidad San Sebastián de las ciudades de Santiago, Concepción, Valdivia y Puerto Montt. A cada estudiante se le aplicó una encuesta alimentaria y se le realizó una evaluación antropométrica. Resultados: el 68% de los estudiantes consume desayuno diariamente, 36,1% y 37,1% consume las porciones recomendadas de frutas y verduras, el 64,9% consume bebidas azucaradas frecuentemente. Se observa una asociación entre un buen peso corporal y el consumo de verduras (&amp;#8805;  2 porciones/día) OR  =  0,662 (0,440-0,996), alimentos integrales OR = 0,474 (0,224-1,002) y un bajo consumo de frituras y snack dulces OR = 0,643 (0,406- 1,019) y OR = 0,545 (0,360-0,825), respectivamente. Conclusiones: los estudiantes presentan una ingesta insuficiente de alimentos saludables y un elevado consumo de alimentos poco saludables, además se observa que la ingesta de verduras y cereales integrales, así como un bajo consumo de frituras y bocadillos dulces se asocian a un estado nutricional normal en los estudiantes evaluados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(4): 1780-1785, oct. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143682</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrones alimentarios asociados a un peso corporal saludable en estudiantes chilenos de la carrera de nutrición y dietética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15076</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
