<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77486</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0973</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Consumption of alcohol, as measured by the AUDIT questionnaire, in patients in methadone maintenance treatment programs and its relation with other associate factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To study the relationship of alcohol consumption, measured with AUDIT test, with methadone dose in patients assigned to Methadone Maintenance Treatment (MMT) Programs, and other factors often present in this population. Material and methods. We took a random sample of 80 patients in the Drug Adiction Treatment Center of Moratalaz, who were given the AUDIT questionnaire. We obtained data related to the pathology and consumption of various substances from medical records. Results. Patients were divided into groups according to whether they had achieved a score higher or lower than the cut scores of proposed by the authors of the test. There was no significant statistically difference between the daily methadone dose, cocaine use, HIV and HCV among these groups. There was a higher prevalence of risk consumption of alcohol among those patients with a dual diagnosis or who consumed benzodiazepines, with statistically significant differences between different groups. Conclusions. The methadone dose is not associated with the consumption of alcohol in our sample, although there is a high prevalence of alcohol consumption problematic for patients in MMTP. Risky alcohol consumption is more frequent within benzodiazepine users and dual diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Radinova, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Estudiar la posible relación entre consumo de alcohol, medido a través del autoinforme AUDIT, con las de opiáceos (TSO), así como su relación con otros factores presentes frecuentemente en esta población. Material y método. Se tomó una muestra aleatoria de 80 pacientes del Centro de Tratamiento de Drogodependencias de Moratalaz, a quienes se les administró el cuestionario AUDIT. Se obtuvieron datos relacionados con la patología de base y el consumo de diferentes sustancias de la historia clínica. Resultados. Se dividió a los pacientes en grupos, dependiendo de si habían obtenido una puntuación superior o inferior a las puntuaciones de corte propuestas por los autores del test. No hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre las medias de metadona diarias, el consumo de cocaína, la infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana y por el virus de la hepatitis C entre dichos grupos. Encontramos una mayor prevalencia de consumo de riesgo de alcohol entre aquellos pacientes con diagnóstico de patología dual o que consumían benzodiacepinas, con diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los diferentes grupos. Conclusiones. La dosis de metadona no tiene relación con el consumo de alcohol en nuestra muestra, aunque existe una alta prevalencia de consumo problemático de alcohol en los pacientes en TSO. El consumo de riesgo de alcohol se da con más frecuencia en usuarios de benzodiacepinas y en personas con patología dual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trastor. adict;11(4): 278-283, oct.-dic. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77486</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de alcohol en pacientes en tratamiento sustitutivo con opiáceos medido con el cuestionario AUDIT y su relación con otros factores asociados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1593^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8866^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34350^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31907^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
