<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99586</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pressure ulcers and chronic wounds: review of scientific evidence on their prevention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic ulcers produce a significant workload for healthcare workers as well as important economic costs. There is neither well-defined data on treatment of chronic ulcers nor their social and economic burdens. Recently, prevention of chronic and pressure ulcers has been taking a significant interest. Various intervention studies were published about prevention of chronic and pressure ulcers. Interventions included tools to detect pressure ulcers&#146; risk, use of special surfaces to lessen the pressure, prevention of pressure ulcers&#146; recurrence and integrated complex measures. Despite the recommendations of many clinical  guidelines, we noticed a lack of eligibility criteria for most of the interventions. Our review presents the available scientific evidence for prevention of chronic and pressure ulcers. The available literature shows lack of evidence for almost all recommended and commonly used measures. There are no sufficient clinical trials of good quality to support the usefulness of many proposed interventions. It is necessary to re-evaluate the quality of intervention studies and guidelines for prevention  of chronic and pressure ulcers before their dissemination and application (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortíz Otero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farouk Allam, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Aguirre, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Arjona, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucena Rabaneda, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las úlceras crónicas suponen una gran carga de trabajo para el personal sanitario así como un importante esfuerzo económico para los sistemas de salud. No existiendo datos bien definidos sobre el tratamiento de las mismas y la carga social y económica que suponen, la prevención de su aparición toma especial importancia, siendo numerosas las propuestas de intervención para lograrlo. Desde el manejo de herramientas de detección de riesgo a la utilización de superficies especiales para disminuir la presión en el encamado, pasando por el uso de medidas para prevenir la recidiva o de medidas complejas integradas. Pese a las recomendaciones de la mayoría de las Guías Clínicas, cuando en nuestro grupo quisimos hacer un acercamiento al problema lo primero que nos llamó la atención es la falta de criterios de idoneidad para el uso de la mayoría de  las intervenciones. Por ello decidimos pasar revista a las pruebas de evidencia científica existente. De los hallazgos de nuestra revisión bibliográfica se desprende una ausencia de evidencia para la práctica totalidad de las medidas recomendadas y utilizadas habitualmente y una escasez de ensayos clínicos de calidad suficiente para respaldar la utilidad de las intervenciones propuestas. Parece claro que es necesario replantearse la calidad de los estudios y la fuerza de recomendación que algunas Guías otorgan a estas medidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;15(1): 13-15, ene.-mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99586</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Úlceras por presión y heridas crónicas: revisión de las evidencias científicas sobre su prevención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54277^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
