<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050854</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: the important biological changes that develop during adolescenceand the influences of socio-economical factors, which enable the human being topass from a dependent childhood to an independent adult life, produce anxiety that mayappear in its different varieties and forms of expression. Our objectives are to determine theprevalence of anxiety in its different forms in a representative sample of adolescents in primarycare centres.Methods and patient: selfadministration of STAIC test in a sample of 1,150 adolescents12-16 years of age, who have been visited in primary care centres in Catalonia from June2002 to May 2003.Results: the 27% (IC95%: 24,4-29,6) of adolescents present anxiety of both types:10,8% (IC95%: 9,1-12,7) anxiety as a temporary state and 16,2% (IC95%14,1-18,4)anxiety as a steady predisposition or as a mixed form. Sex, age, reason for which they consult,monoparental families, brother&#146;s number, place of birth, parents cultural level, all werefactors which were associated, in a statistically significant form, with a greater prevalence ofboth varieties of anxiety.Conclusions: prevalence of anxiety in adolescents who visit primary care centers is high.There is an increase of cases depending on certain factors, such as sex, age, monoparentalfamilies, reasons for which they consult, brother&#146;s number, place of birth and parents academiclevel; the knowledge of them can be useful to us in order to recognise risk factors inclinical practice</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo Piñero, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bofarull Bosch, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñol Moreso, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: los cambios biológicos que se producen durante la adolescenciay las influencias socioculturales que permiten al individuo pasar de la infancia dependientea la edad adulta autónoma producen con frecuencia ansiedad, que se puede presentaren todas sus variantes y expresiones. Nuestros objetivos fueron determinar la prevalencia de la ansiedad, así como la de susvariantes y expresiones, en una muestra representativa de adolescentes en centros de AtenciónPrimaria.Material y métodos: autoadministración del test STAIC a una muestra de 1.150 adolescentesde entre 12 y 15 años de edad atendidos en las consultas de Pediatría de Atención Primariade Cataluña entre junio de 2002 y mayo de 2003.Resultados: el 27,0% (IC95%: 24,4-29,6) de los adolescentes presenta ansiedad decualquier variante, el 10,8% (IC95%: 9,1-12,7) &#147;ansiedad-estado&#148; (A/E) de forma única, yel 16,2% (IC95%: 14,1-18,4) &#147;ansiedad-rasgo&#148; (A/R), única o acompañada de A/E. El género,la edad, el motivo de consulta, el convivir sólo con un progenitor, el lugar de nacimientoy el nivel de estudios de los padres se asociaron de forma estadísticamente significativa conuna mayor prevalencia de cualquier variante de ansiedad estudiada.Conclusiones: la prevalencia de ansiedad entre los adolescentes de Atención Primaria eselevada. Dicha prevalencia aumenta dependiendo de determinados factores como el género, laedad, el motivo de consulta, convivir sólo con un progenitor, el lugar de nacimiento y el nivel deestudios de los padres, los cuales pueden servirnos como signos de alerta en la práctica clínica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;8(30): 19-30, abr.-jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad en adolescentes atendidos en las consultas de Atención Primaria de Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
