<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128601</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychoanalysis and the impact of postmodern ideas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper contrasts modernity with postmodern thinking and attempts to acquaint the reader with the radical revisions of psychoanalytic theory by North American authors based on postmodern ideas about human subjectivity. What these formulations have in common is their criticism of classical theory. These new conceptualizations become progressively more radical theory. These new conceptualizations become progressively more radical regarding theory and technique- They are often presented in a polemical way. Two paradigm shifts are discussed. One divide is between drive theory and relational theory, A second divide proposes that psychoanalytic therapy is dichotomous i.e. originating from two individuals or dialectic. The focus is one the dialectic interplay of the two subjectivities rather than ideas emerging from two separate individuals. Meaning is co-created. The history of two person psychology versus one person psychology controversy is discussed in light of the postmodern arguments. A clinical case is presented to contrast the classical approach with the postmodern approaches. It is very difficult to compare classic psychoanalysis with the postmoderns because there is so much disagreement among the Postmoderns themselves. There is a feeling among the postmoderns that a new paradigm is trying to emerge but that has not yet arrived (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gunther Perdigao, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo contrasta el pensamiento psicoanalítico moderno versus el posmoderno, con el objeto de familiarizar al lector con las profundas revisiones de la teoría psicoanalítica según la entienden los autores norteamericanos posmodernos. Aunque hay muchas controversias entre ellos, en lo que coinciden los diversos autores es en su crítica a la teoría clásica. Gradualmente, sus postulados se han ido extremando en cuanto a la teoría y la técnica, y lo hacen en forma polémica. Está en discusión dos paradigmas diferentes. Una línea divisoria se encuentra entre la teoría de las pulsiones y la de las relaciones objetales. Otra, que sostiene que la terapia psicoanalítica es dicotómica, que se origina entre los individuos, en oposición dialéctica. El énfasis está puesto en el interjuefo dialéctivo de dos subjetividades más que en las ideas que surgen entre dos individuos. Existe una gran dificultad de comparación del psicoanálisis clásico con el de los posmoderno a raíz del escaso consenso existente entre estos últimos. Hay en ellos un sentimiento compartido acerca de la existencia de un nuevo paradigma luchado por emerger pero al que todavía no se ha llegado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(71): 235-255, ene.-abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128601</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicoanálisis y el impacto de las ideas posmodernas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
