<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041478</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acromegaly simulating a neuroblastoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Endocrinology is a specialty that, to a large extent, lacks specific diagnostic tools. Endocrinologists are characterized by their ability to interpret basal and stimulated hormonal data. We describe the case of a male patient initially diagnosed as suffering from an olfactory neuroblastoma with ectopic prolactin secretion, based on histological and radiological studies. After a review of all the clinical and hormonal results, the tumor was finally diagnosed as a growth hormone (GH)- and prolactin-secreting pituitary macroadenoma. In summary, pituitary adenomas that secrete GH and prolactin can sometimes simulate other tumors, especially when hormonal results are not interpreted correctly (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Isidro, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordido, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Castro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La endocrinología es una especialidad que carece, en gran medida, de técnicas diagnósticas específicas. El endocrinólogo se caracteriza por su capacidad para interpretar datos hormonales basales y tras estímulos. Presentamos el caso de un paciente que, en función de los datos histológicos y radiológicos, había sido diagnosticado de secreción ectópica de prolactina por un neuroblastoma olfatorio y en el cual la revisión de los datos clínicos y, especialmente, el estudio hormonal, condujo al diagnóstico correcto de macroadenoma hipofisario secretor de hormona de crecimiento (GH) y prolactina. En resumen, en ocasiones los adenomas hipofisarios secretores de GH y prolactina pueden simular otras neoplasias, especialmente cuando las determinaciones hormonales no se interpretan adecuadamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(9): 512-515, nov. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041478</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acromegalia que simula un neuroblastoma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d178^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31476^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
