<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75395</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Selection and implantation of yeast strains of genus Saccharomyces at a winery regulated by Appellation Contrôlée "Chacolí de Vizcaya/Bizkaiko Txakolina"</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The white wine Chacolía de Vizcaya/Bizkaiko Txakolina is characteristic from The Basque Country region and regulated under Appellation Contrôlée standards (BOPV 14/6/94). The objective of this study was the identification and selection of autochthonous yeast strains, to improve the conditions used to maintain the typical characteristics of this region wines. Yeasts identified as Saccharomyces bayanus isolated around these fields from 1996 to 1998, were subjected to a selective procedure based on enological characteristics and fermentative behaviour. Three of the selected strains were used to inoculate, at winery scale, two grape juice varieties accepted by the Appellation Contrôlée (Hondarrabi Zuri and Folle Blanche). The inoculated strains on the respective vinifications was followed by restriction fragment length polymorphism of mitochondrial DNA (REAmt) method with AluI enzyme, due to their specificity, short outcome, and technological simplicity compared with other molecular typing methods such as: chromosomal karyotyping analyzed by pulsed field gel electrophoresis, Random Amplified Polymorphic DNA-PCR (RAPD-PCR) and restriction fragment length polymorphism using the infrequently cutting enzyme SfiI (REA infrequent). This study demonstrated that strains with different phenotypic traits could show indistinguishable restriction patterns with REAmt, but could be discriminated using other typing methods such as RAPD-PCR, which although showing low reproducibility could be used as complementary to REAmt. Our results demonstrate that in spite of using autochthonous selected strains, the inoculation of musts with a particular strain do not guarantee its predominance and driving fermentation features. Of all yeast strains studied, strain no. 2 showed the best results in sensory testing and at the implantation process. Therefore, it could be used with commercial purposes for the production of Chacolí de Vizcaya/Bizkaiko Txakolina, especially when using musts from Folle Blanche(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sevilla, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rementeria, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amenabar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muguruza, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garaizar, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivanco, AB</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Chacolí de Vizcaya/Bizkaiko Txaxolina es un vino blanco característico del País Vaso con denominación de origen (BOPV 14/6/94). El objetivo del presente estudio fue seleccionar cepas de levaduras autóctonas para mejorar las condiciones de elaboración manteniendo las características propias de los vinos de esta región. Se aislaron levaduras identificadas como Saccharomyces bayanus durante las campañas 1996-1998 y se sometieron a un proceso selectivo en función de sus características enológicas y su comportamiento fermentativo. Tres de las cepas seleccionadas se inocularon a escala de bodega sobre mostos monovarietales de las dos variedades de uva aceptadas en esta denominación de origen, Hondarrabi Zuri y Folle Blanche. La implantación de las cepas inoculadas en las respectivas vinificaciones fue controlada mediante el análisis del polimorfismo de restricción ADN mitocondrial (REAmt) con la comparación con la enzima Alul, dada su especificidad, rapidez y sencillez tecnológica en comparación con otras técnicas de tipificación molecular utilizadas también en este estudio: cariotipificación cromosómica mediante electroforesis en campo pulsado, Random Amplified Polymorphic DNA-pCR (RAPD-pCR) y análisis del polimorfismo de restricción originado por la enzima Sfil de corte infrecuente (REA infrecuente). Este estudio ha demostrado que cepas con comportamientos fenotípicos diferentes presentan los mismos patrones de restricción con REAmt, pero pueden ser diferenciadas con otras técnicas aplicadas en este estudio, como RAPD-PCR, que pese a su baja reproductibilidad pueden ser una herramienta complementaria a REAmt. Nuestros resultados demuestran que, a pesar de utilizar cepas autóctonas seleccionadas, la inoculación de una caldo con una cepa no es garantía de que doina y dirija la fermentación del mosto, ya que una misma cepa puede imponerse o no dependiendo del tipo de mosto y de la campaña de que se trate. De las levaduras estudiadas, la cepa 2 fue la que mejores resultados proporcionó tanto en cata como en implantación, por lo que podría ser utilizada para la producción de Chacolí de Vizcaya con fines comerciales, sobre todo de mostos procedentes de Folle Blanche(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;23(4): 224-232, dic. 2006. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75395</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Selección e implantación de cepas de levadura del género Sccharomyces en la producción de vinos de la Denominación de Origen (DO) Chacolí de Vizcaya/Bizkaiko Txacolina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22155^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22156^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10833</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32635</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12814^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7016^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12814^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12814^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15320^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12814^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36214^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23923^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5394</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30142</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
