<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128023</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opinion of health professionals on adherence and management of long-term treatments in adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess opinion of health professionals about adherence and management of long-term treatments in adolescents in a tertiary hospital.  Method. A cross-sectional study was carried out in the Vall d'Hebron University Hospital in Barcelona, Spain. Participants were health professionals who care adolescents with solid organ transplant, hematologic disease, diabetes, cystic fibrosis or HIV+. Data collection was performed by self-administered questionnaire, developed specifically for this study. Results. A total of 105 professionals (70 %) participated in the study, 80 % were nurses, 56 % of them indicated that treatment compliance was good. 43 % indicated that adherence was not addressed well and 79 % of professionals did not have planned time to conduct health education related to treatment. 19.5 % of nurses and 72.2 % of physicians reported having adherence assessment tools. 39 % of participants made ??suggestions for improvement. Conclusions. Almost half of the professional indicate that the adherence is not adequately addressed. It is important to evaluate adherence to treatment to identify causes of low compliance and establish and evaluate appropriate interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conde Ceña, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Rubio, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cámara Morales, Estefanía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Callés González, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lamarga Delgado, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Gil, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde García, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Angulo, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Milán Cordero, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Juan, M. Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cebrián Batalla, M. Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aceituno López, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farrero Muñoz, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garriga Sánchez, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la opinión de los profesionales sanitarios sobre la adherencia y el manejo de tratamientos de larga duración en adolescentes en un hospital de tercer nivel.  Método. Estudio observacional, descriptivo y transversal, realizado en el Hospital Universitari Vall d'Hebron de Barcelona, España. Los sujetos de estudio fueron los profesionales sanitarios que atienden a los adolescentes trasplantados de órganos sólidos, seropositivos, con enfermedad oncohematológica, diabetes o fibrosis quística. La recogida de datos se realizó mediante cuestionario autocumplimentado, elaborado específicamente para este estudio.  Resultados. Participaron 105 profesionales (70 %). Un 80 % eran enfermeras. El 56 % consideró que el cumplimiento del tratamiento de los adolescentes era bueno. Un 43 % señaló que la adherencia no se abordaba bien. El 79 % de los profesionales no disponían de tiempo planificado para realizar educación sanitaria relacionada con el tratamiento. El 19.5 % de las enfermeras y el 72,2 % de los médicos indicaron disponer de instrumentos de evaluación de la adherencia. El 39 % de los participantes realizó propuestas de mejora.  Conclusiones. Casi la mitad de los profesionales opina que la adherencia terapéutica no se aborda adecuadamente. Es importante la evaluación de la adherencia a los tratamientos para identificar causas de bajo cumplimiento e instaurar y evaluar intervenciones adecuadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(10): 650-656, oct. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128023</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opinión de los profesionales sanitarios sobre la adherencia y manejo de tratamientos de larga duración en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6552^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
