<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132623</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Achievement of physical activity healthy guidelines in hypertensive adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: It seems necessary to educate patients in the need of realize the importance of physical activity to improve their health, and specifically, about the important implications that the intensity of physical activity has for health and fitness benefits. Objective: The aim of this was to evaluate achievement of physical activity recommendations for health in a group of hypertensive controlled patients from two primary care centers: La Estación y La Algodonera located in Talavera de la Reina (Toledo). Methods: Design: Cross-sectional study. Location: Primary care centers: La Estación y La Algodonera located in Talavera de la Reina. Participants: A total of 80 controlled hypertensive patients aged 40 to 60 years old who met the inclusion criteria were invited to the study. A sample of 52 patients obtained valid results to enter the study. Main measures: Minutes of Moderate to vigorous physical activity (MVPA), minutes of light activity and number steps were measured. Data was displayed by gender and weekdays vs weekend days. Results: Only 59.6% of patients achieved the minimum recommendation of 30 minutes of MVPA at least every day to improve health. Male achieved significantly more MVPA during the weekend than female did. Only women presented significant differences between MVPA during week days vs weekend days. Conclusions: 59.6% of hypertensive controlled patients of our sample achieve the minimal physical activity recommendations for health; the rest of the sample should increase their physical activity to achieve the recommendation and to improve their blood pressure levels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aznar Laín, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna Nieto, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero Blanco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalvilla Soria, Diego José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanillas Cruz, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Parece necesario educar a los pacientes en la importancia de realizar AF para mejorar su salud, y específicamente, sobre las implicaciones que la intensidad de la AF tiene para la salud. Objetivo: El propósito de este estudio fue evaluar si se cumplían las recomendaciones de actividad física (AF) para la salud en un grupo de pacientes hipertensos controlados de dos centros de atención primaria: La Estación y La Algodonera, situados en Talavera de la Reina (Toledo). Métodos: Diseño: Estudio descriptivo transversal. Emplazamiento: Centros de atención primaria &#147;La Estación&#148; y &#147;La Algodonera&#148;, situados en Talavera de la Reina.  Participantes: Un total de 80 pacientes hipertensos controlados de 40 a 60 años que cumplían los criterios de inclusión, fueron invitados a formar parte en el estudio, de los cuales fueron analizados los resultados válidos de 52 pacientes. Mediciones principales: Se cuantificó la actividad física diaria con acelerometría, obteniéndose los minutos de AF a intensidad de moderada a vigorosa (AFMV) y de actividad ligera, y el número de pasos. Los datos se presentaron diferenciando los días laborables y los días festivos. Resultados: Sólo un 59,6 % de los sujetos de la muestra cumplía la recomendación de realizar un mínimo de 30 minutos de AF de intensidad de moderada a vigorosa al día para la mejora de la salud. Los hombres realizaron significativamente más minutos de AFMV en los días festivos que las mujeres, y solamente las mujeres, mostraron diferencias significativas en los minutos de AFMV entre en los días laborables respecto a los festivos. Conclusiones: El 59,6% de los pacientes hipertensos controlados de esta muestra cumplían con las recomendaciones mínimas de AF para la salud; el resto debería incrementar su AF para cumplir las recomendaciones y con ello mejorar sus niveles de tensión arterial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(1): 415-428, ene. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132623</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento de las recomendaciones de actividad física para la salud en adultos hipertensos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1821</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
