<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144572</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Small cell carcinoma of the bladder shows low incidence and poor survival; thus, treatment algorithms based on randomized studies are unavailable. The aim of the present study is to review our case series. Methods: Observational retrospective study of 10 patients diagnosed with small cell carcinoma of the bladder between 2006 and 2013. Results: Mean age was 65.7 years; There was only one female in the cohort. In all cases hematuria was the fist symptom. 4 cases presented high-grade papillary urothelial carcinoma with small cell carcinoma. Radical cystectomy was performed in 40% patients, in combination with chemotherapy, radiotherapy or both. Median survival was 330 days (IC 95%: 40.757- 619.243) and only one patient showed complete response. Conclusions: Even when small cell carcinoma of the bladder is a low incidence tumor, its prognosis is worse than that of urothelial carcinoma. Although further randomized studies are needed to best define treatment, this study shows that survival at local stages is optimized by neoadjuvant chemotherapy, followed by radical resection, as the literature suggests (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calleja-Escudero, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortiñas-González, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pesquera-Ortega, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Moreno, Marife</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual-Fernández, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-González, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El carcinoma vesical de células pequeñas presenta una baja incidencia y escasa supervivencia, por lo que no existen esquemas terapéuticos basados en estudios randomizados. Nos planteamos como objetivo revisar nuestra casuística. Métodos: Estudio observacional retrospectivo de 10 pacientes diagnosticados de carcinoma de células pequeñas entre 2006 y 2013. Resultados: La edad media fue de 65,7 años y sólo se presentó en una mujer de los 10 pacientes. Se relacionó en su totalidad con antecedentes de tabaquismo, siendo la forma de presentación la hematuria. 4 casos presentaban carcinoma urotelial de alto grado junto con el componente microcítico. Se realizó cistectomía radical en el 40% de los pacientes, recibiendo además tratamiento con quimioterapia, radioterapia o ambos. La mediana del tiempo de supervivencia fue de 330 días (IC 95%: 40,757 - 619,243). Sólo en un caso obtuvimos respuesta completa. Conclusiones: El carcinoma de células pequeñas de vejiga es un tumor con baja incidencia pero de peor pronóstico que los tumores uroteliales. Aunque se necesiten más estudios randomizados para definir el mejor tratamiento, y nuestra casuística sea limitada, se ha publicado que los mejores resultados en cuanto a supervivencia en los estadios localizados se consiguen con quimioterapia neoayuvante seguida de cirugía radical (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;68(7): 602-608, sept. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carcinoma de células pequeñas de vejiga</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31583^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31583^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1768^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31583^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2338^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31583^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2338^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
