<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043282</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">From an information sheet to a balanced scorecard</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To establish a tool to follow up the objectives agreed on between hospital services and the hospital management staff in a public hospital with 355 beds. Material and method: A multidisciplinary working group was created to establish a draft of indicators for each line of activity (hospitalization, quality, pharmacy, surgery, ambulatory services). The information sheet was given to all the members of the service, heads of service, the staff responsible for healthcare objectives, and other members of staff. Results: The tool created, as well as the indicators used to follow-up the distinct objectives, are presented. Comparisons within and among all the medical and surgical services were established using graphs and monthly follow-up of objectives. Each objective was evaluated in detail and the extent to which each service met its objectives was determined. Conclusions: The information sheet is a tool to evaluate which objectives have been reached. It provides a clear reference for each service and is useful for quality improvement</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Suárez, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Sanjuán, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Pillado, Modesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seco, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Elaborar una herramienta que permita el seguimiento de los objetivos pactados entre los servicios y la gerencia en un hospital de titularidad pública de 355 camas. Material y método: Mediante un grupo de mejora, se elaboró un cuadro de mando que incluye indicadores para las líneas asistenciales pactadas (hospitalización, consultas externas, actividad quirúrgica, calidad y farmacia). Se difundió entre todos los miembros del servicio, los jefes de servicio, los responsables de objetivos asistenciales y los demás profesionales. Resultados: Se señala la herramienta creada, así como los indicadores utilizados para cada una de las líneas asistenciales. Se establecen referencias entre el propio servicio y el conjunto de los servicios quirúrgicos o clínicos, mediante gráficos y seguimientos mensuales de objetivos, a la vez que se valora ponderadamente cada objetivo y se puede conocer además la evaluación del servicio respecto a sus objetivos. Conclusiones: El cuadro de mando elaborado está en línea con los objetivos del centro hospitalario, ofrece una referencia clara y sencilla para situar al propio servicio y permite descubrir mejoras</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;21(1): 13-19, ene. 2006. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hacia el cuadro de mando integral por el cuadro de mando posible</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22552^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33196^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
