<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121194</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Palliative sedation: current situation and areas of improvement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the prevalence, epidemiology and registration status of palliative sedation (PS) prevalence in a teaching hospital, and to establish areas for improvement. Methods. A descriptive retrospective analysis was designed using the records from cancer patients who died between October and December 2010. The variables included were: epidemiological, inpatient unit, refractory symptom, drugs and dosages, and patient participation in the decision making process. The qualitative analysis followed a Delphi process: each participant received the overall performance of the group referred to as mean, median, 25th and 75th percentile. Items selected were those in which there was total or a high consensus.  Results. A total of 53 deaths were identified. Just over half (51.92%) received PS. The mean age was 67.46 and 64% were males. The most frequent diagnosis was lung cancer (32.14%). Fifteen of the patient patients were in the Oncology ward, 7 in Hematology, and 4 at the Emergency Department. The PC team took part in 14 of the sedations performed. A refractory symptom was identified in 20. There were 11 cases of dyspnea and 5 cases of delirium. The mean time between admission and PS was 9.5 days. The mean duration of PS was 1.2 days, with a mean number of 2.6 drugs used. There were 20 informed consents which were all verbal. The mean time from last chemotherapy to death was 82 days. For the Delphi process, 12 oncology or palliative care health professionals were included. A consensus was reached on the minimum data to be recorded in case of PS. This list includes: selection criteria, decision-making process and the sedation evolution. Conclusions. PS was applied in half of the patients who died due to dyspnea or delirium. Selection criteria were identified, as well as the type of PS and patient involvement in decision making process. A consensus was also reached on a minimum dataset that would help the clinician to record relevant information in PS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Juvero, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomar, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taberner, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nabal, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salud, Antonieta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la prevalencia, las características epidemiológicas y la calidad del registro relativos a la sedación paliativa (SP) en un hospital universitario. Establecer áreas de mejora. Material y método.  nálisis descriptivo retrospectivo de los registros clínicos de pacientes oncológicos fallecidos en nuestro centro entre octubre y diciembre de 2010. Las variables analizadas incluyeron: datos epidemiológicos y ubicación de los pacientes, presencia de SP, síntoma que la motivó, grado de participación del paciente y la familia en la toma de decisiones, fármacos y dosis utilizados. El análisis cualitativo se desarrolló mediante 2 rondas Delphi en las que cada participante recibió los resultados globales del grupo. Fueron seleccionados aquellos ítems en los que existía un consenso completo o elevado. Resultados. Identificamos 53 defunciones por cáncer, el 51% recibieron SP. La edad media fue de 67 años, y el 64% fueron varones. El cáncer de pulmón supuso el 32%. Quince pacientes dependían de Oncología, 7 de Hematología y 4 del Servicio de Urgencias. En el 53,85% existió intervención de cuidados paliativos. Los síntomas que motivaron la SP fueron: disnea en 11 casos y delirium en 5. El tiempo medio ingreso-SP fue de 9,5 días (duración media, 1,2 días). La media de fármacos utilizados fue de 2,6, con empleo de morfina en el 100% y midazolam en el 98%. En 20 casos constatamos el registro de consentimiento para su inicio (100% verbal). Doce profesionales participaron en el análisis cualitativo fruto del cual consensuamos una plantilla para mejorar los registros de selección, toma de decisiones y evolución en los casos de SP. Conclusiones. La SP fue motivada por disnea o delirium y se aplicó en la mitad de los pacientes fallecidos. Las áreas de mejora detectadas afectaban al registro de los criterios de selección, al tipo de sedación y a la participación del paciente en la toma de decisiones. Por ello hemos consensuado un conjunto mínimo de datos que facilitará la recogida de información de los profesionales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;29(2): 104-111, mar.-abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121194</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sedación paliativa: situación actual y áreas de mejora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28846^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28846^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28637</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52865^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16765</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
