<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056095</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognosis of patients who recovered after an episode of sudden death</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: Sudden death constitutes a major sanitary problem with        high mortality and serious neurological complications. The objective of        this study was to analyze the prognosis and the characteristics of        patients who initially recovered after an episode of cardiac arrest and        who were admitted to the intensive care unit (ICU).        Method: We retrospectively studied the clinical characteristics and        outcome of 65 patients admitted to the Intensive Care Unit during a 3        years period with aborted sudden death.        Results: 65 patients, 44 (67.7%) men and 21 (32.3%) women. Middle        ages 69.1 ± 13.9. 29 (44.6%) out of hospital and 36 (55.4%) into hospital        sudden death. Cardiopulmonary resuscitation was  10 minutes in 37 (56.9%). 36 (55.4%) of all sudden        deaths were of cardiac origin. 37 patients (56.9%) died and 28 (43.1%)        survived the episode. It was LET in 11 cases (16.9%). 29 (44.6%) of all        had post- anoxic encephalopathy and most died before discharge from        ICU. Of 28 survivors, 5 patients were discharged alive with post-anoxic        encephalopathy (17.8%) and 23 were discharged without neurological        disturbances (82.2%). This was more frequent when sudden death was        into hospital (p 0.009) and cardiopulmonary resuscitation was &lt; 10 minutes        (p 0.045).        Conclusions: High number of the patients admitted to a Intensive        Care unit with aborted sudden death died during ICU stay. Many        patients had post-anoxic encephalopathy and most of these died. So, up        to 35% of the patients admitted after an episode of cardiac arrest were        discharged alive and without severe neurological damage</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ridruejo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zalba, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárcamo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La muerte súbita constituye un grave problema con alta        mortalidad y serias complicaciones neurológicas. El objetivo de este        estudio es analizar el pronóstico y las características de pacientes inicialmente        reanimados tras un episodio de muerte súbita y que son ingresados        en Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI).        Método: Estudio retrospectivo de las características clínicas y estado        al alta de 65 pacientes ingresados en UCI durante un periodo de 3 años        tras una muerte súbita recuperada.        Resultados: 65 pacientes, 44(67,7%) hombres y 21(32,3%) mujeres.        Edad media 69,1 ± 13,9. 29 (44,6%) muertes súbitas extrahospitalarias y        36 intrahospitalarias. La reanimación cardiopulmonar (RCP) fue  10 minutos en 37 (56,9%). Más de la        mitad de los episodios tuvo origen cardiaco 55,4% (36pacientes). 37        pacientes (56,9%) fallecieron y 28 (43,1%) sobrevivieron. Existió limitación        del esfuerzo terapeutico (LET) en 11 casos (16,9%). 29 pacientes        (44,6%) desarrollaron encefalopatía postanóxica (EPA) falleciendo la        mayoría antes del alta. De los 28 supervivientes, 5 fueron dados de alta        vivos con encefalopatía postanóxica (17,8%) y 23 lo hicieron libres de        secuelas neurológicas (82,2%). Esto fué más frecuente cuando la parada        cardiorrespiratoria (PCR) ocurrió dentro del hospital (p 0,009) y la reanimación        duró menos de 10 minutos (p 0,045).        Conclusiones: Un elevado número de pacientes ingresados en UCI        tras sufrir una PCR fallecen durante su estancia. Muchos desarrollan        encefalopatía postanóxica y de ellos la mayoría muere. Pero a pesar de        esto, hasta un 35% de los pacientes admitidos tras una muerte súbita        recuperada son dados de alta sin secuelas neurológicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;24(5): 217-220, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056095</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pronóstico de los pacientes recuperados tras un episodio de muerte súbita</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3662^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2571^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2571^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11611^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
