<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114075</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The biological family from the perspective of kinship fostered adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Previous studies emphasise the importance of the biological family to the welfare of fostered adolescents. However, the majority of these studies only take into consideration the viewpoints of the professionals, foster parents and biological parents, not those of the adolescents themselves. For this reason little is known about the perceptions the adolescents have and the needs they express. Method: This study has gathered data from 57 adolescents in kinship family foster care in Spain (AFE). The study applied qualitative reseach, using focus groups to gather data, and the Atlas.ti programme to analyse the data. The qualitative data give us a more profound understanding of how the fostered adolescents relate to their biological families. Results: The results highlight the specific needs of these adolescents with regard to: a) understanding of their family history, b) the impact of visits from and relationship with their biological family, and c) the relationship between the biological family and the foster family. Conclusions: These findings reveal implications to consider when creating support programmes aimed at this group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mateos, Ainoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balsells, M. Angels</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Violant, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes-Peláez, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorós, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: los estudios anteriores demuestran la importancia que tiene la familia biológica en el bienestar de los adolescentes acogidos. Ahora bien, la mayoría de estos estudios se han realizado tomando como informantes a profesionales, acogedores o padres biológicos y han dejado de lado la perspectiva de los adolescentes. Así pues, conocemos poco sobre cómo es percibido este tema por los propios adolescentes y cuáles son las necesidades que expresan al respecto. Método: la investigación recoge información de 57 adolescentes en situación de acogimiento familiar en familia extensa en España (AFE). La metodología del estudio es cualitativa, se utiliza la técnica del focus grup para recoger información y el programa Atlas.ti para el análisis de datos. Los datos cualitativos nos permiten profundizar en la visión de los adolescentes acogidos en torno al tema de la familia biológica. Resultados: los resultados nos indican necesidades particulares en torno a: a) la comunicación de la historia familiar, b) las visitas y la relación con su familia biológica, y c) la relación entre familia biológica y acogedora. Conclusiones: estos hallazgos sugieren implicaciones para la práctica que pasan por articular programas de apoyo específicos dirigidos a este colectivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);25(3): 349-354, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114075</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La familia biológica desde la perspectiva del adolescente acogido en familia extensa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
