<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146695</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antimicrobial efficacy of photodynamic therapy in the disinfection of root canal: ex vivo study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate the antimicrobial efficacy of photodynamic therapy by employing a solution of ortho toluidine blue dye (AOT) and a light emitting-diode (LED), human teeth ex vivo, were inoculated with Enterococcus faecalis. Materials and methods: We used 34 single-rooted human teeth, which were biomechanically prepared and sterilized. Samples were divided randomly into 5 experimental groups: I (n = 2) positive control, II (n = 10) 2.5% NaOCl + 2.5% NaOCl, III (n = 10) 2.5% NaOCl + AOT + LED, IV (n = 10) 2.5% NACOL + AOT and V (n = 2) negative control. All groups except group V (sterility control) were inoculated with 30 &amp;#956;l of Enterococcus faecalis, and incubated for 24 hours before sealing the outer surface. After performing appropriate treatments, samples were taken, in duplicate, to be processed microbiologically and for the determination of colony forming units (CFU). The Chi-square test was used to evaluate the results of this study. Results: The results showed the development of UFC/ml (2.85 x 107) in Group I and served to compare the other groups. Groups II and III showed no statistically significant differences in the results (p &gt; 0.05) between them and respect to Group V (negative control). However, there were differences between them and Groups I and IV (1.25 x 107). Conclusion: Under the conditions of this study, photodynamic therapy with AOT/LED shown to have antimicrobial potential for use as an adjunct in the biomechanical preparation of root Canals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Scavo, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molgatini, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gliosca, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salaverry, Graciela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Lalis, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia antimicrobiana de la terapia fotodinámica (TFD) mediante el empleo de una solución colorante azul de ortotoluidina (AOT) y una luz emitida por un diodo (LED), en dientes humanos ex vivo, inoculados con Enterococcus faecalis. Meterial y método: Se utilizaron 34 piezas dentarias humanas unirradiculares que fueron preparadas biomecánicamente y esterilizadas. Las muestras fueron divididas al azar en cinco grupos experimentales: I (n = 2) control positivo, II (n = 10) NaOCL 2,5% + NaOCL 2,5%, III (n = 10) NaOCL 2,5% + AOT + LED, IV (n = 10) NaCOL 2,5% + AOT y V (n = 2) control negativo. Todos los grupos, excepto el grupo V (control de esterilidad), fueron inoculados con 30 &amp;#956;l de Enterococcus faecalis e incubados por 24 horas, previo sellado de la superficie externa. Luego de realizar los tratamientos correspondientes se tomaron muestras, por duplicado, para ser procesadas microbiológicamente y efectuar el recuento de unidades formadoras de colonias (UFC). Los resultados fueron evaluados mediante la prueba de Chi cuadrado (X2). Resultados: En el grupo I hubo desarrollo de UFC/ml (2,85 x 107) y se empleó para comparar los otros grupos. Los grupos II, III y V no presentaron desarrollo bacteriano, sin diferencias significativas en sus resultados (p &gt; 0,05). Sin embargo, hubo diferencias entre estos y los grupos I y IV (1,25 x 107). Conclusión: En las condiciones de este estudio la terapia fotodinámica (TFD) con AOT y LED demostró tener potencial antimicrobiano para su uso como coadyuvante en la preparación biomecánica de los conductos radiculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);32(4): 172-176, oct.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146695</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia antimicrobiana de la terapia fotodinámica en la desinfección de los conductos radiculares: estudio ex vivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30421^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27987^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30421^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27987^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52877^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10987^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
