<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60671</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Changes in the population smoking patterns: Barcelona, 1983&#150;2006</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the distribution of smoking in the population and to assess existing trends. Subjects and methods: Cross sectional study in a sample of the resident non-institutionalized population over 14 years of age (n=6,050) in Barcelona (Catalonia, Spain) using the Health Survey of 2006 and comparing trends for 1983&#150;2006 with previous surveys. Independent variables included sex and age. Dependent variables were having ever been a smoker, quitting, and being a current smoker. Prevalence and proportions were estimated, stratifying or adjusting for age. Results: The prevalence of daily smokers was 27.3% for men and 20.6% for women. Age groups smoking more were 25&#150;34 years for men and 35&#150;44 for women. From 1983 to 2006 the decline for men was sharp, and the prevalence for women is now decreasing. The change accelerated progressively for men, in absolute and relative terms. Estimating the probability of quitting for smokers, there was an increase in cessations over this period. The proportion of smokers of an older age is now much smaller. Conclusions: The evolution of the smoking epidemic over the last years shows promising trends. Quit rates have increased, and the decline in prevalence increases among men and has started in women. Smokers are increasingly becoming a minority, although to improve public health it would be desirable to speed the process of change (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borrell, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Sanz, Maica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalbí, Joan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villegas,  Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: presentar la distribución del tabaquismo en la población y valorar las tendencias. Sujetos y métodos: se ha realizado un estudio transversal en una muestra de población no institucionalizada, mayor de 14 años (n=6.050) y residente en Barcelona, a partir de la Encuesta de Salud de 2006, valorando tendencias entre 1983 y 2006 mediante la comparación con encuestas anteriores. Las variables independientes fueron el sexo y la edad, y las dependientes fueron las siguientes: haber sido fumador alguna vez, haber dejado de fumar y fumar actualmente. Se estimaron prevalencias y proporciones estratificadas o ajustadas por edad. Resultados: la prevalencia de fumadores diarios fue del 27,3% en varones y del 20,6% en mujeres. Los grupos de edad más fumadores fueron los de 25-34 años en varones y de 35-44 años en mujeres. Entre 1983 y 2006 la disminución del tabaquismo fue intensa en los varones, mientras que en las mujeres la prevalencia comenzó a descender. El cambio se aceleró progresivamente entre los varones en términos absolutos y relativos. En cuanto a la probabilidad de que los fumadores hubieran dejado de fumar, se apreció un incremento generalizado de los abandonos en dicho período. La proporción de fumadores en edades avanzadas es muy inferior al final del período estudiado. Conclusiones: la evolución de la epidemia tabáquica en los últimos años muestra tendencias esperanzadoras. Las tasas de abandono se incrementan, el declive de prevalencia se acelera en los varones y se ha iniciado en las mujeres. Los fumadores son cada vez más minoritarios, aunque para mejorar la salud pública sería deseable que el proceso de cambio fuera más rápido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);132(11): 414-419, mar. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambios en el patrón de tabaquismo de la población: Barcelona, 1983&#150;2006</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51529</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
