<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144113</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Positioning of headache units in the field of neurology: the importance of OnabotulinumtoxinA and other therapies in the treatment of headaches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic migraine is a disease that affects 0.5-2.5% of the population, depending on the statistics that are analysed and the definition of chronic migraine that is used. It is extraordinarily disabling, since it does not allow the sufferer to carry out any of their scheduled personal, professional or social activities, and it has a great impact on the patients&#146; quality of life, as measured on disability, quality of life and impact on daily activities scales. Yet, nowadays there are treatments that have proven to be effective in cases of chronic migraine, such as OnabotulinumtoxinA. It is a treatment that is well tolerated and with a high rate of efficacy. Yet it is not only a therapeutic tool, but in the world of headaches it has also opened up the doors to invasive treatments, to the learning of techniques and, in short, to placing headaches in referral units that are usually located in tertiary care hospitals. Furthermore, it has also helped to overcome the idea that patients with headache should be visited exclusively by primary care physicians or general neurologists. This is an opportunity to redefine the field of study and the care for headaches that must be seized. In the future, this is going to be complemented by novel treatments with neurostimulation and probably with monoclonal antibodies against the calcitonin gene-related peptide. A revolution has begun in our knowledge and capacity to act. It is our duty to give it the importance and usage it deserves both for our patients and for us as specialists (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres-Ferrús, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo-Rosich, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La migraña crónica es una enfermedad que afecta al 0,5-2,5% de la población según las estadísticas que se analicen y la definición de migraña crónica que se adopte. Es extraordinariamente incapacitante, ya que no permite realizar las actividades personales, profesionales o sociales programadas, y tiene un gran impacto sobre la calidad de vida de los pacientes, medido en escalas de discapacidad, calidad de vida e impacto en la actividad diaria. Sin embargo, actualmente se dispone de tratamientos que han demostrado eficacia en la migraña crónica, como la OnabotulinumtoxinA. Es un tratamiento bien tolerado y con una tasa de eficacia elevada. Pero no es sólo una herramienta terapéutica, sino que ha abierto las puertas en el mundo de la cefalea a la realización de tratamientos invasivos, al aprendizaje de técnicas y, en definitiva, a situar la cefalea en unidades de referencia ubicadas, habitualmente, en hospitales de tercer nivel. Además, ha ayudado a eliminar el concepto de que los pacientes con cefalea deben ser atendidos exclusivamente por médicos de atención primaria o neurólogos generales. Ésta es una oportunidad que debe aprovecharse para redimensionar el campo del estudio y asistencia de la cefalea. En el futuro, esto va a complementarse con novedosos tratamientos con neuroestimulación y, probablemente, con anticuerpos monoclonales contra el péptido relacionado con el gen de la calcitonina. Se ha iniciado una revolución en nuestro conocimiento y capacidad de actuación. Es nuestro deber darle la importancia y uso que se merecen tanto para nuestros pacientes como para nosotros como especialistas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;61(supl.1): s3-s7, sept. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144113</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Posicionamiento de las unidades de cefalea en el ámbito de la neurología: la importancia de laOnabotulinumtoxinA y otras terapias en el tratamiento de la cefalea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5865^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5865^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
