<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044628</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Darbepoietin treatment of anemia secondary to chronic renal failure in dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This Spanish single-arm, multicenter, prospective clinical trial assessed the maintenance        of hemoglobin concentrations (Hb) between 10-13 g/dL with unit doses        of darbepoetin alfa and the safety of the treatment in dialysis patients. Eight-hundred        twenty-six patients with chronic renal failure (CRF) (94% receiving haemodialysis        and 6% receiving peritoneal dialysis) previously maintained on stable recombinant        human erythropoietin (r-HuEPO) therapy with stable hemoglobin (Hb)        concentrations (mean Hb concentration = 11.7 g/dL) were switched to darbepoetin        alfa at a reduced dosing frequency for 24 weeks (a 20-week titration phase        plus a 4-week treatment evaluation phase). Subjects receiving r-HuEPO two or        three times weekly were switched to darbepoetin alfa once weekly, and those.        who were receiving r-HuEPO once weekly were switched to darbepoetin alfa once        every two weeks. The initial dose of darbepoetin alfa was determined from the        r-HuEPO dose at inclusion into the study using a formula equating the peptide        mass of the two molecules and rounding to the nearest available prefilled syringe        dose. Overall, 86.8% of patients completed the 24-weeks of study. Changing the        treatment from r-HuEPO to darbepoetin alfa and increasing the dose interval did        not result in any clinically significant change in the Hb concentration. From baseline        to the evaluation phase, the mean Hb fell 0.09 (95% CI, &#150;0.2; &#150;0.0) g/dl,        with an increase of 0.19 (95% CI, 0.0;0.3) g/dL iv and a decrease of 0.22 (95%        CI, &#150;0.3; &#150;0.1) g/dL sc). This maintenance of the mean Hb concentration was accompanied        by a mean 9.8% reduction of the darbepoetin alfa dose (19.7% (95%        CI, &#150;24.9;-14.2) iv and 4.7% (95% CI, &#150;8.5; &#150;0.7) sc. Treatment with darbepoetin        alfa was well tolerated and no unexpected adverse events were reported. In conclusion,        the replacement of previous r-HuEPO treatment by darbepoetin alfa in the        therapy of anemia secondary to chronic renal failure in diaiyzed patients was effective,        well tolerated, and decreased the frequency of dose administration compared        with the previous r-HuEPO treatment. Darbepoetin alfa administered once        weekly or once every two weeks maintained the baseline Hb levels whilst allowing        dose reduction, which was higher in patients receiving iv darbepoetin alfa</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Otero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Novales, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Castelao, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pallardó, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lladós, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tabernero, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Jaras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este ensayo clínico prospectivo, multicéntrico, de un solo brazo, evaluó el mantenimiento        de las concentraciones de hemoglobina (Hb) entre 10-13 g/dL con darbepoetin        alfa y la seguridad de este tratamiento, en pacientes con insuficiencia        renal crónica (IRC) en diálisis (94% hemodiálisis, 6% diálisis peritoneal, concentración        de Hb basal = 11,7 g/dL) tratados hasta el inicio de este estudio con eritropoyetina        recombinante humana (r-HuEPO). Se incluyeron 826 pacientes con        concentraciones de Hb y dosis de r-HuEPO estables (824 recibieron al menos una        dosis de darbepoetin alfa y fueron evaluables para el análisis de seguridad). Los        pacientes recibieron darbepoetin alfa durante 24 semanas (20 de titulación más        4 de evaluación). La dosis inicial de darbepoetin alfa se determinó a partir de la        dosis previa de r-HuEPO, utilizando la equivalencia en masa peptídica entre ambas        moléculas y ajustando a la jeringa precargada más próxima. Se administró darbepoetin        alfa 1 × semana (en pacientes en tratamiento previo con r-HuEPO 2-3 ×        semana) o cada dos semanas (en los pacientes con r-HuEPO 1 × semana). El        86,8% de los pacientes completaron las 24 semanas de estudio. El cambio del        tratamiento a menor frecuencia de dosificación no produjo modificaciones clínicamente        significativas en la concentración de Hb [los cambios desde la visita        basal al período de evaluación consistieron en un descenso de 0,09 (IC 95%,        &#150;0,2; &#150;0,0) g/dL, con aumento de 0,19 (IC 95% 0,0; 0,3) g/dL en la vía iv y descenso        de 0,22 (IC 95%, &#150;0,3; &#150;0,1) g/dL en la vía sc]. Este mantenimiento de Hb        se acompañó de una reducción media de la dosis de darbepoetin alfa de un 9,8%        (IC 95%, &#150;12,9; &#150;6,6) [19,7% (IC 95%, -24,9;-14,2) (vía iv) y 4,7% (IC 95%, &#150;8,5;        &#150;0,7) (vía sc)]. El tratamiento con darbepoetin alfa fue bien tolerado, no observándose        acontecimientos adversos inesperados. En conclusión, la sustitución de cér-HuEPO por darbepoetin alfa en la terapia de la anemia secundaria a IRC en pacientes        en diálisis fue eficaz, bien tolerada y disminuyó la frecuencia de administración de dosis en comparación con el tratamiento previo con r-HuEPO. Darbepoetin alfa 1 vez por semana o 1 vez cada 2 semanas mantuvo los niveles de Hb basales a la vez que permitió una reducción de la dosis por ambas vías de        administración, siendo mayor en los pacientes tratados por vía iv</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;23(2): 114-124, mar.-abr. 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio multicéntrico de darbepoetin alfa en el tratamiento de la anemia secundaria a insuficiencia renal crónica en diálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55967^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5009^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55967^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d755^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55967^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
