<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95911</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Triage and assignment of responsibility for care in cases of acute intoxication in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the quality of triage and care assignment in cases of acute intoxication.Methods: Three months of triage reports for cases of acute intoxication were reviewed. Patient demographic variables,toxicology screen, symptoms, triage level assigned using the Andorran Medical Triage (MAT) scoring system, delay inproviding care, and department assigned to be responsible for care were included in the analysis. We evaluated the appropriateness of the priority level assigned and the choice of responsible department. The results were compared to those for all emergencies attended. Results: The cases of 123 patients with acute intoxication (mean [SD] age, 41.6 [15] years) were included. Fifty-onepercent were female. Priority classifications were as follows: level 1, 1.6%; level 2, 20.5%; level 3, 36.9%; level 4, 32%,and level 5, 9%. Care was delayed after triage for less than 5 minutes in 19% of the cases, between 5 and 10 minutes in 27%, and longer than 10 minutes in 54%. The distribution of priority levels did not differ significantly from the distribution of other emergency department cases. However, assignment of the department responsible for providing care did differ (P&lt;.001); 60% of the acute intoxication cases were assigned to the internal medicine department and 37% to the psychiatry department. The delay in providing care after triage was shorter in intoxication cases than inother emergencies (P&lt;.001). Of the cases sent for gastrointestinal decontamination, an inappropriate level of priority was assigned in 13.3%. The department assigned to be responsible for care was also inappropriate in those 13.3% of (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Antón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogué, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bohils, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portillo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la calidad del triaje y del circuito asistencial de las intoxicaciones. Método: Durante tres meses, se han revisado los informes de triaje de las intoxicaciones agudas. Se incluyeron variables demográficas, toxicológicas, clínicas, nivel de triajeotorgado por el Modelo Andorrano de Triaje (MAT), demora asistencial y área de primera asistencia. Se valoró en cada caso la adecuación en la priorización de la asistencia y en la elección del área de primera asistencia. Los resultados fueron comparados con aquellos que fueron atendidos en urgencias. Resultados: Se han incluido 123 intoxicados, con una edad media de 41,6 años (DE:15). El 51% fueron mujeres. El sistema clasificó a los intoxicados como nivel I el 1,6%, II el 20,5%, III el 36,9%, IV el 32% y V el 9%. Tras el triaje, la asistencia se demoró menos de 5 min (19%), entre 5-10 min en el 27% o más de 10 min (54%). Cuando se compararon estos resultados con los de las urgencias en general, no se observaron diferencias significativas en cuanto a la estratificación de la prioridad asistencial, pero sí respecto alárea de primera asistencia, que es preferentemente medicina (60%) o psiquiatría (37%) en el caso de los intoxicados (p &lt; 0,001). Cuando se compararon las intoxicaciones y las urgencias generales respecto a la demora entre triaje y asistencia, se constató que la demora asistencial fue menor en las intoxicaciones (p &lt; 0,001). El 13,3% de los intoxicados tributarios de descontaminación digestiva fueron clasificados de forma inadecuada por no priorizar la asistencia. Por el mismo motivo, el área de primera  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);22(5): 338-344, oct. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95911</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación de un sistema de triaje y del circuito asistencial en urgencias al paciente intoxicado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
