<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137936</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine those factors that may be related to the length of second stage of labor delivery and the influence of the duration on neonatal morbidity. Method: This retrospective, observational study was carried out in the maternity service of the Complejo Hospitalario La Mancha-Centro de Alcázar de San Juan in 2002 and 2003. Four hundred seventy-six women with full-term pregnancies and cephalic presentation were studied. The variables measured were the length of labor in minutes, maternal age, parity, onset of labor, mode of delivery, infant birth weight, umbilical artery pH, 1-minute and 5-minute Apgar scores and admission of the newborn in the neonatal intensive care unit. Results: Epidural analgesia was associated with a statistically significant prolongation of the duration of delivery, with a 95% confidence interval of 31 to 44 minutes, and multiparity shortened the duration of delivery by 9.6 to 23.6 minutes. No statistically significant associations (p &gt;0.05) were observed between duration of delivery and umbilical artery pH, Apgar scores or admission of the newborn in the neonatal intensive care unit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual Pedreño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Serrano, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas Adelantado, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer los factores que pueden estar relacionados con la duración del periodo expulsivo y la influencia de esta duración sobre la morbilidad neonatal. Método: Estudio observacional retrospectivo realizado en el Servicio de paritorio del Complejo Hospitalario «La Mancha-Centro» de Alcázar de San Juan durante los años 2002 y 2003. Se estudiaron 476 gestantes a término con presentación cefálica. Las variables estudiadas fueron: el tiempo de expulsivo en minutos, la edad materna, la paridad, el inicio de parto, el tipo de parto, el peso del recién nacido, los valores de pH de arteria umbilical, la puntuación del test de Apgar al minuto y a los 5, y el ingreso del recién nacido en el servicio de pediatría. Resultados: La analgesia epidural produce un aumento estadísticamente significativo en el tiempo de expulsivo con un intervalo de confianza del 95% de entre 31 a 44 minutos, asimismo, el hecho de ser multípara disminuye la duración del expulsivo entre 9,6 y 23,6 minutos. No se encontró asociación estadísticamente significativa (p &gt;0,05) entre la duración del expulsivo y los valores de pH de arteria umbilical, las puntuaciones del test de Apgar e ingreso del recién nacido en el servicio de pediatría. Conclusiones: No se observa que la mayor duración del expulsivo esté asociada a una mayor morbilidad neonatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;5(18): 14-18, 2004. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137936</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la duración del expulsivo sobre la morbilidad neonatal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
