<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82823</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neonatal intracranial haemorrhage secondary to spontaneous rupture of an aneurysm. Illustrative case and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Intracranial arterial aneurysms are little frequent among the pediatric age group but the frequency is still ower in children under 1 year of age and extremely rare in neonates. We present a case, review literature and propose common characteristics and management of this pathology. Case report. A term newborn suffered reduction of the level of conscience. After brain ultrasound examination and CT scan was diagnosed with intraparenchymatous hematoma on the 7th day of life. Intraoperative, after evacuation of this hematoma, we discovered, clipped and extirpated a middle cerebral artery aneurysm without any problems. The patient&#146;s evolution was satisfactory only presenting a slight paresia of his right arm. Conclusion. We review the literature and find 16 cases of neonatal intracranial arterial aneurysms. Mortality rate is about 50%, but keeping in mind better survivals with surgical treatment in the last years. Thus we conclude, when it is possible, in favour of a surgical and precocious treatment of these neonatal aneurysm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giménez Pando, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ollero Ortiz, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Bonet, Luis G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Rivas, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los aneurismas intracraneales arteriales son raros en la edad pediátrica, pero mucho más en menores de 1 año, y más extraños aún en neonatos. Presentamos un caso, revisamos la bibliografía y proponemos características comunes, así como recomendaciones terapéuticas. Caso clínico. Recién nacido a término que sufre deterioro del nivel de conciencia y que tras ecografía y tomografía computarizada cerebrales es diagnosticado de hematoma intraparenquimatoso espontáneo al séptimo día de vida. Tras la  evacuación del hematoma, intraoperatoriamente se detecta aneurisma de la arteria cerebral media, que se clipa y extirpa sin problemas. El paciente evoluciona de forma favorable, permaneciendo como única secuela a los tres años de  seguimiento una ligera paresia en el brazo. Conclusión. Tras revisar la bibliografía, encontramos 16 casos claros de aneurismas neonatales. La mortalidad global es cercana al 50%, pero hay que tener en cuenta que se observan supervivencias mucho mayores tras tratamiento quirúrgico en los últimos años. Por eso concluimos, cuando es posible, a favor de un tratamiento quirúrgico precoz de estas lesiones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(7): 403-408, abr. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82823</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia intracraneal en el neonato secundaria a rotura aneurismática espontánea. Caso ilustrativo y revisión de la bibliografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34262^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34262^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30855^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
