<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27908</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complications of enteral nutrition at home. Results of a multi-centre trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: In spite of the increasing number of home enteral nutrition (HEN) patients, only few articles had reported the frequency of complications related to this treatment. Our multicentric study analyzes the HEN complications in relation to access device and time of treatment.  Method: 92 HEN patients from 8 hospitals were randomly selected. Patients were distributed in relation to the time of treatment and access device (nasogastric tube and percutaneous or surgical gastrostomies). After an educational program, they were filled in an initial questionnaire and repeated it the days 15 and 30. They received a mean of 1650 Kcal of enteral solution. A total of 2760 HEN prospective days were analyzed.  Results: In prospective study 42% of patients had some complication (112 episodes). The most frequent were gastrointestinal (55%) and mechanical (29%); 0.16 complications of patient-year were registered. The most common complications were: extraction (15%), constipation (13%), vomiting (12%) and diarrhoea (10%). The gastrostomy group had more gastrointestinal complications. In retrospective evaluation, percutaneous gastrostomy group had the lowest ratio of complications and nasogastric tube group required more tube replacements (4 vs 2) and had 1.96 episodes/patient (percutaneous group 1.85 and surgical gastrostomy 3.1 episodes/patient).  Conclusion: HEN is safe with low incidence of complications. An adequate educational program is very important and we expect, in the future, to establish an proper National Home Care System (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Grupo Aula Médica, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: A pesar del número creciente de nutrición enteral domiciliaria (NED), sólo algunos artículos recogen la frecuencia de sus complicaciones. Este estudio multicéntrico analiza estas complicaciones en relación a la vía de acceso y la duración del soporte nutricional. Método: Seleccionamos aleatoriamente 92 pacientes con NED de 8 hospitales y se distribuyeron en relación a la duración del soporte y a la vía de acceso: sonda nasogástrica (SNG) y gastrostomías percutánea o quirúrgica. Tras un programa educativo, los pacientes completaron un cuestionario inicial que se repitió en los días 15 y 30.Recibieron una media de 1.650 kcal de fórmula enteral. Se analizaron un total de 2.760 días prospectivos de NED. Resultados: En la fase prospectiva, el 42 por ciento de los pacientes tuvo alguna complicación (112 episodios). Los más frecuentes fueron digestivos (55 por ciento) y mecánicos (29 por ciento); se registraron 0,16 complicaciones por paciente-año. Las complicaciones más comunes fueron: extracción (15 por ciento), estreñimiento (13 por ciento), vómitos (12 por ciento) y diarrea (10 por ciento). El grupo de gastrostomía tuvo más complicaciones digestivas. En el análisis retrospectivo, el grupo de gastrostomía percutánea tuvo menos complicaciones y el de SNG requirió más recambios de sondas (4 frente a 2) y tuvieron 1,96 complicaciones/paciente (grupo de gastrostomía percutánea 1,85 y quirúrgica 3,1). Conclusión: La NED es segura y presenta una baja incidencia de complicaciones. Un programa educativo adecuado es muy útil y esperamos, en el futuro, contribuir a un mejor sistema de atención domiciliaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;18(3): 167-173, mayo 2003. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones de la nutrición enteral domiciliaria. Resultados de un estudio multicéntrico</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Planas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Rosado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pereira, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cos Blanco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de la Cruz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo Pérez, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mellado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Luna, PP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chamorro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camarero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Koning, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wanden-Berghe, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Candela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27908</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23254</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30376</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
