<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148343</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A fundamental experience of learning in my analytic training</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Drawing upon his description of the early phases of the analysis of the second case of official supervision, the author illustrates in his work why this experience became a foundational moment in his formative journey. There are primarily three aspects that are given prominence: 1) the signicant role his supervisor played in helping to manage and to confront the difficult dynamics of transference and countertransference that characterized the early years of this analysis; 2) the transformative factors that have opened up a new avenue in the repetition and in the pathology of traumatic origin pathology put forward for long by the patient, and 3) the making contact for the first time with that area of inter/intrapsychic phenomena that the author, over the years, has widely explored and theorized under the name of «relational dynamics governed by the role reversal» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Borgogno, Franco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Partiendo de la descripción de las fases iniciales del análisis del segundo caso de supervisión oficial, el autor ilustra en su trabajo el por qué esta experiencia se convirtió en un momento fundacional de su recorrido formativo. Esencialmente son tres los aspectos que se resaltan: 1) el importante papel que tuvo el supervisor a la hora de ayudar a gestionar y afrontar las difícies dinámicas de transferencia y contratransferencia que caracterizaron los primeros años de análisis; 2) los factores transformadores que abrieron un nuevo paso en la repetición y en la patología de origen traumático por largo tiempo presentada por el paciente, y 3) el haberse puesto en contacto por primera vez con aquella área de fenómenos interpsíquicos e intrapsíquicos que el autor, pasados los años, ha explorado ampliamente y teorizado bajo el nombre de «dinámicas relacionales gobernadas por la reversión de roles» (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(75): 117-129, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148343</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una experiecia fundamental de aprendizaje en mi formación psicoanalítica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4721^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4721^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8308^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3729</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
