<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105628</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Breast cancer and pregnancy. Analysis of a series of 27 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To perform a descriptive analysis of patients with breast cancer (BC) and pregnancy diagnosed in our centre, as regards the therapeutic methods used and the overall survival of the series. Patients and methods: Between 1982-2009, 5906 patients were diagnosed with BC, of whom 27 (0.46%) were treated for pregnancy-associated BC. We analysed the characteristics, diagnosis, treatments and outcome of these patients in our centre. Results: The mean age at diagnosis was 35 years. Twenty-one patients were diagnosed during pregnancy and six of them in the post-partum period. The mean diagnostic delay from the onset of symptoms was four months. In the immunohistochemical profile performed in 19 patients, 5 (26%) were HER2, 5 (26%) were triple-negative, luminal A in three patients, and luminal B in the other 6 cases. At diagnosis, 5, 9, 11 and 2 patients were classified into stages I, II, III and IV, respectively. Histologically, 21 (78%) were infiltrating ductal carcinomas, 11 (41%) were high grade carcinomas and 4 (15%) were inflammatory carcinomas at diagnosis. Neoadjuvant chemotherapy was prescribed in 16 patients (59%), with no foetal complications detected. All patients underwent surgery; 24 (89%) had modified radical mastectomy while three had conservative surgery. The mean follow-up time was 60 months, in which the overall survival was 70%. Four patients (15%) had local recurrence and 13 (48%) had systemic recurrence. Conclusions: Breast carcinoma during pregnancy is associated with diagnostic delay, advanced stages and high histological grades. Surgical treatment involves a high percentage of radical mastectomies. Chemotherapy did not produce adverse effects in the foetus after the first trimester. The prognosis for BC during pregnancy is similar to that of non-pregnant patients of the same age and tumour stage(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fidalgo, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Báguena Requena, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Garate, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvete Chornet, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Agulló, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo de las Heras, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgués Gasión, Octavio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayol Oltra, Araceli</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar un análisis descriptivo de la serie de pacientes con cáncer de mama (CM) y embarazo diagnosticadas en nuestro centro en relación con los métodos terapéuticos empleados y supervivencia global de la serie. Pacientes y métodos: Entre 1982 y 2009, de 5.906 pacientes diagnosticadas de CM, se trató a 27 pacientes con CM y embarazo (0,46%). Analizamos las características clínicas y anatomopatológicas, el diagnóstico, los tratamientos y la evolución de estas pacientes en nuestro centro. Resultados: La edad media al diagnóstico fue de 35 años. Durante la gestación se diagnosticó a 21 pacientes y en el posparto, a 6. El retraso medio diagnóstico desde el inicio de los síntomas fue de 4 meses. Respecto al perfil inmunohistoquímico determinado en 19 pacientes, 5 (26%) eran receptor 2 de factor de crecimiento epidérmico humano (HER2) positivo; otros 5 (26%), triple negativo; 3, luminal A, y en las 6 restantes, luminal B. Al diagnóstico, se clasificó a 5, 9, 11 y 2 pacientes en estadio I, II, III y IV, respectivamente. Histológicamente, 21 (78%) eran carcinomas ductales infiltrantes; 11 (41%), de alto grado histológico, y 4 casos (15%) presentaron características de carcinoma tipo inflamatorio al diagnóstico. Se pautó quimioterapia neoadyuvante en 16 pacientes (59%), sin que se detectaran complicaciones fetales. Se operó a todas las pacientes, y se realizó mastectomía radical modificada en 24 (89%), así como cirugía conservadora en 3. Con un tiempo medio de seguimiento de 60 meses, la supervivencia global fue del 70%. Cuatro pacientes (15%) presentaron recaída local y 13 (48%), recaída sistémica. Conclusiones: El carcinoma de mama durante el embarazo se asocia con un retraso diagnóstico, estadios avanzados y grados histológicos altos. El tratamiento quirúrgico conlleva un alto porcentaje de mastectomías radicales. La quimioterapia no produjo efectos adversos en el feto tras el primer trimestre de gestación. El pronóstico de CM durante el embarazo es similar al de las pacientes no gestantes de la misma edad y estadio tumoral.(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);25(1): 2-7, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cáncer de mama y embarazo. Análisis de una serie de 27 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31270^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
