<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-059046</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor. Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To report one case of myofibroblasticbladder tumor.METHODS/RESULTS: We report the case of a 30-year-old woman with recurrent urinary tract infections and incidental finding of a bladder mass after abdominal ultrasound. After TUR, inflammatory myofibroblastic tumor of the bladder was diagnosed.CONCLUSION: Myofibroblastic tumor (also known as infla-mmatory pseudotumor or pseudosarcoma) is a benign tumor with mesenchymal origin. Bladder location is very uncom-mon. It must not be misdiagnosed as a malignant neoplasm. Optimal treatment when arising in the bladder is TUR, with excellent long-term prognosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herranz Fernández, L. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arellano Gañán, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Gálvez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coloma del Peso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido Abad, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina Durán, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar un nuevo caso de tumor miofibroblástico vesical.MÉTODO/RESULTADOS: Mujer de 30 años con ITU de repetición y hallazgo incidental de masa vesical en ecografíaabdominal. Tras realización de RTU vesical se diagnosticatumor miofibroblástico inflamatorio de vejiga.CONCLUSIÓN: El tumor miofibroblástico, (también denominadopseudotumor inflamatorio o pseudosarcoma) es un tumor benigno de origen mesenquimal cuya localización vesical es muy poco común, y que no debe ser confundidocon una neoplasia maligna. En caso de presentación vesical el tratamiento consiste en resección transuretral, con buen pronóstico a largo plazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;61(1): 62-64, ene.-feb. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-059046</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor miofibroblástico inflamatorio vesical. Aportación de un nuevo caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9573^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9573^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
