<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64332</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Unsuspected or undiagnosed acute appendicitis could progress to a perforation or could lead to the removal of a normal appendix. Objectives: using a clinical score system as a diagnostic tool for this pathology and can decrease negative appendectomies. Material and method. Prospective and protocolized study. Setting: National Clinicas Hospital. Córdoba. Argentina. Between May 2007 and June 2007 224 patients were studied of which 117 were male and 107 were female with a mean age of 26.65 years. An Alvarado score was performed on all patients on admission. Based on the clinical evidence and a second assessment with the Alvarado Score, surgical exploration was decided in 207 patients. The remaining 17 were excluded due to other pathology. The diagnosis of acute appendicitis was confirmed by surgical finding and histopathological studies. Results. In the surgical findings it was shown that 189 (91%) patients had acute appendicitis. There was no surgical mortality. As regards morbidity, 3.86% had medical and 27% had surgical complications. The histopathology reports showed a normal caecal appendix in 18. Whereas the incidence of negative appendicectomy was about 8.69%. Conclusions. The use of the Alvarado Score together with the surgical and histopathology findings confirmed it was senstive from 6 points for the diagnosis of acute appendicitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palas Zuñiga, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Martín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eduardo Lada, Paul</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carena, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canavosso, Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monjo, Luciano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La apendicitis aguda no sospechada ni diagnosticada puede evolucionar hacia la perforación o, por el contrario, conduce a la remoción de un apéndice normal. El objetivo del estudio fue utilizar un sistema de clasificación, desde un punto de vista clínico, para el diagnóstico de esta enfermedad y lograr disminuir las apendicectomías negativas. Material y método. Estudio prospectivo y protocolizado, que se aplicó en el Hospital Nacional de Clínicas, Córdoba (Argentina). Comprende a 224 pacientes estudiados entre mayo de 2004 y junio de 2007. De ellos, 117 eran varones y 107, mujeres, con una edad promedio de 26,65 años. A todos los pacientes se les realizó al ingreso el Score de Alvarado. Según la clínica y una segunda valoración con el Score se decidió la exploración quirúrgica en 207 pacientes. Se excluyó a los 17 restantes por otras enfermedades. El diagnóstico de apendicitis aguda fue confirmado por los hallazgos quirúrgicos y la anatomía patológica. Resultados. En los hallazgos operatorios hubo 189 (91,3%) pacientes que tenían apendicitis aguda. No hubo mortalidad postoperatoria. En relación con la morbilidad hubo un 3,86% de complicaciones médicas y un 27% quirúrgicas. El informe anatomopatológico mostró en 18 pacientes un apéndice cecal normal. Por lo tanto, la incidencia de las apendicectomías negativas fue del 8,69%. Conclusiones. La utilización del Score en relación con los hallazgos quirúrgicos y anatomopatológicos confirma que fue sensible a partir de 6 puntos para el diagnóstico de apendicitis aguda (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);83(5): 247-251, mayo 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64332</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d26498^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1068^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1068^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1068^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1070^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200805</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
