<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84717</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of nutritional menus offered at noon school in Granada</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: It has been considered a study of nutritional menus offered at noon School in Granada. Balanced diet in children and youth will enable the prevention of diseases in adulthood. Comparing the menus prepared on school and the services offered by catering. Material and methods: The menus are aimed at 5,399 children from Granada, analyzed 354 school menus from 29 centres, public and private schools. Eleven colleges have their own kitchen, while 18 had hired a catering service. The amounts provided in each menu were estimated using standardized photographs of different sizes ration identified by those responsible for the dining room or by weighing Served directly from the ration. Nutritional assessment was determined by software, and the statistical treatment with the program SPSS v. 15.0. Results: There were statistically significant differences in the intakes of energy and nutrients from the menus developed in the centres and catering services. In the catering firms, the available energy and nutrition is similar, and in the menus prepared at the centres, there are significant differences in relation to some nutrients, depending on whether public school or private. Conclusions: The energy, protein and lipid is high and low input from carbohydrates. It is the frequency of excessive consumption of meat and derivatives. To balance the diet of school, it is necessary to complement the menu of midday meals with the rest of the day (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velasco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, AB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olea-Serrano, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero-Plasencia, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariscal-Arcas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Se ha considerado interesante el estudio nutricional de los menús de mediodía ofertados en centros escolares de Granada, ya que la dieta equilibrada en la población infantil y juvenil, permitirá la prevención de enfermedades en la edad adulta. Se comparan los menús elaborados en el propio centro y los ofertados por servicios de catering. Material y métodos: Los menús van dirigidos a 5.399 niños/as granadinos, analizándose 354 menús escolares de 29 centros, públicos, concertados y privados. 11 colegios, disponían de cocina propia, mientras que 18 tenían contratado un servicio de catering. Las cantidades servidas en cada menús se estimaron mediante fotografías estandarizadas con distintos tamaños de ración identificadas por los responsables del comedor o por pesada directa de la ración servida. La valoración nutricional se determinó mediante el programa informático, y para el tratamiento estadístico con el programa SPSS v. 15.0. Resultados: Existen diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el aporte de energía y nutrientes de los menús elaborados en los centros y los servicios de catering. En las empresas de catering, el aporte energético y nutricional es similar, y en los menús elaborados en los centros, existen diferencias significativas en relación a algunos nutrientes, según se trate de colegio público, concertado o privado. Conclusiones: El aporte energético, proteico y lipídico es elevado y bajo el aporte de hidratos de carbono. Es excesiva la frecuencia de consumo de carne y derivados. Para equilibrar la dieta del escolar, es necesario complementar el menú de mediodía con el resto de comidas del día (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(3): 394-399, mayo-jun. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84717</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de los menús escolares servidos en colegios de Granada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12955</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5639</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
