<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048297</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The meeting of Einstein with Cajal (madrid, 1923): a lost tide of fortune</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The year 2005 was the centennial year of the Albert Einstein&#146;s transcendental works that changed forever the humans thoughts on the universe. It is also celebrated the 50th anniversary of his death. It was proclaimed &#145;World Year of Physics&#146; and a multiplicity of celebrations have exhaustively analyzed Einstein&#146;s cardinals contributions. However, among these, the meeting of Einstein with another titanic of science, Santiago Ramón y Cajal, has passed some unnoticed. In this study the circumstances of this meeting are evoked. Development: The parallelisms between the lives of both prominent figures awarded with the Nobel Prize are highlighted. They are the &#145;classic&#146; authors most widely cited in the current scientific literature. The events and persons who made possible that shining but forgotten interview are detailed. Such a meeting took place in Madrid, on the occasion of the Einstein&#146;s trip to Spain in 1923. That travel exceeded his primary scientific nature, reaching the category of a social phenomenon and was widely covered by the printed mass media at that time. Finally, the curious coincidence of the invocation of Cajal&#146;s theories to justify the genius of the German physicist nearly 75 years after their meeting is mentioned. Conclusions: Although it was a brief meeting and the circumstances surrounding it largely unknown, it produced a great impression to Einstein and constitutes a supreme instant in the history of the 20th century</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montes-Santiago, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En el año 2005 se celebró el centenario de los trascendentales trabajos de Albert Einstein que revolucionaron las ideas científicas sobre la estructura del universo. Es además el cincuentenario de su muerte. Por tal motivo fue proclamado &#145;AñoMundial de la Física&#146; y se han realizado múltiples conmemoraciones, analizando exhaustivamente sus aportaciones cardinales a la ciencia. Entre ellas ha pasado prácticamente desapercibida la entrevista que mantuvieron Einstein y Santiago Ramón y Cajal. En este trabajo se analizan las circunstancias de este encuentro entre ambos genios. Desarrollo: Se resaltan los paralelismos entre las vidas de ambos personajes galardonados con el Premio Nobel. Se pormenorizan los acontecimientos y los personajes que posibilitaron aquella luminosa pero olvidada entrevista entre los dos científicos &#145;clásicos&#146; más citados en la literatura científica actual. Tal encuentro se produjo en Madrid, con motivo del viaje de Einstein a España en 1923. El viaje desbordó su primaria naturaleza científica, constituyó un verdadero fenómeno social y alcanzó una amplia repercusión periodística. Se resalta la curiosa coincidencia de la apelación a las teorías del científico español como modo de explicar la genialidad de las concepciones mentales del físico alemán, casi 75 años después de aquel encuentro. Conclusiones: Aunque breve y en circunstancias poco conocidas, tal encuentro produjo una gran impresión en Einstein y constituye un instante supremo en la historia del siglo XX</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(2): 113-117, jul. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El encuentro de Einstein y Cajal (Madrid, 1923): un olvidado momento estelar de la humanidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33249</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9800</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11257</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9639</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
