<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18183</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of frustration and/or harassment in the emotional modulation of Cardiac Defense Response</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examines the emotional modulation of the Cardiac Defense Response (CDR) under conditions of harassment and/or frustration. The heart rate, and the systolic and diastolic blood pressure patterns were recorded in 79 women and 26 men in response to three presentations of an intense acoustic stimulus. The CDR test was performed after two tasks in which a negative emotional state was experimentally induced by frustration and/or harassment. The experimental conditions of the study were: control (C), harassment (H), frustration (F), and frustration+harassment (F+H). The results showed: (1) an enhancement of the second accelerative component of the CDR in the group of frustrated men, and (2) a lower habituation of the blood pressure levels in the first components of the CDR in conditions of frustration+harassment. These results support the idea that aversive reflexes are enhanced in negative emotional states (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez, MN</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyes del Paso, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García León, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se ha analizado la modulación emocional de la Respuesta Cardiaca de Defensa (RCD) en condiciones de hostigamiento y/o frustración. Para ello, se evaluó el patrón de respuesta de la tasa cardiaca (TC), la presión sanguínea sistólica (PSS) y la presión sanguínea diastólica (PSD) de 79 mujeres y 26 hombres ante tres presentaciones de un estímulo auditivo intenso. El test de la RCD se realizaba después de dos tareas, en las que se indujo experimentalmente un estado emocional negativo mediante frustración y/u hostigamiento. Las condiciones experimentales utilizadas en el estudio fueron las siguientes: control (C), hostigamiento (H), frustración (F) y frustración+hostigamiento (F+H) Los resultados mostraron: 1) una potenciación del segundo componente acelerativo de la RCD en el grupo de hombres frustrados y 2) una habituación menor de los niveles de presión sanguínea durante los primeros componentes de la RCD en condiciones de frustración con hostigamiento. Estos resultados apoyan la idea de que los reflejos producidos en condiciones aversivas son potenciados durante estados emocionales negativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(2): 450-455, mayo 2002. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18183</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la frustración y/o el hostigamiento en la modulación emocional de la Respuesta Cardíaca de Defensa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6945</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3687</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6590</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
