<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039034</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of intimate partner violence against women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We have elaborated an Abuse Typology and a survey research based on Goffman&#146;s approach (1971) and on Brown and Levinson&#146;s (1987) concepts of positive and negative face, as systematized by Kerbrat-Orecchioni (1992). A stratified sampling according to the zone of residence upon a population of 450.000 women has been made, and 421 women were interviewed with regard to their experience of abuse in couple relationships. The results of the study indicate that 20.2 % of the population have suffered or are suffering abuse by their partner, with a maximum error of 4.3%. Moreover 6.2% of the women have suffered abuse during the year previous to the interview</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontanil, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Roxana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, Pura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ezama, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha elaborado una tipología del maltrato y una encuesta inspirándonos en los planteamientos de Goffman (1971) y en los conceptos de cara positiva y cara negativa de Brown y Levinson (1987), sistematizados por Kerbrat-Orecchioni (1992). Se ha realizado un muestreo estratificado según la zona de residencia sobre una población de unas 450.000 mujeres y se entrevistó a 421 mujeres sobre sus experiencias respecto al maltrato en parejas. Los resultados del estudio indican que el 20,2% de la población femenina ha sufrido maltratos a manos de su pareja y que el 6,2% de las mujeres han sufrido maltrato durante el último año</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);17(1): 90-95, feb. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039034</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del maltrato de pareja contra las mujeres</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
