<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75539</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">In vitro inhibitory effect of ajoene on Candida isolates recovered from vaginal discharges</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AimsThe main purpose of this work was to evaluate the in vitro activity of ajoene of the Candida, obtained from vaginal discharges.MethodsFor this, 136 samples were analyzed. The yeasts were recovered and identified by conventional mycological methods. The susceptibility to ajoene (at 20, 15, 12.5, 10, 6.25 and 3.125mg/ml) was performed according to the CLSI M27-A2 document with the EUCAST modifications. The ATCC reference strains 90028 (Candida albicans), 22019 (Candida parapsilosis), and 6258 (Candida krusei) were included in this study. The minimal inhibitory concentration (MIC) was considered as the minimal concentration of ajoena able to inhibit 80% of the fungal growth.ResultsFifty five yeasts were recovered, 36 (65.4%) of them were causing candidosis and 19 (34.5%) were colonizing. C. albicans was the most frequent (81.8%) of the six isolated species, prevailing on the patients with candidosis (54.5%). The non-albicans species were less frequently isolated (18.2%), and Candida glabrata was the prevailing agent (7.3%) followed by Candida tropicalis (3.6%), C. krusei, C. parapsilosis, Candida guilliermondii and Candida sp. (1.8% each of them). The susceptibility tests to ajoeno showed inhibition of fungal growth in 98.2% of the isolates, showing MIC values &amp;#10877;15mg/ml, and in (one isolate of C. glabrata) (1.8%) this value was &gt;20mg/ml. The reference strains showed MIC values of 3.125 and 10mg/ml.ConclusionsThe results here presented, obtained from a significant number of isolates, mainly C. albicans, demonstrate, once more, the potential of ajoeno as an antifungal agent(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrero, Sarelie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Hilda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Apitz-Castro, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosEl objetivo del presente trabajo fue evaluar la actividad in vitro del ajoeno sobre levaduras del género Candida, obtenidas de secreciones vaginales.MétodosSe analizaron 136 muestras. Las levaduras se aislaron e identificaron por métodos tradicionales. Se evaluó su sensibilidad al ajoeno (20, 15, 12,5, 10, 6,25 y 3,125mg/ml) según el documento M27-A2 del CLSI (Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute), con modificaciones del EUCAST (European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing). Se incluyeron las cepas ATCC 90028 (Candida albicans), 22019 (Candida parapsilosis) y 6258 (Candida krusei). La concentración mínima inhibitoria (CMI) se consideró la menor concentración de ajoeno capaz de inhibir el 80% del crecimiento fúngico.ResultadosSe recuperaron 55 levaduras, 36 que estaban ocasionando candidiasis (65,4%) y 19 que estaban colonizando (34,5%). De las 6 especies aisladas, C. albicans ocupó el primer lugar (81,8%) y predominó en las pacientes con candidiasis (54,5%). Otras especies del género Candida se aislaron con menor frecuencia (18,2%); Candida glabrata fue la primera en este grupo (7,3%), seguida de Candida tropicalis (3,6%), C. krusei, C. parapsilosis, Candida guilliermondii y Candida sp. (cada una 1,8%). Las pruebas de sensibilidad mostraron inhibición del crecimiento fúngico en un 98,2% de los aislamientos, con una CMI inferior o igual a 15mg/ml de ajoeno, y (un aislamiento de C. glabrata) (1,8%) la CMI fue superior a 20mg/ml. En las cepas control la CMI fue de 3,125 y 10mg/ml.ConclusionesEstos resultados, obtenidos con un número significativo de aislamientos de Candida, en especial de C. albicans, demuestran una vez más el poder antifúngico potencial del ajoeno en las levaduras resistentes a los antifúngicos más comunes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;26(3): 193-189, sept. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75539</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto inhibitorio in vitro de ajoeno sobre aislamientos de Candida recuperados de secreciones vaginales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32951^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2213^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
