<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129448</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of drug interaction between clopidogrel and omeprazole in hospital readmision of patients by a recurrent acute coronary syndrome: A case-control study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the effect of drug interaction between omeprazol and clopidogrel in hospital readmission of patients with acute coronary syndrome (ACS). Design: Case-control study. Location: University Clinic Leon XIII, Medellin, Colombia. Participants: We selected from a prevalent population, between 2009-2010, use of clopidogrel patients on an outpatient basis (less than one year and more than 30 days), and hospital stay for ACS or the presence of a previous ACS. Main measures: A case-patient was defined as one who had a recurrence of ACS and a patient controlis defined as one that no recurrence of ACS. Both groups used ambulatory priorclopidogrel due to ACS. As defined risk factor the joint use of omeprazole and clopidogrel outpatients. Results: During the study, 1680 patients clopidogrel formulated. This group identified 50 cases readmitted with ACS and 76 controls. No statistically significant association was found between use of clopidogrel-omeprazole and increased risk of hospital readmission for ACS (OR: 1.05; 95% CI: 0.516-2.152; P = 0.8851). Conclusions: In this small group of patients with previous SCA, the simultaneous use of clopidogrel with omeprazole does not increase the risk of a readmission by recurrence of this type of coronary event (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ceballos, Mauricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amariles, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betancourth, Piedad María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Holguín, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angulo, Nancy Yaneth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el efecto de la interacción clopidogrel-omeprazol en el reingreso hospitalario de pacientes por recidiva de síndrome coronario agudo (SCA). Diseño: Estudio de casos y controles. Emplazamiento: IPS Universitaria Clínica León XIII, Medellín, Colombia. Participantes: Se seleccionaron a partir de una población prevalente, entre 2009-2010, pacientes con uso de clopidogrel de forma ambulatoria (menor a un año y superior a 30 días), y la estancia hospitalaria por un SCA o la presencia de un SCA previo. Medidas principales: Un paciente-caso se definió como aquel que presentó una recidiva de SCA y un paciente-control se definió como aquel que no presentó recidiva de SCA. Ambos grupos utilizaron ambulatoriamente clopidogrel debido al SCA previo. Como factor de riesgo se definió la utilización conjunta de omeprazol y clopidogrel ambulatoriamente. Resultados: Durante el estudio se formuló clopidogrel a 1.680 pacientes. En este grupo se identificaron 50 casos readmitidos con SCA y 76 controles. No se encontró asociación estadísticamente significativa entre el uso de clopidogrel-omeprazol y un mayor riesgo de reingreso hospitalario por SCA (OR: 1,05; IC 95%: 0,516-2,152; p = 0,8851). Conclusiones: En este pequeño grupo de pacientes con SCA previo, la utilización simultánea de clopidogrel con omeprazol no aumenta el riesgo de un reingreso hospitalario por recurrencia de este tipo de evento coronario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;46(8): 426-432, oct. 2014. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129448</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la interacción clopidogrel-omeprazol en el reingreso hospitalario de pacientes por recidiva de síndrome coronario agudo: estudio de casos y controles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19276^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
