<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91456</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish adaptation of the Need for Closure Scale</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Need for Cognitive Closure (NCC) refers to the motivation to seek and maintain a definitive answer to a given problem. This mental closure allows people to avoid confusion, ambiguity and uncertainty. The NCC plays a critical role in a variety of processes of diverse nature, including intra-personal (e.g., the higher the NCC, the less generation of hypothesis), inter-personal (e.g., decreased empathy), intra-group (e.g., increased desire for consensus), and inter-group (increased in-group favouritism) phenomena. The goal of the present research was to provide a Spanish adaptation of Antonio Pierro and Arie Kruglanski&#146;s Revised NCC Scale (2005, Rev NfCS), examining the reliability and the validity of participants&#146; scores. In the present studies, it was found that the Spanish version of the scale had acceptable internal reliability and adequate factor structure (Study 1), as well as acceptable test-retest reliability and adequate discriminant validity with regard to the scores in another measure of individual differences such as the Need for Cognition (NC, Study 2) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Horcajo, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Darío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gandarillas, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briñol, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Necesidad de Cierre Cognitivo (NCC) se refiere a la motivación de las personas por buscar y mantener una respuesta definitiva ante un problema determinado. Este cierre mental permite evitar la confusión, la ambigüedad y la incertidumbre. La NCC juega un papel importante en multitud de procesos de diferente naturaleza, incluyendo fenómenos intra-personales (e.g., a mayor NCC, se generan menos hipótesis), inter-personales (e.g., reduce la empatía), intra-grupales (e.g., aumenta la búsqueda de consenso) e inter-grupales (e.g., aumenta el favoritismo endo-grupal). El objetivo de la presente investigación fue adaptar al castellano el Test Revisado de NCC (TR-NCC) de Antonio Pierro y Arie Kruglanski (2005), examinando la fiabilidad y la validez de las puntuaciones de los participantes. En los estudios realizados, las puntuaciones de los participantes mostraron una consistencia interna aceptable y una validez factorial adecuada (Estudio 1); así como una fiabilidad temporal también aceptable y una adecuada validez discriminante con respecto a las puntuaciones en otra medida de diferencias individuales como la Necesidad de Cognición (NC, Estudio 2) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(4): 864-870, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91456</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación al castellano del Test de Necesidad de Cierre Cognitivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11775^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
