<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126755</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Symptomatic and asymptomatic interphalageal osteoarthritis: an ultrasonographic study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To date few studies have examined whether ultrasonography can depict morphologic differences in painful and painless osteoarthritis (OA). This study describes and compares the clinical, radiographic and ultrasonographic findings of patients with both painful and painless proximal interphalgeal (PIP) and/or distal interphalgeal (DIP) OA. Methods: Patients with PIP and/or DIP OA (ACR criteria) were prospectively recruited. The clinical rheumatologist chose up to 3 painful joints and up to 3 painless symmetric joints in each patient to define 2 cohorts of OA: symptomatic (SG) and asymptomatic (ASG). A conventional postero-anterior hand x ray was performed and read by one rheumatologist following the OARSI atlas, blinded to clinical and sonographic data. Ultrasound (US) was performed by an experienced rheumatologist, blinded to both clinical and radiographic data in joints previously selected by the clinical rheumatologist. US-pathology was assessed as present or absent as defined in previous reports: osteophytes, joint space narrowing, synovitis, intra-articular power doppler signal, intra-articular bony erosion, and visualization of cartilage. Radiographic and ultrasonographic intrareader reliability test was performed. Results: A total of 50 joints in the SG and ASG were included from 20 right handed women aged 61.85 (46-73) years with PIP and DIP OA diagnosed 6.8 (1-17) years ago. 70% SG joints and ASG were right and left sided respectively. The SG showed significantly more osteophytes, synovitis and non-visualization of joint cartilage. Intrareader radiographic and ultrasonographic agreement was excellent. Conclusion: This study demonstrates that painful PIP and/or DIP OA have more ultrasonographic structural changes and synovitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Usón, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguélez, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Condés, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godo, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Espartero, Cruz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Blasco, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Pocos estudios han examinado si existen diferencias morfológicas detectables con ecografía entre las articulaciones sintomáticas y las que no lo son en pacientes con artrosis. Este estudio describe y compara los hallazgos clínicos, radiológicos y ecográficos de los pacientes con artrosis interfalángica proximal (IFP) y/o distal (IFD) que tienen articulaciones con y sin dolor. Métodos. Prospectivamente, se incluyó a pacientes con artrosis IFP y/o IFD según los criterios ACR. El reumatólogo clínico eligió hasta un máximo de 3 articulaciones dolorosas y 3 articulaciones no dolorosas de localización simétrica en cada paciente para formar 2 cohortes de artrosis: grupo con dolor (GD) y grupo sin dolor (GSD). La radiografía simple postero-anterior de las manos fue leída por un reumatólogo según las recomendaciones del atlas OARSI, ciego a toda información clínica y ecográfica. El estudio ecográfico fue realizado por un reumatólogo en las articulaciones previamente seleccionadas por el clínico ciego a los datos clínicos y radiológicos. Se registraron como ausente o presente: osteofitos, pinzamiento articular, sinovitis, señal Doppler intraarticular, erosiones y visualización del cartílago. Se realizó un estudio de fiabilidad intralector para la radiología y para la ecografía. Resultados. Se estudió un total de 50 articulaciones en cada cohorte de 20 mujeres diestras de 61,85 años de edad (46-73) con artrosis IFP y IFD diagnosticada hace 6,8 años (1-17 años). El 70% de las articulaciones del GD y GSD se localizaron en la mano derecha e izquierda, respectivamente. El GD tenía significativamente más osteofitos, sinovitis y ausencia de cartílago que el GSD. La fiabilidad interlector radiológico y ecográfico fue excelente. Conclusión. La ecografía detecta más daño estructural y sinovitis en las IFP y/o IFD artrósicas que presentan dolor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);10(5): 278-282, sept.-oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Artrosis interfalángica sintomática y asintomática: un estudio ecográfico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7764^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50362^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50364^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5520^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10179^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5520^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50362^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54008^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
