<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052749</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mobbing: its relationships with organizational culture and personal outcomes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A study dealing with the effects of both organizational culture and mobbing on personal and organizational outcomes of a sample of Spanish emergency workers, is reported here. It was found that there is a strong impact of organizational culture dimensions on mobbing, and that mobbing affects job satisfaction, organizational commitment and organizational citizenship behaviour. Results concerning organizational commitment show that this variable is not a mere effect of mobbing in general, but rather that it is also a direct impact of culture on this outcome</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Topa Cantisano, Gabriela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Domínguez, José Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallastegui Galán, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un estudio centrado en los efectos de la cultura organizacional y el acoso laboral en los resultados personales y organizacionales de una muestra de trabajadores españoles de equipos de emergencias se refiere aquí. Se ha encontrado que hay un fuerte impacto de las dimensiones de la cultura en el acoso y que el acoso laboral afecta a la satisfacción laboral, al compromiso organizacional y a las conductas de ciudadanía organizacional. Los resultados relativos al compromiso organizacional muestran que esta variable no es un mero efecto del acoso en general, sino que hay un impacto directo de la cultura en este resultado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(4): 766-771, nov. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052749</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acoso laboral: relaciones con la cultura organizacional y los resultados personales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34633</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
