<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75022</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of kenaf fibre in the elaboration of specific substrates for Pleurotus ostreatus (Jacq. ex Fr.) Kummer cultivation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study, the viability of the kenaf fibre use, alone or combined with cerealstraw, vine shoots and olive mill dried waste, in the elaboration of specificsubstrates for the cultivation of Pleurotus ostreatus (Jacq. ex Fr.) Kummer,second mushroom in importance cultivated in Spain, is described.Furthermore, three different methods of preparation of the substrate have beenconsidered in order to obtain selectivity for the growth and later fruiting ofPleurotus sporophore. As for the production parameters, the best results havebeen provided by the substrates that combined kenaf with straw and with vineshoots, being unfavourable the substrates based in just kenaf or combinedwith olive mill dried waste. As for the treatment applied to the materials, theimmersion in water alone and subsequent pasteurization and thermophilicconditioning, together with the semi-anaerobic fermentation, has beenfavoured in front of the immersion in water with fungicide and laterpasteurization(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo Núñez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Giménez, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perona Zamora, M. Aquilina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe en el presente trabajo el estudio de la viabilidad del empleode sustratos selectivos basados en fibra de kenaf (Hibiscus cannabinus L.),sola o combinada con pajas de cereales, sarmiento de vid y alperujo deaceituna, para el cultivo comercial de Pleurotus ostreatus (Jacq. ex Fr.)Kummer, segundo hongo en importancia cultivado en España. Se hanconsiderado, además, tres métodos diferentes de preparación del sustrato,con objeto de conseguir selectividad y especificidad para el crecimiento yposterior fructificación del hongo objeto de estudio. En el conjunto desustratos, los mejores resultados han sido proporcionados por los basados enkenaf combinado con paja, seguido de la mezcla con sarmientos, resultandodesfavorables los sustratos basados en kenaf solo o combinado con alperujo.En cuanto al tratamiento aplicado a los materiales, el mejor rendimiento hasido proporcionado por los sustratos sometidos a pasteurización yacondicionamiento termófilo, aunque sin diferir significativamente de lafermentación semianaerobia mesófila, mientras que la inmersión en agua confungicida y posterior pasteurización arrojó los peores resultados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;25(1): 57-61, 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75022</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de fibra de kenaf (Hibiscus cannabinus L.) en la elaboración de sustratos específicos para cultivo de Pleurotus ostreatus (Jacq. ex Fr.) Kummer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d25544^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33732^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d369^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3491</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
