<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93957</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of sexual strategies theory in the spanish population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to test some of the main hypotheses derived from Buss&#146; Sexual Strategies Theory on a representative Spanish sample. These hypotheses refer to the different strategies men and woman seem to adopt when they want to engage in a short-term sexual relationship (fling), or in a long-term one (loving relationship). (The technical term «strategies», unlike its equivalent in everyday language, is not meant to imply something necessarily planned or conscious). Data was obtained by self-report from a representative sample of 1949 Spanish people. Almost all the results verify the working hypotheses, conferring some empirical support on the theory from which they were deduced, within an evolutionary Social Psychology paradigm. In any case, it is argued that socialization approaches («double moral» and the social construction of gender role and sexual identity) can also explain most of the differences obtained, in perfect compatibility with biological perspectives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yela, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presente investigación trata de explorar la validez de algunas de las principales hipótesis deducidas de la Teoría de las Estrategias Sexuales de Buss, en una muestra representativa de la población española. Dichas hipótesis hacen referencia a «estrategias» (no necesariamente conscientes ni planeadas) diferentes entre hombres y mujeres a la hora de involucrarse en una relación sexual a corto plazo (coloquialmente «ligar») o a largo plazo («relación amorosa»). Los datos se obtuvieron mediante autoinforme, sobre una muestra representativa de la población española (n= 1.949). Casi todos los resultados obtenidos confirman las hipótesis planteadas, lo cual supone un cierto apoyo empírico a la teoría de la que han sido deducidas, dentro del enfoque evolucionista de la Psicología Social. En cualquier caso, se argumenta que la mayor parte de las diferencias constatadas son también explicables desde los enfoques de la socialización diferencial (la «doble moral» y la construcción social del rol de género y de la identidad sexual), y se comenta la perfecta compatibilidad de ambos enfoques (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);24(1): 48-54, ene.-mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la Teoría de las Estrategias Sexuales en la población española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3106^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33534^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12042^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
