<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162227</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nonfunctioning, small, incidental pancreatic neuroendocrine tumors. Results of a nonoperative approach cohort</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The availability of new imaging techniques has conditioned an increase in the incidental diagnosis of small nonfunctioning pancreatic neuroendocrine tumors (PNET-NF). The best treatment is controversial, some authors advise a conservative approach in selected cases. Our aim is to analyze the evolution of incidental, small size PNET-NF, treated with clinical follow-up without surgery. Methods. We performed a retrospective analysis of a prospective database of patients diagnosed incidentally with PNET-NF since November 2007 to September 2015. We include those with PNET-NF &amp;#8804;2cm and asymptomatic. The diagnosis was performed using imaging tests indicating endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration in case of doubts in the diagnosis. The follow-up was performed at our center, registering clinical and/or radiological changes. Results. We included 24 patients with a median age of 70 years, and a similar distribution in terms of sex. The diagnosis was made through computed tomography multidetector or magnetic resonance imaging and octreotide scan. The tumors were located mainly in the head and neck (46%), with a mean size of 11,5±3,55mm at diagnosis (5-19mm). In 2 cases endoscopic ultrasound fine needle aspiration was used (8%), confirming the diagnosis of low-grade PNET with Ki67&lt;5%. The median follow-up was 39 months (7-100). In 19 patients (79%) they remained the same size, 21% (5) increased its size with a mean of 2,6±2mm (1-6). No cases had progression of disease. Conclusion. In selected patients, non-surgical management of PNET-NF is an option to consider, when they are asymptomatic and &amp;#8804;2cm. Larger studies with more patients and more time of follow-up are needed to validate this non-operative approach (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pelaez Serra, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Secanella Medayo, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Busquets Barenys, Juli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribe Galeano, Catalina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fabregat Prous, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villabona Artero, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Rubio, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Osuna, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. La disponibilidad de nuevas técnicas de imagen ha condicionado un incremento en el diagnóstico incidental de pequeños tumores neuroendocrinos pancreáticos no funcionantes (TNP-NF). El mejor tratamiento de estos tumores es controvertido: algunos autores aconsejan una actitud conservadora en casos seleccionados. Nuestro objetivo es analizar la evolución de TNP-NF incidentales de pequeño tamaño, tratados con seguimiento clínico sin cirugía. Métodos. Se realizó un análisis retrospectivo de una base de datos prospectiva de pacientes diagnosticados incidentalmente de TNP-NF desde noviembre de 2007 hasta septiembre de 2015. Incluimos aquellos con TNP-NF&amp;#8804;2cm y asintomáticos. El diagnóstico se realizó mediante pruebas de imagen, indicando ecoendoscopia-punción en caso de dudas diagnósticas. El seguimiento se hizo en nuestro centro, con registro de cambios clínicos y radiológicos. Resultados. Incluimos a 24 pacientes con una mediana de edad de 70 años y distribución similar en cuanto al sexo. El diagnóstico se realizó mediante tomografía computarizada multidetector, resonancia nuclear magnética y gammagrafía con octreótide. Los tumores se localizaban principalmente en cabeza y cuello (46%), con un tamaño medio de 11,5±3,55mm al diagnóstico (5-19mm). En 2 casos se asoció ecoendoscopia-punción (8%), confirmando el diagnóstico de TNP de bajo grado con Ki67&lt;5%. La mediana de seguimiento fue de 39 meses (7-100). El 79% (19) mantuvieron el mismo tamaño. El 21% (5) aumentó su tamaño con una media de 2,6±2mm (1-6). En ningún caso hubo progresión de enfermedad. Conclusión. En pacientes seleccionados, el manejo no quirúrgico de TNP-NF, asintomáticos y &amp;#8804;2cm es una opción a tener en cuenta. Son necesarios estudios con mayor número de pacientes y un seguimiento mayor para validar esta opción conservadora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);95(2): 83-88, 1 feb., 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162227</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores neuroendocrinos no funcionantes de páncreas incidentales de pequeno tamano: Resultados de una serie con manejo no quirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
