<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058892</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical stress and the influence in sports performance in professional basketball players (First Spanish League)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Professional basketball players are elite sportmen exposed to a high degree of eccentric and anaerobic exercise, and display an intense competition-derived psychophysiological stress that can conditionate their physical performance.         However, little is known concerning the possible methods to prevent and detect psychophysiological stress and its correlated hormonal changes in professional basketball players throughout the season and during competition. Therefore, the aim of the present work was to describe the possible variations in blood circulating levels of ACTH, cortisol and testosterone, as well as testosterone/cortisol ratio.         Taken together, these results suggest that regenerative methods, as well as the planification of resting periods, reduced muscle damage, prevented muscle fatigue and improved muscle regeneration, thus leading to optimal results reached in competition</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Seco Calvo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los jugadores de baloncesto son deportistas de élite, expuestos a un ejercicio con un gran componente excéntrico y anaeróbico y, por consiguiente, la intensa competición deriva en estrés, y puede condicionar la forma física y, consecuentemente, el rendimiento deportivo.         Sin embargo, es poco conocido lo concerniente a los posibles métodos para detectar y prevenir el estrés, lo cual está directamente relacionado con los cambios hormonales que se producen a lo largo de la fase regular de la temporada deportiva.         El propósito de este trabajo es mostrar los datos referentes al comportamiento de las hormonas, cortisol, ACTH y testosterona en relación con el rendimiento deportivo medido a través de la estadística oficial, esto es, medido en términos de eficacia.         Los resultados obtenidos sugieren que los métodos de recuperación (procedimiento fisioterapéutico), así como los períodos de recuperación, dentro de la planificación, podrían reducir el impacto del estrés sobre el organismo del deportista, facilitando los procesos regenerativos, y contribuyendo con ello a mejorar el rendimiento deportivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(5): 207-213, sep.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058892</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés físico y su influencia sobre el rendimiento deportivo en jugadores profesionales de baloncesto ACB</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22498^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
