<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130109</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">&#145;Third day intervention&#146;: An analysis of the factors associated with following the recommendations on the prescribing of antibiotics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Stewardship programs on the use of antibiotics usually include interventions based on non-compulsory recommendations for the prescribers. Factors related to the adherence to expert recommendations, and the implementation of these programmes in daily practice, are of interest. Methods. A randomized, controlled, multicentre intervention study was performed in 32 hospitalization units. Antibiotic prescriptions were evaluated by an infectious disease specialist on the third day. We describe the implementation of the intervention, the factors associated with adherence to recommendations, and the impact of the intervention. Results. A total of 3,192 interventions were carried out. Information sources used to prepare the recommendations varied significantly between centres. A modification was recommended in 65% of cases: withdrawal (47%), change in administration route (26%), change of drugs or number of antibiotics (27%), and change in dose (5%). Simplification of treatment accounted for 75% of all recommendations. Adherence was 68%, with significant differences between hospitals, and higher when the recommendations consisted of a dose adjustment or change of route, during the first intervention period, and also when recommendations were personally commented on, in addition to writing a note in the clinical chart. We did not find any reduction in antibiotic consumption or variation in the incidence of resistant pathogens. Conclusions. An important proportion of antibiotic prescriptions may be susceptible to improvement, most of them towards simplification. The adherence to the intervention was high, but significant variations at different centres were observed, depending on the type of recommendation, and the study period. Those recommendations that were personally commented on were more followed more than those only written (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-San Miguel, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura, Ferrán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnau, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gudiol, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillas, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gurguí, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los programas de control de uso de antibióticos suelen incluir intervenciones basadas en recomendaciones no impositivas a los prescriptores. Interesa conocer los factores relacionados con la adherencia a las recomendaciones y su funcionamiento en la práctica real. Métodos. Estudio multicéntrico, controlado y aleatorizado, realizado en 32 unidades de hospitalización. Especialistas en enfermedades infecciosas revisaron, alrededor del tercer día, las prescripciones de antibióticos, estableciendo recomendaciones. Describimos la implantación de la intervención, analizamos los factores asociados al seguimiento de las recomendaciones y el impacto de la intervención. Resultados. Se realizaron 3.192 intervenciones. Las fuentes de información empleadas para la elaboración de las recomendaciones variaron significativamente entre los centros. En el 65% se recomendó alguna modificación del tratamiento: suspender los antibióticos (47%), modificar la vía de administración (26%), cambiar o variar el número de antibióticos (27%) y cambiar la dosis (5%). En el 75% se recomendó simplificar el tratamiento. La adherencia fue del 68%, con variaciones significativas entre los centros, y fue mayor cuando se recomendó ajuste de dosis o cambio de vía, durante el primer periodo del estudio y cuando las recomendaciones se realizaban, además de por escrito, verbalmente. No se pudo constatar impacto en el consumo de antibióticos ni en la incidencia de patógenos resistentes. Conclusiones. Una elevada proporción de tratamientos antibióticos son susceptibles de modificación, generalmente hacia la simplificación. La adherencia a las recomendaciones fue elevada, aunque variable, dependiendo del centro, del tipo de recomendación, del periodo del estudio y de que la recomendación se realizara mediante un comentario verbal además de escrito (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(10): 654-661, dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130109</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La «intervención del tercer día»: análisis de los factores asociados al seguimiento de recomendaciones sobre la prescripción de antibióticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55050^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
