<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105064</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Secundary augmentation mammoplasty. Evaluation of problems, unsatisfactory results and alternatives for solution</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A series of patients with unsatisfactory results after a breast augmentation surgery with silicone implants is presented in this report. The aim is to identify the most frequent problems and to offer alternatives for their solution. From an universal group of 230 patients with aesthetic breast augmentation surgery done from 2004 to 2009, a selective group of 15patients is presented; out of these, 12 had a surgical procedure done for the first time by another medical team and 3 done by the first author of this paper. After medical evaluation 13 patients had a secondary breast augmentation surgery in order to correct the problems with satisfactory results one year postoperative. Nevertheless, 2 patients had breast stretch marks as first problem in the postoperative period which does not have a definitive solution by now. The possible reasons of the problems are: inadequate or not indicated line of access in 60%; implant size was excessive in 12 patients(80%), out of these, 10 patients requested implants with smaller size and 2 did not agree to get new implants; 2 patients (13.3%) suffered implant rupture before the first postoperative year and 1 patient had rupture after 25 years of the surgical procedure; in 12 patients (80%)there was asymptomatic capsular contracture grade I and II and grade III in 3 patients (20%). There was no information about the manufacturer of the implants in 6 patients (40%) and 10 patients (66%) did not have any information about the importance of having a certificate of guarantee on the implants. We conclude that there is a lack of unified criteria to face the secondary problems after breast augmentation surgery using silicone implants, therefore it is necessary to encourage scientific studies by universities, professional societies and governmental agencies in order to quantify sequels, classify them and offer alternatives for their solution (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berrocal Revueltas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un resumen de pacientes con resultados insatisfactorios tras mamoplastia de aumento con implantes de silicona  con el objetivo de identificar los factores asociados que permitan ayudar a identificar los problemas más frecuentes en este tipo de cirugía y ofrecer alternativas de solución. De un grupo universal de 230 paciente intervenidas quirúrgicamente por mamoplastia de aumento entre 2004 y 2009,  presentamos un grupo de 15, de las cuales 12 habían sido intervenidas por primera vez por otro equipo médico y 3 por el primer autor del trabajo. De ellas,13 tuvieron que ser sometidas a mamoplastia secundaria para corrección de problemas con resultados muy satisfactorios tras un año de postoperatorio.  Sin embargo, 2 pacientes presentaron  como problema inicial estrías mamarias en el postoperatorio inmediato que no han tenido solución definitiva hasta el momento. Las posibles causas de los problemas surgidos tras la mamoplastia primaria fueron: vía de acceso inadecuada  o  no indicada en el 60% de los casos; volumen  excesivo de los implantes en el 80% de los casos (12 pacientes), de las cuales 10 solicitaron  implantes  de menor volumen y 2 rehusaron la colocación de nuevos implantes;  rotura de los implantes antes del primer año de postoperatorio en 2 pacientes (13.3%) y rotura a los 25 años de postoperatorio en 1 paciente; contractura capsular asintomática grado I y II en 12 pacientes (80% de los casos) y degrado III en 3 pacientes (20%).Respecto al certificado de garantía de los implantes, 10 pacientes(66%) no tenían información alguna referente a la importancia del mismo y no encontramos información del fabricante en los implantes retirados en 6 pacientes (40%). Como conclusión, observamos un vacio en cuanto a la unidad de criterios a la hora de encarar los problemas secundarios a la mamoplastia de aumento con prótesis de silicona y, se (..)  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;38(1): 9-26, ene.-mar. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105064</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mamoplastia de aumento secundaria: Evaluación de problemas, resultados insatisfactorios y alternativas de solución</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19574^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33583^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32332^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13206^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
