<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136704</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of 3D vision on mental workload and laparoscopic performance in inexperienced subjects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the effect of vision in three dimensions (3D) versus two dimensions (2D) on mental workload and laparoscopic performance during simulation-based training. Materials and methods: A prospective, randomized crossover study on inexperienced students in operative laparoscopy was conducted. Forty-six candidates executed five standardized exercises on a pelvitrainer with both vision systems (3D and 2D). Laparoscopy performance was assessed using the total time (in seconds) and the number of failed attempts. For workload assessment, the validated NASA-TLX questionnaire was administered. Results: 3D vision improves the performance reducing the time (3D = 1006.08 ± 315.94 vs. 2D = 1309.17 ± 300.28; P &lt; .001) and the total number of failed attempts (3D = .84 ± 1.26 vs. 2D = 1.86 ± 1.60; P &lt; .001). For each exercise, 3 D vision also shows better performance times: «transfer objects» (P = .001), «single knot» (P &lt; .001), «clip and cut» (P &lt; .05), and «needle guidance» (P &lt; .001). Besides, according to the NASA-TLX results, less mental workload is experienced with the use of 3 D (P &lt; .001). However, 3 D vision was associated with greater visual impairment (P &lt; .01) and headaches (P &lt; .05). Conclusion: The incorporation of 3 D systems in laparoscopic training programs would facilitate the acquisition of laparoscopic skills, because they reduce mental workload and improve the performance on inexperienced surgeons. However, some undesirable effects such as visual discomfort or headache are identified initially (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carazo-Carazo, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos-Hernández, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena-Tapia, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco-Valiente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero-Rosa, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Font-Ugalde, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anglada-Curado, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar el efecto de la visión en 3 dimensiones (3D) en comparación con 2 dimensiones (2D) sobre la carga mental de trabajo soportada y el rendimiento laparoscópico en ejercicios de simulación. Material y métodos: Se llevó a cabo un estudio prospectivo aleatorizado cruzado en sujetos sin experiencia en laparoscopia. Se incluyeron 46 participantes, los cuales completaron 5 ejercicios en pelvitrainer basados en un programa validado usando ambos sistemas de visión. El rendimiento se evaluó mediante el tiempo transcurrido y el número de errores cometidos, y la carga mental de trabajo a través del cuestionario validado NASA-TLX. Resultados: Los participantes realizaron las actividades mejor con la visión 3D de forma global en términos de tiempo (3D = 1.006,08 ± 315,94 vs. 2D = 1.309,17 ± 300,28; p &lt; 0,001) y número total de errores (3D = 0,84 ± 1,26 vs. 2D = 1,86 ± 1,60; p &lt; 0,001). Cuando se analizó el tiempo de forma independiente por ejercicios, el uso de 3D mostró diferencias estadísticamente significativas en: «transferencia de objetos» (p = 0,001), «sutura» (p &lt; 0,001), «clipar y cortar» (p &lt; 0,05) y «manejo de la aguja» (p &lt; 0,001). Además, el uso de la visión 3D produjo menos carga mental de trabajo de acuerdo con los resultados del NASA-TLX (p &lt; 0,001), aunque se asoció con un mayor malestar visual (p &lt; 0,01) y dolor de cabeza (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusión: La incorporación de sistemas 3D en cirugía laparoscópica facilitaría la adquisición más temprana de habilidades laparoscópicas, ya que se asocia a un mejor rendimiento y menor carga mental de trabajo en sujetos sin experiencia, si bien existen inicialmente algunos efectos indeseables como malestar visual o dolor de cabeza (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;39(4): 229-235, mayo 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136704</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la visión 3D sobre la carga mental y el rendimiento laparoscópico en individuos sin experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13724^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35390^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35390^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
