<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136596</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Secondary effects of topical application of an essential oil. Allergic contact dermatitis due to tea tree oil</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Tea tree oil is an essential oil, whose use is increasing in our setting, due both to its supposed medicinal effects and to its aromatic properties. We describe our experience with allergic contact dermatitis following the application of this oil. Material and methods. Five patients in the last 5 years (0.4% of all the patients studied in specialized consultation) reacted to a 5% concentration of tea tree oil in Vaseline. Results. All the patients presented strong reactions, and in all cases these were considered relevant. Three of them also reacted to oxidized d-limonene, one of the components of tea tree oil, which is present in our standard series. Conclusions. Different cases have been described in the literature on allergic contact dermatitis due to tea tree oil, but until recently it was infrequent in our setting. With the increased popularity of alternative and natural therapies we have witnessed several cases of sensitization to this essential oil, which had been used to treat several supposedly &#147;infectious&#148; skin diseases, but which were very probably different forms of dermatitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yanguas Bayona, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agulló Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loidi Pascual, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrea García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santesteban Muruzábal, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hervella Garcés, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. El aceite de árbol de té es un aceite esencial, cuyo uso está aumentando en nuestro medio, tanto por sus supuestos efectos medicinales, como por sus propiedades aromáticas. Se describe nuestra experiencia en dermatitis alérgica de contacto tras la aplicación de este aceite. Material y Métodos. Cinco pacientes en los últimos 5 años (0,4% de todos los pacientes estudiados en consulta especializada) reaccionaron a una concentración de 5% de aceite de árbol de té en vaselina. Resultados. Todos los pacientes presentaron reacciones fuertes, y en todos los casos éstas fueron consideradas relevantes. Tres de ellos reaccionaron también a d-limoneno oxidado, uno de los componentes del aceite de árbol de té, que está presente en nuestra serie estándar. Conclusiones. Se han descrito diversos casos en la literatura de dermatitis alérgica de contacto al aceite de árbol de té, pero hasta hace poco ha sido infrecuente en nuestro medio. Con el aumento de popularidad de terapias alternativas y naturales hemos sido testigos de varios casos de sensibilización a este aceite esencial, que había sido utilizado para tratar varias enfermedades de la piel supuestamente &#147;infecciosas&#148;, pero que eran muy probablemente diferentes formas de dermatitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;38(1): 163-167, ene.-abr. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136596</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos secundarios de la aplicación tópica de un aceite de esencial. Dermatitis alérgica de contacto a aceite de árbol de té</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34459^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d904^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30757^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
