<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160001</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-specific musculoskeletal disorders in the proximal upper limb muscles in health workers: Analysis of the presence of trigger points</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">High labor demands in hospitals are associated to muscle pain, hyperalgesia, functional restrictions and behavioral disorders accompanied by muscle injuries. However, most of the research has focused on evaluating ergonomics, stress and workload. Objectives: To determine how many workers in a hospital showed non-specific musculoskeletal disorders (MSDs) confirmed by the presence of Trigger Points (TrPs); to establish the most affected muscles (i. e., sternocleidomastoid, levator scapula, trapeze, infraspinatus, teres minor) by pain according to the side (left or right); and to identify the pain behavior assumed. Material and method: A cross-sectional study was conducted at the Loire VendéeOcéan Hospital, France. The pressure pain threshold measured by algometry was bilaterally compared and evaluated in the proximal upper limb muscles (PULM). Pain behavior was assessed using a self-administered questionnaire. Results: 21 women suffered from non-specific MSDs in PULM, confirmed by TrPs. The pressure pain threshold at the sternocleidomastoid was significant and bilaterally lower compared to other muscles (F4,200=48.879; P&lt;.01). Self-medication for pain relief was frequent in 61.90% of patients. Conclusions: Implementation of active break-time programs aimed to specific muscular groups is required to reduce the risk musculoskeletal disorders in the PULM in the hospital setting. Future studies could investigate if the increased pain in the sternocleidomastoid may be explained by short episodes of low-amplitude but long-duration contractions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esparza, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aladro Gonzalvo, AR</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Altos niveles de exigencia laboral en el medio hospitalario están asociados con dolor muscular, hiperalgesia, restricciones funcionales y trastornos comportamentales acompañados de lesiones musculares. Sin embargo, la mayoría de las investigaciones se han interesado en evaluar la ergonomía, el estrés y la carga de trabajo. Objetivos: Determinar cuántos trabajadores de un centro hospitalario presentaban lesiones musculoesqueléticas no específicas confirmadas por la presencia de puntos gatillo (PG); establecer los músculos (esternocleidomastoideo, elevador de la escápula, trapecio, infraespinoso y redondo menor) más afectados por el dolor según el lado (izquierdo o derecho), e identificar el comportamiento que se asumía frente al dolor. Material y método: Se realizó un estudio transversal en el Centro Hospitalario Loire Vendée Océan, Francia. El umbral de dolor a la presión por algometría fue evaluado y comparado bilateralmente en la musculatura proximal del miembro superior (MPMS). El comportamiento hacia el dolor se evaluó mediante un cuestionario autoadministrado. Resultados: 21 mujeres presentaron lesiones musculoesqueléticas no específicas en la MPMS confirmadas por la presencia de PG. El umbral del dolor fue significativo y bilateralmente menor en el esternocleidomastoideo (F4,200=48,879; p&lt;0,01) en comparación con los otros músculos evaluados. El 61,90% de los pacientes recurría a la automedicación para calmar el dolor muscular. Conclusiones: Se requiere implementar programas de pausas activas dirigidos a grupos musculares específicos, para reducir el riesgo de lesiones musculoesqueléticas de la MPMS en el medio hospitalario. Futuros estudios podrían indagar si el dolor aumentado en el esternocleidomastoideo podría explicarse por episodios de contracción cortos de baja amplitud, pero de una duración prolongada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);39(1): 10-17, ene.-feb. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lesiones musculoesqueléticas no específicas de la musculatura proximal del miembro superior en el personal sanitario: un análisis de la presencia de puntos gatillo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54413</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54546^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55208^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30392^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36501^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10749^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
