<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134964</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intragastric balloon in obesity treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Obesity is considered a chronic and epidemic illness, and difficult to treat. As conservative treatment has a high rate of failure, and considering morbimortality and sequels of surgery, less invasive techniques appeared to contribute to the treatment of this illness. The most implanted technique nowadays is the Intragastric Balloon, considered more efficient as conservative treatments and with less risks tan surgery, but having today a lack of consensus on indications and few information on his limitations, while its apparition in medias promote an important expansion in the 4 last years. In this publication, we do a critical revision, and describe limitations of this treatment, based on the evidences given by literature. We conclude this revision with some recommendations concerning the technique and indications, material and human requiring, need of a Multidisciplinary Team, as well as an adequate control and following  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abilés, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Olmo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mellado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miras, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Culebras, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cancer, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavón, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Breton, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginés, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avilés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazure, RA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escarti, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La obesidad es considerada una enfermedad crónica, epidémica, y de difícil tratamiento. Ante el alto índice de fracasos de los métodos conservadores, y por otra parte, la inevitable morbimortalidad y secuelas ligadas a la cirugía, surgen nuevas técnicas poco invasivas destinadas a contribuir al tratamiento de esta enfermedad. La más implantada actualmente es el Balón Intragástrico, considerado más eficaz que el tratamiento conservador, con menos riesgo que la cirugía pero que adolece adía de hoy de una falta de consenso sobre sus indicaciones y escasa información sobre sus limitaciones, al tiempo que su aparición mediática ha propiciado su gran difusión en los 4 últimos años. En este trabajo se realiza una revisión crítica y se señalan las limitaciones de este tratamiento con base a la evidencia aportada por los estudios publicados hasta la fecha. Como conclusión de dicha revisión, se emiten una serie de recomendaciones respecto a la técnica y sus indicaciones, requisitos materiales y humanos, necesidad de Equipo Multidisciplinar así como del control y seguimiento Adecuados  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;24(2): 139-143, mar.-abr. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134964</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Balón intragástrico en el tratamiento de la obesidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10542^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
