<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150516</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional neuroimaging in the study of parkinsonisms: PET and SPECT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Conventional structural neuroimaging techniques (CT, MRI) are of only limited use in the diagnosis of patients with parkinsonian disorders. In contrast, explorations using nuclear medicine tools (PET and SPECT) can be useful for appraising these patients, since they allow neurochemical and functional aspects to be studied. Aims. This work aims to review the role of functional neuroimaging with PET and SPECT in the study of the nigrostriatal system and other brain functions, with special emphasis on brain SPECT of dopamine transporters with i123-ioflupane and its usefulness in the differential diagnosis of Parkinson's disease and other parkinsonisms. Conclusions. The study of the nigrostriatal function and of other non-dopaminergic systems is useful for the early diagnosis of Parkinson's disease, even in the promoter stage; for differentiating it from essential tremor, from other non-degenerative parkinsonisms (psychogenic, pharmacological, vascular) and from atypical parkinsonisms (multiple system atrophy, progressive supranuclear palsy, corticobasal degeneration); and also for distinguishing Alzheimer's disease from dementia with Lewy bodies. Other tests and radiotracers, for different molecules-mechanisms that occur in Parkinson's disease and other parkinsonisms, are being developed and could be used both to fine-tune the diagnosis even more as well as to gain a better understanding of the molecular mechanisms underlying these diseases and develop new therapeutic targets (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Redondo Robles, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arés Luque, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galiana Ivars, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las técnicas de neuroimagen estructural convencional (TC, RM) tienen una utilidad limitada en el diagnóstico del paciente parkinsoniano. Por el contrario, las exploraciones de Medicina Nuclear (PET y SPECT) pueden ser herramientas útiles para la evaluación de estos pacientes, ya que permiten el estudio de aspectos neuroquímicos y funcionales. Objetivo. Revisar el papel de la neuroimagen funcional con PET Y SPECT en el estudio del sistema nigroestriatal y otras funciones cerebrales, con especial hincapié en el SPECT cerebral de transportadores de dopamina con I123-ioflupano, y su utilidad en el diagnóstico diferencial de la enfermedad de Parkinson y otros parkinsonismos. Conclusiones. El estudio de la función nigro-estriatal y de otros sistemas no dopaminérgicos es útil para el diagnóstico temprano de la enfermedad de Parkinson, incluso en fase promotora; para su diferenciación del temblor esencial, de otros parkinsonismos no degenerativos (psicógeno, farmacológico, vascular) y de parkinsonismos atípicos (atrofia multisistema, parálisis supranuclear progresiva, degeneración corticobasal); y para distinguir la enfermedad de Alzheimer de la demencia por cuerpos de Lewy. Otras pruebas y radiotrazadores, para diferentes moléculas-mecanismos que ocurren en la enfermedad de Parkinson y otros parkinsonismos, están en desarrollo y podrían servir tanto para afinar más en el diagnóstico como para comprender mejor los mecanismos moleculares subyacentes a estas enfermedades y desarrollar nuevas dianas terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;54(supl.4): s33-s39, 3 oct., 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150516</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuroimagen funcional en el estudio de los parkinsonismos: PET y SPECT</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23987</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14595^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34287^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34287^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23987^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
