<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153934</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lean techniques to improve the flow of critically ill patients in a health region with its epicenter in the intensive care unit of a reference hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective:  To analyze whether the application of Lean techniques to improve the flow of critically ill patients in a health region with its epicenter in the intensive care unit (ICU) of a reference hospital. Design: Observational study with pre and post intervention analysis. Setting: ICU of a reference hospital. Patients: We design projects and a value stream map of flow and compared pre and post intervention. Interventions: We recorded demographic data, patient transfers by EMS for lack of beds and delay times in the discharge from ICU to ward. Multidisciplinary meetings and perform daily visual panel, with high priority ICU discharge. We promote temporary relocation of critically ill patients in other special areas of the hospital. We performed a professional satisfaction questionnaire with pre and post implementation of process. We make a statistical analysis of pre and post-intervention comparisons. Results: We planned for 2013 and progressively implemented in 2014. Analysis of patients entering the critical process flow 1) evaluate patients who must transfer for lack of beds, focusing on a diagnosis: pre 10/22 vs. 3/21 post (P=.045); 2) analysis of time delay in the discharge from the ICU to ward: 360.8±163.9minutes in the first period vs. 276.7±149.5 in the second (P=.036); and 3) personal professional satisfaction questionnaire, with 6.6±1.5 points pre vs. 7.5±1.1 in post (P=.001). Analysis of indicators such as the ICU acquired infections, length of ICU stay, the rate of re-admissions and mortality, with no significant differences between the two periods. Conclusions: The application of Lean techniques in the critically ill process had a positive impact on improving patient flow within the health region, noting a decrease of transfers outside the region due to lack of beds, reduced delayed discharge from ICU to conventional ward and increased satisfaction of ICU professionals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vila, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loma-Osorio, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sirvent, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colomer, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martin, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Metje, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar si la aplicación de técnicas «Lean» mejora el flujo de pacientes críticos de una región sanitaria, tomando como epicentro el servicio de medicina intensiva (UCI) del hospital de referencia. Diseño: Estudio observacional con análisis pre y postintervención. Ámbito: UCI del hospital de referencia. Pacientes: Diseñamos proyectos y un mapa de flujo y comparamos características pre y postintervención. Intervenciones: Registramos datos demográficos, de traslados de pacientes por el SEM por falta de camas y los tiempos de demora en la hora de alta de la UCI a planta de hospitalización. Realizamos reuniones multidisciplinarias y panel visual diario, con priorización de altas de UCI. Promovimos la reubicación temporal de pacientes críticos en otras áreas especiales del hospital. Cuestionario de satisfacción profesional con valoración pre y postintervención. Análisis estadístico de las comparaciones pre y postintervención. Resultados: Se planificó durante 2013 y se implementó de forma progresiva en 2014. Las medidas principales fueron: 1) análisis de la entrada de pacientes al flujo del proceso de críticos, evaluando los pacientes que deben trasladarse por falta de camas, centrados en un diagnóstico y un área: 10/22 pre vs. 3/21 post (p=0,045); 2) análisis del tiempo de demora en la hora de alta de UCI a planta de hospitalización: 360,8±163,9min en el primer periodo vs. 276,7±149,5 en el segundo (p=0,036); y 3) cuestionario de satisfacción profesional personal, con 6,6±1,5 puntos pre vs. 7,5±1,1 en post (p=0,001). Análisis de los indicadores de UCI, como son las infecciones adquiridas, los días de estancia, la tasa de reingresos y la mortalidad, sin diferencias significativas entre ambos periodos. Conclusiones: La aplicación de técnicas &#145;Lean&#146; en el proceso de críticos tuvo un impacto positivo en la mejora del flujo de pacientes dentro de la región sanitaria, observando una disminución de los traslados fuera de la región por falta de camas, una reducción en la demora del alta de UCI a hospitalización convencional y un aumento de la satisfacción de los profesionales de la UCI de referencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(5): 266-272, jun.-jul. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153934</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnicas «Lean» para la mejora del flujo de los pacientes críticos de una región sanitaria con epicentro en el servicio de medicina intensiva de un hospital de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10537^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28845^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
