<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154730</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Readmissions due to acute biliary edematous pancreatitis in patients without cholecystectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aims: Analyzing the readmission of patients with acute biliary edematous pancreatitis (ABEP) without cholecystectomy despite a previous episode of mild acute gallstone pancreatitis or lithiasic cholecystitis. Calculating the health costs associated with the non-performance of cholecystectomy. Material and methods: Prospective observational study conducted at a tertiary hospital from July to November 2014. The study has consecutively included inpatients suffering from ABEP who: a) had suffered a previous episode of mild acute gallstone pancreatitis or cholecystitis at least 2 weeks before readmission; and b) had not undergone cholecystectomy despite the lack of contraindications. Results: During the research period, 9 patients (7 females and 2 males) with a mean age of 65.3 years (standard deviation [SD] 19.2) were readmitted. The median number of days between the previous episode of ABEP or cholecystitis and the readmission was 114 days (interquartile range [IQR] 111.0). Reported median overall length of hospital stay was 10 days (IQR = 2.0). Patients underwent a mean of 2.8 (SD = 1.2) ultrasound scans, 1.3 (SD = 0.9) abdominal and pelvic CT, 0.8 (SD = 1.0) MRCP and 0.2 (SD = 0.4) ERCP. The mean cost per patient for each readmission, including hospital stay (143.0 &#128;/day), Emergency Service (332.31 &#128;) and tests performed was 2,381.70 &#128;/patient. Conclusions: Not performing a cholecystectomy within two weeks after a first episode of mild ABEP or cholecystitis contributes to patient readmission due to recurrent pancreatitis, resulting in avoidable treatment costs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Espiga, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Alonso, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Fernández, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García López, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tojo González, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Pérez Pariente, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pipa Muñiz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancebo Mata, Alejo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román Llorente, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela Trastoy, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: analizar los reingresos de pacientes con pancreatitis aguda biliar edematosa (PABE) sin colecistectomía a pesar de un episodio previo de pancreatitis aguda biliar leve o colecistitis litiásica. Calcular el coste sanitario asociado a la no realización de colecistectomía. Material y métodos: estudio observacional prospectivo realizado en el Hospital de Cabueñes, entre julio y noviembre de 2014. Se incluyeron consecutivamente los pacientes ingresados en el Servicio de Digestivo con PABE que: a) habían presentado un episodio previo de pancreatitis aguda biliar leve o colecistitis al menos dos semanas antes del reingreso; y b) no se les había realizado colecistectomía pese a ausencia de contraindicaciones. Resultados: durante el periodo de estudio reingresaron 9 pacientes, 7 mujeres y 2 varones, con una edad media de 65,3 años (desviación estándar [DE] = 19,2). La mediana de días transcurridos desde el episodio previo de PABE o colecistitis hasta su reingreso fue de 114 días (recorrido intercuartílico [RIC] = 111,0). La estancia global mediana de los pacientes fue de 10 días (RIC = 2,0). Los pacientes realizaron una media de 2,8 (DE = 1,2) ecografías, 1,3 (DE = 0,9) TC abdómino-pélvicos, 0,8 (DE = 1,0) RM y 0,2 (DE = 0,4) CPRE. El coste medio de cada reingreso por paciente, incluyendo la estancia hospitalaria (143,0 &#128;/día), en el servicio de Urgencias (332,31 &#128;) y las pruebas realizadas, fue de 2.381,70 &#128;/paciente. Conclusiones: la no realización de colecistectomía en las 2 semanas posteriores a un primer episodio de PABE leve o colecistitis contribuye a los reingresos por pancreatitis recurrentes con los consecuentes gastos evitables asociados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;108(8): 473-478, ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154730</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reingresos por pancreatitis aguda biliar edematosa en pacientes sin colecistectomía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24012^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24012^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10553^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16648^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10553^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
