<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72981</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of knowledge I: university, specializaed training and continuing education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The activity developed by professionals anduniversity teachers is essential to establish the pathways thatcoordinate the health care and university system. The ClinicalManagement Units (CMU) should promote the participationof the professional in the areas of care, management, teachingand investigator.In the University of Seville, eight professors who are specializedin Physical and Rehabilitation Medicine Principles(PRMP) teach the subjects of (PRMP) link to the area ofknowledge of Radiology and Physical Medicine is given by.One of the maximum concerns of the professionals dedicatedto the PRMP is the training of new specialists. The CMUof rehabilitation performs its teaching activities through thedevelopment of a tutelary program for the residents, with some specific contents on theoretical training (clinical sessiontype Critical Appraisal Topics (CAT), classical sessions and be agraphical ones) unpractical training (manipulations).The continuing education is an active and permanentteaching and learning process aimed at updating and improvingknowledge, skills and attitudes of the health care professionals.The CMU of Rehabilitation, through the TeachingCommittee, organizes and gives yearly courses on continuingeducation with 13 teaching hours contributing to the spreadingand knowledge of our specialty.We consider that the CMU within the teaching and traininglevel provides us with the necessary tools to improveknowledge and the quality of the training. This unit providesincentives for the participation in university teaching, elaborationof doctorate theses, contribution to specialized andcontinuing education. Publications in impact journals and investigationare also supported(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Lozano, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Obrero, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen.&#151;La actividad desarrollada por profesionalesy docentes universitarios es primordial para establecer loscauces que coordinen el sistema sanitario y universitario. Lasunidades de gestión clínica (UGC) deben promover la participacióndel profesional en el ámbito asistencial, de gestión,docente e investigador.En la Universidad de Sevilla, la asignatura de principios demedicina física y rehabilitación (MEFYR), vinculada al áreade conocimiento de radiología y medicina física, es impartidapor 8 profesores especialistas en MEFYR.Una de las máximas preocupaciones de los facultativosdedicados a la MEFYR es la formación de nuevos especialistas.La UGC de Rehabilitación lleva a cabo su actividad docentemediante el desarrollo de un programa tutelado paralos residentes, con unos contenidos específicos de formaciónteóricos (sesión clínica tipo Critical Apraisal Topics [CAT], sesionesclásicas y bibliográficas) y prácticos (manipulaciones).La formación continuada es un proceso de enseñanza yaprendizaje activo y permanente destinado a actualizar y mejorarlos conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes de los profesionalessanitarios. La UGC de Rehabilitación, a través de laComisión de Docencia, organiza e imparte cursos anuales deformación continuada de 30 horas lectivas, contribuyendo ala difusión y conocimiento de nuestra especialidad.Consideramos que las UGC, en el plano docente y formativo,nos proporcionan las herramientas necesarias para mejorarel conocimiento y la calidad de la formación. Desdeestas unidades se incentiva: participar en la docencia universitaria,elaborar tesis doctorales y contribuir a la formaciónespecializada y continuada. Se promueven las publicacionesen revistas de impacto y la investigación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);43(3): 106-110, may.-jun.2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72981</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión del conocimiento I: formación universitaria, especializada y formación continuada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4563^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
