<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156841</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endodontic retreatment of an internal root resorption associated with a lateral canal</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Internal root re-absorption (IRR) is a pathology characterized by the destruction of the root canal walls generating a shape of «blister». It is associated with the invasion of the pulp of the tooth, due to the effect of physical, chemical and / or bacterial causes which stimulate clastic activity. Endodontic treatment is presented as the best solution to stop this re-absorption. A clinical case of retrograde root canal re-treatment is reported, where the IRR is associated with the presence of a lateral canal with concomitant periradicular radiolucency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abal Rodríguez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La reabsorción radicular interna (RRI) es una patología que se caracteriza por la destrucción de las paredes del conducto radicular generando una forma de «ampolla». Está asociada a una afección pulpar, por el efecto de causas físicas, químicas y/o bacterianas que estimulan la actividad clástica. El tratamiento endodóntico se presenta como la solución óptima para detener dicha reabsorción. A continuación se muestra un caso clínico de retratamiento ortógrado, donde la RRI está asociada a la presencia de un conducto lateral, concomitante con una radiolucidez perirradicular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);34(1): 23-31, ene.-mar. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156841</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retratamiento endodóntico de una reabsorción radicular interna asociada a un conducto lateral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23439^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12766^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6322^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6322^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33109^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33109^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12766^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12766^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12766^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33109^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32866^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33109^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
