<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150064</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anticipation speed improvement designed as a time series</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the present study, a single case experiment has been designed in order to study the effectiveness of a visual training treatment in anticipation speed improvement. It has been used an A-B-A design, which consists on three phases: the first one of base line (A), the second one of treatment (B) and the third one of treatment removal (A). The dependent variable, which is measured through time, is anticipation speed; the independent variable is the presence or absence of visual training. After choosing an adequate subject, the data taking through time was made, yielding a time series that was then analysed using different techniques (visual analysis, classical statistical analysis, time series analysis). In every case, treatment effectiveness was found (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Uriel, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Jiménez, M Visitación</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo se ha diseñado un experimento de sujeto único para estudiar la eficacia de un tratamiento de entrenamiento visual en la mejora de la velocidad de anticipación. El diseño utilizado es del tipo A-B-A, es decir, que consta de tres fases: una primera de línea base (A), una segunda de tratamiento (B) y una tercera de reversión (A nuevamente). La variable dependiente, medida a lo largo del tiempo, es la velocidad de anticipación; la variable independiente es la presencia o ausencia de entrenamiento visual. Tras elegir un sujeto adecuado, se procedió a la toma de datos a lo largo del tiempo, obteniéndose como resultado una serie temporal que fue analizada utilizando diferentes técnicas (análisis visual, análisis estadístico clásico, análisis de series temporales), encontrándose en todos los casos eficacia del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);12(supl.2): 267-270, 2000. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150064</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora de la velocidad de anticipación mediante un tratamiento de entrenamiento visual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12364^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15186^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54300</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
