<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92530</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ossiculoplasty with titanium prosthesis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The goal of this study was to make a review of the patients who underwent ossicular chain reconstruction with titanium prosthesis during an eight-year period in our Department. Methods: A retrospective study was made on the ossiculoplasty cases over a period of eight years in a Public Hospital District. The information was extracted by clinical process consultation. Between 1999 and 2008, 124 ossiculoplasties using Kurz® titanium prosthesis for chronic otitis media were performed (78 partial ossicular chain reconstructions and 46 total ossicular chain reconstructions). The single stage, staged and revision ossicular chain reconstruction were included in the analysis. All patients had a minimum of 6 month postoperative follow up (mean 3 years and 4 months). Comparisons of preoperative and postoperative pure tone averages were performed. Air-bone gap and implant extrusion rates were measured. The success of the reconstruction was defined as a postoperative air-bone gap (ABG) of 20 dB or better. Results: Successful ossiculoplasty was obtained in 73,1% of partial ossicular reconstruction reconstructions and 30,4% of total ossicular chain reconstructions (P&lt;0.05). The postoperative pure-tone average air-bone gaps was 16 dB in partial reconstructions and 26,7 dB in total reconstructions (P&lt;0.05). There were five cases of prosthesis extrusion. Conclusions: The majority of the ossiculoplasties improved satisfactorily the hearing status. There was no difference in hearing results in one-stage and two-stage partial ossicular chain reconstruction, but there were better hearing results in the cases of two-stage total ossicular chain reconstruction (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Helder</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Certal, Victor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amorim, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carvalho, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martins, Joao</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Revisión de los pacientes sometidos a una reconstrucción de la cadena osicular con prótesis de titanio durante un período de ocho años en nuestro Servicio. Métodos: Hemos revisado retrospectivamente las osiculoplastias realizadas durante un período de ocho años en un hospital público de distrito. La información se ha obtenido mediante consulta del proceso clínico. Entre 1999 y 2008, se realizaran 124 osiculoplastias usando la prótesis de titanio de Kurz® en casos de otitis media crónica (78 reconstrucciones parciales y 46 reconstrucciones totales de la cadena osicular). Se incluyeron en el análisis las reconstrucciones en un solo tiempo y dos tiempos quirúrgicos, así como las cirugías de revisión. Todos los pacientes tuvieron un seguimiento mínimo posquirúrgico de 6 meses (un promedio de 3 años y 4 meses). Se realizaron comparaciones del promedio de tonos puros óseo y aéreo pre y posquirúrgico. Se midieron los porcentajes de la brecha aérea-ósea y los casos de extrusión de la prótesis. Utilizamos como criterio de éxito la brecha aérea-ósea inferior o igual a 20 dB. Resultados: Se lograron osiculoplastias con éxito en el 73,1% de las reconstrucciones osiculares parciales y en el 30,4% de las reconstrucciones osiculares totales (p&lt;0,05). El promedio de la brecha aérea-ósea posquirúrgica fue de 16 dB en las reconstrucciones parciales y de 26,7 dB en las reconstrucciones totales (p&lt;0,05). Se produjeron cinco casos de extrusión de la prótesis. Conclusiones: La mayoría de las osiculoplastias mejoró satisfactoriamente la audición. No se produjo diferencia alguna en los resultados audiométricos de la reconstrucción de la cadena osicular parcial entre uno o dos tiempos quirúrgicos, aunque se obtuvieron mejores resultados audiométricos en los casos de reconstrucción de la cadena osicular total en dos tiempos quirúrgicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;62(4): 295-299, jul.-ago. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osiculoplastia con prótesis de titanio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33581^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30994^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10211^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32310^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33581^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14414^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10211^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
