<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147282</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Causal attribution to cervical cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study aimed to examine the causal attribution for cervical cancer for women with and without the disease. Seventy-eight (78) users from the public healthcare system participated, which were divided into: a clinical group (CG) of women with cervical cancer and a non-clinical group (NCG) of women without cervical cancer. A Form covering sociodemographic and clinical data was utilized along with the Portuguese version of the Illness Perception Questionnaire for ill patients and healthy people. The responses were grouped into six categories: 1) Psychological attributions; 2) Behavioral risk factors; 3) Biological factors; 4) Bad luck; 5) Lack of resources; 6) Chemical agents. The CG attributed more emotional causes to the Cervical Cancer while the NCG more causes associated with behavioral risk factors. These results suggest that women with cancer may blame themselves for the illness. Distorted beliefs about the etiology of cervical cancer can harm preventative conduct and self-care practices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Armiliato, María Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carolina Peuker, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kern de Castro, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vital de Souza, Luísa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio buscó examinar la atribución de causas del cáncer cervical de mujeres con y sin la enfermedad. Participaron setenta y ocho (78) usuarias del sistema público de salud, que fueron divididas en: grupo clínico (GC) de mujeres con cáncer cervical, y grupo no-clínico (GNC) de mujeres sin cáncer cervical. Fue utilizado un cuestionario de datos sociodemográficos y clínicos y la versión en portugués del Illness Perception Questionnaire para pacientes enfermos y personas sanas. Las respuestas fueron agrupadas en seis categorías: 1) Atribuciones psicológicas; 2) Factores de riscos comportamentales; 3) Factores biológicos; 4) Mala suerte; 5) Falta de recursos; 6) Agentes químicos. El GC atribuyó más causas emocionales al cáncer cervical, mientras el GNC atribuyó más causas asociadas a factores de risco comportamentales. Los resultados sugieren que mujeres con cáncer pueden culparse a sí mismas por la enfermedad. Creencias equivocadas sobre la etiología del cáncer cervical pueden perjudicar conductas de prevención y prácticas de autocuidado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);12(2/3): 249-257, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147282</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atribución causal del cáncer cervical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13031^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
