<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61214</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Scientific production of multiple sclerosis and its evolution in the last decade</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The purpose of this study is to relate scientific production on Multiple Sclerosiswith the evolution of knowledge on this disease and to verify the impact caused by MultipleSclerosis on the society in the years of greatest scientific product.Material and method: To do so, we selected three data bases, following time and spacecoverage criteria, and searched for articles dealing with Multiple Sclerosis in the lastdecade. News on the disease was also looked for in two national newspapers of knownimportance, El Paý´s and El Mundo.Results: Different results were obtained according to the years analyzed and a period ofgreater number of articles related with the disease that coincides in scientific productionand impact on the society.Conclusions: As a main conclusion, it has been found that the articles dedicated toMultiple Sclerosis have been increasing considerably in the last decade and that there wasa significant increase in the year 2000, this coinciding with important scientific discoverieson the immune system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Díaz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Igual Camacho, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: el objetivo de este trabajo es relacionar la producción científica acerca de la esclerosis múltiple con la evolución de conocimientos sobre esta enfermedad y comprobar el impacto causado por la misma en la sociedad en los años de mayor producción científica. Material y método: para esto hemos seleccionado tres bases de datos siguiendo criterios de cobertura temporal y espacial y se han buscado artículos que trataran la esclerosis múltiple en la última década. También se buscan noticias sobre la enfermedad en dos periódicos nacionales de conocida relevancia: El País y El Mundo. Resultados: se obtienen resultados diversos según los años analizados y una época de mayor número de artículos relacionados con la enfermedad que coincide en producción científica y en impacto en la sociedad.                            Conclusiones: como conclusión principal se extrae que los artículos dedicados a la esclerosis múltiple han ido aumentando considerablemente en la última década y que existe un aumento destacable en el año 2000, coincidiendo con importantes descubrimientos científicos sobre el sistema inmunológico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);30(6): 262-267, nov.-dic. 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Producción científica de esclerosis múltiple y su evolución en la última década</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50131</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50163</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50089</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
