<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119713</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pneumonia nosocomial and multiresistances in adult in a tertiary referral hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine the incidence and etiology of Nosocomial pneumonia (NP) in adult ICU of Reina Sofia University Hospital (RSUH) of Córdoba. Methodology. The Department of Preventive Medicine of RSUH conducted a prospective cohort study for admitted patients at adults&#146; ICU from 2006 to 2009. The following incidence rates were calculated: accumulated incidence (AI) rate of patients with NP and incidence density of pneumonia associated with mechanical ventilation. We conducted a descriptive statistical analysis with calculation of the frequencies. Results. There were registered 233 patients with NP (AI of NP of admitted patients 5.3/100). About 96.6% of patients with NP were previously subjected to mechanical ventilation (MV). The incidence rate of NP associated MV was 15.7/1000 days of ventilation. Culture was requested to all cases with NP. The most frequent microorganism of NP was Acinetobacter spp. (41.7% of cultures) followed by P.aeruginosa (8%). S.aureus and C.albicans were isolated in 7% of cultures. About 40% of NP were caused by multidrug-resistant microorganisms, like A.baumannii (82.6%) followed by methicillin resistant S. aureus (9.7%). Also we noted the emergence of Stenothropomonas maltophilia (3.9%). Conclusion. Incidence rates of NP in the ICU have declined in the last decade, although our rates are still higher than the reported in other studies. The microorganisms most frequently involved in NP were gram negative, of which the most frequent was A.baumannii. Nearly all isolated microorganisms were multidrug-resistant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farouk Allam, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Crehuet Navajas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán Herrador, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Molina, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la incidencia y etiología de la Neumonía Nosocomial (NN) en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI) de adultos del Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía (HURS) de Córdoba. Metodología. El Servicio de Medicina Preventiva del HURS elaboró un estudio epidemiológico observacional de cohortes prospectivo de los pacientes ingresados en la UCI de adultos entre 2006 y 2009. Se calcularon las siguientes medidas de incidencia: Incidencia Acumulada (IA) de pacientes infectados con NN, IA de neumonías y densidad de incidencia de neumonías asociadas a ventilación mecánica. Se procedió a realizar una estadística descriptiva con cálculos de frecuencias. Resultados. Hubo 233 pacientes con NN (IA de pacientes con  NN=5,3/100 pacientes ingresados). El 96,6% de los pacientes con NN habían estado sometidos a ventilación mecánica (VM)previa. La tasa de incidencia de NN asociada VM fue de 15,7/1000 días de ventilación. Se solicitaron cultivos en todas las  NN. El microorganismo más frecuente causante de NN fue Acinetobacter spp. (41,7% de los aislamientos), seguido de P.aeruginosa (8%), S. aureus y C. albicans, ambos aislados en un 7,1% de los cultivos. El 40% de las NN fueron provocadas por microorganismos multirresistentes, destacando el A. baumannii (82,6%) seguido de S. aureus meticilin resistente (9,7%). Destaca la emergencia de Stenothropomonas maltophilia (3,9%). Conclusión. Las cifras de incidencia de NN en la UCI han disminuido en la última década, pero siguen siendo superiores a las de otros estudios. Los microorganismos más frecuentemente involucrados en la neumonía han sido los gramnegativos, y de ellos en primer lugar A. baumannii. Prácticamente la totalidad de los aislamientos de este microorganismo fueron multirresistentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;17(1): 7-12, ene.-mar. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119713</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía nosocomial y mutirresistencias en una unidad de cuidados intensivos de adultos de un hospital de tercer nivel</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
