<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137426</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The use of intrapartum fetal monitoring in low-risk pregnancies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Intrapartum fetal monitoring is necessary to ensure that the fetus is not exposed to harm. There are a number of techniques for the auscultation of the fetal heartbeat, including the Pinard stethoscope, the Sonicaid system and electronic monitoring. The purpose of this review of the literature was to examine the latest scientific evidence on the use of fetal monitoring during labor, focusing on continuous fetal monitoring and  intermittent fetal  monitoring. The reports found agree in that continuous intrapartum fetal monitoring in low-risk pregnancies is associated with an increase in the rate of cesarean sections and instrumented deliveries. On the other hand, there is no evidence of a decrease in neonatal admissions or changes in the results of the Apgar Score. Thus,  intermittent fetal monitoring is the technique of choice in low-risk pregnancies and should be performed in accordance with established, evidence-based guidelines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La monitorización fetal durante el parto es necesaria para asegurar el bienestar fetal. Para auscultar el latido fetal pueden utilizarse diferentes métodos, como el estetoscopio de Pinard, el Sonicaid y la monitorización electrónica. El propósito de esta revisión bibliográfica es examinar la evidencia científica más reciente sobre el uso de la monitorización fetal durante el parto: monitorización fetal continua frente la monitorización fetal intermitente. Los trabajos encontrados coinciden en señalar que la monitorización fetal continua en gestantes de bajo riesgo durante el parto está asociada a un aumento significativo de la tasa de cesáreas y de partos instrumentados. Por otra parte, no se ha demostrado una disminución en las admisiones neonatales ni en los resultados del test de Apgar. Por tanto, la monitorización fetal de elección en gestantes de bajo riesgo es la monitorización intermitente, y debe realizarse siguiendo unas pautas previamente establecidas y basadas en la evidencia científica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;9(2): 5-11, abr.-jun. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137426</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El uso de la monitorización fetal durante el parto en gestantes de bajo riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5432^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9514</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5432^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23574^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
