<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168562</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nosocomial fever phobia: an infectious fear</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In 1980, Schmitt was the first to coin the term "fever phobia" to describe parents&#146; unrealistic fears about fever. More than 35 years later, this unfounded fear remains. A survey is conducted in Spain to the workers of four public hospitals. Knowledge about fever in children is analyzed, being the main aim of the study. Patients and methods: A descriptive, cross-sectional and multicenter study was conducted from 15th September 2015 to 15th October 2015. 4,830 anonymous surveys were sent by e-mail. A sample size of 450 replies was estimated as sufficient, with a miscalculation &lt;4.4% and a confidence interval of 95% (50% heterogeneity). SPSS v22.0 was used for statistical data analysis. Results: Out of 462 responses were received. Seventy five per cent were women, 56% were under 35 years old, 81% were healthcare professionals and 60% were parents. Results concerning fever knowledge were: 83% affirm that physical methods should be used (not recommended), 60% think that seizures could be prevented with early treatment of fever (false), 56% support that fever should always be treated, even if the child is healthy (wrong) and 41% encourage that antipyretics should be alternated (incorrect). Eighty six per cent of the workers recognized that the fever phobia exists. There are significant differences in responses depending on healthcare and non-healthcare professionals, on being parents or not, and even on gender. Conclusions: A significant percentage of hospital workers, including doctors and pediatricians, are unaware of the existing recommendations on fever in children. This ignorance favors the persistence of fever-phobia, an infectious fear that leads to unnecessary treatments. Adequate transmission of information to families is needed, but every effort will be arduous while healthcare professionals do not believe their own recommendations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Montalvo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carabaño Aguado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falomir Carrasco, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En 1980, Schmitt introdujo el término «fiebre-fobia» para referirse al miedo injustificado que los padres presentaban ante la fiebre de los niños. Más de 35 años después, el temor infundado persiste. El objetivo principal de este trabajo era realizar una encuesta a los trabajadores de cuatro hospitales públicos y analizar el grado de conocimiento sobre la fiebre en niños. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio descriptivo, transversal y multicéntrico. Se enviaron 4.830 encuestas anónimas por correo electrónico a los participantes, entre el 15 de septiembre y el 15 de octubre de 2015. Se llevó a cabo un análisis estadístico mediante el programa SPSS v22.0. Se estimó como suficiente un tamaño muestral de 450 respuestas, con un error &lt;4,4% y un intervalo de confianza del 95% (heterogeneidad del 50%).  Resultados: Se obtuvieron 462 respuestas de los participantes. Un 75% eran mujeres, un 56% tenían menos de 35 años, un 81% eran profesionales sanitarios y un 60% tenían hijos. Respecto al conocimiento sobre la fiebre, un 83% cree que deben usarse las medidas físicas (no recomendado), un 60% piensa que el tratamiento precoz previene las convulsiones (falso), un 56% considera que siempre se debe tratar aunque el niño se encuentre bien (erróneo) y un 41% cree que se deben combinar antitérmicos (incorrecto). Un 86% de los encuestados reconoce que la fiebre-fobia existe. Hay diferencias significativas en los resultados entre sanitarios y no sanitarios, entre encuestados con hijos y sin hijos, e incluso entre sexos. Conclusiones: Un importante porcentaje de los trabajadores hospitalarios, médicos y pediatras incluidos, desconocen las actuales recomendaciones sobre la fiebre en niños. Este desconocimiento favorece la persistencia de la fiebre-fobia, un miedo contagioso que da lugar a tratamientos innecesarios. Se requiere una adecuada transmisión de la información a las familias, pero cualquier esfuerzo será ímprobo mientras los sanitarios no nos creamos nuestras propias recomendaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;75(9/10): 88-95, sept.-oct. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168562</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fiebre-fobia nosocomial: un miedo contagioso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5444^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33125^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2700^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
