<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106897</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How to write Clinical Case Studies in Nursing using the NANDA, NOC, NIC taxonomies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nursing professionals use the nursing process as well as standard languages as working tools. As a result of this, the number of case studies published in scientific publications has increased considerably. The aim of this paper is to suggest a number of proposals which might facilitate the writing process, as well as the development of a certain structure for clinical case studies based on Nursing taxonomies. Furthermore all sections that should be included in such a study are reviewed - title, abstract, introduction, assessment, care plan (diagnosis, planning, execution, evaluation), case management and discussion, as well as bibliography-so that all phases in the nursing process are recorded with the above mentioned taxonomies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montoya Juárez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonill de las Nieves, Candela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Fernández-Gallego, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hueso Montoro, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tirado Pedregosa, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schmidt Río-Del Valle, Jacqueline</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los profesionales de enfermería cuentan como herramienta de trabajo con el proceso enfermero y los lenguajes estandarizados, lo que ha posibilitado en éstos un aumento considerable en la publicación de casos clínicos en revistas científicas. A partir de esta situación, el presente trabajo tiene el objetivo de proponer un conjunto de sugerencias que contribuyan a la labor de redactar y fijar una estructura determinada en un caso clínico en el que se gestionen cuidados basados en el uso de las taxonomías enfermeras, contemplando cada uno de los apartados que debería de contener: desde el título, resumen, introducción, valoración, plan de cuidados (fase de diagnóstico, planificación, ejecución, evaluación), gestión del caso, discusión, hasta la bibliografía, quedando recogidas todas las fases del proceso enfermero, con la ayuda de la taxonomías antes mencionadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;20(1/2): 111-115, ene.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106897</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cómo escribir un caso clínico en Enfermería utilizando Taxonomía NANDA, NOC, NIC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54358</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
