<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050461</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High cardiovascular risk due to inadequate control of risk factors in spanish hypertensive patients seen in the spanish Primary Care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cardiovascular diseases are the main cause of morbidity-mortality in Spain. Hypertension and the other cardiovascular factors are important in the pathophysiological basis of this fact. Control of the main risk factors in treated hypertensives was evaluated in this study. Patients and methods. Multicenter study in hypertensive patients treated in Primary Care. Blood pressure, cardiovascular risk factors as well as registered target organ damage and clinical diseases were measured. Finally, global cardiovascular risk was calculated. Results. Only 17.3% of pharmacologically treated hypertensives were controlled (3.9% of diabetic patients). LDL-cholesterol control deteriorated as the patient's cardiovascular risk pattern increased (90.4% in low risk and 19.9% in high-very high risk). High levels of serum creatinine were detected in 8.3%, microalbuminuria being positive in 15.6%, with 20.8% ventricular hypertrophy. A total of 31% of the patients were diabetic, 59.8% of them having HbA1c &amp;#8805; 6.5%. Global CV risk was high very high in many subjects (65.4%) when European Society of Hypertension-European Society of Cardiology (ESH-ESC) guidelines were used. This percentage was 3.6% when the Spanish-validated Framingham score was used. Conclusions. Blood pressure control as well as main cardiovascular risk factors is poor in this population. Considering this fact plus the number of target organ damage, the global risk is high in many patients according to the European guidelines. Guidelines that do not consider target organ damage do not estimate adequately the risk of this uncontrolled population. This conclusion could explain the clinical tendency of many doctors when attending uncontrolled patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Álvarez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque Otero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martell Claros, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Eady, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las enfermedades cardiovasculares constituyen la causa principal de muerte en España. En su génesis son importantes la hipertensión y otros factores de riesgo. En este estudio se ha valorado el control de los principales componentes de riesgo en hipertensos tratados. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio multicéntrico en hipertensos de Atención Primaria. Se determinaron presiones arteriales, factores de riesgo cardiovascular, lesiones de órganos diana y patologías asociadas calculándose el riesgo cardiovascular global. Resultados. El 17,3% de los hipertensos (3,9% en diabéticos) tenían la presión arterial controlada. El control del colesterol ligado a lipoproteínas de baja densidad empeoró a medida que aumentaba el riesgo (90,4% en riesgo bajo y 19,94% en pacientes de alto/muy alto). El 8,3% tenían creatinina elevada, 15,6% microalbuminuria positiva, 20,8% hipertrofia ventricular. El 31% tenía diabetes y un 59,8% de ellos HbA1c &amp;#8805; 6,5%. Según la guía European Society of Hypertension-European Society of Cardiology (ESH-ESC) el riesgo cardiovascular era alto/muy alto en el 65,4%. Según las tablas de Framingham adaptadas a España este porcentaje era 3,6%. Conclusiones. El grado de control de presiones y otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular fue bajo. La elevada prevalencia de lesión de órgano diana determinó que el riesgo cardiovascular fuera elevado/muy elevado en la mayoría de sujetos según la guía europea, que tiene en cuenta todos estos factores. Las guías que no consideran la lesión orgánica infraestiman el riesgo de estos hipertensos deficientemente controlados y ello podría contribuir a la inercia médica ante la falta de control de los factores de riesgo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;206(10): 477-484, nov. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050461</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alto riesgo cardiovascular por el inadecuado control de los factores de riesgo de hipertensos españoles en Atención Primaria en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
