<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120762</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early complications in ostomized patients receiving or not receiving ostomy-specialized nursing care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: to compare immediate complications in ostomized patients receiving ostomy-specialized nursing care (OSC) or not receiving OSC (no OSC).Methods: a multicenter, national, prospective, quasi-experimental study was carried out to assess ostomy complications and their impact in 402 patients. Results: use of OSC resulted in a reduced proportion of patients with complications. Complications were less severe and had a shorter duration; hospital admissions were also less common and shorter; and less surgical procedures were needed. Furthermore, patients are more able to manage ostomies and require less help for their activities of daily living (ADL). Moreover, anxiety and/or depression feelings resulting from ostomie swere lower in patients receiving OSC. Finally, the number of ostomy bags per 24 hours remained constant in patients receiving OSC, whereas an increasing number of bags was used by patients not receiving OSC.C onclusions: an overall assessment of our findings supports the hypothesis on the importance of professional nursing specialists as reported in literature. Patients&#146; doubts and problems can be solved and complications can be prevented and/or treated. Thus, OSC becomes a healthcare reference for the ostomized patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernánez, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coca, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: comparar las complicaciones inmediatas de los pacientes portadores de ostomía entre enfermos que reciben atención especializada en ostomía (AEO) y entre los que no disponen de esta atención (sin AEO).Método: se realizó un estudio multicéntrico nacional, cuasi experimental y prospectivo, registrando las complicaciones por laostomía y sus implicaciones en 402 pacientes. Resultados: la intervención con AEO reduce el porcentaje de enfermos con complicaciones, siendo menos graves y de menor duración, necesitando menos ingresos hospitalarios, de menos duración y necesidad de otra intervención quirúrgica. También se desenvuelven cada vez mejor con el manejo del estoma, necesitando menos ayuda para realizar las actividades de la vida diaria (AVD). Asimismo, el sentimiento de ansiedad y/o depresión causado por el estoma fue menor en los pacientes con AEO. Por último, el número de bolsas usadas cada 24 horas por los enfermos con AEO es uniforme, en cambio los pacientes sin AEO van aumentando. Conclusiones: la valoración global de los resultados hallados permite apoyar la hipótesis de la importancia del papel de los profesionales enfermeros especializados encontrada en la literatura. La AEO se convierte en la referencia de atención sanitaria del paciente para preguntarle dudas, consultar sus problemas y prevenir y/o tratar las complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(1): 23-31, feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones tempranas en pacientes portadores de ostomías con y sin atención de Enfermería especializada en ostomía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23288^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52527</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23206^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22955^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
