<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138553</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tuberculosis screening program for undocumented immigrant teenagers using the QuantiFERON ®-TB Gold In-Tube test</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: The aim of this study was to determine the prevalence of tuberculosis infection in undocumented immigrant teenagers using a tuberculin skin test (TST) for initial screening and cuantiFERON®-TB Gold In-Tube (QFT-GIT) as a confirmatory test. Patient and method: From 2007 to 2012, under 19 year-old immigrant teenagers from 2 accommodation centers of the Basque Country (Spain) were included in the study. The TST was done in all of them and the QFT-GIT was done in selected patients with a TST &amp;#8805; 5 mm. Results: Eight hundred and forty-five immigrants were included, most of them from Africa (99.5%). Fifty-one percent of immigrants with TST &amp;#8805; 5 mm has a positive QFT-GIT. We found 2 cases of active tuberculosis (2/845: 0.24%). The concordance between TST (&amp;#8805; 10 mm) and QFT-GIT was 63%, with 57% of positive concordance cases and 96% of negative concordances. There were 246 cases with TST &amp;#8805; 10 mm (29%), with significant differences between Magrebis (21.5%) and Subsaharians (67%) (P &lt; .001). Vaccination with Calmette-Guéin bacille was an independent predictor for having a TST &amp;#8805; 10 mm (OR: 2.11; P &lt; .001) and for the discordance TST+/QFT-GIT&amp;#8722;, both for a TST &amp;#8805; 5 and a TST &amp;#8805; 10 mm (OR 2.16, 95% confidence interval [95% CI] 1.46-3.20, and OR 1.91 95% CI 1.23-2.97, respectively). The positive value of QFT-GIT increased significantly as the TST increased, with a positive association in all the cut-off points analyzed: 10-14 mm (OR 7.95, 95% CI 1.79-35.33), 15-19 mm (OR 35, 95% CI 7.93-154.52) and &amp;#8805; 20 mm (OR 91.3, 95% CI 18.20-458.11). Conclusion: Due to the high prevalence of latent tuberculosis infection in Subsaharian immigrants, we recommend implementing screening programs in this population. Using QFT-GIT, the number of candidates for chemoprophylaxis was reduced to 43% compared with TST alone (&amp;#8805; 10 mm) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Antón, Ane</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Altube, Lander</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salinas, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre, Urko</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballaz, Aitor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue conocer la prevalencia de la infección tuberculosa en inmigrantes adolescentes indocumentados utilizando una estrategia con la prueba de la tuberculina (PT) para el cribado inicial y el QuantiFERON®-TB Gold In-Tube (QFT-GIT) como prueba confirmativa. Pacientes y método:  Se incluyeron inmigrantes adolescentes recién llegados a 2 centros de alojamiento del País Vasco (España) entre los años 2007 y 2012. La PT se aplicó en todos los participantes, y el QFT-GIT, selectivamente en los reactores con una PT &amp;#8805; 5 mm. Resultados: Completaron el estudio 845 inmigrantes, mayoritariamente africanos (99,5%). Un 51% de los inmigrantes con una PT &amp;#8805; 5 mm fue QFT-GIT positivo, que corresponde el 17% de toda la muestra. Se encontraron 2 casos con tuberculosis activa (2/845: 0,24%). La concordancia entre la PT (&amp;#8805; 10 mm) y el QFT-GIT fue del 63%, con un 57% de resultados concordantes positivos y un 96% de concordantes negativos. Hubo 246 casos con PT &amp;#8805; 10 mm (29%), con diferencias significativas entre magrebíes (21,5%) y subsaharianos (67%) (p &lt; 0,001). La vacunación con el bacilo Calmette-Guérin fue un predictor independiente de tener una PT &amp;#8805; 10 mm (odds ratio [OR] 2,11, p &lt; 0,001) y de la discordancia PT+/QFT-GIT&amp;#8722;, tanto para una PT &amp;#8805; 5 como para una PT &amp;#8805; 10 mm (OR 2,16, intervalo de confianza del 95% [IC 95%] 1,46-3,20, y OR 1,91, IC 95% 1,23-2,97, respectivamente). La proporción de QFT-GIT positivo aumentó significativamente con el incremento de la positividad de la PT, con asociación positiva en todos los tramos analizados: 10-14 mm (OR 7,95, IC 95% 1,79-35,33), 15-19 mm (OR 35, IC 95% 7,93-154,52) y &amp;#8805; 20 mm (OR 91,3, IC 95% 18,20-458,11). Conclusión: La alta prevalencia de infección tuberculosa latente en los inmigrantes de origen subsahariano hace recomendable la implementación de programas de cribado en esta población. Utilizando el QFT-GIT se redujo en un 43% el número de candidatos a la quimioprofilaxis con arreglo a la PT (&amp;#8805; 10 mm) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);145(1): 7-13, jul. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138553</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cribado de la tuberculosis en inmigrantes adolescentes indocumentados usando el QuantiFERON ®-TB Gold In-Tube</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53483^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31671^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22710^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
