<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75785</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-8831</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Optimization of the bioactivity of pancreatic enzymes with the administration of enteric tablets of sodium bicarbonate</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the efficacy and tolerability of the administrationof acid-resistant enteric tablets of sodium bicarbonate toincrease the duodenal pH and optimize the activity of pancreaticenzymes in patients with cystic fibrosis (CF).Method. Twenty-one children (66% male) with CF were includedin the study. Median age was 11 years (range, 13-23), and meanweight was 32.24 ± 12.2 Kg (range, 13-52). Seven-mm sodium bicarbonatetablets (225 mg) were formulated with a coat dissolutionpoint of ph of 5. Stool content of amylase, lipase, chemotrypsine,fat, sugar and proteins were measured at baseline followingadministration of enzymes, and after 15 days of concomitant treatmentwith sodium bicarbonate (15 g/m2/24 hours). The diet wassimilar throughout the study period.Results. The median dose of lipase was 2,812 U (F.I.P.)/kg/24 hours(range 5,700 U-450 U) with a resulting steatorrhea of 7.79 g% (±3.28 g%). There was a negative linear correlation between lipaseadministration and steatorrhea levels (r=0.16). The stool studiesbefore (B) and after concomitant administration of sodium bicarbonate(CB) showed the following: amylase (u/l) 5,273 ± 3,825 (B)vs. 4,779 ± 3,147 (CB); lipase (u/l) 268 ± 189 (B) vs. 224 ± 167 (CB);chemotrypsine (u/l) 32 ± 33 (B) vs. 31 ± 28 (CB); fat (g%) 7.3 ± 3 (B)vs. 7.79 ± 3.28 (CB); nitrogen (g%) 1.6 ± 0.26 (B) vs. 1.7 ± 0.32 (CB);and sugar (g%) 1.71 ± 0.61 (B) vs. 1.9 ± 0.64 (CB).Conclusions. The stool content of amylase, lipase, chemotrypsineand fat showed a mild decrease in some patients after the concomitantadministration of sodium bicarbonate; however, differenceswere not statistically significant. Future studies with higher dosesof sodium bicarbonate and with coat dissolution point at pH &lt; 5should be explored(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Infante Pina, Dámaso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segarra Canton, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Albert, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tormo Carnicé, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redecillas Ferreira, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. Valorar la efectividad y tolerancia de la administraciónde comprimidos entéricos de bicarbonato sódico con cubiertade ácido resistente con el fin de aumentar el pH duodenal y optimizarla actividad de los enzimas pancreáticos.Método. Fueron incluidos 21 pacientes (66 % varones y 34 % mujeres),con una media de edad de 11 años (intervalo 13-23) y un pesomedio de 32,24 ± 12,2 Kg (intervalo 13-52). Se formularon comprimidosentéricos de bicarbonato sódico de 225 mg con un diámetrode 7 mm con una disgregación de la envoltura a pH 5. Fueron determinadosen estado basal con solo enzimas (B) y tras 15 días detratamiento con bicarbonato (15 g/m2/24 h) repartido con los enzimasa las dosis habituales (CB) los siguientes parámetros en heces:amilasa, lipasa, quimotripsina, grasa, azúcar y proteínas. La dietafue similar durante todo el estudio.Resultados. Las dosis de lipasa administrada a nuestros pacientesmostró una media de 2.812 U (F.I.P)/kg/24 h (rango 5.700 U- 450 U),lo cual conlleva una media de esteatorrea de 7,79 g% (DE 3,28 g%).El estudio estadístico de correlación linear entre el aporte de lipasay los niveles de esteatorrea presentó una correlación negativa (r =0.16). Los resultados en heces mostraron: amilasa u/l (B) 5.273 ±3.825 vs 4.779 ± 3.147 (CB), lipasa u/l 268 ± 189 (B) vs 224 ± 167 (CB);quimotripsina u/l 32 ± 33 (B) vs 31 ± 28 (CB), grasa g% 7,3 ± 3 (B) vs7,79 ± 3,28 (CB), nitrógeno g % 1,6 ± 0,26 (B) vs 1,7 ± 0,32 (CB) y azúcarg% 1,71 ± 0,61 (B) vs 1,9 ± 0,64 (CB).Conclusiones. La determinación de amilasa, lipasa, quimotripsina ygrasa en heces mostraron un ligero descenso en algunos pacientes,pero sin alcanzar diferencia significativa como grupo. Futuros estudioscon un aumento de la dosis de bicarbonato y disgregación dela envoltura a un pH &lt; 5 deberán ser efectuados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. catalan;69(4): 188-192, jul.-ago. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75785</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Optimización de la actividad de las enzimas pancreáticos con comprimidos entéricos de bicarbonato sódico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31036^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31036^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8224^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4420</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4871^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31036^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12509^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1664^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
