<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77550</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cross-cultural adaptation and validation of a Spanish version of a specific instrument to measure health-related quality of life in patients with ankylosing spondylitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To make a cross-cultural adaptation and validation of a version in Spanish of the Ankylosing Spondylitis Quality of Life Questionnaire (ASQoL) for assessing the health-related quality of life (HRQL) of patients with Ankylosing Spondylitis (AS). Patients and methods: A cross-sectional study with test-retest. AS patients (modified New York criteria) were included. Cross-cultural adaptation was done. Construct validity was assessed comparing the ASQoL scores with the SF-36 and EuroQol scores and diseaserelated variables. Internal consistency and reliability (test-retest) were assessed. Feasibility was assessed by the time spent to complete the questionnaire and the number of items without answer. Spearman correlation coefficient, Mann-Whitney U test, and Kruskal-Wallis test were used in the statistical analysis. Cronbach´alpha coefficient and statistic kappa were used for assessing internal consistency and reliability. Results: Fifty-four patients, 37 males (68.5%), with age (mean±SD) 40.5 ± 10.5 years, were included. The ASQoL global score was 6.8 ± 4.7 (median, 7; range, 0-17). The ASQoL scores had high correlations with physical (rho = 0.79) and mental (0.69) SF-36 components, the SF-36 domains pain (0.82), vitality (0.75), and role-physical (0.68), and the most of the disease-related variables. The ASQoL scores were significantly different between patients with different response levels in the health profile of the EuroQol. The Cronbach´alpha coefficient was 0.86. The reliability had kappa = 1 in 12 items and rho = 0.98. The time spent to complete the ASQoL was from 2 to 5 minutes and there only was a missing answer in one patient. Conclusion: The Spanish ASQoL is valid, reliable, and feasible instrument for assessing the HRQL of the AS patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toyos, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Sarabia, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Cruz, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Antequera, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariza-Ariza, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Adaptación transcultural y validación de la versión en español del Ankylosing Spondylitis Quality of Life Questionnaire (ASQoL). Pacientes y métodos: Estudio transversal con prueba testretest. Se incluyeron pacientes con espondilitis anquilosante (EA). Se realizó adaptación transcultural de la versión original del ASQoL mediante traducción y retrotraducción. Se estudiaron validez de constructo, consistencia interna, reproducibilidad y factibilidad. El análisis estadístico se realizó con el coeficiente de correlación de Spearman, la pruebas U de Mann- Whitney y Kruskal-Wallis, el coeficiente alfa de Cronbach y el estadístico kappa. Resultados: Se incluyeron 54 pacientes, 37 (68,5%) varones, con edad (promedio ± DE) 40,5 ± 10,5 años. El ASQoL tuvo una puntuación de 6,8 ± 4,7 (mediana, 7; intervalo, 0-17) y presentó correlaciones altas con los componentes globales físico (rho = 0,79) y mental (0,69) del SF-36 y con los dominios de dolor (0,82), vitalidad (0,75) y rol físico (0,68), así como con la mayoría de variables representativas de la EA. Las puntuaciones del ASQoL fueron significativamente diferentes entre los pacientes con distintos niveles de respuesta en el perfil de salud del EuroQol. El ASQoL tuvo un coeficiente alfa de Cronbach de 0,86. La prueba test-retest se realizó en 10 pacientes con un intervalo de 24 h y tuvo una kappa entre 1 (12 preguntas) y 0,57 (1 pregunta) con rho de 0,98 para las puntuaciones globales. El tiempo empleado osciló entre 2 y 5 min. Conclusiones: La versión en español del ASQoL es válida, fiable y factible de aplicar en nuestro medio para medir la calidad de vida de los pacientes con EA(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);2(2): 64-69, mar.-abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77550</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación transcultural y validación de una versión en español de un instrumento específico para medir calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en pacientes con espondilitis anquilosante: el ASQoL</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13552^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
