<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106434</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing management of intraoperative malignant hyperthermia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Malignant hyperthermia (MH) is a musculoskeletal disorder potentially fatal disease that can occur in response to inhalation of certain anesthetics and muscle relaxants (ICD-10).In Spain, according to the Instituto Carlos III, the incidence of MH reactions ranges between 1:5,000 and 1:50,000-100,000 anesthesia procedures. However, the prevalence of genetic abnormalities that predispose to suffer MH can be as high as 1 in 3,000 individuals.MH syndrome is fatal if untreated, but thanks to the great advances in the understanding of the clinical manifestations and pathophysiology, MH mortality was reduced to less than 5% in 2007.The purpose of this paper is to update the knowledge on MH and presenta response protocol so that the nurse is prepared: to recognize the risk factors and triggers of this condition, to detect signs and symptoms so that they can addressed immediately ,and to know how to prepare and how the method of administration of specific medication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz González, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zorrilla Varela, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrauri Cantero, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cavada Fernández, Melissa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez de Rozas Astigarraga, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Luis, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipertermia maligna (HM) es un trastorno músculo-esquelético potencialmente mortal, que se puede producir como respuesta a la inhalación de ciertos anestésicos y relajantes musculares (CIE-10).En España, según datos del Instituto Carlos III, la incidencia de reacciones de HM oscila entre 1:5.000 y 1:50.000-100.000 anestesias. Sin embargo, la prevalencia de las anomalías genéticas que predisponen a padecerla puede ser tan elevada como 1 de cada 3.000 individuos. El síndrome de HM es mortal si no se trata, pero gracias a los grandes avances en la comprensión de las manifestaciones clínicas y la fisiopatología, la mortalidad por HM se ha reducido a menos del 5% en 2007.El propósito de este trabajo es actualizar los conocimientos sobre la HM y presentar un protocolo de actuación, de manera que la enfermera esté preparada para reconocer los factores de riesgo y desencadenantes de esta situación; detectar signos y síntomas para poder combatirlos de forma inmediata y conocer la forma de preparación y el modo de administración de la medicación específica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;15(9): 63-68, nov. 2012. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106434</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actuación intraoperatoria ante la hipertermia maligna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9657^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8478^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
