<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60034</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of some psychometric properties of the Luria-Initial battery in a sample of Potosino school children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In Mexico, several previous attemptshave been made to obtain standardized data on childrenof different ages in different neuropsychological evaluationtests. These studies have not been sufficient to obtainstandardized data representative of the cultural diversitycharacteristic of the Mexican Republic and specificallyaimed at persons who have some type of cognitive dysfunction.Objectives: This investigation forms a part of the investigationalline whose purpose is to contribute to the validationprocess of the Initial-Luria neuropsychological batteryin the Mexican population. In these articles, we are goingto focus on analyzing some psychometric properties of theLuria-Initial battery.Sample: The sample generating the data include 100boys and girls of pre-school and first grade, whose agesranged from four to six years, of both genders.de Creative CommonsInstruments: Two were applied instruments: Child NeuropsychologicalBattery (Luria-Initial) and Raven ProgressiveMatrices Test.Results: The first step in the analysis was to obtain theinternal and global consistency of the Luria-Initial batteryusing Cronbach's Alpha Coefficient, obtaining a value of0.861, slightly inferior to that of that obtained in the validationprocedure. Regarding the analyses of the internalstructure of the Luria-Initial battery, four factors wereobtained that accounted for 68.512% of the total variance.Conclusions: All the Luria-Initial battery analyzed insubtests and areas has been shown to have good internalconsistence. In regards to the factorial structure, they coincidein number, and disagree in regards to their compositionwith those obtained with the standardized sample (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Isis Orozco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bausela Herreras, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En México, se han realizado algunos intentosprevios para obtener datos normativos de niños de diversasedades en diversas pruebas de evaluación neuropsicológicaestos estudios no han sido suficientes para disponerde datos normativos representativos de la diversidad culturalcaracterística de la Republica Mexicana, y en concretodirigido a personas que presentan algún tipo de afectacióncognitiva.Objetivos: Esta investigación forma parte de la línea deinvestigación que tiene como finalidad contribuir al procesode validación de la batería neuropsicológica Luria- Inicialen población mexicana. En este artículos nos vamos acentrar en analizar algunas propiedades psicométricas dela batería Luria-Inicial.Muestra: La muestra generadora de datos son 100niños/as de preescolar y primer grado de primaria, con edadescomprendidas entre los 4 y 6 años, de ambos sexos.Instrumentos: Dos fueron los instrumentos aplicados:Batería Neuropsicología Infantil (Luria-Inicial) y el Test deMatrices Progresivas de Raven.Resultados: El primer paso en el análisis fue obtenerla consistencia interna global de la batería Luria-Inicial a travésdel Coeficiente Alfa de Cronbach, obteniéndose un valorde 0,861, ligeramente inferior al obtenido en el proceso devalidación. Respecto al análisis de la estructura interna dela batería Luria-Inicial se obtuvieron cuatro factores queexplican el 68,521% de la varianza total.Conclusiones: La batería Luria-Inicial ha mostrado tenerbuena consistencia interna en su totalidad analizada en subtestsy áreas. Por lo que se refiere a la estructura factorial,coinciden en número, discrepan en cuanto a su composicióncon los obtenidos con la muestra normalizada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;49(207): 35-40, ene.-mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60034</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de algunas propiedades psicométricas de la batería Luria-Inicial en una muestra de escolares potosinos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8358^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
