<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131706</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma in childhood: A report of 2 cases report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pheochromocytomas and paragangliomas are rare neuroendocrine tumors in children and most of them are sporadic. However, they represent the most common endocrine tumor in childhood, and hereditary tumor syndromes are most relevant in these age. Advances in genetic, biochemistry and imaging techniques have revised the management of these tumors; thus A biochemical study should be always initiated once the clinical diagnosis is suspected, followed by imaging and molecular studies, particularly in the context of known familial disease.  The diagnostic and therapeutic features are reviewed after the presentation of two clinicalcases, where the second one is a patient with type 1 Neurofibromatosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Temprano, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera Gorostidi, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Garicano, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zakirian Denis, S. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagaseta de Ilúrdoz Uranga, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Justo Ranera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los feocromocitomas y los paragangliomas son tumores neuroendocrinos infrecuentes en pediatría; sin embargo, estos representan el tumor endocrino más frecuente en la infancia. La mayoría son esporádicos, cobrando mayor relevancia los síndromes familiares en edad pediátrica. Los avances en el campo de la genética, en bioquímica y en técnicas de imagen han adaptado el manejo de estos tumores; de modo que el estudio bioquímico debe comenzarse ante todo diagnóstico clínico de sospecha, seguido del estudio por imagen y molecular, más aún ante la existencia de un síndrome familiar conocido. Revisamos aspectos clínicos, diagnósticos y terapéuticos a propósito de 2 casos, presentando el segundo paciente antecedentes de neurofibromatosis tipo 1 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): e175-e180, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131706</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Feocromocitoma y paraganglioma en la infancia: a propósito de 2 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30295^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10868^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6412^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
