<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126125</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cooperative Learning in 21st Century</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The 21st century brings four important challenges in which cooperation plays a central role: (1) a rapidly increasing global interdependence that will result in increas­ing local diversity as well as more frequent and intense conflicts, (2) the increasing number of democracies throughout the world, (3) the need for creative entrepreneurs, and (4) the growing importance of interpersonal relationships that affect the development of personal identity. The tools for meeting these challenges include cooperative learning.  In this article the nature of cooperative learning will be reviewed, the underlying theory of social interdependence will be discussed, and the results of the research on cooperative learning will be briefly reviewed.  The way in which cooperative learning contributes to meeting the four challenges will then be discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Johnson, Roger T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Johnson, David W</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El siglo XXI trae consigo cuatro grandes retos en los que la cooperación juega un papel fundamental: (1) una interdependencia mundial cada vez mayor que se traducirá en el aumento de la diversidad local, así como en conflictos más frecuentes e intensos, (2) el aumento de sistemas democráticos en el mundo, (3) la necesidad de emprendedores creativos y (4) la creciente importancia de las relaciones interpersonales que afectan al desarrollo de la identidad personal. Las herramientas para responder a estos desafíos incluyen el aprendizaje cooperativo. En este artículo se revisará la naturaleza del aprendizaje cooperativo, se discutirá la teoría de la interdependencia social que subyace, y se revisarán, brevemente, los resultados de la investigación sobre el aprendizaje cooperativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(3): 841-851, sept.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aprendizaje cooperativo en el Siglo XXI</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3320</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3423</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3722</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
