<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047833</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vaccines against the human papillomavirus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Persistent infection by human papilloma virus (HPV) is considered to be the main cause of cervical cancer and other ano-genital cancers. Of more than 30 genotypes able to infect the ano-genital tract, it is estimated that, worldwide, HPV 16 and 18 cause 70% of cervical cancers and that HPV 6 and 11 cause more than 90% of genital warts. In the last few years, the morbidity and mortality and health costs associated with cervical cancer and its precursor lesions have stimulated intense research activity to achieve primary prevention of this disease through prophylactic vaccines. Animal tests demonstrated the immunogenic capacity of virus-like particles composed of self-assembled L1 proteins. Clinical trials with 2 prophylactic vaccine prototypes have demonstrated their effectiveness in the prevention of transitory and persistent incident cervical infections caused by HPV 16 and 18, as well as the cytological alterations and cervical lesions associated with these HPV types. With the imminent commercialization of the prophylactic HPV vaccine, there are high hopes for a marked reduction in the rates of cervical cancer and its precursor lesions amongst the vaccinated population within the next few years. At the same time, an intense debate has arisen on the conditions of vaccination (age, applicability, indication in men, composition according to geographic area, need for revaccination, acceptance) and its cost-effectiveness, as well as on the modification of screening conditions for cervical cancer in developed countries and the availability and accessibility of screening in the poorest countries</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castellsagué, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alba, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torné, Aureli</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección persistente por el virus del papiloma humano (VPH) se considera el principal agente causal del cáncer de cuello uterino y de otros cánceres anogenitales. De los más de 30 genotipos capaces de infectar el tracto anogenital se estima que los VPH 16 y 18 causan el 70% de los cánceres de cérvix en todo el mundo, y los VPH 6 y 11 más del 90% de las verrugas genitales. La morbimortalidad y costes sanitarios asociados con el cáncer de cérvix y sus lesiones precursoras han motivado en los últimos años una intensa investigación para conseguir una prevención primaria de dicha patología mediante vacunas profilácticas. En estudios realizados en animales se ha demostrado la capacidad inmunógena de partículas semejantes a virus (virus like particles [VLP]) constituidas por proteínas L1 autoensambladas. En ensayos clínicos realizados con 2 prototipos de vacunas profilácticas se ha demostrado su eficacia en la prevención de infecciones cervicales incidentes transitorias y persistentes causadas por los VPH 16 y 18, así como para las alteraciones citológicas y las lesiones cervicales asociadas a dichos virus. Ante la inminente comercialización de vacunas profilácticas para el VPH, se abre la esperanza de una notable reducción de las tasas de cáncer de cuello uterino y de sus lesiones precursoras entre las poblaciones vacunadas en los próximos años. Al mismo tiempo, se inicia un intenso debate sobre las condiciones de vacunación (edad, aplicabilidad, indicación en varones, composición según el área geográfica, necesidad de revacunación, aceptación), coste-eficacia, modificación de las condiciones de cribado del cáncer de cérvix en los países desarrollados y disponibilidad y accesibilidad a ellas en los países más pobres</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(7): 380-393, jul. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vacunas contra el virus del papiloma humano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23126^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35997^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7295^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d927^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10403^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2623^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24015^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
