<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051602</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How should the results of a scientific study be presented? I. The oralpresentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The results of a research study can be presented through oral communications, posters, conferences and publications, etc. The present article suggests ways in which oral communications and posters can be presented. The sequence of steps leading up to an oral presentation can be divided into writing a summary, designing the graphic material, giving the presentation and defending the results. Posters have a similar structure but this format allows complex experiments to be clearly presented and a variety of illustrations to be introduced, without the strict time constraints that apply to oral presentations. Whichever format is followed, we recommend that authors answer the following questions: what was the question studied and why?, how was it studied?, what were the results?, and what do they mean? These questions help to structure the presentation effectively (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vial, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manterola, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineda, Viviana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los resultados de una investigación se pueden mostrar a través de la presentación de comunicaciones orales, pósteres, conferencias, publicaciones, etc. En este manuscrito se proporcionan sugerencias acerca de la presentación de comunicaciones orales y pósteres.         La secuencia que lleva a la presentación de resultados de forma oral se puede dividir en elaboración del resumen, construcción del material gráfico, presentación y defensa de los resultados. La presentación de resultados mediante pósteres tiene una estructura similar, pero permite presentar experimentos complejos con claridad, introducir variedad de ilustraciones sin la limitación horaria estricta de las comunicaciones orales.  De todos modos, sea cual sea la forma en que se quiera presentar los resultados de una investigación, se recomienda que los autores respondan a los interrogantes siguientes: ¿qué problema se estudió y por qué?, ¿cómo se estudió?, ¿cuáles fueron los hallazgos? y ¿qué significan esos resultados? Esto proporcionará una estructura adecuada a la presentación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);81(1): 12-17, ene. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051602</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo presentar los resultados de una investigación científica? I. La comunicación oral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7980</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29639</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22412</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
