<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63655</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Adrenal myelolipomas are rare benign tumors comprising mature adipose tissue and diverse hematopoietic elements. These neoplasms are usually incidental findings, although bulky masses can generate abdominal pain as well as other symptoms related to compression of adjacent organs. Diagnosis is usually provided by ultrasonography or computed tomography. Asymptomatic patients with tumors with a maximum diameter of less than 6 cm can benefit from periodic surveillance, whereas local compression symptoms and size larger than 6 cm are indications for surgical treatment. We present a case of giant adrenal myelolipoma (..)  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Baena, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Bolaños, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya álvarez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavón de Paz, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martínez, Albertob</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivar Roldán, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El mielolipoma adrenal es un tumor benigno, poco frecuente, compuesto por tejido adiposo maduro y elementos hematopoyéticos diversos. Su hallazgo suele ser incidental, aunque en ocasiones pueden alcanzar gran tamaño y causar dolor abdominal y otros síntomas clínicos. La ecografía y la tomografía computarizada son herramientas útiles en su diagnóstico. Los tumores pequeños (&lt; 6 cm) y asintomáticos pueden tratarse de forma conservadora con vigilancia periódica y los &gt; 6 cm o con síntomas pueden precisar tratamiento quirúrgico. Presentamos un caso de mielolipoma adrenal gigante y a continuación se realiza una revisión de la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;55(3): 139-141, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63655</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d31289^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d318^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d313^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
