<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052736</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The importance of night tooth brushing before sleeping in the prevention of dental caries. Study on childhood population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the present study we are questioning if the three time a day tooth brushing is really essential and if it is the opposite case, what time of the day would be most important for mechanical elimination of dental plaque. For this purpose we have planed a transversal study on 214 pupils aged 6 to 12 years in the period of 2004-05 scheduled school coarse. On each of them was applied the &#147;Partial Exam type III&#148; which is recommended from International Dental Federation and which is considered as standard procedure on prevalence of dental caries study. We obtained following results: 1. Tooth brushing by night before sleeping is a favourable protection factor from dental caries, being correspondent odd-ratio adjusted on 0.339 (interval of confidence is 95% [0.159; 0.722]). 2. Consuming the sugar more than one time a day causes higher risk for dental caries apparition than one time a day consumption of sugar, being correspondent odd-ratio adjusted on 1.998 (interval of confidence is 95% [1.090;3.665]). 3. The children attending public schools have higher risk of dental caries presence than the children attending private schools being correspondent odd-ratio adjusted on 2.019 (interval of confidence is 95% [1.105;3.691]). 4. The objectives on dental caries marked from WHO are carried out on the studied population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vicente Barrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Knezevic, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra Majem, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Limiñana Cañal, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Sedano, TE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Sedano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Henández Perdomo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo nos planteamos si sería imprescindible el cepillado tres veces al día y, en caso contrario, en qué momento del día sería más importante la eliminación mecánica de la placa. Para ello, se planteó un estudio transversal correspondiente a 214 escolares de 6-12 años en el periodo comprendido en el curso 2004-5. A cada niño se le practicó el &#147;Examen parcial o tipo III&#148; recomendado por la Federación Dental Internacional, como procedimiento estándar para un estudio de prevalencia de caries. Hemos obtenido los siguientes resultados: 1. El cepillado de dientes antes de acostarse es un factor protector de la presencia de caries, siendo el correspondiente odd-ratio ajustado de 0.339 (intervalo de confianza al 95% [0.159; 0.722]). 2. El consumir azúcar más de una vez una vez al día tiene más riesgo de aparición de caries que si consumen una vez al día, siendo el correspondiente odd-ratio ajustado de 1.998 (intervalo de confianza al 95% [1.090; 3.665]). 3. Los niños que acuden a un colegio público tienen más riesgo de presentar caries que los que asisten a un colegio privado. Siendo el correspondiente odd-ratio ajustado de 2.019 (intervalo de confianza al 95% [1.105; 3.691]). 4. Se cumplen en la población estudiada los objetivos marcados sobre caries dental por la OMS para el año 2000 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;23(1): 45-50, ene.-feb .2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052736</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia del cepillado antes de acostarse en la prevención de la caries. Estudio en una población infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3781</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14489^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
