<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155060</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personality and clinical tests in Spanish for assessing juvenile offenders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The psychological assessment of offenders is the core of professional activity throughout the juvenile justice system. It ensures the adequacy of the legal and educational measures to be applied in the process. This paper reviews the main tests for psychological assessment available in Spanish, suitable for use by psychology professionals who work with young offenders in the juvenile justice services in Spanish-speaking countries. We classify these tools into three groups: a) Personological, i.e. generic tests, suitable for any professional context in psychology, b) Clinical, i.e. tests whose initial use has been limited to working with adolescents with mental health needs, and c) Forensic, tools that have been specially developed for use in the juvenile justice population. This last group is described in the second part of this article (Wenger &amp; Andres-Pueyo, 2016 b) (which appears in this same issue). The most important instruments of proven utility are presented and reviewed for each group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andres-Pueyo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wenger, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación psicológica de los adolescentes infractores es imprescindible en su recorrido por los servicios de justicia juvenil. Gracias a esta evaluación se garantiza la exigencia legal y la eficiencia de las medidas judiciales y educativas que se prescriben en estos servicios. En el presente artículo, el primero de una serie de dos, se revisan las principales pruebas de evaluación psicológica en español disponibles para profesionales de la psicología que trabajan con adolescentes infractores de los países hispanohablantes. Clasificaremos estas herramientas en tres grupos: a) Personológicas adecuadas para cualquier contexto profesional de la Psicología, b) Clínicas, cuya utilidad inicial se circunscribe al trabajo con adolescentes que presentan necesidades de salud mental y c) Forenses, aquellas desarrolladas especialmente para su uso en adolescentes atendidos en los servicios penales. Los instrumentos forenses se describen en la segunda parte de este artículo (Wenger &amp; Andres-Pueyo, 2016 b) (en este mismo número de la revista). Para cada apartado se presentan y revisan los instrumentos más importantes y de utilidad contrastada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;37(2): 89-106, jun. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155060</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tests personológicos y clínicos en español para evaluar adolescentes infractores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7773^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37692</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16925^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10747^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
