<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87818</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment adherence in Schizophrenia: Nurse practitioners consensus in mental health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Establish a Spanish Consensus on nurse care to increase therapeutic compliance in schizophrenia. Material and methods. An experts committee designed a specific questionnaire having 43 questions. The questions referred to the definition and general assessment of compliance in schizophrenia, factors involved, intervention strategies in outpatients/inpatients and management of long duration injectable antipsychotic drugs a. First, second or third line strategy values of choice were assigned according to the answers obtained for each item. The questionnaire was sent to 160 nurse practitioners. The answers were received with an online electronic system that guaranteed their confidentiality. Results and conclusions. There is maximum agreement on considering the seriousness of the compliance problem, its repercussion in relapses, the patient&#146;s course and increase in health care costs. The strategies preferred to evaluate compliance are: counting of the injectable drug administration and clinical assessment. The workgroup considers that specific intervention is necessary when the patient has already suffered several relapses due to low therapeutic compliance or when null awareness of disease is detected. The promotion of positive patient behaviours on treatment and the patient awareness development about treatment compliance importance are the nurse practitioners favourite strategies to reduce the relapses caused by poor adherence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giner, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Granada, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fornés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lluch, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sales, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Establecer un consenso español sobre cuidados de enfermería para mejorar la adherencia terapéutica en la esquizofrenia. Material y métodos. Un comité de expertos diseñó un cuestionario específico de 43 preguntas con 409 opciones. Las preguntas se referían a: definición y valoración general de la adherencia en la esquizofrenia; factores implicados; estrategias de intervención en pacientes ambulatorios y en unidades de agudos y el manejo de fármacos antipsicóticos inyectables de larga duración. Se asignaron valores de estrategia de elección, primera, segunda o tercera línea, según las respuestas obtenidas para cada ítem. Se envió el cuestionario a 215 enfermeros/as y se recibieron 160 respuestas a través de un sistema electrónico online que garantizaba su confidencialidad. Resultados y conclusiones. Existe el máximo acuerdo en considerar la gravedad del problema de la adherencia, su repercusión en las recaídas y en la evolución del paciente. Las estrategias preferidas para evaluar la adherencia son: el registro de la administración de inyectables y la impresión clínica del paciente. El grupo de trabajo considera que es preciso intervenir de manera específica cuando el paciente ha sufrido ya varias recaídas a causa del bajo cumplimiento terapéutico o se detecta una nula conciencia de enfermedad. La potenciación de las actitudes positivas hacia el tratamiento y el establecimiento de acuerdos con el paciente acerca de la importancia de tomar los fármacos son las estrategias preferidas por el personal de enfermería para reducir las recaídas por falta de adherencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;38(supl.1): 1-45, jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia al tratamiento en la esquizofrenia: Consenso de enfermería en salud mental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12005^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12005^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12005^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
