<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054120</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Food allergies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Food allergens are proteins abe to induced a specific IgE response. The characteristics of a protein determining allergenicity are not yet fully elucidated. However, it is well established that stability is a key issue in determining protein allergenicity when exposure takes place in the gastrointestinal tract. Resistence of proteins to temperature, low pH, and proteolytic enzymes attack is an attribute  of food allergens able to induce sensitization and symptoms upon oral exposure. This is the case of allergens such as betalactoglobulin of cow´s milk, ovomucoid of hen´s egg, fish parvalbumin, shell-fish tropomyosin, 7d globulins of legumes, peanut And treenuts, and lipid transfer protein of fruits. Labile allergens only eliciti symptoms upon oral exposure in individuals previously sensitized through inhalation of skin contact to homologous cross-reactive allergens. This type of labile allergens are the main allergens involved in the Pollen-food allergy syndrome (Pr-10 proteins homologous to Bet v 1, and profilins), and in the Latex-fruit syndrome (chitinases)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Rivas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los alérgenos de alimentos son proteínas capaces de inducir la producción de anticuerpos IgE específicos. No se conocen las características que determinana la alergenicidad de una proteína, pero sis e sabe que la estabilidad es un factor clave para la sensibilización y la inducción de síntomas en exposición por vía digestiva, pudiendo distinguirse dos tipos de alergenos alimentarios, los estables y los hábiles. Los alergenos alimentarios capaces de inducir sensibilización y síntomas tras exposición por vía digestiva son proteínas estables, resistentes a temperatura, pH ácido y a la acción de las enzimas digestivas. Entre estos  alergenos se encuentran las betalactoglobulina de la leche, el ovomucoide del huevo, las pavalbúminas del pescado, las tropomiosinas de mariscos, las globulinas 7S de legumbres y frutos secos y las proteínas transportadoras de lípidos de las frutas. Los alergenos hábiles solamente inducen síntomas en individuos previamente sensibilizados por otra vía (respiratoria, cutánea) frente a un alergeno homólogo con reactividad cruzada. Este tipo de alergenos hábiles son los principales alergenos implicados en el síndrome de alergia al polen y alimentos (proteínas PR-10 homólogas de Bet y 1 y profilinas), y el síndrome látex-frutas (quitinasas)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;62(1): 18-27, ene.-feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054120</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alergenos alimentarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23089^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5651^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23923^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
