<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053436</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">National multicenter survey: the use of intravenous antimicrobial agents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Infectious diseases are currently one of the major health problems worldwide. As a consequence, both nosocomial and community-acquired    infections are responsible for a significant increase in workload and health costs for hospitals, particularly in Intensive Care Units (ICU),    Internal Medicine and Surgery. The use of intravenous antimicrobial agents is common in hospitalized patients. In order to determine the    use of antimicrobial agents and the most frequent procedures used for their administration in Spanish hospitals, a national multicenter survey    was undertaken among ICU, Internal Medicine and Surgery health staff from 63 hospitals, in which data were collected on central and    peripheral catheter manipulation and intravenous administration. Results showed that, in Spain, both catheter manipulation (insertion, maintenance    and removal) and administration of antimicrobial agents are performed by the nursing staff following established protocols, particularly    for central catheters. Moreover, the ICUs had the highest rates of catheter-bearing patients, as well as patients undergoing antimicrobial    treatment, sometimes in combination. The use of intravenous antimicrobial agents in Spanish hospitals results in an increased    workload for the nursing staff and higher health costs, not to mention the risk involved with the use of vascular catheters</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Rodríguez, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Zufiaurre, M. N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las enfermedades infecciosas constituyen uno de los mayores problemas de salud, por lo que tanto la infección hospitalaria como la adquirida    en la comunidad implican una carga asistencial y un gasto sanitario importante en los hospitales, sobre todo en unidades como las    de Cuidados Intensivos, Medicina Interna y Cirugía. Dadas las peculiaridades de los enfermos hospitalizados, el uso de antimicrobianos intravenosos    es habitual. Este estudio multicéntrico pretende conocer el manejo de los antimicrobianos y los procedimientos empleados con    más frecuencia en relación con su administración en los hospitales españoles. Para ello se ha realizado una encuesta entre el personal sanitario    de los servicios anteriormente mencionados de 63 hospitales españoles, en la cual se recogen datos referentes al manejo del catéter,    tanto central como de vía periférica, y a la administración de antimicrobianos intravenosos. Los resultados indican que, en España, tanto el    manejo del catéter (inserción, mantenimiento y retirada) como la administración de antimicrobianos son realizados por el personal de enfermería,    siguiendo protocolos establecidos, fundamentalmente en el manejo del catéter central. Además, la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos    presenta los porcentajes más elevados tanto de pacientes portadores de catéteres como de pacientes con algún tratamiento antimicrobiano,    frecuentemente en asociación. Se concluye que el uso de antimicrobianos intravenosos en los hospitales supone una gran parte del trabajo    asistencial, así como un gasto sanitario importante, sin olvidar los riesgos asociados a la presencia de un catéter vascular</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;19(4): 349-356, dic.2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encuesta multicéntrica nacional sobre utilización de antibióticos intravenosos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6899^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31403</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19210^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6935^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19210^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28567</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22860^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4422^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19210^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2446^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22859^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13885^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
