<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114764</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stress-induced cardiomyopathy, or Takotsubo syndrome: a condition that mimics acute coronary syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Takotsubo syndrome, or stress-induced cardiomyopathy, is a relatively new diagnosis. This syndrome mainly affects postmenopausal women and is often preceded by a stressful event that triggers a clinical picture that is indistinguishable from acute coronary syndrome. Both have similar electrocardiographic findings (ST-segment elevation, corrected QT interval prolongation, T-wave inversion) and raised levels of markers of myocardial damage (although the elevation is less marked in Takotsubo syndrome). Coronary angiography fails to demonstrate significant obstruction. Takotsubo syndrome is characterized by transient systolic dysfunction, with contractile abnormalities in the apical and middle sections of the ventricle wall and compensatory hyperkines is of the base of the heart. The resulting morphology typifies the syndrome and gives rise to another name for the syndrome: apical ballooning. The etiology and pathogenesis of this syndrome are poorly understood, although the most widely accepted hypothesis is that massive release of catecholamines is the culprit. Another popular theory blames the rupture of an atheromatous plaque in the anterior descending coronary artery, with spontaneous lysis of the thrombus covering the plaque. Prognosis is excellent intakotsubo syndrome, differentiating it from acute coronary syndrome. Associated in-hospital mortality is very low (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guzón Illescas, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Blas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de takotsubo o miocardiopatía inducida por estrés es un síndrome relativamente nuevo en la literatura. Afecta fundamentalmente a mujeres postmenopáusicas y frecuentemente es precedido por un episodio estresante como desencadenante del cuadro. Clínicamente se manifiesta de manera indistinguible a un síndrome coronario agudo (SCA); con alteraciones electrocardiográficas similares (elevación del ST, alargamiento QTc, inversión de la onda T) y con elevación de biomarcadores de daño miocárdico(aunque de forma más moderada). Todo ello sin que se objetiven estenosis significativas en la coronariografía. Se caracteriza por una disfunción sistólica transitoria, con alteración de la contractilidad en los segmentos medio y apical del ventrículo y con hipercinesis compensadora de los segmentos basales, lo que le da una morfología típica que también da nombre al síndrome (apical ballooning). Su mecanismo etiopatogénico sigue siendo una incógnita, aunque la hipótesis más aceptada achaca el síndrome a una descarga masiva catecolaminérgica. Otra teoría en boga lo atribuye a la ruptura de una placa ateromatosa en el seno de la arteria coronaria descendente anterior, con lisis espontánea del trombo que se forma sobre dicha placa. Sin embargo, a diferencia del SCA, este síndrome tiene un pronóstico excelente con una mortalidad intrahospitalaria muy baja (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);25(4): 292-300, ago. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Miocardiopatía inducida por estrés o síndrome de takotsubo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9394^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52615^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31983^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
