<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155213</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effect of 12 weeks endurance training at 2 different intensities on GLUT4 mRNA expression of soleus and gastrocnemius muscles in obese mice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to investigate the expression of GLUT4 mRNA in soleus and gastrocnemius muscles in obese mice in response to endurance training. Forty male C57BL/6 mice were used in this study. Eight mice (Normal Base [NB]) served as non-obese non-trained controls, and 32 mice were put on a high fat diet (HFD) regimen (60% kcal fat) for 12 weeks. At week 16, the obese mice were randomized into the following treatment groups (n = 8 each group): Obese Base [OB]; Low Intensity [LI]; High Intensity [HI]; or Obese Control [OC] groups. LI and HI trained for 5 days/week for 12 weeks on a motorized treadmill at 15 m/min on a 5% slope (for LI), and/or at 22 m/min on a 5% slope (for HI). OC mice were kept sedentarily in the cage during the training program. GLUT4 mRNA expression was measured in gastrocnemius and soleus muscles using a Real Time-PCR method. GLUT4 mRNA expression of soleus muscle in LI group increased about 2.2 fold, against about 1.6 fold for gastrocnemius (p &lt; .05). In addition, GLUT4 mRNA expression of soleus and gastrocnemius muscles in LI and HI groups were significantly higher than OB and OC groups (p &lt; .05). It can be concluded that any disturbance in body energy balance, especially by exercise training and/or high fat diet can influence these molecular and cellular mechanisms that act to establish a stable homeostasis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mohebbi, Hamid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hassan-Nia, Sadegh</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rohani, Hadi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue investigar la expresión de mARN de GLUT4 en los músculos sóleo y gastrocnemio en ratones obesos en respuesta al entrenamiento de resistencia. Cuarenta machos C57BL/6 ratones fueron utilizados en este estudio. Ocho ratones (normal base [NB]) sirvieron como no obesos controles no entrenados, y 32 ratones fueron puestos en una dieta alta en grasa (HFD), régimen que siguieron (60% de grasa, kcal) durante 12 semanas. En la semana 16 los ratones obesos fueron distribuidos aleatoriamente en los siguientes grupos de tratamiento (n = 8 cada grupo): base obesos (OB); baja intensidad (LI); alta intensidad (HI); o grupos de control (OC) obesos. LI y HI fueron entrenados durante 5 días/semana durante 12 semanas en una cinta rodante motorizada a 15 m/min en una pendiente del 5% (para LI) y/o en 22 m/min en una pendiente 5% (para HI). Los ratones OCse mantuvieron sedentariamente en la jaula durante el programa de formación. GLUT4 expresión de mRNA se midió en los músculos gastrocnemio y sóleo, utilizando el método en real time-PCR. La expresión de GLUT4 del mARN del músculo sóleo en el grupo LI aumentó aproximadamente &amp;#8764;2,2 veces, frente a &amp;#8764;1,6 veces para los gemelos (p &amp;#8804; 0,05). Además, la expresión de GLUT4 mARN en los músculos sóleo y gastrocnemio en los grupos LI y HI fue significativamente mayor que en OB y en los grupos OC (p &amp;#8804; 0,05). Se puede concluir que cualquier alteración en el equilibrio energético del cuerpo, especialmente por la práctica de ejercicio y/o dieta alta en grasas puede influir en esos mecanismos moleculares y celulares que actúan para establecer una homeostasis estable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);51(191): 93-99, jul.-sept. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155213</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El efecto de 12 semanas de entrenamiento de resistencia con 2 intensidades diferentes en la expresión de GLUT4 mARN en los músculos sóleo y gastrocnemio en ratones obesos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22282^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11238^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50912^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32124^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
