<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-18182</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of teacher's causal attributions on students' academic achievement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study is framed in the context of Weiner&#146;s attributional theory about motivation and emotion. The aim has been to analyze in a natural context the repercussions that adaptive modification of the attributional style of teachers could have on teachers themselves and on their pupils. The sample has been of 200 subjects, 50 teachers and 150 students. The educational level of students ranged from 4th grade of Primary Education to 2nd grade of Secondary Education. The results show that, after the intervention, teachers&#146; attributions changed toward a more adaptive attributional style. This change in the teacher&#146;s attributional style contributed to a reduction in the levels of teachers&#146; burnout, to an improvement of pupils&#146; attributional system, and to an increase in the students&#146; school marks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torre Ramírez, Carmelo de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy Ávila, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio se encuadra dentro del contexto de la teoría de Weiner sobre la motivación y la emoción. El objetivo propuesto ha sido analizar en el medio natural las repercusiones que una modificación de las atribuciones causales de los profesores puede tener sobre éstos y sus alumnos. La muestra ha estado integrada por 200 sujetos de ambos sexos, 50 profesores y 150 alumnos. El nivel educativo al que pertenecían era 4°, 5° y 6° curso de Educación Primaria, así como 1° y 2° curso de Educación Secundaria Obligatoria. Los resultados muestran que, tras la intervención, las atribuciones de los docentes experimentaron un cambio hacia un estilo atribucional más adaptativo, influyendo asimismo en una reducción de los niveles de estrés laboral. Igualmente, el cambio atribucional del docente influyó en la mejora del sistema atribucional de los alumnos, lo que a su vez, contribuyó a un incremento de sus calificaciones escolares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);14(2): 444-449, mayo 2002. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-18182</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de las atribuciones causales del profesor sobre el rendimiento de los alumnos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d133</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
