<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038670</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chromosomal evaluation in patients with bipolar disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The studies on genetic changes are aimed at the molecular level of alterations and have identified the location of the disease susceptible genes, some of wich are shared with schizophrenia. In the bipolar disease, there is little evidence from conventional cytogenetic studies in comparison with other mental pathologies. The purpose of this research was to evaluate the chromosome structure through conventional studies. Materials and methods: This research is prospective and descriptive. 40 female patients with an average age of 42.65 years and 40 adult controls without psychiatric disease were examined. Results: No cytogenetic alterations were observed in the bipolar disorder (BPD) patients, except for one patient in whom one mataphase evidenced hyperdiploidy with a gain of chromosomes 8 and 9. An unexpected high fragile site expression was noted in 26/40 patients (65%) and 4 /40 controls (10%). The chromosomal location of the fragilities observed identifies a distribution pattern concentrated mainly in bands 1(p32), 1(q21), 1(q22), 2(p12), 2(q31), 3(p14), 3(q21), 3(q25), 7(p14), 14 (q22) y 19(p13). It was observed that the 54 breakage points expressed are distributed on 17 of the 22 autosome pairs, with none observed on the sex chromosome pair. Conclusions: The presents results evidence an unexpected high frecuence of chromosomal fragility in BPD patients, without a logic explanation thus far such alteration, its future consecuences and possible relationship with prognosisi and treatment. New studies must be conducted in order to elucidate these questions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arteaga-Vizcaíno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hassanieh, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zuleta-Neumanb, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabala, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías-Duerto, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Weir Medina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Hay pocas noticias sobre estudios de citogenética convencional en pacientes con enfermedad bipolar, no así de estudios moleculares donde se señala la ubicación de genes de susceptibilidad en diversos cromosomas. El objetivo del presente trabajo es evaluar la estructura cromosómica a través de estudios convencionales en pacientes con enfermedad bipolar. Materiales y métodos: Se estudió a 40 pacientes mujeres, con diagnóstico de enfermedad bipolar, con un promedio de edad de 42,65 años (20-67 años). Se utilizó como control a 40 individuos adultos con las mismas edades, sin enfermedad psiquiátrica. Se evaluó la estructura cromosómica mediante estudios convencionales. Resultados: No se observaron alteraciones citogenéticas en las pacientes con enfermedad bipolar, salvo una, en la que en una metafase se evidenció hiperdiploidía con ganancia de los cromosomas 8 y 9. En 26/40 pacientes (65%) y en 4/40 controles (10%) se observó una alta expresión de sitios frágiles (p &lt; 0,05). La ubicación cromosómica de estas fragilidades identifican un patrón de distribución concentrado principalmente en las bandas 1(p32), 1(q21), 1(q22), 2(p12), 2(q31), 3(p14), 3(q21), 3(q25), 7(p14), 14 (q22) y 19(p13). Se apreció que los 54 puntos de ruptura expresados están distribuidos en 17 de los 22 pares de autosomas, y no se observa ninguno en el par de cromosomas sexuales. Conclusiones: Los resultados muestran una frecuencia inesperadamente alta de fragilidad cromosómica en pacientes con enfermedad bipolar, sin que se tenga hasta ahora una explicación lógica para tal alteración, sus consecuencias futuras y su posible relación con el pronóstico y el tratamiento. Se deben llevar a cabo nuevos estudios a fin de dilucidar estos interrogantes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);12(3): 89-94, mayo-jun. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038670</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación cromosómica en pacientes con enfermedad bipolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2922^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
