<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99824</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pulmonary Langerhans cell histiocytosis: report of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pulmonary Langerhans cell histiocytosis is a rare disease of young adults, usually smokers, which is associated with significant morbidity. The course of the disease is unpredictable, ranging from benign self-limiting types with spontaneous regression, to malignant forms with progression to respiratory failure and death. Its cause is unknown, but most authors believe that there is an alteration in immune system regulation in these patients. We report a case of a patient with the diagnosis of pulmonary Langerhans cell histiocytosis and review the clinical characteristics, diagnosis and treatment of this disease. We consider this case of interest due by the low frequency of this disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de Mingo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mena Garrido, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La histiocitosis pulmonar de células de Langerhans es una enfermedad rara de adultos jóvenes, generalmente fumadores, que se asocia con una significativa morbilidad. El curso de esta enfermedad es impredecible, oscilando desde formas benignas autolimitadas hasta formas malignas con evolución progresiva hacia la insuficiencia respiratoria y la muerte. Su causa es desconocida, pero la mayor parte de los autores creen que en estos pacientes hay una alteración en la regulación del sistema inmunológico. Presentamos el caso de un paciente con el diagnóstico de histiocitosis pulmonar de células de Langerhans y revisamos las características clínicas, diagnósticas y terapéuticas de esta enfermedad. Consideramos de interés este caso por la baja frecuencia de esta entidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);38(3): 181-184, abr. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99824</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histiocitosis pulmonar de células de Langerhans: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d308^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31333^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37296^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2020^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2020^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28223^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
