<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166468</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The SHIFT study: the role of ivabradine in the treatment of heart failure and its relevance in clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Systolic Heart failure treatment with I f inhibitor ivabradine Trial (SHIFT) is a case-referent study of a novel approach to the treatment of patients with heart failure. The rationale is that a high heart rate is not only a risk marker for disease but is also a modifiable risk factor that could serve as a therapeutic target in patients with heart failure and depressed systolic function. The study enrolled 6558 patients with chronic heart failure, left ventricular systolic dysfunction (i.e. an ejection fraction &amp;#8804;35%) and a sinus rhythm of 70 beats/min or higher. It was found that the addition of ivabradine resulted in a reduction in the combined endpoint of cardiovascular death or readmission for heart failure, which was mainly due to a reduction in hospitalization for exacerbations of congestive symptoms. In addition, ivabradine also had an additive effect on ventricular remodeling and quality of life, and the adverse effect rate was very low. Taken together, the favorable efficacy and safety of this drug guarantee ivabradine&#146;s inclusion in clinical practice guidelines for heart failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Raposeiras Roubín, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Domínguez, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Juanatey, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anguita Sánchez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Systolic Heart failure treatment with If inhibitor ivabradine Trial (SHIFT) es un estudio de referencia sobre un enfoque novedoso en el tratamiento de los pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca, acorde con el hecho de que la frecuencia cardiaca elevada no sólo es un marcador de riesgo, sino también un factor de riesgo modificable con potencial para ser objetivo terapéutico en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca y función sistólica deprimida. Incluyó a 6.558 pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca crónica, disfunción sistólica ventricular izquierda (fracción de eyección &amp;#8804; 35%) y ritmo sinusal &amp;#8805; 70lpm; se objetivó con ivabradina un beneficio adicional en la reducción del combinado de muerte cardiovascular o reingreso por insuficiencia cardiaca, a expensas fundamentalmente de la reducción de las hospitalizaciones por reagudización de la clínica congestiva. Asimismo, tenía un efecto adicional en el proceso de remodelado ventricular y en la calidad de vida, con una tasa muy baja de efectos secundarios. La combinación de la eficacia y la seguridad de este fármaco es un hecho que sin duda determina la inclusión de la ivabradina en las guías de práctica clínica de insuficiencia cardiaca (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);12(supl.A): 8a-13a, 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio SHIFT: papel de la ivabradina en la insuficiencia cardiaca y su importancia en la práctica clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13230^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31982^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2357^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
