<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041491</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-1637</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improving the shear bond strength of orthodontic brackets</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of this study were: to determine the effect of two adhesion promoters, Enhance-L.C. (Reliance, Itasca, Ill.) and OrthoSolo (Ormco, Sybron Dental Specialities, Tokyo, Japan) on the shear bond strength, and the ammount of adhesive remnant on teeth after debonding brackets (Victory Series, 3M Unitek Dental Products, Monrovia, Calif.); and to find out if Enhance-L.C. is material specific as suggested by the manufacturer or if it has similar effects when used with other orthodontic adhesive systems which do not belong to the same product range. Were divided into five groups of 25, 125 upper premolars: I, Transbond-XT (3M Unitek Dental Products, Monrovia, Calif.); II, Transbond-XT/Enhance-L.C; III, Transbond-XT/OrthoSolo; IV, Light-Bond (Reliance, Itasca, Ill.); and V, Light-Bond/Enhance-L.C. Shear bond strength was tested using a universal test machine and adhesive remnant was quantified using an image analysis equipment. OrthoSolo significantly improved bonding for Transbond-XT adhesive system. Enhance L.C. did not significantly increase bond strength for either Transbond-XT or Light-Bond (the system recommended by the manufacturer). However the combination Light-Bond/Enhance-LC provided a significantly greater bond strength than Transbond-XT and Transbond-XT/Enhance-L.C. (P.005). As for adhesive remnant, no significant increase (P&gt;.05) was observed with the application of the promoters. The use of OrthoSolo is recommended in those cases requiring increased bond strength for Transbond-XT. With Light-Bond system, it is preferible to use Enhance-L.C. when increased bond strength is needed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo González, L. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Hernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos de este estudio fueron: determinar el efecto de 2 promotores de la adhesión, Enhance-L.C. (Reliance, Itasca, Ill.) y OrthoSolo (Ormco, Sybron Dental Specialities, Tokyo, Japan), en la fuerza adhesiva y en el adhesivo remanente tras el descementado de brackets (Victory Series, 3M Unitek Dental Products, Monrovia, Calif.), y comprobar si Enhance-L.C. es específico del material, como sugiere su fabricante, o si su efecto es similar con otros sistemas adhesivos que no pertenezcan a su línea de productos. Ciento veinticinco premolares superiores extraídos se dividieron en 5 grupos de 25 premolares cada uno: I, Transbond-XT (3M Unitek Dental Products, Monrovia, Calif.); II, Transbond-XT/Enhance-L.C.; III, Transbond-XT/OrthoSolo; IV, Light-Bond (Reliance, Itasca, Ill.), y V, Light-Bond/Enhance-L.C. La resistencia a las fuerzas de cizalla se midió en una máquina universal de tests y el adhesivo remanente se cuantificó con un sistema de análisis de imagen. OrthoSolo mejoró significativamente la adhesión de Transbond-XT. Enhance-L.C. no aumentó significativamente la adhesión de Transbond-XT ni de Light-Bond (sistema recomendado por el fabricante). Sin embargo, la combinación Light-Bond/ Enhance-L.C. proporcionó una fuerza adhesiva significativamente mayor que Transbond-XT y Transbond-XT/Enhance-L.C. (p  0,005). En cuanto al adhesivo remanante, no se observó un aumento significativo (p &gt; 0,05) con la aplicación de los potenciadores. Se recomienda la utilización de OrhoSolo en los casos en los que se necesite aumentar la adhesión del sistema Transbond-XT. En cambio, Enhance-L.C. es preferible usarlo con Light-Bond cuando se necesite mayor fuerza adhesiva</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ortod. esp. (Ed. impr.);45(3): 144-149, jul. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041491</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejorando la fuerza adhesiva de los brackets ortodóncicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29217^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30758^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3219^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10149^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3219^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3752^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29217^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10149^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3752^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
