<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047372</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measuring anankastic personality traits</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The authors validate a 20 item scale designed to measure anankastic (obsessive) personality traits: the Mini-Inventory of Anankastic Personality Traits, 2nd version (MIAPT-2).                 Material and methods. The answers of a sample of 418 subject of both genders obtained from the general population were used to analyze construct validity (factorial analysis), its alpha reliability and its internal consistency through the item/total correlations and the two halves test. An additional sample of 22 medical students was used to analyze the concurrent validity of the scale (external criterion: the Maudsley Obsessional-Compulsive Inventory) and the temporary reliability with the testretest method. After this, the total scores of the instrument and the factorial scores were standardized and distributed into percentiles.                 Results. The scale shows good concurrent validity (r = 0.67; p &lt; 0.000) and construct validity (56 % of the total of the variance explained by the factorial analysis) as well as a good internal consistency through the item/total correlations (all p = 0.000) and two halves test (r = 0.71; p &lt; 0.000; with the Spearman-Brown correction R= 0.83). The alpha reliability of the scale (&amp;#945; = 0.84), and the test-retest (r = 0.69; p &lt; 0.000) are high.                 Conclusions. The validated MIAPT-2 shows good validity and reliability to evaluate anankastic personality traits. The authors include an appendix with the scale and the standardization of its total and factorial scores distributed into percentiles to be used in clinical and general population samples</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navío Acosta, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Brieva, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero Villafáfila, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamora Romero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los autores validan una escala de 20 ítems diseñada para medir rasgos anancásticos de la personalidad: el Mini-Inventario de Rasgos Anancásticos de la Personalidad, segunda versión (MIRAP-2).                 Material y métodos. Utilizan las respuestas de una muestra de 418 sujetos de ambos sexos extraídos de la población general para analizar la validez de constructo (análisis factorial), su fiabilidad alfa y su consistencia interna mediante la correlación ítem/total y prueba de las dos mitades. Se utiliza una muestra adicional de 22 estudiantes de medicina para analizar la validez concurrente de la escala (criterio externo: el Maudsley Obsessional-Compulsive Inventory) y la fiabilidad temporal mediante la prueba testretest. Tras ello se procede a estandarizar las puntuaciones totales del instrumento y las puntuaciones factoriales, distribuyéndolas en percentiles.                 Resultados. La escala muestra una buena validez concurrente (r = 0,67; p &lt; 0,000) y validez de constructo (56 % del total de la varianza explicada por el análisis factorial), así como una buena consistencia interna mediante las correlaciones ítem/total (todas p = 0,000) y prueba de las dos mitades (r = 0,71; p &lt; 0,000; con la corrección de Spearman-Brown R= 0,83). La fiabilidad alfa de la escala es elevada (&amp;#945;= 0,84), así como lo es la prueba test-retest (r = 0,69; p &lt; 0,000).                 Conclusiones. La escala validada muestra una buena validez y fiabilidad para evaluar los rasgos anacásticos de la personalidad. Los autores incluyen un apéndice con la escala y la estandarización de sus puntuaciones totales y factoriales distribuidas en percentiles para su uso en muestras tanto clínicas como de la población general</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;34(2): 105-111, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047372</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluando los rasgos anacásticos de la personalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
