<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044206</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge and nursing practice relating to the administration of low weight heparin: evaluation of the administration technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to explore the knowledge and nursing practice relatingto the administration of low weight heparin compoundsMaterial and methods: cross-sectional descriptive study. Thesample consisted of 150 nurses of both genders from the HospitalArnau in Vilanova, Lleida. A self-administered questionnaire wasgiven for the collection of data. The questionnaire had 20 questionson the administration of heparin. Other variables included inthe study were: years in the profession, type of work contract, andfrequency in the administration of heparin.Results: 67,3% loaded using the normal syringe an excessive dose.82,8% applied the technique correctly prefilled syringe as opposedto a 61,3% in the manual syringe technique. Over 75% of registerednurses pass the minimal score required for all the phases,excepting the preparation/dosification phase.Conclusions: using preloaded syringes with heparin improvesdosification to the patients and a better quality control of the totaladministration process. The more years in the profession, the worsethe general results, and the more frequent administration, the betterthe results. This survey is a useful tool for the evaluation of nursingprocedures and to improve the quality of such procedures</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mena Gimeno, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Florensa Cabré, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: explorar los conocimientos y las prácticas enfermerascon respecto a la administración de las Heparinas de Bajo PesoMoléculas (HBPM).Material y método: estudio descriptivo transversal. Se obtuvo unamuestra de 150 enfermeros/as del Hospital Arnau de Vilanova deLleida. Como instrumento para la recogida de los datos se elaboróun cuestionario autocumplimentado de 20 preguntas sobre laadministración de las heparinas. Otras variables incluidas en el estudiofueron: años de profesión, tipo de contrato y frecuencia deadministración de las HBPM.Resultados: el 67,3% cargaban con la jeringa manual un exceso dedosis. Un 82,7% realizaba correctamente la técnica con jeringa precargadafrente a un 61,3% en la técnica jeringa manual. Más de un75% de los enfermeros/as superan la puntuación mínima requeridaen todas las fases excepto en la fase de preparación/dosificación.Conclusiones: con las jeringas precargadas de HBPM mejora ladosificación a los enfermos y el control de calidad del proceso deadministración total. A más años de profesión se objetivan peoresresultados generales y a más frecuencia de administración mejoresresultados. La encuesta es una herramienta útil para la evaluaciónde procedimientos de Enfermería y para mejorar su calidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(2): 14-20, mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044206</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimientos y prácticas enfermeras respecto a la administración de las heparinas de bajo peso molecular: evaluación de la técnica de administración</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11799^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7453^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31696^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
