<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168608</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perception of vasectomy in military women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Analyzing the perception of vasectomy as a method of family planning in military women based on the Nola Pender's theory. Methodology: Phenomenological - Descriptive qualitative approach, one worked with a sample of fourteen women belonging to the military forces, the information is collected through semi - interviews by a script of interviews; data were analyzed in three stages: encoding open, axial coding and selective coding. Results: vasectomy procedure is accepted, they consider it highly effective and a way of organizing economic and emotional stability of the family, likewise an appropriate method of family planning. Conclusion: do military women in a social context where the topic vasectomy is the immediate choice for family planning (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Saldarriaga Genes, Guillermina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Aragón, Shirley Paola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruydíaz Gómez, Keydis Sulay</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la percepción de la vasectomía como método de planificación familiar en mujeres militares basadas en la teoría de acción razonada de Nola Pender. Metodología: Se trabajó con un enfoque cualitativo de tipo fenomenológico-descriptivo, con una muestra de catorce mujeres pertenecientes a las fuerza militares. La información se recolectó por medio de entrevistas semiestructuradas, a través de un guión de entrevista; los datos se analizaron en tres fases: codificación abierta, codificación axial y codificación selectiva. Resultados: El procedimiento de la vasectomía es aceptado y considerado altamente eficaz en tanto forma de organizar la sostenibilidad económica y sentimental de núcleo familiar, así mismo, es percibido como un adecuado método de planificación familiar. Conclusión: Las mujeres militares se desenvuelven en un contexto social donde el tema de la vasectomía es la opción inmediata para la planificación familiar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;26(3): 147-151, jul.-sept. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168608</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de la vasectomía en mujeres militares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15061^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10662</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9077^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15061^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50221</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
