<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057224</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">First two years of experience with BAHA: results in 12 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe our first 2 years&#146; experience following implementation of the BAHA program at our hospitals with special emphasis on the benefits and complications of use in each patient. Material and method: Retrospective review since the beginning of the programme at two Teaching Hospitals in 2004. Twelve patients were implanted with BAHA, and their complications are described, along with hearing loss and their audiological gain with the hearing aid. Results: Eleven patients with BAHA completed the follow-up. The average age was 31.6 ± 18.9 years, and their average conductive hearing loss of was 45.5 dB with an audiological gain of 33.6 dB. We had one patient with a minor complication (mild infection of the skin flap) and another with a major one (loss of the titanium implant). Conclusions: The BAHA programme started in 2004 has generated good results in terms of positive audiological data, patient acceptance and low complication rates</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jaramillo Saffon, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes, Dunia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monroy Barreneche, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán, José Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lora Falquez, José Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Rivera, José Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la experiencia durante los primeros 2 años de implementación del programa de BAHA en nuestras instituciones, puntualizando los beneficios en cada paciente y las complicaciones con su uso. Material y método: Estudio retrospectivo desde el inicio del programa en el 2004 en 2 hospitales universitarios sobre 12 pacientes implantados con BAHA; se describe las complicaciones, su déficit auditivo y su ganancia audiológica con el audífono. Resultados: once pacientes con BAHA completaron el seguimiento, con un promedio de edad de 31,6 ± 18,9 años, con un déficit auditivo conductivo de 45,5 dB en promedio y una ganancia de 33,6 dB, una complicación menor (infección menor del colgajo) y una mayor (pérdida del implante de titanio). Conclusiones: Adelantamos un programa de BAHA con buenos resultados audiológicos, buena aceptación de los pacientes y baja tasa de complicaciones</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(9): 434-436, nov. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057224</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Primeros 2 años de experiencia en BAHA: resultados en 12 pacientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1869^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6466^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6466^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
