<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124969</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Training in communication skills according to residents' and tutors' perspective in medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. During last decades there has been a substantial change from the consideration of communication skills in the curriculum of medicine. Currently, it is considered a core competency of health professionals; it can be trained and improved. Aim. To identify the level of training and the perceived needs of residents and tutors about the learning of communication skills as a first step in designing effective programs adapted to the current context. Subjects and methods. Participants were 131 residents and 79 tutors, from 12 hospitals in Catalonia, who completed a self administered questionnaire via online. Results. 74% of residents and 67% of the tutors had received training in communication skills. Residents and tutors agreed on the valuation of the area in which the training was appropriate (clinical interview) and in areas for improvement (managing emotions, managing difficult situations, and communication with family and caregivers) during the training system of health care professionals. Both showed a high willingness to participate in future training programs. Conclusions. There are deficiencies in communication skills training of residents and tutors of Medicine. One of the challenges is to ensure that residents, regardless of specialty, acquire an optimal level of communicative competence upon completion of the training period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aradilla-Herrero, Amor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinuevo, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nolla-Domenjó, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clèries, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En las últimas décadas se ha producido un cambio sustancial respecto a la consideración de las habilidades comunicativas en el currículo de medicina. Actualmente, se considera una competencia nuclear del profesional sanitario, susceptible de entrenamiento y mejora. Objetivo. Identificar el nivel de formación y las necesidades percibidas de médicos especialistas en formación (MEF) y tutores respecto al aprendizaje de habilidades comunicativas, como primer paso para diseñar programas efectivos adaptados al contexto actual. Sujetos y métodos. Participaron 131 residentes y 79 tutores, de 12 centros hospitalarios de Cataluña, que cumplimentaron vía online un cuestionario autoadministrado. Resultados. Un 74% de residentes y un 67% de los tutores habían recibido formación en habilidades comunicativas. Residentes y tutores coincidieron en la valoración del área en la que la formación es adecuada (entrevista clínica) y en las áreas susceptibles de mejora (manejo de emociones, gestión de situaciones difíciles y comunicación con familiares y cuidadores) durante el programa de MEF. Ambos manifestaron una alta predisposición a participar en futuros programas de formación. Conclusiones. Existen deficiencias en la formación en habilidades comunicativas de residentes y tutores de medicina. Uno de los retos es asegurar que los residentes, independientemente de la especialidad, adquieran un nivel óptimo de competencias comunicativas una vez finalizado el periodo de formación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);17(2): 115-122, jun. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124969</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Formación en habilidades comunicativas desde la perspectiva de residentes y tutores en medicina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11666^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6904^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
