<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98981</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Myiasis as an entity of interest in occupational medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In few occasions, reference to myiasis in the scope of Occupational Medicine has been done. It is a generalized mistake to think that this type of parasitation is exclusive of underdeveloped countries or social layers without the minimal hygiene measures. Nevertheless, it is important to know the etiological agents and to notice the risk that affects certain occupational sectors exposed to organic matter in decay proccessor to certain foods that by their chemical characteristics act of appealing to the Diptera. We studied the cases of myiasis diagnosed in some medical centers located in Granada, Málaga, Almería and Jaén during the period between September 2010 and June 2011 and we considered with special interest those that began byan infestation during the working period. A predominance of Piophila casei (Linnaeus, 1758) and Sarcophaga (Bercaea) africa (Wiedemann, 1824) was observed in laboral myiasis. Also we exhibit the main characteristics of the vital cycle of Diptera of sanitary interest and the safety measures that must be adopted to avoid this type of occupational accident (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Archilla Peña, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Ríos, Gilberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Medina, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En escasas ocasiones se ha hecho referencia a las miasis en el ámbito de la Medicina del Trabajo. Es un error bastante generalizado pensar que este tipo de parasitación es exclusiva de países subdesarrollados o de estratos sociales carentes de las mínimas medidas de higiene. Sin embargo, es importante conocer los agentes etiológicos y advertir del riesgo que afecta a ciertos sectores laborales expuestos a materia orgánica en descomposición o a ciertos alimentos que por sus características químicas actúan de atrayentes para los dípteros. Para ello, estudiamos los casos de miasis que se diagnosticaron en varios centros sanitarios ubicados en Granada, Málaga, Almería y Jaén durante el periodo comprendido entre septiembre de 2010 y junio de2011 y consideramos con especial interés los que se iniciaron por una infestación durante el periodo laboral. Se observa en las miasis laborales un predominio de las especies Piophila casei (Linnaeus, 1758) y Sarcophaga (Bercaea) africa (Wiedemann, 1824). Asimismo, exponemos las principales características del ciclo vital de los dípteros de interés sanitario y las medidas de seguridad que deben adoptarse para evitar este tipo de accidente laboral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;57(225): 331-338, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98981</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las miasis como entidad de interés en Medicina del Trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10461^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4232^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9390^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201100</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
