<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78595</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the last years the organizations have considered theinformation a resourcewithout value but nowadays the informationis an important resourcewhich is necessary tomanageand distribute on a suitable way. The sanitary organizationscould not be unaware of these events. Nevertheless, the grossinformation would not have enough value and it becomesnecessary to deal with it in a proper way. It means that thegross information has to be processed and distributed takinginto account the necessities of the people to whom it is destined.The Information Systems then appear in the organizationlike essential instruments for them.In this study several factors are exposed: the methodologyof the analysis, the design of a hypothetical informationsystem of Infirmary and also the essential concepts to knowhow this information system works nowadays (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Murillo Murillo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén Ríos, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Hernández, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años las organizaciones han pasado deconsiderar la información como un recurso sin valor a considerarlocomo un recurso importante dentro de la organizaciónque es necesario gestionar y distribuir de forma adecuada.Las organizaciones sanitarias no podrían quedarseajenas a estos acontecimientos. Sin embargo, la informaciónen bruto no tendría demasiado valor y se hace necesario tratarlade forma adecuada, es decir, procesada y distribuidasegún las necesidades del usuario al que vaya destinada.Aparecen entonces los Sistemas de Información en las organizacionescomo instrumentos imprescindibles para el funcionamientode las mismas.En este trabajo se expone lametodología de análisis y diseñode un hipotético sistema de información de Enfermería, asícomo los conceptos fundamentales para el conocimiento delestado de la cuestión del mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;8(3): 150-155, jul.-sept. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78595</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis y diseño de unsistema de informaciónen enfermería (Parte I: aproximación teórica)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22412</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200807</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
