<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59285</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of pain in chronic pancreatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abdominal pain is the most frequent symptom in patients with chronic pancreatitis. Between 70 and 90% of patients experience pain at some point in the course of their disease. In patients with alcoholic pancreatitis, pain is usually experienced at disease onset. Two distinct forms of idiopathic chronic pancreatitis can be distinguished: in early-onset (juvenile) idiopathic chronic pancreatitis, pain occurs initially, while in late-onset (senile) idiopathic chronic pancreatitis, pain is delayed or may even be absent.According to several authors, between 27 and 67% of patients require surgery due to lack of response to medical treatment. Pain may reoccur in more than 30% of patients who have undergone surgery and consequently, reintervention is not uncommon. Several treatment options are currently available: medical, endoscopic and surgical. The most appropriate treatment for each patient should be chosen on an individualized basis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abu-Suboh, Monder</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dot, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olsina, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guarner, Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor abdominal es el síntoma que presentan de forma más frecuente los pacientes con pancreatitis crónica. El 70&#150;90% de los pacientes lo experimentan en algún momento de la evolución de la enfermedad; en el caso de los pacientes con pancreatitis alcohólica generalmente esto ocurre al inicio, en los pacientes con pancreatitis idiopática hay una forma de inicio precoz (juvenil), en la que el dolor se presenta en la fase inicial de la enfermedad, y una forma de inicio tardío (senil), en la que el dolor es de instauración tardía o incluso puede no aparecer nunca. Según diferentes autores, entre un 27 y un 67% de los pacientes precisa tratamiento quirúrgico por falta de respuesta al tratamiento médico, y se sabe también que el dolor puede recidivar en más del 30% de los pacientes operados, por lo que no es infrecuente una segunda intervención. Hoy en día disponemos de varias posibilidades de tratamiento (médico, endoscópico o quirúrgico) y es importante elegir de forma individualizada el método más apropiado para cada paciente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;32(2): 109-115, feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del dolor en la pancreatitis crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10382^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29357</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
