<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87275</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9512</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complex psychological processes in children with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: a neuropsychological perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anatomofunctional frontostriatal abnormalities classically identified as the etiologic reason for Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) are also, by extension, the anatopathological substrate of executive deficits found in this population. From Neuropsychology, scientific discipline interested in the study of the  relationship between cortex and cortico-cortical and cortico- subcortical loops with complex psychological processes, there is a great interest to substantiate the nature of neuropsychological deficits that occur in ADHD, in an  attempt to identify potential endophenotypes that characterize this population; an interest that acquires its full dimension due to the fact that there is no biological marker for ADHD. The AIM of this review is an update on  theoretical knowledge accumulated, from Neuropsychology as a conceptual framework of reference, about deficits in memory and executive functions in ADHD population.  We believe that highlighting the value of neuropsychological findings in ADHD should be an essential component in both the diagnosis and rehabilitation of  a multicomponential disorder as ADHD is (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Pérez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las alteraciones anatomofucionales frontoestriatales clásicamente identificadas como razón etiológica del Trastorno por Déficit de Atención con Hiperactividad (TDAH) representan también, por extensión, el substrato anatomopatológico del déficit ejecutivo identificado en esta población.  Desde la Neuropsicología, disciplina científica interesada por el estudio de la relación entre la corteza y los circuitos cortico-corticales y cortico-subcorticales con los procesos psicológicos complejos, existe un gran interés por fundamentar la naturaleza de los déficits neuropsicológicos que acontecen en el TDAH en un intento de identificar  posibles endofenotipos que caractericen a esta población, interés que adquiere toda su dimensión si tenemos en cuenta la inexistencia de un marcador biológico para el TDAH. El objetivo de la presente revisión es una  actualización teórica sobre el conocimiento acumulado desde la Neuropsicología como marco conceptual de referencia, acerca de las alteraciones en Memoria y en Funciones Ejecutivas de la población con TDAH. Consideramos que poner en valor los hallazgos neuropsicológicos en TDAH debe ser un componente esencial tanto en el  diagnóstico como en la rehabilitación de un desorden multicomponencial como es el TDAH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. infanto-juv;27(1): 48-57, ene.-mar. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87275</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Procesos psicológicos complejos en niños con trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad: una perspectiva neuropsicológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
