<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101048</identifier>
<setSpec>0367-2743</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background The study aims to describe the socio-demographic and clinical profile of leprosy patients in the municipality of San Borja &#150; Beni, carrying out campaigns of perception of symptomatic skin through clinical examination, also to describe the socio-demographic and clinical profile of patient with Hansen´s disease and in this way cut the chain of transmission of the disease. Methods: The research is a prospective study with a qualitative-exploratory focus, with a tendency methodological-longitudinal design, not probabilistic, by means of revision campaigns of patients with Hansen´s disease and elaboration of the clinical histories opened at the San Borja´s Modern Hospital. The clinical histories were complemented with the following socio-demographical, clinical variables and laboratory examinations. Results: Most of the affected individuals were women (76%), the average age of the study comprised to the whole group were from 31 to 40 years, married (67%), 13 patients had resided previously in San Borja. The appearance of the first symptoms was very variable with an average interval between 2 and 5 years. The disease presented family antecedents in 12% of those affected, the most frequently reported initial symptom was pruritus 37%; 15% had received a previous treatment to the one recommended by the Who (OMs), injuries were located most frequently in inferior limbs (44%), sensibility alteration was simultaneous in superior and inferior limbs, with main implication of the neural pathways of the external and internal popliteous sciatic nerves (25%). Only 21% had laboratory reports and their history results were negative (-). All patients were diagnosed as paucibacillary leprosy (PB), the Tuberculoid variety (LT) was the most frequent (61%); and 48% of the patients are on treatment. Conclusions: A young patient (in productive age) with a regular income and residing in warm climates, seems to be the profile of the affected individuals with  light anatomo-clinical forms as for example coloration changes in skin before it becomes a more serious problem. The types with light anatomo-clinical forms such as pigmentation changes in skin become a chronic illness. When carrying out a physical exam we found painful and augmented nerves together with weakness. Although this result was only detected in a minority of cases it demonstrates that leprosy is a chronic disease of silent evolution. For this reason, an early diagnosis of the disease and administration of the treatment is important to avoid some degree of deformity of the patients, in an environment where there still exists some degree of stigmatization of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villarroel Ibarra, Britta Ninoscka</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: El estudio pretende describir el perfil sociodemográfico y clínico del enfermo de lepra existente en el Municipio de San Borja-Beni con la realización de campañas de atención de sintomáticos de la piel mediante consulta externa, asimismo describir el perfil sociodemográfico y clínico del enfermo de lepra, para así cortar la cadena de transmisión de la enfermedad. Métodos: El trabajo de investigación es un estudio prospectivo con un enfoque cualitativo, exploratorio, diseño metodológico longitudinal de tendencia, no probabilística, mediante campañas de revisión a pacientes con enfermedad de Hansen y elaboración de las historias clínicas abiertas en el Hospital Moderno San Borja. Las historias clínicas se complementaron con las siguientes variables sociodemográficas, clínicas y exámenes de laboratorio. Resultados: La mayoría de los enfermos fueron mujeres (76%), la edad media del estudio comprendió al grupo entero entre las edades de 31 a 40 años, casados (67%), 13 pacientes tenían una residencia anterior a San Borja, la aparición de los primeros síntomas fue muy variable con una media comprendida entre los 2 y 5 años. La enfermedad presentó antecedentes familiares en un 12% de los afectados, el síntoma inicial más frecuentemente referido fue prurito 37%, un 15% recibió tratamiento previo al esquema de la OMS, las lesiones se localizaban con mayor frecuencia en miembros inferiores (44%) encontrándose alteración de la sensibilidad en miembros superiores e inferiores simultáneamente, con mayor compromiso en los trayectos nerviosos de los nervios ciático poplíteo externo e interno (35%). Sólo un 21% contaban con reportes de laboratorio en su historia  cuyo resultado era negativo (-). A todos los pacientes se los diagnosticó como Lepra paucibacilar (PB), la variedad tuberculoide (LT) fue la más frecuente (61%) y un 48% de los pacientes se encuentra recibiendo tratamiento. Conclusiones: Un paciente, joven, (en edad productiva) con economía regular y resiente en climas cálidos, parece ser el perfil del enfermo, que conformas anatomo-clínicas leves como cambios de coloración en piel se convierten en problemas más serios. Al realizar un buen  examen físico encontramos nervio doloroso, engrosado, pérdida de fuerza. Si bien se encontró en una minoría, estos hallazgos demuestran que es una enfermedad crónica de evolución silenciosa. Por ello, es importante un diagnóstico temprano de la enfermedad y el inicio del tratamiento, para evitar llegar a algún grado de deformidad de los pacientes, en un ambiente donde aún existe cierto grado de estigmatización de la enfermedad. La mayoría de los pacientes abandonaron su tratamiento por diferentes razones. (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fontilles, Rev. leprol;27(2): 117-154, mayo-ago. 2009. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101048</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vigilancia epidemiológica de la lepra: Estudio realizado en el hospital moderno San Borja de Marzo a Octubre de 2007</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31887^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23708^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53481^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53482^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9359^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
