<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81120</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Extinction memory is impaired in schizophrenia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Schizophrenia is associated with abnormalities in emotional processing and social cognition, which might result from disruption of the underlying neural mechanism(s) governing emotional learning and memory. To investigate this possibility, we measured the acquisition and extinction of conditioned fear responses and delayed recall of extinction in schizophrenia and control subjects. Methods: Twenty-eight schizophrenia and 18 demographically matched control subjects underwent a 2-day fear conditioning, extinction learning, and extinction recall procedure, in which skin conductance response (SCR) magnitude was used as the index of conditioned responses. Results: During fear acquisition, 83% of the control subjects and 57% of the patients showed autonomic responsivity (&#147;responders&#148;), and the patients showed larger SCRs to the stimulus that was not paired with the unconditioned stimulus (CS_) than the control subjects. Within the responder group, there was no difference between the patients and control subjects in levels of extinction learning; however, the schizophrenia patients showed significant impairment, relative to the control subjects, in context-dependent recall of the extinction memory. In addition, delusion severity in the patients correlated with baseline skin conductance levels. Conclusions: These data are consistent with prior evidence for a heightened neural response to innocuous stimuli in schizophrenia and elevated arousal levels in psychosis. The finding of deficient extinction recall in schizophrenia patients who showed intact extinction learning suggests that schizophrenia is associated with a disturbance in the neural processes supporting emotional memory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Holt, Daphne J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pitman, Roger K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rauch, Scott L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Walsh, Jared P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orr, Scott</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goff, Donald C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lebron-Milad, Kelimer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Milad, Mohammed R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cassidy, Brittany S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La esquizofrenia se asocia con anomalías del procesamiento emocional y de la cognición social, que pueden ser consecuencia de la desorganización de los mecanismos neurales subyacentes, que determinan el aprendizaje emocionals y la memoria. Para investigar esta posibilidad, evaluamos la adquisición y la extinción de las respuestas condicionadas de miedo y el recuerdo tardío de la extinción en pacientes con esquizofrenia e individuos de control. Métodos: Durante 2 días, se sometió a 28 pacientes con esquizofrenia y a 18 individuos de control emparejados demográficamente con un procedimiento de condicionamiento del miedo, aprendizaje de la extinción y recuerdo de la extinción, en el cual, como índice de las respuestas condicionadas, se usó la magnitud de la respuesta de conductancia cutánea (RCC). Resultados: Durante la tarea de adquisición del miedo, el 83% de los individuos de control y el 57% de los pacientes mostraron sensibilidad neurovegetativa («respondedores») y los pacientes mostraron mayor RCC al estímulo no emparejado con el estímulo incondicionado (EI) que los individuos de control. Dentro del grupo de respondedores, no hubo diferencias entre pacientes e individuos de control en los niveles de aprendizaje de la extinción; sin embargo, en comparación con los individuos de control, los pacientes con esquizofrenia manifestaron un deterioro significativo del recuerdo dependiente del contexto de la memoria de extinción. Además, en ellos la gravedad del delirio se correlacionó con los niveles de conductancia cutánea basal. Conclusiones: Los datos del presente estudio coinciden con las pruebas obtenidas en investigaciones previas de una mayor respuesta neural a los estímulos inocuos en la esquizofrenia y niveles de vigilia elevados en la psicosis. El hallazgo de un recuerdo deficiente de la extinción en pacientes con esquizofrenia que manifestaron un aprendizaje intacto de ella sugiere que la enfermedad se asocia con una alteración de los procesos neurales, que son la base de la memoria emocional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);17(1): 22-31, ene.-mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81120</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La memoria de extinción está deteriorada en la esquizofrenia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5206</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3237</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
