<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054619</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Involvement of neurosteroids in normal and pathological behaviour</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The nervous system synthesises steroids (then called neurosteroids) de novo from cholesterol. These    substances play a role in a number of functions related to the allosteric modulation of the main ionotropic receptors in the    central nervous system (CNS). Aim. To describe the most important behavioural and cognitive processes in which neurosteroids    are involved and which can open up new perspectives for research focused above all on their possible therapeutic use    in pathologies affecting the CNS, such as the cognitive impairment associated to neurodegenerative diseases, addictions like    alcoholism, anxiety disorders, and epilepsy and convulsive behaviour. Development. We provide a brief outline of the concept    of neurosteroids, their synthesis, how they act on receptors for neurotransmitters and their distribution throughout nerve    tissue. We then offer an extensive, up-to-date, critical review of the main psychological processes that they are involved in.    Conclusions. Neurosteroids offer an important therapeutic potential. In epileptiform behaviour, no tolerance is developed to    the anticonvulsive effects of these substances with repeated administration, unlike the case of benzodiazepines, although the    study of synthetic analogues and agents that step up the synthesis of neurosteroids in the CNS seems to be decisive owing to    the limitation imposed by the long-term systemic use of hormones. In anxiety disorders, they offer several advantages that are    comparable to the prototypical anxiolytic agents, that is, benzodiazepines, but also their chief side effects, such as sedation. In    cognitive impairment, the enormous potential for cognitive enhancement in animal models is not reproduced in humans with    dementia, although controlled clinical trials are needed to evaluate the benefits and risks of replacement therapy with steroids</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pallarès, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Darbra, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El sistema nervioso sintetiza esteroides (denominados entonces neuroesteroides) de novo a partir del    colesterol. Estas sustancias participan en numerosas funciones relacionadas con la modulación alostérica de los principales    receptores ionotrópicos del sistema nervioso central (SNC). Objetivo. Describir los procesos conductuales y cognitivos más    importantes en los que participan los neuroesteroides, y que pueden abrir nuevas perspectivas de investigación enfocadas    sobre todo a su posible uso terapéutico en patologías del SNC como el deterioro cognitivo asociado a enfermedades neurodegenerativas,    a adicciones como el alcoholismo, a los trastornos de ansiedad y a la epilepsia y la conducta convulsiva. Desarrollo.    Se describe sucintamente el concepto de neuroesteroide, su síntesis, sus acciones sobre los receptores para neurotransmisores    y su distribución por el tejido nervioso. Posteriormente se revisan de una manera extensa, actualizada, y crítica    los principales procesos psicológicos en los que están implicados. Conclusiones. Los neuroesteroides presentan un importante    potencial terapéutico. En la conducta epileptiforme, los efectos anticonvulsionantes de estas sustancias no se hacen tolerantes    con su administración repetida, como ocurre en el caso de las benzodiacepinas, aunque el estudio de análogos sintéticos    y de agentes que aumentan la síntesis de neuroesteroides en el SNC parece determinante debido a la limitación que plantea    la utilización sistémica de hormonas a largo plazo. En los trastornos de ansiedad presentan ventajas comparables a los    ansiolíticos prototípicos, las benzodiacepinas, pero también sus principales efectos adversos, como la sedación. En el deterioro    cognitivo, el enorme potencial facilitador cognitivo observado en modelos animales no se reproduce en humanos con demencia,    aunque se precisen ensayos clínicos controlados para evaluar beneficios y riesgos de los tratamientos sustitutivos con    esteroides</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;44(11): 661-676, jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054619</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Implicación de los neuroesteroides en la conducta normal y patológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1545^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32115^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13024^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31698^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
