<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166853</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A case of homocystinuria due to cystathionine beta-synthase deficiency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Homocystinuria is an inherited disorder of methionine metabolism, and has a high morbidity-mortality rate. Mutations in the cystathionine beta-synthase gene are the most common cause of homocystinuria, known as classic homocystinuria. More than 150 mutations have been described, with T191M being the most prevalent in Spain. Neonatal identification by newborn screening may prevent severe complications, and allow normal intellectual development. A case is presented of pyridoxine non-responsive homocystinuria due to T353 mutation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro Casado, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juncos Tobarra, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan García, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torío Ruiz, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La homocistinuria es un error innato del metabolismo de la metionina con una alta tasa de morbimortalidad. Mutaciones en la cistationina beta-sintetasa son la causa más frecuente de homocistinuria, conocida esta como homocistinuria clásica. Hay descritas más de 150 mutaciones diferentes, de las cuales la más prevalente en España es la T191M. La detección mediante cribado neonatal puede prevenir las complicaciones más graves de la enfermedad y posibilitar un desarrollo cognitivo normal. Presentamos un caso de homocistinuria clásica debida a la mutación T353M, con fenotipo no respondedor a piridoxina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;10(4): 212-216, oct.-dic. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166853</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Homocistinuria debida a deficiencia de cistationina beta-sintetasa. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6868^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8893^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3560^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3560^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5453^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
