<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158564</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Feasibility and results of the short Diet Quality Screener in Primary Care: EMAP study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the feasibility and results of the self-reported short diet quality screener (sDQS) in Primary Care. The variables associated with difficulty and inadequate diet are also determined. Method: Cross-sectional descriptive study conducted with 196 participants aged &gt;18 years with diabetes mellitus, hypertension, or hypercholesterolaemia, consecutively included from 4 Primary Health Care Centres in Barcelona. The main variables collected were, age, sex, educational level, cardiovascular risk factors, body mass index, time to complete the sDQS, degree of difficulty, and diet score: inadequate diet &amp;#8804;18, adequate in some aspects 19-27, adequate &gt;27. Results:The mean age was 48.8 years (52% males). The analysis of the variables showed that the prevalence of having higher than a primary education level, hypertension, diabetes, hypercholesterolemia, and obesity was 50%, 54.6%, 23.5%, 56.6%, and 27.5%, respectively. The mean time to complete the questionnaire was 2.3min. More than 80% considered it easy or very easy. An inadequate diet was reported by 21.4%, adequate in some aspects by 76.5%, and an adequate diet only by 2%. To be older than 49 years and a low diet quality increased the risk of needing &amp;#8805;2min to complete the sDQS (OR 2.0, 95% CI; 1.0-4.3, and OR 2.3, 95% CI; 1.1-5.1, respectively). Not following a low cholesterol diet and age less than 49 years increased the risk of a low diet quality (OR 2.2; 95% CI: 1.1-4.5, and OR 2.9; 95% CI: 1.2-6.8, respectively). Conclusions: The completion of the sDQS is easy and was not a significant time-burden in Primary Care. A significant proportion of participants with cardiovascular risk reported a low diet quality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calonge Vallejo, Ana Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Cerdán, María Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Rodríguez, María de los Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tobella Andreu, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schröder, Helmut</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baena Díez, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar la viabilidad y resultados del cuestionario autoadministrado sDQS en consultas de atención primaria y las variables asociadas a su dificultad y a una dieta inadecuada. Método: Estudio descriptivo transversal. Participaron 4 centros de salud de Barcelona. Se incluyeron consecutivamente 196 personas &gt;18 años con diabetes mellitus (DM), hipertensión arterial (HTA) o hipercolesterolemia mediante muestreo consecutivo. Las variables principales fueron: edad, sexo, nivel educacional, factores de riesgo cardiovascular, índice de masa corporal, tiempo, dificultad en rellenar el cuestionario y puntuación: dieta inadecuada &amp;#8804;18, adecuada en algunos aspectos 19-27, adecuada &gt;27. Resultados: La edad media fue de 48,8 años (52% varones). El 50% tenían estudios primarios o más. El 54,6% tenían HTA, el 23,5% DM, el 56,6% hipercolesterolemia y el 27,5% obesidad. El tiempo medio para completar el cuestionario fue 2,3min y &gt;80% lo consideraron fácil o muy fácil. Tenían dieta inadecuada el 21,4%, dieta adecuada en algunos aspectos el 76,5% y dieta adecuada el 2%. La edad &gt;49 años (OR 2,0; IC95%: 1,0-4,3) y la dieta inadecuada (OR 2,3; IC95%: 1,1-5,1) se asociaron a un tiempo &amp;#8805;2min para hacer el cuestionario. La edad &amp;#8804;49 años (OR 2,9; IC 95%: 1,2-6,8) y no realizar dieta hipolipemiante (OR 2,2; IC 95%: 1,1-4,5) se asociaron a dieta inadecuada. Conclusiones: El cuestionario autoadministrado sDQS es fácil de aplicar y no representa un aumento de tiempo importante en atención primaria. Una importante proporción de personas realiza una dieta de baja calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);26(6): 351-357, nov.-dic. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158564</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Viabilidad y resultados de un cuestionario breve de calidad dietética en atención primaria: estudio EMAP</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7130^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
