<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109174</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Humanized cesarean sections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To demonstrate the absence of short-term negative effects in cesarean sections followed by skin-to-skin contact, with or without the presence of a companion, and the greater satisfaction of these women. Material and method. A satisfaction survey was designed for use in all women who had undergone a cesarean section. A total of 300 questionnaires were analyzed. Results. Among women accompanied by companions, 98.2% considered this measure to be a source of support. The puerperium was normal in 94.2% of accompanied women versus 87.2% of those who were unaccompanied (p = 0.69). Conclusions. No negative effects on the mother or newborn are associated with either skin-to-skin contact after delivery or the presence of a companion during cesarean section(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tessier España, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hera Lázaro, Cristina de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver Pérez, María de los Reyes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camaño Gutiérrez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández García, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cotelo, Rocío Vellido</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Burguillo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Demostrar la ausencia de efectos negativos a corto plazo en aquellas cesáreas en las que se realiza piel con piel, con o sin la entrada del acompañante, así como una mayor satisfacción de dichas gestantes. Material y método. Se diseñó una encuesta de satisfacción que debía ser cumplimentada por todas las madres a las que se les había realizado una cesárea. Se analizaron 300 encuestas. Resultado. El 98,2% de las mujeres que estuvieron acompañadas consideraron que esto les sirvió de apoyo. El 94,2% de las mujeres con una cesárea con acompañante tuvieron un puerperio normal, frente al 87,2% de cesáreas sin acompañante (p = 0,69). Conclusiones. Tanto el contacto piel con piel como la entrada del acompañante durante una cesárea son actuaciones sin efectos negativos sobre la madre o su recién nacido(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(2): 73-78, feb. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109174</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cesárea humanizada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
