<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160862</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical characteristics and outcomes in a population with disseminated Herpes Zoster: a retrospective cohort study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Shingles is the cutaneous expression of the reactivation of latent varicella zoster virus infection in sensory ganglia. It presents as vesicles in the corresponding dermatome. The condition is called disseminated herpes zoster (DHZ) when more than 2 contiguous dermatomes are affected, more than 20 vesicles are observed outside the initial dermatome, or involvement is systemic. DHZ is rare and most frequently occurs in immunocompromised patients. Objectives. To describe the epidemiology, predisposing factors, clinical presentation, laboratory findings, and clinical course of patients with DHZ, and to compare the findings in immunocompromised and immunocompetent patients. Methodology. We analyzed a retrospective case series of adults hospitalized between February 2010 and October 2015. Results. Forty-one patients with virologically confirmed manifestations of DHZ were included. Stress as a trigger factor was detected in 39% and immunodepression in 58.5%. Immunocompromised patients were younger than the immunocompetent patients (mean ages, 60.5 vs 82 years, P&lt;.01). The 8 immunocompetent patients with no detectable trigger factors were older (mean age, 85 years). In 95% of cases, DHZ was initially limited to a single dermatome and then spread to other dermatomes or became disseminated. Thrombocytopenia was detected in 56% of cases. Complication rates were similar in immunocompromised and immunocompetent patients (54% vs 59%, P&gt;.01). Six patients died; there was no difference in mortality between the 2 groups. Conclusion. This study provides evidence on the relationship between DHZ, the presence of underlying immunodepression, and complications. Immunosenescence may play an important role in the onset of this disease in older immunocompetent patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferreyro, BL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bollea-Garlatti, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galimberti, RL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vacas, AS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, AC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kowalczuk, AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bollea-Garlatti, LA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El herpes zoster es la expresión cutánea de la reactivación de una infección latente en ganglios sensitivos por el virus varicela zoster que se presenta con vesículas en el dermatoma correspondiente. Cuando compromete más de 2 dermatomas contiguos, presenta más de 20 vesículas por fuera del dermatoma inicial o tiene compromiso sistémico se denomina herpes zoster diseminado (HZD). Esta entidad es infrecuente y se suele presentar en pacientes inmunodeprimidos. Objetivos. Describir la epidemiología, factores predisponentes, clínica, laboratorio y evolución clínica de pacientes con HZD. Comparar hallazgos entre inmunodeprimidos e inmunocompetentes. Metodología. Estudio de una serie de casos retrospectiva, en adultos ingresados entre febrero de 2010 y octubre de 2015. Resultados. Se incluyeron 41 pacientes con cuadro clínico de HZD y confirmación virológica. Se detectaron factores de estrés desencadenantes en el 39% y de inmunodepresión en el 58,5%. Los inmunodeprimidos fueron más jóvenes que los inmunocompetentes (60,5 vs 82 años, p&lt;0,01). En 8 casos sin inmunodepresión ni desencadenantes se halló mayor edad (85 años). En el 95% de los casos el HZD comenzó en dermatomas definidos, y luego se extendió a otros o se generalizó. El 56% de los casos presentó trombocitopenia asociada. Las complicaciones afectaron por igual a inmunodeprimidos e inmunocompetentes (54% vs 59%, p&gt;0,01). Fallecieron 6 pacientes, sin diferencias de mortalidad entre ambos grupos. Conclusión. Este estudio aporta evidencia sobre la relación entre el HZD, la presencia de inmunosupresión subyacente y las posibles complicaciones. En pacientes inmunocompetentes, por inmunosenescencia, la edad podría desempeñar un papel importante en la aparición de esta enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;108(2): 145-152, mar. 2017. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160862</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características clínicas y evolutivas de una población con herpes zoster diseminado: un estudio de cohorte retrospectiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30040^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30040^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29202^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6721^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
