<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052664</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Plantar fascitis. Orthopodologic treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Plantar fasciitis is a condition characterized by heel pain. Is the most common cause of heel pain. Plantar fasciitis is the inflammation of the fascia at its origin on the calcaneus. Is characterized by pain located in the antero-internal area of the calcaneus that can be irradiated toward the internal border of the foot. After the inflammatory process, if the pathology persists in a lingering way, degenerative changes can take place. The subjects generally present associated biomechanical alterations as aetiological cause of the fasciitis. These biomechanical alterations could be pronación excess, pes cavus, equine foot, metatarsal pes cavus, or unequeal leg length. All of this conditions are susceptible of being treated by ortopaedic treatment with foot orthoses. The use of foot orthoses allows the normal function of the foot from its neuter position avoiding compensations, understanding that these compensations produces the increase of tension and therefore the inflammation of the fascia. Some studies evidence that the personalized foot orthoses are effective in the treatment of plantar fasciitis when the cause is a biomechanical desequilibre</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Rodríguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Nova, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Martín, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fraile García, P. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fascitis plantar es la causa más frecuente de talalgia y consiste en la inflamación del origen de la fascia a nivel de la tuberosidad antero-interna del calcáneo. Produce dolor localizado en la zona antero-interna del talón, que puede irradiarse hacia el borde interno del pie. Tras el proceso inflamatorio, si la patología persiste de forma prolongada, pueden producirse cambios degenerativos. Generalmente los pacientes presentan alteraciones biomecánicas asociadas como causa etiológica de la fascitis. Estas alteraciones biomecánicas pueden ser el exceso de pronación, pie cavo, pie equino, seudoequino o cavo anterior y asimetrías en la longitud de las extremidades inferiores. Todas estas alteraciones son susceptibles de ser tratadas mediante tratamiento ortopodológico con soportes plantares. El uso de los tratamientos ortopodológicos permite la función normal del pie desde su posición neutra evitando compensaciones, que son las que producen el aumento de tensión y por tanto la inflamación de la fascia. Existen estudios que evidencian que el tratamiento ortopodológico personalizado es eficaz en el tratamiento de la fascitis plantar cuando la causa es una alteración biomecánica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(2): 106-112, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052664</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fascitis Plantar. Tratamiento ortopodológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37270^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8521^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
