<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119242</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Professional psychologists and university training in psychology: looking for references to the Degree in Psychology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The university Degree in Psychology includes a wide variety of content related to different profiles. However, some of them are more useful than others in the professional practice. Therefore, the objective of this study consisted of describing the opinion on the subject of graduates in psychology. With this purpose, a specific questionnaire was designed. The questions were related to the possession and use of knowledge related to each professional profile and also to the content considered the most and the least useful when practicing professional psychology. Also, question related to the possible changes to that degree were included. The most important results demonstrate high demand for practices and the best knowledge and perceived usefulness of the clinical profile, intervention in drug abuse, education and social intervention. These findings should be taken into account when designing curricula in the degree (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zych, Izabela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Ruiz, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los estudios de licenciatura en psicología incluyen una gran variedad de contenidos relacionados con diferentes perfiles profesionales. No obstante, algunos de ellos tienen más utilidad que otros a la hora de ejercer dicha profesión. Por ello, el objetivo del presente estudio ha consistido en describir cuál es la opinión al respecto de licenciadas y licenciados en psicología. Con ese objetivo, se diseñó y administró un cuestionario específico con preguntas relacionadas con la posesión y utilidad de conocimientos relacionados con cada perfil y otras relacionadas con contenidos más y menos útiles a la hora de ejercer la labor de psicólogo y la propuesta de cambios en dicha titulación. Los resultados más importantes demuestran una gran demanda de prácticas y el mayor conocimiento y utilidad percibida del perfil clínico, intervención en drogodependencias, educación e intervención social. Estos hallazgos deberían tenerse en cuenta a la hora de diseñar planes de estudios en dicha titulación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);13(1): 83-96, mar. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Profesionales de la psicología y formación universitaria: buscando referencias para el título de Grado en Psicología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35237</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
