<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149567</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of COPD-6 Vitalograph in Primary Care as tool for smoking cessation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. Primary objective: To assess the evolution of smoking cessation process after using a COPD-6 Vitalograph in smokers that came to a primary care practice (PCP) during a three year period (March 2011- February 2013). Secondary objectives: To assess if there are any new COPD diagnoses and to compare the smoking cessation outcomes to those of a specific smoking cessation practice (SSCP) from another healthcare centre. Methodology. Two devices were used: Vitalograph (electronic device measuring the lung function) and the CO-oximeter, in 176 patients (active search of smokers). Variables: tobacco pack-years, tobacco dependence (shortened Fagerström test), CO in exhaled breath (in parts per million-ppm), personal history of COPD or cardiovascular disease (CVD). The patients performed three forced exhalations and the Vitalograph registered the lung function (FEV1, FEV6, FEV1/FEV6) and the estimated lung age (ELA). Patient attitude was assessed (phases: pre-contemplation, contemplation, preparation) before and after the test, informing them of the outcomes. Patient progress in the smoking cessation process was also recorded. Results. A total of 176 smokers were studied in PCP and 33 in SSCP. PCP/SSCP: age: 45.9/51.6 years old (p = 042); pack-years 25.5/39.3 (p = 0001); patients who quit smoking and used medicines for it 2/9. In PCP: age&#150;ELA 45.9/57.4 (p = 0.000). In SSCP: age-ELA 51.6/74.3 (p = 000). Smoking habit evolution PCP/SSCP: cessation 24.5%/48.5% (p = 004). Difference 24%. CI difference (6.4-42.8%). In PCP new COPD diagnosis in 6 smokers. Conclusions. COPD-6 Vitalograph is a fast and easy to use tool in day-to-day practice. The percentage of smoking cessation is better in SSCP, although a high smoking cessation rate was obtained in PCP (active search) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pruteanu, DF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón-García, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correcher-Salvador, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Principal: valorar la evolución del tabaquismo tras usar el Vitalograph COPD-6 en los fumadores que acuden a una consulta de medicina familiar (CMF) a lo largo de 3 años (3/2011-2/2013). Secundarios: valorar si se producen nuevos diagnósticos de EPOC y comparar los datos de abandono tabáquico con los de una consulta específica de tabaquismo (CET) de otro CS. Metodología. Se ha utilizado el vitalograph (medidor manual electrónico de la función pulmonar) y el cooxímetro en 176 fumadores (búsqueda activa). Variables: nivel de consumo (paquetes/año), grado dependencia tabáquica (test de Fageström breve), CO exhalado en partes por millón (ppm), antecedentes personales de EPOC o enfermedad cardiovascular (ECV). El paciente realiza 3 maniobras de espiración forzada y el vitalograph registra la función pulmonar (FEV1, FEV6, FEV1/FEV6) y la edad pulmonar estimada (EPE). Valoramos la actitud del paciente (fases: precontemplación, contemplación y preparación) antes y después de realizar la prueba e indicarle los resultados. Valoración de la evolución tabáquica de los pacientes. Resultados. En la CMF se han evaluado 176 fumadores y en la CET 33. CMF/CET: edad 45,9/51,6 años (p = 0,042); paquetes año 25,5/39,3 (p = 0,0001); pacientes que abandonan tabaquismo que utilizan fármacos para deshabituación 2/9. En CMF: edad-EPE 45,9/57,4 (p = 0,000). En CET: edad-EPE 51,6/74,3 (p = 0,000). Evolución consumo CMF/CET: abandono 24,5%/48,5% (p = 0,004). IC diferencia (6,4-42,8%). En CMF nuevo diagnóstico EPOC en 6 fumadores. Conclusiones. El Vitalograph COPD-6 es un instrumento fácil y rápido de usar en la consulta diaria. El porcentaje de abandono tabáquico en la CMF (búsqueda activa) el abandono logrado es alto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);42(2): 75-80, mar. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149567</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso del Vitalograph COPD-6 en atención primaria como herramienta para la deshabituación tabáquica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
