<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96844</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Monoarthritis in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Monoarthritis, defined as the inflammation of a joint, may be either acute or chronic and arise from a variety of causes. Septic arthritis is responsible for the highest rates of morbidity and mortality. The most common cause is the presence of microcrystals. A clinical history and careful physical examination are of great help in establishing the cause. Bilateral radiographs of the joints are essential. Unless contraindicated, arthrocentesis should be undertaken to establish the etiologic diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Revuelta Evrard, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La monoartritis es la inflamación de una articulación, que puede ser aguda o crónica. Su etiología es múltiple, siendo la artritis séptica el cuadro con mayor morbimortalidad. La monoartritis por microcristales es la más frecuente. Una historia clínica y una exploración física precisa resulta de gran ayuda para establecer el diagnóstico etiológico de la enfermedad. La radiología bilateral de las articulaciones resulta fundamental. Siempre que no esté contraindicado debería realizarse una artrocentesis para el diagnóstico etiológico de una monoartritis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(3): 218-225, jun. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monoartritis en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23228^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7760^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23949^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
