<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88789</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Presentation of positive stimuli like procedure to control the anxiety in sressful situations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study has been realized by the interest of valued individualemente based experimentally the development of a model of intervention for the decrease of the anxiety, by means of the presentation of positive stimuli. The characteristics of the sample are the following ones: 60 sportsmen of Seville (average of age 21,6 years), divided by sex and type of sport (indivdual or of equipment). This study is the integration of the results of the profile psicofisiológico and those of the effect of the presentation of words and positive images in the sportsmen's anxiety of competition, for feedback of failure. Lops proved with the analysis of variance of repeated measures, is the following ones: There are significant differences in the temperature of the left hand F (3,168) = 35,330 p=0,000; significant Differences in the temperature of the right hand F (3,168) = 40,750 p=0,000; significant Differences in the cardiac pulse F (3,168) = 48,378 p = 0,000; significant Differences in the subjective evaluation F (3,168) = 56,560 p=0,000. In conclusion, the profile psicofisiológico is a useful tool for the evaluation of the anxiety and in this case in him sport, in turn the presentation indivdualizada of words and positive images has showed a trend to the disminucuón of the response of anxiety. The obtained results reveal the relevancy of this practice ( Exhibition to positive stimuli) to control the anxiety, suggesting, thus, his usefulness in programs of therapeutic intervention directed to the control and managings of this emotional response (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estrada Contreras, Omar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Fernández, M. Angeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Córdoba, Eugenio A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio se ha realizado con el interés de fundamentar experimentalmente el desarrollo de un modelo de intervención para la disminución de la ansiedad, por medio de la presentación de estímulos positivos, valorados individualemente. Las características de la muestra son las siguientes: 60 deportistas de Sevilla (media de edad 21,6 años), divididos por sexo y tipo de deporte (indivdual o de equipo). Este estudio es la integración de los resultados del perfil psicofisiológico y los del efecto de la presentación de palabras e imágenes positivas en la ansiedad de deportistas de competición, por retroalimentación de fracaso. Lops resultados con el análisis de varianza de medidas repetidas, son los siguientes: Hay diferencias significativas en la temperatura de la mano izquierda F (3,168)= 35,330 p=0,000; Diferencias significativas en la temperatura de la mano derecha F (3,168)= 40,750 p=0,000; Diferencias significativas en el pulso cardiaco F (3,168)= 48,378 p= 0,000; Diferencias significativas en la evaluación subjetiva F (3,168)= 56,560 p=0,000. En conclusión, el perfil psicofisiológico es una herramienta útil para la evaluación de la ansiedad y en este caso en él deporte, a su vez la presentación indivdualizada de palabras e imágenes positivas ha mostrado una tendencia a la disminucuón de la respuesta de ansiedad. Los resultados obtenidos ponen de manifiesto la relevancia de esta práctica (exposición a estímulos positivos) para controlar la ansiedad, sugiriendo, de este modo, su utilidad en programas de intervención terapéutica encaminados al control y manejos de esta respuesta emocional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;28(2): 225-236, mayo-ago. 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88789</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Presentación de estímulos positivos como procedimiento para controlar la ansiedad en situaciones estresantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7349^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7349^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7349^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7349^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7349^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7349^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7349^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
