<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-25869</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cognitive and behavioral approaches: an evaluation of two programmes with unemployed</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">According to the Bureau of Labour Organisation in 2000 there were sixty million people between 15-24 looking actively for a job (BLO, 2001). The psychologists are aware of this problem and have developed programmes to help the unemployed enter into the working life. In this study we compare the effectiveness of two schemes developed to enhance the skills of the unemployed to get a job. The results suggest that the cognitive treatment reduced the period of search, and facilitated the transition of the young into the working life. Nevertheless, previous research has showed that the effectiveness of these programmes is closely related to the profile of the target group. Keeping this in mind, we finally turn to specific guidelines that set the stage for effective use of these schemes with young unemployed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aramburu-Zabala Higuera, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Según la Organización Internacional del Trabajo en 2000 había sesenta millones de jóvenes entre 15 y 24 años que buscaban activamente un trabajo (OIT, 2001). Los psicólogos son conscientes de este problema y han elaborado programas de intervención para ayudar a los desempleados a incorporarse a la vida activa. En este artículo se compara la eficacia de dos modelos de intervención cuya meta es mejorar las destrezas de los jóvenes para conseguir empleo. Los resultados del estudio sugieren que la intervención cognitiva reduce el tiempo de búsqueda y facilita la transición al mundo del trabajo. Sin embargo, otras investigaciones han probado que la efectividad de los programas depende estrechamente del perfil del grupo meta. Por esta razón, en la parte final presentamos una serie de directrices para mejorar la eficacia de estos programas con desempleados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(2): 183-189, mayo 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-25869</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfoques cognitivo y conductual: evaluación de dos programas de intervención con desempleados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7754</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14877^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
