<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92726</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">nterview that occupies to us, bases on experience lived by pair (Elia and Daniel) who wanted to live the childbirth of their first daughter (Illary) of the possible most natural form, for that reason decided that it was born at home. Their access to institutions or professionals (midwives) who helped them to make their desire, it was relatively easy to live in an autonomous community (Cataluña) in which the supply with respect to the childbirth at home is superior to other communities within the existing shortage in such scope. After inquiring into the process and the existing supply, they were decided by a specialized association, which was part or the midwife comprised that finally took care of them (real name are omitted). The title given to this history, peixet (translated the Castilian it means the small fish), is due to this being the affectionate nickname given by these parents to their daughter, when taking place the birth in the water. Their final valuation of the childbirth is positive, wishing to repeat it, in spite of the economic cost and of the lack of support and social understanding (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Feijóo, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El relato biográfico que nos ocupa, se basa en la experiencia vivida por una pareja (Elia y Daniel) que quería vivir el parto de su primera hija (Illary) de la forma más natural posible, por eso decidieron que naciera en casa. Su acceso a instituciones o profesionales (matronas) que los ayudaran a realizar su deseo, fue relativamente fácil, al vivir en una comunidad autónoma (Cataluña) en la que la oferta con respecto al parto en casa es superior a otras comunidades, dentro de la escasez existente en tal ámbito. Tras informarse del proceso y de la oferta existente, se decidieron por una asociación especializada, de la que formaba parte la matrona que finalmente los atendió (se omiten nombres reales). El título dado a esta historia, el peixet (traducido al castellano significa el pececillo), se debe a ser este el apodo cariñoso dado por estos padres a su hija, al producirse el nacimiento en el agua. Su valoración final del parto es positiva, deseando repetirla, a pesar del coste económico y de la falta de apoyo y comprensión social (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;18(1): 57-60, ene. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El &#147;peixet&#148;. La experiencia de parir en casa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9514</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32196^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
