<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88302</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testicular Tumours in Infancy and children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: prepubertal testicular tumours are different from those that appear during adulthood. Traditionally, they were considered to be malignant, however benign testicular tumours are actually more frequent at this age. Materials and methods: we analysed our experience in the treatment of testicular tumours in children &amp;#8804; 13, with the intention of evaluating the use of partial orchiectomy. From 1984 to 2008, we diagnosed and treated 15 testicular tumours in children at our centre. We examined the therapeutic approach employed, underlining the possibility of testicular conservation in selected patients and we have analysed the results. Results: the clinical presentation in 80% of the cases was an increase in testicle size with palpable mass. We performed 4 radical orchiectomies (27%) and 11 tumourectomies (73%). All the benign lesions in the final pathological anatomy were treated with tumourectomy: four epidermoid cysts, one hemangioma, one lipoma, one fibrous hamartoma, one juvenile granulosa tumour and one splenogonadal fusion. We also successfully and conservatively treated two cases of teratoma. The cases that received radical treatment were a yolk sac tumour (Stage I), two mixed germ cell tumours and one gonadoblastoma. Conclusions: there are more cases of benign testicular tumours than malignant tumours during puberty. In the event of a palpable testicular mass with negative tumour markers, conservative treatment by means of a tumourectomy may be considered. However, the lesion must be removed completely to prevent recurrence (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villavicencio, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angerri, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garat, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caffaratti, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bujons, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los tumores testiculares prepuberales son distintos a los que se presentan en la edad adulta. Tradicionalmente han sido considerados malignos, pero realmente los tumores testiculares benignos son más frecuentes en esta edad. Material y métodos: revisamos nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento de los tumores testiculares en niños &amp;#8804; 13 años con intención de evaluar el empleo de orquiectomía parcial. Desde 1984 hasta 2008 hemos diagnosticado y tratado en nuestro centro 15 tumores testiculares en edad pediátrica. Se revisa la actitud terapéutica empleada con énfasis en la posibilidad de preservación testicular en pacientes seleccionados y se evalúan los resultados. Resultados: la forma de presentación clínica en el 80% de los casos fue aumento del tamaño testicular con masa palpable. Se realizaron 4 orquiectomías radicales (27%) y 11 tumorectomías (73%). Todas las lesiones benignas en la anatomía patológica definitiva fueron tratadas con tumorectomía: cuatro quistes epidermoides, un hemangioma, un lipoma, un hamartoma fibroso, un tumor de la granulosa juvenil y una fusión espleno-gonadal. También fueron tratados con éxito de forma conservadora dos casos de teratoma. Los casos tratados de manera radical fueron un caso de tumor de saco vitelino (estadio I), dos tumores germinales mixtos y un gonadoblastoma. Conclusiones: los tumores testiculares en la edad prepuberal benignos predominan sobre los malignos. Ante una masa testicular palpable con marcadores tumorales negativos se puede plantear un tratamiento conservador mediante tumorectomía. No obstante, la lesión debe ser completamente extirpada para evitar recurrencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;35(2): 93-98, feb. 2011. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88302</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores testiculares en la infancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6376^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6542^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8242^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4895^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
