<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97373</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of amniotic membrane dressings in patients with skin damage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The application of amniotic membranes in patients diagnosed with skin damage is a valid treatment option. A care plan following the Virginia Henderson model and NANDA, NOC and NIC taxonomy was applied to 36 patients admitted to the Dr. Miguel Enríquez hospital with different cutaneous lesions. This membrane has already been used for years due to its healing properties. These are attributed to antimicrobial properties reducing infection risk and promoting epithelial activity. They can decrease the need for the use of antibiotics, expendable materials, and can be applied during long periods of healing. This decreases the cost of wide spectrum antibiotic treatments, as well as the time patients spend in hospital. We present the results of this application in cases with several types of skin lesions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Noa Hernández,  Jose Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera González, Elier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Rojo, Carlos A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aplicación de membrana amniótica en pacientes con diagnóstico enfermero de deterioro de la integridad cutánea es una alternativa válida. Se aplicó el plan de cuidaos según el modelo de Virginia Henderson y la taxonomía NANDA, NOC y NIC a 36 pacientes ingresados en el hospital Dr. Miguel Enríquez con diferentes lesiones cutáneas. Esta membrana se ha utilizado hace ya algunos años por sus propiedades curativas. Se le atribuyen propiedades antimicrobianas reduciendo el riesgo de infección y actividad promotora de epitelización. Permiten disminuir el uso de antibióticos, materiales gastables y aplicación entre curas de periodos prolongados; lo que permite disminuir los costos por tratamientos de antibióticos de amplio espectro, así como el tiempo de hospitalización de los pacientes. Por sus resultados presentamos estos casos de aplicación en varios tipos de lesiones de la piel (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);21(1): 43-46, ene.-feb. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97373</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de apósitos de membrana amniótica en pacientes con deterioro de la integridad cutánea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32666^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31039^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54250^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d665</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15344^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
