<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143626</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adolescents and video games</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The appearance of video games as a form of child and adolescent entertainment has raised a great deal of debate and concem about the possible negative consequences they could have on the development and the behaviour of those that play with them on a regular basis. In this study. 207 adolescents aged 10 to 17 from different primary and secondary schools in Huelva were selected. The results indicate that this activity is quite extended among youths, with certain differences related to gender: most video game players are male, and they spend more than twice the time on this activity than female players. On the other hand, video players and non video players do not differ significantly on academic achievement or the basic structure of personality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López López, M José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Jariego, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de los videojuegos como forma de entretenimiento de niños y adolescentes ha suscitado una gran polémica y preocupación acerca de las posibles consecuencias negativas que pudieran tener sobre el desarrollo y la conducta de aquellos que los utilizan con regularidad. En este trabajo se seleccionan 207 adolescentes entre 10 Y 17 años pertenecientes a distintos centros escolares de Primaria y Secundaria de Huelva capital. Los resultados indican que el grado de implantación de esta actividad es bastante elevado, apareciendo de forma manifiesta diferencias asociadas al género: la mayoría de videojugadores son chicos, dedicando más del doble de tiempo que las chicas. Por otra parte, videojugadores y no videojugadores no difieren significativamente ni en cuanto al rendimiento ni en la estructura básica de personalidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;21(1): 89-99, 2003. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los adolescentes y los videojuegos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14876</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32579^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
