<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162312</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of family in patient with neurological pathology and acute confusional syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Given the type of pathology and age of patients in the inpatient unit of Neurology, Hospital de Cabueñes (Gijón), acute confusional syndrome (ACS) is very common in this service. Objective. To determine the influence of the family, within the limits of the hospital, in patients with neurological disease suffering from SCA. Methodology. A prospective, observational, descriptive study of 53 patients with neurological disease that suffered from SCA was performed. The study variables were: disorientation, agitation, medication, effectiveness, and body grip on each shift with and without family. All those patients suffering from any dementia or psychiatric problem before entering were discarded. Results. The mean age of the patients was 83 years old. The most common pathology was ICTUS. The patients with family were 47.4 % versus 52.6 % without family in three shifts. 70.3 % of the patients became disoriented with family; for patients without family the percentage increased up to 83.8 %. As far as nervousness is concerned, 11.4 % of the patients with family experienced this behaviour in the three shifts; nofamily patients suffering from nervousness were 29.4 %. Medication was administered to 33 % of the patients with family, and to 44 % of no-family patients. The effectiveness was 66.5 % for patients with family and 48 % for no-family patients. The use of body grip in the three shifts was 7.6 % for patients with family and 64.5 % for no-family patients. Conclusions. Family has a beneficial effect on neurological patients with ACS, specially by reducing the use of mechanical restraint, helping to preserve the dignity of elderly patients in an adverse environment such as hospital (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gómez, M Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la Unidad de Hospitalización de Neurología del Hospital de Cabueñes (Gijón), por el tipo de patología y edad de los pacientes, el síndrome confusional agudo (SCA) es muy frecuente. Objetivo. Determinar la influencia que ejerce la familia, dentro del ámbito hospitalario, en el paciente con patología neurológica, que presenta SCA. Metodología. Se realizó un estudio observacional, descriptivo prospectivo de 53 pacientes con patología neurológica que presentaron SCA. Las variables a estudio fueron: desorientación, agitación, medicación, efectividad y sujeción en cada turno, con familia y sin familia. Se descartaron todos aquellos pacientes que padecían, antes del ingreso, cualquier tipo de demencia o problema psiquiátrico. Resultados. La edad media de los pacientes estudiados fue de 83 años. La patología más común fue el ictus. Con familia estuvieron un 47.4 %, frente a un 52.6 % sin familia en los tres turnos. Se desorientó un 70.3 % con familia, frente a un 83.8 % sin familia. En cuanto a la agitación, con familia fue el 11.4 % en los tres turnos. Sin familia el 29.4 %. Se administró medicación con familia en el 33 %. Sin familia en el 44 %. La efectividad con familia fue de un 66.5 % y sin familia de un 48 %. La sujeción con familia fue del 7.6 % en los tres turnos y sin familia del 64.5 %. Conclusiones. La familia produce un efecto beneficioso en el paciente neurológico con SCA, sobre todo reduciendo el uso de contención mecánica, ayudando a preservar la dignidad del paciente anciano dentro de un medio adverso como es el hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;40(4): 281-286, abr. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162312</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la familia en el paciente hospitalizado con patología neurológica cuando presete síndrome confusional agudo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3707^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
