<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166171</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessing myocardial viability by magnetic resonance imaging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Assessment of residual myocardial viability in a patient with severe regional or global left ventricular systolic dysfunction is clinically important for planning therapy because revascularization of dysfunctional, but viable, myocardium may improve left ventricular function and prognosis. Cardiac magnetic resonance enables the myocardium to be visualized with an excellent spatial resolution, which is not as dependent on the patient&#146;s physical condition as echocardiography. Moreover, radioactive materials are not required. Cardiac magnetic resonance can detect and assess myocardial viability using a number of different techniques. At present, the most readily available and promising method is based on delayed contrast enhancement with gadolinium. Available data show that cardiac magnetic resonance is superior to other currently used techniques. The combination of delayed contrast enhancement and low-dose dobutamine cardiac magnetic resonance seems to provide the best method for predicting functional recovery after revascularization. Therefore, cardiac magnetic resonance must be regarded as an established technique for evaluating myocardial viability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catalán, Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caralt, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pare, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asín, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La identificación de la viabilidad miocárdica residual en un paciente con una importante disfunción sistólica ventricular regional o global es de gran relevancia clínica para planificar la estrategia terapéutica, ya que la revascularización del miocardio disfuncionante pero viable puede mejorar la función ventricular izquierda y el pronóstico. La cardiorresonancia magnética (CRM) permite la visualización del miocardio con una excelente resolución espacial, que no es tan dependiente de la constitución física del paciente como la ecocardiografía ni implica el uso de productos radiactivos. La CRM puede detectar y evaluar la viabilidad miocárdica mediante diferentes técnicas, pero la de mejor disponibilidad y la más prometedora está basada en el realce tardío con gadolinio. Los datos disponibles muestran que la CRM es superior a otras técnicas usadas actualmente. El mejor método para predecir la recuperación funcional después de la revascularización parece ser el uso combinado del realce tardío y dosis bajas de dobutamina con CRM. Por tanto, la CRM debe ser considerada entre las técnicas establecidas para evaluar la viabilidad miocárdica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);6(supl.E): 49e-56e, 2006. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la viabilidad miocárdica mediante resonancia magnética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52612^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3346^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28085</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31288^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
