<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048803</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relationship between the levels of salivary cortisol and the presence of xerostomia in menopausal women. A preliminary study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Xerostomia is a particularly frequent occurrence among menopausal women, and is often associated with depression.Objectives: To evaluate the relationship between unstimulated salivary flow rate and the presence of xerostomia, and to determine the levels of salivary cortisol and its relationship with xerostomia.Study design: Thirty women were selected from patients attending the Department of Medicine and Buccofacial surgery, and formed into two groups, study and control. Samples of unstimulated salivary flow were collected, and the amounts of salivary cortisol determined using the ELISA technique (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay).Results: The mean unstimulated salivary flow rates for the control and study group were 0.37 ± 0.28 ml/min and 0.24 ± 0.18 ml/min, respectively. The concentration of salivary cortisol was 3.47 ± 1.64 ng/ml for the control group and 2.29 ± 2.60 ng/ml for the study group. The statistical tests applied showed no significant differences for either variable between the two groups in the study</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Pintor, Rosa M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Vallejo, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Cantor, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arriba de la Fuente, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera Gómez, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La xerostomía es un síntoma especialmente frecuente en las mujeres en torno a la menopausia, que se asocia en muchas ocasiones con estados depresivos.Objetivos: Valorar la relación entre las cifras del flujo salival total no estimulado y la presencia de xerostomía, y determinarlos niveles de cortisol salival y su relación con la misma.Diseño del estudio: Se seleccionaron 30 mujeres de los pacientes que acuden al Departamento de Medicina y Cirugía Bucofacial y se formaron dos grupos, estudio y control. Se recogieron muestras de flujo salival total no estimulado y mediante técnica de ELISA se determinaron las cifras de cortisol salival.Resultados: Las medias de flujo salival total no estimulado para el grupo control y estudio fueron de 0.37± 0.28 ml/min. y de 0.24± 0.18 ml/min. respectivamente. La concentración de cortisol salival fue de 3.47± 1.64 ng/ml. para el grupo control y de 2.29± 2.60 ng/ml. para el grupo estudio. Las pruebas estadísticas aplicadas no mostraron diferencias significativasentre los dos grupos del estudio para ambas variables.Conclusiones: Los resultados del presente estudio indican que no existe relación entre las variaciones en el flujo salival total no estimulado y las concentraciones de cortisol correspondientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(5): 407-412, ago. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048803</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre los niveles de cortisol salival y la presencia de xerostomía en mujeres menopaúsicas. Estudio preliminar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15386^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12847^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15386^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22498^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12844^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12838^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12838^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
