<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112903</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of acute coronary syndromes in Spain: estimation of the number of cases and trends from 2005 to 2049</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Acute coronary syndromes are a leading cause of mortality, morbidity, and health care cost in Spain. The aims of this report are to estimate the number of acute coronary syndromes cases in the Spanish population in 2013 and 2021, and the trend from 2005 to 2049. We estimated the number of acute coronary syndromes cases by sex and Spanish autonomous community using data from the most updated population and hospital registries. We present the estimated number of cases with an exact 95% confidence interval, assuming that the number of cases followed a Poisson distribution. There will be 115 752 acute coronary syndromes cases in Spain in 2013 (95% confidence interval, 114 822-116 687). Within 28 days, 39 086 of these patients will die and 85 326 will be hospitalized. Non-ST segment elevation acute coronary syndromes (56%) and acute myocardial infarction (81%) will be the most common admission and discharge diagnoses, respectively. We estimate approximately 109 772 acute coronary syndromes cases in 2021 (95% confidence interval, 108 868-110 635). The trend of acute coronary syndromes cases from 2005 to 2049 will stabilize in the population aged 25 to 74 years, but increase in those older than 74 years. Due to population aging, the number of acute coronary syndrome cases will increase overall until 2049, it may stabilize in the population aged &lt;75 years. The acute coronary syndromes case-fatality has decreased in hospitalized patients but the proportion of sudden deaths remains unchanged (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dégano, Irene R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elosua, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrugat, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome coronario agudo es una de las principales causas de mortalidad, morbilidad y coste sanitario en España. Los objetivos del presente estudio son estimar el número de casos de síndrome coronario agudo en España en 2013 y 2021, así como la tendencia en el periodo 2005¿2049. Se estimó el número de casos de síndrome coronario agudo según el sexo y la comunidad autónoma utilizando datos de los registros más actualizados. Se presenta el número de casos estimado y el intervalo de confianza exacto del 95% asumiendo una distribución de Poisson. En 2013 habrá unos 115.752 (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 114.822-116.687) casos de síndrome coronario agudo en España. De estos, 39.086 morirán durante los primeros 28 días y 85.326 serán hospitalizados. Los diagnósticos más comunes al ingreso y al alta serán síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del ST (56%) e infarto agudo de miocardio (81%) respectivamente. En 2021 el número de casos de síndrome coronario agudo se situará en 109.772 (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 108.868-110.635). La tendencia en el número de casos de síndrome coronario agudo entre 2005 y 2049 tenderá a estabilizarse en la población de 25 a 74 años y aumentar significativamente en la población mayor de 74 años. Los casos de síndrome coronario agudo aumentarán hasta el año 2049 debido al envejecimiento de la población, aunque parece estabilizarse en la población menor de 75 años. La letalidad del síndrome coronario agudo entre los pacientes hospitalizados se ha reducido, pero la proporción de muertes súbitas se mantiene sin cambios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;66(6): 472-481, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112903</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología del síndrome coronario agudo en España: estimación del número de casos y la tendencia de 2005 a 2049</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d800^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d800^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11758^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30163^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16128</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3662^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50289</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
