<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042997</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Schizophreniform disorder. A 5-year prospective follow-up study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: We performed a 5-year prospective study to evaluate the temporal stability of a provisional diagnosis of schizophreniform disorder (SFD) and evaluate the predictive value of the good prognostic features defined in the DSM-IV. Subjects and Methods: The sample consisted of 38 patients (23 men and 15 women) admitted to our hospital from 1996 to 1998 for a first psychotic episode. Four follow-up interviews were obtained: at the first, second, third and fifth years of follow-up. Patients were evaluated by means of the Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS), the Strauss-Carpenter Scale, the Structured Clinical Interview of the DSM-IV (SCID) and the Global Assessment of Functioning Scale (GAF Scale) of the DSM-IV. Results: Twenty-seven patients completed the study. A total of 25.9% retained the diagnosis of SFD and 59.2% were classified as having a disorder of the schizophrenic spectrum. The presence of good prognostic features at the index admission was associated with better outcome, but not with maintenance of the diagnosis of SFD. After 5 years of follow-up, patients with SFD showed significantly better outcomes than did schizophrenic patients. Conclusions: After 5 years of follow-up most of the patients continued to have symptoms and met the criteria for schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder, confirming the low stability of a provisional diagnosis of SFD. The results of this study suggest an association between good prognostic features and better outcome, but not with maintenance of a diagnosis of SFD</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Egea, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Sola, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corripio-Collado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Quiroga, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Blanco, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escartí, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Martínez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Estudio prospectivo de 5 años, cuyo objetivo es evaluar la estabilidad temporal del diagnóstico de trastorno esquizofreniforme (TE) provisional y evaluar la validez predictiva de las características de buen pronóstico que define el Manual Diagnóstico y Estadístico de los Trastornos Mentales (DSM-IV). Sujetos y métodos: La muestra consta de 38 pacientes (23 varones y 15 mujeres) ingresados en el hospital, entre 1996 y 1998, por un primer episodio psicótico. Se realizaron 4 entrevistas de seguimiento: en el primer, segundo, tercer y quinto años. Los pacientes se evaluaron mediante la Brief Psychiatric Rating Scale (BPRS), la Escala de Evolución de Strauss-Carpenter, la entrevista clínica estructurada del DSM-IV (SCID) y la Escala de Evaluación de la Actividad Global (EEAG). Resultados: Completaron el seguimiento de 5 años 27 pacientes. El 25,9% mantenía el diagnóstico de TE a los 5 años y el 59,2% se clasificaron dentro del espectro esquizofrénico. La presencia en el primer ingreso de características de buen pronóstico se asoció con una mejor evolución a los 5 años, pero no se asoció al mantenimiento del diagnóstico de TE. Los pacientes que mantuvieron el diagnóstico de TE presentaron mejor evolución que los pacientes esquizofrénicos. Conclusiones: Tras 5 años de seguimiento, la mayoría de los pacientes continúan presentando síntomas y cumplen criterios de esquizofrenia o trastorno esquizoafectivo, lo que confirma la baja estabilidad del diagnóstico TE. Los hallazgos sugieren una asociación entre las características de buen pronóstico y una mejor evolución, aunque no se observa asociación con el mantenimiento del diagnóstico TE</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);13(1): 1-7, ene.-feb. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042997</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno esquizofreniforme. Estudio prospectivo de 5 años de seguimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
