<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78791</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Schizophrenia treatment. Critical review on the drugs and mechanisms of action of antipsychotics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Schizophrenic treatment was developed during the second half of the last century, mainly within the context of the development of antipsychotic drugs. Even though there has been significant progress due to the availability and use of multiple drugs, these can still be classified into three basic groups of antipsychotic drugs (atypical antipsychotics, typical antipsychotics and dopamine partial agonist antipsychotics). Their primary antipsychotic mechanism is still the action on the dopamine systems. Many of the second-generation antipsychotics are believed to offer advantages over first-generation agents in the treatment for schizophrenia. However, the drug properties that provide the different therapeutic effects from those of the first generation are not clear and some adverse effects may still affect the patient&#146;s health and quality of life. Furthermore, the efficacy of the antipsychotics is limited. This has led to the use of adjuvant medications to strengthen the treatment effects. On the other hand, work is being done on the development of new research lines to develop new nondopaminergic antipsychotic drugs, with not very successful results. The aim of this paper is to make a brief review on the current therapeutic armamentarium for schizophrenia, the strategies to develop drugs, and theories of mechanisms of action of antipsychotics. Emphasis is placed on the new therapeutic targets for the development of future treatments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tajima, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Marsá, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ibor, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento de la esquizofrenia ha evolucionado a lo largo de la segunda mitad del siglo pasado, principalmente gracias al desarrollo de los fármacos antipsicóticos. A pesar del gran avance realizado, que ha permitido la disponibilidad y uso de nuevos y diferentes fármacos, éstos continuan constituyendo tres grupos básicos (atipsicóticos típicos, atípicos y agonistas parciales dopaminérgicos), y todos ellos tienen como principal mecanismo de acción, la actuación sobre los sistemas dopaminérgicos. Se cree que una gran parte de los antipsicóticos de segunda generación (antipsicóticos atípicos y agonistas parciales dopaminérgicos) ofrecen ventajas añadidas a los de primera generación en el tratamiento de la esquizofrenia. No obstante, las propiedades farmacológicas y terapéuticas que confieren respecto a los de primera generación no están claras, y ciertos efectos colaterales pueden todavía, afectar a la salud y calidad de vida del paciente. Además, la eficacia de los antipsicóticos es limitada, lo que ha llevado a la utilización de medicaciones adyuvantes para potenciar los efectos del tratamiento. Por otro lado, se ha trabajado en el desarrollo de nuevas líneas de investigación para el desarrollo de nuevos fármacos antipsicóticos no dopaminérgicos, siendo los resultados poco exitosos. Este artículo realiza una breve revisión crítica sobre el actual arsenal terapéutico para la esquizofrenia, estrategias de desarrollo de fármacos, y teorías sobre los mecanismos de acción de los antipsicóticos, centrándose en las nuevas dianas terapéuticas para el desarrollo de futuros tratamientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(6): 330-342, nov.-dic. 2009. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78791</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento para la esquizofrenia.  Revisión crítica sobre la farmacología y mecanismos de acción de los antipsicóticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32309^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1570^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
