<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74100</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Identification of elderly subjects with mental illness and its relationship with self-perception of health in a rural community setting. A cross-sectional study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. This paper aims to deal with the increaseof the burden of mental disorders in the elderly populationand scarce prevalence data in the rural communitysetting and the poor evidence in rural settings. Our aim wasto identify elderly adults with neuropsychiatric morbidity(anxiety, depression and dysthymia) in rural communityarea, and their relationship to self-perception of one&#146;s healthcondition.MATERIAL AND METHODS. A cohort made up of subjectsover 65 years (n = 165) from Garcibuey (C1) and Villanuevadel Conde (C2), Salamanca, was studied. We used aquestionnaire based on the SABE study from Pan-AmericanHealth Organization/World Health Organization (PAHO/WHO) to evaluate personal data, health and nutritionalstatus and social issues in elderly subjects. Data was collectedbetween November 06 - February 07 by direct personalinterview and systematic review of medical record.RESULTS AND CONCLUSIONS. Forty-one (25.2%) ofthe cohort have suffered or are suffering a neuropsychiatricdisorder, 9 of whom are currently under medical treatment.A total of 63.4% live alone or with a partner; 22 (53.6%) perceivetheir health status as fair or bad. A total of 65.8% consumepsychodrugs. Neuropsychiatric disorders are more frequentin women (28 [68.2%]) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bernardini, D. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Serna, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macías Núñez, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN. El incremento de la carga de los trastornos mentales en la población de mayores y los pocos datos de prevalencia en medio rural comunitario son la razón de esta comunicación. Nuestro objetivo fue identificar adultos mayores con trastornos neuropsiquiátricos (ansiedad, depresión, distimia) en medio comunitario rural y su relación con la autopercepción del estado de salud. MATERIAL Y MÉTODOS. Estudiamos una cohorte de mayores de 65 años (n = 165) de Garcibuey (C1) y Villanueva del Conde (C2), dos pueblos de la provincia de Salamanca. Utilizamos un cuestionario realizado en base al de la Organización Panamericana de la Salud/Organización Mundial de la Salud (OPS/OMS) para el estudio SABE que revela aspectos en 4 dominios diferentes: datos demográficos, estado de salud, estado nutricional y aspectos sociales de los adultos mayores. Los datos se obtuvieron entre noviembre de 2006 y febrero de 2007 por entrevista directa y revisión sistemática de historias clínicas. Utilizamos para el tratamiento estadístico el paquete SPSS 12.0. RESULTADOS Y CONCLUSIONES. Cuarenta y una (25,2%) de las personas han sufrido o sufren un trastorno neuropsiquiátrico, 121 (74,2%) no. Nueve están bajo tratamiento médico farmacológico. El 63,4% vive solo o con su pareja; 22 (53,6%) perciben su estado de salud como malo o regular. El 65,8% consume psicofármacos. Las mujeres (28 [68,2%]) fueron las más afectadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(10): 475-477, dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74100</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Identificación de mayores con trastornos mentales y su relación con autopercepción de salud en medio comunitario rural. Estudio de corte transversal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32616</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33144^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
