<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95826</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Services portfolio of a department of Endocrinology and Clinical Nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract Endocrinology and Clinical Nutrition are branches of Medicine that deal with thestudy of physiology of body glands and hormones and their disorders, intermediate metabolism of nutrients, enteral and parenteral nutrition, promotion of health by prevention of diet-relateddiseases, and appropriate use of the diagnostic, therapeutic, and preventive tools related tothese disciplines. Development of Endocrinology and Clinical Nutrition support services requiresaccurate definition and management of a number of complex resources, both human and material, as well as adequate planning of the care provided. It is therefore essential to know theservices portfolio of an ideal Department of Endocrinology and Clinical Nutrition because thisis a useful, valid and necessary tool to optimize the available resources, to increase efficiency,and to improve the quality of care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Enterría, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tinahones Madueño, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente Delgado, Almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Endocrinología y Nutrición es la rama de la Medicina que se ocupa del estudio de la fisiología y patología del sistema endocrino, del metabolismo de las sustancias nutritivas, de la nutrición natural y artificial, de la promoción de la salud mediante la prevención de las enfermedades relacionadas con la dieta y de las correspondientes técnicas diagnósticas, terapéuticas y preventivas utilizadas en estas áreas del conocimiento médico. El desarrollo de estas actividades requiere la definición y la gestión de una serie de recursos complejos, tanto humanos como materiales, así como una correcta planificación del trabajo asistencial. Por lo tanto, resulta imprescindible conocer la Cartera de Servicios de un Servicio/Sección o Departamento de Endocrinología y Nutrición, ya que es una herramienta necesaria, válida y útil para optimizar los recursos disponibles, aumentar la eficacia y la rentabilidad de la actuación médica y mejorar la calidad de la asistencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;58(3): 127-142, mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cartera de Servicios de Endocrinología y Nutrición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52458</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4786</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6905^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
