<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102634</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do Macro-Contextual Characteristics Account for Individual Rates of Adolescent Deviance? A Nine-Country Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The current study tested whether macro, country-level characteristics (per capita income, crime rate, divorce rate, drinking age, and median population age) account for variability in individual-level deviant behavior. Based on a sample of N = 14,290 adolescents from nine different countries (Hungary, Japan, the Netherlands, Slovenia, Spain, Switzerland, Taiwan, Turkey, and the United States), key findings include that (a) for all deviance measures, with the exception of alcohol use (vandalism, drug use, school misconduct, general deviance, theft, and assault), factor structures were largely invariant across the nine countries; (2) between-country variability comprised a significant proportion of variance in all seven deviance indices (particularly for less serious forms of deviance, and less so for more serious forms, such as theft or assault); and (3) only national crime rates explained significant variability in any of the deviance indices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chen, Pan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vazsonyi, Alexander T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schwartz, Seth J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio analizó si las características macro, a nivel de país (renta per cápita, índices de criminalidad, índices de divorcio, edad a la que se permite consumir alcohol, y edad media de la población) explicaban la variabilidad de la conducta desviada a nivel individual. La muestra estaba compuesta N = 14.290 adolescentes procedentes de nueve países diferentes (Hungría, Japón, Países Bajos, Eslovenia, España, Suiza, Taiwan, Turquía y los Estados Unidos); los resultados más importantes indican que: (1) para todas las medidas de desviación, con la excepción del consumo de alcohol (vandalismo, consumo de drogas, mal comportamiento en la escuela, desviación general, robos y agresión), los factores eran, en gran parte, invariantes en los nueve países; (2) la variabilidad entre países incluyó una proporción significativa de varianza en los siete índices de desviación (especialmente para las formas menos severas de desviación, y menos para las formas más serias, como robo o agresión); y (3) sólo los índices nacionales de criminalidad explicaban una cantidad significativa de variabilidad en cualquiera de los índices de desviación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(3): 643-653, oct.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102634</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Explican las características macro-contextuales los índices individuales de desviación adolescente? Un estudio en nueve países</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13302^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53813^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
