<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90030</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validity and reliability of a synthetic hospital health care quality indicator</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Benchmarking between different health organisations is a useful tool for improving quality, but it requires using valid and reliable indicators so that comparisons may be based on objective data. The aim of this work is to verify the validity and reliability of a synthetic hospital health care quality indicator. Material and methods. A cross-sectional study was conducted over a five-year period on the Quality Plan indicators of 10 hospitals, under the model of the European Foundation of Quality Management (EFQM). Reliability was checked using the Cronbach's alpha coefficient. The validity was determined using a cluster analyses (dendrogram), examining relationships between different indicator results, and by means of an exploratory analysis of the correlations between the process indicators and results indicators proposed by the US Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ). Results. An «acceptable» reliability was found (&amp;#945;=0.759). No clusters were found that corresponded to the set of criteria of the EFQM model, or any significant correlations with the results indicators. Conclusions. It is proposed to continue devising indicators that could empirically be shown to be valid in order to be incorporated into synthetic indicators, in such a way that the efficiency of health care management in all hospitals may be compared(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mira Solves, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martín, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejero González, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El benchmarking entre diferentes organizaciones sanitarias es una herramienta útil para la mejora de la calidad, pero requiere contar con indicadores válidos y fiables para que las comparaciones se basen en datos objetivos. El objetivo de este trabajo es contrastar la validez y la fiabilidad de un indicador sintético de calidad de la atención hospitalaria. Material y métodos. Estudio transversal, sobre los indicadores del Plan de Calidad de 10 hospitales, bajo el modelo de la European Fondation of Quality Management (EFQM) en un periodo de 5 años. Se contrasta la fiabilidad, mediante el coeficiente alfa de Cronbach. La validez se contrasta mediante un análisis de conglomerados (dendograma), explorando asociaciones entre resultados de indicadores diferentes, y mediante un análisis exploratorio de las correlaciones entre los indicadores de proceso y los indicadores de resultados propuestos por la Agencia Norteamericana de Investigación en Calidad (AHRQ). Resultados. Se ha encontrado una fiabilidad «aceptable» (&amp;#945;=0,759). No se han hallado conglomerados que respondan a la agrupación de criterios del modelo EFQM ni correlaciones significativas con los indicadores de resultados. Conclusiones. Se propone continuar elaborando indicadores que se muestren empíricamente válidos para integrarse en indicadores sintéticos, de forma que pueda compararse la eficiencia de la gestión sanitaria en todos los hospitales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;26(4): 234-241, jul.-ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validez y fiabilidad de un indicador sintético de calidad de la atención hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17140</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
