<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167762</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The effectiveness of a learning strategies program for university students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: University lecturers often complain about their students' lack of learning strategies, but not many universities in Spain offer specific courses in this area. Studies on their effectiveness are also rare. Method: This study presents the results of a Learning Strategies Course implemented at the School of Teacher Training and Education, University of Oviedo, Spain. A quasi-experimental design was used with an experi-mental (n = 60) and a control group (n = 57) of students on the Educational Psychology course. A Spanish adaptation of the Motivated Strategies for Learning Questionnaire (MSLQ): the CEAMR2 was used as a pre and post-test measure. Group A (EG) received training in learning strategies, while group B (CG) received no training. Results: Post-test measures showed significant differences in five out of the ten learning strategies assessed: elaboration, organization, repetition, self-questioning and study space, and also an improvement in one out of the six motivational scales: control of learning beliefs. Discussion: The results suggest that learning strategies courses with proven effectiveness should be offered to university students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sierra y Arizmendiarrieta, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roces Montero, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: los profesores universitarios se quejan de la forma de estudiar sus alumnos, pero escasean en nuestro país cursos específicos en este área y estudios sobre su eficacia. Método: presentamos los resultados obtenidos con el Curso de  Estrategias de Aprendizaje en un grupo de estudiantes de la Facultad de Formación del Profesorado y Educación de la Universidad de Oviedo. Se utilizó un diseño quasi-experimental con grupo experimental (n = 60) y grupo de control(n = 57), formados por estudiantes de primer curso de la asignatura Psicología de la Educación. Se utilizó el Cuestionario de Estrategias de Aprendizaje y Motivación (CEAM-R2), adaptación del MSLQ, como medida pre y post-test. El grupo A (GE) recibió entrenamiento en estrategias de aprendizaje, mientras que el grupo B (GC) no lo recibió. Resultados: el posttest muestra diferencias significativas en cinco de las diez estrategias de aprendizaje evaluadas: elaboración, organización, repetición, auto-interrogación y lugar de estudio, y también en una de las seis escalas motivacionales: creencias de control del aprendizaje. Discusión: los resultados sugieren que se deberían ofertar a los universitarios cursos de estrategias de aprendizaje eficaces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);29(4): 527-532, nov. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167762</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de un programa de mejora de las estrategias de aprendizaje en la enseñanza superior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54305</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13063^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16869</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12025^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51609</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
