<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119396</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive factors of response to erytrhocytapheresis in patients with biochemical iron overload with or without hereditary hemochromatosis type 1</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Progressive increase of iron stores leads to the development of varied diseases, some of them irreversible. Until now, phlebotomy has been the cornerstone in the treatment of iron overload. Nevertheless, each erytrhocytapheresis procedure removes more than twice the volume of red cells and iron than phlebotomy, allowing to achieve iron depletion in shorter time. Our aim was to describe clinical features and analytical tests parameters of patients with iron overload, to analyze global and subsets results, to suggest predictive factors of response and to evaluate security of the procedure. Patients and method: Descriptive, longitudinal and prospective study of 663 procedures corresponding to 35 patients (December 2002 to October 2011). Response was defined as a serum ferritine value lower than 50 ng/mL during two months. Statistical analysis was done with SPSS® v 17.0 and the minimum level of statistical significance was defined as p-value &lt; 0,05. Results: Seventy-seven percent of patients reached response with 11 (interquartile range 1-42) erytrhocytapheresis procedures and at 11 (1-108) months. Eighty-seven point five percent of patients who did not achieve response had their ferritine values reduced in more than 50%. The decrease of all iron metabolism parameters was statistically significant. Statistically significant predictive factors of response to erytrhocytapheresis were: patients younger than 60 years-old, hereditary hemochromatosis cases, and patients who had received treatment with phlebotomies prior to erytrhocytapheresis. Conclusions: Erytrhocytapheresis is a secure and effective procedure for iron depletion in patients with iron overload, especially in high risk hereditary hemochromatosis cases that do not respond to phlebotomies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Parra Salinas, Ingrid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Erce, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes Limon, Anel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Recasens Flores, Valle</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernandez Mosteirin, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: El aumento progresivo de los depósitos de hierro favorece el desarrollo de diversas entidades, algunas de ellas irreversibles. La piedra angular terapéutica en la sobrecarga férrica ha sido, hasta ahora, la flebotomía. Sin embargo, la eritroaféresis extrae más del doble de hematíes y hierro en cada sesión que una flebotomía convencional, permitiendo alcanzar la depleción férrica en menor tiempo. Los objetivos de este estudio fueron describir las características clínicas y parámetros analíticos de pacientes con sobrecarga férrica tratados mediante eritroaféresis, analizar los resultados globales y por subgrupos, y postular factores predictores de respuesta, así como valorar la seguridad de la técnica. Pacientes y método:  Estudio descriptivo, longitudinal y prospectivo de 663 sesiones de eritroaféresis correspondientes a 35 pacientes (entre diciembre de 2002 y octubre de 2011). La respuesta se definió como una cifra de ferritina sérica menor a 50 ng/ml durante dos meses. Para el análisis estadístico se empleó el programa SPSS® versión 17.0 y el nivel mínimo de significación estadística se estableció en un valor de p &lt; 0,05. Resultados:  Alcanzaron la respuesta el 77% de los pacientes, con una mediana de 11 (intervalo intercuartílico 1-42) sesiones de eritroaféresis y al cabo de una mediana de 11 (1-108) meses. El 87,5% de los pacientes que no lograron la respuesta redujeron sus valores de ferritina en más del 50%. El descenso en todos los parámetros del metabolismo del hierro fue estadísticamente significativo en el global de pacientes. Fueron factores predictores de respuesta a las eritroaféresis con significación estadística: edad &lt; 60 años, casos de hemocromatosis hereditaria y pacientes con flebotomías previas al inicio de las eritroaféresis. Conclusiones: La eritroaféresis es una técnica efectiva y segura para la depleción férrica en pacientes con sobrecarga de hierro, especialmente en los casos de hemocromatosis hereditaria de alto riesgo que no responden a las flebotomías (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);142(5): 187-191, mar. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119396</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictores de respuesta a las eritroaféresis terapéuticas en pacientes con sobrecarga férrica bioquímica con hemocromatosis hereditaria tipo 1 y sin ella</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32960^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32650^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6582^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1808^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4999</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28902^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
