<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122007</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Photosensitivity Due to Thiazides</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Thiazides are widely used diuretics that first became available in the 1950s. The first reports of photosensitivity reactions to thiazides were published shortly after the introduction of these drugs, but few cases have been described since. We review all the cases of photosensitivity due to thiazides published up to December 2011. We found 62 cases, 33 in women and 29 in men. The most common presentation was eczematous lesions in a photodistributed pattern, and the most common causative agent was hydrochlorothiazide. The results of photobiological studies were published in only some of the cases reviewed. In most cases, phototesting revealed an abnormal response to UV-A alone or to both UV-A and UV-B. In some cases, the results of phototesting were normal and only photopatch testing yielded abnormal results. Diagnosis of photosensitivity due to thiazides requires a high degree of suspicion. Ideally, diagnosis should be confirmed by a photobiological study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Bernal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Pazos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-González, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Granados, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toribio, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las tiazidas son diuréticos que se comenzaron a usar en la década de 1950 y su uso está muy extendido en la actualidad. Poco después de su introducción se describieron las primeras reacciones de fotosensibilidad, aunque han sido descritas solo de forma infrecuente con posterioridad. Revisamos los casos de fotosensibilidad por tiazidas publicados hasta diciembre de 2011. Encontramos 62 casos, de los cuales 33 eran mujeres y 29 varones. La forma de presentación más común fue con lesiones eccematosas fotodistribuidas. La hidroclorotiazida fue el agente causal más frecuente. Solo algunos casos publicados recogen el resultado del estudio fotobiológico. En la mayoría el fototest mostró un respuesta alterada a ultravioleta A (UVA) sola y a UVA + ultravioleta B (UVB). En algunos casos el fototest fue normal y solo el fotoparche estaba alterado. El diagnóstico de fotosensibilidad por tiazidas requiere un alto índice de sospecha. De forma ideal debería confirmarse mediante estudio fotobiológico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;105(4): 359-366, mayo 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122007</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fotosensibilidad por tiazidas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50539^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4553^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11217^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14865^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32089^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7005^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
