<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84427</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0559</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ) for persons with disability who are ageing: preliminary study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The goal of this paper is the elaboration of an instrument to assess quality of life (QL) ofageing persons with disability. It has been applied to a sample of 2.292 persons olderthan 45 years, from different regions of Spain. The need of QL assessment instruments forthis group of persons with disability who are ageing will allow us to make valid and reliablemeasures to plan efficient intervention actions and strategies, and has motivated thecreation of this Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ). The analysis of the scale psychometricproperties shows high internal consistency, Cronbach´s alfa of 0,92. Scale dimensionalityoffers a hexafactorial solution that tests six of the main QL dimensions, such as, physicalwell being, social inclusion, emotional well being, personal development and self-determination,interpersonal relationship and material well being. These results give evidence ofthe QLQ suitability to assess the QL, as it is perceived by the sample of our study, theageing persons with disability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González González, Meni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Martínez, Benito</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcedo Rodríguez, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado Díaz, Antonio-León</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rozada Rodríguez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es la elaboración de un instrumento para evaluar la calidadde vida (CV) de las personas con discapacidad que envejecen. Se ha aplicado a una muestrade 2.292 personas con discapacidad mayores de 45 años procedentes de distintascomunidades autónomas del territorio español. La necesidad de disponer de instrumentosde evaluación de CV para este colectivo de personas con discapacidad que envejecen, quenos permitan realizar medidas fiables y válidas sobre las que planificar actuaciones yestrategias de intervención eficaces, ha orientado la elaboración de esta Escala de Calidadde Vida (ECV). El análisis de las propiedades psicométricas de la escala muestra unaelevada consistencia interna, alfa de Cronbach de 0,92. La dimensionalidad de la escalaarroja una solución hexafactorial que muestrea seis de las principales dimensiones de CV,en concreto, bienestar físico, inclusión social, bienestar emocional, desarrollo personal yautodeterminación, relaciones interpersonales y bienestar material. Estos resultados evidencianla adecuación de la ECV para evaluar la CV tal y como es percibida por la muestrade nuestro estudio, las personas con discapacidad que envejecen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Interv. psicosoc;17(2): 153-167, ene.  2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84427</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Escala de Calidad de Vida (ECV) para personas condiscapacidad que envejecen: estudio preliminar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
