<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167091</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ultrasound evaluation of diaphragm function and its application in critical patients, mechanical ventilation and brachial plexus block</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Before diaphragm ultrasonography, assessment of diaphragm function was very difficult due to the complex nature of its exploration. The use of this new technique has shed light on diagnostic problems and treatment with an improvement in final outcomes for critically ill patients, in whom the incidence of diaphragm weakness or dysfunction has been underestimated. Better knowledge of diaphragm function enables us earlier diagnosis by quantification of diaphragm contractile activity or evaluation of functional status after delivery of plexus block anaesthesia, facilitating therapeutic decisions. It is also being used as a guide in the process of weaning from mechanical ventilation or as the safest approach for braquial plexus block. In this review we present how to perform a systematic exploration of diaphragm function and its clinical implications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana Gordon, F de B de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fajardo Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nacarino Alcorta, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La valoración de la función diafragmática ha sido clásicamente poco considerada debido a la dificultad de su exploración. La aparición de la ecografía diafragmática ha aportado luz al problema y ofrece un terreno amplio que mejora significativamente nuestra capacidad diagnóstica y terapéutica en el paciente crítico o en los pacientes sometidos a anestesia regional del plexo braquial. La parálisis o la hipoquinesia diafragmática aparece como un problema mucho más frecuente de lo que se creía. La ecografía permite su diagnóstico precoz así como la cuantificación dinámica del problema facilitando la toma de decisiones preventivas y terapéuticas precoces. También se está delineando como un instrumento de guía en el proceso de destete de la ventilación mecánica y en el abordaje más seguro del plexo braquial. En este trabajo presentamos la sistemática de su exploración y su utilización clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;64(9): 513-521, nov. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167091</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración ecográfica de la función diafragmática y sus aplicaciones en el paciente crítico, en ventilación mecánica y en la anestesia del plexo braquial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10727^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22421^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12553^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1942^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22421^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12553^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10727^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
