<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111505</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement of balance in Parkinson's disease patients using calisthenics and recreational physical exercise: a pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Parkinson's disease (PD) has some characteristic symptoms that affect voluntary movement. Standing out among them is reduced balance capacity. This pilot study aimed to describe the effects on balance capacity of persons with PD of a short calisthenics and recreational physical exercise program. Material and methods. Twenty-three patients (Hoehn &amp; Yahr Staging Scale) with a mean age of 73±8.4 years and 2.17±0.7 severity of involvement participated in a two weekly, one hour session program. The program was based on the performance of calisthenics and recreational exercises. The program included two sessions per week of one hour each, over a seven week period. The balance test included in the «Short Physical Performance Battery» (composed of the «Side by Side» test; «Semitandem Stand» and «Tandem Stand») was performed to assess the effects of the intervention on the participant's balance capacity. Results. All the participants finished the study, participating in a total of 14 sessions. Considering the difference between the initial and final score obtained in the total score of the tests performed (from 2.9 to 3.1 points), no significant differences were observed. When total time reached in each test was compared separately, it could be seen that the participants increased their balance level in each one of them. However, the differences were only significant for the «Tandem Stand» test (P=.011). Conclusion. A short calisthenics-recreational exercise training program is well-tolerated by patients with Parkinson's Disease. However, its effects on their balance capacity do not seem to be very great(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ríos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abal, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cancela, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayán, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La enfermedad de Parkinson (EP), presenta unos síntomas característicos que afectan al movimiento voluntario, y entre los que destaca una reducida capacidad de equilibrio. El propósito de este estudio piloto fue determinar los efectos que sobre la misma tiene la realización de un programa de ejercicio calisténico-recreativo de corta duración.  Material y métodos. Un total de 23 pacientes con una edad media de 73±8,4 años y un nivel de afectación de 2,17±0,7 (Hoehn &amp; Yahr Staging Scale), desarrollaron un programa de ejercicio calisténico-recreativo, a razón de 2 sesiones de una hora semanales, durante 7 semanas. La prueba de equilibrio de la batería Short Physical Performance (compuesto por las pruebas Side by Side; Semitandem Stand y Tandem Stand), fue realizada para determinar los efectos de la intervención sobre esta capacidad. Resultados. Todos los participantes finalizaron el estudio, desarrollándose un total de 14 sesiones. No se observaron diferencias significativas en la capacidad de equilibrio a juzgar por la diferencia entre la puntuación inicial y final obtenida en la puntuación total de las pruebas realizadas (de 2,9 a 3,1 puntos). Al comparar el tiempo total alcanzado en cada prueba por separado, se pudo apreciar que los participantes incrementaron su nivel de equilibrio en cada una de las mismas, si bien las diferencias solo se mostraron significativas para la prueba Tandem Stand (p=0,011). Conclusión. Un programa de ejercicio calisténico-recreativo de corta duración, es bien tolerado por los pacientes con Parkinson, aunque sus efectos sobre el equilibrio parecen no ser de gran magnitud(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);47(1): 22-26, ene.-mar.2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111505</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora del equilibrio en los enfermos de Parkinson mediante el ejercicio calisténico-recreativo: un estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24230^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34223^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
