<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109851</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1582</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Atypical clinical manifestations in occult breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Occult breast cancer is currently defined as that which is expressed in metastatic lymph node tumors without a clinical or radiographic finding of a primary tumor in the breast. The frequency of this entity is low, representing between 0.3 and 0.8% of all breast cancers. We report the case of a patient with left supraclavicular lymphadenopathy secondary to occult carcinoma of the breast. The diagnosis was reached after multiple imaging studies and detection of mammaglobin in the immunohistochemical analysis of the adenopathy. We reviewed the medical literature and found no published case of an occult breast tumor detected in a left supraclavicular node(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Medrano, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensio Díaz, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnal Burró, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Camino, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Blanco, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Reviriego, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer de mama oculto se define actualmente como aquella neoplasia que se expresa con una adenopatía metastásica, sin manifestación clínica ni radiológica del tumor primario en la mama. Su frecuencia es baja, del orden del 0,3 al 0,8% de todos los cánceres de mama. Presentamos el caso de una paciente con una adenopatía supraclavicular izquierda secundaria a carcinoma oculto de mama. A este diagnóstico se llegó tras múltiples estudios de imagen y después de detectar la mamaglobina en el estudio inmunohistoquímico de la adenopatía. Revisamos la literatura médica, sin que hayamos encontrado ningún caso publicado en el que un cáncer oculto de mama se manifieste a través de un ganglio supraclavicular izquierdo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. senol. patol. mamar. (Ed. impr.);26(1): 33-37, ene.-mar. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109851</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manifestación clínica atípica de un cáncer oculto de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
