<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050130</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1473</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neuropsychological impairment in patients with intracraneal aneurysms: surgical versus endovascular treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To describe the neuropsychological status of patients with intracranial aneurysms and to compare the cognitive status of patients with intracranial aneurysm treated by surgical or endovascular methods. Material and methods. Ninety-three cases with intracranial aneurysms treated with surgery (n = 56) or embolization (n = 37) were included. A neuropsychological assessment was applied to both groups retrospectively, at least one year after treatment. Results. Neuropsychological impairment was found in both groups. 35.7% of the patients treated with surgery and 43.2%, of those treated with embolization did not show any cognitive impairment. Visual Memory and Cued Recall of verbal information are better inpatients treated by embolization. Conclusions. Our results show that a large proportion of patients with intracranial aneurysms have cognitive impairment after treatment. Endovascular management may cause less impairment in visual and verbal memory. However, bleeding may be the most important factor to explain these cognitive impairments</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Meersmans, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saura, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arjona, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Katati, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco-Giménez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escamilla, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jorques, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcázar, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>minués, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Describir el rendimiento neuropsicológico de pacientes con aneurismas cerebrales que han sido tratados mediante cirugía o embolización, y determinarla existencia de diferencias en función de la modalidad de tratamiento. Material y métodos. Serie clínica compuesta por 93pacientes voluntarios, con aneurismas cerebrales, tratados mediante cirugía (n = 56) o embolización (n = 37). A ambos grupos se les realizó una evaluación neuropsicológica retrospectiva, al menos un año después de realizar el tratamiento. Resultados. En ambos grupos se encontraron pacientes con déficit neuropsicológicos. En el grupo de pacientes tratados quirúrgicamente el porcentaje de pacientes sin ninguna afectación neuropsicológica es del 35.7%, mientras que en el grupo de pacientes embolizados este porcentaje asciende al 43.2%. Los análisis muestran una ejecución mejor en el grupo de tratamiento endovascular, respecto al quirúrgico, sólo en memoria visual y en el recuerdo con claves de la memoria verbal. Conclusiones. Años después del tratamiento, un importante porcentaje de pacientes presenta alteraciones neuropsicológicas. El tratamiento endovascular se asocia con un mejor rendimiento en memoria visual yen el recuerdo con claves de la memoria verbal, aunque explica un porcentaje muy escaso de la varianza. Por lo tanto, en la explicación del deterioro neuropsicológico parece más importante el propio efecto de la hemorragia que la modalidad de intervención</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurocirugia (Astur);17(1): 34-45, mar. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050130</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alteraciones neuropsicológicas en pacientes con aneurismas cerebrales: tratamiento quirúrgico versus tratamiento endovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4695</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2569^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
