<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144779</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5705</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Latest advances in acute pancreatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present article analyses the main presentations on acute pancreatitis at Digestive Disease Week 2015. Arterial pseudoaneurysm is an uncommon complication of acute pancreatitis (incidence 0.7%) and mortality from this cause is currently anecdotal. Diabetes mellitus has little impact on the clinical course of acute pancreatitis, unlike cirrhosis, which doubles the risk of mortality. Intake of unsaturated fat could be associated with an increased severity of acute pancreatitis and is a confounding factor in studies evaluating the relationship between obesity and morbidity and mortality. PET-CT (positron emission tomography-computed tomography) could be a non-invasive tool to detect infection of collections in acute pancreatitis. Peripancreatic fat necrosis is less frequent than pancreatic fat necrosis and is associated with a better clinical course. If the clinical course is poor, increasing the calibre of the percutaneous drains used in the treatment of infected necrosis can avoid surgery in 20% of patients. The use of low molecular-weight heparin in moderate or severe pancreatitis could be associated with a better clinical course, specifically with a lower incidence of necrosis. In acute recurrent pancreatitis, simvastatin is a promising drug for prophylaxis of new episodes of acute pancreatitis. Nutritional support through a nasogastric tube does not improve clinical course compared with oral nutrition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Madaria, Enrique de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo se analizan las principales comunicaciones presentadas en la Digestive Disease Week 2015 sobre pancreatitis aguda. El seudoaneurisma arterial es una complicación infrecuente de la pancreatitis aguda (incidencia del 0,7%) y su mortalidad en la actualidad es anecdótica. Padecer una diabetes mellitus tiene poco impacto en el curso clínico de la pancreatitis aguda, al contrario que presentar una cirrosis, que está asociada al doble de mortalidad. El consumo de grasas insaturadas podría asociarse a mayor gravedad en pancreatitis aguda, y es un factor de confusión en los estudios que evalúan la relación entre obesidad y morbimortalidad. La PET-TC (tomografía por emisión de positrones-tomografía computarizada) podría ser una herramienta diagnóstica no invasiva de infección de colecciones en el seno de una pancreatitis aguda. La necrosis de la grasa peripancreática es menos frecuente que la pancreática, y se asocia a mejor evolución. Una estrategia de aumentar el calibre de los drenajes percutáneos usados en el tratamiento de la necrosis infectada en caso de mala evolución puede evitar la cirugía en un 20% de pacientes. El uso de heparina de bajo peso molecular en pancreatitis aguda moderada a grave podría asociarse a mejor evolución, en concreto a menor incidencia de necrosis. La simvastatina es un fármaco prometedor para la profilaxis de nuevos episodios de pancreatitis aguda, en el contexto de pancreatitis aguda recurrente. La nutrición por sonda nasogástrica no se asocia a mejor evolución si se compara con nutrición oral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gastroenterol Hepatol;38(supl.1): 100-105, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144779</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Últimos avances en pancreatitis aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30856^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33420^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
