<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106277</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypoglycemic effect of cooked lupinus mutabilis and its purified alkaloids in subjects with type-2 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Developing countries are experiencing an epidemic of chronic non-communicable chronic diseases with high socio-economic costs. Studies of traditional foods with beneficial health properties could contribute to diminish these problems. Legumes rich in proteins like Lupinus mutabilis decreases blood glucose and improves insulin sensitivity in animals and humans. We report the results of a phase II clinical trial conducted to assess the role of cooked L. mutabilis and its purified alkaloids on blood glucose and insulin in volunteers with diabetes. Results indicate that consumption of cooked L. mutabilis or its purified alkaloids decreased blood glucose and insulin levels. The decreases in serum glucose concentrations from base line to 90 minutes were statistically significant within both treatment groups; however, there were not differences between groups. Serum insulin levels were also decreased in both groups however the differences were not statistically significant. None of the volunteers in either group presented side effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Narváez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baldeón, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villacrés, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fornasini, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los países en vías de desarrollo están sufriendo una epidemia de enfermedades crónicas no transmisibles con costos socio-económicos grandes. El estudio de alimentos tradicionales con efectos benéficos para la salud podría contribuir a solucionar estos problemas. El consumo de leguminosas ricas en proteínas como Lupinus mutabilis disminuye las concentraciones de glucosa e insulina en animales y humanos. Aquí se reportan los resultados de un estudio clínico fase II realizado para evaluar la eficacia de L. mutabilis cocido y de un extracto de alcaloides de L. mutabilis en las concentraciones de glucosa e insulina sanguíneas en voluntarios con diabetes. Los resultados indican que el consumo de L. mutabilis cocido o de sus alcaloides purificados disminuyeron las concentraciones de glucosa e insulina en sangre. La disminución en las concentraciones de glucosa sanguínea entre la línea basal y los 90 minutos después del tratamiento fueron estadísticamente significativas dentro de cada grupo de tratamiento, sin embargo no hubieron diferencias entre los grupos. Los niveles de insulina también disminuyeron en ambos grupos pero las diferencias no fueron estadísticamente significativas. Ninguno de los voluntarios presentó efectos adversos a los tratamientos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(4): 1261-1266, jul.-ago. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106277</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto hipoglicemiante de lupinus mutabilis cocinado y sus alcaloides en sujetos con diabetes tipo-2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36839</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d472^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
