<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74890</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of emotional intelligence in patients with psychopathology: preliminary results using the TMMS-24 and the MSCEIT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study presents some preliminayr results concerning the convenience of the use of different instruments to assess Emotional Intelligence (IE) in subjects with psychological disorder. Method: 62 patients with ether agoraphobia, or cocaine addiction, or disthymia were administered a self-report questionnaire of Perceived Emotional Intelligence, the TMMS-24, and an execution test of El, the MSCEIT. Results: The scores of the three groups in both instruetns were situated in the normal range r below. None o the three subfactors of the TMMS.-24 but various subfactors of the MSCEIT as well as the total scale discrimanated between the clinical groups; the disthymia group presented the lowest IE scores. Correlations between the two instruments were non significant, except for one. Discussion: Results indicate that the two instruments assess different aspects of EL; they also suggest that the use of the MSCEIT sees to be more adequate when dealing with clnical population(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chamarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oberst, U. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farriols, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizeretti, N. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan unos resultados preliminares respecto a la conveniencia del empleo de diferentes instrumentos para evaluar la Intelegencia Emocional (IE) en población psicopatología. Método. 62 pacients con agorafobia, distimia o adicción a cocaína fueron evaluados con un cuestionario de autoinforme para la IE Percibida, el TMMS-24 y con un instrumento de ejecución, e MSCEIT. Resultados: La puntuaciones de los grupos en ambas escalas se situaban en la nrmalidad o por debajo. Mientras ninguno de los subfactores de TMMS-24 discriinaba entre los grupos clínicos, varios subfactores y la escala todatal del MSCEIT lo hacía de for a significativa, presentando el grupo de los distímicos la IE más baja de los tres grupos. Las correlaciones entre las subescalas de los dos instrumentos no fueron significativas a excepcion de una. Discusión. Los resultados indican que los dos instrumentos iden aspectos diferentes de la inteligenica eocional: además se sugiere que parece más adecuado el uso del MSCEIT con población clínica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;12(2/3): 355-364, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74890</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la inteligencia emocional en pacientes con Psicopatologia: resultados preliminares usando TMMS-24 y el MSCEIT</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33144^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d383^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d383^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33144^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
