<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106058</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The ostomyzed patient's adaptation to social and family environment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Knowing how a person deals with and adapts to a colostomy along a two years period. Methods: Qualitative case study. The case shows a colostomyzed patient due to a rectal cancer. Data collected through semistructured interviews to the patient and a relative at two different moments: during hospitalization and two years later. The four interviews were recorded, transcribed and analyzed according to Taylor-Bogdan Method. Results: Confrontation strategies aimed at alleviate negative emotions by delegating the cares of the stoma to relatives are key during hospitalization. Two years later, there is a higher concern for practical questions and the patient can finally reach autonomy. The report shows the aspects leading to adaptation and the changes the ostomy brings about in the patient's life. Conclusions: Ostomyzed people require individualized care based on their biopsycosocial dimension (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Crespillo Díaz, Antonia Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Muñoz, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer el afrontamiento y adaptación de una persona colostomizada a lo largo de dos años. Metodología: Estudio cualitativo de un caso. Se ilustra el caso de un paciente colostomizado a causa de un cáncer de recto. Los datos se recogieron mediante entrevistas semiestructuradas al paciente y al familiar en dos tiempos distintos, durante la hospitalización y a los dos años. Las cuatro entrevistas se grabaron, trascribieron y analizaron según el método de Taylor-Bogdan. Resultados: Durante la hospitalización priman las estrategias de afrontamiento dirigidas a aliviar las emociones negativas delegando los cuidados del estoma en su familiar. A los dos años se observa una preocupación mayor por las cuestiones prácticas logrando finalmente ser autónomo. Se descubren los aspectos que han contribuido a esa adaptación y los cambios provocados por la ostomía en su vida. Conclusiones: Se evidencia la necesidad de un cuidado individualizado que considere al ostomizado en su dimensión biopsicosocial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;21(1/2): 43-47, ene.-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106058</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La adaptación al entorno sociofamiliar del paciente ostomizado. Estudio cualitativo de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22955^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
