<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85925</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of Pediatric Emergency Departments in regional hospitals of the Community of Valencia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There are some Spanish research about the demand and assistance for PEDs in Third Level Hospitals; however, few studies have examined the issue on Regional Hospitals. The focus of this study is to acknowledge the actual situation of both, organization and functioning of the Pediatric Emergency Departments in Regional Hospitals of the Valencian Community (VC). Material and methods: A web-based survey was forwarded to all Pediatric Services in Regional Hospitals in the Valencian Community during January 2010. This survey compiled 54questions about: contact data, hospital data, medical emergency, and data on medical duty and pediatric emergency service data. Demographic data related to global and under 15 years old population corresponds to the Sanitary Coverage Area of each hospital and were obtained from the Population Information System (SIP) of the Council of the Generalitat Valenciana. Results: A total population of 2,450,159 (46.8% of the total of the Valencian Community population) is attended in 15 Regional Hospitals of the VC. 15.5% (376,683) are under 15 years of age. There are a total number of 121 pediatric physicians (PP) (5-13 per hospital). In most of the hospitals (12) there is only one pediatrician on duty that sees 20-30% of the children that go to the emergency guard. Nowadays 11.6% of the pediatricians are exempt from being on-call duty and in the next5 years there will be exempt pediatricians in most hospitals. Only 5 hospitals have Pediatric residents, Primary Attention Pediatricians contributes to Continued Attention in only nine hospitals. Pediatric Emergency is attended within the framework of General Emergencies. There is not an adequate accomplishment of some quality indicators in PEDs. Conclusions: Almost half of the children in the Valencian Community are attended in Health Departments where specialized pediatric assistance depends on a Regional Hospital. Nowadays, these hospitals do not have enough human resources to guarantee the assistance to all the children taken to PEDs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blasco González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Dios, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Rigual, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se han realizado estudios en España sobre la demanda y la asistencia en los servicios de urgencias pediátricas (SUP) en los hospitales de tercer nivel; sin embargo, son escasos los realizados en hospitales comarcales. El objetivo de este estudio es conocer el funcionamiento y la organización de las urgencias pediátricas de los hospitales comarcales de la Comunidad Valenciana. Material y métodos: Encuesta remitida por correo electrónico a los servicios de pediatría de los hospitales comarcales de la Comunidad Valenciana durante enero de 2010. La encuesta contiene 54 preguntas sobre datos de contacto, del hospital, de la guardia médica y del área pediátrica de urgencias. La información relativa a la población total y menor de 15 años correspondiente al área de cobertura de cada hospital se extrae del Sistema de Información Poblacional (SIP) de la Generalitat Valenciana. Resultados: Los 15 hospitales comarcales de la Comunidad Valenciana abarcan una población SIP total de 2.450.159 (un 46,8% del total de población de la comunidad), y 376.683 (15,5%) son menores de 15 años. El número de pediatras hospitalarios es de 121 (entre 5 y 13 por hospital). En la mayoría de hospitales (12) sólo hay un pediatra de guardia que atiende al 20-30% de los niños que acuden a urgencias. Actualmente, un 11,6% de los pediatras no realizan guardias, y se calcula que en 5 años en la mayoría de los hospitales algún pediatra estará exento de ellas. Sólo 5 hospitales disponen de residentes de pediatría y 9 cuentan con la colaboración de algún pediatra de atención primaria. La urgencia pediátrica se atiende dentro del área de urgencias generales. No existe un adecuado cumplimiento de ciertos indicadores de calidad de los SUP. Conclusiones: Casi la mitad de los niños de la Comunidad Valenciana son atendidos en departamentos donde la asistencia pediátrica especializada depende de un hospital comarcal. En la actualidad estos hospitales no disponen de recursos humanos suficientes para garantizar dicha asistencia a todos los niños que acuden a urgencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;69(1): 17-26, ene. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de las urgencias de pediatría en los hospitales comarcales de la Comunidad Valenciana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1294^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37716^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37716^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
