<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75887</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Results: Correlations were seen between the ACSM calculation and the PAR/PAF questionnaire according to time of arrival (p &lt; 0.001, r2 = 0,94), (PNS, r2 = 0.00), and according to age (PNS, r2 =0.00), (p &lt; 0.001, r2 = 0.87), n = 81, respectively. When differentiating by age group, with the calculation of the ACSM and the PAR/PAF, a significant correlation was found in the in&gt; 30 years group according to time of arrival (p &lt; 0.001, r2 = 0.95), (PNS, r2 = 0.09), respectively. Results compared depending on age, ACSM (PNS,r2 =0.03), PAR/PAF (p &lt; 0.001, r2 = 78). In the &lt; 30 years group, compared with the methods the time of arrival, the calculation of the ACSM showed a high correlation (p &lt; 0.001, r2 = 0.97), compare to the PAR/PAF calculation (PNS, r2 = 0.03). When comparing the two methods and their relationship withage, there were no significant correlations (r2 = 22) and (r2 = 0.05). A correlation between the two methods for indirectly estimating VO2 max in the half-marathon runners was found only in the &gt; 30 years group (p &lt; 0.01, r = 32), n = 65.                                                 Conclusion: This study showed a higher adjusted r2, which reflected the quality and the prediction power of the models. The authors conclude that cardiorespiratory assessment by non-exercise models in epidemiological studies could be feasible(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Vélez, Robinson</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Ávila, José Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Alban, Carlos Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agredo Zuñiga, Ricardo Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dosman González, Viviana Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resultados: Se encontraron correlaciones entre el cálculo del ACSM y el cuestionario PAR/PAF en función al tiempo de llegada (p &lt; 0,001, r2 = 0,94), (pNS, r2 = 0,00), y en función de la edad (pNS, r2 = 0,00), (p &lt; 0,001, r2 = 0,87), n = 81, respectivamente. Al diferenciarlos por grupos de edad, con el cálculo del ACSM y el PAR/PAF en mayores de 30 años, se encontró una importante correlación en función al tiempo de llegada (p &lt; 0,001, r2 = 0,95), (pNS, r2 = 0,09), respectivamente. Resultados contrarios en función de la edad, ACSM (pNS, r2 = 0,03), PAR/PAF (p &lt; 0,001, r2 = 0,78). En menores de 30 años, comparados los métodos con el tiempo de llegada, el cálculo del ACSM demostró una alta correlación (p &lt; 0,001, r2 = 0,97), contraria al cálculo del PAR/PAF (pNS, r2 = 0,03). Al comparar ambos métodos y su relación con la edad, no se encontraron correlaciones significativas (r2 = 0,22) y (r2 = 0,05). La correlación entre ambos métodos para estimar de manera indirecta el VO2máx en corredores de media maratón sólo fue encontrada en el grupo de mayores de 30 años (p &lt; 0,01, r = 0,32), n=65.                                        Conclusiones: Los modelos de predicción del VO2máx pueden constituirse en una alternativa viable para la evaluación de la capacidad funcional en estudios epidemiológicos. A pesar de esto, ambos métodos presentan un grado bajo de correlación, lo cual hace necesario futuras investigaciones para su validez(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);44(162): 57-65, abr.-jun. 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75887</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis comparativo del VO2máx estimado mediante las ecuaciones desarrolladas por Jackson et al y el American College of Sport Medicine en corredores de maratón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12793</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
