<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146608</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Football on and off the field. Challenges in transition from junior to elite</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One of the transitions that has received less attention in the scientific literature is the transition from junior to professional sport specifically in football. Based on the development model of Wylleman and Lavallee (2004), the objective of this study is to explore the challenges that juniors football players had in making the transition into elite football in a retrospective manner. In addition, this study analyse specificities challenges of this transition according to gender. 8 males and 8 females were interviewed about their experience with the transition to elite football. The results are divided into two main topics: challenges associated with the football on the field and challenges associated with the football off the field (e.g., structure, social conception). The analysis shows that challenges that football players must cope on the field are produced on the athletes and psychological levels. Off the field challenges are produced too on those levels and, in addition, on psychosocial and academic/laboral levels. Relevance to face with success these challenges and their importance for correct adaptation to the elite of football is discussion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Amado, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Chamorro, Jose</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torregrosa, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Oliva, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una de las transiciones que ha recibido menos atención en la literatura científica es la transición de junior al deporte profesional, en concreto al fútbol de élite. Basados en el modelo de desarrollo deportivo de Wylleman y Lavallee (2004), el objetivo de este estudio es explorar de forma retrospectiva los desafíos que tuvieron que afrontar futbolistas junior al realizar la transición a la élite del fútbol. Además, se analizan las especificidades de los desafíos en función del género al realizar dicha transición. Se entrevistaron 8 chicos y 8 chicas sobre sus experiencias en la transición a la élite del fútbol. Los resultados se distribuyen en dos apartados principales: desafíos asociados al fútbol dentro del campo y desafíos asociados al fútbol fuera del campo (e.g., estructura, concepción social). El análisis de contenido muestra que los desafíos a los que tienen que hacer frente los futbolistas dentro del campo se asocian a los niveles deportivo y psicológico. Los desafíos fuera del campo además de asociarse con estos dos niveles, se asocian también a los niveles psicosocial y académico/laboral. Las diferencias respecto a los desafíos que se encuentran chicos y chicas se asocian únicamente a la categoría fútbol fuera del campo. Se discute la relevancia de afrontar con éxito estos desafíos y su importancia para una correcta adaptación a la élite del fútbol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;25(1): 81-89, 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146608</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El fútbol dentro del campo y fuera de él: Desafíos en la transición a la élite</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
