<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043163</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Is necessary to practice orchiectomy inpatients with post-puberal maldescended testes?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The cryptorchidism is a risk factor for testicular cancer and is associated with cancer in the contraleteral testicle. The mechanism that leads to an increased risk of causes in a cryptorchid testis is unclear. Materials and Methods: We analyzed 25 patients of 20-years old for maldescended testicles we practiced orchiectomy in 22 testicles and orchiopexy in 7 testicles. The time patients had the testicles in an anomalous location were between 20-51 years. Results: The elder patients with maldescends testicles came because the couldn&#146;t feel the testicle in the scrotum and the 16% of them because of infertility. Only 1 of 25 cases (4%) were demonstrated cancer with pure seminoma. Conclusions: In the following up of the patients none of them presented contralateral testicle cancer between 5-10 years. The patients who were practiced the orchiopexy no-one presented testicular cancer between 5-11 years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Granados Loarca, E. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esau Ortega, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Ojetivo: La criptorquidia es un factor de riesgo de cáncer de testículo, y se ha asociado con cáncer en el testículo contralateral. Los mecanismos por lo cual incrementa el riesgo de cáncer en el testículo criptorquídicono está claro. Material y Métodos: Se analizaron 25 pacientes mayores de 20 años que acudieron por Testículo no Descendido (TND); a los cuales se les practicó orquidectomía en 22 testículos y orquidopexia en 7 testículos. El tiempo que los pacientes tuvieron el/los testículos en localización anómala, osciló entre 20-51 años. Resultados: Los pacientes mayores con TND suelen acudir por no palparse el testículo en el escroto, y el 16% por infertilidad. Sólo en 1/25 casos (4%) se demostró cáncer que fue un seminoma puro. Conclusiones: En el seguimiento de los pacientes, ninguno presentó cáncer en el testículo contralateral entre 5-10 años. En los pacientes en los que se efectuó orquidopexia ninguno presentó cáncer del testículo entre 5-11 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;29(10): 969-973, nov.-dic. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043163</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Es necesaria la orquidectomía en los pacientes con testículo no descendido post-puberal?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3473^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23533^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3473^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
