<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119086</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Traumatic events in Psychology college students and current post-traumatic symptomatology, depression, anxiety and stress</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this work was to study the influence of a history of traumatic events, their type and characteristics, and personal factors on current post-traumatic symptomatology, depression, anxiety and stress among college students of psychology. Four hundred thirty-two college students completed a questionnaire of traumatic events and scales of depression, anxiety, stress and posttraumatic symptomatology. Current symptomatology was associated with the following variables: having a history of traumatic events, having suffered maltreatment/abuse/rape or a traumatic experience that the person refuses to tell, having experienced more than one type of traumatic event or more than one event, and having perceived the worst event as highly traumatic. The last three were the most important variables. Non-sexual violent crimes and intentional traumatic events were not associated with increased symptomatology. Results suggest that most college students, like other people, show great resilience to traumatic events, although this ability is more easily overwhelmed given certain characteristics of the events and the person</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toribio, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bados, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grego, Antonella</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo fue estudiar en universitarios de Psicología la influencia de la historia de eventos traumáticos, el tipo y características de estos y factores personales en la sintomatología postraumática, de depresión, ansiedad y estrés en la actualidad. Cuatrocientos treinta y dos universitarios contestaron un cuestionario de acontecimientos traumáticos y escalas de depresión, ansiedad, estrés y sintomatología postraumática. La sintomatología actual estuvo asociada con tener una historia de experiencias traumáticas, haber padecido maltrato/abuso/forzamiento sexual o una experiencia traumática que no se quería contar, haber experimentado más de un tipo de evento traumático o más de un evento y haber percibido como altamente traumático el peor acontecimiento experimentado. Estas tres últimas variables fueron las más importantes. Los delitos violentos no sexuales y los eventos traumáticos deliberadamente causados por otros no estuvieron asociados con una mayor sintomatología. Los resultados sugieren que la mayoría de universitarios, al igual que otras personas, muestran una gran capacidad de resiliencia ante los eventos traumáticos, aunque esta capacidad se ve más fácilmente desbordada bajo ciertas características de los eventos y la persona (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;21(2): 303-319, mayo-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119086</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eventos traumáticos en universitarios de psicología y sintomatología postraumática, de depresión, ansiedad y estrés en la actualidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
