<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60047</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The impact of statins use in clinically localized prostate cancer treated with radical prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Use of statins has been associated with reduced risk, progression and mortality of some tumors, including prostate cancer (CaP).According to recent Studies, long-term treatment with statins significantly reduces the risk of PC and also confers a protective effect against advanced or aggressive CaP. However, there is no conclusive data regarding the potential effect on patients diagnosed with clinically localized CaP undergoing radical treatment. Materials and methods: A retrospective study was performed in a cohort of 250 patients that did not undergo screening and diagnosis in clinical practice of localized CaP (T1c-T2cNxM0). All patients were treated with radical prostatectomy between 2001 and 2008. Data about clinical and pathological findings, and also the existence of dyslipemia as well as treatment with statins for at least 5 years was collected and analyzed. A logistic regression analysis was performed to determine the independent predictive variables related with a more favorable pathology. Results: In our study, we found a relationship, using a univariate analysis, between treatment with statins and the presence of insignificant carcinoma in the group with low or intermediate risk of recurrence. However, this relationship is not independent when we applied a multivariate analysis. Discussion: Hypothesis about the potential effect of the statins preventing or inhibiting the development of high risk CaP needs to be proven applying specific clinical trials designed for this purpose. There isn&#146;t conclusive data that demonstrate that statins lower the risk of development of potentially lethal high grade CaP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arango Toro, Octavio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fumadó Ciutat, Lluis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bielsa Galí, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente Garin, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frances Comalat, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rijo Mora, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El empleo de estatinas se ha relacionado con la reducción del riesgo, progresión y mortalidad de algunos tumores, incluyendo el cáncer de próstata (CP). Según estudios recientes el tratamiento con estatinas a largo plazo no reduce significativamente el riesgo de padecer CP pero parece conferir un efecto protector frente al CP avanzado o agresivo. No existen datos concluyentes del efecto potencial en los pacientes diagnosticados de CP clínicamente localizado y sometidos a tratamiento radical. Material y métodos: Se realiza un análisis retrospectivo en una cohorte de 250 pacientes no sometidos a cribado y diagnosticados en la práctica clínica de CP localizado (T1c-T2cNxM0) tratados con prostatectomía radical desde el año 2001 a 2008. Se recogen las variables clínicas y patológicas además de la existencia de dislipemia y el tratamiento con estatinasdurante al menos 5 años. Se empleó un análisis de regresión logística para determinar las variables independientes predictoras de una patología más favorable. Resultados: En el análisis univariante hemos encontrado relación entre el tratamiento con estatinas, la presencia de carcinoma insignificante y el grupo de riesgo de recidiva bajo o intermedio. Sin embargo, está relación no es independiente en el análisis multivariante. Discusión: La hipótesis sobre el potencial efecto de las estatinas en la prevención o la inhibición del desarrollo del cáncer de alto riesgo necesita de ensayos clínicos diseñados para analizar este objetivo. Existen datos no concluyentes que parecen favorecer a los pacientes tratados con estatinas presentando un menor riesgo de CP de alto grado y probablemente letal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;33(4): 351-355, abr. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60047</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del empleo de estatinas en el cáncer de próstata clínicamente localizado tratado con prostatectomía radical</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
