<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109184</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of new diagnostic criteria for osteoporosis in type 2 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Recent data suggest new diagnostic criteria for osteoporosis in type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM): femoral neck Tscore below -1.9 in women and below -2.1 in men. Our objective was to evaluate the percentage of patients diagnosed with osteoporosis according to these new criteria in a population of T2DM patients, and to analyse if there were differences compared to the WHO criteria for osteoporosis. Material and methods: Cross-sectional study including 78 T2DM patients. Bone mineral density (BMD) was evaluated by dual X-Ray absorptiometry (DXA, Hologic QDR 4500). The percentage of patients with osteoporosis was determined using the WHO criteria (T-score &lt;2.5) and also according to the new criteria. Data were processed and analysed with SPSS 15.0. Results: Mean age was 57.8 years (57.8±6.4). According to the WHO criteria, 19% of patients had lumbar osteoporosis, 2.6% osteoporosis in femoral neck (FN), and 4% in total femur (TF). When the new criteria were used, 29% of patients had lumbar spine osteoporosis, 11.5% FN osteoporosis, and 10% TF osteoporosis (P&lt;.05 for all compared to WHO classification). Conclusions: The application of the new criteria for diagnosis of osteoporosis in T2DM enables a higher number of cases to be identified, which can help to improve the assessment of fracture risk in T2DM(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Reyes García, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rozas Moreno, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Martín, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varsavsky, Mariela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Gallardo, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Torres, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Datos recientes sugieren nuevos puntos de corte para el diagnóstico de osteoporosis en la diabetes tipo 2 (DM2): T-score femoral &#150;1,9 en la mujer y &#150;2,1 en varones. Nuestro objetivo fue evaluar el porcentaje de pacientes diagnosticados de osteoporosis según estos nuevos criterios en una muestra de pacientes con DM2, y analizar si existen diferencias con los criterios clásicos de la OMS. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal con 78 pacientes con DM2. Se evaluó la densidad mineral ósea (DMO) por dual X-Ray absorptiometry (DXA, Hologic QDR 4500). El porcentaje de pacientes con osteoporosis se determinó según los criterios clásicos de la OMS (T-score &lt; &#150;2,5) y de acuerdo con los nuevos criterios. Los resultados se analizaron con el programa SPSS 15.0. Resultados: La edad media ± desviación estándar de los pacientes fue 57,8 años (57,8 ± 6,4). El 44,8% eran mujeres (n = 35) y el 55,2%, varones (n = 43). Según los criterios clásicos de la OMS, un 19% de los pacientes presentaron osteoporosis en la columna lumbar (CL), el 2,6% en cuello femoral (CF) y el 4% en cadera total (CT). Aplicando los nuevos criterios, un 29% de pacientes presentaron osteoporosis en CL, un 11,5% en CF y un 10% en CT (p &lt; 0,05 respecto a criterios de la OMS). Conclusiones: La aplicación de los nuevos criterios propuestos para el diagnóstico de osteoporosis en DM2 permite la identificación de un mayor número de casos, por lo que creemos que su uso puede ayudar a una mejor evaluación del riesgo de fractura en la DM2(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;28(5): 114-117, sep.-oct. 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109184</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de nuevos criterios de osteoporosis en la diabetes tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24502^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24543^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
