<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93377</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analyze clinical trials performed in our setting for the past three years from a gender-related standpoint.Material and methods: A retrospective study of 101 trials in which the pharmacy department of a 1,240-bed university hospital took part.Data sources: protocols and summary reports by the pharmacy department, Gecos® software program, trial follow-up cards,reception records, sample dispensation and returns, and yearly reports.Results: 17 trials included women only, 13 trials included men only, and 71 trials included patients of both genders.In female-only trials the most commonly studied condition was breast cancer (70.6%), the most common phases were phase III(47.1%) and II (41.2%) and the most commonly studied drugs were docetaxel (17.7%) and trastuzumab (11.8%).In male-only trials the most commonly studied condition was erectile dysfunction (92.3%), the most common phase was phaseIII (76.9%) and the most commonly studied drugs were tadalafil(38.5%) and vardenafil (30.8%).In trials without gender-related inclusion criteria the most commonly studied conditions included colon cancer (11.3%), lung cancer(11.3%), and renal failure (9.9%); the most common phase was phase III (57.7%) and the most frequently assayed drugs were interferon alpha-2a, gemcitabine and ribavirin. Overall participation rate was 62.3% for males and 37.7% for females.Conclusions: a) Regardless of gender, the most commonly studied condition was cancer, with breast cancer being most common in female-only trials and erectile dysfunction in male-only trials; b)male and female participation followed a 2:1 ratio in trials without gender-related inclusion criteria; and c) phase III was most commonamongst all trials considered, with phase II having a relevant role inwomen-only trials as per guidelines favoring inclusion in early trials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Idoipe, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izuel-Rami, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cilveti, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arenere, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar desde la perspectiva de género los ensayos clínicos llevados a cabo en nuestro medio en los tres últimos años. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo sobre una muestra de 101 ensayos realizados con la participación del servicio de farmacia de un hospital universitario de 1.240 camas. Fuentes de datos: protocolos e informes-resumen elaborados por el servicio de farmacia, programa informático Gecos®, fichas de seguimiento de ensayos, registro de recepción, dispensación y devolución de muestras e informes anuales.Resultados: 17 ensayos analizados incluían exclusivamente mujeres, 13 sólo hombres y 71 pacientes de ambos sexos. En ensayos de participación exclusivamente femenina la patología más estudiada fue cáncer de mama (70,6%), las fases de ensayo más frecuentes la III (47,1%) y la II (41,2%) y los medicamentos más investigados docetaxel (17,7%) y trastuzumab (11,8%).En ensayos de participación exclusivamente masculina disfunción eréctil fue la patología más estudiada (92,3%), la fase III lamás frecuente (76,9%) y tadalafilo (38,5%) y vardenafilo (30,8%)los fármacos más implicados.En ensayos sin criterios de inclusión  (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;28(6): 445-453, ene. -dic. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93377</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del género en investigación clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
