<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99212</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Predialysis is a clinical situation in which the patient has significant impairment of kidney function that will ultimately lead to either death or inclusion in kidney replacement therapy (dialysis and/or transplantation).Since a practical and effective dialysis technique was introduced, the length and quality of survival of patients with end-stage renal failure has constantly increased. Contraindications for dialysis are almost never of a renal origin. The obstacles are the concomitant diseases of the patient. The age of the patient may be one of these obstacles. The average age at initiation of dialysis in our country is currently 67 years and over 50% of patients are 60 years old or older.&#149; Decision making From an ethical viewpoint, there is a consensus in stating that anything that can technically be done, should be done. The principle of non maleficence and respect for the autonomy of the patients are «prima facie» principles when the physician has (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bardón Otero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarrias Lorenz, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila Paz, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La pre-diálisis es una situación clínica en la que el paciente tiene una importante afectación de la función renal y cuyo destino final será la muerte o la inclusión en tratamiento renal sustitutivo (diálisis y/o trasplante).Desde que se logró implantar la técnica de diálisis deforma práctica y eficaz, cada vez es mayor y mejor la supervivencia de los pacientes en insuficiencia renal terminal Las contraindicaciones a la diálisis, casi nunca son de origen renal. Los impedimentos son las enfermedades concomitantes del paciente. Uno de estos impedimentos podría ser la vejez del individuo. Actualmente la edad (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;28(supl.3): 119-122, ene.-dic. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99212</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El paciente en pre-diálisis: toma de decisiones y libre elección terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
