<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84304</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impulsivity as a predictor of smoking relapse</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: This paper aims to establish whether people with high impulsivity scores are also more likely to take up smoking again in the first six months after cessation. Method: We studied a sample of 92 people who had voluntarily decided to give up smoking, using the BIS-11 impulsivity score and recording the number of cigarettes smoked in the first six months after cessation. All subjects attended cognitive behavioural group therapy and were given nicotine replacement drug therapy. Results: Our results show that impulsivity is a predictor of smoking relapse. Conclusions: Impulsivity is a predictor of smoking relapse in people who had voluntarily decided to give up smoking (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perea-Baena, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oña-Compan, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El presente estudio pretende averiguar si las personas que puntúan más alto en impulsividad tendrán más probabilidades de volver a fumar durante los seis primeros meses tras el abandono del tabaco. Método: Se estudió, en una muestra de 92 personas que decidieron voluntariamente abandonar el hábito, las puntuaciones de impulsividad con el BIS-11 y los cigarrillos fumados en los seis primeros meses tras el abandono. Todas las personas fueron sometidas a tratamiento psicológico cognitivo-conductual en grupo y a tratamiento farmacológico con terapia sustitutiva de nicotina. Resultados: Los resultados muestran que la impulsividad es un predictor de vuelta al consumo en la muestra analizada. Conclusiones: la impulsividad es un predictor de recaída en personas que desean abandonar el consumo de tabaco (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(1): 1-6, ene.-abr. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84304</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impulsividad como predictor de recaída en el abandono de tabaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7353^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
