<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-168613</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disability vs dependency. Differential terminology and its recognition process</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Disability and dependency are near situations upon their concept, however, they cannot be compared between them. Each of them determine particular and differentiated conditions; with specific limitations for the individual. Nevertheless the mention above we realize, through our daily praxis, that the both terms are wrong used by the Public Administration users and by social and health professionals as well. After the review of available current bibliography, this article aims the concept clarification and the critical analysis of the both terms. The processes for the administrative recognition of these terms will be exposed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Rodríguez, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La discapacidad y la dependencia son situaciones conceptualmente próximas pero no equiparables. Cada una de ellas determina unas condiciones concretas y diferenciadas, con limitaciones específicas para el individuo. Sin embargo, en nuestra praxis diaria observamos que son términos comprendidos erróneamente por las personas usuarias de las Administraciones Públicas y usadas también de forma inapropiada por los profesionales del ámbito social y sanitario. Tras la pertinente revisión de la literatura existente, el presente artículo tiene como objetivo la clarificación conceptual y el análisis crítico de los dos términos exponiendo, asimismo, los procedimientos para el reconocimiento administrativo de ambos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;26(3): 170-174, jul.-sept. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-168613</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Discapacidad vs dependencia. Terminología diferencial y procedimiento para su reconocimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28588^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28445^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28445^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
