<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120775</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of care indicators for the care of human immunodeficiency virus-infected individuals, adapted to the pediatric age</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Since infection with human immunode&amp;#64257;ciency virus (HIV) was &amp;#64257;rst described, there have been many advances in its diagnosis, monitoring and treatment. However, few contributions are related to the area of health care quality. In this sense, the Spanish Study Group on AIDS (GESIDA) has developed a set of quality care indicators for adult patients living with HIV infection that includes a total of 66 indicators, 22 of which are considered to be relevant. Standards were calculated for each of them in order to re&amp;#64258;ect the level of the quality of care offered to these patients. Similar documents for pediatric patients are currently lacking. Methods: Preparation of a set of quality care indicators applicable to pediatric patients based on the GESIDA document and the Spanish Guidelines for monitoring of pediatric patients infected with HIV. Each indicator was analysed with respect to the required standards in all patients under 18 years of age followed-up in our Unit, with the aim of evaluating the quality of care provided. Results: A total of 61 indicators were collected (51 from the GESIDA document and 10 from currently available pediatric guidelines), 30 of which were considered to be relevant. An overall compliance of81%-83% was obtained when assessing the relevant indicators Conclusion: The availability of health care quality standards is essential for the care of pediatric HIV infected patients. The assessment of these indicators in our Unit yielded satisfactory result (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Figueras, Concepció</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Provens, Ana Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Nalda, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espiau, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler-Palacín, Pere</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Polo, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Desde la descripción de la infección por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) se han producido muchos avances en su diagnóstico, seguimiento y tratamiento. Sin embargo, son escasas las aportaciones relacionadas con el área de calidad asistencial. En este sentido, el Grupo de Estudio de Sida (GESIDA) ha elaborado un documento con 66 indicadores de calidad asistencial para la atención de los adultos que viven con el VIH &#151;de los que 22 se consideran relevantes&#151; que recoge con sus estándares de cumplimiento requeridos correspondientes. No disponemos de un documento de estas características para el paciente pediátrico. Métodos Elaboración de indicadores de calidad aplicables a la edad pediátrica a partir del documento de GESIDA y las Guías Españolas para el seguimiento del paciente pediátrico infectado por el VIH. Se analizó cada uno de los indicadores respecto a los estándares requeridos en todos los pacientes &lt; 18 años controlados en nuestra unidad con el fin de evaluar la asistencia ofrecida. Resultados Se obtuvo un total de 61 indicadores, 51 adaptados del documento GESIDA para la población adulta y 10 adecuados según las guías pediátricas, de los cuales 30 se consideraron relevantes. Se obtuvo un cumplimiento global del 81%, y del 83% en los indicadores relevantes. Conclusión La creación y el cumplimiento de unos estándares de calidad asistencial es imprescindible en la atención del paciente pediátrico infectado por el VIH. La evaluación del seguimiento de nuestros pacientes a partir de estos indicadores ofreció resultados satisfactorios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(3): 160-169, mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120775</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicadores de calidad asistencial para la atención de personas que viven con el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana, adaptados a la edad pediátrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
