<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91712</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypochondroplasia. Clinical, radiological and genetic diagnosis. Base don two early observations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hipochondroplasia is an osteochondrodyplasia characterized by short stature. Clinical and molecularly similar to achondroplasia since the shortening of legs and bowing of the extremities occur in both syndromes The causative mutations of both entities are in the FGFR3 gene. Misdiagnosis is common since clinical manifestations are subtle in hypochondroplasia. The knowledge, identification and genetic assessment are necessary to avoid possible complications and to evaluate orthopedic therapy with leg lengthening combined with correction of bowlegs as an alternative until we have something else to offer to these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Niaza Rosas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Toral, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llano Rivas, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vivanco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipocondroplasia es una forma de hipocrecimiento por osteocondordisplasi, de posible infradiagnóstico y transmisión autosómica dominante. Forma menor de la condroplasia, con mutación igualmente localizada en el gen FGFR3, su conocimiento y precocidad en la identificación conducen al asesoramiento genético, a disminuir con medidas de higiene física sus posibles complicaciones y a plantear el alargamiento óseo para mejorar la falla final, mientras no tengamos otras soluciones médicas para ella (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;66(3): 167-170, mayo-jun. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91712</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipocondroplasia. Diagnóstico Clínico, radiológico y genético. A propósito de dos observaciones precoces</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1877^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2856^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2856^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
