<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129115</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Promoting healthy eating in Secondary Education: consensus on assessment indicators</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The aim of the present study was to establish a  consensus among experts on indicators that define  secondary schools as promoters of healthy eating. Method: The Delphi technique has been used with three  successive shipments through online questionnaires and table of contents via email. A total of 68 experts in nutrition  and health promotion have participated. Results: Three main indicators for the promotion of healthy  eating in secondary schools have been proposed and agreed: 1. Related to the school (the most important indicators are associated with the school plan, the curriculum and teacher training) 2. Related to the school cafeteria (food supply,  healthy product placement and advertising) 3. Related to the community (community participation and training of other members of the learning environment and family). Conclusions: This material is the basis for the development of tools that allow us to make a diagnosis on the promotion of healthy eating for Secondary Schools (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Padilla, Francisca M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frigolet Maceras, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Haro, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, Angustias</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El objetivo del presente estudio ha sido  establecer un consenso entre personas expertas sobre indicadores que definen a los centros de Educación  Secundaria como promotores de una alimentación saludable. Método: Se ha utilizado la técnica Delphi con tres envíos  sucesivos a través de cuestionarios online y cuadro de  contenidos mediante correo electrónico. Han participado un  total de 68 expertos y expertas en alimentación y promoción de salud. Resultados: Se han propuesto y consensuado tres grandes bloques con los correspondientes indicadores de promoción de una alimentación saludable en los centros de Educación Secundaria: 1. Relacionados con el Centro (los indicadores de mayor relevancia están relacionados, con el proyecto  educativo del centro, el currículum escolar y la formación del profesorado) 2. Relacionados con la Cafetería del centro  (oferta alimentaria, ubicación de productos saludables y  publicidad) 3. Relacionados con la comunidad (participación comunitaria y formación de otros miembros del entorno educativo y familiar). Conclusiones: Este material supone la base para la  elaboración de instrumentos que permitan realizar un diagnóstico sobre la promoción de la alimentación saludable en los Institutos de Enseñanza Secundaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;18(3): 145-150, jul.-sept. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129115</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La promoción de la alimentación saludable en Educación Secundaria: consenso sobre indicadores de valoración</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24455^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30863^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30863^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30863^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38359</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36411</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
