<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156442</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Occupational asthma caused byt wo different agents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe a case of a worker with occupational asthma caused by two separate etiologic agents, resulting from mixed exposures in different work areas. Isocyanates and epoxy resins are established causes of occupational disease, and their role in this case was confirmed by immediate and delayed pulmonary function testing, together with a specific bronchial challenge. A thorough evaluation of exposure to harmful substances in the workplace is essential, together with continued clinical monitoring following cessation of exposure in order to verify clinical improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Frías Jiménez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ibáñez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Arcediano, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Audicana Berasategui, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girao Popolizio, Italo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el caso de una trabajadora con asma ocupacional en el que se detecta un doble agente etiológico condicionado por la exposición mixta en distintas áreas de trabajo. Los isocianatos y resinas epoxi se han descrito como responsables de enfermedad profesional y se ha confirmado su relevancia en las pruebas de función pulmonar tanto de manera inmediata como tardía y en la prueba de provocación bronquial específica. Se destaca la necesidad de evaluar exhaustivamente la exposición a sustancias en el ambiente laboral y comprobar la mejoría clínica tras el cese permanente de la exposición a los agentes implicados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);19(4): 231-233, oct.-dic. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156442</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asma ocupacional por doble agente causal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d16359^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31380^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31380^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31380^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31380^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16359^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4933^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4933^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
