<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127582</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Iodine nutrition in pregnant women from Oviedo area. Is iodine supplementation necessary?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective In Asturias, where iodine deficiency was eradicated in school children by the year 2000, iodine deficiency persisted in pregnant women, who were recommended to use of iodine supplementation. The aim of this study was to determine the iodine nutrition of pregnant women in our area and whether or not iodine supplements are needed. Material and methods Throughout May and June 2013 we studied the iodine nutrition and thyroid function during the first trimester of pregnancy in 173 women in the health area of Oviedo. Results The median urinary iodine was 197 &amp;#956;g/L. Iodinated supplements were used by 47% of women, which had a yoduria median higher than those not taking iodinated supplements (247 vs. 138 &amp;#956;g/L; p &lt; .001), and also a higher TSH (2.30 vs 1.94 mU/L) although not significantly different. Yoduria was also higher in women who took more than 2 servings of dairy products (median: 230 &amp;#956;g/L) than those who took less (median: 191 &amp;#956;g/L). Within the group of women who were not taking iodine supplements, those regularly using iodized salt in the kitchen (47%) had a median urinary iodine concentration of 190 &amp;#956;g/L indicating iodine sufficiency. Conclusions Iodinated supplements seem unnecessary nowadays in pregnant women of Oviedo who regularly take iodized salt and our recommendation in these cases should be to continue the use of iodized salt in the recommended amounts during pregnancy and consume at least two daily servings of milk or dairy products (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Caballero, María Galiana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Alvarez, Elías</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Torre, Edelmiro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rabal Artal, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ares Blanco, Jessica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Gutiérrez, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Fernández, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Naya, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo En Asturias, donde la deficiencia de yodo fue erradicada en los escolares en el año 2000, persistía una deficiencia de yodo en las mujeres embarazadas, por lo que se les recomendaba la utilización de suplementos yodados. El objetivo de este estudio es conocer la nutrición de yodo de las mujeres embarazadas de nuestra área y la necesidad o no de suplementos yodados. Material y métodos Durante mayo y junio de 2013 hemos estudiado la nutrición de yodo y la función tiroidea en el primer trimestre del embarazo de 173 mujeres del área sanitaria de Oviedo. Resultados La mediana de la yoduria fue 197 &amp;#956;g/L. Tomaban suplementos yodados el 47% de las mujeres, con una mediana de yoduria superior a la de las que no tomaban suplementos yodados (247 vs 138 &amp;#956;g/L; &lt;0,001) y también una TSH superior (2,30 vs 1,94 mU/L), aunque no significativamente diferente. La yoduria fue también superior en las mujeres que tomaban más de 2 raciones de productos lácteos (mediana: 230 &amp;#956;g/L) que en aquellas que tomaban menos de 2 raciones (mediana: 191 &amp;#956;g/L). Dentro del grupo de mujeres que no tomaban suplementos yodados, aquellas que utilizaban habitualmente sal yodada en la cocina (47%), tenían una mediana de yoduria de 190 &amp;#956;g/L, indicativa de suficiencia de yodo. Conclusión En la actualidad los suplementos yodados serían innecesarios en las mujeres embarazadas de nuestra entorno que consumen de forma habitual sal yodada y la recomendación en estos casos debería ser la de continuar utilizando la sal yodada en la cantidad recomendada en la gestación, así como consumir al menos dos raciones diarias de leche o productos lácteos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(8): 404-409, oct. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127582</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nutrición de yodo en mujeres embarazadas del área de Oviedo. ¿Es necesaria la suplementación con yodo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7619^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16596^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
