<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132783</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0952</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Herbal medicinal products: the challenge of the quality and the Pharmacopoeia as a tool for achieving it</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The quality of herbal medicinal products (HMP) is a challenge, mainly due to the difficulties linked to the variability and complexity of herbal drugs and herbal preparations, the limited knowledge of their active constituents, the possible adulterations and contaminations, as well as the influence of the production processes.This is a surmountable challenge. This requires having the quality as an objective from the beginning of the production chain, to establish strict controls on all stages, to improve the knowledge of the product, to optimize and to validate the production processes, to work under accepted international guidelines and to establish quality specifications.The European Pharmacopoeia, in Spain in the Royal Spanish Pharmacopoeia, is a key tool to overcome the challenge and maintaining high levels of quality of HMP in the EU. This is because the European Pharmacopoeia is an updated and transparent regulatory document, harmonized and agreed by 37 countries, which provides a unique collection of monographs and methods for the analysis of herbal drugs and preparations, and is also a provider of reference substances (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cañigueral Folcará, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La calidad de los medicamentos a base de plantas (MP) constituye un reto, principalmente por las dificultades ligadas a la variabilidad y complejidad de las drogas y preparados vegetales, el conocimiento limitado de sus constituyentes activos, la posibilidad de adulteraciones y contaminaciones, así como la influencia de los procesos de producción. Se trata de un reto superable. Para ello es necesario tener la calidad como objetivo desde el inicio de la cadena productiva, establecer controles estrictos de todas las etapas, mejorar el conocimiento del producto, optimizar y validar los procesos de producción, trabajar bajo las directrices internacionales aceptadas y establecer especificaciones de calidad.La Farmacopea Europea, en España dentro de la Real Farmacopea Española, constituye una herramienta clave para la superación del reto y el mantenimiento de altos niveles de calidad para los MP en la UE. Esto es así porque la Farmacopea Europea es un documento normativo actualizado, transparente, consensuado y armonizado por 37 países, que proporciona una colección singular de monografías y métodos para el análisis de drogas y preparados vegetales, siendo además un proveedor de sustancias de referencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. fitoter;13(2): 101-122, jul.-dic.2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132783</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medicamentos a base de plantas: el reto de la calidad y la Farmacopea como herramienta para alcanzarla</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16704</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36266^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11379^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11025^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
