<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87627</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">International Federation for Emergency Medicine Model Curriculum for Emergency Medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There is a critical and growing need for emergency physicians and emergency medicine resources worldwide. To meet this need, physicians must be trained to deliver time-sensitive interventions and life-saving emergency care. Currently, there is no internationally recognized, standard curriculum that defines the basic minimum standards for emergency medicine education. To address this lack, the International Federation for Emergency Medicine (IFEM) convened a committee of international physicians, health professionals and other experts in emergency medicine and international emergency medicine development, to outline a curriculum for foundation training of medical students in emergency medicine. This curriculum document represents the consensus of recommendations by this committee. The curriculum is designed with a focus on the basic minimum emergency medicine educational content that any medical school should be delivering to its students during their undergraduate years of training. It is designed, not to be prescriptive, but to assist educators and emergency medicine leadership in advancing physician education in basic emergency medicine content. The content would be relevant, not just for communities with mature emergency medicine systems, but also for developing nations or for nations seeking to expand emergency medicine within current educational structures. We anticipate that there will be wide variability in how this curriculum is implemented and taught, reflecting the existing educational milieu, the resources available, and the goals of the institutions&#146; educational leadership (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>International Federation For Emergency Medicine</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hay una necesidad crítica y creciente de médicos de urgencias y emergencias, así como de recursos para la Medicina de Urgencias y Emergencias (MUE) en todo el mundo. Para satisfacer esta necesidad, los médicos deben poder realizar intervenciones rápidas (time-sensitive) que salven vidas. Actualmente, no hay un plan de estudios estándar internacionalmente reconocido que defina las normas básicas de la formación en la MUE. Para hacer frente a esta falta, la Federación Internacional de Medicina de Urgencias(IFEM) convocó a una comisión internacional de médicos, profesionales de la salud y otros expertos en MUE y en el desarrollo internacional de la MUE, con el fin de elaborar un plan de estudios para la formación básica en ME de estudiantes de medicina. Este documento representa el consenso de las recomendaciones de esta comisión. El plan de estudios está diseñado con un enfoque sobre el mínimo contenido educativo que cualquier facultad de medicina debe impartir a sus alumnos durante sus años de formación de pregrado. Está diseñado no de forma prescriptiva sino para ayudar a los educadores y directores en la promoción de la formación básica de futuros médicos en el contenido de MUE. El contenido sería pertinente, no sólo para las comunidades maduras con sistemas de MUE, sino también para las naciones en desarrollo o para las naciones que tratan de ampliar la MUE dentro de las estructuras educativas actuales. Prevemos que habrá amplia variabilidad en la forma en que se aplique y se enseñe este plan de estudios, lo que refleja el actual entorno educativo, los recursos disponibles y los objetivos de las instituciones educativas de liderazgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);21(6): 451-455, dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87627</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Federación Internacional de Medicina de Urgencias: Modelo de plan de estudios para la formación deestudiantes en Medicina de Urgencias y Emergencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52888^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12958^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51692^s22082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28460</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3499^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
