<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118798</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4466</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mariano de la Paz Graells pronouncement on the herpetological works of Eduardo Boscá: analysis of a XIX century scientific evaluation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A scientific evaluation, requested by the naturalist Eduardo Boscá to the Spanish Dirección General de Instrucción Pública in 1891, is made known and analyzed. In this request, Boscá asks for an evaluation of his zoological publications dealing with amphibians and reptiles, completed between 1877 and 1883. The evaluation is made by the Spanish Real Academia de Ciencias through an unpublished comprehensive and critical Dictum written by Mariano de la Paz Graells in 1893. Through this Dictum we can perceive the real quality standards then required for taxonomy and faunistics, information not easily inferable from publications or mail correspondence. The analysis of this Dictum is here framed in the biographical history of the scientists involved, and also in the development of herpetology and Ibero-Balearic biodiversity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Albaladejo, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Prieto, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchiz, Borja</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se analiza y da a conocer una evaluación científica solicitada por el naturalista Eduardo Boscá a la Dirección General de Instrucción Pública en 1891 en la que pide le sean valoradas sus publicaciones sobre zoología de anfibios y reptiles, aparecidas entre 1877 y 1883. La evaluación la realiza Mariano de la Paz Graells en 1893 por encargo de la Real Academia de Ciencias mediante un extenso y crítico Dictamen inédito. A través de las críticas del informe podemos conocer los estándares reales de calidad entonces exigibles en taxonomía y faunística, no fácilmente deducibles de publicaciones ni de correspondencia epistolar. El Dictamen se encuadra en la historia biográfica de los científicos implicados, y en el desarrollo de la herpetología y la biodiversidad ibero-balear (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Asclepio;65(2): 1-14[p23], jul.-dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dictamen de Mariano de la Paz Graells sobre la obra herpetológica de Eduardo Boscá: análisis de una evaluación científica del siglo XIX</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37752^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38364</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15441^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10573^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
