<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97620</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Herpetic endotheliitis and trabeculitis with delayed corneal involvement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 62-year-old man with previous renal transplant and immunosuppressive treatment presented with decreased visual acuity (20/100) in his left eye, corneal oedema and intraocular pressure of 46mmHg. One month later an inferior marginal dendritic keratitis appeared. Corneal scraping and real-time polymerase chain reaction showed herpes simplex virus (HSV).        Discussion: The autoimmune corneal endotheliopathy or acute idiopathic corneal endotheliitis is characterised by corneal stromal oedema and keratic precipitates. HSV might be secreted from the trabeculum, innervated by the trigeminal nerve. This hypothesis is supported by the clinical observation that the corneal stromal oedema usually starts from the periphery(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Díaz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mencía-Gutiérrez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo-Arroyo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Pérez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero-Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Varón de 62 años de edad con trasplante renal y tratamiento inmunosupresor que acude por disminución de la visión (20/100) en ojo izquierdo, edema corneal y presión intraocular de 46mmHg. Un mes después aparece queratitis dendrítica marginal inferior. El raspado corneal y la proteína C reactiva demuestran la presencia de un virus del herpes simple (HVS).                                                   Discusión: La epiteliopatía corneal autoinmunitaria o endotelitis idiopática corneal se caracteriza por edema corneal y precipitados queráticos. Se cree que el HVS podría ser secretado desde el trabeculum, inervado por el nervio trigémino, apoyado clínicamente por la progresión del edema estromal desde la periferia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;87(2): 47-49, feb. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97620</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endotelitis y trabeculitis herpética con afectación corneal tardía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6720^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24636^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22889^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14522^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
