<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86220</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retrospective study of the complications of temporary catheters for haemodialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyze the duration and causes of removing complications for temporary catheters for haemodialysis. We studied 1409 catheters which were implanted on 608 patients in haemodialysis chronic (60.9 ± 15.5 years, 341 females (56%) and 267 males (44%). 280 (46%) patients received 1 catheter and 144 (24%) 2 catheters. We analyzed 546 catheters retired exclusively by complications. Mean duration of the catheters (n=546) of was 21±36 days. The main catheters complications that forced their retreat were: 75% for deficit blood flow rate, 11% infection, 6%, for loss of surgical suture, 3% for occlusion, 3% for elbowed. The deficit blood flow rate appeared to the 18 ± 34 days and the la infection to the 29±50 days. Mean duration of the catheters was of the 16±32 days for the left side and 23±38 for right side (p&lt;0.0001). When we compared the different blood vessel, mean duration of the catheters was of the 25.3±43 days for the jugular, 17.5±23 for the subclavia, and 11.9±10 days for the femoral, being significant differences among jugular-subclavia and femoral vein (p&lt;0.05). When comparing the duration, among a single lumen vs dual lumen, in catheters retired by complications, they were not significant differences (multivariate analysis). We can conclude that the duration, of the catheters placed in jugular or subclavia veins and right side is superior to the placed in femoral vein or left side, being recommended its use therefore as temporary access in HD, also facilitating the patient&#146;s mobility and ambulatory dialysis. We have not found, at least in our study, differs in the duration among the single lumen versus dual lumen catheters (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Contreras Abad, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Cuesta, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Montero, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suanes Cabello, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Delgado, María Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Benítez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos de este estudio fueron analizar la duración y las causas de retirada de los catéteres temporales para hemodiálisis Hemos estudiado 1409 catéteres que fueron implantados en 608 pacientes en hemodiálisis periódicas (60.9 ± 15.5 años, 341 mujeres (56%) y 267 hombres (44%). 280 (46%) pacientes recibieron 1 catéter y 144 (24%) 2 catéteres. Posteriormente se analizaron 546 catéteres retirados exclusivamente por complicaciones. La duración media de todos los catéteres (n=546) fue de 21±36 días. Las causas más frecuentes de retirada de catéteres por complicaciones fueron: 75% por déficit de flujo sanguíneo, 11% por infección, 6% por pérdida de sutura, 3% por oclusión, 3% por acodamiento. El déficit de flujo apareció a los 18 ± 34 días y la infección 29±50 días. La duración media de los catéteres implantados en el lado izquierdo fue 16±32 días y para el lado derecho 23±38 días (p&lt;0.0001). Cuando analizamos la duración de los catéteres entre las distintas venas utilizadas, la duración media fue de 2 5.3±43 días para la yugular, 17.5±23 para la subclavia, y 11.9±10 días para la femoral, siendo las diferencias estadísticamente entre la yugularsubclavia y la vena femoral (p&lt;0.05). Cuando comparamos la duración entre los de una sola luz frente a los de doble luz, en los catéteres retirados por complicaciones no se encuentran diferencias significativas (análisis multivariante). Podemos concluir, que la duración de los catéteres temporales colocados en vena yugular o subclavia y en el lado derecho, es significativamente superior a los colocados en vena femoral o lado izquierdo. No encontramos diferencias en la duración entre los catéteres de una o doble luz, al menos en nuestro estudio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;14(1): 43-49, ene.-mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86220</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio retrospectivo de las complicaciones de los catéteres temporales para hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5372^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13738^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5372^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13738^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
