<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84935</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Axillary approach for transcatheter aortic valve implantation: optimization of the endovascular treatment for the aortic valve stenosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: To validate the axillary approach as a safe and efficient option for the transcatheter aortic valve implantation in patients who have contraindication for femoral approach at three Spanish hospitals. Methods: We included patients with severe symptomatic aortic stenosis at very high or prohibitive surgical risk, selected by a multidisciplinary team, for transcatheter aortic valve implantation, and had contraindication to the femoral approach. Results: We included 19 of 186 (10.5%) patients, who were implanted a percutaneous aortic valve, between November 2008 and March 2010. Themean age was 78.3 (standard deviation [SD] +/- 8.65) years and 73.7% were males. The mean logistic EuroSCORE was 28.7% (SD +/- 16.3%). The procedural success rate was 100%. After the procedure the maximum transvalve gradient decreased from 81.7 mmHg (SD +/- 21.5) to 15.8 mmHg (SD +/- 5.5), and no patient presented residual aortic regurgitation &gt;2. The all-cause mortality, with a mean follow-up time of 9.2 (SD +/- 3.2) months was 10.5%, and the in-hospital and 30-day mortality rates were 0%. The global incidence of major complications due to the procedure was 15.7%. Definitive pacemaker implantation was carried out for atrioventricular block in 8 patients (44.4%). Conclusions: The axillary approach for transcatheter aortic valve implantation using the CoreValveW and contraindication to the femoral approach is safe and efficient for selected patients, with excellent results in terms of success implantation and in hospital and 30-day mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Briales, JuanH</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Íñigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morís, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-García, Antonio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avanzas, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trillo-Nouche, Ramiro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Otero, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-García, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto-Castro, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Validar el acceso axilar como una opción eficaz y segura para el implante percutáneo de válvula aórtica percutánea CoreValve®, en pacientes con contraindicación para el acceso femoral, en tres hospitales españoles. Métodos. Incluimos a pacientes con estenosis aórtica severa sintomática y alto riesgo quirúrgico o contraindicación para cirugía, seleccionados por un equipo multidisciplinario para implante percutáneo de válvula aórtica; además, los pacientes tenían contraindicación para el abordaje arterial femoral. Resultados. Incluimos a 19 de los 186 pacientes (10,2%) a los que se implantó una válvula percutánea entre noviembre de 2008 y marzo de 2010. La media de edad era 78,3±8,65 años y el 73,7% eran varones. El EuroSCORE logístico medio de la muestra fue del 28,7%±16,3%. La tasa de éxito de implante fue del 100%. Tras el implante, el gradiente transvalvular máximo pasó de 81,7±21,5 a 15,8±5,5 mmHg, y ningún paciente presentó insuficiencia aórtica residual &gt; 2. La mortalidad total, con un seguimiento medio de 9,2±3,2 meses, fue del 10,5%, con nula mortalidad intraoperatoria y a los 30 días. La incidencia total de complicaciones mayores atribuibles al procedimiento fue del 15,7%. Se implantó marcapasos definitivo por bloqueo auriculoventricular en 8 pacientes (44,4%). Conclusiones. El uso del acceso axilar en pacientes seleccionados para implante percutáneo de válvula aórtica CoreValve® con contraindicación para el acceso femoral es seguro y eficaz y proporciona excelentes resultados en términos de éxito del implante y mortalidad, tanto intrahospitalaria como a los 30 días (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(2): 121-126, feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84935</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acceso axilar en el implante percutáneo de la válvula aórtica: optimización del tratamiento endovascular de la estenosis aórtica severa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1378^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1028^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1378^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11916^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
