<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106586</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-5434</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The first steps of Medicine Veterinary in Las Palmas de Gran Canaria (1904-1910)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The official veterinary service in Las Palmas de Gran Canaria was established between 1904 and 1910. In its beginnings, the local authority was forced to improvise and suffered from lack of experience, in an effort to procure veterinary teaching positions and most importantly, a veterinary service to cover the needs across its territory. This article analyses the process from its early days characterised by the implementation of legislation and a strong desire to put in place disease prevention strategies. Attitudes were markedly tainted by the reformist spirit that characterised the beginning of the century in the Canarian Archipelago(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín del Castillo J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre 1904 y 1910 se define el servicio veterinario municipal en Las Palmas de Gran Canaria. Es una etapa fundacional, sellada por la improvisación del gobierno local, el amateurismo de las conductas y las necesidades de garantizar un orden básico en la dotación de plazas de Profesor Veterinario y, sobre todo, la de procurar la sanidad animal en el territorio. En el presente, se analiza este proceso que transcurre desde la aceptación de la normativa legal del ramo, con todas sus consecuencias, hasta el definitivo afán preventivo. Por encima de la breve trama veterinaria, se advierten las claves históricas del reformismo de principios de siglo en el archipiélago canario(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. vet. Murcia;27: 5-21, ene.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106586</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los primeros pasos de la medicina veterinaria en Las Palmas de Gran Canaria (1904-1910)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31978</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4590^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8065^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15134^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15134^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8065^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50337</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8065^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15134^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
