<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051811</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Estimation of prevalence, incidence and sex ratio of transsexualism in Catalonia according to health care demand</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To estimate the epidemiology of transsexualism in the autonomous community of Catalonia according to data gathered at the Hospital Clinic of Barcelona, the single public hospital providing specialized psychiatric and endocrinological care for transsexual patients in this community.    Patients and methods. Prevalence was calculated on the basis of the total number of patients diagnosed of transsexualism (ICD-10, F64.0) at the Hospital Clinic and living in Catalonia, and the incidence by counting all new cases of transsexuals for the last 5 years, based on the population census between 15 and 65 years of age.        Results. During the period from 1996 through 2004 a total of 201 subjects were referred to this hospital with complaints of gender dysphoria. Transsexualism was diagnosed in 182 patients, 161 of whom were living in Catalonia. This yields a prevalence rate in Catalonia of 1:21,031 males and 1:48,096 females. The sex ratio was 2.6. Annual incidence in the last five years was 0.73/100,000/year.        Discussion. The low prevalence compared with recently published data from European Union countries may be due to the relatively few years of data collection and to the low clinical demand because surgical procedures costs are not covered by the public health insurance. In contrast, the high incidence may be due to the increasing demand since 2000, when a more benevolent and tolerant social climate in Spain started</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Godás Sieso, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Halperin Rabinovich, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gil, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trilla García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peri Nogués, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puig Domingo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal Hagemeijer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se realiza una estimación de la distribución epidemiológica del transexualismo en Cataluña según la demanda observada en el Hospital Clínic de Barcelona, que es el único hospital público que proporciona atención psiquiátrica y endocrinológica especializada a estos pacientes en esta comunidad autónoma.    Pacientes y método. La prevalencia se calculó según el número total de pacientes diagnosticados de transexualismo (CIE-10, F64.0) en el Hospital Clínic residentes en Cataluña y la incidencia según el número de pacientes con nuevo diagnóstico durante los últimos 5 años en relación con los datos de población de edad entre 15 y 65 años.        Resultados. Entre los años 1996 y 2004 solicitaron atención por disforia de género un total de 201 pacientes. Se diagnosticó transexualismo en 182 pacientes, de los cuales 161 vivían en Cataluña. La prevalencia estimada de transexualismo en Cataluña fue de 1:21.031 varones y 1:48.096 mujeres. La razón de sexos fue de 2,6 a favor del grupo de transexuales hombre a mujer. La incidencia media anual en los últimos 5 años fue de 0,72/100.000 habitantes/año.        Discusión. La baja prevalencia observada, en comparación con los datos publicados por países de la Unión Europea, se puede atribuir al período corto de recogida de datos y a la baja demanda registrada al no estar financiado el tratamiento de reasignación de sexo por el Sistema Nacional de Salud. La elevada incidencia se puede atribuir al incremento de la demanda desde el año 2000, que coincide con un clima social de mayor aceptación y tolerancia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;34(5): 295-302, sept.-oct. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051811</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimación de la prevalencia, incidencia y razón de sexos del transexualismo en Cataluña según la demanda asistencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33534^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13115^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6453^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
