<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166735</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9218</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The "I-VALOR" program: standardized, protocolized, and registered drug indications for community pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In 2013, the Sociedad Española de Farmacia Familiar y Comunitaria (SEFAC) [Spanish Society of Community Pharmacy] launched the Revisa(R) project. Managed by the Medicines Use Review (MUR) Subcommittee, part of the Professional Services Committee, the project takes its inspiration from the British MUR service and seeks to introduce a similar service throughout Spain. Since then, training courses have been delivered, specification documents drawn up, and protocols standardized, to enable community pharmacy to deliver the service to the public in an appropriate and consistent manner. A module to manage the service has also been developed in SEFAC e_XPERT, a computer program designed by SEFAC to manage professional pharmaceutical services. In 2016, SEFAC completed the first research study linked to the medicines use review service, designed to pilot its work in pharmaceutical practice. This report presents the time and cost results obtained by analyzing the data collected as part of the Revisa(R) project from 64 pharmacies in Spain between March and July 2016. The aim is to provide community pharmacy with the information required to establish the appropriate fees for the delivery of this service, based on evidence obtained from pharmaceutical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Agua Soler, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Bermúdez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jódar Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baixauli Fernández, VJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el año 2013 la Sociedad Española de Farmacia Familiar y Comunitaria (SEFAC), mediante la subcomisión de revisión del uso de los medicamentos (RUM), integrada en la comisión de servicios profesionales e inspirada en el servicio británico MUR (Medicines Use Review), puso en marcha el proyecto Revisa(R) con el fin de implantar este servicio en España. Desde entonces se han realizado cursos de capacitación, elaborado documentos de especificaciones y protocolos normalizados que permitan al farmacéutico comunitario prestar de manera adecuada y homogénea este servicio a la población. También se desarrolló un módulo para la gestión de este servicio en SEFAC e_XPERT, aplicación informática desarrollada por SEFAC para la gestión de los servicios profesionales farmacéuticos. En 2016 SEFAC llevó a cabo el primer estudio de investigación relacionado con el servicio de revisión del uso de los medicamentos con el fin de pilotar su prestación en la práctica farmacéutica. En este informe se presentan los resultados de tiempo y costes obtenidos del análisis de los datos del proyecto Revisa(R) realizado en 64 farmacias de España durante los meses de marzo a julio de 2016. Se pretende con ello facilitar al farmacéutico comunitario la información necesaria para permitirle establecer unos honorarios para la prestación de este servicio apoyado en la evidencia obtenida en la práctica farmacéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. comunitarios (Internet);9(3): 20-24, sept. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166735</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Proyecto "Revisa(R)". Impacto del servicio de revisión del uso de los medicamentos en España. Informe de tiempos y costes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10795^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4398^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31495^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30152^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55050^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55050^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
