<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91511</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence and relationship between physical activity and abnormal eating attitudes in spanish women university students in health and education sciences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Future education and health professionals will be responsible for promoting physical activity and correct eating habits among the general population. This work aims to describe the prevalence and the degree of correlation between physical level and eating disorders in a sample made of nursing, physiotherapy and education female students. Methods: A total of 258 female students doing university courses during the academic year 2009-2010 at theUniversity ofVigo (Pontevedra&#146;s Campus) and who were registered in nursing (87), physiotherapy (73) and education (98) took part in this transversal descriptive study. The International Physical Activity Questionnaire and the Eating Attitude Test were used to assess the prevalence of physical activity and eating disturbed attitudes respectively. Results: The data showed that 63 (64,7%) of nursing students and 63 (72,1%) of education students reported the higher physical inactivity values, while 19 (19.4%) and 13 (15,3%) of them were likely to suffer from eating disorders respectively. Significant differences were found between the academic degree and the physical activity level of the sample (chi2=10,265; Sig.&lt;0,05). The degree of association observed between physical activity energy expenditure and the existence of eating disturbed attitudes was only significant among education students (OR= 3,58; IC 95%= 1,29-9,93; Sig.&lt;0.05). Conclusion: An important prevalence of physical inactivity and eating disturbed attitudes seems to exist attitudes among education and nursing students. There is a chance that the performance of intense physical activity could be related to inadequate eating habits(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cancela Carral, Jose María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayán Pérez, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: Los futuros profesionales de la salud y de la educación serán los responsables de promover la práctica de actividad física y la correcta alimentación entre la población. Los objetivos de este trabajo son conocer la prevalencia y grado de asociación existente entre el nivel de actividad física y los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria en una población de mujeres estudiantes de enfermería, fisioterapia y magisterio. Método: Un total de 258 estudiantes universitarias matriculadas en el curso académico 2009-2010 en la Universidad de Vigo de las titulaciones de enfermería (87), fisioterapia (73) y magisterio (98), participaron en este estudio descriptivo-transversal. El nivel de actividad física fue valorado mediante el &#147;International Physical Activity Questionnaire&#148; y los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria mediante el &#147;Eating Attitude Test&#148;. Resultados: Los mayores niveles de inactividad física se detectaron en enfermería 63 (72,1%) y magisterio 63 (64,7%). Los trastornos de la conducta alimentaria fueron observados también en estas dos titulaciones: enfermería 13 (15,3%) y magisterio 19 (19,4%). Se encontraron diferencias significativas entre la titulación cursada y el nivel de actividad física (chi2=10,265; Sig.&lt;0,05). La asociación entre el gasto calórico derivado de la práctica de actividad física, y la posibilidad de padecer trastornos de la conducta alimentaria, fue significativa únicamente entre las estudiantes de magisterio (OR=3,58; IC 95%=1,29-9,93; Sig.&lt;0,05). Conclusiones: La inactividad física y los desórdenes alimenticios tienen una importante prevalencia entre las alumnas matriculadas en magisterio y enfermería. Existe la posibilidad de que la realización de actividad física intensa confluya con las actitudes alimenticias anómalas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;85(5): 499-505, sep.-oct.2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91511</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia y relación entre el nivel de actividad física y las actitudes alimenticias anómalas en estudiantes universitarias españolas de ciencias de la salud y la educación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52503^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
