<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130619</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perioperative management for liver transplant in a patient with familial amyloid polyneuropathy with heart involvement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Familial amyloid polyneuropathy (FAP) is a systemic amyloidosis caused by mutated transthyretin. Cardiac amyloidosis, the major prognostic determinant in systemic amyloidosis, is characterized by infiltration of the myocardium, leading to cardiomyopathy and conduction disturbances. Liver transplantation is the only curative option for patients with FAP. The case is presented of a 36-year-old patient with type i FAP with cardiac involvement, proposed for liver transplant surgery, which was successfully performed without any preoperative event of interest (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mellado Miras, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Herrera Rodríguez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Domínguez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sosa, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La polineuropatía amiloidótica familiar (PAF) es una amiloidosis sistémica causada por la mutación de la transtirretina. La amiloidosis cardíaca, el determinante pronóstico principal de la amiloidosis sistémica, se caracteriza por infiltración del miocardio, dando lugar a cardiomiopatía y alteraciones de la conducción. El trasplante hepático es la única opción curativa para los pacientes afectos de PAF. Presentamos el caso de un paciente de 36 años con PAF tipo i con afectación cardíaca propuesto para cirugía de trasplante hepático, la cual fue llevada a cabo con éxito sin eventos perioperatorios de interés (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;62(1): 46-48, ene. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130619</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo perioperatorio del trasplante hepático en la polineuropatía amiloidótica familiar con afectación cardíaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29476^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d775^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24347^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36030^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36014^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36014^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
