<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92442</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Safety and efficacy of polyethylene glycol 3350 plus electrolytes for the treatment of functional constipation in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Polyethylene glycol 3350 plus electrolytes (PEG+E) efficacy has been validated in some studies, but not many have evaluated its safety in children. The aim of our study was to evaluate the safety; renal, malabsorption or excessive production of gas and efficacy of PEG+E treatment in our paediatric population. Patients and methods: Fifteen patients who suffered functional constipation (Rome III criteria) were evaluated. Median age was 6.2 years (r 2-9). All patients had normal renal function. PEG+E were administered for 4weeks (4WP). The mean dose was 0.44g/kg/day, titrated according to age, weight and response. Urine screens (sodium and osmolality) were performed at the beginning and 4WP. Stool sample NIRA (near-infrared reflectance analysis) and hydrogen breath test analysis samples were performed at 4WP. To analyse the efficacy of the treatment, the number of stools per week and stool form type (Bristol stool scale) were recorded. Results: The number of stools per week was higher after 4weeks (2.46±0.71 vs 5.29±1.68, P&lt;0.001), as well as the stool form score (2.47±1.24 vs 4.5±0.91, P&lt;0.001). No statistical differences were obtained between urine sodium and urine osmolality values at the beginning and 4WP. After 4WP the NIRA median values were normal in all patients [fat 4.45% (range (r) 3.6-7.09); nitrogen 0.78% (r 0.4-1); sugars 1.4% (r 0.47-2.35) and water 68% (r 59-74)]. Median breath hydrogen test was 7ppm (r 2-18). Conclusions: No adverse effects on biochemistry values or gastrointestinal disturbances were observed. PEG+E can be recommended for the treatment of functional constipation in children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Beltrán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto Rey, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilalta Casas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segarra Canton, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redecillas Ferreiro, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Infante Pina, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miserachs Barba, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo del trabajo ha sido evaluar la seguridad del PEG 3350 con electrolitos (PEG+E) a nivel renal y digestivo. Objetivo secundario: valorar su eficacia y dosis de efectividad. Pacientes y métodos: Quince pacientes con estreñimiento funcional (criterios de Roma III) y función renal normal fueron evaluados. La mediana de edad fue de 6,2 años (r=2-9). Sobres pediátricos de PEG+E fueron administrados durante 4 semanas (4ST) La dosis media administrada fue de 0,44g/kg/día. La natruria y osmolaridad urinaria se midieron al inicio y a las 4ST. La determinación de principios inmediatos en heces mediante FENIR (análisis de reflexión de infrarrojos) y una prueba de hidrógeno espirado fueron efectuadas a las 4ST. La eficacia del tratamiento fue evaluada mediante el cambio en el número de deposiciones por semana y la consistencia de las heces (escala de Bristol). Resultados: A las 4ST el número de deposiciones por semana fue de 5,29±1,68 vs 2,46±0,71 al inicio (p&lt;0,001). La puntuación de la escala de Bristol fue de 4,5±0,91 tras 4TS vs 2,47±1,24 al inicio (p&lt;0,001). No se encontraron diferencias estadísticas entre los valores de sodio y osmolalidad en orina al inicio vs 4ST. Los valores de FENIR fueron normales en todos los pacientes. La prueba del aliento de hidrógeno fue normal con una mediana de 7ppm. Conclusiones: No se observaron efectos adversos renales ni alteraciones digestivas. El PEG+E puede ser recomendado para el tratamiento del estreñimiento funcional en los niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);75(2): 89-95, ago. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92442</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguridad y eficacia del polietilenglicol 3350 con electrolitos en el tratamiento del estreñimiento funcional en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52847^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11527^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
