<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88844</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parent-Doctor relations in oncology: a qualitative approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We want to learn how parents of children with cancer perceive their relationship with hospital staff, especially with doctors. We used group-based qualitative methodology. The sample is composed of 14 mothers/fathers whose children contracted the disease more than two years previously. All parents want information that is both intelligible and detailed. The word cancer has a strong social stigma and is avoided when giving information to parents and to children. Communication between doctors and parents can lead to situations of tension during diagnosis and relapses. Parents trust the professionalism of doctors. Parents also want doctors to be competent and to have human qualities. The preparation of reports by physicians is the task most criticized by parents (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fortes, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espada, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este artículo es conocer cómo los padres de niños enfermos de cáncer perciben sus relaciones con el personal sanitario, fundamentalmente con los médicos. Se ha utilizado una metodología de investigación cualitativa y grupal. La muestra la constituyen catorce madres/padres cuyos hijos hace más de dos años que han contraído la enfermedad. Los padres desean información inteligible, detallada y suficiente. La palabra cáncer tiene un gran estigma social, por lo que se intenta evitar cuando se da información a los padres y niños. La comunicación entre los médicos y padres puede tener momentos de tensión en el diagnóstico, recidivas, etc. Los padres confían en la profesionalidad de los médicos y desean que tengan, además de una buena competencia profesional, cualidades humanas. La elaboración de los informes por los médicos es la tarea más criticada por los padres (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;33(3): 277-285, sept.-dic. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88844</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relaciones padres-médicos en oncología: un enfoque cualitativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14746</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8662^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8662^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8662^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8662^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8662^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
