<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74688</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal outcomes depending on the doses of betamethasone administered in pregnant women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To evaluate perinatal outcomes between different doses of antenatal corticosteroids.Subjects and methods: Retrospective study of 61single pregnancies at risk of premature birth, withn o other associated pathology and with at least one standard dose of intramuscular betamethasone (two doses of 12 mg/24h). There were two study groups: Group 1: standard dose, and Group 2: one or more additional weekly doses of 12 mg. Maternal variables: gestational weeks at the beginning of steroid treatment, weeks at delivery, type of birth, puerperal pathology; neonatal variables: sex, Apgar score, weight, height and cephalic perimeter at birth, and neonatal pathology. We performed a descriptive and comparative study on both groups. Results: No statistically significant differences were found between the groups. However, there were more cases of bronchopulmonary dysplasia (P=.09) in group 1.Conclusions: Repeated weekly doses of corticosteroids do not improve perinatal outcomes and are not associated with adverse effects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lucio González, Laura Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campuzano Martín, Samuel Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Caamaño, María Pía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero Gomis, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Vega, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar los resultados perinatales entre diferentes dosis de corticoides antenatales. Sujetos y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de61 gestaciones únicas con amenaza de parto prematuro, sin otra patología asociada, y con al menos una dosis estándar de betametasona por vía intramuscular (2 dosis de 12 mg/24 h). Dos grupos de estudio: grupo 1: dosis estándar, y grupo 2: una o más dosis adicionales semanales de 12 mg de betametasona. Variables maternas: semanas de gestación al inicio del tratamiento corticoideo, semanas al parto, tipo de parto, patología puerperal, entre otras; variables neonatales: sexo, índice de Apgar, peso, talla, perímetro cefálico y patología neonatal. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo y comparativo de ambos grupos. Resultados: No hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en los grupos. Sin embargo, se registraron más casos de displasia broncopulmonar(p = 0,09) en el grupo 1.Conclusiones: La repetición semanal de las dosis de corticoides no mejora los resultados perinatales ni asocia efectos adversos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);52(11): 627-633, nov. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74688</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados perinatales en función de la dosis de betametasona administrada en gestantes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2024^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22355^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
