<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82506</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychopathology, characteristics of violence and dropout in male batterers treatment programs: results of an intervention service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper deals with male violence toward female partners and the analysis of some variables related to this aggressive behavior. We study the type of violence perpetrated and some indicators of psychopathology, such as personality disorders, previous psychiatric or psychological care, substance abuse and jealous behavior, among others. In addition, we examine the relationship between these variables and the fact that the men do not complete the treatment program. For this purpose, we employed a sample of 118 men who voluntarily participated in an intervention service, and we carried out an ex post facto analysis. With regard to possible relations of dependence or independence among the variables considered, the results show dependence between the possibility of dropping out of the treatment and the presence of psychological or psychiatric history, and patterns of alcohol consumption and consumption of other drugs. In contrast, the existence of personality disorders, jealous behavior, type of violence used, onset or duration of violent behavior are independent of the possibility of dropping out of the treatment program(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jodrá Esteban, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boira Sarto, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo trata sobre la violencia masculina dentro de la pareja y analiza algunas variables relacionadas con este comportamiento agresivo. Se estudia el tipo de violencia ejercida y algunos indicadores de psicopatología, como los trastornos de personalidad, la atención psiquiátrica o psicológica previa, el abuso de drogas y el comportamiento de celos, entre otros. Además, se examina la relación entre estas variables y el hecho de que los hombres no completen el programa de tratamiento. Para ello, se ha considerado una muestra de 118 hombres, que participaron voluntariamente en un dispositivo de intervención, y se ha realizado un análisis ex post facto. Con respecto a las posibles relaciones de dependencia o de independencia entre las variables consideradas, los resultados muestran una relación de dependencia entre la posibilidad de abandono del tratamiento y la existencia de historia psicológica o psiquiátrica, la pauta de consumo de alcohol y la pauta de consumo de otras drogas. Por el contrario, la existencia de trastornos de personalidad, el comportamiento de celos, el tipo de violencia empleada, el inicio de la conducta violenta y su duración son independientes de la posibilidad de abandonar el tratamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(4): 593-599, 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82506</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicopatología, características de la violencia y abandonos en programas para hombres violentos con la pareja: resultados en un dispositivo de intervención</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1907^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29106^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3224^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
