<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158467</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Geographical distribution of mortality by Parkinson&#146;s disease and its association with air lead levels in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative disease, and the etiology of its sporadic form is unknown. The present study analyzes the temporal and spatial variations of mortality by PD in Spain over a period of 14 years and its relationship with lead concentration levels in the atmosphere. Method: An ecological study was performed, in which deaths by PD and age group in 50 Spanish provinces between 2000 and 2013 were analyzed. The annual trend of PD mortality was assessed using the nonparametric Spearman&#146;s Rho test. Finally, the relationship between lead concentration levels in the air and mortality by PD was evaluated. Results: Between 2000 and 2013, 36,180 patients with PD died in Spain. There is an increasing trend in mortality through PD over the study period (P &lt; 0,0001). La Rioja, Asturias, Basque Country and the Lower Ebro valley were the regions with the highest values of PD mortality. Those regions with the highest lead concentrations also showed higher mortality by this disease in people over 64 (P = .02). Conclusions: Over our period of study, there has been an increase in mortality through PD in Spain, with the northernmost half of the country registering the highest values. Mortality in men was higher than mortality in women. Moreover, a direct correlation was found between lead levels in the air and mortality through PD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado-Alvarado, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santurtún, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riancho, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos y objetivo: La enfermedad de Parkinson (EP) es la segunda dolencia neurodegenerativa más frecuente y su etiología en las formas esporádicas es desconocida. El presente estudio analiza las variaciones temporales y geográficas en la mortalidad por EP en España a lo largo de los últimos 14 años, y la relación entre la mortalidad por EP y los niveles de plomo en las partículas del aire. Método: Se ha realizado un estudio ecológico en el que se han analizado las muertes por EP por grupos de edad, en las 50 provincias españolas entre 2000 y 2013. La tendencia anual de la mortalidad por EP se calculó mediante el test no paramétrico Rho de Spearman. Finalmente, se analizó la asociación entre los niveles de plomo y la mortalidad por EP. Resultados: Entre 2000 y 2013 fallecieron en España 36.180 pacientes con EP. Existe una tendencia ascendente en la mortalidad por EP a lo largo del período estudiado (p &lt; 0,0001). La Rioja, Asturias, el País Vasco y el valle del Bajo Ebro acumulan la mayor incidencia de mortalidad por EP. En las regiones con más plomo, la tasa de mortalidad por EP en mayores de 64 años es superior (p = 0,02). Conclusiones: En la última década la mortalidad por EP ha aumentado en España, siendo la mitad norte del país la que registra una mayor incidencia. La mortalidad en varones fue mayor que en mujeres. Además, se encuentra una asociación entre los niveles de plomo en el aire y la tasa de mortalidad por EP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);147(11): 481-487, dic. 2016. mapas, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patrón geográfico de la mortalidad por enfermedad de Parkinson en España y su asociación con los niveles de plomo en el aire</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8033^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34353^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d400^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32400^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37724^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
