<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74730</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analgesic efficacy of the association of duloxetine plus pregabalin in neuropathic pain: experience in 60 patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The efficacy of duloxetine and pregabalin has been demonstrated separately and both drugs are approved by the Food and Drug Administration for the treatment of specific types of neuropathic pain. Our objective was to determine whether the association of both drugs improves their analgesic effectiveness and the effect of this association on patients&#146; quality of life. Material and methods: We studied 60 patients with severe neuropathic pain (visual analog scale [VAS] &gt; 6) over a 3-month period. The patients were randomized to three groups (n = 20): group A (duloxetine 30 mg/24 h the first 3 days followed by 60 mg/24 hat breakfast, with progressive increases of 30 mg every 3 days until pain relief was achieved). Group B (pregabalin 75 mg/night for the first 3 days, with increases of 75 mg every 3 days until pain relief was achieved. Group C (A+B). The variables studied were age, sex, diagnosis, VAS; stabbing pain, dull pain and allodynia (VAS); the dose required for pain relief &gt; 50%, and subjective feeling of overall symptom improvement in patients and their sleep quality (0-3: 0 = none; 1 = mild; 2 = moderate; 3 = excellent). Patients were evaluated weekly in the first month, every 15 days in the second month and then once a month. Results: No significant differences were found in age or diagnosis among the three groups. The most common diagnoses were cervical and lumbar radiculopathy (68%), fibrosis after lumbar disc surgery (17%), lumbar canal stenosis (12%) and postherpetic neuralgia (8%).There were more women, except in group A, with equal distribution of men and women (50% F/M). Pain relief &gt; 50% was achieved with 96.2 ± 24.1 mg of duloxetine in 60% of patients in group A, 532 ± 63mg of pregabalin in 68% of patients in group B, and 298.5 ±56 mg of pregabalin plus 65.2 ± 31.1 mg of duloxetine in 73% of patients in group C (p &gt;0.05)...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castro Bande, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Gutiérrez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segado Jiménez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peralta Espinosa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Gutiérrez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cánovas Martínez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Duloxetina y pregabalina han demostrado su eficacia por separado, y cuentan con la aprobación de la Food and Drug Administration para el tratamiento de determinados tipos de dolor neuropático. Nuestro objetivo fue valorar si la asociación de ambos puede mejorar su eficacia analgésica y el impacto de esta asociación en la calidad de vida del paciente. Material y métodos: Se estudiaron 60 pacientes con dolor neuropático severo (escala visual analógica [EVA] &gt; 6) durante un período de 3 meses. Se distribuyeron aleatoriamente en 3 grupos (n = 20): grupo A (duloxetina 30 mg/24 h los primeros 3 días y luego 60 mg/24 h en medio del desayuno, con incrementos progresivos de 30 mg/3 días hasta alivio del dolor); grupo B (pregabalina 75 mg/noche los primeros 3 días, con incrementos de 75 mg/3 días hasta alivio del dolor; pautado/12 h), y grupo C (A + B). Las variables estudiadas fueron: edad; sexo; diagnóstico; EVA; componente lancinante, sordo y alodinia (EVA); dosis necesaria para alivio del dolor &gt; 50%; impresión clínica de mejoría del paciente y del sueño (0-3; 0: nula, 1: leve, 2: moderada y 3: importante), y efectos indeseables. Los pacientes fueron evaluados semanalmente el primer mes, cada 15 días el segundo mes y luego mensualmente. Resultados: No se encontraron diferencias significativas en edad y diagnóstico según el grupo, siendo los diagnósticos más frecuentes: radiculopatía cervical y lumbar (68%), fibrosisposcirugía (17%), estenosis de canal (12%) y neuralgia postherpética (8%). Hubo un predominio del sexo femenino, excepto en el grupo A, con una distribución similar (50% F/M). La reducción del dolor &gt; 50% se produjo con: 96,2 ± 24,1 mg de duloxetina en el 60% de los pacientes del grupo A; 532 ± 63 mg de pregabalina en el 68% de los pacientes del B, y 298,5± 56 mg de pregabalina + 65,2 ± 31,1 mg de duloxetina en el 73% de los pacientes del C (p&lt; 0,05)...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;16(7): 381-385, oct. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74730</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia analgésica de la asociación duloxetina más pregabalina en el dolor neuropático: experiencia en 60 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
