<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97063</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bullying</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Bullying or peer violence causes much suffering. Although traditionally the relationship between bully-bullied is the most emphasized in literature, there are more players. Because of the distress caused to the victim, the reinforcement received by the stalker whose aggressive behavior goes unpunished, and the learned helplessness of spectators, it must be tackled as a group and social problem. Prevention is the best cure and we should work as a team in schools, including students, families and in some cases the pediatrician (as a promoter of physical and mental health in childhood)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Armero Pedreira, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernardino Cuesta, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonet de Luna, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El bullying, acoso escolar o violencia entre iguales, produce mucho sufrimiento en quienes lo padecen. Aunque tradicionalmente se suele enfatizar la relación acosador-acosado, hay más actores. Tanto por la angustia que causa a la víctima, por el refuerzo que recibe el acosador cuyas conductas agresivas quedan impunes, como por la insensibilización o indefensión aprendida de los espectadores, debe ser abordado como un problema grupal y social. El mejor tratamiento es la prevención y se debe trabajar desde el colegio, incluyendo a los alumnos, las familias y en algunos casos al pediatra (en cuanto promotor de la salud física y mental en la infancia)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;13(52): 661-670, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acoso escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2716^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2716^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2716^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13700^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19101^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
