<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051379</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-811X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prenatal diagnosis and multicolor spectral kariotyping characterization of the extra structurally abnormal chromosomes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Extra structurally abnormal chromosomes (ESACs) are small supernumerary chromosomes often associated with developmental abnormalities. We have revised 9,987 prenatal cytogenetic studies of amniotic fluid cells finding 3 cases with the presence of ESACs. Each of these chromosomes was analyzed with various staining techniques in orden to determine its structure, and with molecular cytogenetics techniques such FISH (fluorescence in situ hibridization) and SKY (multicolor spectral kariotyping). In two cases we could determine the presence of ESACs in other normal members of the families. In the third case a de novo ESAC was detected, and the chromosomal origin could be identified by SKY: 47,XX,+der(22)(q12-qter). The introduction of molecular cytogenetics techniques such SKY has a great impact on the correct diagnosis and we offered the genetic counseling according with the need of the patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cigudosa García, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rancel Torres, M. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correa Rancel, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero Gómez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Miranda, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Troyano Luque, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bajo Arenas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mercé Alberto, L. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfonso Hernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cromosomas extra estructuralmente anormales (ESAC) son pequeños cromosomas supernumerarios asociados con cierta frecuencia con el desarrollo de anormalidades. Hemos revisado 9.987 estudios citogenéticos prenatales de células de líquido amniótico, encontrando tres casos con presencia de ESAC. Cada uno de estos cromosomas fueron analizados con varias técnicas con el fin de determinar su estructura, y con las técnicas citogenéticas moleculares como el FISH (hibridización in situ por fluorescencia) y SKY (cariotipo espectral multicolor). En dos casos pudimos determinar la presencia de ESAC en otros miembros normales de la familia. Un tercer caso de ESAC de novo fue detectado, y el origen cromosómico pudo ser determinado por SKY: 47,xx,+der(22) (q12-qter). La introducción de las técnicas de citogenética molecular como el SKY tiene un importante impacto en el correcto diagnóstico y en el consejo genético de acuerdo con la necesidad del paciente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. diagn. trat. prenat. (Ed. impr.);18(2): 54-57, abr.-jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico prenatal y caracterización por SKY (cariotipo espectral multicolor) de cromosomas extra estructuralmente anormales (ESAC)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5950^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2918</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37590^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d668</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34542^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
