<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78319</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analgesic efficacy of oral transmucosal fentanyl citrate in rectal breakthrough pain in oncologic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Breakthrough pain is a little-known entity that is infrequently diagnosed and consequently inadequately evaluated and treated. In particular, cancer patients can experience rectal defecation breakthrough pain due to the tumor, the side effects of treatment (surgery, radiotherapy and/or chemotherapy) or both. Recently, a new system of administration has been developed, oral transmucosal fentanyl citrate (OTFC; Actiq®), which is a highly efficient method for rapid onset of analgesia. The aim of this study was to evaluate the efficiency of OTFC as an analgesic for a highly specific subgroup of cancer patients. Patients and methods: We retrospectively reviewed 10 cancer patients treated with OTFC for rectal defecation breakthrough pain not previously treated with opioids between January 2006 and July 2009 in our Radiotherapy Service. Patients reporting rectal pain in consultations were evaluated by a Visual Analog Scale (VAS) (0-10). Results: The mean breakthrough pain VAS score was reduced from 7 (range 5-9) before OTFC to 1.9 (range 1-3) after the treatment. All patients reported pain control with a dose of 200 &amp;#956;g of OTFC except two patients who required progressive doses of 400 and600 &amp;#956;g, respectively. The degree of patient satisfaction was excellent-good in 90% of the patients. No patients reported undesirable effects related to the use of OTFC. Conclusions: Although our series is small and our results are therefore preliminary, we can recommend OTFC as the ideal analgesic due to its speed of onset and safety in the treatment of rectal defecation breakthrough pain. OTFC is easy and comfortable to administer and is short lasting. This option can be used by patients outside the home, thus preserving their independence. OTFC can be considered for the relief of breakthrough pain of other etiologies (oncological and non-oncological) in outpatients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zurita, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tovar, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El dolor irruptivo es una necesidad clínica desconocida que todavía se diagnostica poco y, por lo tanto, se evalúa y se trata de modo inadecuado. Concretamente, en los pacientes oncológicos se puede presentar un dolor rectal irruptivo defecatorio debido al tumor, los efectos secundarios de los tratamientos administrados (cirugía, radioterapia y/o quimioterapia) o ambos. Recientemente, ha aparecido un sistema de administración transmucosa oral, citrato de fentanilo oral transmucosa (CFOT) (Actiq®) como método de alta eficacia para un inicio rápido de la analgesia. El objetivo de este trabajo es valorarla eficacia de CFOT como analgésico en este subgrupo tan específico de pacientes oncológicos. Pacientes y métodos: Entre enero de 2006 y julio de 2009 hemos revisado retrospectivamente un total de 10 pacientes tratados en nuestro servicio con CFOT por dolor rectal irruptivo defecatorio no premedicados con opiáceos. Cuando los pacientes referían en consulta dolor rectal se les valoraba con una escala visual analógica (EVA) (0-10). Resultados: La puntuación media premedicación con CFOT de dolor irruptivo defecatorio con la EVA fue de 7 (rango: 5-9). La puntuación media tras el tratamiento pasó a ser 1,9 (rango: 1-3). Todos refirieron controlar el dolor con dosis de 200 &amp;#956;g de CFOT, salvo 2 pacientes que precisaron dosis progresivas de 400 y 600 &amp;#956;g, respectivamente. El grado de satisfacción de los pacientes fue excelente-bueno en el 90% de los casos. Ningún paciente refirió efectos indeseables relacionados con el uso de CFOT. Conclusiones: Aunque nuestra serie es corta y, por lo tanto, sus resultados son muy preliminares, podemos recomendar el CFOT como analgésico ideal por su rapidez y seguridad para el tratamiento del dolor rectal irruptivo defecatorio. Es de fácil y cómoda administración, y de corta duración..(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;17(1): 16-21, ene.-feb. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78319</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia analgésica del citrato de fentanilo oral transmucosa en el dolor rectal irruptivo de pacientes oncológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d772^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d772^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28037^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
