<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159045</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The informal economy: an occupational health issue</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Informal economy must be differentiated from concepts such as informal employment and the informal sector, each with its own characteristics. There are several types of informal workers that are grouped into several categories according to their work. The families of these workers are grouped into vulnerable job, which is also not beneficial for health coverage. Informal working conditions mean great morbidity resulting in economic losses and a large number of quality-adjusted life year, especially among young populations and women. Health policies are needed to reduce socio-economic inequalities, improve the training of health professionals and the accessibility of health services to these workers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Begoña Cueva Oliver, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asunción Vidal Martínez, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rigo Martínez, María Vicenta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lobato Cañón, José Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>José Luis Carretero Ares, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La economía informal se debe diferenciar de conceptos tales como empleo informal y sector informal, cada uno con sus propias características. Existen varios tipos de trabajadores informales que se agrupan en varias categorías según su labor. Los familiares de estos trabajadores se agrupan dentro del empleo vulnerable, que no se benefician tampoco de coberturas sanitarias. El empleo informal condiciona una gran morbimortalidad que se traduce en pérdidas económicas y gran número de años de vida perdidos por discapacidad, especialmente entre poblaciones jóvenes y mujeres. Son necesarias políticas sanitarias encaminadas a disminuir las desigualdades socioeconómicas, mejorando la capacitación de profesionales sanitarios y la accesibilidad a los servicios sanitarios de estos trabajadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);20(1): 30-32, ene.-mar. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159045</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Economía informal, un problema de salud laboral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12831^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12831^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
