<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97001</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">GESITRA-SEIMC/REIPI recommendations for the management of cytomegalovirus infection in solid-organ transplant patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract Cytomegalovirus infection remains a major complication of solid organ transplantation. In 2005 the Spanish Transplantation Infection Study Group (GESITRA) of the Spanish Society of Infectious Diseases and Clinical Microbiology (SEIMC) developed consensus guidelines for the prevention and treatment of CMV infection in solid organ transplant recipients. Since then, numerous publications have clarified or questioned the aspects covered in the previous document. These aspects include the situations and populations who must receive prophylaxis and its duration, the selection of the best diagnosis and monitoring technique and the best therapeutic strategy. For these reasons, we have developed new consensus guidelines to include the latest recommendations on post-transplant CMV management based on new evidence available (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fortún, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lumbreras, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez-Bernot, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Vernet, Salvador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varo, Evaristo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Len, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rumbao, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castón, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zurbano, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pahissa, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo-Leiro, Maria G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frauca, Esteban</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fariñas, M. Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavaldá, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre-Cisneros, Julian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monforte, Victor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gurguí, Mercé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carratalá, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantisán, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordero, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Juan, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montejo, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervera, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín-Dávila, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La infección por citomegalovirus (CMV) constituye una complicación importante en los pacientes sometidos a trasplante de órgano sólido (TOS). En el año 2005 el Grupo de Estudio de Infección en el Trasplante (GESITRA) de la Sociedad Española de Microbiología Clínica y Enfermedades Infecciosas (SEIMC) elaboró un documento de consenso para la profilaxis y el tratamiento de la infección por CMV en pacientes sometidos a TOS. Desde entonces han sido numerosas las publicaciones que o bien han aclarado, o bien han planteado nuevas dudas respecto a los aspectos tratados en el anterior documento. Entre estos aspectos se encuentran las situaciones y poblaciones que deben recibir profilaxis y su duración, la elección de la mejor técnica para el diagnóstico y monitorización y la elección de la mejor estrategia terapéutica. Todo ello justifica la necesidad de elaborar un nuevo documento de consenso que incluya las últimas recomendaciones en el manejo de la infección por CMV post-trasplante en base a las nuevas evidencias disponibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;29(10): 735-758, dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97001</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones GESITRA-SEIMC/REIPI para el manejo de la infección por citomegalovirus en pacientes trasplantados de órgano sólido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3605^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31818^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
