<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95084</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relevance of psychosocial intervention in breast cancer patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cancer diagnosis and disease progression induce high levels of stress than in some people go along with depression and anxiety. Objectives: To analyze the incidence of psychological alterations in breast cancer patients and possible modifications by a cognitive-behavioral treatment, that included relaxation and guided-imagery as well as stress management. Methods: Depression, anxiety and alexithymia were diagnosed by the use of Beck2 Depression Inventory, Spielberger´State/Trait Anxie3ty Inventory and Toronto Alexithymia Scale in 26 breast cancer patients and 18 controls without cancer with mean age 48 ± 11 years. Eight patients attended for 5 days to a psychosocial intervention program. Depression, anxiety, alexithymia and perceived physical well-being were measured before and one week after program attendance. Results: Higher frequency of depression, state and trait anxiety was detected in patients in opposition to controls who showed higher frequency of alexithymia. Patients showed increased severity of depression and alexithymia. Furthermore, a higher percentage of patients showed simultaneous expression of depression and state/trait anxiety. Lower levels of state anxiety levels (p&lt;0.02) and trait anxiety were detected after support program attendance. Patients with previous depression diagnosis did not showed depression indicators after intervention. Conclusion: Breast cancer patients showed higher incidence of psychological alterations than persons without cancer. Psychological Interventions can increase the quality of life in breast cancer patients by de3creasing the anxiety and depression they present (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mendoza, Andreína</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna, Gissell</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pocino, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canelones, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palacios, Luis E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castés, Marianela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico de cáncer y su progresión, genera altos niveles de estrés que se acompañan en algunos casos con alteraciones psicológicas. Objetivos: Analizar la incidencia de alteraciones psicológicas en pacientes con cáncer de mama y su posible modificación mediante un tratamiento cognitivo-conductual, que aplica relajación, imaginación guiada y otras técnicas de control de estrés. Método: Se evaluó la presencia de depresión, ansiedad y alexitimia mediante el Inventario de Depresión de Beck, el Inventario de Ansiedad Estado/Rasgo de Spielberger y la Escala de Alexitimia de Toronto, en 26 pacientes con cáncer de mama y 18 controles sin cáncer, con edad promedio de 48 ±11 años. Ocho pacientes participaron durante 5 días en un programa de intervención psicosocial y se midió depresión, ansiedad, alexitimia y bienestar físico percibido, antes y una semana después de participar en el programa. Resultados: Las pacientes presentaron mayor frecuencia de depresión, ansiedad estado y rasgo; las mujeres del grupo control presentaron mayor frecuencia de alexitimia. Se observó mayor severidad de depresión y alexitimia en las pacientes. UN mayor porcentaje de pacientes presentó simultáneamente depresión y ansiedad estado/rasgo. La participación en el programa de apoyo psicosocial determinó disminución en los niveles de ansiedad estado (p&lt;0.02) y ansiedad rasgo. Pacientes con diagnóstico previo de depresión no presentaron indicadores de la misma después de la intervención. Conclusiones: Las pacientes con cáncer de mama presentan más alteraciones psicológicas que las personas sin cáncer. La intervención psicosocial puede mejorar la calidad de vida del paciente con cáncer de mama al disminuir la ansiedad y la depresión que frecuentemente acompañan a la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);4(1): 59-73, jun. 2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95084</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La relevancia de la intervención psicosocial en pacientes con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
