<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82193</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence in adults of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder using the medical records of primary care</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background:ADHD in adults is not uncommon and, according to recent epidemiological data, has a population prevalence of 3-4%. However, there is major unawareness of this disorder among doctors, particularly in primary care. The aim of this study is to determine the prevalence of the diagnosis of ADHD recorded in adults and the proportion of patients with drug prescriptions for this disorder in primary care. Methods:This is a cross-sectional study on databases of computerised primary care medical records. The target population is adults (18-44 years) assigned to primary care centres of the Catalan Health Institute (n = 2,452,107). We obtained the proportion of patients with ADHD (F90/ICD-10 code) registered as active problem, and the proportion of patients with a specific prescription for ADHD in adults: methylphenidate, methylphenidate extended release or atomoxetine. Results:The prevalence of recorded ADHD is 0.04% (0.07% in men, 0.02% in women). The percentage of patients with a specific prescription for ADHD is 0.07% (0.08% in men, 0.05% in women). 32.05% of ADHD patients had specific prescription. Conclusion:The diagnosis of ADHD in adults and specific treatment are extremely low in primary care. These results contrast with population data: registered ADHD is 1/85 of the population prevalence(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Cortacans, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragonès, Enric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñol, Josep Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Quiroga, Josep Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento:El TDAH en adultos no es infrecuente y, según datos epidemiológicos recientes, tiene una prevalencia poblacional del 3-4%. Sin embargo, existe un gran desconocimiento sobre este trastorno entre los médicos, particularmente en atención primaria. El objetivo de este trabajo es determinar la prevalencia del diagnóstico registrado de TDAH en adultos y la proporción de pacientes con prescripción farmacológica para este trastorno en atención primaria. Métodos:Se trata de un estudio transversal sobre las bases de datos de las historias clínicas electrónicas de atención primaria. La población diana son los adultos (18-44 años) adscritos a centros de salud del Instituto Catalán de la Salud (n=2.452.107). Hemos obtenido la proporción de pacientes con diagnóstico de TDAH (código F90/CIE-10) en la lista de problemas activos, y la proporción de pacientes con prescripción activa de un fármaco específico para el TDAH en adultos: metilfenidato, metilfenidato de liberación prolongada o atomoxetina. Resultados:La prevalencia de TDAH registrado es del 0,04% (0,07% en hombres; 0,02% en mujeres). Los pacientes con prescripción para TDAH son el 0,07% (0,08% en hombres; 0,05% en mujeres). El 32,05% de los TDAH tenían prescripción específica. Conclusión:El diagnóstico en adultos de TDAH y el tratamiento específico son extremadamente bajos en atención primaria. Estos resultados contrastan con los datos poblacionales: el TDAH registrado es 1/85 de la prevalencia poblacional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;84(4): 415-420, jul.-ago.2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia del déficit de atención e hiperactividad en personas adultas según el registro de las historias clínicas informatizadas de atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29040^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29040^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29040^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29040^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
