<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76954</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">In utero intracranial hemorrhage caused by neonatal alloimmune thrombocytopenia (NAIT). Report of two cases and literature update</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The neonatal alloimmune thrombocytopenia (NAIT) is the commonest cause of early isolated severe thrombocytopenia in the healthy newborn. It&#146;s the result of maternal alloimmunization against fetal platelet antigens. However, the pathophysiologic mechanism is not well known yet. Alloantibodies cross the placenta in early stages of pregnancy provoking serious complications in the newborn such as intracranial hemorrhage. Case report: We present two cases of in utero intracranial hemorrhage caused by TNAI. In one of them a large intraparenchymal hemorrhage (IPH) was the first clinical symptom, how everhe recovered platelet count with just one transfusion of an aleatory donor, not needing further treatment. The second one exhibited at first an intraventricular hemorrhage (IVH) and was treated with serial transfusions of HPA-1a negative platelets and intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG).Discussion and conclusions: The NAIT appears commonly as an isolated and severe thrombocytopenia in the newborn period. The diagnosis is made after excluding other causes of neonatal thrombocytopenia, and is confirmed proving the presence of maternal antiplatelet alloantibodies. Due to the severity of its consequences, when confronted with the suspicion of TNAI, a platelet transfusion should to be performed immediately preferably with negative antigen platelets to avoid bleeding. Since there is a high risk of recurrence in following gestations the availability of an established protocol is recommended. The future challenge is the establishment of antenatal screening programs similar to that performed in Rh isoimmunization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Argiles Aparicio, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ledo García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maraguat Idarraga, U</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saénz González, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vento Torres, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peinador García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cubells García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dasí Carpio, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La trombopenia neonatal aloinmune (TNAI) es la causa más frecuente de trombopenia grave, aislada y precoz en el recién nacido sano. Es el resultado de la aloinmunización materna frente a antígenos plaquetarios humanos (HPA) del feto. El mecanismo fisiopatológico todavía es poco conocido. El paso de anticuerpos se produce en etapas tempranas de la gestación con consecuencias graves, como la hemorragia intracraneal. Casos clínicos: Se presentan dos casos de hemorragia intracraneal intraútero secundarios a TNAI. El primero de ellos seinicia con una gran hemorragia intraparenquimatosa, y requiere una única transfusión de donante aleatorio para remontar la cifra de plaquetas. El segundo se presenta con una hemorragia intraventricular y se trata con transfusiones seriadas de plaquetasHPA-1a negativas e inmunoglobulina intravenosa. Discusión y conclusiones: La TNAI se presenta generalmente como una trombopenia aislada y grave en el recién nacido. Eldiagnóstico es de exclusión y se confirma mediante la detección de anticuerpos antiplaquetarios en la madre. Dada la gravedad de las consecuencias, ante la sospecha de TNAI, deben realizarse de inmediato transfusiones de plaquetas, preferentemente de las compatibles, para evitar hemorragias. El riesgo de recurrencia en futuras gestaciones es muy elevado, por lo que se debe establecer un protocolo de manejo de éstas. El reto de futuro es el establecimiento de un cribado antenatal, como ya se hace con la isoinmunización Rh (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;67(7): 325-329, jul. 2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76954</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemorragia intracraneal intraútero por trombopenia neonatal aloinmune: a propósito de dos casos y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52623^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34262^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52623^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52623^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52623^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34262^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34262^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31176</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
