<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62221</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Few investigations have focused their attentionon the study of neuropsychological deterioration associated tohuman inmunodeficiency virus (HIV) and hepatitis C virus (HCV)coinfection. This study has aimed to evaluate neuropsychologicalperformance and neuropsychological impairment rates in HIVand HCV positive patients (HIV+/HCV+) of Spanish nationality ofthe region of Galicia.Method. Three groups of 122 subjects underwent neuropsychologicalevaluation: 55 HIV+, 29 HIV/HCV+ and 34 seronegativeto both HIV/HCV. All subjects gave their written informedconsent and underwent the same evaluation process.Results. HIV+ and HIV/HCV+ patients showed significantlylower levels of neuropsychological performance in all neuropsychologicaldomains evaluated in comparison with the controlgroup. Nevertheless, only visual memory showed significantlydifferences between both groups. The rate of neuropsychologicalimpairment of HIV+/HCV+ patients (62%) was significantly greaterthan that of HIV+ (38%).Conclusions. HIV and HIV/HCV infection are related to low levelsof neuropsychological performance, HIV/HCV patients showinglower performance in visual memory tasks. HIV/HCV coinfectionrepresents a neuropsychological impairment risk factor in HIV patients,because it influences the probability of having neuropsychologicalimpairment. However, this may not only be related withHCV, but also with being in methadone-maintenance programs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Failde Garrido, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simón López, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Castro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Álvarez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Pocas investigaciones han centrado su atenciónen el estudio del deterioro neuropsicológico asociado a la coinfecciónpor los virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) y de la hepatitisC (VHC). El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar el rendimientoneuropsicológico y las tasas de deterioro neuropsicológico en pacientesgallegos seropositivos coinfectados por VIH/VHC.Método. Se realizó una evaluación neuropsicológica a tres gruposde 122 sujetos, 59 infectados por VIH, 29 coinfectados porVIH/VHC y 34 seronegativos a ambos virus. Todos los sujetos dieronel consentimiento informado y fueron sometidos al mismo procesode evaluación.Resultados. Los pacientes monoinfectados por VIH y los coinfectadospor VIH/VHC mostraron niveles significativamente más bajosde rendimiento neuropsicológico que el grupo control en todaslas funciones estudiadas, apreciándose diferencias significativas entreel grupo de monoinfectados y coinfectados únicamente en elfactor que evalúa la memoria visual. En cuanto a las tasas de deterioroneuropsicológico, éstas fueron significativamente más elevadasen el grupo de pacientes coinfectados (62%) frente al de monoinfectados(38%).Conclusiones. La infección por VIH y la coinfección por VIH yVHC se asocia a niveles de rendimiento bajos, mostrando los pacientescoinfectados un rendimiento más bajo en tareas de memoria visual.La coinfección por VIH/VHC representa un factor de riesgo dedaño neuropsicológico en sujetos seropositivos al VIH, ya que influyede forma significativa en la probabilidad que tienen éstos de presentardeterioro neuropsicológico, si bien ésta pudiera estar relacionadano sólo con el VHC, sino también con la permanencia en programasde mantenimiento con metadona (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;24(3): 154-159, abr. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rendimiento neuropsicológicoen pacientes coinfectadospor virus de la inmunodeficienciahumana (VIH) y de la hepatitis C (VHC)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30351</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
