<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149548</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of the cardiovascular predictive value of MDRD and CKD-EPI in estimating chronic kidney disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To assess predictive value of the cardiovascular prognosis by comparing the two most used formulas for the estimation of glomerular filtration rate in hypertensive patients. Material and methods. A retrospective cohort study was designed that included 405 patients diagnosed with essential hypertension. The patients were referred from Primary Care to the Hypertension and Vascular Risk Unit between January 1, 1998 and August 31, 1999. Blood pressure measurements, blood and urine analysis, and echocardiography were simultaneously performed. They were followed up for 12.5 years (mean [± IQR]: 10.61 [± 3.11] years) and 174 events were recorded. Results. The study included 405 patients (53.8% women), with a mean age of 55.5 years. The estimated glomerular filtration rate according to the MDRD and CKD-EPI equations was 73.9 ± 2.6 mL/min/1.73 m2 and 76.9 ± 2.2 mL/min/1.73 m2, respectively. The prevalence of chronic kidney disease was 31.6% and 23.9%, respectively. Using the CKD-EPI equation led to the re-classification of 22.9% of patients. The incidence rate ratio (IRR [95% CI] for chronic kidney disease identified by the MDRD equation was 2.4 [1.8-3.3], and for the CKD-EPI calculation it was 2.5 [1.8 to 3.3]). Conclusions. Both equations estimate similar magnitudes of renal function, although the CKD-EPI equation has less false positives, and both have similar prognostic values in patients at high cardiovascular risk as well those at low risk (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Paz, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermida-Ameijeiras, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Gómez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cinza-Sanjurjo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Juanatey, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Comparar el valor predictivo, en el pronóstico cardiovascular, de las fórmulas más empleadas para la estimación del filtrado glomerular en pacientes hipertensos. Material y métodos. Se diseñó un estudio de cohortes retrospectivo, que incluyó los 405 pacientes diagnosticados de HTA esencial que fueron remitidos a la Unidad de Hipertensión y Riesgo Vascular, desde atención primaria, entre el 1 de enero de 1998 y el 31 de agosto de 1999 y a los que se les realizó simultáneamente un estudio de MAPA, análisis de sangre y orina y ecocardiográfico. Se realizó el seguimiento a lo largo de 12,5 años (mediana [± RiQ]: 10,61 [± 3,11] años) y se registraron 174 eventos. Resultados. Se incluyeron 405 pacientes (53,8% mujeres), con una edad media de 55,5 años. El filtrado glomerular estimado según las fórmulas MDRD y CKD-EPI fue de 73,9 ± 2,6 ml/min/1,73 m2 y 76,9 ± 2,2 ml/min/1,73 m2, respectivamente. La prevalencia de enfermedad renal crónica fue del 31,6 y del 23,9%, respectivamente. El uso de la ecuación CKD-EPI obligó a reclasificar al 22,9% de los pacientes. La RTI [IC 95%] para la enfermedad renal crónica identificada por la ecuación MDRD fue de 2,4 [1,8-3,3], y para el cálculo con CKD-EPI fue de 2,5 [1,8-3,3]). Conclusiones. Ambas fórmulas estiman magnitudes semejantes de función renal, aunque la ecuación CKD-EPI evita algunos falsos positivos, y ambas tienen similar valor pronóstico en pacientes tanto de alto como bajo riesgo cardiovascular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);42(1): 11-18, ene.-feb. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149548</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación del valor predictivo cardiovascular de MDRD y CKD-EPI en la estimación de la enfermedad renal crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32137^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
