<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-27951</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of psychoactive drugs in patients attending GPs' surgeries in the Principality of Asturias (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study we analyze the use of psychoactive drugs in patients attending GPs&#146; surgeries in the Principality of Asturias, as well as the variables related to the use of these substances. The sample was made up of 602 people selected by means of cluster sampling in two stages. The results indicate that 37.9% of patients consume psychoactive drugs. Use of such drugs is significantly greater in women, in housewives, in unemployed and in people with low educational level. Anxiety disorders, sleep disorders and depressive symptoms are the most common reasons for their use. Criteria of dependence on these types of substances were fulfilled in 28% of the sample. These results indicate very high rates of consumption, and suggest the need to implement strategies for reducing the use of psychoactive drugs in this population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez García, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Hermida, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Secades Villa, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez García, Elías</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valderrey Barbero, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo Seco, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analiza el consumo de psicofármacos en los pacientes que acuden a los centros de Atención Primaria del Principado de Asturias, así como las variables relacionadas con el uso de estas sustancias. La muestra se compuso de 602 personas seleccionadas mediante un muestreo por conglomerados en dos etapas. Los resultados señalan que el 37,9 por ciento de los pacientes consume psicofármacos. El consumo de estos medicamentos es significativamente superior en las mujeres, en las amas de casa, en los desempleados y en las personas con bajo nivel educativo. Los trastornos de ansiedad, del sueño y los síntomas depresivos son los motivos más frecuentes. El 28 por ciento de la muestra cumplía los criterios de dependencia a este tipo de sustancias. Estos resultados indican unas tasas de consumo muy elevadas y sugieren la necesidad de la puesta en marcha dé estrategias que reduzcan el uso de psicofármacos en esta población (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(4): 650-655, nov. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-27951</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El consumo de psicofármacos en pacientes que acuden a Atencion Primaria en el Principado de Asturias (España)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12038^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14543^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12038^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200311</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
