<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73672</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inguinal ureteral hernia: a clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To describe a clinical case of ureteral inguinal hernia and to comment briefly about the topic.METHODS: 80 year-old patient with, hypertension, left inguinal hernia sugery, right hemicolectomy for colon adenocarcinoma and cholecystectomy. Intravenous urogram casually found that the right ureter was leaving the abdominal cavity though the right inguinal duct and then returned to the abdomen.RESULTS: CT scan confirmed the diagnosis. Due to the advanced age of the patient, comorbidities and the absence of symptoms, conservative treatment was decided.CONCLUSIONS: Ureteral hernias through the inguinal duct are uncommon. There are 2 types: paraperitoneal and extraperitoneal. The most common is the paraperitoneal (80%) which is accompanied by hernia sac and can appear with other abdominal organs. The extraperitoneal often accompanied by retroperitoneal fat. Both types of hernias are usually indirect. Treatment is usually herniorrhaphy(AU)  </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casas Nebra, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chantada Abal, Venancio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Reboledo, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez R. Losada, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponce Díaz-Reixa, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez Dacal, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarraonandia Andraca, Antón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Breijo, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Describir caso clínico de hernia ureteral inguinal y luego comentar brevemente tema.MÉTODOS: Paciente 80 años hipertenso con hernia inguinal izquierda operada, hemicolectomia derecha por adenocarcinoma de colon y colecistectomia. En urografía intravenosa como hallazgo se identifica uréter derecho en posición ectópica que sale de la cavidad abdominal por región inguinal derecha para luego volver al abdomen.RESULTADOS: Se realiza TAC que confirma diagnostico. Debido a la edad avanzada del paciente, comorbilidades y ausencia de síntomas, se decidió actitud expectante.                                               CONCLUSIONES: Las hernias urterales a través del conducto inguinal son poco frecuentes. Existen 2 tipos: paraperitoneal y extraperitoneal. La más frecuente es la paraperitoneal (80%) donde se acompaña de saco herniario y pueden aparecer otros órganos intra abdominales. La extraperitoneal suele acompañarse de grasa retroperitoneal. Ambos tipos de hernias suelen se indirectas. El tratamiento suele ser la herniorrafia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;62(9): 755-757, nov. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73672</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hernia ureteral inguinal: caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6711^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14916^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
