<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050405</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-3655</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessing the necessities in pharmaceutical care of immigrants in Campo de Gibraltar</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Some specific barriers impede the normal integration of the immigrant in the healthcare system, and those barriers are augmented in non legal immigrants. Pharmacists can contribute in improving immigrants&#146; healthcare and pharmaceutical care. Objective: To analyze pharmaceutical care received and drug accessibility of non-legal immigrants in the area of Campo de Gibraltar. Methods: We carried out personal interviews to immigrants. Questionnaires translated into three languages (Arabian English and French) we revalidated (translation retro-translation) and used. Two translators interviewed the immigrants in one of those languages, the one chosen by the interviewed patient. Results: Immigrants present negative clinical outcomes associated with their medication and economic difficulties to acquire their medicines. To improve pharmaceutical care they are receiving, they demand more information on their illnesses, the use of their medicines, and bigger accessibility to them. Conclusions: Immigrants were not worried about health care or pharmaceutical care, because they have other major worries produced by their legal status. Nevertheless, they constitute a group with higher risk of presenting negative clinical outcomes of medication. Medicines&#146; expenditure constitutes a barrier to the healthcare process, reduced by NGOs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Faus, Maria José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espejo, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Existen barreras específicas que condicionan la normal integración del colectivo inmigrante al sistema sanitario público y que están incrementadas en los inmigrantes en situación administrativa irregular. Los farmacéuticos pueden contribuir en la mejora de la atención sanitaria y farmacéutica de estos pacientes. Objetivo: Analizar la atención farmacéutica recibida y la accesibilidad a los medicamentos o prestación farmacéutica de los inmigrantes en situación administrativa irregular de la zona del Campo de Gibraltar. Método: Realizamos entrevistas estructuradas e individuales a inmigrantes personalmente. Se usaron cuestionarios en español o traducidos (a tres idiomas: árabe, inglés y francés), y validados (traducción y re-traducción). Dos traductores intérpretes realizaron las preguntas a los inmigrantes en una de las lenguas traducidas elegida por los entrevistados. Resultados: Los inmigrantes presentan resultados clínicos negativos de la medicación y dificultades económicas para adquirir los medicamentos. Para mejorar la atención farmacéutica que reciben demandan mayor información sobre enfermedades, el uso de los medicamentos y facilidades de acceso a los mismos. Conclusiones: Los inmigrantes no muestran preocupación por los problemas en la atención sanitaria o farmacéutica, por tener otras preocupaciones derivadas de su situación administrativa, sin embargo, constituyen un colectivo con mayor riesgo de presentar resultados clínicos negativos de la medicación . La aportación económica de los medicamentos constituye una barrera en el proceso de su asistencia sanitaria, subsanado por las ONG (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. pract. (Granada, Internet);4(1): 24-33, ene.-mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050405</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación de las necesidades en atención farmacéutica de los inmigrantes del Campo de Gibraltar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3175</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33118</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11016^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
