<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-64077</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Multiple myeloma (MM) is a plasm-cell neoplasm, thatis characterized by a monoclonal protein in the serum or urine. Bortezomib is an efficacy drug for the second line treatment of MM. Patients and method: We conducted a retrospective study of 21 consecutive cases with refractory MM treated with bortezomib and dexamethasone as second line therapy, with the objective of analyzing the overall response rate (primary end point), the progression-free survival (PFS), the overall survival (OS), the duration of response (DR) and toxicity profile (second end points). Results: In our study we found an overall response rate of 70%. With a median follow-up of 15 months, we had a median PFS of 12 months (95% CI: 2-21 months), with a median OS of 17 months (95% CI: 2-32 months), and a median DR of 9 months (95% CI: 5-13 months). Fourtyseven percent of patients had neuropathy, the 33% thrombocytopenia,13.33% anemia and 26.66% diarrhea. Conclusions: The combination of bortezomib and dexamethasone is an effective and safe treatment in second line of refractory MM, with amanageable toxicity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Khosravi Shahi, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Manga, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabín Domínguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encinas García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izarzugaza Perón, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El mieloma múltiple (MM) es una neoplasia de células plasmáticas, que se caracteriza por la presencia de una proteína monoclonal en suero u orina. Bortezomib es un fármaco eficaz en el tratamiento de segunda línea del MM. Pacientes y métodos: Hemos realizado un estudio retrospectivo de una serie de 21 casos consecutivos de MM refractario a los que hemos tratado con bortezomib y dexametasona en segundas líneas, con el objetivo de analizar la tasa de respuesta (objetivo primario), la supervivencia libre de progresión (SLP), la supervivencia global (SG), la duración de respuesta (DR) y la toxicidad (objetivos secundarios). Resultados: En nuestro estudio hemos encontrado una tasa de respuesta total de 70%. Con una mediana de seguimiento de 15 meses, hemos obtenido una mediana de SLP de 12 meses (IC95%: 2-21 meses), una mediana de SG de 17 meses (IC95%:2-32 meses) y una mediana de DR de 9 meses (IC95%: 5-13 meses). El 47 % de los pacientes presentaron neuropatía,el 33% trombocitopenia, 13,33% anemia, y 26,66% diarrea. Conclusiones: La combinación de bortezomib y dexametasona es un tratamiento efectivo y seguro en segundas líneas de MM refractario, con una toxicidad manejable</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;25(2): 73-77, feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-64077</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d22418^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1878^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23938^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9293^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d974^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
