<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93626</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Area strain: normal values for a new parameter in healthy people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The echocardiographic technology known as three-dimensional wall motion tracking offers three-dimensional images of the myocardium and provides multiple measures of deformation, one of which is known as &#147;area strain&#148; (AS), which combines left ventricular longitudinal and circumferential deformations. Our aim was to describe the normal maximum systolic reference AS value in a sample of healthy subjects. Sixty consecutive subjects without known cardiovascular risk factors or diseases were enrolled, and left ventricular AS was measured. Overall mean AS was &#150;38.87±5.89%. Mean values at the level of the basal, middle, and apical segments were &#150;38.42%±7.58%, &#150;38.74%±6.34%, and &amp;#8722;43.18%±12.81%, respectively. Thus, our results show for the first time the reference values for AS in healthy subjects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Millán, Mariángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quezada, Maribel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamorano, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lennie, Vera</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Isla, Leopoldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guinea, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macaya, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tecnología ecocardiográfica denominada three-dimensional wall motion tracking es capaz de realizar un seguimiento tridimensional del miocardio y obtener múltiples valores de su deformación, entre los que se encuentra el area strain (AS), que combina el análisis de la deformación longitudinal y circunferencial del ventrículo izquierdo. Nuestro objetivo es describir el valor sistólico máximo normal de referencia de AS en una muestra de sujetos sanos. Se reclutó a 60 sujetos consecutivos, sin enfermedad ni factores de riesgo cardiovascular conocidos, y se les cuantificó el AS del ventrículo izquierdo. El valor promedio de AS fue &#150;38,87 ± 5,89%. Los valores promedio a nivel de los segmentos basales, medio y apicales fueron &#150;38,42 ± 7,58%, &#150;38,74 ± 6,34% y &#150;43,18 ± 12,81% respectivamente. Por lo tanto, nuestros resultados muestran, por primera vez, los valores de referencia de AS en sujetos sanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;64(12): 1194-1197, dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93626</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Area strain: umbrales de normalidad de un nuevo parámetro en sujetos sanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33091^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33091^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35390^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33091^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
