<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90311</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Measure of human resource management practices: psychometric properties and factorial structure of the questionnaire PRH-33</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the present article we study the psychometric properties of a scale (PRH-33) designed to determine human resources practices in organizations. To do so, we administered an initial pool of 97 items related to these practices. 374 company directors from different manufacturing sectors participated. The exploratory factorial analysis of the 97 items revealed a structure consisting of two factors: development (the professional growth of individuals) and training (the use of processes, procedures and tools). To obtain a shorter scale, we selected the 33 items with the highest saturations in the aforementioned factors. The two subscales obtained had the necessary level of reliability. These results show that the present scale (PRH-33) is a highly useful tool for correctly evaluating organizational human resources practices (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boada-Grau, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Ripoll, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente artículo estudiamos las propiedades psicométricas de una escala (PRH-33) creada con el objetivo de diagnosticar las prácticas de recursos humanos en las organizaciones. Con este propósito se administró un pool inicial de 97 ítems relacionados con dichas prácticas. Participaron 374 directivos de empresas de distintos sectores productivos. El análisis factorial exploratorio de los 97 ítems mostró una estructura constituida por dos factores: desarrollo (crecimiento profesional de las personas) y formalización (uso de procesos, procedimientos y herramientas). Con el propósito de obtener una escala de menor longitud se seleccionaron los 33 ítems con las saturaciones más elevadas en los dos factores mencionados. Las dos subescalas obtenidas mostraron unas fiabilidades apropiadas. A partir de estos resultados, la presente escala (PRH-33) puede convertirse en un instrumento de gran utilidad para evaluar de manera apropiada las prácticas organizacionales sobre recursos humanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(2): 527-535, mayo-ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medida de las prácticas de recursos humanos: propiedades psicométricas y estructura factorial del cuestionario PRH-33</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15338^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10751</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
