<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153960</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of a Spanish version of the Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To examine the psychometric properties of a Spanish version of the C-SSRS (Sp-CSSRS). Method. Data are from a naturalistic, cross-sectional, multicentre, validation study, including 467 psychiatric outpatients, 242 of whom had a history of suicide attempt. The study measures were: C-SSRS; the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HDRS); the Beck Suicide Intent Scale; the Medical Damage Scale. Results. Construct validity: Pearson coefficient between the C-SSRS severity (C-Sev) and intensity (C-Int) of ideation subscale scores was 0.44 (P &lt; .000) for the total sample. Likewise, Pearson coefficient between C-Sev score and HDRS item 3 was 0.56 (P &lt; .000). For the sub-sample of patients with suicide attempt, significant Pearson correlations were found between the C-Sev and the Beck Suicide Intent Scale scores (r = 0.22; P = .001). Discriminant validity: Significant differences were found in C-Sev and C-Int scores between patients with and without suicide attempt (P &lt; .000). The C-Sev score discriminated between patients based on HDRS item 3 (P &lt; .009). Sensitivity to change: Linear regression showed that a one-unit decrease in HDRS item 3 corresponded to a decrease of 5.08 units in the C-Sev score (P = .141). A one-unit change in HDRS item 3 corresponded to a change of 13.51 on the C-Int assessments (P = .007). Cronbach's alpha was 0.53 for C-Int. The principal component analysis identified 2 components that explain 55.66% of the total variance (C-Int). Conclusion. The data support that the Sp-C-SSRS is a reliable and valid instrument for assessing suicidal ideation and behaviour in daily clinical practice and research settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáiz, Pilar A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Mesa, Eva M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bobes, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Posner, Kelly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oquendo, María A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Portilla, María Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Al-Halabí, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido, Marlén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cervilla, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benabarre, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burón, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Álvarez, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarrete, María Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñiz, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Examinar las propiedades psicométricas de la versión en español de la escala C-SSRS (Sp-CSSRS). Método. Estudio de validación naturalista, transversal y multicéntrico. Muestra: 467 pacientes psiquiátricos ambulatorios (242 con tentativa de suicidio previa). Instrumentos: C-SSRS; Escala de Hamilton para la Depresión (HDRS); Escala de Intencionalidad Suicida de Beck; Escala de Gravedad Médica de la Tentativa (MDS). Resultados. Validez del constructo: el coeficiente de Pearson entre la subescala de gravedad (C-Grave) y la de intensidad (C-Int) de la Sp-C-SSRS fue 0,44 (p &lt; 0,000). El coeficiente de Pearson entre C-Grave y el ítem 3 de la HDRS fue 0,56 (p &lt; 0,000). Para la submuestra de pacientes con tentativa de suicidio previa, se encontró una correlación estadísticamente significativa entre C-Grave y la Escala de Intencionalidad Suicida de Beck (r = 0,22; p = 0,001). Validez discriminante: se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre las puntuaciones de C-Grave y de C-Int entre pacientes con tentativa de suicidio y sin ella (p &lt; 0,000). La puntuación de la C-Grave clasificó adecuadamente a los pacientes en función de su puntuación en el ítem 3 de la HDRS (p &lt; 0,009). Sensibilidad al cambio: la regresión lineal mostró que la disminución de una unidad en el ítem 3 de la HDRS se correspondió con la disminución de 5,08 unidades en la C-Grave (p = 0,141). El cambio de una unidad en el ítem 3 de la HDRS se correspondió con un cambio de 13,51 unidades en la C-Int (p = 0,007). El alfa de Cronbach fue 0,53. El análisis factorial de la C-Int identificó 2 componentes que explicaron el 55,66% de la varianza total. Conclusión. La Sp-C-SSRS es un instrumento fiable y válido para evaluar la ideación y la conducta suicidas en la práctica clínica y en contextos de investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);9(3): 134-142, jul.-sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación de la versión en español de la Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (Escala Columbia para Evaluar el Riesgo de Suicidio)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13791^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13792^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
