<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107733</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High Incidence of Bloodstream Infection Due to Gram-negative Bacilli in Patients With Pulmonary Hypertension Receiving Intravenous Treprostinil</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: An excessive risk for bacteremia has recently been reported in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH) treated with intravenous treprostinil. We aimed to assess this association in a cohort of patients from a Spanish referral center. Patients and methods: We performed a retrospective cohort study that included 55 patients diagnosed with PAH who received a continuous intravenous infusion of a prostanoid (epoprostenol or treprostinil) for &amp;#8805;1month at our center between January 1991 and December 2011. The risk factors associated with the incidence of bacteremia were analyzed with the log-rank test. Results: After a total follow-up of 64,453 treatment days, we found 12 episodes of bacteremia: Staphylococcus aureus (5 episodes), non-fermenting gram-negative bacilli (4 episodes), other gram-positive cocci (2 episodes), and Enterobacter cloacae (one episode). The incidence of bacteremia was 0.118 episodes per 1,000 treatment days in patients receiving epoprostenol versus 0.938 episodes per 1,000 treatment-days in patients receiving treprostinil (P=.0037). All episodes of bacteremia due to Gram-negative bacilli were diagnosed in patients on treprostinil. In the univariate analysis the treatment with intravenous treprostinil was associated with the incidence of bacteremia (hazard ratio: 4.09; 95% confidence interval: 1.24-14.53), although the low number of events prevented us from performing a multivariate analysis. Conclusions: Therapy with intravenous treprostinil is associated with a higher risk for bacteremia, especially due to non-fermenting Gram-negative bacilli. This association should be taken in consideration when choosing empirical antibiotic therapy for patients with PAH and sepsis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Ruiz, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Hernández, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Cano, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Medrano, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Recientemente se ha comunicado un exceso de riesgo de bacteriemia en pacientes con hipertensión arterial pulmonar (HAP) que reciben tratamiento con treprostinil intravenoso. Pretendemos evaluar esta asociación en una unidad de referencia española. Pacientes y método: Estudio de cohortes retrospectivo con inclusión de 55 pacientes con HAP seguidos en nuestro centro y que recibieron tratamiento mediante perfusión intravenosa continua con un prostanoide (epoprostenol o treprostinil) durante &amp;#8805;1mes entre enero de 1991 y diciembre de 2011. Analizamos mediante el test de log-rank los factores asociados a la incidencia de bacteriemia. Resultados: Tras un seguimiento total de 64.453 días se documentaron 12 episodios de bacteriemia: Staphylococcus aureus (5 episodios), bacilos gramnegativos (BGN) no fermentadores (4 episodios), otros cocos grampositivos (2 episodios) y Enterobacter cloacae (un episodio). La incidencia de bacteriemia fue de 0,118 episodios por 1.000 días de tratamiento con epoprostenol, frente a 0,938 episodios por 1.000 días de tratamiento con treprostinil (p=0,0037). Todos los casos de bacteriemia por BGN tuvieron lugar en pacientes que recibían treprostinil. En el análisis univariante el tratamiento con treprostinil se asoció a la incidencia de bacteriemia (hazard ratio: 4,09; intervalo de confianza del 95%: 1,24-14,53), si bien el limitado número de eventos impidió la realización de un modelo multivariante. Conclusiones: El tratamiento con treprostinil intravenoso conlleva un mayor riesgo de bacteriemia, especialmente por BGN no fermentadores. Esta asociación debe ser tenida en cuenta en la elección del tratamiento antibiótico empírico en pacientes con HAP y sepsis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;48(12): 443-447, dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107733</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alta incidencia de bacteriemia por bacilos gramnegativos en pacientes con hipertensión pulmonar tratados con treprostinil por vía intravenosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30074^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7155^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7450</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29280^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6241^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
