<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048753</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Misleading presentation of rhombencephalitis due to Listeria monocytogenes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Rhombencephalitis due to Listeria monocytogenes may present in a variety of forms.    Case report. We describe the case of a 76 years old male presenting with an acute symmetrical palsy of fifth, seventh, ninth-tenth cranial nerves, ophtalmoparesia and miosis, without evident signs of long tract lesion, mimicking a peripheral nervous system or neuromuscular junction disease. The results of the blood cultures and    the magnetic resonance imaging gave the diagnosis of rhombencephalitis due to Listeria.    Conclusions. Rhombencephalitis due to Listeria monocytogenes may present as a symmetric palsy of cranial nerves, therefore it can mimic a cranial nerves multineuritis syndrome</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sebastián, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bautista Espinal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marinas Alejo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Gutiérrez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Massó, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La romboencefalitis por Listeria monocytogenes es una infección del sistema nervioso que se puede presentar de formas muy variadas.    Caso clínico. Presentamos a un paciente de 76 años con afectación aguda simétrica de los pares craneales quinto, séptimo, noveno-décimo junto con oftalmoparesia y miosis, sin signos claros de lesión de vías largas de tronco, que orientaron inicialmente a sospechar una enfermedad del sistema nervioso periférico o de placa motora. El resultado de los hemocultivos y de las imágenes de resonancia magnética permitió establecer el diagnóstico de romboencefalitis por Listeria.    Conclusiones. La romboencefalitis por Listeria monocytogenes puede manifestarse en forma de parálisis aguda simétrica de pares craneales, pudiendo ser confundida con un cuadro de multineuritis de pares craneales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;20(10): 694-697, dic. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048753</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Romboencefalitis por Listeria de presentación equívoca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8261^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19338</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8261^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19338^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8262</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
