<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99896</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic burden of hip fracture in our community (North of Gran Canaria)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Fix the incidence of hip fracture and set it&#146;s burden (direct and indirect costs associated) in 12 months. Population and methodology: A one year (Sept 2006-Aug 2007), longitudinal, prospective, observational, cohort study of 65 y.o and older people with a hip fracture in the north of Gran Canaria. Descriptive analysis of the direct cost in terms of clinical diagnostic and therapeutic procedures, professional home care attention, private and public nursing home, orthopaedic devices adquired and reforms at home addresses have been considered as well as the indirect cost, the so called «ceased profit», that is to say, the lost of productivity of those remunerated who have to abandon their occupations to take care of the patient. Results: The incidence was 437,5 cases per 100.000 people/year. Hospital cost was 2.444.556,4 &#128;. Total economic burden was 6.253.177,9 &#128;, as a result of the sum of direct and indirect costs, 5.392.452,8 (86,3%) and 860.725,1 &#128; (13,7%) respectively. Private and public financing represented 78% and 22% of the direct cost (5.400.000 &#128;) respectively. Indirect cost represented 860.000 &#128;. Conclusion: Our incidence is lower than the national rate. Traslation to public nurse homes should be limited as necessary due to its high cost. Social support should be encouraged to help the families of these patients with limited economic resources (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Deive Maggiolo, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Santana, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jacinto, R. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre García, M. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Moreu, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la incidencia de la fractura de cadera osteoporótica en nuestro medio y el consumo total de recursos económicos directos e indirectos durante 12 meses. Material y método: Estudio longitudinal prospectivo no intervencionista de una cohorte de pacientes mayores de 65 años del área norte de Gran Canaria afectos de una fractura de cadera osteoporótica, entre septiembre de 2006 y agosto de 2007. Análisis descriptivo del coste de los procesos diagnósticos y terapéuticos y el coste por hora de la atención domiciliaria, de las residencias privadas y de los centros de crónicos concertados con la Consejería, los costes de las reformas domiciliarias precisadas a partir de la fractura y los derivados de la adquisición de mobiliario adaptado y de material ortopédico. Resultados: La incidencia acumulada fue de 437,5 casos/100.000 habitantes/año. El coste por hospitalización fue de 2.444.556,4 &#128; y representó el 39% del gasto total. El coste total, 6.253.177,9 &#128;, se obtuvo sumando el coste directo, 5.392.452,8 &#128; (86,3%), y el indirecto, 860.725,1 &#128; (13,7%). Las aportaciones pública y privada constituyeron respectivamente el 78% y el 22% del coste directo. El coste indirecto se estimó en 860.725,1 &#128;. Conclusiones: La incidencia está por debajo de la media nacional. El traslado a los centros de crónicos incrementa considerablemente el gasto, por lo que deben ser adecuadamente controlados, y los servicios sociales destinados a la ayuda a las familias de los pacientes con problemas económicos, potenciados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);23(1): 15-21, ene.-mar. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99896</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio del impacto económico de las fracturas de cadera en nuestro medio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50090</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16648^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6856^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3376^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
