<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88580</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Haemophilia: exercise and sport</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Physical exercise and sports is one of the basic foundations in the treatment of haemophilia.This article gives a brief description of the characteristics of haemophilia, and throughan exhaustive literature review, the importance of the physical condition, as regards preventionand treatment of musculoskeletal lesions in the haemophilic patient, is also analysed.Haemophilia is a hereditary haematological disease, characteristic orthopaedic lesions. Itaffects males and has a deficiency of clotting factors which causes haemorrhages, includingspontaneous (in severe patients without treatment). The most common lesions are: haemarthrosis,synovitis, muscle haematomas and haemophilic arthritis. The physical condition of thehaemophilic patient, controlled by clotting factor replacement therapy, is fundamental andrequires physiotherapy, physical exercise and sport.Based on the recommendations by expert committees of the World Haemophilia Foundation(WFH) and using major data bases and search strategies with key words, 756 references wereobtained, of which on 74 passed the inclusion criteria.The publications were grouped by subject area, differentiating review articles, observationalstudies and clinical experiences, experimental studies and interventionist actions on specificparameters of physical condition.It concludes with important evidence on the recommendation of physical exercise and sportin haemophilia, the consensus on its suitability for the physical and social wellbeing of thepatients and the need to increase scientific works in this respect(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Querol, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valencia-Peris, Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallach, José Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Moreno, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Devís-Devís, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Alenda, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El ejercicio físico y el deporte constituyen uno de los pilares básicos en el tratamientode la hemofilia. Este trabajo describe un resumen de las características de la hemofiliay, a través de una exhaustiva revisión bibliográfica, se analiza la importancia de la condiciónfísica, en relación con la prevención y el tratamiento de las lesiones musculoesqueléticas en elpaciente hemofílico.La hemofilia es una enfermedad hematológica hereditaria, con lesiones ortopédicas características.Afecta a individuos varones y presenta un déficit de factores de la coagulación queprovoca hemorragias incluso espontáneas (en pacientes graves sin tratamiento). Las lesionesmás frecuentes son: hemartrosis, sinovitis, hematomas musculares y artropatía hemofílica. Lacondición física del paciente hemofílico, instrumentada mediante terapia sustitutiva de factoresde la coagulación, es fundamental y requiere fisioterapia, ejercicio físico y deporte.Basándonos en las recomendaciones de los comités de expertos de la Federación Mundial deHemofilia (WFH) y utilizando las principales bases de datos, mediante estrategias de búsquedacon palabras clave, se obtuvieron 756 referencias, de las que tan sólo 74 superaron los criteriosde inclusión.Las publicaciones se agruparon por áreas temáticas, diferenciando artículos de revisión,trabajos observacionales y experiencias clínicas, estudios experimentales y actuaciones intervencionistassobre parámetros concretos de la condición física.Se concluye con la evidencia de la importancia de la recomendación del ejercicio físico ydeporte en la hemofilia, el consenso en su idoneidad para el bienestar físico, psíquico y socialde los pacientes, y la necesidad de incrementar los trabajos científicos al respecto(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);46(169): 29-39, ene.-mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88580</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hemofilia: ejercicio y deporte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6619^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6619^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
