<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139910</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A healthy nutrition and exercise daily are the main cause and protection to avoid the obesity and overweight</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Obesity is a common health problem at school age. We performed a study to determine lifestyles in relation to nutrition and exercise, drug use, and interpersonal relationships, and leisure-time in students in a Secondary School. Methods: We invited to participate some 269 students between 12 and 15 years and permission was sought from their families. Socio-demographic data, measurement of weight and height and collected information on dietary and physical activity were collected through a questionnaire. Results: We observed lower BMI among young people when 4 dietary recommendations are satisfied or 3 dietary recommendations in addition to daily exercise. In this group 2.7 out of 10 individuals are classified either as obese or overweight, with significant differences between BMI and year of birth: the older, the higher BMI. So that, with increasing age, BMI increases, yielding values of BMI for overweight in boys and girls at the age 14-15 years. There are discrepancies between how students perceive their body and actual BMI values. Conclusion: Between 70% and 80% of secondary students have inadequate consumption of sweets, bakery products and soft drinks with sugar, and only 17% practice physical exercise daily (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Murillo, Berta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falguera Alegre, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osinaga Cenoz, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldaba Yaben, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urzainqui Martínez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La obesidad es un problema de salud frecuente en la edad escolar. Se ha realizado un estudio para conocer los estilos de vida en relación a la nutrición y ejercicio físico, consumo de drogas, relaciones interpersonales y afectivas, y ocio y tiempo libre en alumnos de un Instituto de Enseñanza Secundaria. Métodos: Se invitó a participar a 269 alumnos entre 12 y 15 años y se solicitó autorización a sus familias. Se recogieron datos sociodemográficos, medición del peso y de la talla y recogió información sobre hábitos alimentarios y de actividad física mediante un cuestionario. Resultados: Se ha observado menor índice de masa corporal entre la población joven si se siguen 4 recomendaciones alimentarias o 3 recomendaciones alimentarias además de ejercicio físico diario. En este colectivo se han observado 2,7 personas obesas o con sobrepeso de cada 10, habiendo diferencias significativas entre el IMC y el año de nacimiento: cuanto más edad, mayor IMC. De tal forma que, al aumentar de edad, se incrementa el IMC, obteniéndose valores de sobrepeso en chicos y chicas a la edad de 14-15 años. La percepción del cuerpo que tiene el alumnado difiere de los valores reales. Conclusiones: Entre un 70% y un 80% del alumnado de secundaria hace un consumo no adecuado de dulces, bollería industrial y refrescos con azúcar, y sólo un 17% hace ejercicio físico diariamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;20(3): 91-98, jul.-sept. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139910</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una alimentación sana y el ejercicio físico son los factores determinantes y protectores para evitar la obesidad y el sobrepeso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37738^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
