<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155247</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">D-dimer testing in the emergency department: age adjustment, inappropriateuse, and ability to predict the extension and severity of pulmonary embolism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate whether using D-dimer test results adjusted for age according to the formula proposed by Douma et al. improves diagnostic accuracy; to assess the appropriateness of ordering D-dimer tests on clinical suspicion of pulmonary embolism; and to explore the association of test results with the extension and severity of the embolism. Methods. Retrospective observational study of 1833 cases in which D-dimer testing was ordered for patients in our hospital&#146;s emergency department in the course of a year. We calculated sensitivity, specificity, and positive and negative predictive values using our hospital&#146;s D-dimer cutoff of 250 &amp;#956;g/mL adjusted for age with a modification of Douma et al.&#146;s formula. When information about pulmonary embolism extension and severity was on record, we assessed the correlation with test results. Results. Adjusting D-dimer level for age increased the number of true negatives and the specificity and positive predictive value of the test. D-dimer level correlated significantly with the extension of pulmonary embolism (r=0.41, P&lt;.05) but not with clinical severity. Conclusions. Adjusting the D-dimer test result by age improves accuracy in the diagnosis of pulmonary embolism, even though clinical suspicion in Spain does not follow guideline recommendations. Our findings suggest that Ddimer level correlates with the extension but not the severity of pulmonary embolism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Berraondo Fraile, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Vazquéz, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón Capilla, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bediaga Collado, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan Samper, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Fabrellas, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Konishi, Izumi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Valorar la mejora de la precisión diagnóstica del dímero D (DD) al ajustar por la edad aplicando la fórmula publicada por Douma et al., así como evaluar la adecuación de la solicitud del DD a la sospecha clínica y relacionar sus valores con la extensión y gravedad de la embolia pulmonar. Método. Estudio observacional, retrospectivo que incluye 1.833 pacientes atendidos en el servicio de urgencias de nuestro hospital a lo largo de 1 año, a los que se solicitó determinación del DD. Se calculó sensibilidad, especificidad, valor predictivo positivo y negativo de su valor utilizando el punto de corte de nuestro centro (250 &amp;#956;g/mL) y ajustado por edad (fórmula de Douma et al. modificada) y se correlacionó con la extensión y gravedad de la embolia pulmonar cuando la hubo. Resultados. El ajuste por edad del valor de DD supone aumentar la proporción de casos verdaderos negativos, la especificidad y el valor predictivo positivo de esta determinación. Se encuentra una correlación significativa entre el valor del DD con la extensión de la embolia pulmonar (r = 0,41, p &lt; 0,05) pero no con la gravedad clínica del episodio.  Conclusiones. El ajuste del DD por la edad mejora la precisión diagnóstica de la embolia pulmonar, aunque, en nuestro entorno, su sospecha no se establece siguiendo las guías recomendadas. El valor del DD se relaciona con la extensión pero no con la gravedad de la embolia pulmonar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);28(4): 223-228, ago. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155247</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la utilización del dímero D en urgencias: ajuste por edad, uso inapropiado y predicción de extensión y gravedad de la embolia pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3868^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
