<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128593</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">On some problems of psychoanalytic technique brought about by projective identification and counteridentification</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The autor pursues a line of investigation begun in earlier Works, placing the emphasis upon a partial and specific aspects of the analyst´s countertransference response faced with the patientçs excessive use of projective identification. For this he proposes the term projective counteridentification. Starting with a synthesis and updating of the nature and degrees of operance of the projective mechanisms in the transference situation, the author goes on to consider what it is that takes place in the analyst, within whom the projective identification acts and brings about changes. He considers it inadequate, within this specific context, merely to note that the analyst is the passive recipient of the analysand´s repeated projections, or that he reacts to them under the influence of his own neurotic remnants. He brings into sharp relief another specific form of reaction evoked exclusively or predominantly by that which has been projected and placed into him; and by that which is carried passively to come to play the different roles contained within these projections. He examines the inevitable ramifications for analytic technique, illustrated by several analytic situations where these processes emerged and operated most intensely (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grinberg, León</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autor continúa con una línea de investigación iniciada en trabajos anteriores cuyo acento está puesto en un aspecto parcial y específico de la respuesta contratransferencial del analista ante la excesiva utilización de la identificación proyectiva por parte del paciente, y para la cual propuso el término de &#147;contraidentificación proyectiva&#148;. Partiendo de una síntesis y actualizaciones de la naturaleza y grados de operancia de los mecanismos poryectivos en la situación transferencial, el autor se detiene en el examen de lo que acontece en el analista, dentro del cual la identificación proyectiva actúa y produce modificaciones. Considera que, en ese particular contexto, no es suficiente señalar que el analista es el receptor pasivo de las reiteradas proyecciones del analizado, o que reacciona frente a las mismas influido por sus remanentes neuróticos. Destaca otra forma particular de reacción provocada exclusiva o predominantemente por lo que ha sido proyectado y &#147;ubicado&#148; dentro de él y por lo que se ve &#147;llevado&#148; pasivamente a desempeñar los distintos papeles contenidos en dichas proyecciones. Estudia la inevitable repercusión que esto produce en la técnica y lo ilustra con algunas situaciones analíticas, en las que dichos procesos surgieron y operaron con mayor intensidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(71): 59-65, ene.-abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128593</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sobre algunos problemas de técnica psicoanalítica determinados por la identificación y contraidentificación proyectivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
