<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153956</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endophthalmitis of probable endogenous origin caused by Scedosporium boydii: a case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Mycotic ocular infections caused by the Scedosporium apiospermum species complex are challenging to treat because of the delayed diagnoses and poor responses to antifungal drugs and surgical treatment. Case report. A case of a 69-year-old male patient with a history of diabetes mellitus type 2 and prior surgery on the right femur is described. In the 10 days prior to the ophthalmic consultation he started with ocular pain, adding to a previous and progressive loss of visual acuity in his right eye. The diagnosis of endophthalmitis of probable endogenous origin was established. Despite medical treatment, the patient's condition worsened and, due to the imminent risks, an enucleation was performed. Smears of the enucleation tissue revealed fungal cells, and the cultures yielded a fungus belonging to the S. apiospermum species complex, which was identified as Scedosporium boydii by morphological characteristics and sequencing of a PCR amplicon. Conclusions. A diagnosis of endophthalmitis of probable endogenous origin in the right eye was based on a previous right femur surgery. Potential risk to the patient led to enucleation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Hernández, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanzzini-Zago, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corredor-Casas, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Reyes, Abelardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzano-Gayosso, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Martínez, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alba Orozco, Alan Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Las infecciones micóticas oculares causadas por el complejo de especies de Scedosporium apiospermum son un reto en el tratamiento por su diagnóstico tardío y la pobre respuesta a los antimicóticos y al tratamiento quirúrgico. Caso clínico. Se describe el caso de un paciente de sexo masculino de 69 años con antecedentes de diabetes mellitus de tipo 2 y cirugía previa del fémur derecho. Diez días antes de la consulta oftalmológica comenzó con dolor ocular que se sumaba a una pérdida previa y progresiva de la capacidad visual en el ojo derecho. Se estableció el diagnóstico de endoftalmitis de posible origen endógeno. A pesar del tratamiento, el paciente no presentó mejoría y por los inminentes riesgos se decidió llevar a cabo una enucleación. El frotis a partir del tejido enucleado mostró células fúngicas y los cultivos revelaron un hongo perteneciente al complejo S. apiospermum, identificado como Scedosporium boydii por procedimientos morfológicos y por secuenciación de un amplicón de PCR. Conclusiones.  El diagnóstico de endoftalmitis de probable origen endógeno en el ojo derecho se basó en el antecedente de una cirugía previa de fémur, cuyos riesgos para el paciente condujeron a una enucleación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;33(2): 122-125, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153956</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endoftalmitis de probable origen endógeno causada por Scedosporium boydii. Informe de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24638^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23633^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23633^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24638^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35306^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
