<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132642</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Animal assisted interventions in neurorehabilitation: A review of the most recent literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: While conventional wisdom has always affirmed the value of animals in promoting human health and well-being, only recently has their therapeutic role in medicine become a topic for dedicated research. Animal assisted interventions (AAI) can be classified as animal-assisted activities, animal-assisted therapy, and service animal programs. Objective: The aim of this review is to analyse original papers addressing AAI and neurological diseases and published in the most influential medical journals between 2001 and 2012, and discuss their findings in the light of what may be of interest in the field of neurology.Discussion: We selected a total of 23 articles on neurorehabilitation in cerebral palsy, pervasive developmental disorders, multiple sclerosis, spinal cord injury, stroke, and mental disorders. The main therapeutic results were improvement on the Gross Motor Function Classification Scale and in upper limb dexterity (cerebral palsy); improvement in social functioning and interaction;  reductions in stress, anxiety, and loneliness (pervasive developmental disorders andmental disorders); and decreased spasticity with improved balance (multiple sclerosis, spinal cord injury, stroke). Conclusion: These interventions, performed with highly specialised animals in very specific  neurological populations, deliver an increasing body of scientific evidence suggesting that theyare an effective complement to other existing therapies. In these diseases, further high-quality studies are warranted in order to define the most appropriate programmes for therapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Lasa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero Alcaide, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela Donoso, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Máximo Bocanegra, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferriero, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atín Arratibel, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Aunque siempre se ha afirmado el valor de los animales en la promoción del bienestar y la salud del ser humano, solo recientemente su papel terapéutico en medicina se ha convertido en el foco de investigación especializada. Las intervenciones asistidas poranimales pueden dividirse en actividades asistidas por animales, terapia asistida por animales y programas de animales de servicio.  Objetivo: El objetivo de esta revisión es analizar las publicaciones realizadas entre 2001 y 2012 en las revistas médicas más importantes, relacionadas con el campo de la rehabilitación de las enfermedades neurológicas, y discutir estos hallazgos a la luz de lo que pueda ser de interés para la neurología. Discusión: Se seleccionaron un total de 23 artículos de intervenciones en el campo de la parálisis cerebral infantil, trastornos generalizados del desarrollo, esclerosis múltiple, lesión medular, accidente cerebrovascular y trastornos mentales. Los principales resultados terapéuticos fueron: mejoría en la Gross Motor Function y en el manejo del miembro superior (parálisis cerebral infantil); aumento de la socialización y el contacto con el medio ambiente, reducción del estrés y la ansiedad y sentimientos de soledad (trastornos generalizados del desarrollo y trastornos mentales); disminución de la espasticidad y mejoría del equilibrio (esclerosis múltiple, lesión medular, accidente cerebrovascular). Conclusiones: Estas intervenciones asistidas con un tipo de animales muy limitado utilizadas en grupos clínicos neurológicos muy específicos muestran cada vez más pruebas científicas, como método complementario a otras terapias ya existentes. En estas enfermedades, se necesitan más estudios de alta calidad metodológica que permitan definir los programas más apropiados para la aplicación terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;30(1): 1-7, ene.-feb. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132642</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervenciones asistidas por animales en neurorrehabilitación: una revisión de la literatura más reciente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53695^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53695^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53695^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4345^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53695^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53695^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
