<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83149</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intravenous urography is died. Long live the computerized tomography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Very important changes have happened in the field of the genitourinary image during the last half of the 20th century, so that for most of the historical intravenous urography indications, nowadays the computerized tomography (CT) is technique of choice. The aim of this report is to perform an update in the correct use of the imaging techniques in the adult-related most frequent urological pathology, including: urolithiasis, haematuria, infections, tumours, surgery follow-up and pyelectasis, specially focused in CT. A brief historical review of the urological imaging techniques is performed, emphasizing the physical principles. In the second part, the role played by plain X-ray, ultrasound, CT and MR in the different urological pathologies are reviewed, discussing the sensibility and specificity of each technique. A brief reflection is finally carried out over of the radiation doses (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Burgos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante la última mitad del siglo xx se han producido cambios muy importantes en el campo de la imagen genitourinaria, de forma que para la mayor parte de las históricas indicaciones de la urografía intravenosa la tomografía computarizada (TC) es ahora la técnica de elección. El objetivo de este trabajo es realizar una actualización del correcto uso de las pruebas de imagen, con especial enfoque en la TC, en la patología urológica del adulto revisando las entidades más frecuentes: litiasis, hematuria, infecciones, tumores, controles de cirugía y pielectasia. Hacemos un breve recorrido histórico por las pruebas de imagen utilizadas en urología a través de los años, haciendo hincapié en sus fundamentos físicos. En la segunda parte revisamos las diferentes patologías urológicas y el papel que desempeñan la radiografía simple, la ecografía, la TC y la resonancia magnética, analizando su sensibilidad y su especificidad. Por último, hacemos una breve reflexión acerca de las dosis de radiación de los diferentes métodos radiológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;34(9): 764-774, oct. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83149</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La urografía intravenosa ha muerto, viva la tomografía computarizada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27962^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7022^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52133^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29575^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6566^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12140^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201010</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
