<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130646</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7113</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transitory first degree atrioventricular block in patient with poisoning for drug abuse and alcohol: the Holiday Heart Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alcohol intoxication and drug abuse are a common cause of visits to emergency rooms. Arrhythmias and electrocardiographic changes due to alcohol intake is called Holiday Heart Syndrome. It is defined as a rhythm or cardiac conduction alterations associated to the consumption of alcohol, reversed after the poisoning, in a person without known heart disease. The most common alteration is atrial fibrillation. We report the case of a young patient that presented in the emergency room by poisoning with different drugs and alcohol who presented transitory first degree atrioventricular block. We discussed the possible causal effect of drugs and alcohol consumed in the electrocardiographic changes in this patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Supervía Caparrós, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echarte Pazos, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Fernández, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baño López, F. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre Tejedo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poveda Velázquez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las intoxicaciones por alcohol y drogas de abuso son una causa frecuente de consulta en los Servicios de Urgencias. Las alteraciones electrocardiográficas y las arritmias debidas a la ingesta de alcohol se conocen como Holiday Heart Syndrome. Este síndrome se define como la presencia de alteraciones del ritmo o de la conducción cardiaca asociadas al consumo de alcohol que revierten tras la intoxicación y que se producen en una persona sin enfermedad cardiaca conocida. La alteración más común es la fibrilación auricular. Se presenta el caso de una paciente joven que ingresa en urgencias por intoxicación por alcohol y diferentes drogas y que presentaba un bloqueo auriculoventricular de primer grado transitorio. Se discute el posible efecto causal de las drogas y del alcohol en los cambios electrocardiográficos observados en esta paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. toxicol;31(1): 68-70, ene.-jun. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130646</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueo auriculoventricular transitorio de primer grado en paciente con poliintoxicación por drogas de abuso y etanol: the Holiday Heart Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52608^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1150^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52608^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52608^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d431^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52608^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d439^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
