<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115466</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of all patients with more than one autoantibody against extractable nuclear antigens over a three year period in order to establish a time interval for repeating the test</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The presence of anti-ENA antibodies often precedes the onset of disease and the establishment of a diagnosis. This leads to a repeat request of the autoimmune profile of the patient. ENA patterns often do not change and their repetition does not provide relevant clinical information and leads to ineffective testing. Our objective was to establish a minimum time below which the repetition of anti-ENA patterns would not be appropriate. Material and methods. A retrospective study was conducted on all the samples with an ENA result between December 2005 and December 2008. The study included all patients with more than one result. All of them were referred from specialist care. The change in the profile of ENA was studied in each patient, and the probability of change in the ENA pattern over a time interval was calculated using the Kaplan and Meier analysis of survival. Results. The results showed a probability of 75% that there would be no change with 10 months as a minimum time to repetition, 80% with 8 months, 85% with 6 months, 91% with 4 months, and 96% with 2 months. Conclusions. The minimum time to repeat the ENA study should not be less than 82 days (5% probability of a changing ENA pattern) in the absence of new clinical symptoms. Each center should set an interval of repetition between 2 and 10 months (4% and 25% probability of changing ENA pattern, respectively)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caro Narros, María del Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacheco Delgado, María Santiaga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Menchero, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La presencia de anticuerpos anti-ENA precede con frecuencia al inicio de la enfermedad y al establecimiento de un diagnóstico, lo que conlleva la solicitud reiterada del perfil autoinmune. Los patrones de ENA a menudo no se modifican, por lo que su repetición no proporciona información clínica relevante y genera un consumo inefectivo. Nuestro objetivo fue establecer un intervalo mínimo de repetición por debajo del cual la repetición del estudio no sería procedente. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de todas las muestras con resultado para ENA comprendidas entre diciembre de 2005 y diciembre de 2008. Se incluyeron en el estudio todos los pacientes con más de un resultado. Todos ellos fueron remitidos desde atención especializada. Se analizó para cada paciente el cambio en el perfil de ENA y se calculó la probabilidad de cambio del patrón en un intervalo de tiempo mediante un análisis de supervivencia de Kaplan y Meier. Resultados. No habrá cambio en el patrón de ENA con una probabilidad del 75% en un intervalo de 10 meses, con un 80% en 8 meses, con un 85% en 6 meses, con un 91% en 4 meses y con un 96% en 2 meses. Conclusiones. El tiempo mínimo para la reevaluación del perfil de ENA no debe ser inferior a 82 d (probabilidad de cambio del patrón de ENA del 5%) en ausencia de otros datos clínicos que lo sugieran. Cada centro debería fijar un intervalo de tiempo mínimo de repetición entre 2 y 10 meses (probabilidades de cambio del patrón de ENA entre el 4 y el 25%)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;6(3): 110-114, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115466</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de todos los pacientes con más de un resultado para autoanticuerpos contra antígenos extraíbles del núcleo en 3 años para establecer un criterio de intervalo de repetición de la prueba</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33124^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33124^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3258^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3258^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d948</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3260^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28302^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
