<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056305</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-guided training program in the use of bioinformatic tools for undergraduate students of clinical biochemistry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The great scientific and technological advances of recent decades have brought biological investigation into the postgenomic age. The ready availability of crucial information for the development of new projects has caused a paradigm shift in biological investigation, in which a solid training in bioinformatics is now a basic requirement. This study presents the results of the incorporation of a self-guided practical program to introduce students of clinical biochemistry to the use of bioinformatic resources. The activities comprised genomic, transcriptomic and proteomic analysis of a gene with biomedical implications. The design of specific primers for the amplification of a fragment of the gene was proposed as a technological application. The RasMol program, version 2.7.2 (&#148; by Herbert Bernstein 1998-2000) was used to analyses biological functions. In groups of three or four, students studying cellular and molecular biology as part of their degree in biochemistry at the National University of Misiones were asked to provide concrete answers to questions using bioinformatic analysis. The results showed that 100% of the students were able to answer all the questions. However, a wider-ranging treatment of molecular visualization programs is needed for future applications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cariaga Martinez, Ariel Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapata, Pedro Darío</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante las últimas décadas el gran avance científico y tecnológico llevó a la investigación biológica a las puertas de la era postgenómica. La disponibilidad de información crucial para el desarrollo de nuevos proyectos ha provocado un cambio de paradigma en la investigación biológica demandándole profesionales que cuenten con formación en Bioinformática. En este trabajo se muestran los resultados de la incorporación de un trabajo práctico autoguiado para introducir a alumnos que estudien Bioquímica al uso de recursos bioinformáticos aplicándolos a un ejemplo concreto. Las actividades consisten en la realización de un análisis genómico, transcriptómico y proteómico de un gen con implicaciones biomédicas. Además se plantea como aplicación tecnológica el diseño de cebadores específicos para la amplificación de un fragmento del gen. Como último punto se propone analizar la función biológica mediante el programa de visualización molecular RasMol versión 2.7.2 (&#148;por Herbert Bernstein 1998-2000). La metodología incluye grupos de 3-4 alumnos que cursan Biología Celular y Molecular de la Carrera de Bioquímica de la Universidad Nacional de Misiones, solicitándoseles respuestas concretas que se obtienen a través del análisis bioinformático. Los resultados de la aplicación del trabajo práctico autoguiado demuestran que el 100% de los alumnos fueron capaces de responder las consignas. Sin embargo se necesita mayor manejo de programas de visualización molecular para futuras aplicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);9(4B): 207-211, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056305</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de un trabajo práctico autoguiado para la formación en el uso de herramientas bioinformáticas de alumnos de pregrado en Bioquímica Clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1695^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1695^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1695^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4586^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4586^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4586^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19131</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33149^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4586^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4586^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19244^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19245</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
