<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164153</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric analysis of the Teaching Styles Survey in Physical Education (TSPE)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of the study was to analyze the psychometric properties of the questionnaire which values teaching styles with which preferentially identify physical education teachers. The sample was composed of 120 secondary school teachers. In designing of the instrument they started from a DEMEVI questionnaire to which 12 experts judges got the validation of content. After the respective factor, exploratory and confirmatory analysis, five-factor model and 20 items were obtained, which showed satisfactory indexes of adjustment. Acceptable levels of internal consistency and temporal stability were obtained. Teachers under 30 years valued more the cognitive, participatory and socializing styles while men under 30 years of age identified more with traditional character styles compared to women of the same age who preferred the cognitive ones. The teaching styles questionnaire in physical education provides reliable and valid evidence for use (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Merino-Barrero, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Murcia, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valero-Valenzuela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo principal fue analizar las propiedades psicométricas del cuestionario que valora los estilos de enseñanza con los que se identifican preferentemente los docentes de educación física. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 120 docentes de Educación Secundaria. Para el diseño del instrumento se partió del cuestionario DEMEVI al que 12 jueces expertos dieron la validación de contenido. Tras los respectivos análisis factoriales, exploratorios y confirmatorios, se obtuvo un modelo de cinco factores y de 20 ítems presentando índices de ajuste satisfactorios. Se obtuvieron niveles aceptables de consistencia interna y estabilidad temporal. El profesorado menor de 30 años valoraba más los estilos cognitivos, participativos y socializadores, mientras que en función del sexo, los hombres menores de 30 años se identificaban más con estilos de carácter tradicional frente a las mujeres de la misma edad que preferían los cognitivos. El cuestionario de estilos de enseñanza en educación física proporciona evidencias fiables y válidas para su uso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;17(66): 225-241, jun. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164153</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis psicométrico del Cuestionario Estilos de Enseñanza en Educación Física (EEEF)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4587^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
