<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91275</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parental presence in the operating room: effect on the quality of anesthetic induction and postoperative agitation in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Various nonpharmacologic strategies for reducing anxiety in children and improving cooperation during induction of anesthesia have been investigated. Parental presence during anesthetic induction has been the alternative studied most often, especially in English-speaking populations. Mixed results have been reported, however. The aim of this study was to evaluate the quality of anesthetic induction and the development of postoperative agitation in Spanish children undergoing ear, nose, or throat surgery with or without parental presence in the operating room. Patients and methods: Children in American Society of Anesthesiologists class 1 or 2 who were scheduled for ear, nose or throat surgery under inhalation anesthesia were randomized to 2 groups for presence or absence of a parent in the operating room. The induction experience was classified as easy, carried out with moderate resistance, or traumatic. The postoperative period was assessed as easy or traumatic. Results: Forty children were randomized. Time to onset of anesthesia was similar in the 2 groups. Induction was easy for 65% of the children with parental presence and for 25% of the children without a parent present (P&lt;.05). Induction was traumatic for 25% in the parental presence group and for 35% in the parental absence group (P&lt;.05). The incidence of moderate resistance during induction was similar in the 2 groups; the quality of the postoperative experience was also similar. Conclusions: Parental presence during induction of inhalation anesthesia improves the induction experience of nonpremeditated Spanish children, increasing the incidence of easy induction and decreasing the presence of traumatic induction. The quality of the postoperative experience is similar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balaguer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soliveres, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estruch, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solaz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Se han investigado diversas alternativas no farmacológicas para reducir el estrés y mejorar la cooperación de los niños durante la inducción anestésica. La presencia de los padres durante la inducción anestésica ha sido la intervención más comúnmente estudiada, sobre todo en la población anglosajona y con resultados contradictorios. El objetivo del presente trabajo es evaluar la calidad de la inducción anestésica y del postoperatorio según la presencia paterna o no durante la misma en niños españoles no premedicados sometidos a cirugía otorrinolaringológica. Pacientes y métodos: Niños ASA I-II programados para cirugía otorrinolaringológica con inducción inhalatoria, asignados de forma aleatoria a dos grupos, según entraran los padres (grupo P) o no (grupo C) en el quirófano. La calidad de la inducción anestésica fue valorada como suave, moderada o traumática y el postoperatorio como suave o traumático. Resultados: Se incluyeron 40 niños. El tiempo de inducción anestésica fue similar en ambos grupos. Hubo una inducción suave en el 65% de los niños del grupo P frente al 25% en el grupo C (p&lt;0,05), y una inducción traumática en el 25% de los niños del grupo P, frente al 35% del grupo C (p&lt;0,05). La incidencia de inducción moderada y la calidad de postoperatorio fueron similares en ambos grupos. Conclusión: La presencia paterna durante la inducción de la anestesia inhalatoria mejora la calidad de la inducción del niño no premedicado, aumentando la incidencia de inducciones suaves frente a las traumáticas. No se han encontrado diferencias en la calidad del postoperatorio(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(8): 472-476, oct. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91275</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de la presencia paterna en quirófano sobre la calidad de la inducción anestésica y agitación postoperatoria en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10216^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d787^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10216^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
