<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043988</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-123X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of dental arches characteristics in two age groups</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Dimensional characteristics of dental arches between two groups of age, adolescentsand adults, are compared to analyze the variations associated with age, sex and influence oforthodontic treatment. Material and methods: Two samples of 88 pairs of stone models from adolescents(average age, 14.05 years) and 65 from adults (average age, 22.15 years) were selected. Aftercast scanning, a digital program was used to measure dental mesiodistal diameters, intercanine andintermolar widths, arch lengths and lower dental crowding. For the statistic analysis the samples ofeach age group were divided by sex and by the fact of having been treated or not with orthodontics.Results: The values of the mesiodistal diameters in males were greater than in females, and greater inadolescents than in adults, especially in females. The intercanine distance decreased with age in femalesand the maxillary intermolar distance decreased in untreated females, while the mandibular oneincreased in males. Both arch lengths decreased in both sexes, mainly in the untreated individuals. Thereis an increase of the anteroinferior dental crowding with age in both sexes in the treated group.Conclusions: The loss of dental material with age associated to a greater decrease of arch length couldbe another factor in the later crowding. Also the mesial displacement of the teeth to a narrower partof the arch could explain the decrease in the intercanine and intermolar widths</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paredes-Gallardo, Vanessa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cibrián-Ortiz de Anda, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gandía-Franco, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paulino, Vera Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Se comparan las características dimensionales de las arcadas dentarias entredos grupos de edades diferentes, adolescentes y adultos jóvenes, para analizar las variaciones asociadasa la edad, sexo y a la influencia del tratamiento ortodóncico. Material y método: Se utilizaron dosmuestras: 88 pares de modelos de escayola de adolescentes (edad media 14,05 años) y 65 de adultos(edad media 22,15 años). Se usó un método digital para la medición de los diámetros mesiodistales delos dientes, distancias intercaninas e intermolares, longitudes de las arcadas y se obtuvo el apiñamientodentario inferior. Para el análisis estadístico se agruparon las muestras de cada grupo de edad porsexos y por tratados/no tratados con ortodoncia. Resultados: Los diámetros mesiodistales de los chicoseran mayores a los de las chicas y los de los adolescentes mayores que los de los adultos, sobretodo en el sexo femenino. La distancia intercanina disminuyó con la edad en las chicas y la intermolarsuperior disminuyó en las chicas no tratadas, mientras que la inferior aumenta en los chicos. Ambaslongitudes de arcada tienden a disminuir en ambos sexos y sobre todo en los grupos de no tratados.Existó un aumento del apiñamiento inferior con la edad en ambos sexos en los individuos tratados.Conclusiones: La pérdida de material dentario con el paso de los años unido a una mayor pérdida delongitud de la arcada podría ser otro factor en el apiñamiento terciario. A su vez, el desplazamientodentario a mesial podría explicar la disminución de los diámetros transversales de caninos y molares,al ocupar una zona más estrecha del arco dentario</dc:description>
<dc:source>RCOE;10(1): 47-54, ene.-feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043988</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución de las características de las arcadas dentarias en dos grupos de edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3737^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9997^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
