<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156436</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A rare case of not perforating double internal root resorption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Root resorption might be broadly classified into external or internal resorption by the location of the resorption in relation to the root surface. Internal root resorption is a relatively rare occurrence, and its etiology and pathogenesis have not been completely elucidated. This article shows the complexity of upper lateral incisor with a double not perforating root resorption and the significance of CBCT imaging in the confirmation of the three-dimensional resorption of teeth. The importance of the preoperative radiographic examination as well as radiographs during treatment is necessary. From a differential diagnosis perspective, the advent of cone beam computed tomography has considerably enhanced the clinician&#146;s capability of diagnosing internal root resorption. Nevertheless, root canal treatment remains the treatment of choice for this pathologic condition to date. The tooth was clinically and radiographically healthy at the 24-month follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nieto Salas, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sierra Lorenzo, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estévez, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cisneros Cabello, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La reabsorción radicular podría ser clasificada en externa o interna dependiendo de la localización de la misma en relación con la superficie de la raíz afectada. La reabsorción interna es relativamente poco frecuente, y su etiología y patogénesis no esta todavía del todo clara. Este artículo muestra la complejidad de un incisivo lateral superior con una doble reabsorción radicular no perforante y la importancia de la CBCT para la confirmación tridimensional de la reabsorción dental, su diagnóstico y clasificación. Tiene gran importancia el examen de la radiografía preoperatoria y el de las realizadas durante el tratamiento. Desde una perspectiva de diagnóstico diferencial, la llegada de la CBCT ha mejorado considerablemente la capacidad clínica de diagnóstico de la reabsorción radicular interna. Sin embargo, hasta la fecha, el tratamiento de conductos sigue siendo el tratamiento de elección para este tipo de patologías pulpares. En el seguimiento del caso que se presenta, el diente muestra signos clínicos y radiográficos de salud a los 24 meses después del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);34(2): 83-89, abr.-jun. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incisivo lateral superior con doble reabsorción interna</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52853^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14484^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52853^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11326^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24694^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14484^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11326^s22065</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24694^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7358^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52853^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3819^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4790^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3819^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
