<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142259</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The understanding, attitude and use of nutrition label among consumers (China)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: the aim of this study was to investigate the understanding, attitude and use of nutrition label among consumers in china. Methods: a cross-sectional survey with a self-structured questionnaire was conducted among 1153 consumers, who were recruited from different supermarkets during March to May 2014 in Wuhu city of china. Results: the result shows that the subjective understanding of nutrition labels was moderate (62.8% of respondents) but the objective understanding was varied. The attitudes toward nutrition label was positive in participates who had a higher confidence and satisfaction of nutrition label. 59.2% of the respondents indicated &#145;sometimes&#146; and 28.7% &#145;always&#146; reading nutrition label. The most frequently reading of nutrition label food was milk (57.5%), followed by infant food (33.3%), and nutrient was protein 51.5%, vitamin (49.8%) and fat (29.4%). None of demographic characteristics was associated with the understanding, attitude and use of nutrition label except education. Conclusions: participates of our study had a moderate understanding, positive attitude and higher frequent using nutrition label. Although the code of nutrition label became mandatory, more additional strategies for nutrition label are still needed, so as to improve consumers&#146; the cognition of nutrition label (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Li, Haibo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liang, Yali</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chen, Yujuan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huang , Junxia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zhu, Yu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Song, Jiangen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wen, Yufeng</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yuan, Hui</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: el objetivo de este estudio fue investigar el conocimiento, la actitud y el uso de la etiqueta nutricional entre los consumidores en China. Métodos: estudio transversal con un cuestionario estructurado que fue realizada entre 1.153 consumidores, que fueron reclutados a partir de diferentes supermercados durante marzo a mayo de 2014 en la ciudad de Wuhu de China. Resultados: el resultado muestra que la comprensión subjetiva de las etiquetas nutricionales fue moderada (el 62,8% de los encuestados), pero el objetivo entendimiento fue variado. Las actitudes hacia la etiqueta nutricional fueron positivas en aquellos participantes con mayor confianza y satisfacción en las mismas. Respecto a la lectura de las etiquetas, el 59,2 % de los encuestados contestó que &#147;a veces&#148; y el 28,7 % que &#147;siempre&#148;. La lectura de la etiqueta nutricional de alimentos que con mayor frecuencia se realizó fue la de la leche (57,5%), seguida por la alimentación infantil (33,3%), proteínas y nutrientes (51,5%), vitaminas (49,8%) y grasas (29,4%). Ninguna de las características demográficas se asoció con el conocimiento, la actitud y el uso de la etiqueta nutricional, excepto la educación. Conclusiones: Las personas que participaron en nuestro estudio tenían una comprensión moderada, mostrando una actitud más positiva aquellos que la utilizan con más frecuencia. Aunque la etiqueta nutricional se convirtió en obligatoria, aún son necesarias estrategias adicionales, así como fomentar su conocimiento por parte de los consumidores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(6): 2703-2710, jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142259</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El conocimiento, la actitud y el uso de la etiqueta nutricional entre los consumidores (China)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2727</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5641</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5654^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
