<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135968</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6567</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Importance of Primary Health-Care Professionals in the Sanitary Education About Organ Donation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To determine the influence of the information on donation generated from primary health-care on the attitude towards organ donation. Design. Descriptive transversal study. Setting. 45 municipalities of Murcia Region, Spain. Participants. The population in this study was randomly selected and stratified according to age, sex, and geographic localization among people over &gt;=15 years of age (n=1887). Interventions and measures. The attitude was evaluated according to a questionnaire psychosocial aspects of donation. There is valued the information transmitted on donation to the population from primary care (group A) or other informative sources (group B), and if this information was to favour or in opposition to the same one. Statistics: * 2 test, t Student, and logistic regression analysis. Results. Of 1887 surveys, 129 cases (group A) (7%) had received information from primary care. In this group, the 89% is in favour of the donation. In 120 cases the received information was favourable, presenting an attitude in favour of the donation of 93%, whereas in all 9 remaining cases the information was in against, decreasing the attitude to favour up to 44% (P&lt;.05). In the group B (n=1758) the attitude in favour of the donation was of 65% (P&lt;.05, with regard to the group A). The 62% (n=1083) received favourable information, improving in them the favourable attitude towards the donation up to 74%. The rest (38%; n=675) had received also unfavourable information, decreasing his attitude to favour up to 51% (P&lt;.05). Conclusions. Little information about organ donation is transmitted from primary care, but when it is realized a very positive impact has if it is favourable and very negative if it is unfavourable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Romero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos Zambudio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Martínez, M M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conesa Bernal, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canteras Jordana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla Paricio, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Determinar la influencia de la información sobre donación generada desde atención primaria (AP) en la actitud poblacional. Diseño. Estudio descriptivo, transversal. Emplazamiento. Un total de 45 municipios de la Comunidad Autónoma de Murcia. Participantes. Muestra aleatoria y estratificada por edad, sexo y localización geográfica entre la población &gt;= 15 años (n = 1.887). Mediciones principales. Encuesta psicosocial sobre donación y trasplante de órganos. Se valora la información transmitida desde AP (grupo A) u otras fuentes informativas (grupo B), y su impacto en la actitud hacia la donación. Se analizan diversas variables psicosociales. Se aplicaron los tests de la * 2 y de la t de Student y un análisis de regresión logística. Resultados. De los 1.887 encuestados, 129 del grupo A (7%) habían recibido información desde AP. En este grupo, el 89% está a favor de la donación. En 120 casos la información recibida fue favorable, con una actitud a favor del tema del 93%, mientras que en los 9 casos restantes la información fue en contra, con lo que dicha actitud favorable descendió al 44%  (p &lt; 0,05). En el grupo B (n = 1.758), la actitud a favor de la donación fue del 65% (p &lt; 0,05, respecto al grupo A). El 62% (n = 1.083) recibió una información favorable, con una actitud a favor del 74%. El resto (38%; n = 675) había recibido también información desfavorable, por lo que su actitud favorable disminuyó hasta el 51% (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones. Se transmite poca información sobre donación desde AP. Sin embargo, cuando se realiza, tiene un impacto muy positivo si es favorable y muy negativo si es desfavorable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Aten Primaria;34(10): 528-533, dic. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135968</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de los profesionales de atención primaria en la educación sanitaria de la donación de órganos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19279^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
