<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108155</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prescription of systemic cold and cough drugs to children 0-13 years old. An unresolved problem</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Upper respiratory tract infections are the most common cause of paediatric consultation, generating a high volume of prescriptions of drugs with unfavourable risk-benefit ratio. The aim of this study is to describe the prescription of systemic cough and cold medicines to children under 14 years of age in Castilla y León and analyse its variability. Population and methods: A count was made of the prescriptions for the R05 therapeutic subgroup (antitussives and mucolytics) and the R01B pharmacological therapeutic subgroup (nasal decongestants for systemic use), prescribed for children under the age of 14 in the Public Health System between 2005-2010. The number of prescriptions was analysed as crude and age-adjusted rates, as well as a a multivariate analysis (Poisson regression) of the variability associated with health area, the urban/rural environment, age, and year of prescription. Results: There were 806,785 prescriptions for systemic cough and cold drugs given to an exposed population of 1,580,229 person-years. Prescription rates (per 100 person-years) were 20.7 (antitussives), 7.0 (sympathomimetic) and 23.4 (mucolytics). These drugs were employed more often in children &lt;4 years. The prescription of mucolytics and sympathomimetics was highest at age of 1 year (rates=41.9 and 18.7, respectively) and of antitussives at 3 years (35.7). Multivariate analysis showed that in rural areas the prescription was higher than in urban areas, and that there were also significant differences between health areas. Conclusions: Between 2005 and 2010 there was a high prescription of systemic cough and cold medicines, especially in children under 2 years old, and often outside the recommended conditions of use, and there was a high geographic variabilty(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano Garcinuño, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Quirós, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casares Alonso, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Barbero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La infección de las vías respiratorias superiores es el motivo de consulta pediátrica más frecuente, generando un elevado volumen de prescripción de fármacos con desfavorable relación riesgo-beneficio. El objetivo del estudio es describir la prescripción de anticatarrales por vía sistémica a menores de 14 años en Castilla y León y analizar su variabilidad. Población y métodos: Se contabilizaron las prescripciones de los subgrupos R05 (antitusivos y mucolíticos) y R01B (simpaticomiméticos) realizadas a menores de 14 años en el sistema público de salud entre 2005-2010. Se analizaron las prescripciones como tasas crudas y ajustadas por edad, y se realizó un análisis multivariante (regresión de Poisson) de la variabilidad relacionada con el área sanitaria, el ámbito urbano/rural, la edad y el año de prescripción. Resultados: Hubo 806.785 prescripciones de anticatarrales sistémicos realizadas a una población expuesta de 1.580.229 personas-año. Las tasas de prescripción (por 100 personas-año) fueron de 20,7 (antitusivos), 7,0 (simpaticomiméticos) y 23,4 (mucolíticos). Las tasas eran mayores en los niños menores de 4 años. La prescripción máxima de mucolíticos y simpaticomiméticos ocurrió a la edad de 1 año (tasas de 41,9 y 18,7) y la de antitusivos a los 3 años (35,7). El análisis multivariante demostró una mayor prescripción en el medio rural y diferencias notables entre áreas. El número de prescripciones disminuyó entre 2005 y 2010, pero no hubo una tendencia estable en esa reducción. Conclusiones: Entre 2005 y 2010 la prescripción de anticatarrales sistémicos fue alta, alejada de las recomendaciones internacionales de tratamiento y con una marcada variabilidad geográfica(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);78(1): 43-50, ene. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prescripción de fármacos anticatarrales de uso sistémico a niños de 0-13 años. Un problema no resuelto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5198^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3170^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1000^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15066^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54123^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201301</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
