<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122223</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association of age and sex with intensity of exposure to bicycle use in Spain, 1993-2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: To estimate the association of age and sex with the intensity of exposure of cyclists in Spain, between 1993 and 2009, in a global way and for subtypes of use. Methods: From the distribution of cyclists passively involved in collisions with other vehicles included in the register of the Spanish General Traffic Directorate between 1993 and 2009, we have estimated the increase in intensity of exposure by age groups and sex, for global exposure and for subtypes of exposure (e.g. riding with or without a helmet, or riding on an open road or in urban areas), using males aged 45-49 as a reference. Results: Males have a greater exposure than females and this difference increases with age, although it has tended to decrease in recent years. In both sexes the exposure is greater in young people and goes down with age, while in males the excess in young people has disappeared in recent years. Regarding subtypes of use, female underexposure riding on an open road should be highlighted, as well as overexposure in both women and extreme age groups among non-helmet users. Conclusion: There is a close association of age and sex with the intensity of bicycle use, which changes depending on the type of use and the time period considered. Consequently, estimations of the effect of factors affecting the accident rate and the morbidity and mortality of cyclists in Spain have to be adjusted by the age and sex of the cyclist (AU) </dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Mejías, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lardelli Claret, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Ruiz, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luna del Castillo, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amezcua Prieto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Moleón, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Estimar la asociación de la edad y el sexo con la intensidad de exposición de los ciclistas en España, entre 1993 y 2009, globalmente y para subtipos de uso. Métodos: A partir de la distribución de los ciclistas pasivamente implicados en colisiones con otros vehículos, incluidos en el registro de la Dirección General de Tráfic oentre 1993 y 2009, se ha estimado el incremento en la intensidad de exposición por grupos de edad y sexo para la exposición global y para subtipos de exposición (conducción con o sin casco, en carretera o en zona urbana), tomando como referencia los varones de 45-49 años. Resultados. Los varones presentan una mayor exposición que las mujeres, diferencias que aumentan con la edad, aunque tienden a reducirse en años más recientes. En ambos sexos la exposición es mayor en jóvenes y desciende con la edad, si bien en los varones el exceso en los jóvenes desaparece en los últimos años. Por subtipos de uso, destaca la menor exposición de las mujeres en la conducción en carretera, así como la mayor exposición, en las mujeres y en los grupos de edad extremos, entre los no usuarios de casco. Conclusión: Existe una estrecha asociación entre el sexo y la edad con la intensidad de uso de la bicicleta, que cambia en función del tipo de uso y del período considerado. En consecuencia, las estimaciones del efecto de los factores que inciden sobre la accidentalidad y la morbi-mortalidad de los ciclistas en España deben ser ajustadas por la edad y el sexo del ciclista (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;37(1): 35-46, ene.-abr. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación de la edad y el sexo con la intensidad de la exposición al uso de la bicicleta en España, 1993-2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d62</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1667^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
