<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151198</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New non-invasive method for early detection of metabolic syndrome in the working population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We propose a new method for the early detection of metabolic syndrome in the working population, which was free of biomarkers (non-invasive) and based on anthropometric variables, and to validate it in a new working population. Prevalence studies and diagnostic test accuracy to determine the anthropometric variables associated with metabolic syndrome, as well as the screening validity of the new method proposed, were carried out between 2013 and 2015 on 636 and 550 workers, respectively. The anthropometric variables analysed were: blood pressure, body mass index, waist circumference, waist-height ratio, body fat percentage and waist-hip ratio. We performed a multivariate logistic regression analysis and obtained receiver operating curves to determine the predictive ability of the variables. The new method for the early detection of metabolic syndrome we present is based on a decision tree using chi-squared automatic interaction detection methodology. The overall prevalence of metabolic syndrome was 14.9%. The area under the curve for waistheight ratio and waist circumference was 0.91 and 0.90, respectively. The anthropometric variables associated with metabolic syndrome in the adjusted model were waist-height ratio, body mass index, blood pressure and body fat percentage. The decision tree was configured from the waist-height ratio (&amp;#8805;0.55) and hypertension (blood pressure &amp;#8805;128/85 mmHg), with a sensitivity of 91.6% and a specificity of 95.7% obtained. In conclusion, the early detection of metabolic syndrome in a healthy population is possible through non-invasive methods, based on anthropometric indicators such as waist-height ratio and blood pressure. This method has a high degree of predictive validity and its use can be recommended in any healthcare context (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vargas Prada, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se propone desarrollar y validar un nuevo método no invasivo (libre de biomarcadores sanguíneos) para la detección precoz del síndrome metabólico en población trabajadora, y que se basa en la medición de variables antropométricas. Entre 2013 y 2015, se llevaron a cabo dos estudios epidemiológicos: uno de prevalencia, con 636 trabajadores, para determinar las variables antropométricas asociados con el síndrome metabólico; y otro de pruebas diagnósticas, con 550 trabajadores, para validar el nuevo método de detección precoz frente a una prueba de referencia. Las variables antropométricas analizadas fueron: presión arterial, índice de masa corporal, perímetro abdominal, índice cinturaaltura, porcentaje de grasa corporal e índice cintura-cadera. Se realizó un análisis de regresión logística multivariante y se obtuvieron curvas ROC para determinar la capacidad predictiva de las variables. El nuevo método para la detección precoz del síndrome metabólico se basa en árboles de decisión creados con metodología CHAID (detección automática de interacciones mediante chi-cuadrado). La prevalencia global de síndrome metabólico fue del 14,9%. El área bajo la curva obtenida para el índice cintura-altura y el perímetro abdominal fue 0,91 y 0,90, respectivamente. Las variables antropométricas asociadas con el síndrome metabólico en el modelo ajustado fueron índice cintura-altura, índice de masa corporal, la presión arterial y el porcentaje de grasa corporal. El árbol de decisión se configuró a partir del índice cinturaaltura (&amp;#8805;0.55) y la hipertensión (presión arterial &amp;#8805;128/85 mmHg), obteniendo una sensibilidad del 91,6% y una especificidad del 95,7%. En conclusión, la detección precoz del síndrome metabólico en una población sana es posible a través de métodos no invasivos, basados en indicadores antropométricos como el índice cintura-altura y la presión arterial. El método propuesto tiene un alto grado de validez predictiva y su uso podría recomendarse en cualquier contexto de la atención sanitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);19(2): 118-120, abr.-jun. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151198</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevo método no invasivo para la detección temprana del síndrome metabólico en la población trabajadora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38802^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53219^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55111^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
