<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87303</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of aortic dissection</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The clinical manifestations of the acute aortic dissection depend on the variations of the sanguineous flow in the sanguineous channel and the extension of the peripheral or central occlusion of the artery. A cross-sectional descriptive study was made using like universe to all the patients withdrawn with the diagnosis of aortic dissection of Dark-brown the Provincial Hospital &#147; Saturnine &#148; of Santiago of Cuba in the period of January of the 2000 to October of the 2005 with the objective to  know the behavior this organization finding like result that the aortic dissection predominated in patients of 58 years, masculine sex and the black race; the average for this disease was of 21 days, the personal antecedent of arterial hypertension  was found in a great percentage of the cases; the predominant symptoms and signs were the thoracic pain, and own of the arterial hypertension and the aortic insufficiency, the methods diagnoses but used were transesophageal echocardiography,  the abdominal ultrasound, the aortography and the computed tomography, the more frequent aortic dissections were acute and the type I and II that begins in the ascending aorta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez de la Guardia, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagaró del Campo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Limonta, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las manifestaciones clínicas de la disección aórtica aguda dependen de las variaciones del flujo sanguíneo en el canal sanguíneo y la extensión de la oclusión periférica o central de la arteria. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo transversal empleando como universo a todos los pacientes egresados con el diagnóstico de disección aórtica del Hospital Provincial &#147;Saturnino Lora&#148; de Santiago de Cuba en el periodo de enero del 2000 a octubre del 2005 con el objetivo de conocer el comportamiento de esta entidad hallando como resultado que la disección aórtica predominó en pacientes de 58 años, del sexo masculino  y la raza negra ; la estadía promedio para esta enfermedad fue de 21 días, el antecedente personal de hipertensión arterial fue encontrado en un gran porcentaje de los casos; los síntomas y signos predominantes fueron el dolor torácico, y los propios de la hipertensión arterial y la insuficiencia aórtica, los métodos diagnósticos mas empleados fueron el ecocardiograma transtorácico, el ultrasonido abdominal, la aortografía y la tomografía axial computarizada, las disecciones aórticas más  frecuentes fueron agudas y los tipo I y II que comienzan en la aorta ascendente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;10(4): 222-226, oct.-dic. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87303</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comportameinto de la disección aórtica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1023^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d795^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
