<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136847</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of smoking cessation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The benefits of smoking cessation are particularly relevants in terms of mortality reduction and enlargement of life expectancy for any age group and for both sexes. CHD and cerebrovascular morbidity and mortality benefit from giving up smoking as well as the complications rate of coronary surgery. The incidence of COPD clearly decrease after smoking cessation and the drop of age-related respiratory function move closer to the non smoker one. Lung cancer incidence is the most clearly influenced by the abstinence. Specially important is the benefit for the fetus of the pregnant woman who give up smoking during the first three months. The main goal is smoking cessation, but even partial reductions in smoking habit entail harm and risk reduction. In any case, the benefits of smoking cessation overcome the transitories withdrawal syndromerelated troubles and incoveniences (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardell, Helios</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saltó, Esteve</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Abandonar el hábito tabáquico comporta beneficios en términos de reducción de la mortalidad y aumento de la expectativa de vida, para cualquier grupo de edad y para ambos sexos. Tanto la morbi-mortalidad coronaria como la cerebrovascular se benefician de la cesación, así como la tasa de complicaciones postcirugía coronaria. La morbi-mortalidad por EPOC también disminuye en el ex-fumador y el declive de la función respiratoria con la edad se acerca a la del no fumador. De todos los cánceres, el de pulmón es el que más se beneficia del abandono del hábito. Especialmente importante es el beneficio para el feto de la embarazada fumadora que deja de fumar durante del primer trimestre del embarazo. Y, aunque el objetivo siempre es el de la cesación completa, hay que señalar que reducciones parciales del consumo de cigarrillos también se acompañan de una disminución de riesgo. En todos los casos, los beneficios son sensiblemente superiores a los inconvenientes de la cesación (síndrome de abstinencia), que son de carácter transitorio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);16(supl.2): 131-142, 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136847</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios de dejar de fumar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
