<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106887</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The experience of the dependence to a psychoactive drug in a consumer drug</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Qualitative, phenomenological research following Schutz, referential sociological, whose objective is to know the experience of the phenomenon of dependence or addiction to a consumer of drugs in treatment in an open centre, based on the following questions guide path: How do you start drug experience? What were the reasons for drug use? You how is it installing dependence to them? How gave account which had become dependent drug? The speech of consumers identified seven categories Schutz, referential, that showing significant aspects of the experience. To analyze them lived type drugs featuring addiction and understanding of the existential reasons that influenced the installation of this dependency, deepening the understanding of the phenomenon, thereby granting consumer could understand better c (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Basso Musso, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Investigación cualitativa, de trayectoria fenomenológica, siguiendo el referencial sociológico de Schutz, cuyo objetivo es conocer la vivencia del fenómeno de la dependencia o adicción, en un consumidor de drogas psicoactivas en tratamiento en un Centro Abierto, teniendo como base las siguientes preguntas orientadoras: ¿Cómo se inició la experiencia de consumo de drogas? ¿Cuáles fueron los motivos para consumir drogas? ¿Cómo se va instalando la dependencia a ellas? ¿Cómo se dio cuenta que se había hecho dependiente a la droga? En el discurso de los consumidores se identificaron siete categorías del referencial de Shutz, que muestran aspectos significativos de la vivencia. Al analizarlas se pudo comprender al tipo vivido del consumidor de drogas psicoactivas que presenta adicción y el entendimiento de los motivos existenciales que influyeron en la instalación de esta dependencia, profundizándose así el conocimiento del fenómeno, lo que permitirá otorgarles un mejor cuidado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;20(1/2): 61-65, ene.-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106887</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La vivencia de la dependencia en un consumidor de drogas psicoactivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54297</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
