<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138956</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnosis of acute follicular conjunctivitis: A 5-year retrospective analysis in a referral center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective and methods:  A retrospective analysis was performed using the medical records in a referral center in Mexico over a period of 5 years, in order to determine the frequency of acute follicular conjunctivitis. Results and conclusions: A total of 859,986 ophthalmology consultations were given, from which 8,930 were diagnosed with acute follicular conjunctivitis (1.03% of the total). The number of patients diagnosed range between 100 and 200 in the majority of months. In August 2012 an increase was observed with 308 cases, and then decreasing after two months. This study did not demonstrate a highest frequency by month, with exception of year 2012 that showed a peak incidence in the third trimester (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nuñez-Rivera, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serna-Ojeda, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quevedo-Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo y métodos: Para determinar la frecuencia de la conjuntivitis folicular aguda, se analizó de manera retrospectiva los expedientes médicos en un centro de referencia en México durante un periodo de 5 años. Resultados y conclusiones: Un total de 859.986 consultas oftalmológicas fueron otorgadas, de las cuales 8.930 fueron diagnosticadas con conjuntivitis folicular aguda (1,03% del total). En la mayoría de los meses hubo un rango entre 100 y 200 pacientes. En agosto de 2012 se observó un aumento con 308 casos, disminuyendo después de 2 meses. Nuestro estudio no demostró una mayor frecuencia por mes, con excepción del año 2012 que presentó un pico en la incidencia durante el tercer trimestre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;90(8): 389-391, ago. 2015. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138956</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico de conjuntivitis folicular aguda: un análisis retrospectivo de 5 años en un centro de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d265^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28288^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3255^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27971^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27872^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d265^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
