<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051091</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Drug consumption during adolescence is an important health problem due to the beginningin early ages, the high consumption of tobacco and alcohol, and the progressive increaseof other drugs as cocaine and cannabis; also because of the physical, psychological,emotional and social consequences for the young person and his future. Adolescence is adynamic process of great vulnerability and risks. It is important to remember the dangerousbehaviours to which young people expose themselves, as well as the risk and protection factors; drug consumption is a complex and multifactorial process. The best treatmentagainst substance abuse is the prevention, to be done at the office during the periodic healthexaminations and also acting in several environments of the young people: family,school and society in general. Paediatricians have a strategic position to act. This article reviewsthe scientific evidences and the force of the recommendation on the preventive activitiesto avoid the use and abuse of substances during childhood and adolescence. Most ofthe preventive activities during adolescence have not demonstrated any effectiveness, beingat the present time under revision. The preventive programs held at schools have demonstratedtheir effectiveness to improve the knowledge about tobacco, alcohol and drugs andeven for developing negative attitudes towards the substance use; but they do not have hadany influence on the decrease of drug consumption</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Vicario, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montón Álvarez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de drogas en la adolescencia representa un problema de salud pública, debidoa su inicio en edades precoces, el importante consumo de tabaco y alcohol, el progresivoaumento de otras como cocaína y cannabis, así como por las consecuencias físicas, psicológicas,emocionales y sociales para el joven y su futuro.La adolescencia es un proceso dinámico de gran vulnerabilidad y riesgos. Es importantetener presentes los comportamientos arriesgados a los que se exponen los jóvenes, asícomo los factores de riesgo y protección, ya que el consumo de drogas es un proceso complejoy multifactorial.El mejor tratamiento del abuso de substancias es la prevención, que se realizará en laconsulta durante los exámenes periódicos de salud, y trabajando en los diferentes ambientesdonde se mueve el joven: familia, escuela y sociedad en general. El pediatra ocupa unaposición estratégica para actuar.En este artículo se han revisado las evidencias científicas y la fuerza de la recomendaciónsobre las actividades preventivas que hay que realizar para evitar el uso y abuso de lassubstancias en la infancia y adolescencia. La mayoría de estas actividades no han demostradosu efectividad y están en la actualidad en revisión. Los programas preventivos en laescuela han demostrado efectividad para aumentar los conocimientos sobre tabaco, alcoholy drogas, además de favorecer actitudes negativas hacia el uso de substancias; pero nohan tenido efecto sobre la disminución del consumo de éstas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;8(supl.7): 113-127, jul.-sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051091</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evidencias y medidas preventivas en el abuso de sustancias durante la adolescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24887^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
