<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67196</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-4723</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: 1. To characterize travelling people fulfilling the mandatory islamic obligation to visit the holy places in Saudi Arabia (Hajj or Umra) and, 2. To determine the risk of travel compared with a travelling immigrant to native country cohort. Method: Data recorded from travellers consulting to carryout some kind of pilgrimage to Saudi Arabia (group H)from 06/99 to 01/03 are analyzed and they were compared with a group of travelling immigrants during the same period (group IV).Results: In the group H 23 travellers were identified, of whom they were immigrants 15 (65.2%) and Spanish 8(34.8%). They carried out Umra 13 (56.5%) and Hajj10 (43.5%). They resided during periods &gt; 2 years in Europe 19 (82.6%; IC 95%: 67.3-97.9) and they visited further countries 7 (30.4%). There where not significant differences between groups H and IV concerning lenght of journey and number of considered risk travels. Travellers from group IV consulted most frequently in periods &lt; 15days prior to the journey (p&lt;0.001), which suggests the existence of better planning and knowledge about pretravel preventive measures among group H. Any health problem abroad was recorded in 8.6% of group H and23.1% of group IV. Conclusions: A substantial part of islamic pilgrims have yet a spanish-native origin. Travelling pilgrims displayed risk factors to develop health problems in a similar proportion to which display the immigrants who visit their native countries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Urbiztondo, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valerio, Lluís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Octavi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Isnard, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: 1. Caracterizar a los viajeros que se desplazan a Arabia Saudita con motivo de la peregrinación a los lugares santos islámicos (Hajj o Umra) y, 2. Determinar el riesgo del viaje en relación a una cohorte de inmigrantes viajeros a sus países de origen. Población y método: Se analizan datos procedentes de peregrinos (grupo H) durante el periodo 06/99-01/03 y se comparan con un grupo de inmigrantes viajeros consultantes durante el mismo periodo (grupo IV).Resultados: En el grupo H fueron identificados 23 viajeros-inmigrantes 15 (65,2%) y españoles 8 (34,8%)- .Tomaron parte en la Umra 13 (56,5%) y en el Hajj 10(43,5%). Habían residido por periodos &gt; 2 años en Europa 19 (82,6%; IC95%: 67,3-97,9) y visitaron otro país 7 (30,4%). No se hallaron diferencias significativas entre los grupos H e IV en cuanto a días de duración del viaje y nº de viajes de riesgo. Los viajeros del grupo IV consultaron con mayor frecuencia en periodos &lt; 15 días previos a la partida (p&lt;0,001), lo que ello sugiere la existencia de mayor planificación y conocimiento de actividades preventivas del grupo H. Presentaron algún problema de salud el 8,6% del los viajeros del grupo H y el 23,1% del grupo IV. Conclusiones: Una parte sustancial de los peregrinos es de origen autóctono. Los peregrinos presentaron factores de riesgo para el desarrollo de problemas de salud en una proporción similar a la que presentan los inmigrantes que visitan sus países de origen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. emerg;7(2): 120-124, abr.-jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67196</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14587</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12911^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
