<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151403</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Administrative prevalence of insomnia and associated clinical features in patients with addiction during active substance use</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. A bidirectional relation between substance use and insomnia has been described, although there are few studies examining insomnia in the population of people with addiction. The aim of this study was to describe the prevalence of insomnia during active substance use in patients with addiction and its associated clinical features. Patients and Methods. Descriptive study in patients diagnosed with substance dependence disorder admitted to a Hospital Detoxification Unit. The existence of insomnia prior to admission was assessed using the Oviedo Sleep Questionnaire (OSQ). Demographic variables, consumptionrelated clinical variables, and diagnostic variables were collected and the SCID-I and -II (Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV) and CAADID (Conners&#146; Adult ADHD Diagnostic Interview for DSM-IV) were administered to evaluate the psychiatric diagnoses. Bivariate and multivariate analyses were made of the data. Results. 481 patients (72.6% men, age 40.6±10.1 years) were enrolled. 64.3% of the patients reported insomnia during active substance use. The most common type of insomnia was fragmented nocturnal sleep (49.9%). The factors significantly associated with insomnia were polysubstance drug use, medical comorbidities (most notably, infectious diseases), anxiety disorder, personality disorder (particularly cluster C), a greater number of previous admissions for detoxication, and early age at onset of substance use. Conclusions. Insomnia is highly prevalent in patients with addiction during active use of the substance. Fragmented nocturnal sleep was the most common type of insomnia. Patients with addiction and comorbid anxiety disorder, medical comorbidity, and early onset of dependence were more likely to experience insomnia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grau López, Lara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Daigre, Constanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Egido, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roncero, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez Cintas, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau López, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se ha descrito una relación bidireccional entre el uso de sustancias y el insomnio, aunque existen escasos estudios sobre el insomnio en la población adicta. El objetivo es describir la prevalencia de insomnio durante el consumo activo de las sustancias en pacientes adictos y sus características clínicas asociadas. Pacientes y Metodología. Estudio descriptivo en pacientes diagnosticados de trastorno por dependencia de sustancias que ingresaron en una Unidad Hospitalaria de Desintoxicación. Se evaluó el insomnio previo al ingreso mediante el Cuestionario de Oviedo de Calidad del Sueño (COS). Se recogieron variables demográficas, clínicas referidas al consumo y diagnósticas y se realizaron las entrevistas SCID-I y II y CAADID para evaluar los diagnósticos psiquiátricos. Se realizó un análisis bivariante y multivariante de los datos. Resultados. Se incluyeron 481 pacientes (72,6% varones, edad 40,6±10,1 años). El 64,3% de los pacientes refirieron insomnio durante el consumo activo de la sustancia. El tipo de insomnio más frecuente fue el sueño nocturno fragmentado (49,9%). Los factores relacionados significativamente con el insomnio fueron policonsumidores, comorbilidad médica (destacando enfermedades infecciosas), trastorno de ansiedad, trastorno de personalidad (destacando cluster C), mayor número de ingresos de desintoxicación previos y edad de inicio del consumo más temprana. Conclusiones. El insomnio es muy prevalente en pacientes adictos durante el consumo activo de la sustancia. El sueño nocturno fragmentado es el tipo de insomnio más frecuente. Los pacientes adictos con trastorno de ansiedad comórbido, comorbilidad médica e inicio precoz de la dependencia tienen mayor probabilidad de presentar insomnio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;44(2): 64-71, mar.-abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151403</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia administrativa del insomnio en pacientes adictos durante el consumo activo de las sustancias y características clínicas asociadas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53387^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23312</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7493^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
