<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158923</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pneumonia and acute glomerulonephritis in the childhood, an unusual association?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Different pathogens are involved in the develop­ment of acute glomerulonephritis; the association between bacterial pneumonia and acute glomerulonephritis has been rarely reported. Patients and methods: Retrospective study of patients admitted to our hospital from 2005 to 2015 with an acute glomerulonephritis and pneumonia diagnosis, excluding those who had in the previous month either streptococcal pharyngeal infection, skin infection or pneumonia. Results: 3 patients had pneumonia and glomerulonephritis. Pneumonias were lobar and suggestive of bacterial infection. The clinical manifestations of glomerulonephritis and pneumonia were simultaneous. The ASO was high and C3 was low in all patients. A patient presented a bacteremia by Streptococcus pneumoniae and another one, positive urine pneumococcal antigen. All patients developed an acute nephritic syndrome. Its treatment was conservative; the evolution was excellent in all cases. C3 reached a normal value in all of them. The average hospitalization days were 8. Conclusions: Our study provides new evidences about the association between pneumonia and acute glomerulonephritis. It stands out that glomerulonephritis and the infectious process are simultaneous. ASO could not be specific for Streptococcus pyogenes infection, or perhaps these patients had an APSGN oligosymptomatic that was worsened by pneumococcal infection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Penela Vélez de Guevara, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zafra Anta, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Vao-Bel, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Alacio, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballesteros García, MM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grasa Lozano, CD</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En el desarrollo de la glomerulonefritis aguda están implicados diferentes patógenos; se ha descrito con poca frecuencia la asociación entre neumonía bacteriana y glomerulonefritis aguda. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de los pacientes ingresados en nuestro hospital entre los años 2005 y 2015 con diagnóstico de glomerulonefritis aguda y neumonía; se excluyeron los que presentaron faringoamigdalitis estreptocócica, infección cutánea o neumonía en el mes previo. Resultados: Tres pacientes presentaron neumonía y glomerulonefritis. Las neumonías fueron lobares e indicativas de infección bacteriana. Las manifestaciones clínicas de glomerulonefritis fueron simultáneas al diagnóstico de neumonía. Los anticuerpos antiestreptolisina (ASLO) se encontraban aumentados en todos los pacientes, y el componente sérico C3 era bajo. Un paciente presentó una bacteriemia por Streptococcus pneumoniae serotipo 33, y otro un antígeno positivo de neumococo en orina. Todos los pacientes desarrollaron un síndrome nefrítico agudo. Se llevó a cabo un tratamiento conservador, con una evolución excelente en todos los casos. El complemento se normalizó en todos ellos. El tiempo medio de ingreso fue de 8 días. Conclusiones: Este estudio aporta nuevas evidencias sobre la asociación entre neumonía y glomerulonefritis aguda. Destaca que la glomerulonefritis es simultánea al cuadro infeccioso. Los ASLO pueden no ser específicos de infección por Streptococcus pyogenes, o bien estos pacientes habían presentado una glomerulonefritis aguda postestreptocócica poco sintomática que se agravó debido a la infección neumocócica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;74(11): e239-e242, dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158923</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neumonía y glomerulonefritis aguda en la infancia. ¿Una asociación infrecuente?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6065^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13683^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
