<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149049</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Syndromic  autism I: general aspects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and development. The diagnosis of autism is based on the identification of certain behavioural criteria, but there is no biological test that allows us to diagnose the disorder. Yet, a considerable number of cases of autism, estimated to be somewhere between 11 and 37%, are linked to specific syndromes that can be identified according to their clinical characteristics, or by means of some biological marker. These cases are known as syndromic autism or &#145;double syndromes&#146;. There is a relation between autism and certain genetic and metabolic diseases, epilepsy, infections of the nervous system, intrauterine exposure to certain substances and perinatal pathologies. Conclusions. The aim of this review is to guide the professional in the diagnosis of autistic children in order to rationalise the process by ruling out any underlying disease or syndrome related to the autistic condition. At the same time, we stress aetiological aspects of these syndromes, which make it easier to understand the biological bases of autism (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Artigas Pallarés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gabau Vila, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guitart Feliubadaló, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y desarrollo. El diagnóstico de autismo se basa en la identificación de determinados criterios conductuales. No existe ninguna prueba biológica que permita diagnosticar el autismo. Sin embargo, un número considerable de casos de autismo, estimado entre el 11 y 37 %, está asociado a síndromes específicos, que pueden ser identificado en base a las características clínicas, o mediante algún marcador biológico. Estos casos se conocen como autismo sindrómico o &#145;síndromes dobles&#146;. Existe una relación entre el autismo y ciertas enfermedades genéticas, metabólicas, epilepsia, infecciones del sistema nervioso, exposición intrauterina a determinadas sustancias y patología perinatal. Conclusiones. Con esta revisión se pretende orientar al profesional que diagnostica niños autistas, con el fin de racionalizar el proceso dirigido a descartar cualquier enfermedad o síndrome subyacente relacionado con el cuadro autista. Al mismo tiempo, se hace énfasis en aspectos etioló- gicos de estos síndromes, que facilitan la comprensión de las bases biológicas del autismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;40(supl.1): s143-s150, 15 ene. 2005. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149049</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El autismo sindrómico: I. Aspectos generales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
