<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150565</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish consensus for the management of patients with advanced radioactive iodine refractory differentiated thyroid cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Approximately one third of the patients with differentiated thyroid cancer (DTC) who develop structurally-evident metastatic disease are refractory to radioactive iodine (RAI). Most deaths from thyroid cancer occur in these patients. The main objective of this consensus is to address the most controversial aspects of management of these patients. Methods: On behalf of the Spanish Society of Endocrinology &amp; Nutrition (SEEN) and the Spanish Group for Orphan and Infrequent Tumors (GETHI), the Spanish Task Force for Thyroid Cancer, consisting of endocrinologists and oncologists, reviewed the relevant literature and prepared a series of clinically relevant questions related to management of advanced RAI-refractory DTC. Results: Ten clinically relevant questions were identified by the task force. In answering to these 10 questions, the task force included recommendations regarding the best definition of refractoriness; the best therapeutic options including watchful waiting, local therapies, and systemic therapy (e.g. kinase inhibitors), when sodium iodide symporter (NIS) restoration may be expected; and how recent advances in molecular biology have increased our understanding of the disease. Conclusions: In response to our appointment as a task force by the SEEN and GHETI, we developed a consensus to help in clinical management of patients with advanced RAI-refractory DTC. We think that this consensus will provide helpful and current recommendations that will help patients with this disorder to get optimal medical care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Fonseca, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galofré, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zafón Llopis, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capdevila, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría Sandi, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón y Cajal Asensio, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro González, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riesco-Eizaguirre, Garcilaso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sáez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Alrededor de un tercio de los pacientes con cáncer diferenciado de tiroides (CDT) que desarrollan enfermedad metastásica estructural son refractarios al yodo radiactivo. Desafortunadamente, la mayoría de las muertes debidas al cáncer de tiroides ocurren en pacientes con CDT avanzado refractario al yodo radiactivo. El principal objetivo de este consenso es abordar los aspectos más controvertidos del manejo de estos pacientes. Métodos: En nombre de la Sociedad Española de Endocrinología y Nutrición (SEEN) y del Grupo Español de Tumores Raros e Infrecuentes (GETHI), el grupo de trabajo para el Cáncer de Tiroides, compuesto por endocrinólogos y oncólogos, revisó la literatura más destacada y desarrolló una serie de preguntas clínicamente relevantes concernientes al manejo de los pacientes con CDT refractario. Resultados: Diez preguntas clínicamente relevantes fueron identificadas por el grupo de trabajo. En las respuestas el grupo incluyó recomendaciones sobre la mejor definición de la refractariedad, las mejores opciones terapéuticas, entre las cuales se incluyen la actitud expectante, las terapias locales y la terapia sistémica (por ejemplo inhibidores de tirosín-cinasa), cuándo esperar la recaptación de yodo radiactivo mediada por NIS y cómo los recientes avances en genética molecular han ayudado a comprender mejor la enfermedad. Conclusión: En respuesta a nuestro compromiso como grupo de trabajo de la SEEN y GETHI hemos creado un consenso para asistir al manejo clínico de los pacientes con CDT avanzado refractario al yodo radiactivo. Pensamos que este consenso proporcionará unas recomendaciones útiles y actualizadas que ayuden a los pacientes con esta enfermedad a tener un cuidado óptimo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;63(4): e17-e24, abr. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150565</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consenso español sobre el tratamiento de los pacientes con cáncer de tiroides diferenciado avanzado resistente al yodo radiactivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
