<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044965</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recombinant activated factor VII in the postanesthetic recovery unit: review of 16 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe a series of 16 cases in which recombinantactivated factor VII (rFVIIa) was used in our postanestheticrecovery unit.The mean age of the patients was 53.5 years (range, 30-84 years). Eleven were men and 5 women. The mean doseof rFVIIa used was 75 µg·kg-1 (range, 60-90 µg·kg-1) and25% of the patients needed a second dose. All the patientshad postoperative bleeding, 62.5% after general surgery,25% after a liver transplant, and 12.5% after a lung transplant.rFVIIa therapy was effective in 66% of the patients andno adverse thrombotic events related to treatment wereobserved.rFVIIa can be an efficacious therapeutic option for bleedingand coagulation disorders that are refractory to conventionalreplacement therapy. Approval to use rFVIIa inthis setting and the establishment of indications should bebased on further research</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pita Zapata, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Etxániz Álvarez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pose Cambeiro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duro Tacón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rama Maceiras, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Describimos una serie de 16 pacientes en los que seutilizó el factor VII recombinante activado (rFVIIa) ennuestro Servicio de Reanimación.La media de edad fue de 53,5 años (30-84), 11 varonesy 5 mujeres. La dosis media de rFVIIa utilizada fue de75 µg kg-1 (60-90 µg kg-1) precisando repetir la dosis en el25% de los casos. Todos los pacientes padecían complicacioneshemorrágicas postoperatorias, el 62,5% trascirugía general, el 25% tras trasplante hepático y el12,5% tras trasplante pulmonar.En el 66% de los enfermos, el factor fue efectivo y nohubo episodios trombóticos clínicos secundarios al tratamiento.El rFVIIa puede ser un arma terapéutica efectiva enhemorragias con coagulopatía refractarias al tratamientosustitutivo habitual. La aprobación para su uso eneste contexto así como la determinación de sus indicacionesprecisa de más estudios de investigación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;53(3): 159-162, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044965</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización del rFVIIa en una Unidad de Reanimación. Revisión de 16 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22171^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22171^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22171^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32645^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4403</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6626^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6626^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29477</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
