<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040901</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endoscopic treatment of Zenker&#146;s diverticulum</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We report our experience in the endoscopic (flexible) treatment of Zenker's diverticulum.   Patients and method. Three patients with medium-sized Zenker's diverticula were treated by endoscopic cricopharyngeal myotomy with a modified needle-knife sphincterotome through a therapeutic gastroscope. The procedure was performed in the digestive endoscopy unit under conscious sedation without anesthetic support. Result. Endoscopic cricopharyngeal myotomy was completed in a single session without immediate or late complications. In all three patients dysphagia disappeared and all were discharged at 48 hours with a solid diet. After 12, 18 and 17 months of follow-up there has been no recurrence of dysphagia or other symptoms attributable to Zenker's diverticulum.  Conclusion. Flexible endoscopic cricopharyngeal myotomy is a simple, effective and safe treatment of Zenker's diverticulum that avoids the need for open cervical surgery and general anesthesia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Arellano, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Lama, Yago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morena, Emilio de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño, Ramiro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás, Esperanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Presentamos nuestra experiencia en el tratamiento endoscópico del divertículo de Zenker.  Pacientes y método. Tres pacientes con divertículos de Zenker de tamaño medio fueron sometidos a una cricofaringomiotomía endoscópica realizada con un esfinterotomo de aguja modificado a través de un gastroscopio terapéutico. El procedimiento se realizó en la unidad de endoscopia digestiva bajo sedación consciente sin apoyo anestésico. Resultado. La cricofaringomiotomía endoscópica se completó en una única sesión sin complicaciones inmediatas ni tardías. En los 3 pacientes desapareció completamente la disfagia y todos fueron dados de alta a las 48 h con indicación de dieta sólida. Tras 12, 18 y 17 meses de seguimiento no ha reaparecido la disfagia ni otros síntomas atribuibles al divertículo de Zenker.   Conclusión. La cricofaringomiotomía mediante endoscopio flexible es un tratamiento simple, eficaz y seguro del divertículo de Zenker que ahorra la cirugía abierta cervical y la anestesia general (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);78(4): 256-259, oct. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040901</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento endoscópico del divertículo de Zenker</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10803^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23977^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29740^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10803^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29740^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10803^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29740^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
