<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-103925</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Distal femoral bypass under local anaesthesia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The aim of this article is to present our experience in performing distal femoralby pass under local anaesthesia for high risk patients. Material and methods: Lower limb revascularisation surgery under local anaesthesia was performed on 8 patients in our centre between January and May 2010. The common characteristics of the patients were, advanced age, chronic is chaemic heart disease on antiplatelet treatment, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Results: All 8 patients (100%) tolerated the procedure well without having to resort to sedation or invasive an aesthetic procedures. The receiving artery was the posterior tibialin 6 cases (75%) and the popliteal and peroneal in 1 (12%). Early patency of the graft was achieved 7 patients and 1 had early thrombosis with a supracondylar amputation. The technique used was femoral-popliteal in 1 case, femoral-posterior tibial in 6 cases, and popliteal-peroneal in 1 case. The saphenous vein was the graft used, inverted in 1 patient(12%), and in situ in 7 (88%) with a 3 mm BARDTM valvotomy. There were no post-operative complications as regards haemorrhage, infections or death. A minor amputation was performed on 3 patients (37%), and after a mean of 3 months (1-4 months) follow-up,7 cases were free of major amputation. Conclusions: Revascularisation of the distal zone of the lower limbs can be safely and effectively performed using local anaesthesia, avoiding the risks of general anaesthesia and without the need to stop antiplatelet treatment. Anatomical problems (obesity) may limit the procedure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Taboada Martín, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cassinello Martínez, Norberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez García, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Glenn-Ray López, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo de este trabajo es transmitir nuestra experiencia en by pass arterial femorodistal bajo anestesia local para pacientes de alto riesgo. Material y métodos De enero a mayo de 2010 hasta 8 pacientes han sido intervenidos en nuestro centro de cirugía de revascularización en miembros inferiores bajo anestesia local. Las características comunes de los pacientes eran la edad avanzada, cardiopatía isquémica crónica en tratamiento con antiagregantes plaquetarios y la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC).Resultados Los 8 pacientes (100%) toleraron de forma adecuada el procedimiento sin recurrir a sedación ni a procedimientos anestésicos invasivos. La arteria receptora fue la tibial posterior en 6 de ellos (75%) y la poplítea y peronea en uno (12%). En 7 casos logramos permeabilidad precoz del injerto y uno presentó trombosis precoz con amputación supracondílea; la técnica empleada fue femoropoplíteo en un caso, femorotibial posterior en 6 casos y poplíteo-peroneo en otro. El injerto utilizado fue la vena safena mayor, invertida en un paciente (12%) e in situ en 7 (88%) con valvulotomo BARD&#153;, 3mm. Las complicaciones postoperatorias fueron del 0% para hemorragia, infección y muerte; en 3 pacientes (37%) amputación menor y, tras un periodo de seguimiento medio de 3 meses (1-4 meses), 7 casos están libres de amputación mayor. Conclusiones La revascularización del territorio distal de los miembros inferiores puede llevarse a cabo mediante anestesia local de forma segura y eficaz, sin necesidad de retirar antiagregantes ni asumir los riesgos de la anestesia general. La anatomía desfavorable (obesidad) puede limitar el procedimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);90(7): 460-464, ago.-sept. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-103925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">By pass arterial femorodistal bajo anestesia local</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d783^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23162^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12878^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23812^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
