<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041889</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Democratisation of the relationship between nurse/citizen: the informed consent</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">From the beginning of time, the people (population) and those individuals who have been responsiblefor healthcare have established some relations that, in general, have been vertical indifferent degrees, according to the historical evolution and different professions. With the recognitionof human rights and the democratisation of social relations, this trend is also startingto have an effect among healthcare professionals and the users. It is collected in the bioethicalprinciple of autonomy and reflected in the informed consent.&#149; Nursing professionals, given the role that they have assumed now, must re-examine their relationshipwith the users and the process of information that the users need in order to reachwell informed and free decisions regarding their health</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oltra Rodríguez, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riestra Rodríguez, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde el principio de los tiempos, la población y las figuras que se han encargado de los cuidadosde su salud han establecido unas relaciones que en general han sido verticales en distintosgrados, según la evolución histórica y las distintas profesiones. Con el reconocimientode los derechos de las personas y la democratización de las relaciones sociales, esta corrientetambién comienza a calar entre los profesionales de la salud y los usuarios, es recogida en elprincipio bioético de la autonomía y plasmada en el consentimiento informado.&#149; Los profesionales de Enfermería, dado el rol que asumen en la actualidad, deben replantearsesu relación con los usuarios y con el proceso de información que estos precisan para tomar decisioneslibres sobre su salud</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;8(6): 67-71, jul. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041889</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La democratización de las relaciones enfermera/ciudadano: el consentimiento informado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
