<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65779</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of pulmonary thromboembolism in a young patient triggered by a long haul travel, in which a homocygotic mutation in the gene of the metilentetrahidrofolate reductase was demonstrated. This mutation can cause hyperhomocysteinemia that is a recognized risk factor for venous thromboembolism (VTE). In the management of these patients, the levels of homocysteine should be lowered, as well as use of thromboprophylaxis before transitory risk situations. It is important to know when the screening should be performed, because they are behind an important number of cases of VTE</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llombart-Cantó, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Senen-Español, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho-Chust, J. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chiner-Vives, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mediero-Carrasco, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luz Andreu-Rodríguez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de tromboembolismo pulmonar en paciente joven desencadenada por un viaje de larga duración, en el que se demostró una mutación homocigota en el gen de la metilentetrahidrofolato reductasa. Esta mutación puede provocar una hiperhomocisteinemia, que es un factor de riesgo conocido para enfermedad tromboembólica venosa (ETV). En el manejo de estos pacientes se deben descender los niveles de homocisteína, así como realizar profilaxis tromboembólica ante situaciones de riesgo transitorias. Es importante conocer cuándo debe ser realizado su screening, ya que se encuentran detrás de un importante número de casos de ETV</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;25(4): 183-186, abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65779</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33361^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27886^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27886^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12092^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
