<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128981</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Transparotid approach for the open reduction of subcondylar fractures. Surgical technique and analysis of complications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Several options exist for the treatment of subcondylar jaw fractures. The anterior transparotid approach is one of the therapeutic options for open reduction and internal fixation. The aim of this communication was to describe the surgical technique and analyze the related complications. Patients and methods: A clinical review was made of 31 patients with 34 subcondylar fractures, all treated surgically via an anterior transparotid approach using osteosynthesis plates and screws. Results: No complications occurred in 22 of 31 patients (70.97%) and the postoperative occlusion was good in 28 patients (90.32%). The complications related with the approach in our case series were: 2 cases of facial paresia (5.88%), both mild and transitory; 6 cases of salivary fistulae (17.65%), all self-limited; and 3 surgical wound infections (8.82%), 2 resolved with antibiotics and one with antibiotics and surgical drainage. Plate fracture, a complication unrelated to the approach but related to the type of osteosynthesis, occurred in 2 cases (5.88%). Conclusions: The anterior transparotid approach is safe, with a low risk of facial nerve injury. The technique gives the surgeon an adequate surgical field that allows the placement and easy fixation of a second osteosynthesis plate in the anterior part of the fracture. The resulting scar is cosmetically acceptable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montalvo Moreno, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jubilla, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Díaz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zubillaga Rodríguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Aniceto, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Flores, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existen varias opciones para el tratamiento de las fracturas subcondíleas. El abordaje transparotídeo anterior es una de las posibilidades terapéuticas para su reducción abierta y su fijación interna. El objetivo de este artículo es realizar una descripción de la técnica quirúrgica y analizar las complicaciones asociadas. Material y métodos: Se realizó una revisión clínica sobre un total de 31 pacientes con 34 fracturas subcondíleas, todas ellas tratadas quirúrgicamente con un abordaje transparotídeo anterior, usando placas y tornillos de osteosíntesis. Resultados: No se registraron complicaciones de ningún tipo en 22 de los 31 pacientes (70,97%), con buena oclusión posquirúrgica en 28 de ellos (90,32%). Las complicaciones relacionadas con el abordaje en nuestra serie de casos fueron las siguientes: 2 casos de paresia facial (5,88%), que en ambos fue leve y transitoria; 6 casos de fístula salival (17,65%), siendo en todos ellos autolimitadas, y 3 infecciones de la herida quirúrgica (8,82%): 2 resueltas con antibióticos y una que requirió también drenaje quirúrgico. Como complicación no relacionada con el tipo de abordaje sino con el tipo de osteosíntesis, hubo 2 casos de fractura de placa de osteosíntesis (5,88%). Conclusiones: El abordaje transparotídeo anterior es seguro, con un bajo riesgo lesivo para el nervio facial. Esta técnica proporciona un adecuado campo quirúrgico que permite la colocación y la fácil fijación de una segunda placa de osteosíntesis en la parte anterior de la fractura. La cicatriz resultante es estética(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;33(1): 9-14, ene.-mar. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128981</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje transparotídeo para la reducción abierta de las fracturas subcondíleas. Técnica quirúrgica y análisis de sus complicaciones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6545^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6545^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13896^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
