<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119085</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk of violence and psychopathy in different typologies of delinquency: an empirical study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study focuses on the identification of various criminal typologies through a number of socio-demographic, criminal and recidivism risk variables in a prison sample of the Region of Madrid. The results obtained with 138 participants, assessed with the Violence Risk Appraisal Guide (VRAG) showed significant differences in the risk factors of violence according to the criminal typologies identified previously. Particularly, the severity of the victim&#146;s damage, together with antisocial and deviant behaviors (PCL-R, factor 2), were associated significantly with the first criminal typology, while non-violent offenses and an older age in the commission of crime were predictors for the second typology. These results show the relevance and usefulness of the offender typologies&#146; analysis to assess specifically the risk of violence in the prediction, risk management and intervention in prison settings</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Andreu Rdríguez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Fernández, María Elena de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graña Gómez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio se centra en la identificación de varias tipologías delictivas a través de una serie de variables sociodemográficas, delictivas y de riesgo de reincidencia en una muestra penitenciaria de la Comunidad de Madrid. Los resultados obtenidos con 138 participantes, evaluados con la &#147;Guía de valoración del riesgo de violencia&#148; (VRG), muestran diferencias estadísticamente significativas en los factores de riesgo de violencia analizados en cada una de las dos tipologías delictivas identificadas previamente. En concreto, la mayor gravedad de la lesión producida en la víctima conjuntamente con las conductas antisociales y desviadas (factor 2 de la PCL-R) fueron los factores predictores más asociados a la primera tipología delictiva; mientras que la comisión de delitos no violentos y una mayor edad en la comisión del delito fueron los factores más asociados a la segunda tipología. Estos resultados señalan la importancia y utilidad de establecer diferentes tipologías empíricas de delincuentes para valorar específicamente la capacidad predictiva de los factores de riesgo de violencia de cara a una mayor eficiencia de la valoración, manejo del riesgo delictivo e intervención en contextos penitenciarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;21(2): 289-301, mayo-ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119085</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de violencia y psicopatía en distintas tipologías delictivas: un estudio empírico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3433^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53813^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
