<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84582</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Activities of the fight against echinococcosis-hidatidosis group in Elvas and Alandroal in Portugal</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The activity of the Group for the Control of Echinococcosis-Hydatidosis takes place in Elvas and Alandroal counties, north-east Alentejo, Portugal, an area where the prevalence of parasitism by Echinococcus granulosus is very high. This factor led to the first survey in 1991 and later, in 1998, to the establishment of a multidisciplinary group dedicated to the control of hydatidosis. The group carries out different activities: Surveys in humans (epidemiological questionnaire, blood collection and abdominal ultrasound survey); health education (talks for rural citizens, distribution of information in paper format, individual interviews with the target populations, collection of epidemiological data); close interaction/ collaboration with the Hospital de Santa Luzia de Elvas (serological analysis of collected sera; clinical evaluation of patients and surgery). Eighteen rural population areas were surveyed, representing 7.8% of the population. The activity of this multidisciplinary group aims at developing activity in the definitive host and livestock, having as a main goal the eradication of the parasite(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro Cid, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barros Fontes, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Mira, G. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carola Espiguinha Cortes, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silveira, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los rastreos se desarrollan en un área del nordeste Alentejano donde se registran elevadas incidencias de parasitación por Echinococcus granulosus. Ello condujo al establecimiento del primer programa de rastreo de la hidatidosis en el año 1991 y a la formación del primer Grupo Voluntario Multidisciplinario de Lucha contra la Equinococosis-Hidatidosis en el año 1998. El grupo actúa con diferentes actividades: rastreos (cuestionarios epidemiológicos, extracción de sangre y ecografía abdominal); educación sanitaria (sensibilización e información a las poblaciones rurales, distribución de trípticos; entrevistas individuales con formación sanitaria y de recogida de datos epidemiológicos), y articulación con el Hospital de Santa Luzia de Elvas (consulta de hidatidologia y cirugía). Se han rastreado 18 localidades habiendo alcanzado el 7,8% de la población. El objetivo del grupo es avanzar para el estudio de esta enfermedad en la población animal, y tiene como meta ya no sólo el control sino también la erradicación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;1(3): 100-105, jul.-dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84582</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rastreos del grupo de lucha contra la equinococosis-hidatidosis en los municipios de Elvas y Alandroal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4509^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33983</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
