<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115612</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Semidirect thrust technique for rotation disorder in the atlas with index finger contact</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Due to the large anatomical and functional differences, the study of the craniocervical region is separated from the rest of the cervical column. The craniocervical junction is considered as responsible for very different signs and symptoms to those we find in the inferior cervical spine, such as for example vertigo, headaches with different origins, etc. The objective of the thrust technique for an atlas rotation disorder with index finger contact is to return mobility and functionality to the vertebra. It is important to master the basic principles of performing the technique to be able to apply the correct therapeutic procedure after having ruled out the possible risks of manipulation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mata-Guerrero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espí-López, G. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peinado-Asensio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Debido a sus grandes diferencias, anatómicas y funcionales, el estudio de la región craneocervical se separa del resto de la columna cervical. El complejo craneocervical se considera responsable de signos y síntomas muy diferentes a los que encontramos en el raquis cervical inferior, como por ejemplo vértigos, cefaleas de distinto origen, etc. El objetivo de la técnica de thrust para una disfunción en rotación del atlas con contacto indexial es devolver la movilidad y funcionalidad a la vértebra. Es importante dominar los principios básicos de realización de la técnica para poder aplicar una correcta intervención terapéutica tras haber descartado los posibles riesgos de la manipulación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. J. Ost. Clin. Rel. Res;7(2): 84-90, mayo-ago. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115612</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnica semidirecta de thrust para una disfunción en rotación del atlas, con contacto indexial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1277^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1277^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
