<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054025</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retinopathy of prematurity in the XXI century in a developing country: an emergency that should be resolved</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction Retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) is the first cause of childhood blindness in Argentina and is reaching epidemic proportions. To gain greater insight into the issues involved in this epidemic, we analyzed the characteristics of the infants referred for treatment of very severe ROP to the Dr. Juan P. Garrahan Pediatric Hospital, located in the city of Buenos Aires. Methods We performed a retrospective study of patients referred for ROP from 01/01/96 to 12/31/03. Very severe ROP was defined as threshold disease or worse in both eyes, plus disease in zones 1 or 2, or Rush disease. Unusual patients were defined as those with very severe ROP with a gestational age (GA) of &gt; 31 weeks or birth weight (BW) &gt; 1500 g. Patients were divided into two groups according to the distance between the referring center and our hospital: group A consisted of those from nearby areas (&amp;#8804; 70 km) and group B comprised those from areas &gt; 70 km from the hospital. Results During the study period, the number of cases progressively increased while the proportion of &#147;unusual&#148; patients slightly decreased. The total number of infants referred was 809 and 14 % were unusual patients; 55 % had very severe ROP, 89% were treated, and 7% were referred too late and lost the opportunity for treatment. Group B comprised 61 % of the infants referred. Very severe ROP was present in 53 % of patients in group A and in 56 % of those in group B. The mean GA was 29.5 +/- 3.1 weeks in group A and 30.8 +/- 2.6 in group B (p &lt; 0.001); 90.5% of the patients in group A and 64 % of those in group B required mechanical ventilation (p &lt; 0.001). No predictors for very severe ROP were found in multifactorial analysis. Conclusions We report a childhood epidemic of blindness in which the prevalence of very severe ROP increased during the study period and the disease occurred in large, fairly mature newborns. The differences found in relation to the referring center and the lack of correlation between very severe ROP and prematurity or the use of mechanical ventilation suggests substantial disparity in healthcare, which should be taken into account when planning prevention strategies</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sola, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novalia, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dilgera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bauera, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falbo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galina, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manzitti, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouzas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz González, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La retinopatía del prematuro (RdP) es la primera causa de ceguera infantil en Argentina, de alcances epidémicos. Con el objetivo de mejorar el conocimiento de factores involucrados en esta epidemia, analizamos las características de los niños derivados para tratamiento de RdP severa al Hospital de Pediatría Juan P. Garrahan, ubicado en la ciudad de Buenos Aires. Métodos: Revisión retrospectiva de pacientes admitidos por RdP entre el 1 de enero de 1996 y el 31 de diciembre de 2003. RdP severa = enfermedad umbral en ambos ojos o peor, enfermedad plus en zona 1 o 2, o enfermedad de Rush. Pacientes &#147;inusuales&#148; son definidos aquéllos con RdP grave y edad gestacional (EG) &gt; 31 semanas o peso al nacer (PN) &gt; 1.500 g. Los pacientes se dividieron en 2 grupos según distancia de procedencia en relación a nuestro hospital: grupo A de procedencia cercana (&amp;#8804; 70 km) y grupo B amás de 70 km. Resultados: Durante el período de estudio hubo un aumento progresivo del número de casos, con escasa reducción de casos &#147;inusuales&#148;. El total de niños referidos fue de 809, con 14% de casos &#147;inusuales&#148;; 55 % presentó formas severas, 89% recibió tratamiento y 7% perdió oportunidad por derivación tardía. El 61 % perteneció al grupo B; la incidencia de RdP severa fue de 53 % en A y 56 % en B. La media de EG fue 29,5 +/- 3,1 semanas en el grupo A y de 30,8 +/- 2,6 en el B (p &lt; 0,001); 90,5 % en A y 64 % en B requirió asistencia ventilatoria mecánica (p &lt; 0,001). No se encontraron factores predictivos de RdP grave en el análisis multivariable. Conclusiones: En esta epidemia de ceguera durante la niñez, la prevalencia de formas severas de RdP aumentó durante los años del estudio y la enfermedad ocurre aún en prematuros cercanos al término. Las diferencias según el lugar de procedencia y la falta de asociación de RdP grave con inmadurez o uso de ventilación mecánica, sugieren una importante disparidad en los cuidados de salud que debería tomarse en cuenta al planificar estrategias de prevención</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);66(6): 551-558, jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054025</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La retinopatía del prematuro en el siglo XXI en un país en desarrollo: una urgencia que debe ser resuelta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1121^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28259^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28259^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
