<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050531</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radial closing wedge osteotomy for Kienböck´s disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">For therapeutic success of Kienböck´s disease an earlydiagnosis and surgery in early stages are important,where there are possibilities of a spontaneous recoveringwith probable parcial revascularization and themaintainment of the shape of lunate bone by means ofdecompression and revascularization.Radial closing wedge osteotomy is a simple techniquethat produces good results with scant complications inpatients with radiologic stages I to IIIA on the Lichtmanscale.The goal of treatment, surgical techniques and longtermclinical and radiographic surveillance are presentand discused</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Delgado Serrano, P. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Morenilla, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Sanz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para el éxito terapéutico de la enfermedad de Kienböck sonimportantes el diagnóstico precoz y la cirugía en los estadiosprecoces, donde son posibles un restablecimiento espontáneocon una probable revascularización parcial y el mantenimientode la forma del semilunar mediante medidas descompresivasy de revascularización.La osteotomía de cierre en cuña radial es una técnica sencillaque presenta buenos resultados y escasas complicacionesen pacientes con estadios radiológicos I-IIIA de la clasificaciónde Lichtman.Se presentan las bases de tratamiento, técnicas quirúrgicasy los resultados clínicos y radiográficos a largo plazo de estalesión</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;4(supl.1): 45-51, dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050531</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteotomía de cierre en cuña del radio en la enfermedad de Kienböck</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12318^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13049^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
