<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94770</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Radiovisiographic evaluation of the adaptation of the master cone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: The objective of this study was to evaluate in vitro the adaptationof the master cone, by the radiographic and radiovisiographic methods in 40 teeth wih single root canals instrumented with a standardized tecnique up to the working length wih a K File # 40. Materials and ethods: The teeth were radiographic and radiovisiogrphic pictures taken before an after the experience with an otoraial incidence and proximo proximal with the positioner Endoray II (Dentsply, Maillefer). To do the master cones apical of gutta-percha # 40 were used (Dentsply Maillefer), which were introduced in the prepared root canas, adjusting them to the working length. The radiographic evaluation was done by wo observers, using a magnifying glass 6 X, on a microscope, whereas the radiovsiographic picture was analyzed directly in the PC monitor. The registered information was evaluated statistically used was evaluated by means of kappa coefficiente and the binmial test. Results: Were detected that by means of incidence proximo proximal a 68% of not adapted cones, whereas by means of ortorradial incidence only an 18%. In the incidence proximo proximal the sensitivity of the radiovisiographic method was only 30%, that the 70% of the pieces classified as adapted by radiovisiographic ictures were classified as not adapted by conventional radiographic pictures. The specificity hovwever was 92% that  means that only the 8% of false positive by radiovisiographic ws observed. Conclusions: In this study conditions the radiovisiographic method showed a poor agreement with the radiographic method, for both incidences, proximo proximal and ortorrdial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Od del Val, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hilú, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar in vitro la adaptación del cono principal por ls métodos radiográfico y radiovisiográfico en 40 dientes unirrdiculares instrumentados con una técnica estandarizada hasta la longitu de trabjo con una lima K# 40. Material y métods: Fueron radiografiados y radiovisiografiados antes y luego d la experiencia con una incidencia ortorradial y próximo proximal con el posicionador Endoray II (Dentsply). Para efectuar la conometría se utlizaron conos de gutapercha # 40 (Dentsply Maillefer), que fueron introducidos dentro de los conductos radiculares preparados, ajustándolos a la longitud de trabajo. La evaluación radiográfica fue realizada utilizando una upa de magnificción 6 X, sobre un negatoscopio, mientras que la radovisiografica se analizó directamente en el monitor de la PC. Los datos registrados fueron evaluados estadísticamente mediante el coeficiente kappa y la prueba bnomial. Resultados: La evaluación radiográfica tvo mediante la incidencia próximo proximal un 68% de conos no adaptdos, mientras que mediatne incidencia ortorradial solo un 18%. En la incidencia próxmo proximal la sensibiliad del método radiovisiográfico comparado con el rdiográfico fue de solo el 30% , es decir que el 70% de las piezas clasificadas como adaptaas por radiovisiografía fueron clasificadas como no adaptadas por radiografía convencional. La especificidad en cambio fue elevada, del 92%, es decir, que solo se observó un 8% de falsos positivos por radiovisiografí. Conclusiones: En las condiciones de este estudio el método radiovisiográfico mostró pobre concordancia con el método radiográfico en mas incidencias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);27(2): 75-79, abr.-jun. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94770</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación radiovisiográfica de la adaptación del cono principal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32944^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14485^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23439^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
