<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68877</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Currently available antidepressant drugs are far from optimal. On the one hand, approximately 30% patients are treatment-resistant, while on the other, there is a 3-4 week delay between the start of treatment and the onset of therapeutic effects. Knowledge of the neurobiology of depression is essential for the development of new therapeutic strategies. Objective: The present article aims to review the neurobiological bases of the noradrenergic system, one of the main targets of antidepressant drugs. Development: we describe current knowledge of the anatomy and function of the most important noradrenergic nucleus, the locus coeruleus, and its interaction with different neurotransmission systems, as well as of the role of alfa2-adrenoceptors in the mechanism of action of antidepressant drugs. Conclusions: Study of neurotransmission targets for antidepressants seems to be the most effective approach for the design of new antidepressant drugs. In this context, the alfa2-adrenoceptors play a major role in the mechanism of action of these agents. In addition, antidepressants, whether with a noradrenergic or a serotonergic profile, are able to modulate the noradrenergic system, demonstrating that both systems are modulated at the same time in the central nervous system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Callado, Luis Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, Jorge Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meana, José Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los tratamientos antidepresivos delos que se dispone en la actualidad se encuentran aún muy lejos de ser óptimos. Por un lado hay un porcentaje de pacientes que no responden a los tratamientos y además hay un período de retraso de unas 3-4 semanas entre el inicio del tratamiento y la aparición del efecto terapéutico. El conocimiento dela neurobiología de la enfermedad resulta imprescindible para el desarrollo de nuevos tratamientos. Objetivo: Revisar las bases neurobiológicas de uno de los sistemas diana de los fármacos antidepresivos, el sistema noradrenérgico. Desarrollo: se describe la anatomía y la función del núcleo noradrenérgico más importante, el locus coeruleus, su interacción con los demás sistemas de neurotransmisión, así como el papel de los receptores adrenérgicos alfa2 en el mecanismo de acción de los fármacos antidepresivos. Conclusiones: El estudio profundo de los sistemas de neurotransmisión diana de los antidepresivos es el mejor abordaje como fuente de conocimiento para el diseño de nuevas estrategias antidepresivas. Los receptores adrenérgicos alfa2 parecen tener un papel muy relevante en el mecanismo de acción de estos fármacos. Además, los antidepresivos tanto de perfil noradrenérgico como serotoninérgico son capaces de modular el sistema noradrenérgico, lo que evidencia que ambos sistemas son modulados conjuntamente en el SNC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);15(5): 162-174, oct.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68877</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24347^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31144^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22546^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
