<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136459</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An Invasive Strategy in Non-ST-Segment Elevation Acute Coronary Syndromes. From Large Trials to the Real World</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. We report the impact on prognosis of an invasive strategy used at our center for non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome. Patients and method. We analyzed 504 consecutive patients with typical chest pain, electrocardiographic changes or increased troponin I serum values, who were divided into 2 cohorts: a) conservative group, 272 patients admitted between October 2001 and September 2002 and managed with a conservative strategy, and b) invasive group, 232 patients admitted between October 2002 and September 2003 for whom an invasive strategy was recommended. We recorded major events (death or reinfarction) and minor events (readmission or need for post- discharge revascularization) within a 12-week follow-up period. Results. In the invasive group in-hospital angioplasty (21% vs 35%, P&lt;.0001) and in-hospital revascularization (33% vs 48%, P=.001) increased. There were no significant differences between the conservative and the invasive group regarding major events (17% vs 15%). The invasive group was associated with a reduction in minor events (17% vs 9%, P=.01). The incidence of any event was reduced (28% vs 20%, P=.04). In the multivariate analysis for the whole group (n=504) the invasive strategy significantly reduced minor events (hazard ratio 0.5 [0.3- 0.8], P=.008) and any event (hazard ratio 0.5 [0.3-0.8], P=.005), but not major events (hazard ratio 0.6 [0.4-1.1], P=.09). Conclusions. The results observed in recent randomized clinical trials regarding the use of an invasive strategy were confirmed in the real world. In the short term, the benefits seem to be confined to a reduction in minor events, i.e., fewer readmissions and less need for postdischarge revascularization (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fácila, Lorenzo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchís, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bodí, Vicent</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chorro, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pellicer, Mauricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bertomeu, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, Vicent</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch, María J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llácer, Àngel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Consuegra, Luciano</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Presentamos el impacto pronóstico de una estrategia invasiva (EI) en el síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST en nuestra institución. Pacientes y método. Se ha estudiado a 504 pacientes consecutivos con dolor torácico típico, cambios electrocardiográficos y elevación de la troponina I divididos en 2 cohortes: a) grupo conservador, 272 pacientes ingresa- dos entre octubre de 2001 y septiembre de 2002, manejados con una estrategia conservadora (EC); b) grupo invasivo, 232 pacientes ingresados entre octubre de 2002 y septiembre de 2003 y en los que se recomendó una EI. Se recogieron los eventos mayores (defunción o reinfarto) y menores (reingreso o necesidad de revascularización postalta) durante 12 semanas. Resultados. En el grupo invasivo se incrementó la angioplastia prealta (el 21 frente al 35%; p &lt; 0,0001) y la revascularización prealta (el 33 frente al 48%; p = 0,001). No hubo diferencias entre los grupos conservador e invasivo en relación con los eventos mayores (el 17 frente al 15%). El grupo invasivo se relacionó con menos eventos menores (el 17 frente al 9%; p = 0,01). La incidencia de cualquier evento se redujo (un 28 frente a un 20%; p = 0,04). En el análisis multivariado global (n = 504), el manejo invasivo fue un predictor independiente de menos eventos menores (hazard ratio [HR] = 0,5; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 0,3-0,8; p = 0,008) y de cualquier evento (HR = 0,5; IC del 95%, 0,3-0,8; p = 0,005), pero no de menos eventos mayores (HR = 0,6; IC del 95%, 0,4-1,1; p = 0,09). Conclusiones. Los resultados de los estudios aleatorizados recientes respecto al uso de una EI se confirman en el mundo real. En una perspectiva a corto plazo los beneficios se centran especialmente en una reducción de eventos menores: menos reingresos y menor necesidad de revascularización postalta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;57(12): 1143-1150, dic. 2004. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136459</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategia invasiva en el síndrome coronario agudo sin elevación del segmento ST. De los grandes estudios al mundo real</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d800^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d800^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
