<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038925</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Schooltooth decay ratio from Barbastro Primary Care Service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Oral Health Unit from Barbastro (Insalud Health Centre) completed between 2000 and 2002 an epidemiologic study of the tooth decay for 1,665 scholars between 6 and 14 years old. The global prevalence obtained totalled 41.49%. By age groups, it totalled 33% at 6, 57.14% at 12 and 71.24% at 14 years old. CAO-D index were 0.06 at 6, 1.52 at 12 and 3.64 at 14.When comparing these ratios with similar ratios from surrounding regions, we conclude that results obtained from our study are lower in the 6 years old group, similar in the 12 years old group and higher in the 14 years old group restauration ratios are lower at 12 years old and significantly lower at 14 years old (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Martí, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio Calvo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Bistué, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante los años 2000-2002, dentro de las actividades de la Unidad de Salud Buco-dental del Centro de Salud del Insalud de Barbastro, se realiza un estudio epidemiológico de caries sobre 1665 escolares con edades comprendidas entre los 6 y los 14 años. Se encuentra una prevalencia total del 41'49%, siendo a los 6 años del 33%, a los 12 del 57'14% y a los 14 años del 71'24%. Los índices CAO-D son de 0'06 a los 6 años, de 1'52 a los 12 y de 3'64 a los 14 años de edad. Al comparar con los índices de otras regiones de nuestro entorno, tenemos unos índices bajos a los 6 años, estamos en una zona media a los 12 años y muy altos a los 14. Siendo los índices de restauración a los 12 años bajos, y a los 14 muy bajos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;21(1): 355-360, ene.-feb. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indices epidemiológicos de caries de la población escolar atendida en el Centro de Salud de Barbastro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28452</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10090^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
