<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166216</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic significance of heart rate in the general population and in patients with coronary artery disease and hypertension. Possible mechanisms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Numerous epidemiological studies have shown that a raised heart rate is associated with higher overall and cardiovascular mortality, once other cardiovascular risk factors have been adjusted for. Most of these studies have involved the general population; only a few concerned hypertensives and patients with stable coronary artery disease. The association between a raised heart rate and increased morbidity and mortality is more marked in men than women. Although an increase in heart rate could be a marker of underlying disease, which would explain the association with increased mortality, it is clear that this does not appear to be the case. On the contrary, there is evidence that a raised heart rate is linked to increased sympathetic activity, high blood pressure, obesity, metabolic syndrome, and atherosclerosis progression. Similarly, it has been shown that a raised heart rate is also associated with the disruption of coronary atherosclerotic plaque. Given these findings, it is reasonable that clinicians should now recognize heart rate as a useful independent cardiovascular risk factor. Future studies will tell us whether targeted reductions in heart rate improve prognosis in patients in whom it is raised (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lázaro-Salvador, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Padial, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-González, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Numerosos estudios epidemiológicos han demostrado que hay relación entre el aumento de la frecuencia cardiaca y el incremento de la mortalidad total y cardiovascular tras ajustar por otros factores de riesgo cardiovascular. La mayoría de los estudios ha analizado poblaciones generales, mientras que sólo unos pocos han considerado poblaciones de pacientes hipertensos o con enfermedad coronaria estable. Esta relación entre aumento de la frecuencia cardiaca y morbimortalidad es más evidente en los varones que en las mujeres. Aunque el aumento de la frecuencia cardiaca puede ser un marcador de alguna enfermedad subyacente, lo que podría explicar la asociación con incremento de la mortalidad, lo cierto es que ésta no parece ser la causa. Hay evidencias de que el aumento de la frecuencia cardiaca se asocia con aumento de la actividad del sistema simpático, con aumento de la presión arterial, con obesidad y síndrome metabólico y con progresión de la aterosclerosis. De igual forma, se ha observado asociación entre el incremento de la frecuencia cardiaca y la rotura de la placa aterosclerótica coronaria. Dada esta información, parece razonable que los clínicos comencemos a valorar la importancia de la frecuencia cardiaca como un factor de riesgo independiente. Futuros estudios nos indicarán si la reducción selectiva de la frecuencia cardiaca mejora el pronóstico de los pacientes con frecuencia cardiaca elevada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);7(supl.D): 2d-8d, 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166216</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia pronóstica de la frecuencia cardiaca en la población general y en pacientes con enfermedad arterial coronaria e hipertensión arterial. Posibles mecanismos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19139^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
