<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94501</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Noncoronary chest pain with raised cardiac biomarkers: report of 15 cases consistent with a diagnosis of acute myocarditis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The patients in this series were brought to the emergency department with non coronary chest pain but had electrocardiographic abnormalities and/or raised cardiac biomarkers, consistent with a diagnosis of myocarditis. The study period was 20 months, during which we saw 15 such patients (14 men, 1 woman). The mean (SD) age was 32(12) years; 6 of the patients were smokers. Most (12 patients) had no vascular risk factors, 13 patients had ST segmentel evation, and 6 developed heart failure. An electrocardiogram was recorded in 10 cases; the traces were normal in 8 cases. Cardiac catheterization, performed in 4 patients, revealed no coronary lesions. In 3 patients the diagnosis of myocarditis was based on nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estella, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio revisa una serie de casos atendidos en urgencias ingresados por dolor torácico no coronario pero que presentaban alteraciones en el ECG y/o biomarcadores elevados, compatible todo ello con el diagnóstico de miocarditis. El periodo de estudio fue de 20 meses, durante el cual se incluyeron 15 enfermos: 14 hombres y una mujer. La edad media fue de 32 ± 12 años, 6 eran fumadores. La mayoría de los enfermos(12) no presentaba factores de riesgo vascular, 13 presentaron elevación del segmento ST y 6 enfermos desarrollaron insuficiencia cardiaca. Se realizó ecocardiografía en 10 enfermos y en 8 fue normal. En 4 pacientes se realizó cateterismo cardiaco sin detectarse lesiones coronarias y en 3 el diagnóstico de miocarditis se obtuvo mediante la realización de resonancia nuclear magnética (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(5): 375-377, oct. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94501</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor torácico no coronario con biomarcadores cardiacos elevados: presentación de 15 casos compatibles con miocarditis aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9397^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19100^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
