<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79267</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the relationship between the number of citations and the quality evaluated by experts in psychology journals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study analyzes the relationship between the number of citations as calculated by the IN-RECS database and the quality evaluated by experts. The articles published in journals of the Spanish Psychological Association between 1996 and 2008 and selected by the Editorial Board of Psychology in Spain were the subject of the study. Psychology in Spain is a journal that includes the best papers published throughout the previous year, chosen by the Editorial Board made up of fifty specialists of acknowledged prestige within Spanish psychology and translated into English. The number of the citations of the 140 original articles republished in Psychology in Spain was compared to the number of the citations of the 140 randomly selected articles. Additionally, the study searched for a relationship between the number of the articles selected from each journal and their mean number of citations. The number of citations received by the best articles as evaluated by experts is significantly higher than the number of citations of the randomly selected articles. Also, the number of citations is higher in the articles from the most frequently selected journals. A statistically significant relation between the quality evaluated by experts and the number of the citations was found(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zych, Izabela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buela-Casal, Gualberto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio analiza la relación entre el número de citas, calculado por la base de datos INRECS y la calidad evaluada por expertos. Los artículos publicados en revistas del Colegio Oficial de Psicólogos entre 1996 y 2008 y seleccionados por el Comité Editorial de Psychology in Spain fueron el objetivo del estudio. Psychology in Spain es una revista que incluye los mejores artículos publicados durante el año anterior y seleccionados por el Comité Editorial que incluye cincuenta especialistas de reconocido prestigio dentro de la Psicología española y traducidos al inglés. El número de citas de los 140 artículos originales publicados nuevamente en Psychology in Spain fue comparado con el número de citas de otros 140 artículos seleccionados aleatoriamente. Además, se estudió la relación entre el número de artículos seleccionados de cada revista y su media de citas. Los resultados demostraron que el número de citas de los mejores artículos según los expertos fue significativamente más alto que el número de citas de los artículos seleccionados aleatoriamente. Igualmente, el número de citas es más alto en los artículos de las revistas seleccionadas con mayor frecuencia. Se encontró una relación estadísticamente significativa entre la calidad evaluada por los expertos y las citas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(2): 270-276, 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79267</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la relación entre el número de citas y la calidad evaluada por los expertos en revistas de psicología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50088</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37706</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33954</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10573^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10573^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10573^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50089</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
