<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046234</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reno-uretero-vesical lithiasis on a double-J catheter. Mode of presentation of acute abdomen in an immigrant patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Formation of huge dimension calculus on "Pig Tail" catheter is so rare. We describe the case of an immigrant female patient who was seen in "Emergency Room" and needed urgent surgery. She was complaining of the presence of ureteric catheter for the last eight years. The formation of urinary calculi on a neglected (abandoned) urinary catheter is not, relatively, unfrequent and depends on several factors such as: urinary stasis, infection and specially on the time it should be forgotten like this case. We have different techniques to resolve them like ESWL, endoscopic or open surgery removal. This last was the choice of our&#146;s (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Núñez Delgado, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig Álvaro, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz de la Fuente, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Issa-Masad Khozouz, Z</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Bailén, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de formación de cálculo de grandes dimensiones sobre catéter ureteral doble J en una paciente inmigrante tras la permanencia de ocho años, precisando extirpación quirúrgica. La formación de incrustaciones cálcicas sobre catéteres ureterales es un hecho relativamente frecuente que depende de factores como el éstasis urinario, la infección y sobre todo del tiempo de permanencia como ocurrió en este caso. Para resolverlos disponemos de diversas técnicas eficaces como la ESWL (extracorporeal shock wave lithotripsy), la extracción endoscópica y la cirugía como último recurso que finalmente fue la empleada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);18(3): 180-182, jun. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046234</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Litiasis reno-uretero-vesical sobre catéter doble J. Forma de presentación de abdomen agudo en paciente inmigrante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16091</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24370^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
