<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053680</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High-risk hypertrophic cardiomyopathy associated with a novel mutation in cardiac Myosin-binding protein C</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy is an autosomal dominant inherited disease characterized by ventricular hypertrophy and myofibril disarray. Mutations responsible for hypertrophic cardiomyopathy have been identified in 11 genes that encode for cardiac sarcomere proteins. Traditionally, hypertrophic cardiomyopathy due to mutation of the myosin-binding protein C gene (MYBPC3) has been thought to follow a benign course. We report a family with several members affected by hypertrophic cardiomyopathy in which there was a high incidence of sudden death. Disease was presumably caused by the substitution of cytosine by guanine at nucleotide 269 of MYBPC3 mRNA. This mutation, which has not previously been described, modifies codon 79, which encodes for the incorporation of a tyrosine, and gives rise to a stop codon. The mutation described here appears to confer a higher risk than that previously associated with hypertrophic cardiomyopathy due to MYBPC3 gene mutation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Pulpón, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kontny, Frederic</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berge, Knut Eric</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segovia, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Pavía, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leren, Trond P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molano, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La miocardiopatía hipertrófica (MCH) es una enfermedad genética de herencia autosómica dominante carac-terizada por incremento en la masa ventricular y desor-ganización miofibrilar. Se han identificado mutaciones causantes de MCH en 11 genes de proteínas del sarcómero cardiaco. La MCH causada por mutaciones en el gen de la proteína C fijadora de miosina (MYBPC3) tradicionalmente se ha considerado de curso benigno. Presentamos a una familia con varios miembros afectados de MCH y alta incidencia de muerte súbita, presumiblemente como consecuencia de la sustitución de citosina por guanina en el nucleótido 269 del ARNm del gen MYBPC3. Esta mutación, no descrita previamente, modifica el codón 79, que codifica la incorporación del aminoácido tirosina y da lugar a un codón de terminación. La mutación descrita parece conferir un riesgo mayor que el atribuido hasta el momento a la MCH secundaria a mutaciones en el gen MYBPC3</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(3): 311-314, mar. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053680</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Miocardiopatía hipertrófica de alto riesgo asociada con una nueva mutación en la proteína C fijadora de miosina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22311^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9851</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6702^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3662^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30486^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19021^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29449^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
