<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140080</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life and overall survival in high risk patients after radical cystectomy with a simple urinary derivation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate quality of life (QoL) and overall survival after radical cystectomy with cutaneous ureterostomies for locally advanced bladder cancer in elderly patients with high surgical risk. Methods: Fifty eight patients older than 74 years (mean age 80,6&amp;#8239;±&amp;#8239;4,3) with locally advanced bladder cancer (group A), underwent radical cystectomy and ureterocutaneous diversion. Patients completed the EORTC QLQC30 before and six months after surgery to assess functional, clinical and QoL outcomes. The same evaluation was carried out in a control group (group B) of 29 patients (mean age 82,3&amp;#8239;±&amp;#8239;3,8 years), who had refused cystectomy. Questionnaires were also administered to patients of both groups who survived at least 20 months and 5 years. Results: All patients presented with an ASA score &amp;#8805;&amp;#8239;3. Mean hospital stay was 15.1 days (±&amp;#8239;4.8) in group A and 23.5 days (±&amp;#8239;4.1) in Group B. No intraoperative complications occurred in group A. Postoperative overall survival evaluated within 6 months in group A was 97% versus 79% in group B (p&amp;#8239;&lt;&amp;#8239;0.001). Conclusion: Radical cystectomy with cutaneous ureterostomy represents a valid alternative in elderly patients with invasive bladder cancer and high operative risk. Comparison between two groups showed a statistically significant difference for almost all the Qol related parameters and for short and medium term overall survival (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Subba, Enrica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pappalardo, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macchione, Luciano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Butticè, Salvatore</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magno, Carlo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mucciardi, Giuseppe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galì, Alessandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mucciardi&amp;#8239;, Massimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benedetto, Antonina di</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Inferrera, Antonino</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la calidad de vida (QoL) y supervivencia global tras cistectomía radical con ureterostomías cutáneas por cáncer localmente avanzado de vejiga en pacientes ancianos con alto riesgo quirúrgico. Métodos: Cincuenta y ocho pacientes, mayores de 74 años (edad media 80,6&amp;#8239;±&amp;#8239;4,3) con cáncer de vejiga localmente avanzado (grupo A), fueron sometidos a una cistectomía radical y derivación ureterocutánea. Los pacientes completaron el cuestionario EORTC QLQC30 antes y 6 meses después de la cirugía para valoración de resultados funcionales, clínicos y de QoL. La misma evaluación fue realizada en un grupo control (grupo B) de 29 pacientes (edad media 82,3&amp;#8239;±&amp;#8239;3,8 años), que habían rechazado la cistectomía. Los cuestionarios también fueron remitidos a pacientes de ambos grupos que sobrevivieron a los 20 meses y a los 5 años. Resultados: Todos los pacientes presentaron un ASA &amp;#8805;&amp;#8239;3. La estancia hospitalaria media fue de 15,1 días (±&amp;#8239;4,8) en el grupo A y de 23,5 días (±&amp;#8239;4,1) en el grupo B. No hubo complicaciones intraoperatorias en el grupo A. La supervivencia global postoperatoria evaluada a los 6 meses en el grupo A fue del 97 vs 79% en el grupo B (p&amp;#8239;&lt;&amp;#8239;0,001). La relación de calidad de vida e ítems de función y síntomas entre los 2 grupos a los 6 meses mostró una mejoría significativa de todos los parámetros en el grupo A (p&amp;#8239;&lt;&amp;#8239;0,001). Esta ventaja de los pacientes del grupo A fue todavía más evidente a los 20 meses y a los 5 años. La supervivencia a corto plazo y a los 20 meses fue significativamente mayor en el grupo A (p&amp;#8239;&lt;&amp;#8239;0,001). Conclusión: La cistectomía radical con ureterostomía cutánea representa una alternativa válida en pacientes ancianos con cáncer de vejiga invasivo y alto riesgo quirúrgico. La comparación entre los grupos mostró una diferencia significativa en casi todos los parámetros relacionados con la QoL y con respecto a la supervivencia a corto y medio plazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);93(6): 368-374, jun.-jul. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140080</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida y supervivencia global en pacientes de alto riesgo tras cistectomía radical con una derivación urinaria simple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28417</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14947^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
