<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93696</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An internist in the Prado Museum. The challenge of &#147;the naked eye&#148; diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Painting and medicine include the humans. They describe, investigate, diagnose and magnify them, with the idea of being able to offer them a cure. The aim of this paper is to describe the disease through the eyes of the painting. To do so, we have selected the pictures exhibited in the Prado Museum and have described the diseases that they express and that may attract the attention of a good physician. All of this has then been contrasted with the opinion of experts in medicine and painting(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Seco, M. del Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La pintura y la medicina engloban al ser humano, lo describen, lo investigan, lo diagnostican y lo magnifican, con idea de poder embellecerlo y con el fin de ofrecerle cura. El objetivo de este artículo es describir la enfermedad desde los ojos de la pintura. Para ello se han seleccionado los cuadros expuestos en el Museo Nacional del Prado, describiendo en ellos las enfermedades que expresan y que a ojos de un buen médico, pueden llamar la atención. Todo ello contrastado posteriormente con la opinión de expertos en medicina y pintura(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;211(11): 591-595, dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93696</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una internista en el Museo Nacional del Prado. La facies en la pintura: ¿espejo del alma?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9336</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10337^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10337^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9336^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8683</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
