<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058390</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Auditory and corporal laterality, logoaudiometry, and monaural hearing aid gain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objective: To identify the auditory or clinical test that has the best correlation with the ear in which we apply the monaural hearing aid in symmetric bilateral hearing loss.         Material and method: A total of 37 adult patients with symmetric bilateral hearing loss were examined regarding the correlation between the best score in speech discrimination test, corporal laterality, auditory laterality with dichotic digits in Spanish and score for filtered words with monaural hearing aid.         Results: The best correlation was obtained between auditory laterality and gain with hearing aid (0.940).         Conclusions: The dichotic test for auditory laterality is a good tool for identifying the best ear in which to apply a monaural hearing aid. The results of this paper suggest the necessity to apply this test in patients before a hearing aid is indicated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peñaloza-López, Yolanda R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gudiño, Paula K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancha-Jiménez, Sabino de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pedroza, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavides, Mariela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivo: Identificar la correlación de las pruebas audiológicas o clínicas respecto al lado en que se obtiene la mejor ganancia del auxiliar auditivo monoaural en hipoacusia bilateral simétrica.         Material y método: Se examinó a 37 pacientes adultos con hipoacusia bilateral simétrica, respecto a la correlación entre la máxima captación fonémica de la logoaudiometría, la lateralidad corporal, la lateralidad auditiva con la prueba de dígitos dióticos en español, la utilidad social de la audición y la ganancia de auxiliares auditivos.         Resultados: La correlación más alta se obtuvo para lateralidad auditiva respecto a la ganancia del audífono (0,940).         Conclusiones: La prueba de dígitos dióticos para la lateralidad auditiva es útil para identificar el mejor oído para la aplicación monoaural de auxiliar auditivo en casos de hipoacusia bilateral simétrica. Este resultado es importante, ya que indica la necesidad de aplicar la prueba de lateralidad auditiva antes de indicar el uso de auxiliar auditivo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(10): 458-463, dic. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058390</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Lateralidad auditiva y corporal, logoaudiometría y ganancia del audífono monoaural. Aplicación en hipoacusia bilateral simétrica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1304^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29162</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6464^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6464^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8018^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6461</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
