<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155158</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Disk disease and arthrosic degenerative disease of the column are responsible of most radicular pains. The physiopathologic mechanism of radicular pain has not been fully established, but probably several mechanical, ischemic and inflammatory (chemical radiculitis) factors act simultaneously. There are many processes that may cause radicular pain: disk hernias, tumors, infections, traumas, etc. A correct clinical history and examination guides the diagnosis, which is confirmed by Magnetic Resonance. The treatment must have an etiologic focus. In disk and degenerative pathology, the conservative therapy allows an improvement in 80-90 per cent of the patients. When despite an appropriate etiologic therapy (medical and/or surgical), the radicular pain persists, a neurosurgical management of pain is required, with procedures involving the roots (rhizotomies), the spinal cord (DREZ, cordotomies ) and through neuroestimulation (peripheral, medullar or cerebral). The ideal therapy would be the most effective, the less invasive, the less morbid, the most comfortable for the patient and the one with the less economic cost (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Comuñas, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las hernias discales y la enfermedad degenerativa artrósica de la columna son responsables de la gran mayoría de los dolores radiculares. El mecanismo fisiopatológico de la p roducción del dolor radicular no  ha sido completamente establecido, probablemente factores mecánicos, isquémicos e inflamatorios (radiculitis química) actuarían conjuntamente. Existe una gran número de procesos que pueden dar origen a un dolor radicular: hernias de disco, tumores, infecciones, traumatismos, etc. Una correcta historia clínica y exploración orientan el diagnóstico, que confirmará la Resonancia Magnética. El tratamiento debe ser etiológico. En patología discal y degenerativa el tratamiento conservador consigue una mejoría en el 80-90% de los pacientes. Cuando a pesar del tratamiento etiológico adecuado (médico y/o quirúrgico) persiste el dolor radicular es preciso efectuar un tratamiento neuroquirúrgico del dolor, mediante intervenciones sobre las raíces (rizotomías), sobre la médula espinal (DREZ, cordotomías) y mediante intervenciones de neuroestimulación (periférica, medular o cerebral). El tratamiento ideal debe ser el más eficaz, el menos invasivo, el de menor morbilidad, el más confortable para el paciente y el de menor coste económico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;7(supl.2): 36-48, 2000. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155158</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor radicular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9682^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9682^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12282^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32619^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12282^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13510^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12282^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9630^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13510^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13510^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25565^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
