<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153266</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of platelet rich plasma and growth factors on the regeneration and chronic pain associated with intervertebral disc disease. Systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine the effect of platelet-rich plasma and growth factors on regeneration and reduction of pain in degenerative disc disease. Methods: Systematic review of the literature. The recommendations of the Cochrane Collaboration Cochrane outlined in the Handbook for Systematic Reviews of interventions was followed; randomized clinical trials preclinical and clinical phases which evaluated the effect of platelet-rich plasma or growth factors for degenerative disc disease between september 1/2013 to september 30/2014, published in PubMed, MEDLINE and LILACS were included. Results: The initial search 11 items of which 3 met the selection criteria determined for this review were identified. Search strategy where citations related to the three main articles were reviewed was conducted. Of these only 6 met the selection criteria. Threw two articles in academic google search, leaving a total of 10 studies were included in the final analysis. In this review we include in the search not only those studies in vitro but also those studies in murine models and human study. From these studies, most of them were done in vitro (6), in animal models (2) and in humans (2). In those studies where this study was evaluated PRP and growth factors on cells or tissues of the intervertebral disc is selected alone. To know the effect these substances have to be evaluated in both preclinical and clinical studies. All studies reviewed agreed on the anti-inflammatory effect, repair, and even proliferator improvement in pain, vertebral discopathy. Conclusions: The results of studies showing the anti-inflammatory effect, repair, and even proliferator improvement in pain, vertebral discopathy. None of them mention whether this increased matrix synthesis would lead to greater tissue fibrosis and further deterioration, so that studies in animals or humans should focus on evaluating increased monitoring, to assess late effects of therapy. Therefore we can conclude that the focus points of the present investigation should point to more understand the mechanism of disc degeneration together with the benefits of PRP to treat it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Santos, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Huerta, JC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canseco Aguilar, CP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llano Conrado, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tenopala Villegas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar el efecto del plasma rico en plaquetas y factores de crecimiento sobre la regeneración y la reducción del dolor en discopatía degenerativa. Material y método: Revisión sistemática de la literatura. Se siguió las recomendaciones de la colaboración Cochrane expuestas en el Cochrane Hand book for Systematic Reviews of interventions. Se incluyeron ensayos clínicos aleatorizados fases preclínicas y clínicas donde evaluaban el efecto del plasma rico en plaquetas o factores de crecimiento sobre la discopatía degenerativa entre el 1 de septiembre de 2013 y el 30 de septiembre de 2014, publicados en PubMed, MEDLINE y LILACS. Resultados: En la búsqueda inicial se identificaron 11 artículos, de los cuales 3 cumplieron los criterios de selección determinados para esta revisión. Se realizó estrategia de búsqueda donde se revisaron las citas relacionadas de los tres artículos principales. De éstos, sólo 6 cumplieron los criterios de selección. Se incluyeron dos artículos más que arrojó la búsqueda en google académico, quedando un total de 10 estudios para el análisis final. En esta revisión, nosotros incluimos en la búsqueda de no sólo aquellos estudios realizados in vitro, sino además aquellos estudios en modelos murinos y estudio realizado en humanos. De estos estudios, la mayor parte de ellos fueron realizados in vitro (6), en modelos animales (2) y en humanos (2). En este estudio se seleccionaron sólo aquellos estudios donde fue evaluado el PRP y/o los factores de crecimiento sobre las células o tejidos del disco intervertebral. Para poder conocer el efecto que estas sustancias, tienen que ser evaluadas en estudios tanto preclínicos como clínicos. Todos los estudios analizados coincidieron sobre el efecto antiinflamatorio, reparador, proliferador e incluso en la mejoría del dolor de la discopatía vertebral. Conclusiones: Los resultados de los estudios muestra el efecto antiinflamatorio, reparador, proliferador e incluso en la mejoría del dolor de la discopatía vertebral. En ninguno de ellos se mencionó si este aumento de la síntesis de la matriz conllevaría a una mayor fibrosis del tejido y mayor deterioro, por lo que los estudios en animales o en humanos deberían enfocarse a evaluar un seguimiento mayor para poder evaluar los efectos tardíos de la terapia. Por lo tanto, podemos concluir que los puntos de enfoque de la investigación actual debe apuntar hacia entender más el mecanismo de la degeneración discal conjuntamente con los beneficios del PRP en tratarla (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;23(3): 145-153, mayo-jun. 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto del plasma rico en plaquetas y/o factores de crecimiento sobre la regeneración y el dolor crónico asociado a discopatía intervertebral. Revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34314^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34314^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37364^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19167^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19167^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7567^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7567^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7567^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
