<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59238</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Griscelli-Prunieras syndrome: report of two cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Griscelli-Prunieras syndrome (GS) is a rare autosomal recessive disorder characterized by partial albinism. His pathogenic mechanism is associated with defects in the packaging of melanin and other cellular proteins. GS is classified into 3 types based on the genetic and molecular features. Mutations in the genes which cause GS are known. We report two first cases described in Spain who presented a silver-gray sheen of the hair and a severe immune disorder. They were studied for mutations principally related to this syndrome. Two patients showed the Rab27a mutation (frequently associated with GS2). The natural disorder evolution differs considerably among the various forms, so a genetic study is essential in GS to achieve the most accurate prognosis and treatment possible(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fortuny Guasch, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martorell Sampol, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noguera Julian, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Carretero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricart Campos, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Griscelli-Prunieras (SGP) es una rara entidad de herencia autonómica recesiva que se presenta con albinismo parcial. Su patogenia se explica por alteraciones en los genes que regulan el transporte de melanosomas. Se han descrito tres tipos en base a sus características genéticas y moleculares. Se conocen las mutaciones relacionadas con este síndrome. A continuación presentamos dos pacientes, no descritos anteriormente en España, que presentaban un cabello gris-plateado característico e inmunodeficiencia cuyo estudio genético demostró la mutación en el gen Rab27A (asociado al SG2). El pronóstico y tratamiento difiere considerablemente entre las diferentes formas de la enfermedad, por lo que el diagnóstico genético precoz es fundamental para poder establecer un pronóstico y tratamiento adecuados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);70(2): 164-167, feb. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59238</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Griscelli-Prunieras: a propósito de dos casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33683^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29082^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29082^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9346^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
