<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052908</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cytokines and other immunological parameters as markers of distant organ involvement in acute pancreatitis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: There is a role of immunologic proinflammatory mediators in pathogenesis of distant organ disfunction in acute pancreatitis (AP). The aim is to evaluate the relationship between those mediators and liver, kidney and lung disfunction in patients with AP. Patients and method: On the day of admission in 34 patients with AP, biochemical parameters of liver function, cretinine and arterial partial pressure of oxygen (PO2) were determined, and cut points were established. Soluble tumor necrosis factor receptor I (sTNFRI), interleukin (IL) 1 receptor antagonist (IL-1Ra), IL-6, soluble IL-6 receptor (sIL-6R), IL-18, and intercellular adhesion molecule-1 (ICAM-1) were determined on days 1, 2, 3 and 7, and were compared between patients with biochemical parameters and PO2 on admission higher or lower than an established cut point. Results: Levels of sTNFRI, IL-18 and ICAM-1 were significantly higher and sustained, and IL-6 only the first day, in patients with parameters of liver function above the cut point. sTNFRI, IL-1Ra and ICAM-1 early showed significantly higher levels in relation with serum creatinine, and these and also IL-6 in those with PO2 below 60 mmHg. Conclusions: sTNFRI, IL-6, IL-18 and ICAM-1 behaved as early markers of hepatic alteration, sTNFRI, IL-1Ra and ICAM-1 of renal disfunction and these and IL-6 of lung injury</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arranz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almaraz, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caro-Patón, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrote, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Alonso, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saracíbar, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Es conocido el papel que desempeñan los mediadores inmunológicos proinflamatorios en la patogenia de algunas alteraciones de órganos distantes en la pancreatitis aguda (PA). El objetivo de este estudio ha sido evaluar la relación entre dichos mediadores y la afectación hepática, renal y pulmonar en pacientes con PA. Pacientes y método: En 34 pacientes con PA se valoraron el día del ingreso, parámetros bioquímicos de función hepática, creatinina y presión parcial de oxígeno (PO2) arterial, y se establecieron puntos de corte. Se determinaron el receptor soluble tipo I del factor de necrosis tumoral (sTNFRI), el receptor antagonista de la interleucina (IL) 1 (IL-1Ra), la IL-6, el receptor soluble de la IL-6 (sIL-6R), la IL-18 y la molécula de adherencia intercelular-1 (ICAM-1) los días 1, 2, 3 y 7, y se compararon entre los pacientes con los parámetros en el momento del ingreso (bioquímicos y PO2) superiores o inferiores a un punto de corte establecido. Resultados: Se encontraron valores significativamente más elevados y mantenidos de sTNFRI, IL-18 e ICAM-1, y de IL-6 sólo el primer día, en los pacientes con algún parámetro de función hepática superior al punto de corte. sTNFRI, IL-1Ra e ICAM-1 presentaban al inicio valores significativamente superiores en los pacientes en relación con la creatinina, y de éstos e IL-6 en los que presentaban PO2 inferior a 60 mmHg. Conclusiones: sTNFRI, IL-6, IL-18 e ICAM-1 se comportaron como marcadores tempranos de lesión hepática; sTNFRI, IL-1Ra e ICAM-1, de disfunción renal, y éstos e IL-6, de afectación pulmonar</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(11): 401-406, mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052908</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Citocinas y otros parámetros inmunológicos como marcadores de alteración de órganos a distancia en la pancreatitis aguda</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24555^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33854^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31092^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29472^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8285^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32940^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
