<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156817</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Popularity and peer relationships in the classroom: A prospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper analyzes in depth the network of popularity among classmates and the connections that this phenomenon maintains with different kinds of relationships (i.e., positive, neutral, and negative) that take place within the classroom. We use Social Network Analysis (SNA) to identify interaction contexts in the classroom. Different kinds of relationships in 20 classrooms from two secondary schools located in the suburban area of Mexico City were assessed. The research data was provided by 660 students (67% girls; 33% boys). Cohesion measures were calculated for positive, neutral, negative, and popularity networks. Cluster analysis shows two profiles based on structural properties of the networks that we have called «Neutral Symmetric» and «Positive Asymmetric». The first one presents low homophily relative to sex, predominance of positive and neutral relationships, and a significant level of negative links. The second profile presents a heterogeneous distribution according to sex, high homophily and high rates of cohesion in positive relationships. Regression analysis shows that the number of students per class is negatively related to the positive network density, and positively related to the negative network density. The simultaneous comparison of multiple networks shows that popularity is associated with being immersed in positive relationships. By contrast, the data suggest certain incompatibility between being popular and being immersed in negative relationships. The findings are discussed in order to improve school life and public policies in education (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos-Vidal, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo analiza la red de popularidad entre los compañeros de clase y la conexión que este fenómeno establece con diferentes tipos de relaciones (positivas, neutras y negativas) que se producen dentro del aula. Empleamos el Análisis de Redes Sociales (ARS) para identificar contextos de interacción en el aula. Evaluamos diferentes tipos de relaciones en 20 clases pertenecientes a dos centros de educación secundaria localizados en el área suburbana de la Ciudad de México. Participaron en total 660 estudiantes (67% mujeres, 33% varones), que proporcionaron los datos de la investigación. Calculamos los indicadores de cohesión para las redes positivas, neutras, negativas y de popularidad. Los análisis de clúster muestran dos perfiles basados en las propiedades estructurales de las redes que denominamos «simétrico neutro» y «asimétrico positivo». El primero presenta una distribución equilibrada entre sexos, baja homofilia y predominancia de relaciones neutras y positivas y el segundo muestra una distribución asimétrica de alumnos en función del sexo, elevada heterofilia y alta cohesión en relaciones positivas. Los análisis de regresión muestran que el número de alumnos por clase se relaciona de forma negativa con la densidad de la red positiva y de forma positiva con la densidad de la red negativa. La comparación simultánea de múltiples redes muestra que la popularidad se asocia con estar inmerso en relaciones positivas. Por el contrario los datos indican cierta incompatibilidad entre el hecho de ser popular y estar inmerso en relaciones negativas. Se discuten los hallazgos para mejorar la convivencia escolar y las políticas públicas en materia educativa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);22(2): 113-124, dic. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156817</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Popularidad y relaciones entre iguales en el aula: un estudio prospectivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
