<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046544</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Amyotrophic neuralgia associated to unilateral diaphragmatic paralysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Amyotrophic neuralgia or Parsonage-Turner syndrome is considered as a form of multiple mononeuropathy that affects the brachial plexus, injuring, in order of frequency, the circumflex, suprascapular, long thoracic, musculocutaneous and radial nerves. The case of a 45 year old male with background of ulcerous colitis referred to our Rehabilitation Service for an electromyographic study due to suspicion of amyotrophic neuralgia is presented. The picture began with an episode of acute pain of the right shoulder followed by weakness in scapulohumeral musculature and paresthesias in lateral factor of the arm. Months later, he had a picture of dyspnea in decubitus and intolerance to physical exercise due to respiratory distress, these symptoms persisting after one and a half year of initiating the painful picture. Finally, the patient was diagnosed of diaphragmatic paralysis secondary to brachial neuropathy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bermejo-Fernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arjona-Carmona, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villelabeitia-Jaureguizar, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Bravo Rueda, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibarra-Luzar, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neuralgia amiotrófica o síndrome de Parsonage-Turner es considerada como una forma de mononeuropatía múltiple que afecta al plexo braquial, lesionando en orden de frecuencia a los nervios circunflejo, supraescapular, torácico largo, musculocutáneo y radial. Se presenta un caso de un varón de 45 años con antecedentes de colitis ulcerosa remitido a nuestro Servicio de Rehabilitación para un estudio electromiográfico por sospecha de neuralgia amiotrófica. El cuadro se inició con un episodio de dolor agudo en el hombro derecho seguido de debilidad en la musculatura escapulohumeral y parestesias en cara lateral del brazo. Meses después presentó un cuadro de disnea en decúbito e intolerancia al ejercicio físico por dificultad respiratoria, persistiendo dicha sintomatología después de año y medio de iniciarse el cuadro doloroso. Finalmente el paciente fue diagnosticado de parálisis diafragmática secundaria a la neuropatía braquial</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(4): 219-222, jul. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046544</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuralgia amiotrófica asociada a parálisis diafragmática unilateral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12553^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4648^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2616^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
