<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046989</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology and costs of severe sepsis in Madrid. A hospital discharge study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective. Severe sepsis is a complex syndrome to define, diagnose and treat. This population-based study describes the epidemiology of sepsis in the Region of Madrid, estimates its incidence and mortality, and assesses its impact on hospital stays and costs. Patients and methods. The source of information was the Minimum Basic Hospital Data Set from the Region of Madrid in 2001. Severe sepsis cases were defined as discharges with a combination of organic failure and presence or suspicion of infection through a combination of codes previously proposed and utilized. A descriptive study was performed, incidence rates were calculated, lengths of stay and costs were estimated, and mortality was analyzed. Results. 6,968 episodes were identified. Mean age was 62.5 year. 59.7% were male. Annual incidence was 14.1/10,000 inhabitants, being highest for those 84 and older (230.8/10,000). 1.7 infections per episode were detected. More frequently identified microorganisms were Streptococcus sp., Staphylococcus sp., Escherichia coli and Candida sp. The most frequent organic dysfunctions were renal (39.7%) and respiratory (35.7%). Mortality was 33%. Mortality was higher in cases with more than one organic failure, hepatic dysfunction or cancer. Mean length of stay was 28.9 day. Annual overall costs were 70 million euros. Conclusions. Severe sepsis is a frequent process, with a high mortality and a significant impact on health care resource utilization</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iñigo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sendra, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouza, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarría-Santamera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo. La sepsis grave es un síndrome complejo de definir, diagnosticar y tratar. Este trabajo de base poblacional describe la epidemiología de la sepsis grave en la Comunidad de Madrid, estima su incidencia y mortalidad y evalúa su impacto en estancias y costes. Pacientes y método. La fuente de información fue el conjunto mínimo básico de datos de la Comunidad de Madrid del año 2001. Se definieron como casos de sepsis grave aquellos en los que existía la presencia de fracaso orgánico y presencia o sospecha de infección a partir de la combinación de códigos de enfermedad y códigos de procedimientos utilizando criterios propuestos y utilizados previamente. Se efectuó un estudio descriptivo, se calcularon tasas poblacionales de incidencia de sepsis, se obtuvieron las estancias medias, se estimó el coste y se analizó la mortalidad por sepsis. Resultados. Se identificaron 6.968 episodios. La edad media fue de 62,5 años. El 59,7% eran hombres. La incidencia anual fue de 14,1/10.000 habitantes, siendo máxima en los mayores de 84 años (230,8/10.000). Se detectaron 1,7 infecciones por episodio. Los microorganismos más frecuentes fueron Streptococcus sp., Staphylococcus sp., Escherichia coli y Candida sp. Las disfunciones orgánicas más frecuentes fueron renal (39,7%) y respiratoria (35,7%). La mortalidad global fue de un 33% y era superior para los episodios con más de una disfunción orgánica, disfunción hepática, o neoplasia. La estancia media fue de 28,9 días. El coste anual de la atención a la sepsis grave en la Comunidad de Madrid es de 70 millones de euros. Conclusiones. La sepsis grave es un proceso frecuente, presenta una elevada mortalidad y tiene un importante impacto en consumo de recursos asistenciales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);30(5): 197-203, jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046989</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología y costes de la sepsis grave en Madrid. Estudio de altas hospitalarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
