<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147327</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience of cooperation in Turkana (Kenya). A nurse look</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Speaking of international cooperation on many occasions we generate some associated with concepts far removed from what really is image. What we will capture in this experience it is not intended to alarm or create scenarios manipulated or magnify poverty, lack of resources or human misery ... only pretend to be faithful to reality as far and near at the same time as we tell . Two nurses and a professor at the University of Alicante (Spain) developed in Turkana (Kenya) a draft Community intervention in which public participation is central to its development. The main objective of the intervention is to identify major health needs and how people can respond to them independently and responsibly. The project is initiated by identifying community leaders through whom are involved in the community to begin the process of health education which responds to the health needs of the latter. After almost a year of intervention have been achieved key objectives related to hygiene, nutrition and care during pregnancy and childbirth (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Riera, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent Rubio, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Higón, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hablar de Cooperación internacional en muchas ocasiones nos genera cierta imagen asociada con conceptos muy alejados de lo que realmente es. Lo que vamos a plasmar en esta experiencia no pretende alarmar, ni crear escenarios manipulados, ni magnificar la pobreza, la falta de recursos o la miseria humana&#133; tan solo pretende ser fiel a una realidad tan lejana y cercana al mismo tiempo como la que narramos. Dos enfermeros y un profesor de la Universidad de Alicante (España) desarrollan en Turkana (Kenia) un proyecto de intervención Comunitaria en la que la participación de la población es el eje de su desarrollo. El principal objetivo de la intervención es la identificación de las principales necesidades de salud y la manera como la población puede responder a ellas de manera autónoma y responsable. El proyecto se inicia con la identificación de los líderes comunitarios a través de los cuales se interviene en la comunidad para iniciar el proceso de educación para la salud que de respuesta a las necesidades de salud de ésta. Tras casi un año de intervención se han logrado objetivos clave relacionados con la higiene, la alimentación y la atención al embarazo y parto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;19(43): 116-126, sept.-dic. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147327</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia de cooperación en Turkana (Kenia). Una mirada enfermera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3183^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7799</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29771^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54367</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
