<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049429</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preventive treatment with topiramate enhances the quality of life of patients with migraine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Topiramate has recently proved to be safe and effective in the prevention of migraine and is currentlythe only neuromodulatory drug indicated for the prevention of migraine in Spain. Aim. To evaluate the adherence, effectivenessand safety of preventive treatment with topiramate in patients diagnosed with migraine. Patients and methods. A prospective,observational, multi-centre study was conducted in general neurology departments. Patients eligible for the study were thosewith migraine, above 14 years of age, who needed preventive treatment and in whom other preventive treatments had failed orfor whom topiramate was believed to be the most suitable therapy as regards its profile of side effects. The effectiveness of thetreatment, patient satisfaction, side effects and loss of body weight were all evaluated. Effectiveness of the treatment wasevaluated by means of the reduction in the frequency of migraines and the score obtained on the Headache Impact Test (HIT-6).Results. A total of 79 patients were evaluated. The dosage of topiramate ranged between 25 and 200 mg/day, with an average of100 mg/day. 19% of the patients dropped out of the study due to side effects. Paresthesias were the most frequent reason fordropping out. No serious side effects were observed. 14% of the patients lost more than 5% of the base weight. The percentageof patients who responded was 58%. The degree of satisfaction of the patients who completed the follow-up was: good (80%),regular (11%) and poor (9%). Conclusions. Preventive treatment with topiramate significantly reduces the impact of migraineand the disability that results from it. Treatment is satisfactory and improves the quality of life in a large percentage of patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sempere, A. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa-Martínez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morera-Guitart, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medrano, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Izquierdo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El topiramato ha demostrado recientementeser seguro y efectivo en la prevención de la migraña y en la actualidades el único fármaco neuromodulador con indicación parala prevención de la migraña en España. Objetivo. Evaluar la adherencia,la eficacia y la seguridad del tratamiento preventivo con topiramatoen pacientes diagnosticados de migraña. Pacientes y métodos.Se realizó un estudio multicéntrico prospectivo observacionalen las consultas de neurología general. Se incluyeron pacientescon migraña mayores de 14 años que requerían un tratamiento preventivo y en los que habían fallado otros tratamientos preventivos oen los que cuales se consideraba más adecuado el topiramato enfunción de su perfil de efectos adversos. Se evaluó la eficacia deltratamiento, la satisfacción del paciente, los efectos adversos y lareducción del peso corporal. La eficacia del tratamiento se valoró através de la reducción en la frecuencia de migrañas y en la puntuacióndel Headache Impact Test (HIT-6). Resultados. Se evaluaron79 pacientes. La dosis de topiramato osciló entre 25 y 200 mg/día,con una mediana de 100 mg/día. El 19% de los pacientes abandonóel estudio por efectos adversos. La causa más frecuente de abandonofueron las parestesias. No se observaron efectos adversos graves.El 14% de los pacientes experimentó una pérdida de peso superioral 5% del basal. El porcentaje de pacientes respondedores fuedel 58%. El grado de satisfacción de los pacientes que completaronel seguimiento fue buena (80%), regular (11%) y mala (9%). Conclusiones.El tratamiento preventivo con topiramato reduce significativamenteel impacto y la discapacidad de la migraña. El tratamientoes satisfactorio y mejora la calidad de vida en un porcentajeimportante de pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(5): 259-263, sept. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049429</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El tratamiento preventivo con topiramato mejora la calidad de vida de los pacientes con migraña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5768^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5768^s22003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5768^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
