<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144267</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malyugin ring for intraoperative miosis in femtosecond laser phacovitrectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the usefulness of the Malyugin ring in poor pupil dilation during phacoemulsification assisted with femtosecond laser with 23 gauge pars plana vitrectomy. Method: A 57-year-old female with cataract and vitreous hemorrhage, and poor pupil dilation (5.5 mm). The phacoemulsification assisted with femtosecond laser, using Malyugin ring after capsulorrhexis, followed by pars plana vitrectomy, and removing at the end without complications. Results: A successfull intraoperative pupil dilation was achieved without complications, with a final BCVA of 20/40. Conclusions: The Malyugin ring is an effective alternative in cases with poor pupil dilation in femtophacovitrectomy, preserving the anatomical and functional integrity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Cortes,  CA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Máynez, GA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Romero, JO</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantero Vergara, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la utilidad del anillo de Malyugin transoperatorio en escasa dilatación pupilar durante facoemulsificación asistida con láser de Fs combinado con vitrectomía pars plana 23 G (femtofacovitrectomía). Método: Se presenta una mujer de 57 años con catarata y hemorragia vítrea, dilatación pupilar de 5,5 mm. Se realiza facoemulsificación asistida con láser de femtosegundo, colocando anillo de Malyugin posterior a extracción de cápsula anterior, seguido de vitrectomía pars plana y retirándolo al final. Resultados: Se logró una dilatación pupilar transoperatoria adecuada, sin complicaciones, con una agudeza visual posoperatoria de 20/40. Conclusiones: El uso del anillo de Malyugin puede ser una alternativa útil en casos con escasa dilatación pupilar en femtofacovitrectomía, conservando la integridad anatómica-funcional pupilar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;90(9): 435-438, sept. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144267</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anillo de Malyugin para miosis intraoperatoria en femtofacovitrectomía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24786^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24786^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24786^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24786^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19378^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19378^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19378^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19378^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
