<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67366</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The readability of written texts aimed at patients is an indicator of quality. Szigriszt made an adaptation of the RES Flesch Score, calling it &amp;#147;Escala de Nivel de Perspicuidad&amp;#148; (Clarity Level Scale), to measure the difficulty in reading a text. But Szigriszt used a text sample that was neither representative nor random, which is why the conclusions are not sufficiently consistent. The aim of this article is to complete the process begun by Szigriszt, review the Szigriszt Scale, comparing it with Flesch&amp;#146;s scale, and propose a scale according to Spanish reading habits.  Methods. Descriptive study. Two hundred and ten documents of 3 types were selected at random: Stationary magazines, school textbooks and scientific magazines. Three fragments of at least 500 words were chosen at random from each one, from the beginning, middle and end. The Flesch-Szigriszt Index (Índice de Legibilidad de Flesch-Szigriszt [IFSZ]), available on the INFLESZ program, was calculated. The scores were classified according to the Flesch and Szigriszt scales.  Results. The readability of the stationary magazines is 60, of scientific magazines 37.9, and school textbooks 67.39.  Conclusions. Only the scientific magazines are situated between 0 and 50. There are no publications with scores lower than 15. Szigrsizt locates &amp;#147;Normal&amp;#148; from 50; Flesch from 60. An intermediate position is adopted and a new scale is proposed: the INFLESZ Scale, which establishes 5 sections: &amp;#147;Very difficult&amp;#148; (&lt;80), &amp;#147;Somewhat difficult&amp;#148; (40-55), &amp;#147;Normal&amp;#148; (55-65), &amp;#147;Quite easy&amp;#148; (65-80) and &amp;#147;Very easy&amp;#148; (&gt;80). Neither the Clarity Level Scale of Szigriszt nor the RES Flesch Score are adapted to Spanish reading habits. In the case of texts on health, there is a greater probability of their being read and understood if they exceed 55 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simón Lorda, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escalona, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marijuán, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melguizo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrio Cantalejo, IM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La legibilidad de los textos escritos dirigidos a pacientes es un indicador de calidad asistencial. Szigriszt realizó una adaptación de la Escala RES de Flesch, a la que llamó Escala de nivel de Perspicuidad&amp;#148;, para medir la dificultad de lectura de un texto. Pero no utilizó una muestra ni representativa ni aleatoria de textos, por lo que sus conclusiones no tienen suficiente consistencia.  El objetivo del trabajo es completar el proceso abierto por Szigriszt, revisar su escala comparándola con la original de Flesch y proponer una escala más ajustada a los hábitos lectores españoles.  Material y métodos. Estudio descriptivo. Se seleccionan aleatoriamente 210 publicaciones de 3 tipos: quiosco, textos escolares y revistas científicas. De cada una se eligen al azar tres fragmentos de al menos 500 palabras, del principio, medio y final. Se calcula el Índice de Flesch-Szigriszt (IFSZ) accesible en el programa informático INFLESZ. Las puntuaciones se clasificaron según las escalas de Flesch y Szigriszt.  Resultados. La legibilidad del &amp;#147;Quiosco de adultos&amp;#148; es 60; de las &amp;#147;Revistas científicas&amp;#148; 37,9 y de los &amp;#147;Libros escolares&amp;#148; 67,39.  Conclusiones. Entre 0 y 50 están sólo las revistas científicas. No existen publicaciones con puntuaciones inferiores a 15. Szigrsizt sitúa lo &amp;#147;Normal&amp;#148; a partir de 50; Flesch a partir de 60. Se adopta una posición intermedia y se propone una nueva escala: Escala INFLESZ que establece 5 tramos: &amp;#147;Muy Difícil&amp;#148; (&lt;40), Algo Difícil&amp;#148; (40-55), &amp;#147;Normal&amp;#148; (55-65), Bastante Fácil&amp;#148; (65-80) y &amp;#147;Muy Fácil&amp;#148; (&gt;80). Ni la Escala de Nivel de Perspicuidad de Szigriszt ni la Escala RES de Flesch son adecuadas para los hábitos lectores españoles. Los textos sobre salud tendrán mayor probabilidad de ser leídos y comprendidos si superan la puntuación 55 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;31(2): 135-152, mayo-ago.2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67366</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14043^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12077^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12077^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
