<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73355</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Postprandial reactive hypoglycemia: myth or reality?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Postprandial reactive hypoglycemia is characterized by symptomsthat are compatible with hypoglycemia in a postprandial situation,usually within 4 hours of eating, coinciding with blood sugar levelsbelow 60 mg/dl. This entity has been widely questioned, mainly dueto the different criteria used to define hypoglycemia, to the lack ofspecificity concerning its clinical manifestations and to the inappropriateuse of the glucose tolerance test. A large part of the confusionis due to the diagnostic procedure used. Most fundamental are theinterpretation of the clinical manifestations reported by the patienttogether with the blood sugar concentration at the time when thesymptoms occur. The clinical manifestations reported by the patientscan be made evident through different diagnostic tests. The maintests are the glucose tolerance test, the hyperglucidic breakfast test,ambulatory capillary blood glucose monitoring and continuous interstitialglucose monitoring. At first these patients are treated with a lowcarbohydratediet, with meals spread throughout the day. However,some of those patients will require a pharmacological treatment. Themost commonly used drugs are the a-glucosidase inhibitors, althoughmany others have been used(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escalada, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Botella, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipoglucemia reactiva posprandial se caracteriza por síntomascompatibles con hipoglucemia en situación posprandial, habitualmentedurante las 4 horas postingesta, coincidiendo con glucemiasmenores de 60 mg/dL. Esta entidad ha sido muy cuestionada, fundamentalmentedebido a los diferentes criterios utilizados para ladefinición de hipoglucemia, a la inespecificidad de la clínica y al usoinapropiado de la sobrecarga oral de glucosa. Gran parte de la confusiónse debe al procedimiento diagnóstico utilizado. Lo fundamentales la interpretación de la clínica que refiere el paciente junto conla concentración glucémica en el momento de los síntomas. La clínicareferida por los pacientes se puede poner de manifiesto condiferentes test diagnósticos. Los principales son la sobrecarga oralde glucosa, el test de desayuno hiperglucídico, la monitorizaciónambulatoria de glucemia capilar y la monitorización continua de glucosaintersticial. Inicialmente estos pacientes son tratados con unaalimentación baja en hidratos de carbono, con ingestas repartidas alo largo del día. Sin embargo, algunos de ellos necesitarán tratamientofarmacológico. Los fármacos más utilizados son los inhibidoresde las alfaglucosidasas, aunque se han utilizado otros muchos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;25(4): 287-292, jul.-ago. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hipoglucemia reactiva posprandial: ¿mito o realidad?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6096^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33167</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d520^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
