<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98384</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dynamic factors of recidivism among drug-dependent prisoners in therapeutic community treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study identifies the dynamic variables of recidivism in a sample of drug-dependent inmates released from Burgos prison (Spain) in the third prison grade to finish their prison sentence in a Therapeutic Community. The documentary sources, consulted for collecting information of 120 subjects, males and between 21 and 40 years (age of release), were the prison record, the classification and treatment protocol, and the social record. Applying a descriptive statistical analysis with contingency tables, the characteristics of the variables that showed higher percentages of recidivism were: lack of work habits, HIV infectious disease, higher scores in extraversion, finalizing the treatment with expulsion or abandonment, and shorter stay in a therapeutic community. These results suggest that relapse prevention can achieve positive results, if we achieve a significant influence on these variables through the penitentiary treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carcedo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio identifica las variables dinámicas de la reincidencia en una muestra de reclusos drogodependientes que fueron excarcelados en tercer grado del Centro Penitenciario de Burgos (España) para computar su pena privativa de libertad por el tratamiento en una comunidad terapéutica. Las fuentes documentales consultadas para la recogida de información de 120 varones, entre 21 y 44 años (edad de excarcelación) fueron el protocolo de clasificación y tratamiento, el expediente penitenciario y el expediente social. Aplicando un análisis estadístico descriptivo mediante tablas de contingencia, las características de las variables que mostraron porcentajes más altos de reincidencia fueron: la ausencia de hábitos laborales, la patología infecciosa por VIH, los niveles altos de extraversión, la finalización del tratamiento extrapenitenciario en comunidad terapéutica con expulsión o abandono y el menor tiempo de permanencia en la comunidad terapéutica. Estos resultados sugieren que la prevención de la reincidencia puede tener resultados positivos, si somos capaces de influir sobre estas variables a través del tratamiento penitenciario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;18(3): 613-627, sept.-dic. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98384</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores dinámicos de la reincidencia de reclusos drogodependientes en tratamiento en comunidad terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5221</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31825^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10546^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11766^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
