<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72495</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spondylodiscitis: Diagnosis and medium-long term follow up of 18 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Spondylodiscitis is an uncommon disease in children. It is often misdiagnosed or the diagnosis is made late in the course of illness. Objectives: To review the clinical, analytical and radiological characteristics of children with spondylodiscitis in the Materno-Infantil Hospital of Malaga. Patients and methods: Retrospective cohort study on children diagnosed with spondylodiscitis, during a period of 11 years. Results: Eighteen patients were included in the study. Spondylodiscitis was more frequent in patients younger than 3 years old and older than 12 years old. The average time of delay in diagnosis was 26.9 days. In 8 cases the diagnosis was missed initially. Three clinical patterns appeared: in children under 3 years of age, refusing to walk and sit (100%) and irritability (42%); between 3 and 12 years of age, limb (100%) and abdominal pain (100%); in adolescents, back pain (75%). Fever was present in 38% of the cases, and low-grade fever in 8 (44%). A total of 50% of the patients had a moderate leucocytosis, and a slight increase in ESR; the most frequent location was L3-L4. X-ray diagnosis was pathological in 88% of the cases. The initial MRI diagnosed 100% of the cases. In addition, nerve roots damage (5 cases), inflammatory masses/paravertebral abscesses (5), epidural abscess (1) and psoas abscesses (2) were detected. A total of 94% of the children received antibiotics and 100% of the children underwent immobilization. All patients recovered early after the beginning of treatment, with the exception of those affected by psoas abscesses. The radiological follow-up was done in 17 patients (12 by MRI). After a mean of 14 months (rank 1&#150;48), persistent diminution of disc space was seen in 100% of the children, and improvement of soft-tissue inflammation. Clinically (follow-up only in 11 patients) all patients regained normal mobility and only 27% had moderate pain. Conclusion: Spondylodiscitis, whose delay in the diagnosis is frequent, is a serious illness. Complications include abscesses and nerve root damage. MRI is the study of choice to determine the extension to neighbouring tissues (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez León, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Pascual, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinosa Fernández, M. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tapia Moreno, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Gómez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La espondilodiscitis en niños es poco frecuente. Es habitual un retraso en el diagnóstico y errores en el mismo. Objetivos: Revisar las características clínicas, analíticas y radiológicas de los niños con espondilodiscitis en el Hospital Materno-Infantil Carlos Haya de Málaga. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de los niños diagnosticados de espondilodiscitis en este hospital, durante un período de 10 años. Resultados: Se estudiaron 18 pacientes. Fue más frecuente en menores de 3 años y mayores de 12. El tiempo medio de retraso en el diagnóstico resultó de 26,9 días, con diagnóstico inicial erróneo en 8 casos. Se presentaron 3 patrones clínicos: en menores de 3 años, rechazo de la marcha y sedestación (100%) e irritabilidad (42%); entre 3 y 12 años, impotencia funcional de extremidades inferiores (EEII) (100%) y dolor abdominal (100%); en adolescentes, molestias de la espalda (75%). Apareció fiebre en el 38% de los casos y febrícula en 8 casos (44%). El 50% presentó leucocitosis moderada, con discreta elevación de la velocidad de sedimentación globular. Las localizaciones más frecuentes fueron L3-L4 y L4-L5. La radiografía al diagnóstico resultó patológica en el 83% de los casos. La RM al ingreso fue diagnóstica en el 100%. Detectó además afectación de raíces nerviosas (5 casos), masas inflamatorias/abscesos paravertebrales (5), absceso epidural (1) y abscesos del psoas (2). Recibió tratamiento antibiótico el 94% de los niños e inmovilización el 100%. Todos experimentaron rápida mejoría tras el inicio del tratamiento, excepto los afectados de abscesos del psoas. El seguimiento radiológico, realizado en 17 pacientes (12 mediante RM), a los 14 meses de media (rango 1&#150;48), mostró disminución o desaparición del espacio discal en el 100% de los niños y mejoría de las masas de partes blandas. En el seguimiento clínico (recogido en 11 pacientes) todos conservaban motilidad normal y el 27% dolor leve-moderado. Conclusión: La espondilodiscitis, cuyo retraso en el diagnóstico es frecuente, no es una entidad banal, ya que puede complicarse con abscesos y daño de raíces nerviosas. La RM es la prueba de elección para determinar su extensión a los tejidos vecinos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(5): 391-399, nov. 2009. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72495</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Espondilodiscitis: diagnóstico y seguimiento a medio-largo plazo de 18 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8141^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23612^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d41^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
