<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97685</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Involuntary outpatient treatment (IOT) for severe mental patients: current situation in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Involuntary Outpatient Treatment (IOT) expects to improve treatment compliance and, therefore, prevent the impairment of patients with severe mental illness, as well as the risk for them and others. Besides IOT introduction defenders and opponent&#146;s states, scientific literature offers contradictory results. Legislative changes have been taken in the vast majority of our neighbouring countries in order to regulate IOT application. There is no legal regulation in Spain; however, OIT application is possible in certain Spanish cities. This article reviews IOT in Spain and surrounding countries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calabuig-Crespo, Roman</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lera-Calatayud, Calatayud</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Prieto, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal-Cercós, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Viadel, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañete-Nicolás, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asensio-Pascual, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido-Rodríguez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento ambulatorio involuntario (TAI) pretende mejorar la adherencia al tratamiento y, por tanto, prevenirlas recaídas y el deterioro de las personas con enfermedad mental grave. Además de las posiciones manifestadas a favor y en contra con la introducción del TAI, los estudios publicados en la literatura médica obtienen también resultados contradictorios. En la mayoría de los países de nuestro entorno, se han producido cambios legislativos que regulan su aplicación. En la actualidad no existe en España una normativa legal, sin embargo, es posible su aplicación en el ámbito local de algunas ciudades españolas. En este artículo se pretende hacer una revisión del TAI en los países de nuestro entorno y España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;40(1): 27-33, ene.-feb. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97685</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situacion en España del tratamiento ambulatorio involuntario (TAI) para enfermos mentales graves</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
