<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118340</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Surgical site infections: Antibiotic prophylaxis in surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Surgical site infections (SSI) are very common, and represent more than 20% of all hospital-acquired infections. SSIs are associated with a higher mortality, as well as to an extended hospital stay and costs, depending on the surgical procedure and type of SSI. Advances in control practices for these infections include improvement in operating room ventilation, sterilization methods, barriers, and surgical techniques, as well as in surgical antimicrobial prophylaxis. For the latter, the antimicrobial agent should: be active against the most common pathogens, be administered in an appropriate dosage and in a timeframe to ensure serum and tissue concentrations over the period of potential contamination, be safe, and be administered over the shortest effective time period to minimize adverse events, development of resistances, and cost (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Asensio, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones de la localización quirúrgica (ILQ) son muy frecuentes y representan más del 20% del total de infecciones hospitalarias. Las ILQ se asocian a una mayor mortalidad y a un exceso de la estancia hospitalaria y de los costes, dependiendo del procedimiento quirúrgico y del tipo de ILQ. Los avances en las prácticas de control de estas infecciones incluyen la mejora en la ventilación de los quirófanos, en los métodos de esterilización, en las barreras, en las técnicas quirúrgicas y en la profilaxis antibiótica. Para dicha profilaxis el agente antimicrobiano debería: ser activo frente a los patógenos más frecuentes, ser administrado en una dosis apropiada y en un momento que asegure concentraciones en suero y tejido durante el periodo de la potencial contaminación, ser seguro, y ser administrado durante el más corto periodo de tiempo efectivo para minimizar los efectos adversos, el desarrollo de resistencias y los costes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(1): 48-53, ene. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118340</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección de la localización quirúrgica. Profilaxis antimicrobiana en cirugía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13912^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
