<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157379</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Expert Recommendations on Treating Psoriasis in Special Circumstances (Part II)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: There is insufficient information on how best to treat moderate to severe psoriasis in difficult clinical circumstances. Material and methods: We considered 5 areas where there is conflicting or insufficient evidence: pediatric psoriasis, risk of infection in patients being treated with biologics, psoriasis in difficult locations, biologic drug survival, and impact of disease on quality of life. Following discussion of the issues by an expert panel of dermatologists specialized in the management of psoriasis, participants answered a questionnaire survey according to the Delphi method. Results: Consensus was reached on 66 (70.9%) of the 93 items analyzed; the experts agreed with 49 statements and disagreed with 17. It was agreed that body mass index, metabolic comorbidities, and quality of life should be monitored in children with psoriasis. The experts also agreed that the most appropriate systemic treatment for this age group was methotrexate, while the most appropriate biologic treatment was etanercept. Although it was recognized that the available evidence was inconsistent and difficult to extrapolate, the panel agreed that biologic drug survival could be increased by flexible, individualized dosing regimens, continuous treatment, and combination therapies. Finally, consensus was reached on using the Dermatology Quality of Life Index to assess treatment effectiveness and aid decision-making in clinical practice. Conclusions: The structured opinion of experts guides decision-making regarding aspects of clinical practice for which there is incomplete or conflicting information (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Yanguas, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas, R de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Ferriols, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: En situaciones clínicas difíciles de psoriasis moderada y grave la información sobre las estrategias terapéuticas más adecuadas es insuficiente. Material y métodos: Se plantearon 5 escenarios: psoriasis pediátrica, infecciones en pacientes tratados con biológicos, localizaciones difíciles, supervivencia de las terapias biológicas e impacto en la calidad de vida, identificando aquellas cuestiones en las que la evidencia era controvertida o insuficiente. Tras la discusión con un grupo de dermatólogos expertos en el manejo de la psoriasis moderada-grave, se llevó a cabo un cuestionario que fue implementado según la metodología Delphi. Resultados: Se alcanzó el consenso en 66 de los 93 ítems finales planteados (70,9%) (49 en el acuerdo, 17 en el desacuerdo). Se acordó la conveniencia de incorporar la evaluación del índice de masa corporal, las comorbilidades metabólicas y la medición de la calidad de vida en el seguimiento de la psoriasis infantil. En este grupo de edad, el metotrexato y el etanercept se consideraron las mejores opciones de tratamiento sistémico y biológico, respectivamente. Aunque la evidencia científica se interpretó como heterogénea y de difícil extrapolación, se consensuó que la individualización y la flexibilidad en las dosis, el tratamiento continuo y las combinaciones terapéuticas incrementaban la supervivencia del fármaco. Se acordó la conveniencia de incorporar el índice de calidad de vida en dermatología como marcador de eficacia terapéutica y en la toma de decisiones en la práctica clínica. Conclusiones: La opinión estructurada de los expertos contribuye en la toma de decisiones en aquellos aspectos en los que la información disponible es incompleta o contradictoria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;107(9): 712-729, nov. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157379</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones de expertos para el tratamiento de la psoriasis en situaciones especiales (II)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
