<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145512</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Description of indexes based on the adherence to the Mediterranean Dietary Pattern: a review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: diet quality indexes are tools are aimed at quantifying the compliance to a defined dietary pattern. These indexes are a combined measure of dietary factors (food groups, foods, nutrients and ratios) and/ or lifestyles factors. The Mediterranean Diet (MD) is a dietary pattern characterized by their positive effects against chronic diseases. There have been many indexes proposed for the assessment of this dietary pattern. An evaluation of their composition and health benefits is therefore convenient. Objective: the objective is to evaluate indexes of adherence to the MD with regard to their definition, methodological issues and validation as reported in epidemiological studies. Methods: we searched in PubMed for studies that developed MD Indexes up to October 2014. Results: a total number of 22 indexes were identified, with differences regarding the number of components (7-28), scoring (0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 8 or 10, in case of compliance), range (0-100) and type of components (which could be food groups/foods or their combination, with nutrients). Among the positive components, fruits and vegetables were the most common and meats, among the negative components. There were also differences with regard to their composition and evaluation (e.g. criteria of moderate alcohol consumption), as well as with the scoring system (in medians, terciles or established servings). Conclusions: this review suggests that since there is great heterogeneity in the definition of MD. It would be therefore convenient to establish more clearly the components to be included and to establish commonly defined criteria to quantify this dietary pattern (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Villanova, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amiano, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azpiri, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Ruiz, Angela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra Hernández, Eduardo J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Montes, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los índices de calidad la de dieta son herramientas que sirven para cuantificar el cumplimiento de un patrón dietético definido. Estos índices son una medida combinada de factores dietéticos (grupos alimenticios, alimentos, nutrientes y ratios) y/o estilos de vida. La dieta mediterránea (DM) es un patrón dietético que se caracteriza por sus efectos positivos contra ciertas enfermedades crónicas. Existen numerosos índices propuestos para la valoración de este patrón dietético. Es por lo tanto conveniente una evaluación de su composición y sus efectos sobre la salud. Objetivo: el objetivo es evaluar los índices de adhesión al patrón dietético mediterráneo en cuanto a su definición, aspectos metodológicos y validación en estudios epidemiológicos. Métodos: se buscaron en PubMed estudios que desarrollaron índices de DM hasta octubre de 2014. Resultados: se identificaron un total de 22 índices, con diferencias en cuanto al número de componentes (7-28), puntuación (0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 8 o 10, en el caso de cumplimiento), rango (0-100) y tipo de componentes (grupos de alimentos/alimentos o su combinación con nutrientes). Entre los componentes positivos, los más comunes fueron frutas y verduras, y carnes entre los negativos. También hubo diferencias con respecto a su composición y evaluación (p. ej. criterios de consumo moderado de alcohol), así como con el sistema de puntuación (en medianas, terciles o raciones establecidas). Conclusiones: esta revisión sugiere que existe una gran heterogeneidad en la definición de DM. Sería por tanto apropiado establecer con mayor claridad los componentes que deben incluirse, así como definir criterios comunes para cuantificar este patrón dietético (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(5): 1872-1884, nov. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145512</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de índices basados en la adhesión al patrón dietético mediterráneo: una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54847^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
