<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121746</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Communication pathology. Teaching project for child nursing. Dyslalias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dyslalia, bad known as a language disorder, is undoubtedly one of the most common childhood speech communication pathologies. Although nursing provide health care to children with these difficulties along different services, pregraduate and postgraduate training regarding communication pathology is very poor. Through an extensive updated searched literature in the Virtual Library System of Andalusia Public Health, is intended to present the most relevant aspects about dyslalia with pure teaching objective with the aim of improving nursing records, getting correct use in speech therapy terminology and achieving quality and identity in providing nursing care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campos Palomo, Álvaro David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Palomo, Laura Deseada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La dislalia, mal conocida como trastorno del lenguaje, es sin duda una de las patologías de la comunicación, concretamente del habla, más común en la infancia. A pesar de que en los distintos servicios de salud en los que presta sus cuidados la profesión de enfermería se encuentran niños con estas dificultades, la formación profesional tanto pre como postgrado es muy deficiente en lo que a patología de la comunicación respecta. Mediante una exhaustiva búsqueda bibliográfica actualizada en la Biblioteca Virtual del Sistema Público de Salud de Andalucía, se pretende dar a conocer los aspectos más relevantes de las dislalias con un objetivo púramente docente, lo que resultará en una mejora en los registros de enfermería, en el uso correcto de la terminología logopédica y en un avance en la coordinación interprofesional, consiguiendo con ello dar calidad e identidad a los cuidados de enfermería (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;13(34): 444-452, abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121746</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patologías de la comunicación. Proyecto docente para enfermería infantil. Dislalias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3178^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29287^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29287^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1191^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52965^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29287^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
