<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96020</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biliary complications after liver transplant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">There have been biliary complications since the beginning of liver transplants, and is a topic of great interest due to its high incidence, as well as their influence on morbidity and mortality. The biliary fistula is currently uncommon and its management is straightforward. Anastomotic stenosis continues to have an incidence of 10-15%. Although the current treatment of choice is endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP), surgical treatment (hepatico-jejunostomy) continues to have an important role. Non-anastomotic stenosis has an incidence of 5-10%, and is associated with ischaemic or immunological factors, and usually involves a re-transplant. Choledocholithiasis has an incidence of 5-10%, with the treatment of choice being ERCP. However the treatment of biliary complications should be individualised. We must take into account, liver function, the general health status of the patient, and the availability and experience of the team in the different therapeutic options (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fabregat, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lladó, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torras, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baliellas, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rafecas, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las complicaciones biliares postrasplante hepático han sido desde los incios de su historia tema de gran interés por su elevada incidencia, y su influencia en la morbi mortalidad. La fístula biliar es actualmente infrecuente, y su manejo sencillo. La estenosis anastomótica mantiene una incidencia del 10-15%. Si bien se considera que el tratamiento de elección actual es mediante CPRE, el tratamiento quirúrgico (hepaticoyeyunostomía) sigue teniendo un papel relevante. Las estenosis no-anastomóticas tienen una incidencia del 5-10%, se relacionan con factores isquémicos o inmunológicos y su tratamiento habitualmente es el retrasplante. La coledocolitiasis tiene una incidencia del 5-10%, siendo el tratamiento de elección la CPRE. Sin embargo, el tratamiento de las complicaciones biliares, deberá ser individualizado. Deberemos tener en cuenta el momento del diagnóstico, la función hepática, el estado general del paciente, y la disponibilidad y experiencia del equipo en las diferentes opciones terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);90(1): 4-10, ene. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones biliares tras el trasplante hepático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38794^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29326^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201201</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
