<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142339</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional status at the time of admission among patients admitted to a tertiary-care paediatric hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze the nutrition status of the pediatric patients at the time of hospital admission throughout a calendar year in a tertiary level hospital and to identify those patients and/or groups of pathologies with a higher risk of malnutrition. Material and methods: retrospective evaluation of nutrition status of 852 patients hospitalized in 2013 in a pediatric hospital (462 males and 390 females). Sex, age, body mass index at the moment of admission and days of hospitalization and diagnosis codified according to the International Classification of Diseases were registered. Results: the prevalence of malnutrition patients registered at the moment of admission was 8.2%. Excess body weight (overweight and obesity) was detected in 18% of the patients. The diseases of the nervous system (22.9%), together with the diseases of the respiratory system, the infectious diseases (18.6%), the congenital malformations (11.4%) and the diseases of the genitorurinary system (8.6%) account for 84.4% of the cases with malnutrition. Conclusions: the overall prevalence rate for malnutrition in pediatric patients at the moment of admission in our hospital was 8.2%, being this figure similar to those published in occidental countries. It should be mandatory to accomplish an initial screening and follow up during hospitalization of younger patients and those suffering from diseases of the nervous and/or respiratory system and, especially, from congenital diseases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vaquero Íñigo, Ibone</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durá Travé, Teodoro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Benavides, Aida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Aguirre, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iceta Elízaga, Ainhoa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Martín García, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la situación nutricional de los pacientes en el momento del ingreso hospitalario a lo largo de un año natural e identificar a aquellos pacientes y/o grupos de enfermedades con mayor riesgo de malnutrición. Material y métodos: valoración retrospectiva de la situación nutricional de 852 pacientes hospitalizados durante el año 2013 en un hospital pediátrico (462 varones y 390 mujeres). De cada paciente se registraron el sexo, edad, peso y talla, índice de masa corporal (IMC), estancia hospitalaria y diagnóstico según la Clasificación Internacional de las Enfermedades (CIE-10). Resultados: la prevalencia de malnutrición al ingreso era del 8,2%, y la de sobrepeso/obesidad del 18%. Las enfermedades neurológicas (22,9%), junto con las respiratorias (22,9%), infecciosas (18,6%), malformaciones congénitas (11,4%) y genitourinarias (8,6%) representaban el 84,4% de los casos de malnutrición. Conclusiones: la tasa de prevalencia de malnutrición en los pacientes pediátricos al ingreso era del 8,2%; siendo esta cifra prácticamente similar a las publicadas en los países occidentales. Los pacientes con menor edad y afectos de enfermedades neurológicas y/o respiratorias y, especialmente, con enfermedades congénitas tenían un mayor riesgo de presentar malnutrición, siendo preceptivo realizar un cribado nutricional inicial y un seguimiento durante su hospitalización (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(6): 2465-2471, jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142339</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación nutricional en el momento del ingreso en un hospital pediátrico terciario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23583^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6932^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
