<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131529</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality indicators design: acute pain process in the emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Title: Quality indicators design: acute pain process in the emergency department The evaluation of the quality of care delivered in the pediatric emergency department (PED) requires tools such as quality indicators, which consider the most important aspects and allow monitoring. Given the importance of the process of pain in clinical practice, it is essential to assess the current approach to the acute pain process in the PED and develop quality indicators for acute pain process evaluation. The aim of this paper is to present the process of developing quality indicators for the assessment of pain processing in the PED. The indicators&#146; develop is done by consensus of the authors and discussion in the Pain&#146;s Hospital Commission. They are   based on the adult&#146;s indicators and pediatric needs. To createeach indicator we use the methodology recommended by the &#147;Grupo de Trabajo de Definición de Indicadores de la Agencia de Evaluación y Tecnología e Investigación Médica del Servicio Catalán de Salud&#148;. Seven indicators are developed: two indicators about the pain diagnosis, and five about the pain treatment. The application of indicators developed let you know if the process is appropriate and implement improvement measures (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trenchs Sainz de la Maza, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luaces Cubells, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Constantí, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jabalera Contreras, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perello Riera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evaluación de la calidad de la asistencia prestada en los servicios de urgencias pediátricas requiere herramientas como los indicadores de calidad, que contemplen sus aspectos más importantes y permitan su monitorización. Dada la importancia del proceso del dolor en la práctica clínica, es imprescindible disponer de indicadores que nos permitan evaluarlo de forma correcta, detectar situaciones de mejora y crear programas de autoevaluación de la calidad. El objetivo de este trabajo es presentar el proceso de elaboración de indicadores de calidad para la evaluación del proceso del dolor en urgencias. El diseño de los indicadores se realiza por consenso de los autores y discusión en la Comisión del Dolor del Hospital Sant Joan de Déu a partir de los existentes en adultos y las necesidades pediátricas. La metodología para crear cada indicador es la misma que ha utilizado el Grupo de Trabajo de Definición de Indicadores de la Agencia de Evaluación y Tecnología e Investigación Médica del Servicio Catalán de Salud. Se diseñan siete indicadores: dos valoran el diagnóstico del  dolor y cinco su tratamiento. La aplicación de los indicadores diseñados permitirá saber si el proceso es adecuado e implementar medidas de mejora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;72(11): e379-e383, dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131529</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diseño de indicadores de calidad: el proceso del dolor agudo en el servicio de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10565^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
