<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108643</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of the pharmaceutical performances in a department of hospital pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The aim of this study was to describe the pharmacist performances undertaken in a Department of Hospital Pharmacy, to assess the degree of acceptance by the medical staff and to evaluate their clinical significance. Methods: A retrospective and descriptive study about the pharmacist performances done in official form from the Drug Distribution System of medications in Unitary Doses of the Pharmacy Department at the University Hospital. The variables collected were: demographic data of patients and the pharmacotherapy of pharmacist performances. The information was registered into a Microsoft Office Excel® database. A modified and adapted Iaser ® methodology was employed to define the interventions and assess their significance and clinical impact. To evaluate the degree of acceptance, a computerized system of the Pharmacy Department was used. Processing Statistics: SPSS®. Results: A total of 484 pharmacist performances were recorded during the 6 months the study lasted. Major ATC groups of drugs involved were: J-Anti-infective (37%), C-Cardiology (23%) and ADigestive (19%). The degree of acceptance was almost of 50%. The most frequent causes of action were modifications of drug dose / schedule / route of administration for inadequate dosage (39.5%) or suggesting different therapeutical alternatives due to the absence of the drug in the pharmaceutical guide (33.1%). 75% of the pharmacist performances were considered signifi cant. Conclusions: The validation of medical orders by the pharmacist detects drug-related problems and can prevent and resolve negative outcomes associated with medication. The results indicate that it would be necessary to introduce measures of improvement to increase the degree of acceptance by the physician, such as the implantation of more effi cient communication systems. The collaboration between a patient care team is absolutely necessary to improve the quality of our health services and ensure the patients safety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aznar Prats, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Ferrando, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Gil, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las actuaciones farmacéuticas realizadas en un servicio de farmacia hospitalaria, evaluando su grado de aceptación por parte del personal médico y valorando su significación clínica. Método: Estudio descriptivo y retrospectivo de las actuaciones farmacéuticas realizadas mediante un impreso oficial desde el sistema de distribución de medicamentos en dosis unitarias del servicio de farmacia de un hospital universitario. Variables recogidas: datos sociodemográficos del paciente y datos farmacoterapéuticos de la actuación farmacéutica. La información se registró en una base de datos Microsoft Office Excel®. Para tipificar las actuaciones y valorar su significación o impacto clínico (idoneidad de la actuación farmacéutica) se empleó el método Iaser® modifi cado y adaptado. Para evaluar el grado de aceptación se utilizó el sistema informático de gestión del servicio de farmacia. El procesamiento estadístico se realizó mediante el programa SPSS®. Resultados: Se registraron 484 actuaciones farmacéuticas durante los 6 meses de duración del estudio. Los grupos ATC mayoritarios de los fármacos implicados fueron: J-antiinfecciosos (37%), C-cardiovascular (23%) y A-digestivo (19%). El grado de aceptación fue casi del 50%. Los motivos más frecuentes de actuación farmacéutica fueron la modificación de la dosis/pauta/vía de administración por una posología inadecuada (39,5%) y plantear alguna alternativa terapéutica debido a un medicamento no incluido en la Guía Farmacoterapéutica (33,1%). En cuanto a la idoneidad de las citadas actuaciones, el 75% se consideraron significativas. Conclusiones: La validación de las prescripciones médicas por parte del farmacéutico permite detectar problemas relacionados con los medicamentos y prevenir y/o resolver resultados negativos asociados a la medicación. Los resultados obtenidos nos indican que sería necesario establecer medidas de mejora para incrementar el grado de aceptación por el personal médico facultativo, como la implantación de un sistema de comunicación más eficaz. La colaboración dentro de un equipo clínico multidisciplinario es necesaria para mejorar la calidad asistencial y garantizar la seguridad de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;13(2): 66-73, mar.-abr. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108643</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de las actuaciones farmacéuticas realizadas en un servicio de farmacia hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
