<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057229</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-695X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic compliance and quality of life in chronic patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine treatment compliance and health perception at two Primary Health Centres,        in which a standardized treatment protocol was used.        Design. Clinical trial.        Setting. Primary Health Centres at Sillería and Ocaña (Toledo).        Subjects. Patients aged &amp;#8805; 18 years, in the portfolio services being treated for hypertension, dyslipidaemia        and diabetes. A simple random sampling from the lists of these patients was made.        Main measurement. Patients in both groups were given a sheet setting out health-dietary measures        and advice on treatment compliance. The intervention group were also given a sheet of chronic treatments..        There were four two-monthly visits over a follow-up period of eight months. Pill count was        used to determine treatment compliance. At the fi rst and last visit the Spanish version of the EuroQol-        5D was performed.        Results. A total of 309 patients with an average age of 69.2 ± 10.7 years were included in the study        (55.3% were women). Of these patients, 156 patients were randomised to the intervention group and        153 to the control group. At the fi nal visit, 173 patients had good treatment compliance (63.1%; CI        95%, 57.4 - 68.8), as opposed to 152 at the baseline visit (55.5%; CI 95%, 49.6 - 61.4), Chi-square =        96.7 and p &lt; 0,0001. At the fi nal visit, no signifi cant differences were found between the two groups        as regards treatment compliance. There were no differences in health perception between the two        study groups.        Conclusions. The standardized treatment document did not contribute to an improvement in treatment        compliance in the intervention group. Interventionand follow-up improved treatment compliance in both groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Vega, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Abuin, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gozalo Yuste, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Calcerrada Jiménez, Rosa María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orueta Sánchez, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Comas Samper, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cristóbal Rodríguez Roca, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Moreno, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cid Calo, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lougedo Calderón, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Calvo, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer el cumplimiento terapéutico y percepción de salud en dos Centros de Salud, en los        que se utilizó un documento normalizado de tratamiento.        Diseño. Ensayo clínico.        Emplazamiento. Zonas de Salud de Sillería y Ocaña (Toledo).        Participantes. Pacientes, de edad &amp;#8805; 18 años, en cartera de servicios que siguen tratamiento para la        hipertensión, dislipemia y Diabetes Mellitus. Se realizó un muestreo aleatorio simple de los listados        de estos pacientes.        Mediciones principales. En los dos grupos se entregó un documento sobre medidas higiénico-dietéticas        y consejos de cumplimentación farmacológica. En el grupo de intervención además del documento        anterior se entregó una hoja de tratamientos crónicos. Se realizaron cuatro visitas bimensuales        en un periodo de seguimiento de ocho meses. Para el estudio del cumplimento terapéutico se utilizó el        recuento de comprimidos. En la primera y última visita se pasó la versión española del EuroQol-5D.        Resultados. Se incluyeron en el estudio 309 pacientes con una edad media de 69,2 ± 10,7 años        (55,3% eran mujeres). Un total de 156 pacientes fueron aleatorizados al grupo de intervención y 153        al grupo control.        En la última visita 173 pacientes cumplieron adecuadamente el tratamiento (63,1%; IC 95%: 57,4        - 68,8), frente a 152 en la visita basal del estudio (55,5%; IC 95%: 49,6 - 61,4), Chi-cuadrado = 96,7        y p &lt; 0,0001.        Al analizar el número de pacientes cumplidores por grupo de estudio, en la visita fi nal, no se encontraron        diferencias signifi cativas entre ambos grupos. Los grupos del estudio no mostraron diferencias        en la percepción de su propia salud.        Conclusiones. El documento normalizado de tratamiento no aportó una mejora en el cumplimiento        terapéutico del grupo de intervención. La intervención realizada en ambos grupos y el seguimiento        mejoró el cumplimiento terapéutico en ambos grupos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. clín. med. fam;2(1): 5-10, jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057229</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cumplimiento terapéutico y calidad de vida en pacientes crónicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
