<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59515</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intrasession pain and chronic pain in patients receiving haemodialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pain is a prevalent symptom in haemodialysis, but frequentlygoes unnoticed. The limited amount of studies dealing with painin dialysis refer mainly to chronic pain.Objectives: to learn about the characteristics of pain duringhaemodialysis sessions and about the chronic pain experiencedby patients undergoing this treatment, analgesic measurestaken and the possible interference of pain with dailylife activities (DLA), as well as the differences between bothtypes of pain.Design: cross-sectional, descriptive study that included alloverage patients who had received haemodialysis for over amonth in the Haemodialysis Unit of the Manacor Hospital betweenfebruary 2005 and february 2006.Methodology: pain assessment in two phases: intradialysispain and chronic pain, using several measurement scales:McGill Pain Questionnaire (MPQ) for quantitative and qualitativecharacteristics of pain; Analog Visual Scale (AVS) forpain intensity; Pain Management Index (PMI) for assessmentof pharmacological measures and the Brief Pain Inventory(BPI) for exploration of pain in relation to DLAs.Results and conclusions: 27 patients (mean age 66,7±13,6)presenting a high prevalence of intradialysis pain, of moderateintensity, and most frequently caused by ischemic pain,were analyzed. Posture, modification of dialysis parameters,physical measures and pharmacological treatment lessenedthe pain. The prevalence of chronic pain was also high, thoughsignificantly less than intrasession pain, and most frequentlyderived from a musculoskeletal origin. Pain intensity wasmild or moderate and was significantly better treated. The durationof dialysis was significantly associated with pain intensityand pain intensity with hyperthyroidism levels. Generalactivity and movement/walking were the DLAs mostaffected by pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sánchez, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Calero, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Navarro, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calls Ginesta, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor es un síntoma prevalente en hemodiálisis, pero pasa frecuentementeinadvertido. Los escasos estudios sobre el dolor en diálisis hacen referencia principalmente al dolor crónico. Objetivos: conocer las características del dolor durante la sesión de hemodiálisis y las del dolor crónico en pacientes que reciben esta terapia, las medidas analgésicas utilizadas y la posible interferencia del dolor en las actividades de la vida diaria (AVDs),así como las diferencias entre los dos tipos de dolor. Diseño: estudio descriptivo y transversal, en el que se incluyeron todos los pacientes mayores de edad que recibían hemodiálisisdurante más de un mes en la Unidad de Hemodiálisis del Hospital de Manacor, entre febrero de 2005 y febrerode 2006. Metodología: valoración del dolor en dos fases: dolor intradialisisy dolor crónico, mediante diversas escalas de medición: McGill Pain Questionnaire (MPQ) para las características cuantitativas y cualitativas del dolor; Escala VisualAnalógica (EVA) para la intensidad del dolor; Índice del Manejo del dolor (PMI) para evaluación de medidas farmacológicas y el Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) para la exploración del dolor en relación con las AVDs. Resultados y conclusiones: se analizaron 27 pacientes (edad media 66,7±13,6) con alta prevalencia de dolor intradiálisis, de intensidad moderada, siendo la causa más frecuente el dolor isquémico. La postura, la modificación de los parámetros de la diálisis, las medidas físicas y el tratamiento farmacológico mejoraban este dolor. La prevalencia de (...) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;12(2): 12-18, mar. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59515</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor intrasesión y dolor crónicoen pacientes que reciben hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7140^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d712^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
