<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131094</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of health information about the influenza vaccine on internet</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The quality of health information on internet is a question of concern to governments and users. Our aim was to determine the extent to which information about the influenza vaccine adheres to the gold standard set by the Spanish Health Ministry. Methods. Between June and July 2014 information on indications, adverse effects and counter-indications of the vaccine was evaluated to see if it adhered to this gold standard. This information was obtained through Google, using terms provided by medical students. A univariate analysis was performed, where the variable result was getting information that adhered correctly to the standard, and explanatory variables were the type of origin of the information and its country. Results. Using the terms provided by 104 students, we obtained 134 different web links. Adhesion reached 65.7% (88/134) with respect to indication in health workers (HW). Nineteen point four percent provided incorrect information on indication in pregnant women. There was significantly better adherence in the information from official public health bodies (indication in HW (OR: 2.6), pregnant women (OR: 5.4) and immunodepressed patients (OR: 2.2). Adherence of information on Spanish web links was worse (indication in pregnancy (OR: 0.3) and counter-indication if allergic to eggs (OR: 0.5). Conclusions. Adhesion was improvable. It&#146;s necessary to promote that internet users use official public health bodies websites when they search information regarding influenza vaccine on internet (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández-García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Celador, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. La calidad de la información sanitaria en internet preocupa a gobiernos y usuarios. Nuestro objetivo fue determinar en qué medida la información sobre la vacuna antigripal se adhiere al gold estándar representado por lo establecido por el Ministerio de Sanidad español. Material y métodos. Entre junio-julio 2014 se evaluó la adhesión al gold estándar de la información sobre indicaciones, efectos adversos y contraindicaciones de la vacuna. Dicha información se obtuvo a través de Google, utilizando términos proporcionados por estudiantes de medicina. Se realizó un análisis univariante, donde variable resultado fue obtener información correctamente adherida, y variables explicativas fueron el tipo de origen de la información y su país. Resultados. Con los términos de 104 alumnos se obtuvieron 134 enlaces web diferentes. La adhesión alcanzó el 65,7% (88/134) en cuanto a la indicación en trabajadores sanitarios (TS). El 19,4% aportaron información incorrecta sobre indicación en embarazadas. La información de organismos oficiales de salud pública se adhirió significativamente mejor (indicación en TS (OR: 2,6), embarazadas (OR: 5,4) e inmunodeprimidos (OR: 2,2). La información de enlaces web españoles se adhirió peor (indicación en embarazo (OR: 0,3) y contraindicación si alergia al huevo (OR: 0,5). Conclusiones. El nivel de adhesión detectado fue mejorable. Se debe urgir y promocionar en los usuarios la utilización de las páginas web de organismos oficiales de salud pública cuando busquen información sobre la vacuna antigripal en internet (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;37(3): 371-380, sept.-dic. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la información sanitaria disponible en internet sobre la vacuna antigripal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
