<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045345</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Differential characteristics of primary acute pericarditis and severe pericardial effusion without tamponade</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim or our study was to evaluate the main clinical and etiological features or primary acute pericarditis with severe pericardial effusion without cardiac tamponade. Our experience included 35 patients with this problem diagnosed in the last 5 years. Patients with a previous potential etiology for acute pericarditis were excluded. The diagnostic protocol identified a specific etiology in 20% of patients, the most frequent being idiopathic forms. Patients with severe pericardial effusion without cardiac tamponade who had a favourable clinical outcome on nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs therapy presented a lower proportion of specific etiology than those with a poor response to this therapy (8% versus 45%; p = 0.03). An exhaustive etiological investigation, including diagnostic pericardiocentesis should be reserved for these patients with unfavourable response to antiinflammatory drug therapy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de Castroviejo del Campo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Siles Rubio, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anguita Sánchez, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Domínguez, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es evaluar las principales características clínicas y etiológicas de las pericarditis agudas primarias que se inician con derrame severo sin taponamiento. Presentamos nuestra experiencia en 35 pacientes en los últimos 5 años. Todos los pacientes en los que hubiese una causa potencial de pericarditis en la primera valoración clínica fueron descartados. El protocolo diagnóstico encaminado a la búsqueda de una etiología específica ha obtenido un rendimiento global del 20%, siendo, por tanto, las formas idiopáticas las más frecuentes. Los casos con derrame severo y respuesta favorable al tratamiento presentaron menor proporción de etiologías específicas que los que no respondieron al tratamiento con antiinflamatorios no esteroideos (el 8% frente al 45%; p = 0,03). Es, por tanto,en estos últimos en los que se justificaría una investigación etiológica exhaustiva, incluyendo una pericardiocentesis diagnóstica dada la mayor probabilidad de hallar una causa específica de la enfermedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;206(3): 141-143, mar. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045345</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características diferenciales de las pericarditis agudas primarias con derrame pericárdico severo sin taponamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10682^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10682^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10681^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10681^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
