<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73653</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ciprofloxacin-associated bilateral Achilles tendinitis in absence of risk factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ciprofloxacin is the quinolone used most, which is why there are more cases of tendon disease reported for this drug. The quinolone-induced clinical picture of tendinitis is characterized by its rapid initiation and its preferentially affected site is the Achilles tendon. The appearance of tendinitis may occur from the second-third day until the fifth or sixth week of treatment initiation, the involvement frequently being bilateral. The symptoms generally disappear after withdrawing the antibiotic. As associated risk factors, we can mention elderly age, prolonged treatment with corticosteroids, renal failure, multiresistant tuberculosis, hemodialysis, peripheral vascular disease and associated rheumatic disease. There is no effective complementary method for its diagnosis, the diagnosis always being clinical. Withdrawal of the drug is essential for the reestablishment of normality of the tendinous condition, although adequate and early management does not prevent a long recovery time and there is always risk of functional sequel. New quinolones are continuing appearing and their use is increasing. This reaction is common to the group so that follow-up of the patients who are going to be administered quinolones would be recommendable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Muñiz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abadín  Delgado, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañamero Espejo, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alanís Lopez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El ciprofloxacino es la quinolona más usada; debido a esto, el mayor número de casos de tendinopatías comunicados se deben a su uso. El cuadro clínico de la tendinitis producida por quinolonas se caracteriza por su instauración rápida y por afectar como localización preferente al tendón de Aquiles. La aparición de la tendinitis puede suceder desde el segundo o tercer día hasta la quinta o sexta semana de iniciado el tratamiento, siendo con frecuencia la afectación bilateral y soliendo desaparecer la sintomatología al retirar el antibiótico. Como factores de riesgo asociados podemos citar la edad avanzada, el tratamiento prolongado con corticoides, la insuficiencia renal, la tuberculosis multirresistente, la hemodiálisis, la vasculopatía periférica y la enfermedad reumática asociada. Para el diagnóstico no existe ningún método complementario efectivo, siendo en todos los casos el diagnóstico clínico. La retirada del fármaco es esencial para el restablecimiento a la normalidad de la patología tendinosa, aunque el manejo adecuado y temprano no previene de un tiempo de recuperación prolongado, existiendo siempre el riesgo de una secuela funcional. Cada vez están apareciendo nuevas quinolonas y está aumentando su utilización, siendo esta reacción común de grupo, por lo que sería recomendable el seguimiento de los pacientes a los que se les administran quinolonas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(8): 415-416, oct. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73653</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendinitis aquílea bilateral por ciprofloxacino en ausencia de factores de riesgo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d134^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12496</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d134^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24008^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d903^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24008^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
