<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167274</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1989</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The woman and the care of life. Historical understanding and future perspectives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over the ages of humanity, women has established a special relationship life care &amp;#769;s with the most vulnerable. Women dedicated to the professional care have always existed, also to the unpaid home care of the sick, elderly, with some disability, and children. This study has been carried out a historical and current verification of this question, marking its most characteristic and significant features. From that perspective, we tried to answer these key questions: causes that have motivated this fact, its social consequences and, finally, the most important future implications for all, men and women that, surely, we will be caregivers and strapped for care in our illness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Massé García, M Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mujer ha establecido una especial relación con el cuidado de la vida más vulnerable durante toda la historia de la humanidad hasta nuestros días. Siempre ha habido y hay, aunque en proporciones muy desigualmente repartidas, mujeres dedicadas al cuidado profesional y también al cuidado no remunerado domiciliario de las personas enfermas, ancianas, con alguna discapacidad, de los niños. En este estudio se ha llevado a cabo una constatación histórica y actual de esta realidad, marcando sus rasgos más característicos y significativos. Y, a partir de ahí, intenta responder a las cuestiones clave que surgen: las causas que han motivado este hecho, sus consecuencias sociales y, finalmente, las más importantes implicaciones de futuro para todos, hombres y mujeres que, tarde o temprano, seremos tanto cuidadores como necesitados de los cuidados en nuestra enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad Bioet;28(94): 291-301, sept.-dic. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167274</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La mujer y el cuidado de la vida. Comprensión histórica y perspectivas de futuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13124</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15330^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11254^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15329^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5082</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30989^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
