<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80073</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic adrenalectomy: Presentation of 43 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The aim of the study was to present and analyse our experience in laparoscopic adrenalectomy (LA).Materials and methods Descriptive and retrospective study including LA performed over 8 years, between 2000 and 2008 in our hospital. Results A total of 43 LA were performed to 41 patients using a transperitoneal lateral approach. Indications for adrenalectomy included hyperaldosteronism (19), non-functioning adenoma (8), phaeochromocytoma (6), Cushing's syndrome (6), metastasis (3) and adrenal primary tumour (1). Median postoperative hospital stay was 3 days and the median size of the masses was 30mm (range: 4&#150;155mm) Complications occurred in 3 patients (2 respiratory infections, and 1 intraoperative bleeding). There was no mortality. Only one case needed conversion to open adrenalectomy; no patients required reintervention. Conclusion Laparoscopic adrenalectomy is a safe and effective method in the treatment of adrenal masses and it can be performed with minimal risk and morbidity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ladra González, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamborino Caramés, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beiras Torrado, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puñal, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beiras Sarasquete, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paredes Cotoré, Jesús Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parada González, Purificación</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Lesquereux, Lucía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El propósito del estudio es exponer y analizar nuestra experiencia en adrenalectomía laparoscópica (AL).Material y métodos Estudio descriptivo y retrospectivo sobre AL realizada en nuestro centro desde enero de 2000 hasta diciembre de 2008.ResultadosSe realizaron un total de 43 AL a 41 pacientes mediante abordaje transperitoneal lateral. La mediana de edad de los pacientes intervenidos se situó en 53 años. La principal indicación en frecuencia de nuestra serie fue el hiperaldosteronismo (19), seguido de incidentalomas (8), feocromocitomas (6), síndrome de Cushing (6), lesiones metastásicas (3) y carcinoma suprarrenal primario (1). La media de estancia hospitalaria poscirugía fue de 3 días y la media del tamaño de las masas fue de 30mm (rango: 4&#150;155mm). No hubo mortalidad en nuestra serie. La necesidad de conversión se redujo a un caso; en ningún caso fue necesario reintervenir a un paciente. ConclusionesLa AL es una técnica segura y eficaz en el tratamiento de tumores suprarrenales que puede realizarse con riesgo y morbilidad mínima (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);87(3): 159-164, mar. 2010. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80073</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adrenalectomía laparoscópica: presentación de 43 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d318^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d310^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
