<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89950</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treating acute postoperative pain: evaluation of results on the surgical ward</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe management of acute postoperative pain on the surgical ward. To study the relationship between pain and a variety of surgical procedures and approaches. To determine the level of information patients received, their expectations, and their satisfaction with treatment of postoperative pain. Patients and methods: Cross-sectional observational study by survey and review of patient records. We studied 234 patients, including all who were hospitalized for more than 24 hours after scheduled or emergency operations. The main variables recorded were pain intensity at rest and during movement, including on the day after surgery, and the surgical procedure and approach. Results: The prevalence of pain (&gt;3 on a numerical scale) on the surgical ward was 33% at rest and 66% during movement. The prevalence of intense pain (&gt;6 on the numerical scale) was 1.7% at rest and 7.3% during movement. Factors related to greater pain intensity were timing, that is, the first day after surgery, when 74.4% of patients experienced their most intense pain; type of surgery and approach (P&lt;.004); and expecting to experience moderate or intense pain (P&lt;.001). Conclusions: Recording the prevalence of postoperative pain on a surgical ward provides information about the real situation of acute postoperative pain control. Pain on movement is a principal indicator for detecting groups of patients for whom analgesic protocols could be improved. Type of surgery and approach is a fundamental factor to consider when comparing the results of analgesic protocols(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Verd, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteve, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Describir el tratamiento global del dolor agudo postoperatorio en las salas de hospitalización quirúrgicas. Relacionar el grado de dolor con los distintos tipos de abordajes y procedimientos quirúrgicos. Por último, registrar el grado de información, las expectativas y la satisfacción de los pacientes con la atención recibida en el tratamiento del dolor postoperatorio. Pacientes y Métodos: Estudio observacional transversal mediante entrevista y revisión de historia clínica. Se evaluaron 234 pacientes, incluyendo todos los pacientes postoperados ingresados más de 24 horas a partir del día de la intervención quirúrgica, de cirugía programada o urgente. Los principales parámetros registrados fueron, la intensidad del dolor en reposo y en movimiento, el día del postoperatorio, el tipo de abordaje y el procedimiento quirúrgico. Resultados: El registro del dolor agudo postoperatorio en las salas quirúrgicas, mostró una prevalencia de dolor en reposo (valor en la escala numérica &gt; 3) del 33% y en movimiento del 66%. El porcentaje de dolor intenso (valor en la escala numérica &gt; 6) en reposo fue de 1,7% y en movimiento de 7,3%. Los factores que se relacionaron con la mayor intensidad del dolor fueron, el primer día del postoperatorio, en el que el 74,4% de los pacientes presentaron los valores máximos de dolor, el tipo de abordaje y procedimiento quirúrgico (p &lt; 0,004), y finalmente las expectativas de sufrir dolor moderado o intenso (p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: Registrar la prevalencia del dolor postoperatorio en las salas de hospitalización quirúrgicas nos permite conocer el estado actual del tratamiento del dolor agudo postoperatorio. El dolor al movimiento es uno de los principales indicadores para detectar grupos de pacientes en los que es posible mejorar las pautas analgésicas. El abordaje y el tipo de procedimiento quirúrgico es un factor básico a tener en cuenta para poder comparar resultados analgésicos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(6): 353-361, jun.-jul. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89950</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención del dolor agudo postoperatorio: evaluación de resultados en las salas de hospitalización quirúrgicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23920^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201107</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
