<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167993</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Idiopathic isolated foetal ascites</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Isolated foetal ascites is uncommon since, in most instances, it is diagnosed as being part of a clinical condition known as hydrops fetalis. We report the case of a 31-year-old secundigravida of 32 weeks and 5 days who came to A&amp;E due to the finding of isolated massive foetal ascites and polyhydramnios in a routine ultrasound. The pregnancy had had a normal course until this point. Relevant data include a nuchal translucency (NT) in the first trimester above the 99th percentile with aneuploidy screening, normal early echocardiography and ultrasound at 20 weeks without pathological findings. Once the patient was admitted to hospital, tocolysis and foetal lung maturation were indicated as well as completion of a foetal morphological ultrasound study, foetal Doppler including middle cerebral artery peak systolic velocity, irregular antibodies, TORCH and parvovirus B19 serological tests, diagnostic (study of congenital infections) and reduction amniocentesis. The tests were negative; therefore the diagnosis was isolated foetal ascites. The pregnancy was terminated by caesarean section at 33 weeks and 3 days due to pathological cardiotocography (CTG) findings. The ascites had no effect on neonatal development (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Granero Asencio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fontán Atalaya, IM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cea García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Río Romero, I del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miceli, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La ascitis fetal aislada es un cuadro poco frecuente, ya que en la mayoría de ocasiones se diagnostica formando parte del cuadro de hidrops fetal. Presentamos el caso de una secundigesta de 31 años y 32 semanas y 5 días, que acude a urgencias por el hallazgo de polihidramnios y ascitis fetal masiva aislada en una ecografía rutinaria. La gestación había tenido una evolución normal hasta el momento. Como dato relevante presentó una translucencia nucal (TN) en el primer trimestre por encima del percentil 99, con un estudio de aneuploidías y ecocardiografía precoz normales, y una ecografía a las 20 semanas sin hallazgos patológicos. Una vez ingresada la paciente se indica tocólisis, maduración pulmonar fetal, se completa el estudio ecográfico morfológico fetal, Doppler fetal incluyendo pico de velocidad sistólica de la arteria cerebral media, anticuerpos irregulares, serologías TORCH y parvovirus B19, amniocentesis diagnóstica (estudio de infecciones congénitas) y evacuadora. Las pruebas realizadas resultaron negativas, por lo que se diagnosticó de ascitis fetal aislada, finalizándose la gestación mediante cesárea a las 33 semanas y 3 días por un registro cardiotocográfico (RCTG) patológico. La ascitis no tuvo repercusión en el desarrollo neonatal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);44(4): 174-178, oct.-dic. 2017. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167993</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ascitis fetal aislada idiopática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38800^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38800^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1208</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1208^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1208^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23848^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
