<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148030</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological impact and quality of life in patients with temporary and definitive ostomy. Stoma Feeling Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to assess the psychological or emotional impact of stoma creation on patients, and if there are differences in the psychological impact and quality of life between persons with a temporary stoma and those with a definitive stoma. Method: an observational, controlled and multicentre study. The population included in this study were persons who had recently undergone surgery to create an ileostomy or colostomy. The study consisted of an inclusion visit immediately after surgery and a final visit three months after inclusion. It was conducted in public and private health centres in Spain, under regular care conditions, and according to clinical practice. The tools used for the analysis of the study variables were the Quality of Life Questionnaire (Stoma-QoL) and the NANDA, NIC and NOC taxonomies. Results: out of the 814 patients in the study, 61.5% were male, with a mean 62.5 years of age. Regarding the type ofostomy, 57% were colostomies vs. 43% of ileostomies. In terms of the comparative analysis between patients with temporary and definitive ostomy, the results regarding the number of indicators of NOC outcomes selected were a mean 7.8 in temporary ostomy and 7.2 in definitive ostomy, but these were not statistically significant (p= 0.1809). Regarding the assessment of the indicators selected within each suggested NOC, outcomes were very similar, and no significant differences were found in any parameter between patients with temporary or definitive ostomy. Discussion and conclusions: the assessment of the outcomes reveals that there are no significant differences in the outcomes for NOC indicators between patients with a temporary or definitive stoma three months after the ostomy procedure. Regarding the assessment of quality of life through the validated Stoma QoL questionnaire, a higher score has been recorded in patients with definitive ostomy, but this difference has not been statistically significant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quintana Jiménez, Paloma De la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquer Casas, Glòria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montesinos Gálvez, Ana Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Manzanares, M Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar la afectación psicológica o impacto emocional que tiene la creación de un estoma para el paciente y si existen diferencias en dicha afectación y en la calidad de vida entre personas con estomas temporales y aquellas que son portadoras de estomas definitivos. Método: estudio observacional controlado y Objetivo: evaluar la afectación psicológica o impacto emocional que tiene la creación de un estoma para el paciente y si existen diferencias en dicha afectación y en la calidad de vida entre personas con estomas temporales y aquellas que son portadoras de estomas definitivos. Método: estudio observacional controlado y multicéntrico. La población incluida en el estudio está formada por personas recién intervenidas y portadoras de una colostomía o una ileostomía. El estudio consta de una visita de inclusión en el postoperatorio inmediato y una visita final a los tres meses de la inclusión. Se desarrolló en consultas de centros públicos y privados de España, en las condiciones asistenciales habituales y de acuerdo a la práctica clínica. Las herramientas utilizadas para el análisis de las variables del estudio son el Cuestionario de Calidad de Vida (Stoma-QoL) y las taxonomías NANDA, NIC y NOC. Resultados: de los 814 pacientes del estudio, el 61,5% eran hombres, con una edad media de 62,5 años. En cuanto al tipo de ostomías, el 57% eran colostomías frente a un 43% de ileostomías. En cuanto al análisis comparativo entre pacientes con ostomías temporales y definitivas, encontramos que la media de indicadores de los resultados NOC seleccionados es de 7,8 enostomías temporales y 7,2 en ostomías definitivas, pero sin ser estadísticamente significativos (p= 0,1809). En cuanto a la valoración de los indicadores seleccionados dentro de cada NOC propuesto, los resultados fueron muy similares, sin encontrar en ningún parámetro diferencias significativas entre pacientes con (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;18(10): 24-31, dic. 2015. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148030</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Afectación psicológica y calidad de vida del paciente ostomizado temporal y definitivo. Estudio Stoma Feeling</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23206^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23288^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22955^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
