<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113864</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Potential effect of simvastatin in tissue regeneration</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Simvastatin (SIM) is a lactone which is used to lower cholesterol. Studies in vitro and in animals have been shown to induce osteoblastic activity and leads to bone formation by increasing the expression of bone morphogenetic protein-2. The SIM also promote bone formation, suppresses the synthesis of mevalonate and pyrophosphates, which in turn inhibit the formation and activity of osteoclasts. The SIM is a potential therapeutic agent for patients with osteoporosis and may facilitate the development of therapeutic strategies designed to repair local bone abnormalities such as periodontal lesions, periapical lesions, alveolar ridge defects and bone defects associated with implants. It was also indicated as the active ingredient to accelerate cell differentiation in human dental pulp. However, controlled clinical trials are required further corroborating the results of investigations inexperimental animal models (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ardila Medina, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La simvastatina (SIM) es una lactona que se utilizan para disminuir el colesterol. Estudios in vitro yen animales han demostrado que induce la actividad osteoblástica y conduce a la formación ósea incrementando la expresión de la proteína morfogenética ósea-2. La SIM además de promover la formación ósea, suprime la síntesis de mevalonatos y pirofosfatos que a su vez inhiben la formación y actividad de los osteoclastos. La SIM es un potencial agente terapéutico para los pacientes conosteoporosis y puede facilitar el desarrollo de estrategias terapéuticas locales diseñadas para reparar anormalidades óseas como lesiones periodontales, lesiones periapicales, defectos del reborde alveolar y defectos óseos asociados a implantes. También se ha indicado como ingrediente activo para acelerar la diferenciación celular en la pulpa dental humana. Sin embargo, se requieren más ensayos clínicos controlados que corroboren los resultados obtenidos por las investigaciones realizadas en modelos animales de experimentación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;25(1): 11-16, abr. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113864</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto potencial de la simvastatina en la regeneración tisular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2489^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1886^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33420^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28854^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
