<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-16185</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laryngeal infection by rhodococcus equi in a patient with aids</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Rhodococcus equi is an aerobic gram positive pleomorphic bacillus, that was isolated for the first time like a producer of bronchopneumonia in young horses. Every time more often, it is being recognized as a pathogen in humans, mainly in the immunodepressed population. We described a case, until now exceptional, of laryngeal infection by Rhodococcus equi in a patient with positive serology for the virus of the human immunodeficiency (HIV), and we reviewed some clinical and epidemiological characteristics of the infections by this germ. The treatment is riphampicine and/or erythromycin, being the prognosis bad, because usually they are immunodepressed patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Rhodococcus equies un bacilo aerobio gram positivo pleomórfico, que fue aislado por primera vez como productor de bronconeumonía en caballos jóvenes. Cada vez con mayor frecuencia, está siendo reconocido como patógeno en humanos, sobre todo en la población inmunocomprometida. Describimos un caso, hasta ahora excepcional, de infección laríngea por Rhodococcus equi en un paciente con serología positiva para el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH), y revisamos algunas características clínicas y epidemiológicas de las infecciones por este germen. El tratamiento es rifampicina y/o eritromicina, siendo el pronóstico malo, pues suelen ser pacientes inmunocomprometidos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;53(10): 783-788, dic. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Laringitis por rhodococcus equi en paciente con sida</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Grau Alario, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Climent, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez Vaillo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Mateu, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faubel Serra, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llavero Segovia, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lazaro Santander, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Cuenca, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-16185</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d12705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7998</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d201^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28123^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d914</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28027^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29842^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
