<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79435</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: endoanal ultrasonography can detect organic causesof anal pain without pathology on physical examination. Theaim of this study is to evaluate the importance of endoanal ultrasonographyin the diagnosis and therapeutic management of idiopathicand functional anal pain.Material and methods: retrospective study, between 15March 2005 and 15 June 2008, of all patients with proctalgiaand normal examination or with alterations not responsible foranal pain at proctologic exam that have undergone an endoanalultrasonography.Results: a total of 90 patients were analyzed, with a meanage of 50.5 years, 58% were female. Twenty-three patients hadfunctional anal pain clinic criteria. Endoanal ultrasonography revealedalterations in 49% of patients. The primary findings werechanges in sphincters in 14 patients, followed by anal sepsis in 12patients, anal fissure in 10 patients, perirectal lesions in 6 patientsand ulcer of the anal canal in 2 patients. Of the patients withsphincter defects, 5 patients had criteria of chronic anal pain. Inthis group of patients, no differences were found in manometricand defecographic results between the different ultrasound abnormalities.Conclusions: the endoanal ultrasonography detected occultorganic lesions to proctologic examination, in half the patientswith anal pain. Ultrasound abnormalities were found in 22% ofpatients with functional anal pain. However, there was no correlationbetween ultrasound findings and physiological studies, andtherefore could not find etiological or pathogenic factors of functionalanal pain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lago, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pimentel, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saraiva, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinto, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieira, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Areias, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro-Poças, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: la ecografía endoanal puede detectar causas orgánicasen el dolor anal sin patología en la exploración física. El objetivode este estudio es evaluar la importancia de la ecografía endoanalen el diagnóstico y en el abordaje terapéutico del dolor analidiopática y funcional.Material y métodos: estudio retrospectivo realizado entre el15 de marzo de 2005 y el 15 de junio de 2008, en todos los pacientesreferenciados para hacerse la ecografía endoanal, debido adolor anal con exploración física normal o sin alteraciones que justifiquenel dolor anal.Resultados: analizamos 90 pacientes con edad media de50,5 años, 58% mujeres. Veintitrés pacientes presentaban criteriosde dolor anal funcional. La ecografía endoanal reveló alteracionesen el 49% de los casos. Las alteraciones más frecuentesfueron las alteraciones esfinterianas, en 14 pacientes,seguido de sepsis anal, en 12 pacientes, de fisura anal, en 10pacientes, de las lesiones perirrectales, en 6 pacientes y de úlceradel canal anal, en 2 pacientes. De los pacientes con alteracionesesfinterianas, 5 pacientes tenían criterios de dolor crónico.En este grupo de pacientes, no se encuentran diferenciasen los hallazgos manométricos y defecográficos entre las diferentesalteraciones ecográficas.Conclusiones: la ecografía endoanal detectó lesiones estructuralesno sospechadas en el examen físico en la mitad de los enfermoscon dolor anal. Se han encontrado alteraciones ecográficasen el 22% de los pacientes con dolor anal funcional. Sinembargo, no se encontró correlación entre los hallazgos ecográficosy los estudios fisiológicos, así que no fue posible encontrar factoresetiológicos o patogénicos del dolor anal funcional(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;102(5): 308-313, mayo 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79435</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de los hallazgos ecográficos en el dolor anal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24282^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8537^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35318^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24282^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35318^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29304^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
