<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99722</identifier>
<setSpec>0014-2565</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cutaneous tuberculosis in an area of Mallorca (2003-2011)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective. Tuberculosis is an important health care problem, even in our setting. The objective of this study is to describe clinic and epidemiological features of cutaneous tuberculosis in our area. Patients and methods. A retrospective study was performed of all patients diagnosed of cutaneous tuberculosis in a hospital in Mallorca (Spain) from January 2003 to July 2011. The clinical forms, diagnostic methods used, treatment used and clinical course were recorded. Results. Twenty-eight cases of cutaneous tuberculosis were diagnosed (5.9% of the tuberculosis cases diagnosed in this period), 15 with classic cutaneous tuberculosis (14 scrofuloderma, 1 empyema necessitatis) and 13 patients with tuberculids (8 erythema induratum of Bazin disease and 5 erythema nodosum). Scrofulodermas came from lymph nodes in 10 of the patients, infected bone in 4 and pleural in one case; 13/28 patients came from other continents. Most of the patients were treatment with 3-4 tuberculostatic drugs, with favorable course. Conclusions. Cutaneous tuberculosis is not uncommon in our setting. In classic cutaneous tuberculosis culture is the gold standard diagnostic method while tuberculids are most commonly diagnosed by histology(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Losada-López, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taberner, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Gasalla, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cifuentes-Luna, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terrasa, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arquinio, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo. La tuberculosis constituye un importante problema sanitario, también en nuestro medio. Este estudio sepropone describir las características clínicas y epidemiológicas de la tuberculosis cutánea en nuestro medio. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de los casos de tuberculosis cutánea diagnosticados de enero de 2003 a julio de 2011 en un hospital de Mallorca. Se registraron las formas clínicas, la metodología diagnóstica empleada, el tratamiento utilizado y la evolución clínica. Resultados. Se diagnosticaron 28 casos de tuberculosis con afectación cutánea (5,9% del total de tuberculosis), tuberculosis verdadera en 15 casos (14 escrofulodermas, un empiema necessitatis) y tubercúlides en el resto (8 casos de eritema indurado de Bazin y 5 de eritema nodoso). El foco de origen de los escrofulodermas fue ganglionar (10), óseo (4) y pleural (1); 13/28 pacientes eran originarios de otros continentes. La mayoría de los pacientes fueron tratados con 3-4 fármacos tuberculostáticos, evolucionando favorablemente. Conclusión. La tuberculosis cutánea no es infrecuente en nuestro medio. En las tuberculosis cutáneas verdaderas el cultivo es el método diagnóstico más rentable, mientras que en las tubercúlides generalmente la histología es la que proporciona el diagnóstico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Clin Esp;212(4): 179-183, abr.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99722</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tuberculosis cutánea en una zona de Mallorca (2003-2011)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4980^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9358^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14782^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4980^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7705^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28004^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28004^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14782^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
