<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118674</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Feasibility and safety of hospital discharge 24 hours after laparoscopic radical prostatectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: Minimally invasive techniques for the surgical treatment of prostate cancer have aimed to achieve the same functional and oncological outcomes of open surgery with a significant decrease in postoperative morbidity and a subsequent decreasing hospital stay. These improvements are important in the current economic context. Our aim was to evaluate the feasibility and safety of hospital discharge 24 h after laparoscopic radical prostatectomy (LRP). METHODS: A total of 266 consecutive patients with clinical diagnosis of localized prostate cancer consecutively treated with extraperitoneal LRP between May 2007 and December 2010 were analyzed. There were no exclusion criteria for the surgical procedure. Patients were discharged in less than 24 h only in the case of absence of medical complications, with drainage of less than 50 mL allowing its removal before discharge, normal oral feeding tolerance, no significant hematuria by bladder catheter and good functional recovery of the patient. All surgery-related complications that occurred within 90 days after surgery were recorded and were classified according to the modified Clavien scale. RESULTS: A total of 266 patients who underwent LRP were studied with a median follow-up of 34 months. 80 (30.1%) patients were discharged from the hospital in less than 24h. 89 (33.4%) patients were discharged within 48 h and 97 (36.5 %) after 48h.The mean hospital stay of the entire case series was 2.9 days (SD 3.08). The mean hospital stay of patients who were discharged after 48h was 5,5 days (SD 3.94).Thirty-one patients (10.7%) experienced post-surgical complications. 25 (9.3%) of them were classified as Clavien I or II, and 6 (2.2%) Clavien III or IV. A total of 9 (3.3%) patients were readmitted. Of the group of patients who were discharged within 24h only one was readmitted due to hematuria. CONCLUSIONS: Extraperitoneal LRP is the standard treatment for localized prostate cancer in our institution. This treatment reliably and safely allows a hospital stay shorter than 24 h in a significant percentage of our patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blázquez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña, Enrique de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Las técnicas mínimamente invasivas en el tratamiento quirúrgico del cáncer de próstata tienen como objetivo alcanzar los mismos resultados oncológicos y funcionales que la cirugía abierta con un descenso en la morbilidad postoperatoria y una consiguiente disminución de la estancia hospitalaria. Estas mejoras son importantes en el actual contexto socioeconómico. Nuestro objetivo ha sido evaluar la viabilidad y la seguridad del alta hospitalaria a las 24 h tras prostatectomía radical laparoscópica (PRL). MÉTODOS: Se analizaron un total de 266 pacientes, con diagnóstico clínico de cáncer de próstata localizado, sometidos de forma consecutiva a PRL por vía extraperitoneal entre Mayo de 2007 y Diciembre de 2010. No existieron criterios de exclusión para la indicación de la técnica quirúrgica. Los pacientes fueron dados de alta en menos de 24 horas en ausencia de complicaciones médicas, con débito por el drenaje menor de 50cc que permitió la retirada del mismo previo al alta, tolerancia oral normal, ausencia de hematuria significativa por sonda vesical y buena recuperación funcional del paciente. Se recogieron todo tipo de complicaciones relacionadas con la cirugía durante los 90 días posteriores a la intervención y fueron clasificadas según la escala de Clavien modificada. RESULTADOS: Se analizaron un total de 266 pacientes sometidos a PRL con una mediana de seguimiento de 34 meses. 80 (30,1%) pacientes fueron dados de alta con un ingreso hospitalario menor de 24h.89 (33,4%) pacientes fueron dados de alta en 48h y 97 (36,5 %) en un tiempo mayor de 48h.La estancia media (DE) de la serie global fue de 2,9 días (3,08). La estancia media de los pacientes dados de alta en más de 48h (36,5%) fue de 5,5 (DE: 3,94) días. 31 pacientes (10,7%) sufrieron complicaciones postquirúrgicas de los cuales 25 (9,3%) fueron clasificadas como Clavien I ó II y 6 (2,2%) fueron complicaciones graves clasificadas como Clavien III ó IV. Un total de 9 (3,3%) pacientes requirieron reingreso hospitalario. Del grupo de pacientes que fueron dados de alta en 24h sólo uno precisó reingreso por hematuria. CONCLUSIONES: En nuestro centro la Prostatectomía radical laparoscópica por vía extraperitoneal es el estándar de tratamiento para el cáncer de próstata localizado permitiendo de manera fiable y segura una estancia hospitalaria menor de 24h en un porcentaje considerable de nuestros pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(10): 931-938, dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118674</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Viabilidad y seguridad del alta hospitalaria a las 24 horas tras prostatectomía radical laparoscópica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
