<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94768</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clenalness of the root canal walls using a combination of 2, 5% sodium hypoclorte &#150; 10% citric acid and 2% chlorhexidine &#150; 10% citric acid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: In this study the cleanliness of the root canal walls was copared, using as irrigators the combinations of 2,5% sodium hypochlorite &#150; 10% citric acid, and 2% chrohexidene &#150; 10% citric acid. Material and methods: 35 single- rooted human premolars, recently extracted wereused. The same roots were instrumented and irigated with the combinatios mentioned above , then roots were sectione and observed with Scanning Electron Microscopic in cervical, middle and apical levels. Reslts: The results  showed cleanliness o the root canal walls with the use of both combiations, being statistcaly more significantin the third middle, the one obtained with the combination of 2,5% sodium hypochlorite &#150;10% citric acid (p=0 0&lt;0,05). Conclussions: The association of 2,5% sodium hypochloite 10% citic acid was more efficiente than the combination of 2% chorhexidine- 10% citric acid (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Del Carril, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmos Fassi, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rusco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El propósito de este estudio fue comparar el grado de limpieza de lasparedes del conducto radicular utilizando como irrigantes la combinación de hipoclorito de sodio 2,5% - ácido cítrico 10% y clorhexidina 2%  ácitdo cítrico 10%. Material  y métodos: Se emplearon raíces de 35 premolares, unirradiculares de conducos rectos recientemente extraídos. L amismas fueron instrumentadas e irigadas con ls soluciones citadas, secciondas longitudinalmente y observadas al MEB a nivel cervial, medio y apical. Resultados: Los resultados indicaron limpieza de las paredes del conducto radicular con el uso de ambas cobinaciones,siendo en e terci medio, estadísticamente más efectiva la obtenida con a asociación hipoclori de sodio 2,5% - ácido cítrico 10% (p= 0,00&lt;0,05). Conclusioes: La asociacion d ehipoclorito de sodio 2,5% - ácido cítirico 10% demostró mayor apacidad para remover la capa residual que la asociación de clorexidina 2%- ácido citrico 10% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);27(2): 63-67, abr.-jun. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94768</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Limpieza de las paredes del conducto usando una combinaciónde hipoclorito de sodio 2, 5% - ácido cítrico 10% y clorhexidina 2% - ácido citrico 10%</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13358^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2755^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32979^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12763^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
