<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050117</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Smoking and diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Cardiovascular risk in individuals with diabetes is two-fold        higher among smokers as compared to non-smokers. Moreover,        smoking increases the risk of the development and deterioration of        microvascular complications. The aim of the present study was to        determine the prevalence of cigarette smoking and several        characteristics of the smoking habit among diabetics in our patient        population. Patients and methods: Eight hundred and six diabetic        subjects were included in the study. The patients were classified as: type        1 (n= 70), type 2 (n= 674), gestational (n= 36) and other variants (n=        26). Moreover, the place of residence of the patients (urbal/rural) was        considered. In the group of smokers, the degree of nicotine dependence        was determined by means of the Fagerström test. Results: One        hundred and ten patients (13.6%) were smokers, while the remaining        696 (86.4%) were non-smokers. Significant differences were observed        in the percentage of smokers among the patients with type 1 diabetes        (38.6%) with respect to those with type 2 (10.5%) and gestational        (11.1%) diabetes. Moreover, statistically significant differences were        observed between the percentage of male smokers (24.1%) as        compared to female smokers (6.8%) and between the percentage of        urban smokers (18.1%) as compared to those living in rural areas        (11.6%). Among the smokers, 33.3% had a strong dependence on        nicotine, while 48.5% had a moderate dependence and the remaining        18.2% had a slight dependence. Conclusions: These results show        that a substantial percentage of individuals with diabetes are smokers,        especially in the group of patients with type 1 diabetes and other        variants. Male sex and an urban setting are factors that predispose to        the smoking habit. The finding that only a third of the diabetic smokers        were strongly dependent on nicotine suggests that the programs        focusing on smoking cessation could be highly successful</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fraile, A. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Escolá, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Alonso, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andía, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Guzmán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El riesgo cardiovascular del individuo diabético se        duplica en pacientes fumadores respecto a los no fumadores. Además,        el tabaquismo aumenta el riesgo de aparición y deterioro de        complicaciones microvasculares. El objetivo del estudio fue conocer la        prevalencia del tabaquismo y algunas características del hábito de fumar        en la población diabética de nuestro medio. Pacientes y métodos:        Se incluyeron en el estudio 806 individuos diabéticos. Los pacientes se        clasificaron en: diabetes tipo 1 (n= 70), tipo 2 (n= 674), gestacional        (n= 36) y otras diabetes (n= 26). Además, se consideró el lugar de        residencia de los pacientes (urbano/rural). En los pacientes que        fumaban, se determinó el grado de dependencia al tabaco mediante el        test de Fagerström. Resultados: Ciento diez pacientes (13,6%)        fumaban, mientras que los 696 restantes (86,4%) no fumaban. Se        encontraron diferencias significativas en el porcentaje de fumadores en        el grupo de diabetes tipo 1 (38,6%) respecto a los grupos de tipo 2        (10,5%) y gestacional (11,1%). También se encontraron diferencias en        el porcentaje de varones fumadores (24,1%) respecto al de mujeres        fumadoras (6,8%), así como en el de fumadores que residían en área        urbana (18,1%) respecto a los que vivían en el medio rural (11,6%). En        el grupo de fumadores, un 33,3% tenía una alta dependencia del        tabaco, mientras que el 48,5% presentaba una dependencia moderada        y el 18,2% restante una baja dependencia. Conclusiones: Estos        resultados demuestran que un porcentaje considerable de individuos        diabéticos fuma, en especial en los grupos de diabetes mellitus tipo 1 y        otras diabetes. El sexo masculino, junto con la residencia en área        urbana, constituyen factores que predisponen al hábito de fumar. El        hecho de que sólo uno de cada tres diabéticos fumadores tenga una        alta dependencia a la nicotina sugiere que los programas encaminados        a la deshabituación tabáquica podrían tener un notable éxito</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;22(3): 223-227, jul.-sept. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hábito tabáquico y diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
