<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140071</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-7823</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New approaches in deception detection ii. Active interviewing strategies and contextual information</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Meta-analytical evidence shows that behavioural indicators of deception are scant, poorly diagnostic and inconsistent. This has yielded a shift in deception detection research. Rather than passively scrutinising the communication sender to find tell-tale behavioural indicators of deception, the deception judge needs to (a) adopt an active role by using interviewing techniques specifically designed to detect deception, or (b) focus on contextual (rather than behavioural) deception cues. In the previous paper (Masip &amp; Herrero, 2015a), we reviewed the antecedents of this change in focus, as well as the theoretical grounding of the new approaches. Here we describe specific interviewing strategies for detecting deception, as well as the (still scant) research on contextual deception indicia. In doing this, we hope to offer the reader a detailed perspective on the recent developments in this specific area of psychology and law (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herrero, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masip, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evidencia meta-analítica muestra que los indicadores conductuales de la mentira son escasos, poco diagnósticos y cambiantes. Esto ha propiciado un cambio de orientación en la investigación sobre detección de mentiras: ya no se trata de escudriñar atenta pero pasivamente al emisor de la comunicación en busca de indicadores conductuales reveladores de mentira; por el contrario, es necesario (a) adoptar un rol activo, empleando modalidades de entrevista diseñadas específicamente para detectar mentiras, o (b) atender a indicios contextuales (en lugar de conductuales) del engaño. En el artículo anterior (Masip y Herrero, 2015a) revisamos los antecedentes de este cambio de orientación, así como el trasfondo teórico de las nuevas aproximaciones. Aquí describimos estrategias concretas de entrevista para detectar mentiras, así como la (aún escasa) investigación sobre indicios contextuales del engaño. Con ello, esperamos ofrecer al lector una panorámica detallada de los desarrollos recientes en esta parcela concreta de la Psicología Jurídica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pap. psicol;36(2): 96-108, jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140071</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas aproximaciones en detección de mentiras II. Estrategias activas de entrevista e información contextual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3435^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3435^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8190^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3435^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1545^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8190</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
