<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158144</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-5967</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the child and adolescent psychiatrc day hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Child and Adolescent psychiatric Day Hospital (CAPDH)bases its intervention model in institutional therapy. This intervention has been extensively validated in the treatment of various mental disorders in childhood and adolescence, and it has been proposed for the intervention of severe mental illness in this population. However , the optimal structure of this device has not been well established. We present a possible structural scheme for a clinical actuation guide in child and adolescent day hospital and individual action plan work, based on the experience of the Hospital Mancha Centro. Also , we present the research project currently underway in our unit developing a neuropsychological evaluation algorithm for Autism Spectrum Disorders in (CAPDH). Also we opened the discussion for the proposed clinical indicators of possible developments in HDDIJ (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuertes Beneítez, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León Allué, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Carpintero Abad, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Pérez, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Pascual, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villero Luque, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Hospital de Di&amp;#769;a Infanto Juvenil (HDDIJ) basa su modelo de intervencio&amp;#769;n en la terapia institucional. Este recurso ha sido ampliamente validado en el tratamiento de diferentes trastornos mentales de la infancia y adolescencia, y se propone para la intervencio&amp;#769;n de la patologi&amp;#769;a mental grave en esta poblacio&amp;#769;n. Sin embargo, la estructura o&amp;#769;ptima de este dispositivo no ha sido bien establecida. En este trabajo presentamos a modo de ejemplo un posible esquema para estructurar la gui&amp;#769;a de actuacio&amp;#769;n interna de un hospital de di&amp;#769;a infanto juvenil y del plan de intervencio&amp;#769;n individualizado de trabajo con cada nin&amp;#771;o, basado en la experiencia del Hospital Mancha Centro. Asi&amp;#769; mismo, presentamos el proyecto de investigacio&amp;#769;n actualmente en marcha en nuestra unidad de elaboracio&amp;#769;n de un algoritmo de evaluacio&amp;#769;n neuropsicolo&amp;#769;gica para Trastornos del Espectro Autista en el HDDIJ. Abrimos igualmente el debate para la propuesta de posibles indicadores cli&amp;#769;nicos de evolucio&amp;#769;n en HDDIJ (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psiquiatr. psicoter. niño adolesc;(61): 17-33, ene.-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del Hospital de Día Infanto Juvenil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10744</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2717^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28416^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3648^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3648^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
