<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113316</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional and oncologic results of the surgical salvage in the management of recurrent nasopharyngeal carcinomas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To evaluate the indications and results of the surgical salvage in the treatment of recurrent nasopharyngeal carcinoma at the primary site. Material and Method: Twelve patients with biopsy-proven recurrent nasopharyngeal cancer were managed with the subtemporal-preauricular 6 and facial translocation 6 approaches. One patient was staged as having recurrent T stage (rT1) 1 disease; 3 patients, rT2; 2 patients, rT3; and 6 patients rT4. Results: With a mean follow-up of 3 years, the 3-year actuarial survival rate was 42%. Survival for recurrent T stage was as follows: rT1, 100%; rT2, 67%; rT3, 50%; rT4,17%. Survival rates for patiens with rT3 and rT4 disease without intracranial disease are 40%. Conclusions: Facial translocation and subtemporal-preauricular approaches are versatile surgical techniques for radical resection of nasopharyngeal recurrences with an acceptable morbidity. The long term survival results are encouraging for rT1-rT3tumors and also for rT4 without intracranial extension of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabanillas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estelrrich, PM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Cassati, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los resultados de la cirugía de rescate en el tratamiento de las recidivas locales de los carcinomas nasofaríngeos. Material y Método: Doce pacientes con recidivas locales de carcinomas nasofaríngeos se intervinieron mediante una vía subtemporal-preauricular6 o una translocación facial6. El estadio de la recidiva se clasificó en un paciente como rT1; 3 como rT2; 2, como rT3; y 6 comorT4. Resultados: La supervivencia global a los 3 años fue del42%; subdividida por estadios: rT1, 100%; rT2, 67%; rT3,50%; rT4, 17%. La supervivencia de los pacientes con enfermedad localmente avanzada sin progresión intracraneal fue del 40%. Conclusiones: La translocación facial y el abordaje subtemporal-preauricular posibilitan una resección completa de las recidivas nasofaríngeas, incurriendo en una morbilidad aceptable. La supervivencia a largo plazo de los pacientes con recidivas clasificadas como rT1-rT3 resulta esperanzadora, incluso la de los clasificados como rT4 sin afectación intracraneal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;56(9): 416-422, nov. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113316</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados oncológicos y funcionales de la cirugía de rescate en las recidivas locales de los carcinomas nasofaríngeos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28208^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
