<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122056</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Etiology of acute ataxia in pediatric emergencies: 11 years experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Changes in gait are a common reason for consultation in pediatric emergencies, however cases of true gait ataxia are rare in pediatric patients. The main concern of professional emergency lies in the exclusion of serious causes of this clinical syndrome, fortunately in most cases the origin in childhood is usually benign and self-limiting process. Among the acquired ataxias, the most common form of presentation in the pediatric emergency is usually that of acute ataxia, which are those whose evolution is less than 72 hours in a previously healthy child. In this review we have analyzed the cases of acquired ataxia evaluated in our pediatric emergency department during a period of 11 years and what was the diagnostic approach. In our series of cases the most common cause of acute ataxia was postinfectious (39.13% of total), followed by the tumoral origin (17.39%) and secondary to ingestion of toxic agents (13.04%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Caamaño, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sobrino, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Gutiérrez, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las alteraciones en la marcha son un motivo de consulta habitual en las urgencias pediátricas; sin embargo, los casos de verdadera marcha atáxica son muy infrecuentes en los pacientes pediátricos. La principal preocupación del profesional de urgencias radica en excluir las causas graves de este síndrome clínico; afortunadamente, en la mayoría de casos en la infancia, su origen suele ser un proceso benigno y autolimitado. Dentro de las ataxias adquiridas, la forma más habitual de presentación en los servicios de urgencias suele ser la aguda, cuya evolución es menor de 72 horas en un niño previamente sano. En esta revisión hemos analizado los casos de ataxia adquirida valorados en nuestro servicio de urgencias pediátricas durante un periodo de 11 años, así como su enfoque diagnóstico. En nuestra serie, la causa más frecuente de ataxia aguda fue la postinfecciosa (un 39,13% del total), seguida de las de origen tumoral (17,39%) y las intoxicaciones (13,04%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;72(4): 88-91, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122056</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiología de la ataxia aguda en urgencias pediátricas: experiencia de 11 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4742^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34316^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2561^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28561^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
