<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045245</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing on the net (II): international institutional resources</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At present, nearly all the institutions involve in the practice and research innursing have a place on the Internet. In line with the previous work of thisseries which showed the existence of different Spanish institutional resourcesrelating to the Nursing setting, this second part presents a series of institutionalresources at international level. The description of these resources hasbeen structured into: Societies and professional associations (InternationalNursing Council, American Nurses Associations, etc.), professionals colleges(Royal College of Nursing and &#147;Colegio de Enfermeras Chilenas&#148;, etc.) as wellas governmental entities (Pan-American Association of Health and WorldHealth Organisation)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cristina Bojo Canales, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hoy en día, prácticamente todas las instituciones relacionadas con la prácticay la investigación de la Enfermería tienen su sitio en la red. Continuando conla línea del anterior trabajo de esta serie, en el que se daba cuenta de la existenciade distintos recursos institucionales españoles relacionados con elentorno de la Enfermería, en esta segunda parte se ofrecen una serie de fuentes,también de carácter institucional, pero de ámbito internacional. La descripciónde estos recursos se ha estructurado en: Sociedades y AsociacionesProfesionales (Consejo Internacional de Enfermería, American NursesAssociation, etc.), Colegios Profesionales (Royal College of Nursing y Colegiode Enfermeras Chilenas, etc.) y Organismos Gubernamentales (OrganizaciónPanamericana de la Salud y Organización Mundial de la Salud)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;9(3): 50-55, abr. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045245</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermería en la red (II): recursos institucionales internacionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1659</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23784^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
