<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123072</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Magnitude and Management of Metabolic Syndrome in Spain in 2008-2010: The ENRICA Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives Few studies in Spain have reported the distribution of metabolic syndrome using the harmonized definition and that of premorbid metabolic syndrome, which consists of metabolic syndrome without diabetes mellitus or cardiovascular disease. Moreover, their regional distributions and clinical management are unknown. The present study examined the distributions and clinical management of both syndromes in Spain. Methods This cross-sectional study was performed from 2008 to 2010 in 11 149 representative individuals of the Spanish population aged 18 years or older. Data were obtained through standardized physical examination, and analytical measurements were done in a central laboratory. Results The prevalences (95% confidence interval) of metabolic syndrome and premorbid metabolic syndrome were 22.7% (21.7%-23.7%) and 16.9% (16.0%-17.8%), respectively. The frequency of both syndromes increased with age and was higher in men than in women up to 65 years; above this age, the frequency was higher in women. The communities of the south of Spain and the Balearic and Canary islands had the highest prevalence of both syndromes, in some regions reaching double that of the community with the lowest prevalence. About one third of patients with premorbid metabolic syndrome reported that they had not received health recommendations to improve their lifestyles; of those that did receive advice, adherence was low, particularly for reducing weight (31.9%) and salt intake (38.3%). Conclusions The prevalence of metabolic syndrome is high in Spain and considerable geographical differences exist in its distribution. There is substantial room for improvement in the clinical management of premorbid metabolic syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López García, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guallar-Castillón, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Graciani, Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León-Muñoz, Luz M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez- Artalejo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Francisco Pérez, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Banegas, José R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Fisac, Juan Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos Pocos estudios en España han descrito la distribución del síndrome metabólico según la definición armonizada, y del síndrome metabólico premórbido, que es el síndrome metabólico sin diabetes mellitus o enfermedad cardiovascular. Además, se desconoce la distribución por comunidades autónomas y su manejo clínico. Este trabajo examina la distribución y el manejo clínico de ambos síndromes en España. Métodos Estudio transversal realizado de 2008 a 2010 sobre 11.149 personas representativas de la población española de 18 o más años. La información se obtuvo mediante examen físico estandarizado y las determinaciones analíticas se hicieron en un laboratorio central. Resultados La prevalencia (intervalo de confianza del 95%) de síndrome metabólico fue del 22,7% (21,7-23,7) y la del premórbido, el 16,9% (16,0-17,8). La frecuencia de ambos síndromes aumentó con la edad y fue mayor en varones que en mujeres hasta los 65 años; a partir de esa edad, fue mayor entre las mujeres. Las comunidades del sur de España y las insulares fueron las de mayor prevalencia de ambos síndromes, y en algún caso resultó el doble que la de la comunidad de menor prevalencia. Aproximadamente un tercio de los pacientes con síndrome metabólico premórbido declararon no recibir consejo sanitario para mejorar sus estilos de vida; entre los que recibieron consejo, el seguimiento fue bajo, especialmente para perder peso (31,9%) y reducir la sal (38,3%).Conclusiones La prevalencia de síndrome metabólico es elevada en España. Hay importantes diferencias geográficas en su distribución y sustanciales oportunidades de mejora del manejo clínico del síndrome metabólico premórbido(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;67(5): 367-373, mayo 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123072</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Magnitud y manejo del síndrome metabólico en España en 2008-2010: Estudio ENRICA</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
