<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158600</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety sensitivity and smoking: a review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Smoking is a major public health problem and the leading preventable cause of morbidity and mortality worldwide. In recent years a high prevalence of smoking has been detected in people with psychological disorders. It has been proposed that certain psychological vulnerability factors could explain, at least in part, the relationship between smoking, anxiety and emotional disorders, such as anxiety sensitivity, anhedonia or distress tolerance. This paper is a descriptive review that focuses on analyze the role of anxiety sensitivity in relation to smoking-related variables, concluding that there is evidence that shows that this construct has an influence on smoking behaviour, its maintenance and the process of smoking cessation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Becoña, Elisardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Vispo , Carmela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fumar constituye un grave problema de salud pública, siendo la primera causa evitable de morbimortalidad en el mundo. En las últimas décadas se ha observado una elevada prevalencia de consumo de tabaco en personas con diferentes trastornos psicopatológicos. Se ha propuesto la existencia de factores de vulnerabilidad psicológica como, por ejemplo, la sensibilidad a la ansiedad, la anhedonia o la tolerancia al malestar, que podrían explicar, al menos en parte, la relación entre fumar y la ansiedad y otros trastornos emocionales. Este trabajo es una revisión descriptiva de la literatura que se centra en analizar el papel de la sensibilidad a la ansiedad en relación con el consumo de tabaco, concluyéndose que existe evidencia de que esta variable influye en varios aspectos relacionados con la conducta de fumar, su mantenimiento y en el proceso de dejar de fumar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;22(2): 118-122, jul.-dic. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158600</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La sensibilidad a la ansiedad y el consumo de tabaco: una revisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d347^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4258</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
