<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65748</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the present work, the consequences of the sanitary assistance activity of the pharmacist in a group of patients with high blood pressure are analyzed. The Drug Related Problems (DRP), detected in these patients at a community pharmacy, that could generate Negative Results Associated to the Medication (NRM) were studied, carrying out a classification with respect to the pharmacotherapy qualities of necessity, effectiveness and security. The impact of the communication channel used in the intervention (pharmacist-patient or pharmacist-patient-doctor) in its final result was also studied. Better result was obtained when the collaboration with the doctor was selected. This study also remarks the need to overcome some barriers that hinders a better application of this pharmacotherapeutic monitoring service and a greater integration of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arias, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría López, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo se analizan las consecuencias de la actividad asistencial del farmacéutico en un grupo de pacientes hipertensos de una oficina de farmacia. Se han estudiado los diferentes Problemas Relacionados con la Medicación (PRM) que podrían dar lugar a la aparición de Resultados Negativos asociados a la Medicación (RNM), clasificándolos y relacionándolos con las cualidades de necesidad, efectividad y seguridad de la farmacoterapia. La incidencia de la vía de comunicación utilizada en la intervención (farmacéutico-paciente o farmacéutico-paciente médico)sobre el resultado final de ésta fue investigada, observándose un mejor resultado si se requería la colaboración del médico. En este estudio se ha puesto de manifiesto la necesidad de solucionar determinadas trabas que dificultan la mejor aplicación del servicio de seguimiento farmacoterapéutico a los pacientes y la inclusión de un mayor número de personas en éste (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;49(1): 39-50, 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65748</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3186^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4398^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4403^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4408^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4398^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3186^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4403^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
