<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165408</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Echocardiographic Assessment of Asynchrony</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac resynchronization therapy has been shown to be effective in selected patients with heart failure. The current selection criteria are: a) New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional class III or IV heart failure despite optimized medical therapy; b) depressed left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF&lt;35%); c) left ventricular end-diastolic diameter 55 mm; and d) a wide QRS complex (&gt;130 ms) with evidence of left bundle branch block (LBBB). However, these criteria are under revision. Around 30% of patients selected using these criteria do not respond to resynchronization therapy. There is a poor correlation between QRS interval and mechanical asynchrony, with over 51% of patients with a QRS interval less than 120 ms having mechanical asynchrony. Echocardiography is better at assessing mechanical asynchrony than QRS interval measurement. Moreover, recent data suggest that echocardiography provides the best predictors of improvement after resynchronization therapy. Several methods have been shown to be useful in predicting a good response. However, there are discrepancies between the results of the different methods and no consensus on the best approach has yet been reached. Nevertheless, echocardiography should be included in any evaluation of candidates for resynchronization therapy. The aim of this article was to review the benefits and limitations of existing criteria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moya-Mur, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Tirados, Blanca M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Madrid, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zamorano, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez de Isla, Leopoldo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia de resincronización cardíaca ha logrado beneficios tanto a corto como a largo plazo en determinados pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca. Los criterios actuales de selección para la implantación de un marcapasos bicameral son: a) insuficiencia cardíaca en clase funcional III-IV de la NYHA (New York Heart Association) a pesar de un tratamiento óptimo; b) función ventricular izquierda deprimida (FEVI &lt; 35%); c) diámetro telediastólico del ventrículo izquierdo &amp;#8805; 55 mm, y d) morfología de bloqueo de rama izquierda en el electrocardiograma, con una duración del complejo QRS &gt; 130 ms. Pero estos criterios están en revisión. Si consideramos como criterio para la resincronización un complejo QRS &gt; 130 ms, aproximadamente un 30% de los pacientes no responden de manera favorable a la terapia. Se sabe que hasta un 51% de los pacientes con un complejo QRS &lt; 120 ms tiene asincronía mecánica durante la sístole. Además, la duración del QRS tiene una escasa correlación con la asincronía intraventricular. La ecocardiografía es una técnica superior para evaluar la asincronía mecánica y los datos actuales indican que es la técnica que mejor predice la mejoría tras la resincronización. Diversos métodos han demostrado su eficacia en este sentido y, aunque hay discrepancia de unos métodos a otros y no se ha definido aún el método ideal, la ecocardiografía debería estar incluida en la evaluación de los posibles candidatos para resincronización. El objetivo de esta monografía es revisar los criterios analizados hasta la actualidad, sus ventajas y sus limitaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);5(supl.B): 35b-45b, 2005. graf, tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración ecocardiográfica de la asincronía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54223^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33091^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33091^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33091^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23233^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23623^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
