<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75100</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spanish version of the Dysexecutive Questionnaire (DEX-Sp): psychometric properties in addicts and non-clinical sample</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Several studies have shown evidence of executive function impairment associated with substance abuse. This suggests the potential usefulness of a baseline assessment measure to screen for dysexecutive impairments in individuals beginning treatment. The Dysexecutive Questionnaire (DEX) is a test widely used to estimate executive dysfunction. The main objective of this work is to study the psychometric properties of the Spanish version of the Dysexecutive Questionnaire (DEX-Sp). A complementary goal is to study its potential utility for initial screening in addicted individuals seeking treatment. Method: A sample of 131 non-clinical and 127 clinical individuals meeting the DSM-IV-TR substance abuse or dependence criteria were recruited. Results: Internal consistency of the questionnaire was assessed (Cronbach&#146;s ¬ =0.91), as well as other reliability indicators. Exploratory and confirmatory factor analysis offers four- and five-factor solutions. Also tested were the dimensionality and structural model and its convergent and discriminant validity with other instruments. Differences between clinical and non-clinical individuals and total scores were also analyzed. Conclusions: The data suggest that the Spanish version of the DEX is a useful measure for assessing general symptoms of dysexecutive syndrome, and a valid, reliable and adequate screening test for estimating cognitive impairment associated with substance abuse (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>LLanero Luque, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo Mota, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivar Arroyo, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Sánchez de León, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bouso Saiz, José Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedrero Pérez, Eduardo José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Puerta, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Diversos estudios han evidenciado el deterioro de las funciones ejecutivas asociado al abuso de sustancias. Este hecho sugiere la conveniencia de contar con algún instrumento de cribado que sirva para establecer una línea base sobre los déficits que presentan los sujetos que inician tratamiento. El Cuestionario Disejecutivo (DEX) es un test ampliamente utilizado para estimar disfunción ejecutiva. El principal objetivo del presente trabajo se centra en estudiar las propiedades de la versión española del Cuestionario Disejecutivo (DEX-Sp). Complementariamente se pretende estudiar su potencial utilidad como instrumento de cribado en adictos en tratamiento. Método: 131 sujetos de población no clínica y 127 adictos (con criterios DSM-IVTR para abuso o dependencia). Resultados: Se estudia la consistencia interna (¬ de Cronbach = 0,91) entre otros indicadores de fiabilidad. El análisis factorial exploratorio y confirmatorio ofrece soluciones de 4 y 5 factores. Se estudió la dimensionalidad y el modelo estructural de base, así como la validez convergente y discriminante. Se estudiaron las diferencias apreciadas entre adictos y población no clínica. Conclusiones: Los datos sugieren que la versión española del DEX es un instrumento útil para evaluar síntomas disejecutivos generales, con la suficiente fiabilidad y validez para explorar deterioro cognitivo asociado al abuso desustancias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);21(2): 155-166, mar.-jun. 2009. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75100</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Versión española del Cuestionario Disejecutivo (DEX-Sp): propiedades psicométricas en adictos y población no clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33521</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
