<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95964</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stress and occupational satisfaction of nurses in hospitals of the province of Toledo</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the level of occupational satisfaction and work relatedor occupational stressors perceived by nursing professionals in the hospital setting and to analyse the influence of the work place and sociooccupational factors both on satisfaction as well as on work-related stressors. Material and method: Design: descriptive and cross-sectional multicenter study. Study population: Nurses from Toledo hospitals. Sample design and sampling: proportional, probabilistic, stratified. Sample size n = 299 subjects.Variables and measurements: socio-occupational variables collected by means of a self-developed registry form and main study variables (occupational satisfaction and work-related stressors) collected by means of Font Roja validated questionnaires and the Occupational Stressors Inventory. Following an initial first descriptive analysis, the statistical significance of mean differences was assessed by using the Student t test, ANOVA and posthoc tests. Results: Overall satisfaction at the work place: 74,59 (CI 95%:73,79-75,38).Occupational stressors 42,84 (IC95%:41,29-44,37). Relationship between stressors and rotation shift (p &lt; 0,05). The dimension relationship with workpeers is related to age and work experience (p = 0,001 and p = 0,047). Stressorfactors: death and age-related suffering, shift and work experience (p &lt; 0,05).Conclusions: The level of satisfaction in nursing professionals working in Toledo hospitals is intermediate and the stressors rank higher than those foundin the literature. There is a strong negative influence involving rotation shiftson the stressors. The work load, death and suffering are the most frequently found stressors, coinciding with other similar jobs. The results obtained point to the necessity of developing coping strategies for nursing professionals, especially among the youngest ones and those with less experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Layos, María Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pleite Gómez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Alaminos, María Angustias</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Morcillo, Jaime</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrejón Mora, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Marcos, Antolín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: determinar el nivel de satisfacción laboral y estresores laborales percibidos por los profesionales de Enfermería del ámbito hospitalario y analizarla influencia del centro de trabajo y factores sociolaborales tanto en la satisfacción como en los estresores laborales. Material y método: diseño descriptivo y transversal, multicéntrico. Población: enfermeras de los hospitales toledanos. Diseño muestral y muestreo: probabilístico estratificado proporcional. Tamaño muestral n = 299 sujetos. Variables y medición: sociolaborales mediante hoja de registro de elaboración propia y las principales del estudio (satisfacción laboral y estresores laborales) mediante cuestionarios validados Font Roja y Escala de Estresores Laborales. Tras un primer análisis descriptivo, la significación estadística de las diferencias de medias se valoró mediante la prueba de T de Student, ANOVA y pruebas post hoc. Resultados: satisfacción laboral global: 74,59 (IC95%:73,79-75,38). Estresores laborales 42,84 (IC95%:41,29-44,37). Relación estresores y turno rotatorio (p&lt; 0,05). La dimensión relación con los compañeros presenta relación con edad y experiencia laboral (p = 0,001 y p = 0,047). Factores estresores: muerte y sufrimiento relacionados con edad, turno y experiencia laboral (p &lt; 0,05).Conclusiones: la satisfacción en los profesionales enfermeros de los hospitales toledanos es intermedia y los estresores están más elevados que lo encontrado en bibliografía. Existe una importante influencia negativa del turno rotatorio sobre los estresores. La carga de trabajo, la muerte y el sufrimiento son los estresores más frecuentes, concordando con otros trabajos similares. Los resultados obtenidos plantean la necesidad de estrategias de afrontamiento para los profesionales enfermeros, especialmente los más jóvenes y con menor experiencia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(8): 8-14, oct. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95964</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés y satisfacción laboral de las enfermeras de hospitales toledanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
