<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73947</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE. To evaluate the opinion of Spanish hypertensive patients regarding different aspects of treatment adherence. METHODS. Descriptive, cross-sectional study conducted by surveying hypertensive patients on stable anti-hypertensive treatment in Spanish Primary Care centres. Demographic data were collected and compliance was measured using the Batalla, Morisky-Green and Haynes-Sackett tests; the patients were asked why they had not taken the tablets on some occasion, what they considered to be the most common cause of non-compliance and which adherence-enhancing strategies they would like their doctor or nurse to adopt. RESULTS. A total of 4,952 patients (91.9%) were included in the study (mean age: 62.6 years [SD 10.7]; 47.2%women). Compliance was estimated to be 90.3% (CI 99%= 89.2-91.4), 11.3% (CI 99% = 10.1-12.5) and 69.5% (CI99% = 67.8-71.2) according to the Haynes-Sackett, Morisky-Green and Batalla test, respectively. The most common reasons for not taking the medication were forgetfulness(77.4% [CI 99% = 67.8-71.2]), running out of medication(45.4% [CI 99% = 43.6-47.2]) and not feeling well (34.5%[CI 99% = 32.8-36.2]). Forgetfulness was considered to be the primary cause of non-compliance (80.3% [CI 99% =78.8-81.8]). The patients&#146; preferred strategies for improving adherence varied between 88.6% (CI 99% = 87.4-89.8) for the prescription of the least number of tablets possible and 10.8% (CI 99% = 9.7-11.9) for e-mail contact with the physician. CONCLUSIONS. The main cause of non-compliance is forgetfulness; the preferred strategy for patients is the simplification of treatment regimens and there is little interest in using new technologies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Contreras, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figuera-Von Wichmann, M. de la</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS. Evaluar la opinión de los hipertensos españoles sobre diferentes aspectos relacionados con el cumplimiento terapéutico. METODOLOGÍA. Estudio descriptivo transversal mediante una encuesta a pacientes hipertensos en tratamiento antihipertensivo estable, realizada en centros de Atención Primaria de España. Se recogieron datos demográficos, se midió el cumplimiento mediante los cuestionarios de Batalla, Morisky-Green y Haynes-Sackett, y se interrogó sobre las causas por las que dejaban de tomar los comprimidos en alguna ocasión, la causa que consideraban más frecuente de incumplimiento y las estrategias que desearían que su médico o enfermera realizasen para mejorar el cumplimiento. RESULTADOS. Se incluyeron 4.952 pacientes (91,9%)(edad media: 62,6 años; desviación estándar [DE] 10,7 y47,2% mujeres). Fueron cumplidores el 90,3% (intervalo de confianza [IC] 99% = 89,2-91,4) mediante el cuestionario de Haynes-Sackett, el 11,3% (IC 99%=10,1-12,5) según Morisky-Green y el 69,5% (IC 99% = 67,8-71,2) según el de Batalla. Las causas más frecuentes por las cuales dejaron de tomar alguna vez la medicación fueron los olvidos involuntarios(77,4% [IC 99% = 67,8-71,2]) quedarse sin medicación(45,4% [IC 99% = 43,6-47,2]) y no encontrarse bien (34,5%[IC 99% = 32,8-36,2]). La causa de incumplimiento considerada como principal fueron los olvidos (80,3% [IC 99% =78,8-81,8]). Entre las estrategias que los pacientes deseaban para mejorar el cumplimiento, las preferencias oscilaron entre el 88,6% (IC 99% = 87,4-89,8) para la prescripción del menor número posible de comprimidos y el 10,8% (IC 99%= 9,7-11,9) para el contacto con el médico por correo electrónico. CONCLUSIONES. La principal causa de incumplimiento son los olvidos casuales, la estrategia preferida es la simplificación del tratamiento y los pacientes encuestados muestran escasas preferencias por el uso de nuevas tecnologías (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(8): 369-375, oct. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73947</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la situación actual del cumplimiento terapéutico en la hipertensión arterial en España, en opinión de los pacientes. Proyecto Cumplex II</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d962^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
