<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058279</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Values of high-density lipoprotein cholesterol in the pediatric population and risk of thrombosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction         There is evidence of the protective effect of high-density lipoprotein (HDL)-cholesterol against atheroma plaque formation and of its role in cholesterol efflux from cells, as well as its anti-oxidative and inflammatory modulating response properties. Low HDL-cholesterol levels have been associated with a prothrombotic state.         Objective         To determine the relationship between HDL-cholesterol and lipidic and hemostatic parameters.         Patients and methods         We studied 110 children (50 girls, 60 boys) aged between 6 and 7 years old. Lipid profile, D-dimer, plasminogen activator inhibitor (PAI) and fibrinogen were determined.         Results         The mean values of the studied parameters were as follows: total cholesterol (192.92 ± 26.01 mg/dl), HDL-cholesterol (72.87 ± 15.69 mg/dl), low-density lipoprotein-cholesterol (109.46 ± 23.30 mg/dl), triglycerides (56.24 ± 20.35 mg/dl), apolipoprotein B (91.96 ± 14.93 mg/dl), apolipoprotein A1 (168.4 ± 24.55 mg/dl), lipoprotein(a) logarithm (1.76 ± 1.36 mg/dl), plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 logarithm (PAI-1) (3.77 ± 3.93 U/ml), D-dimer logarithm (5.53 ± 0.49 ng/ml) and fibrinogen (268.61 ± 48.59 mg/dl).When the sample was divided into two groups according to HDL-cholesterol levels, children with lower levels showed significantly higher values of total cholesterol/HDL-cholesterol, fibrinogen and PAI. HDL-cholesterol levels were directly and significantly associated with total cholesterol and apolipoprotein A1 and negatively and significantly associated with the total cholesterol/HDL-cholesterol ratio, fibrinogen and PAI.         Conclusion         The children studied had high HDL-cholesterol levels, which could be responsible for the high total cholesterol levels. High values of HDL-cholesterol are significantly associated with a reduction in thrombotic risk</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vacas Rius, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magro López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez de Lafuente Chivite, J. Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iriarte Ezkurdia, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez Meabe, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molinero de Miguel, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafita Bernar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Gutiérrez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sagastagoitia Gorostiza, J. D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción         Existen evidencias del papel protector que el colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad (c-HDL) puede ejercer frente a la formación de la placa de ateroma y de su implicación en el transporte reverso de colesterol, así como de sus propiedades antioxidantes y moduladoras de la respuesta inflamatoria. También se han relacionado concentraciones bajas con un estado protrombótico.         Objetivo         Determinar la relación existente entre el c-HDL y los parámetros lipídicos y hemostáticos.         Pacientes y métodos         Un total de 110 niños (50 niñas, 60 niños) de entre 6 y 7 años. Se determinó el perfil lipídico, dímero-D, inhibidor del activador del plasminógeno y fibrinógeno.         Resultados         Los valores medios de los parámetros estudiados fueron colesterol total (192,92 ± 26,01 mg/dl), c-HDL (72,87 ± 15,69 mg/dl), colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (c-LDL) (109,46 ± 23,30 mg/dl), triglicéridos (56,24 ± 20,35 mg/dl), apolipoproteína B (apo B) (91,96 ± 14,93 mg/dl), apo A1 (168,4 ± 24,55 mg/dl), logaritmo lipoproteína(a) (1,76 ± 1,36 mg/dl), logaritmo del inhibidor del activador del plasminógeno tipo 1 (PAI-1) (3,77 ± 3,93 U/ml), logaritmo del dímero-D (5,53 ± 0,49 ng/ml) y fibrinógeno (268,61 ± 48,59 mg/dl). Al dividir la muestra en dos grupos, atendiendo a las concentraciones de c-HDL, los niños con valores más bajos presentaron concentraciones más elevadas y estadísticamente significativas de colesterol total/c-HDL, fibrinógeno y PAI. Los valores de c-HDL se asociaron directa y significativamente con colesterol total y apo A1 e inversa y significativamente con el cociente colesterol total/c-HDL, fibrinógeno y el PAI.         Conclusión         La población infantil estudiada presentó valores elevados de c-HDL, y éstos pudieron ser los responsables del incremento de colesterol total. Aumentos en su concentración se asociaron de manera significativa con una disminución del riesgo trombótico</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);67(6): 567-571, dic. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058279</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valores de colesterol HDL en la población infantil y riesgo trombótico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38142^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8250^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14679^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22179</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11392</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14312^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
