<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164468</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospital discharge criteria for very low birth weight newborns</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hospital discharge criteria for the pre-term newborn are mainly based on physiological competences (thermoregulation, respiratory stability, and feeding skills), although family support and ability to care for the baby, as well as a well-planned discharge are also cornerstones to ensure a successful discharge. In this article, the Committee of Standards of the Spanish Society of Neonatology reviews the current hospital discharge criteria in order for it to be useful as a clinical guide in Spanish neonatal units (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Luna, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leante Castellanos, Jose Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz López, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavente Fernández, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Redondo, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Muñuzuri, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rite Gracia, Segundo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Campillo, Cèsar W</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los criterios de alta del recién nacido pretérmino se basan principalmente en los denominados criterios fisiológicos (termorregulación, estabilidad respiratoria y la capacidad para realizar alimentación oral), sin que podamos olvidar la importancia de la adquisición de competencias por parte de los padres para el cuidado de sus hijos y la necesidad de una adecuada planificación del alta como pilares de un alta con plenas garantías. En este documento del Comité de Estándares de la Sociedad Española de Neonatología se revisan los criterios de alta del recién nacido pretérmino con objeto de que pueda ser útil como guía en la planificación del alta y para unificar criterios entre las distintas Unidades de Neonatología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);87(1): 54.e1-54.e8, jul. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Criterios de alta hospitalaria para el recién nacido de muy bajo peso al nacimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24213^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52501</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
