<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104028</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of early administration of levosimendan in emergency department in patients with acute heart failure: a randomized pilot clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To compare the efficacy and safety of early levosimendan administration in addition to standard treatment in patients with severe symptoms of decompensated heart failure attended in the emergency department (ED).Methods: A single-center, prospective, third-party blinded, randomized, placebo controlled, pilot study was performed in 45 patients with advanced heart failure attended in the ED. Patients were randomized 1:1 to receive intravenous levosimendan or placebo in addition to standard care. The primary endpoint was improvement in baseline dyspnea over24 hours. Improvement of orthopnea, jugular ingurgitation and peripheral edema, cumulated diuresis and changes insystolic and diastolic blood pressure and in heart and respiratory rates were also registered. Adverse events during treatment were recorded. Patients were followed for 7 days and at 1 and 6 months after hospital discharge for all causes of hospital readmission, mortality or both. Results: Dyspnea improved faster and in more patients with the use of levosimendan (P&lt;0.05). Similar findings were found for orthopnea (P&lt;0.05), with no differences for the remaining variables. Adverse effects were observed in 20% and25% of patients in the levosimendan and placebo groups, respectively (P=NS), with no patients withdrawn from the protocol. No differences were seen with respect to readmission, mortality or both outcomes in combination. Conclusion: Early treatment with levosimendan produces no significant differences in readmission or mortality rates, although it is associated with a significant clinical benefit in terms of improvement in dyspnea and orthopnea compared with placebo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carbajosa-Dalmau, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorens, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llanos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapater, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar la eficacia y la seguridad de la administración precoz de levosimendán junto con la terapia convencional en pacientes con síntomas graves de insuficiencia cardiaca aguda (ICA) atendidos en un servicio de urgencias (SU).Método: Estudio piloto de intervención controlado con placebo, aleatorizado, tripleciego, unicéntrico, y que incluyó 45 pacientes con ICA avanzada atendidos en un SU. Los pacientes fueron aleatorizados 1:1 para recibir levosimendán o placebo añadido al tratamiento convencional. El objetivo primario fue la mejoría de la disnea basal las primeras 24 horas. También se registró la mejoría de la ortopnea, la ingurgitación yugular, el edema periférico, la diuresis acumulada, las modificaciones en la presión arterial sistólica y diastólica y en la frecuencia respiratoria y cardiaca. Se recogió los eventos adversos durante la administración del tratamiento. Se realizó un seguimiento de todos los pacientes a los 7 días, y en el primer y sexto mes tras el alta hospitalaria, y se registró la mortalidad y los reingresos hospitalarios por cualquier causa o su combinación. Resultados: La disnea mejoró más rápido y en más pacientes con la administración delevosimendán (p &lt; 0,05). Resultados similares se encontraron con la ortopnea(p &lt; 0,05), sin diferencias significativas en el resto de las variables. Aparecieron efectos adversos en el 20% y en el 25% de los pacientes con levosimendán y placebo respectivamente (p = NS), pero en ningún caso motivó la retirada del paciente del estudio. No se observó diferencias respecto al reingreso, la mortalidad o la variable combinada .Conclusiones: El tratamiento precoz con levosimendán no produce diferencias estadísticamente significativas respecto el reingreso o la mortalidad, aunque sí se asocia con un beneficio clínico significativo en términos de mejoría de la disnea y la ortopnea comparado con placebo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);24(4): 268-276, ago. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104028</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la administración precoz de levosimendán en urgencias en pacientes con insuficiencia cardiaca aguda: un ensayo clínico piloto aleatorizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24613^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2357^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201208</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
