<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042629</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Compressive osteotomes for expansion and maxilla sinus floor lifting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: The aim of this article is to assess the efficiency of the technique for the posterior alveolar expansion and elevation of the upper maxillary alveolar ridge through the use of compressive osteotomes (Quirurgical Bontempi, España) which have been specifically designed for Osseotite NT and Osseotite NT Certain of 3i implants (Implants Innovations, USA). Materials and Methods: 24 adult patients (16 female and 12 male), who were selected according to Albrektsson&#146;s inclusion and exclusion criteria, took part in the study. All the patients presented bone deficiency in the width and height of the upper maxilla. 48 Osseotite implants were performed (four Osseotite Standard; six Osseotite NT; 38 NT Certain (3i, Implants Innovations, CA, USA)). Implant diameters were 4 mm in 44 cases and 5 mm in 4 cases with lengths varying between 11.5 (n = 4) and 13 mm. (n = 44). The alveolar ridges of the 24 patients had initial widths from 1.5 mm to 5 mm and heights between 5 and 13mm. Results: The data obtained were analysed using the SPSS 11.0 program. In the 48 areas treated with immediate implants, an increase in bone height of 6.75 mm ± 1.25 mm. was achieved. In the case of the alveolar expansion for the 48 implants, the average was 3.2 mm. ± 0.15 mm. Conclusions: The technique for alveolar expansion and elevation of the upper maxilla with compressive osseotomes can lead to a 100% success rate after a 9-month follow-up of the implants and insertion of prostheses. It is a highly predictable surgical procedure which allows implants to be performed at the same time as surgery, thus reducing the number of such interventions while recovering aesthetic and functional losses in the patient</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo Guirado, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saez Yuguero, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Zamora, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo de este artículo es evaluar la eficacia de la técnica del ensanchamiento alveolar posterior y elevación del rebordealveolar del maxilar superior mediante el uso de los osteótomos compresivos ( Quirurgical Bontempi, España) especialmente diseñados para los implantes Osseotite NT y Osseotite NT Certain de 3i ( Implants Innovations, USA). Material y métodos: En el estudio se incluyeron 24 pacientes (16 mujeres y 8 hombres) siguiendo los criterios de inclusión y exclusiónde Albrektsson, que presentaban un déficit óseo en anchura y altura del maxilar superior. Se colocaron 48 implantes Osseotite ( cuatro Osseotite Standard, seis Ossoetite NT y treinta y ocho NT Certain (3i, Implantes Innovations, CA, USA). El diámetro de los implantes fueron 44 de 4 mm y 4 de 5 mm con longitudes que variaban entre 11.5 (n=4) y 13 mm (n= 44). La cresta alveolar inicial tenía una anchura que variaba de 1.5mm a 5 mm y una altura que oscilaba entre 5 mm y 13 mm en los 24 pacientes. Resultados: Los datos obtenidos fueron analizados con el programa SPSS 11.0. En los 48 sitios tratados donde se colocaron los implantes inmediatos se obtuvo un aumento de altura ósea de 6.75 mm ± 1.25 mm. En el ensanchamiento alveolar de los 48 sitios implantados la media fue de 3.2 mm ± 0.15 mm. Conclusiones: La técnica de ensanchamiento y elevación alveolar del maxilar superior con osteótomos compresivos permiteobtener un porcentaje de éxito de un 100 % a los 9 meses de seguimiento en los implantes y prótesis colocadas. Es un procedimiento quirúrgico con alta predictibilidad y además permite la colocación los implantes en el mismo acto quirúrgico reduciendo el número de cirugías, devolviendo la estética y función del paciente perdidas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);11(1): 52-55, ene. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042629</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ensanchamiento y elevación del suelo sinusal maxilar con osteotomos compresivos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24237^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29433^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13897^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13897^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28854^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8611^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30761</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
