<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111725</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multidisciplinary guidelines for the management of community-acquired pneumonia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) is an infectious respiratory disease with an incidence that ranges from 3 to 8 cases per 1,000 inhabitants per year. This incidence increases with age and comorbidities. Forty per cent of CAP patients require hospitalization and around 10% of these patients are admitted in an Intensive Care Unit (ICU). Several studies have suggested that the implementation of clinical guidelines has a positive impact in the outcome of patients including mortality and length of stay. The more recent and used guidelines are those from Infectious Diseases Society of America/American Thoracic Society, published in 2007, the 2009 from the British Thoracic Society, and that from the European Respiratory Society/European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, published in 2010. In Spain, the most recently released guideline is the Sociedad Española de Neumología y Cirugía Torácica-2011 guideline. The present guidelines GNAC are designed to be used by the majority of health-care professionals that can participate in the care of CAP patients including diagnosis, decision of hospital and ICU admission, treatment and prevention. The Centro Cochrane Iberoamericano (CCIB) has participated in summarizing the previous guidelines and in the bibliography search. For each one of the following sections the panel of experts has developed a table with recommendations classified according to its evidence, strength and practical applicability using the Grading of Recommendations of Assessment Development and Evaluations (GRADE) system: 1. Epidemiology, microbiological etiology and antibiotic resistances. 2. Clinical and microbiological diagnosis. 3. Prognostic scales and decision of hospital admission. 4. ICU admission criteria. 5. Empirical and definitive antibiotic treatment. 6. Treatment failure. 7. Prevention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Menéndez, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barberán, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falguera, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olaechea, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La neumonía adquirida en la comunidad (NAC) es una enfermedad infecciosa respiratoria aguda que tiene una incidencia que oscila entre 3 y 8 casos por 1.000 habitantes por año. Esta incidencia aumenta con la edad y las comorbilidades. El 40% de los pacientes con NAC requieren ingreso hospitalario y alrededor del 10% necesitan ser admitidos en una Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos (UCI). La mortalidad global de la NAC está alrededor del 10%. Diversos estudios han sugerido que la implementación de guías clínicas mejora la evolución del paciente tanto en mortalidad como en estancia hospitalaria. Las guías clínicas más recientes y más utilizadas son la de la Infectious Diseases Society of America/American Thoracic Society, publicada en 2007, la de la British Thoracic Society, publicada en 2009, y la de la European Respiratory Society en colaboracio´n con la European Society of Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, publicada en 2011. En España, la más reciente es la normativa de la Sociedad Española de Neumología y Cirugía Torácica, publicada en el año 2010. La presente guía clínica GNAC es multidisciplinar y ha contado con la ayuda del Centro Cochrane Iberoamericano (CCIB) para la síntesis de las guías previas y la selección de la bibliografía. Esta guía clínica está diseñada para ser utilizada por todos los profesionales que pueden participar en el proceso asistencial de la NAC en sus vertientes diagnóstica, de caracterización de la gravedad, de tratamiento y de prevención. Para cada uno de los siguientes apartados se han desarrollado tablas con recomendaciones donde se clasifica su evidencia, la fortaleza de la misma y su aplicabilidad práctica según la clasificación Grading of Recommendations of Assessment Development and Evaluations (GRADE): 1. Epidemiología, etiología microbiana y resistencias microbianas. 2. Diagnóstico clínico y microbiológico. 3. Escalas pronósticas y decisión de ingreso hospitalario. 4. Criterios de ingreso en la UCI. 5. Tratamiento antibiótico empírico y tratamiento antibiótico definitivo. 6. Falta de respuesta al tratamiento antibiótico. 7. Vacunaciones en la prevención de la NAC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);140(5): 223.e1-223.e19, mar. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Guía multidisciplinar para la valoración pronóstica, diagnóstico y tratamiento de la neumonía adquirida en la comunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28632</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
