<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88665</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacist role in the nutrition area at the European level</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Once graduated, the pharmacist can choose a high number of professional skills, both in public and private sectors. The most frequent professional skills of the pharmacist can be included in 4 different fields: Pharmacy Office (Communitary Pharmacy), Hospital Pharmacy, Distribution andPharmaceutical Industry or Analysis and Public Health. At the pharmacy office level, the pharmacist, along with the medicines dispensation, exercises an out-standing role as health adviser. The statistics reveal that 25% of the pharmacy customers do not acquire medicines, but they only ask for a sanitary advice, including nutrition and dietetic consultations. Moreover, in the last years nutritive supplements have been included within the pharmaceutical sales. Thus, the pharmacist should be formed about nutritional topics. Another professional skill, like the pharmaceutical inspection, includes drinkable water and non-animal foodstuffs analyses. Then, the pharmacist should have a wide knowledge on legislation, health and food analysis. On the other hand, the pharmaceutical industry includes a wide variety of professional skills, including technical direction, quality control, commercial management, scientific documentation or analysis. Finally, the agro-alimentary industry has experienced important changes in the last decades, demanding professionals in the matter, like dietitians or food analysts. In this sense, the pharmacist, across the new degree in Pharmacy, must acquire a solid base in the nutrition and bromatology field. Therefore, the competences gathered in the Disposition CIN / 2137/2008 reveals the importance of the formation of the future pharmacist in the nutrition area(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olalla-Herrera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-López, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giménez-Martínez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samaniego-Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanca-Herrera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artacho-Martín-Lagos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Villanova, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Alarcón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rufián-Henares, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera-Vique, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerra-Hernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mesías-García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada-Granados, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-García de la Serrana, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una vez licenciado, el farmacéutico puede optar por un elevado número de salidas profesionales, tanto en el sector público al servicio de los diferentes cuerpos y administraciones, como en el sector privado. Los perfiles profesionales más frecuentes del farmacéutico pueden englobarse en 4 modalidades: Oficina de Farmacia (Farmacia Comunitaria), Farmacia Hospitalaria, Distribución e Industria Farmacéutica o Análisis y Salud Pública. A nivel de oficina de farmacia, el farmacéutico, junto a la dispensación de medicamentos, ejerce un destacado papel como asesor y consejero de salud. Las estadísticas desvelan que una de cada cuatro personas que entran en una farmacia no adquiere medicamentos, sino que sólo pide un consejo sanitario, incluyendo asesoría sobre dietas, alimentación y nutrición. Además, la aparición en los últimos años de complementos alimenticios, de venta en farmacia, hace que el farmacéutico deba formarse y comportarse como profesional en lo que respecta a temas de nutrición. Otra salida profesional, como la inspección Farmacéutica, incluye la supervisión de agua y alimentos no animales, por lo que el farmacéutico debe tener un amplio conocimiento sobre la legislación, sanidad y análisis de alimentos. Por otro lado, la industria farmacéutica incluye una amplia variedad de salidas profesionales, incluyéndose dirección técnica, control de calidad y de fabricación, gestión comercial, documentación científica o análisis. La industria agroalimentaria ha experimentado importantes cambios en las últimas décadas, exigiendo profesionales en la materia, como dietistas o analistas bromatológicos, dentro de un equipo multidisciplinar. En este sentido, el farmacéutico, a través del nuevo grado en Farmacia, debe adquirir una base sólida en el campo de la nutrición y bromatología. Así, las competencias recogidas en la Orden CIN/2137/2008 ponen de manifiesto la importancia de la formación del futuro farmacéutico en el ámbito de la alimentación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.2): 435-442, mayo 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88665</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfil del farmacéutico en el ámbito de la nutrición a nivel europeo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29564^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52458^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10794^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3189^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4582^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3193^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10786^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5158^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52503^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
