<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162641</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mental fatigue impairs the basketball free-throw performance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mental fatigue has a negative effect on endurance tasks, but little is known about its effect on sports skills precision. The aim of this study was to check if mental stress reduces the free throw effectiveness in basketball. 18 semi-professional players performed the experiment. The experimental group performed the 2-back memory task, while another control group performed the Oddball version of the same test, a version that does not generate fatigue of the central executive. Participants in the experimental group had a lower rate of success than the control group. These results demonstrate the negative influence of mental fatigue on precision skills such as free throw in basketball (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alarcón López, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ureña Ortín, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas Vélez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fatiga mental tiene un efecto negativo en tareas de resistencia, pero poco se sabe de su efecto en habilidades deportivas de precisión. El objetivo de este estudio fue comprobar si el esfuerzo mental reduce la eficacia de los tiros libre en baloncesto. 18 jugadores semiprofesionales realizaron el experimento. El grupo experimental realizó la prueba de memoria 2-back, mientras otro grupo control realizó la versión Oddball de la misma tarea, una versión que no genera fatiga del ejecutivo central. Los participantes del grupo experimental tuvieron un porcentaje de acierto inferior al del grupo control. Estos resultados demuestran la influencia negativa de la fatiga mental sobre habilidades de precisión como es el tiro libre en baloncesto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.1): 33-36, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162641</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La fatiga mental deteriora el rendimiento en el tiro libre en baloncesto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5326^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19084^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
