<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143335</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Progression of urinary protein excretion after kidney transplantation: A marker for poor long-term prognosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Post-transplantation proteinuria is a risk factor for graft failure. A progressive decline in renal graft function is a predictor for mortality in kidney transplant patients. Objectives: To assess the development and the progression of urinary protein excretion (UPE) in the first year post-transplant in recipients of kidney transplants and its effect on patient and graft outcomes. Materials and methods: We analysed 1815 patients with 24-h UPE measurements available at 3 and 12 months post-transplant. Patients were divided based on their UPE level: below 300mg, 300&#150;1000mg and over 1000mg (at 3 and 12 months), and changes over time were analysed. Results: At 3 months, 65.7% had UPE below 300mg/24h, 29.6% 300&#150;1000mg/24h and 4.7% over 1000mg/24h. At one year, 71.6% had UPE below 300mg/24h, 24.1% 300&#150;1000mg/24h and 4.4% over 1000mg/24h. In 208 patients (12%), the UPE progressed, in 1233 (70.5%) it remained stable and in 306 (17.5%) an improvement was observed. We found that the level of UPE influenced graft survival, particularly if a progression occurred. Recipient's age and renal function at one year were found to be predictive factors for mortality, while proteinuria and renal function were predictive factors for graft survival. Conclusions: Proteinuria after transplantation, essentially when it progresses, is a marker of a poor prognosis and a predictor for graft survival. Progression of proteinuria is associated with poorer renal function and lower graft survival rates (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabello Díaz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Gil, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osuna Ortega, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrego Hinojosa, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodriguez Benot, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mazuecos Blanca, Auxiliadora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro De La Nuez, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bedoya Pérez, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gentil Govantes, Miguel Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La proteinuria después de un trasplante renal constituye un factor de riesgo para el fallo del injerto. Una disminución progresiva de la función del injerto renal es un predictor de la mortalidad en los pacientes trasplantados renales. Objetivos: Analizar la aparición y la progresión de una excreción urinaria de proteínas (EUP) en el primer año siguiente al trasplante en pacientes trasplantados renales, y su efecto sobre la evolución del paciente y del injerto. Material y métodos: Analizamos un total de 1815 pacientes en los que se dispuso de determinaciones de la EUP de 24 horas a los 3 y a los 12 meses del trasplante. Dividimos a los pacientes según el nivel de EUP, de la siguiente forma: inferior a 300mg, 300-1000mg y más de 1000mg (a los 3 y 12 meses), y analizamos los cambios a lo largo del tiempo. Resultados: A los 3 meses, el 65,7% presentaban una EUP inferior a 300mg/24h, el 29,6% 300-1000mg/24h y el 4,7% más de 1000mg/24h. A un año, el 71,6% tenían una EUP inferior a 300mg/24h, el 24,1% 300-1000mg/24h y el 4,4% más de 1000mg/24h. En 208 pacientes (12%), la EUP mostró una progresión, en 1233 (70,5%) se mantuvo estable y en 306 (17,5%) se observó una mejoría. Observamos que el nivel de EUP influía en la supervivencia del injerto, en especial si se producía una progresión. La edad y la función renal del receptor al año del trasplante fueron factores predictivos de la mortalidad, mientras que la proteinuria y la función renal lo fueron de la supervivencia del injerto. Conclusiones: La proteinuria después del trasplante, fundamentalmente cuando muestra una progresión, es un marcador de mal pronóstico y un factor predictivo de la supervivencia del injerto. La progresión de la proteinuria se asocia a una peor función renal y a una tasa de supervivencia del injerto inferior (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;35(4): 374-378, jul.-ago. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143335</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Progresión de la excreción urinaria de proteínas después del trasplante renal: un marcador de mal pronóstico a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
