<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154104</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-2159</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Where to look when looking at faces: visual scanning is determined by gender, expression and tasks demands</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Visual scanning of faces was studied during categorization of expression and gender with the aim of revealing possible differences in the perceptual mechanisms that mediate analysis of these facial properties. A more distributed scanning pattern, with increased fixation in the lower face, was observed in the expression compared to the gender task. Distribution of fixations across the upper and lower face also varied depending on the specific gender and expression of the viewed faces, with female faces and faces showing anger attracting more fixations to the eye region. Variations reflecting an interaction between gender and expression were also observed. However, the nature of these modulations suggests a differential influence of perceptual interactions and social/affective value on eye movement measures and on pupil size. Collectively, these results show that the visual inspection of faces is determined in a complex manner by the specific demands of different categorization tasks and by the perceptual and social/affective properties of the emotional expressions shown by either male or female faces (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero-Ferreiro, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Gutiérrez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Moreno, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se ha estudiado la inspección visual de caras durante tareas de categorización de expresión y género con el objetivo de encontrar posibles diferencias en los mecanismos perceptuales que medían el análisis de las propiedades faciales. Se observó un patrón de inspección visual más distribuido con un incremento de fijaciones en la parte baja de la cara durante la tarea de expresión frente a la tarea de género. La distribución de las fijaciones en torno a la parte superior e inferior de la cara también varió dependiendo del género y de la expresión de las caras con un número mayor de fijaciones en la región de los ojos para las caras de ira femeninas. Los resultados indicaron también una interacción entre género y expresión. La naturaleza de estas modulaciones sugiere una influencia diferencial sobre las medidas oculares y el tamaño de la pupila dependientes del tipo de tarea y del valor socio-afectivo de los estímulos. En conjunto, estos resultados muestran que la inspección visual de caras está determinada de una manera compleja por las demandas específicas de diferentes tareas de categorización; por las propiedades perceptivas y por la naturaleza de las expresiones emocionales mostradas por caras masculinas y femeninas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>PsicolÔogica (Valencia, Ed. impr.);37(2): 127-150, 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154104</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dónde mirar cuando miramos caras: el escaneo visual está determinado por el género, la expresión y las demandas de la tarea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10337^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12026^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12026^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15197^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9819^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10557^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1301^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6391</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12039^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5250</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
