<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129093</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the efficiency of a therapeutic educational program for morbid obese individuals: integral group education</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the changes produced in the body mass index, fat mass and lean mass, of a group of obese patients that participated in the therapeutic  educational program: Integral education in group for weight control. Methodology: 57 obese patients with average age 47,49 ((±SD) 11,8 years including a range between 18 and 75 years were studied, 33,3% men and 66,7% women. Four sessions to measure anthropometric parameters using an a body mass analyzer repeated after 12 months to evaluate the results. Results: The difference between the initial and the final BMI (p= 0,016) was   significant. The difference between the initial fat initial and middle measurement obtained significant results (p= 0,001), as well as between the initial and the final measurement (p= 0,001). Differences of the average lean mass did not obtained statistical significance. Discussion and conclusions: Group education applied to morbid obese contribute to the decrease of BMI and the medium-term fat mass (one year) maintaining the muscular mass. Practical implications: Designing strategies optimizing resources, it is useful to the obese (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Puerta, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Aured, María Lourdes de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre Barbero, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pardo, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañones Castelló, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ruiz, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los cambios producidos en el Índice de Masa Corporal, masa grasa y masa magra de los obesos que han asistido al programa terapéutico educativo: Educación integral en grupo para control de peso. Metodología: Estudio de 57 pacientes obesos, con edad media (±DE) de 47,49 de ±11,8 años, comprendida entre los 18 y 75 años, de los cuales un 33,3% son varones y un 66,7 % mujeres. Se realizaron cuatro sesiones para medir parámetros antropométricos, utilizando un   analizador de la masa corporal. A los 12 meses se evalúan los resultados obtenidos. Resultados: La diferencia entre el IMC de inicio y la final (p=0,016) resultó significativa. La diferencia entre la masa grasa de inicio y la medida media, obtuvo resultados significativos (p=0,001), como lo fueron los resultados de la primera medida y la última (p=0,001). Las   diferencias de las medias de masa magra, no obtuvieron significación estadística. Conclusiones: Los talleres de educación en grupo aplicados a obesos mórbidos colaboran en la disminución del IMC y la masa grasa, a medio plazo (un año) manteniendo la masa muscular. Implicaciones prácticas: Diseñar estrategias optimizando los recursos resulta útil al obeso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;17(3): 134-138, jul.-sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129093</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la eficacia de un programa educativo en grupo para obesos mórbidos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
