<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94258</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inhaled antibiotic therapy in cystic fibrosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cystic fibrosis is the most frequent fatal genetically-transmitted disease among Caucasians. Chronic bronchialinfection, especially by Pseudomonas aeruginosa, is the main cause of morbidity and mortality in this disease.Aerosolized antibiotic therapy achieves high drug concentrations in the airway with low toxicity, allowingchronic use. Currently, two antibiotics have been approved for inhalation therapy, tobramycin inhalationsolution and colistimethate sodium aerosol. There is less evidence from clinical trials for the latter. The mainindication for these drugs is chronic bronchial colonization by P. aeruginosa, although there is increasingevidence of the importance of the primary infection by this bacterium, whether treated by oral or intravenousantibiotics or not. More controversial is the use of aerosolized antibiotic therapy in bacterial prophylaxis orrespiratory exacerbations. For many years, intravenous formulations of distinct antibiotics for aerosolized usehave been employed, which are in distinct phases of research for use in nebulizer therapy. In addition to beingused to treat P. aeruginosa infection, aerosolized antibiotics have been used to treat other pathogens such asmethicillin-resistant Staphylococus aureus, Mycobacterium abscessus and Aspergillus fumigatus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salcedo Posadas, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón Moreno, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Punter, Rosa Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fibrosis quística es la enfermedad genética letal más frecuente en la población caucasiana. La infecciónbronquial crónica, especialmente por Pseudomonas aeruginosa, es la principal causa de morbimortalidad deesta patología. El tratamiento antibiótico por aerosol alcanza altas concentraciones en la vía aérea con bajatoxicidad, por lo que permite el empleo crónico. En la actualidad hay 2 antibióticos aprobados para su usoinhalatorio, la tobramicina en solución para inhalación y el colistimetato de sodio, existiendo con este últimomenos evidencias en estudios clínicos. La indicación fundamental es la colonización bronquial crónica por P.aeruginosa, aunque cada vez se demuestra más relevancia en la primoinfección por esta bacteria, acompañadao no de antibióticos por vía oral o intravenosos. Más controvertido es el uso de la aerosolterapia antibiótica enla profilaxis bacteriana o en la exacerbación respiratoria. Durante muchos años se han estado empleandoformulaciones intravenosas de distintos antibióticos en aerosol, las cuales están en distintas fases de investigaciónpara su lanzamiento como presentación por vía nebulizada. Además de su indicación en el tratamientode la infección por P. aeruginosa se han empleado otros antibióticos en aerosol para otros patógenos comoStaphylococus aureus resistentes a meticilina, Mycobacterium abscessus o Aspergillus fumigatus(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(supl.6): 14-18, jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94258</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Antibioterapia inhalada en la fibrosis quística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3122^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3122^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24008^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24008^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14419^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11988^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
