<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78648</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Opinion and beliefs of pregnancy women in prenatal control related to oral health and pregnant</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vital processes have created questions to humankind. People&amp;#146;s culture gives non-scientific response to some of it, changing beliefs into myths. Related to oral health, several cultures believe that pregnant women could suffer more frequently dental caries than general population, is considered normal that "by each one baby, mother lost a teeth", and some pregnant patients are not able to receive dental treatment, because this procedures could produce damages to fetus in develop; important situation considering absence of information that dental procedures expose to such a low risk to patients in some physicians, whom refuse authorize to pregnant women to receive dental treatment. Culture has a deep relationship to life styles, social relations and self-help; in these intervention mechanisms are based health promotion. The research seeks to know the ideas have a group of pregnant women in prenatal control related to oral health and pregnant. Was made a survey with 5 closed questions, applied to 65 pregnant woman randomly selected. 98% of women think that through pregnant period is necessary to visit a dentist, 60% believe that pregnant cause dental caries and 70% thinks that pregnant could cause lost of tooth. Mayor efforts in education, considering cultural factors, are required through prenatal control to improve knowledge as well as self care in oral health in these patients group (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Fernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oporto Venegas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón,  AM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustos Medina, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rico Williams, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Gómez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los procesos vitales son motivo de preguntas para la humanidad. La cultura popular da respuestas a éstas, no siempre científicamente, transformando las creencias en mitos. En salud oral, se cree que las embarazadas desarrollarían caries más fácilmente que la población general, considerándose normal que &#147;por cada hijo se pierda un diente&#148;, y mujeres embarazadas no desean recibir atención odontológica por el daño que podría producir al feto el uso de anestésicos locales, hecho importante ante la carencia de información del bajo riesgo que poseen para el paciente éstos procedimientos por algunos médicos, quienes rehusan someter a embarazadas a tratamientos dentales. La cultura tiene una profunda relación en el estilo de vida, sociabilización y autoayuda, mecanismos de intervención que serían cimientos que basan la promoción en salud. La investigación busca conocer las ideas que posee un grupo de embarazadas en control prenatal, en torno a la salud oral y el embarazo. Fue confeccionada una encuesta con 5 preguntas cerradas, aplicándose a 65 embarazadas seleccionadas aleatoriamente. La muestra fue obtenida por conveniencia. El 98% de las encuestadas cree que durante el embarazo es necesario consultar al odontólogo, el 60% cree que el embarazo produce caries y el 70% cree que el embarazo puede producir pérdida de piezas dentarias. Se requieren más esfuerzos en educación durante el control prenatal para entregar conocimientos adecuados a las embarazadas en relación a salud oral y embarazo, incluyendo el factor cultural, que les permita mejorarlas medidas de auto cuidado durante este período (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;25(3): 147-154, mayo-jun. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78648</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Opiniones y creencias de embarazadas encontrol prenatal relacionadas con salud oral y embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28452</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
