<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129943</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetives: To analyze the influence of the different pre-cystectomy factors, both clinical and pathological, in the follow up of patients with no residual tumor ( pT0 ) in the pathological examination of the radical cystectomy specimen as predictors of tumor recurrence. Secondly we intend to compare overall survival, disease free survival and cancer-specific survival with the rest of cystectomy patients in our series. Methods: Between 1985 and 2010, radical cystectomy was performed in 280 patients with bladder cancer, being 41 pT0 (14.6%). We analyzed potential predictors for overall survival and disease-free survival: age, sex , number of transurethral resections of bladder tumor before cystectomy , tumor type , tumor grade, tumor stage, tumor size, number of tumors, associated Cis and previous instillations. We used univariate analysis of Cox regression. Survival analysis was performed using Kaplan &#150; Meier curves and log-rank test. Results: Mean age was 61.7 years and 37 patients were males (90.2%). Stages before cystectomy were pT1 in eight (19.5%) , pT2 in 31 (75.6%) and Cis in two (4.9 %) with tumor grade III in 37 (90.2%). Cystectomy specimens revealed the presence of papillary transitional cell carcinoma in 38 (92.7%) cases. The median number of pre-cistectomy-TURBT was one. Eleven patients (26.8%) received intravesical instillations. Six patients (14.63 %) had tumor recurrence and 10 (24.4 %) died from causes unrelated to the disease. None of the variables analyzed was statistically significant in the univariate analysis as a predictor of tumor recurrence. With a median follow up of 70 months (3-272) disease-free survival and overall survival at five years were 85.9% and 72.8% respectively. Compared to the non pT0 cystectomies in our series, pT0 had a statistically significant difference for better recurrence-free survival (63.4 % and 36.8%, respectively in pT0 and no-pT0 patients) (p&lt;0,05) (...)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Portillo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gala, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuetnes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Truán, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos Juanatey, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrión, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Analizar la influencia de los diferentes factores pre-cistectomía tanto clínicos como anatomopatológicos, en el seguimiento de pacientes con estudio anatomopatológico de la pieza de cistectomía radical con ausencia de tumor residual (pT0), como factores predictivos de recurrencia tumoral en estos pa¬cientes. En segundo lugar pretendemos comparar la su-pervivencia global, supervivencia libre de enfermedad y la supervivencia cáncer específica con las del resto de pacientes cistectomizados de nuestra serie. Métodos: Entre 1985-2010 se intervinieron 280 pa¬cientes de cistectomía radical por causa tumoral, de los cuales 41 fueron pT0 (14,6%). Se exploraron los potenciales factores predictores para supervivencia global y supervivencia libre de enfermedad: edad, sexo, número de resecciones transuretrales de vejiga previas a la cistectomía, tipo tumoral, grado, estadio, tamaño tumoral   número de tumores, Cis asociado e instilaciones previas usando un análisis univariado de regresión de Cox. El análisis de supervivencia se realizó mediante curvas de Kaplan-Meier y Log-Rank test.  Resultados: La edad media fue 61,7 años y 37 (90,2%) de ellos fueron varones. Los estadios previos a la cistectomía fueron pT1 en ocho (19,5%), pT2 en 31 (75,6%), y Cis en dos (4,9%), con un grado tu¬moral III en 37 (90,2%). La anatomía patológica (AP), reveló la presencia de carcinoma transicional papilar en 38 (92,7%) casos. La mediana de RTU-V previas fue una. Habían recibido instilaciones endovesicales 11 (26,8%) pacientes. Seis pacientes (14,63%) pre¬sentaron recidiva tumoral y diez (24,4%) fallecieron por causas ajenas a la enfermedad. Ninguna de las variables analizadas resultó ser estadísticamente significativa en el estudio univariado como predictora de recurrencia tumoral. Con una mediana de seguimiento de 70 meses (3-272), la supervivencia libre de enfermedad y supervivencia global fueron del 85,9% y del 72,8% a los cinco años respectivamente (...) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(9): 764-469, nov. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictivos de la evolución de los pacientes pTo Post-Cistectomía Radical por causa tumoral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
