<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047871</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of methylene blue in the treatment of vasoplegic syndrome of post-operative heart surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Vasoplegia is a frequent complication in post-operative heart surgery and determines a significant increase in morbidity-mortality. When vasoplegia persists in spite of optimized fluid therapy with the use of Swan-Ganz catheter, we have a safe, effective and economical alternative, methylene blue. We present the case of a patient who developed vasoplegia refractory to treatment and shock in the scheduled post-operative period of myocardial revascularization. The use of a single dose of methylene blue resolved the hemodynamic instability and allowed for total discontinuation of vasoactive drugs. Thus, we present this new indication of methylene blue, still not approved by the corresponding bodies, for which no national publications have been found and its clinical management and the absence of adverse effects after its use</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vera-Almazán, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora-Ordóñez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Palomino, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernandez Sierra, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galeas-López, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Llorente, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La vasoplejía es una complicación frecuente en el postoperatorio de cirugía cardíaca y determina un importante aumento en la morbi-mortalidad. Cuando a pesar de una fluidoterapia optimizada con el uso del catéter Swan-Ganz y una perfusión de noradrenalina persiste la vasoplejía, disponemos de una alternativa segura, eficaz y económica, el azul de metileno. Presentamos el caso de un paciente que en el postoperatorio programado de revascularización miocárdica desarrolló una vasoplejía refractaria al tratamiento y shock. La utilización de una sola dosis de azul de metileno resolvió la inestabilidad hemodinámica y permitió la suspensión total de los fármacos vasoactivos. Por tanto, se expone esta novedosa indicación del azul de metileno, aún no aprobada por los organismos correspondientes, de la que no hemos encontrado publicaciones nacionales, así como su manejo clínico y la ausencia de efectos adversos tras su utilización</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);30(6): 293-296, ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047871</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de azul de metileno en el tratamiento del síndrome vasopléjico del postoperatorio de cirugía cardíaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4871^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8936^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
