<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137413</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anxiety before exams in college: A single-case study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study presents a cognitive-behavioral therapy applied to a 20 year old female college student with high levels of test anxiety. In addition to the clinical interview, the following questionnaires were administered: Self-Assessment Questionnaire, Achievement Anxiety Test, Study Habits Self Re-port, State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, and Self-Esteem Scale. Based on this assessment, the main objective was to reduce anxiety levels prior to exams and the specific objectives were the removal of distorted thoughts and avoidance behaviors, as well as im-proving studying skills and increasing self-esteem. The intervention was carried out in thirteen treatment sessions in which several cognitive-behavioral techniques were used: psychoeducation, cognitive re-structuring, systematic desensitization, problem solving strategies and assertiveness. On completion of the treatment, a notable reduction of anxiety levels and a successful academic performance were found. In addition, patient scores improved throughout the follow-up. These results support the efficacy of cognitive-behavioral therapy in the treatment of test anxiety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mayo Pais, Mª Emma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreira Trillo, Vanesa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Freire, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio presenta la intervención realizada desde una aproximación cognitivo-conductual a una paciente universitaria de 20 años con elevada ansiedad ante los exámenes. Durante la fase de evaluación se llevó a cabo una entrevista clínica y se administraron los siguientes instrumentos: Cuestionario de Autoevaluación, Cuestionario de Ansiedad ante los Exámenes, Cuestionario de Hábitos de Estudio, Inventario de Ansiedad Estado-Rasgo y Escala de Autoestima. A partir de la evaluación se estableció como objetivo principal de la terapia disminuir los niveles de ansiedad ante los exámenes y como objetivos específicos: eliminar los pensamientos distorsionados y las conductas de evitación, mejorar las técnicas de estudio y aumentar la autoestima. La intervención se desarrolló en 13 sesiones de tratamiento mediante técnicas cognitivo-conductuales: psicoeducación, re-estructuración cognitiva, desensibilización sistemática y entrenamiento en resolución de problemas y asertividad. Finalizado el tratamiento, se registró un descenso notable en los niveles de ansiedad de la paciente y un rendimiento académico exitoso. Además, las calificaciones de la paciente mejoraron a lo largo del seguimiento. Estos resultados apoyan la eficacia de la terapia cognitivo-conductual en el tratamiento de la ansiedad ante los exámenes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;21(1): 21-33, ene.-jun. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ansiedad antes los exámenes en la Universidad: estudio de caso único</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
