<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75756</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pain clinics and palliative care in Mexico: management of opioid-induced constipation. Conclusions of an expert group</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At the end of September 2008, 15 leading figures in pain treatment and palliative care in Mexico met in Mexico City to design a clinical guideline on the use of opioids and the secondary effects of these drugs, with special emphasis on constipation. A new treatment scheme was proposed. The participants currently work in pain or palliative care units throughout Mexico and some are active participants in the design of regulatory measures on opioid use. During the drafting of this guideline, the law reforming palliative treatment in Mexico was passed and came into effect on 6th January, 2009 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morgenstern, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Solares, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aréchiga, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores Cantisani, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A finales de septiembre de 2008, 15 líderes de opinión en el tratamiento del dolor y los cuidados paliativos de México se reunieron en la ciudad de México con el objetivo de elaborar una guía clínica acerca del uso de opiáceos y sus efectos secundarios, con especial acento en el estreñimiento, y se propuso un nuevo esquema de tratamiento. Los participantes trabajan actualmente en unidades de dolor o de paliativos por todo México y algunos son participante activos en la elaboración de medidas reguladoras sobre el uso de opiáceos. Durante la elaboración de esta guía, se ha publicado la Ley de Reforma del Tratamiento Paliativo de México, que ha entrado en vigor el 6 de enero de 2009 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;16(8): 468-481, nov.-dic. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75756</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Clínicas del dolor y cuidados paliativos en México: manejo del estreñimiento inducido por opiáceos. Conclusiones de un grupo de expertos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31907^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3267^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31205^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31205^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9463^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
