<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108686</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Phenomenological experience of interview with users of crack: an experience report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aidms of this paper is to describe the experience of one of the authors in obtaining reports of crack users using the phenomenological interview. Walk in this process were considered key strategies for approaching the subject of this study, since they supported the familiarity and empathy researcher-subject to this overriding methodological strategy. This manifested itself as a strategy for the seizure of intrinsic meanings about death and dying for userto-be-crack. Obtaining reports reflect the experience of them in the consumption of crack cocaine led to the fact that the absence of an existential sense, one can be and being in the world (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Fernando José Guedes da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteiro, Claudete Ferreira de Souza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>pt</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este trabajo es describir la experiencia de uno de los autores en la obtención de informes de los consumidores de crack con la entrevista fenomenológica. Caminar en este proceso se consideraron las principales estrategias para abordar el tema de este estudio, ya que el apoyo de la familiaridad y la empatía investigador-sujeto de esta estrategia metodológica predominante. Esto se manifestó como una estrategia para la toma de los significados intrínsecos sobre la muerte para el usuario-aser-crack. Obtención de informes reflejan la experiencia de ellos en el consumo de cocaína llevó al hecho de que la ausencia de un sentido existencial, se puede estar y ser en el mundo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;16(32): 18-22, ene.-abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108686</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia fenomenológica de la entrevista con consumidores de crack: un relato de experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30172^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7569</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
