<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86397</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pediatric bipolar disorder: on one case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the case of a 14 year old male without antecendents of psychiatric treatment, although oneyear ago, following a surgical intervention on his knee,he presented a period of greater despondency and socialwithdrawal. Since three months ago he has beenmore euphoric and hyperactive, with conflicts with hisfamily and friends.He came to the Accidents and Emergencies Serviceof this hospital accompanied by his father. Evaluationby the Psychiatry Service was requested facing thepresence of maniac symptoms (psychomotor anxiety,verbal incontinence, dysphoria and delusions of grandeur).Following evaluation it was decided to send himto the Psychiatric Hospitalization Unit for diagnosticevaluation and treatment.During his hospital stay the patient was diagnosedas having bipolar disorder (in its maniac phase) and along term treatment was initiated with a mind stabilizer(Valproic acid) and antipsychotic (Risperidone). Followingthe stay he was sent to the Mental Health Centre for follow up and evaluation of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ojer, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leache, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un varón de 14 años sinantecedentes de tratamiento psiquiátrico, aunque haceun año, tras una intervención quirúrgica de rodilla,presenta una época de mayor desánimo y retraimientosocial. Desde hace tres meses se muestra más eufóricoe hiperactivo, con conflictos con su familia y amigos.Acude al Servicio de Urgencias de este hospitalacompañado de su padre. Se solicita entonces valoraciónpor parte del Servicio de Psiquiatría ante la presenciade síntomas maniacos (inquietud psicomotriz,verborrea, disforia y delirios de grandeza). Tras la valoraciónse decide ingreso en Unidad de HospitalizaciónPsiquiátrica para evaluación diagnóstica y tratamiento.Durante el ingreso se diagnosticó al paciente detrastorno bipolar (en fase maniaca) y se instauró untratamiento a largo plazo con un estabilizador del ánimo(ácido valproico) y un antipsicótico (risperidona).Tras el ingreso fue remitido a su Centro de Salud Mentalpara control del tratamiento y de la evolución de la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;33(1): 103-106, ene.-abr. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86397</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno bipolar infantil: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29291^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32618^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1738^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
