<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137010</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Plasma vitamin D levels in native and immigrant children under the age of 6 years of different ethnic origins</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Nutritional rickets is an emergent disease in Spain, and occurs particularly in black and dark-skinned infants and children from immigrant populations. The aim of this work was to ascertain the vitamin D reserve in a population of native and immigrant children under the age of 6 years. Population and methods: A prospective study was conducted at a Primary Healthcare Centre in Salt (Girona). Patients: 307 children with the following origin and race distribution: Caucasian (n=85; 28%), Sub-Saharan (n=101; 32.5%); Maghrebí (n=87, 28.0%); Central-American (n=20; 6.4%) and Indo-Pakistani (n=14; 4.5%). The biochemistry blood parameters studied were: calcium, phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase, 25-hydroxivitamin D, and parathormone. A nutritional survey was used to estimate calcium and vitamin D intake and degree of sun exposure. Results: Vitamin D deficiency (&lt;20ng/ml) was detected in Caucasians (8%), Sub-Saharans (18%), Central-Americans (20%), Maghrebís (34.5%), and Indo-Pakistanis (64%). Of the children studied (n=9), 2.9% had serious vitamin D deficiency (&lt; 10ng/ml); only one child of Sub-Saharan origin met the biochemical criteria for classical rickets. The prevalence of vitamin D deficiency was significantly higher in children not receiving vitamin D supplements in the first year of life. Conclusions: Plasma vitamin D concentrations were deficient in 22.5% of children under the age of six, being more prevalent in children of Indo-Pakistani and Maghrebí origin (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Audí Parera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa Lezcano, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yeste Fernández, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Muro, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín Muñoz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Cancio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El raquitismo carencial es una enfermedad emergente en nuestro medio y se describe especialmente en lactantes y niños inmigrantes de raza negra o piel oscura procedentes de países en vías de desarrollo. El objetivo de este trabajo está dirigido a conocer el estado nutricional de vitamina D en lactantes y niños inmigrantes de diferentes etnias de edad inferior a 6 años y compararlo con una población infantil autóctona. Población y métodos: Estudio prospectivo efectuado en un Centro de Asistencia Primaria de la localidad de Salt (Girona). Población: 307 niños con la siguiente distribución por origen y etnia: caucásicos (n=85; 28%), subsaharianos (n=101; 32,5%); magrebíes (n=87, 28,0%); centroamericanos (n=20; 6,4%) e indopakistaníes (n=14; 4,5%). Parámetros bioquímicos evaluados: calcemia, fosforemia, fosfatasa alcalina, 25-hidroxivitamina D y parathormona. Encuesta nutricional para estimar la ingesta de calcio, el aporte de vitamina D y el grado de exposición solar. Resultados: Presentan déficit de vitamina D (&lt; 20ng/ml) el 8% de los niños de origen caucásico, el 18% de los subsaharianos, el 20% de los centroamericanos, el 34,5% de los magrebíes y el 64% de los niños de origen indopakistaní. El 2,9% de los niños estudiados (n=9) presentan déficit grave de vitamina D (&lt; 10ng/ml), de los que tan solo un niño de origen subsahariano reúne criterios bioquímicos de raquitismo clásico. La prevalencia de la deficiencia de vitamina D es significativamente más elevada en los niños sin suplementación con vitamina D durante el primer año de vida. Conclusiones: El 22,5% de los niños menores de 6 años de edad presenta concentraciones plasmáticas en rango deficitario de vitamina D, siendo más prevalente en los niños de origen indopakistaní y magrebí (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(5): 316-324, mayo 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137010</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Niveles plasmáticos de vitamina D en población autóctona y en poblaciones inmigrantes de diferentes etnias menores de 6 años de edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15208^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50272</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23096^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55207^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201505</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
