<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85727</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How do adolescents want sex education to be and why?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: the objective of this study is to determine theopinion of adolescents themselves about affective-sex educationthat they receive in order to identify the needs of theseyoung individuals and assess the factors that prompt theincongruence between the information they receive andtheir behaviour regarding sex.Material and methods: the study was carried out using aqualitative methodology, developing discussion groups withteenagers between the ages of 13 and 18 years, from thecapital and province of Salamanca.Results: adolescents believe that sex education at school couldbe improved by focusing more on the practical aspects andless on reproduction, including aspects in the scope of affectionand employing more real-life methods. An insufficientlevel of theoretical knowledge is perceived, with norms validatedby the group that escape formal education, as well asa need to improve communication within the family setting.Conclusions: it is necessary to voice out these young peoples ideas and makes the learning significant and self-guided.It is necessary to develop a more active role in the youngsters,with special emphasis on the female gender. Sex educationmust be made extensive to the family setting and improvedboth in form and substance in the school setting. The schoolnurse is considered to be the most appropriate professionalto develop a quality affective-sex education (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fraile Maceín, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: el objetivo de este estudio se centra en conocerla opinión de los propios adolescentes acerca de la educaciónafectivo-sexual que reciben, para identificar las necesidadesde estos y valorar los factores que provocan la incongruenciaentre la información que obtienen y sucomportamiento en el ámbito sexual.Material y métodos: metodología cualitativa, desarrollandogrupos de discusión con adolescentes entre 13 y 18 años,de Salamanca capital y provincia.Resultados: los adolescentes creen que la educación sexualen la escuela se podría mejorar incidiendo en aspectos prácticosy menos en la reproducción, incluyendo aspectos delcampo afectivo y usando métodos más cercanos. Se percibeun nivel de conocimientos teóricos insuficiente, con normasvalidadas por el grupo que se escapan a la educaciónformal, así como una comunicación mejorable dentro delámbito familiar.Conclusiones: se hace necesario dar voz a los adolescentesy posibilitar un aprendizaje significativo y autónomo. Es necesariodesarrollar un papel más activo de los jóvenes, incidiendoen el sexo femenino. La educación sexual debe serextendida al ámbito familiar y mejorada en fondo y formaen el ámbito escolar. La enfermera escolar se considera comomuy adecuada para desarrollar una educación afectivo-sexualde calidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;13(5): 69-74, jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85727</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cómo quieren los adolescentes que seala educación sexual y por qué?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33920</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13116^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
