<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73852</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conservative treatment of scoliosis: orthosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">At the moment is controversial the levelof evidence about the preservative treatment of the adolescentidiopathic scoliosis (AIS). Objective. To analyse the evidence about effectiveness ofbrace used in the treatment of the AIS.Search strategy. Medline, PubMed, Cochrane Library from1992 to 2009.Selection of studies. Those that satisfy minimum requirementsof quality methodological investigation.Synthesis of results. Analysis of the factors that influencethe final result of the orthotic treatment, time of use ofbrace, effectiveness, abandonment of orthesis and evolutionof the curve after the use of the brace.Conclusion. The level of evidence of the orthotic treatmentfor AIS is of recommendation degree B-silver, reasonwhy an investigation of greater methodological quality inthe future using the systems defined by the Scoliosis ResearchSociety and the Spinal Orthopaedic RehabilitationTreatment would be advisable and as well as to evaluate theincidence on the quality of life of these patients(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora Amérigo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Moreno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de la Puente Molinero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñalver Barrios, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento conservador de la escoliosisidiopática del adolescente (EIA) no se puede establecer actualmentede manera categórica e irrefutable, y es relativoel nivel de evidencia existente.Objetivo. Realizar un análisis de la efectividad de los principalescorsés utilizados en el tratamiento de la EIA.Estrategia de búsqueda. Medline, PubMed, Cochrane Librarydesde 1992 a 2009.Selección de estudios. Aquellos que cumplen unos requisitosmínimos de calidad en cuanto a metodología de investigación.Síntesis de resultados. Análisis de los factores que más influyenen el resultado final del tratamiento ortésico, tiempo deutilización de la ortesis al día y global durante el cre cimiento,criterio de efectividad/inefectividad, abandono de la ortesis yevolución de la curva tras la retirada de la ortesis.Conclusión. El nivel de evidencia del tratamiento conservadorortésico de la EIA es de grado de recomendaciónB-plata, por lo que sería aconsejable una investigación demayor calidad metodológica en el futuro usando los sistemasdefinidos por la Scoliosis Research Society y el Spinal Orthopaedicand Rehabilitation Treatment, así como evaluar laincidencia sobre la calidad de vida de estos pacientes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);43(6): 287-292, nov.-dic. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento conservador de la escoliosis: ortesis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10166^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2415^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12980^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
