<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119374</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rivastigmine as treatment for patients with mild to moderately severe Alzheimer disease under normal clinical practice conditions. The ENTERPRISE study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Alzheimer disease (AD) causes progressive cognitive decline leading to loss of independence for activities of daily living; rivastigmine is one of the drugs used for symptomatic management. Objective: To assess the therapeutic use of different pharmaceutical forms of rivastigmine in patients with AD in normal clinical practice. Patients and methods: Cross-sectional, observational, multi-centre study conducted on patients with mild to moderate AD treated with rivastigmine in Spanish outpatient clinics specialising in Geriatrics, Psychiatry, and Neurology. Data regarding use of oral (OR) and transdermal (TDR) rivastigmine, compliance (degree of adherence), and caregiver satisfaction with treatment were evaluated. Results: In total, 2252 patients with a mean age of 77.2 years were included; 60.2% were women. AD was moderate to moderately severe in 58.4%. Rivastigmine treatment was started orally in 54.4% of the patients and transdermally in 45.6%; 35.6% of those who started treatment by the OR route switched to TDR. A single dose adjustment was sufficient for 77.5% of patients on TDR treatment vs 11.8% of patients receiving OR treatment. More patients on TDR treatment (80.8% vs. 57.1% on OR treatment) reached the maximum therapeutic dose of rivastigmine and did so in a shorter period of time (51.6 vs 205.8 days). Compliance rates (60.5% vs 47.2%) and caregivers&#146; satisfaction with treatment (89.4% vs 81.9%) were also higher for TDR. Conclusions: In normal clinical practice, using the TDR route of administration improves dose titration and drug compliance, allowing more patients to reach the maximum recommended dose of rivastigmine in a shorter time period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Jentoft, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA) produce un deterioro cognitivo progresivo que conlleva la pérdida de independencia para las actividades de la vida diaria, siendo la rivastigmina uno de los fármacos utilizados para su tratamiento sintomático. Objetivo: Evaluar el manejo terapéutico con distintas formas galénicas de rivastigmina, en sujetos con EA en la práctica clínica habitual. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio transversal, multicéntrico realizado en consultas españolas de Geriatría, Psiquiatría y Neurología, en sujetos con EA de leve a moderadamente grave que recibían rivastigmina. Se recogieron datos sobre el modo de uso de rivastigmina oral (RO) y transdérmica (RTD), el cumplimiento terapéutico (grado de adherencia) y la satisfacción del cuidador. Resultados: Se evaluaron 2.252 sujetos con edad media de 77,2 años; 60,2% mujeres. El 58,4% presentaban EA moderada-moderadamente grave. El 54,4% habían iniciado el tratamiento con RO y el 45,6% con RTD; el 35,6% de aquellos con RO cambiaron a la vía transdérmica. El 77,5% con RTD requirió un solo ajuste de dosis vs. 11,8% con RO. El 80,8% de los sujetos con RTD alcanzaron la dosis máxima de rivastigmina (vs. 57,1% RO) en menos tiempo (51,6 vs. 205,8 días). El cumplimiento fue mayor con RTD (60,5 vs. 47,2%) así como el porcentaje de cuidadores satisfechos con el tratamiento (89,4 vs.81,9%). Conclusiones: En la práctica clínica habitual, la RTD facilita la dosificación y mejora el cumplimiento, permitiendo a un mayor porcentaje de sujetos alcanzar la dosis máxima recomendada de rivastigmina en un plazo de tiempo menor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;29(1): 1-10, ene.-feb. 2014. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119374</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo terapéutico con rivastigmina en pacientes con enfermedad de Alzheimer de leve a moderadamente grave en condiciones de práctica clínica habitual. Estudio ENTERPRISE</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
