<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108852</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reading as a protective factor against cognitive decline</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To determine whether reading is a protective factor against cognitive decline in the populationaged over 65 years.Methods: We performed an unmatched case-control study in the Fuente de San Luis Health Center inValencia, Spain. A total of 153 subjects aged more than 65 years old were studied, corresponding to 51cases and 102 controls. Cognitive impairment was measured by the version of the Mini-Mental State Examination adapted and validated to Spanish. Reading habits were assessed with the scale of the Federaciónde Gremios y Editores de Espana&#152; .Results: Logistic regression showed a signi&amp;#64257;cant association with the habit of frequent reading for morethan 5 years, complete primary school education, and age lower than 75 yearsConclusions: Reading is a protective factor against cognitive impairment. This protection is greater infrequent readers with a history of reading of over 5 years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Esteve Esteve, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collado Gil, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar si la lectura constituye un factor protector frente al deterioro cognitivo en la población mayor de 65 años. Métodos: Estudio de casos y controles no emparejados. Emplazamiento: Centro de Salud Fuente de SanLuis, Valencia, Espana. Se estudiaron 153 personas mayores de 65 años (51 casos y 102 controles). Se midió el deterioro cognitivo mediante el Miniexamen Cognitivo de Lobo, y el hábito de lectura con laescala de la Federación de Gremios y Editores de España. Resultados: Mediante regresión logística mostraron asociación signi&amp;#64257;cativa el hábito de lectura frecuentedurante más de 5 años, los estudios primarios completos y la edad menor de 75 años. Conclusiones: El hábito de lectura es un factor protector de deterioro cognitivo, y la protección es mayoren los lectores frecuentes cuya historia de lectura supera los 5 años (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;27(1): 68-71, Ene. -Feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El hábito de lectura como factor protector de deterioro cognitivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29986</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
