<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111685</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development and follow-up of autism spectrum disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Autism spectrum disorders are neurodevelopmental disorders with qualitative impairment in functioning domains and areas of human characteristically. It is important to know how is the outcome in the adolescent and adult age of these people to provide the services and support needed. Development. We review the most important follow-up studies have been conducted in autism spectrum disorders, realices the kind of designs that have been carried out and the results obtained in different areas of development and independent functioning.  Conclusions. Improvements in outcome but these are generally poor in the population. A small proportion close or around 25% are experiencing better outcome. These cases generally correspond to what is known as high-functioning autism or Asperger síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Freire Prudencio, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Navarro, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martos Pérez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayuda Pascual, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llorente Comí, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los trastornos del espectro autista son trastornos del neurodesarrollo con alteraciones cualitativas en dominios y áreas de funcionamiento característicamente humanas. Es importante conocer cómo es la evolución en la edad adolescente y adulta de estas personas para proveer los servicios y apoyos necesarios. Desarrollo. Se revisan los estudios más importantes de seguimiento que se han realizado en los trastornos del espectro autista, se da cuenta del tipo de diseños que se han llevado a cabo y de los resultados obtenidos en distintos ámbitos del desarrollo y del funcionamiento independiente. Conclusión. Las mejoras en la evolución, aunque presentes, son generalmente pobres en la mayor parte de la población. Una pequeña proporción, cercana o en torno al 25%, experimenta mejor evolución. Dichos casos suelen corresponderse  con lo que se denomina autismo de alto funcionamiento o síndrome de Asperger (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;56(supl.1): S61-S66, feb. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111685</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución y seguimiento de los trastornos del espectro autista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1538</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2704</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
