<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111668</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical Case: Assessment and Intervention in a Case of Separation Anxiety in an Adopted Child</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this study, the case of a 3 year-old girl adopted from Nepal is reported. The child had been suffering separation anxiety and attachment problems, especially over the previous year. These difficulties were interfering negatively in the family dynamics. A diagnosis is made of the child&#146;s difficulties through a clinical interview, observation instruments and conduct standardized testing. Observation instruments were used in sessions with the parents, as were records of behavioral response from the adoptive parents in relation to the child&#146;s behavioral problems. The intervention was based on parent management training  with the girl, with operant techniques and from an emotional development and attachment perspective. It describes the evolution of the problem and the case follow-up (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fdez-Zúñiga Marcos de León, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cogolludo Núñez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe el caso de una niña 3, 1 años de edad adoptada en Nepal que presenta ansiedad de separación, problemas de conducta y de vinculación, especialmente durante el último año. Estas dificultades interfieren negativamente en la dinámica familiar. Se realiza un diagnostico de las dificultades de la niña por medio de una entrevista clínica, instrumentos de observación de la conducta y pruebas estandarizadas. Con los padres se utilizaron instrumentos de observación en sesión y registros conductuales en relación a sus respuestas ante las conductas problemáticas de la niña. Se llevó a cabo una intervención basada en el entrenamiento cognitivo conductual de los padres con la niña, con técnicas operantes y desde una perspectiva del desarrollo emocional y del establecimiento de vínculo. Se describe la evolución del problema y el seguimiento del caso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;23(3): 235-245, nov. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111668</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caso Clínico: Evaluación e Intervención en un Caso de Ansiedad por Separación de una Niña Adoptada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1015^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23894^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5300^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201211</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
