<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129094</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Antioxidant minerals in mature breast milk of two groups ethnic from Venezuela</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Breast milk micronutrient content represents the ideal food for the baby in the body?s defenses against free radicals. Our objective was to determine the micronutrient content of antioxidants in mature breast milk of women belonging to two indigenous groups in the Zulia region. Materials and methods: We collected 68 samples of breast milk and 65 samples Bari Wayuú. For comparative  purposes were taken 76 samples of milk from non-indigenous women. The total concentrations of copper and zinc were determined by atomic absorption spectrometry. Vitamin C was  quantified by phosphotungstic acid method. The data were analyzed using the ANOVA and Tukey tests (SPSS 12.0). Results: The results showed significant variations between groups (p &lt;0.05). Copper values were lower in breast milk Bari (0.12 ± 0.02 mg / L), when compared with  non-indigenous (0.34 ± 0.04 mg / L) (p &lt;0.05) but was statistically similar to Wayuú group (0.21 ± 0.03 mg/ L). Zinc is found at lower concentrations in Bari (0.66± 0.07 mg / L) compared with Wayuú milks (2.63 ± 0.43 mg / L) and non-indigenous (2.17 ± 0.34 mg / L) (p &lt;0.05). The content of vitamin C was significantly lower in Bari (5.81 ± 1.62 mg / L) and Wayuu (5.83 ± 3.24 mg / L) vs. the control group (35.66 ± 15.94 mg / L) (p &lt;0.05). Conclusions: We observed a significant reduction in  micronutrients analyzed in mature breast milk samples and Wayuú Bari, which could cause a deficiency of these  antioxidants in children who are exclusively breastfed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez-García, Elda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo-Henríquez, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maury-Sintjago, Eduard</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ugas, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La leche materna por su contenido de  micronutrientes representa el alimento ideal para el neonato en las defensas del organismo contra los radicales libres. Nuestro objetivo fue determinar el contenido de  micronutrientes antioxidantes en leche materna madura de mujeres perteneciente a dos grupos indígenas de la región zuliana. Materiales y métodos: Se colectaron 68 muestras de leche materna Barí y 65 muestras de Wayuú. Con propósitos comparativos se tomaron 76 muestras de leche de mujeres no indígenas. Las concentraciones totales de cobre y zinc fueron determinadas mediante espectrometría de absorción atómica. La vitamina C se cuantificó por el método del ácido fosfotúngstico. Los datos fueron analizados mediante las pruebas de ANOVA y Tukey (SPSS 12.0). Resultados: Los resultados obtenidos mostraron variaciones significativas entre los grupos (p&lt;0,05). Los valores de cobre fueron más bajos en leche materna Barí (0,12±0,02 mg/L), cuando se comparó con las no indígenas (0,34±0,04 mg/L) (p&lt;0,05), pero fue estadísticamente similar al grupo Wayuú (0,21±0,03 mg/L). El zinc se encontró a concentraciones más bajas en las Barí (0,66±0,07 mg/L) en comparación con las leches de Wayuú (2,63±0,43 mg/L) y no indígenas (2,17±0,34 mg/L) (p&lt;0,05). El contenido de vitamina C fue significativamente más bajo en las Barí (5,81±1,62 mg/L) y Wayuú (5,83±3,24 mg/L) vs. el grupo control (35,66±15,94 mg/L) (p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones: Se observó una importante disminución de los micronutrientes analizados en las muestras de leche materna madura Barí y Wayuú, lo que pudiera causar deficiencia de estos antioxidantes en los niños que reciben lactancia materna exclusiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;17(3): 139-145, jul.-sept. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129094</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Micronutrientes antioxidantes en leche materna madura de dos grupos indígenas venezolanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14523^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29124^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29124^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29124^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
