<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136223</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyperbaric oxygen therapy. Otorhinolaryngological indications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hyperbaric oxygen therapy is based on the increase in partial pressure of oxygen in the tissues through oxygen diffusion from plasma. This increase has positive physiological effects on tissues, such as an increase in cell renewal and the bactericidal action of polymorphonuclear leukocytes, a direct bactericidal action, and neovascularization. The large increase in partial pressure of oxygen in plasma allows direct diffusion through tissues, reaching hypoxic areas and regions with little capillary permeability. In the last 40 years, the possible applications of hyperbaric oxygen therapy in otorhinolaryngology (ORL) have been investigated. Possible  areas of application are hypoxic processes secondary toradiotherapy (radionecrosis, osteonecrosis, osteomyelitis), infections (malignant otitis externa, fasciitis) or vascular disorders (sudden hearing loss syndrome). We describe the physiological mechanisms of the application of hyperbaric oxygen therapy and review its indications in ORL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casamitjana Claramunt, José F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Desola Ala, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento con oxigenoterapia en cámara hiperbárica (OHB) se basa en el aumento de la presión parcial de oxígeno en los tejidos facilitado por la difusión de éste desde el plasma. Dicho aumento conlleva repercusiones fisiológicas positivas sobre los tejidos, como son el aumento de la regeneración celular, el incremento de la acción bactericida de los leucocitos polimorfonucleares, una acción bactericida directa y la neovascularización. El gran aumento de la presión parcial de O2 en el plasma permite la difusión directa a través de los tejidos, llegando a zonas de escasa permeabilidad capilar e hipóxicas. En los últimos 40 años  se han investigado sus posibles aplicaciones también en el ámbito otorrinolaringológico, en el que destacan los procesos hipóxicos secundarios a la radioterapia (radionecrosis, osteonecrosis, osteomielitis), las infecciones (otitis externa maligna, fascitis) o los trastornos vasculares (síndrome de la hipoacusia súbita). Realizamos una introducción a los mecanismos fisiológicos de su aplicación y revisamos sus indicaciones en otorrinolaringología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(supl.2): 70-78, dic. 2007. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Oxigenoterapia hiperbárica. Indicaciones otorrinolaringológicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7110^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14399^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3656^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10200^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9527^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27888^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10210^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7110^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10282^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7110^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7110^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
