<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149914</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive Model for Anxiety and Depression in Spanish Patients with Stable Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The association between chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and anxiety and depression is not yet completely characterized, and differences between countries may exist. We used a predictive model to assess this association in a Spanish population. Patients and method: Prospective transversal descriptive study of 204 patients with stable COPD. Concomitant anxiety or depression were diagnosed by psychiatric assessment, using the diagnostic criteria of the 10th revision of the International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems (ICD-10). Sociodemographic, clinical and lung function parameters were analyzed. Results: In total, 36% of stable COPD patients had psychiatric comorbidities, but 76% were unaware of their diagnosis. Nineteen percent had a pure anxiety disorder, 9.8% had isolated depression, and 7.3% had a mixed anxiety-depression disorder. Predictive variables in the multivariate analysis were younger age, higher educational level, lack of home support, higher BODE index, and greater number of exacerbations. The ROC curve of the model had an AUC of 0.765 (P&lt;0.001). Conclusions: In COPD, concomitant psychiatric disorders are significantly associated with sociodemographic factors. Anxiety disorders are more common than depression. Patients with more severe COPD, according to BODE, younger patients and those with a higher educational level have a greater risk of being diagnosed with anxiety or depression in a structured psychiatric interview. In our population, most patients with psychiatric comorbidities remain unidentified (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Casas Maldonado, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Vargas, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Velázquez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales García, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Jiménez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Gutiérrez, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La asociación entre la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) y la ansiedad o la depresión no se conoce adecuadamente, y puede haber diferencias entre distintos países. Investigamos un modelo predictivo para esta asociación en una población española. Pacientes y método: Estudio prospectivo descriptivo transversal incluyendo 204 pacientes con EPOC estable. Se diagnostica la presencia de ansiedad o depresión mediante valoración psiquiátrica, aplicando los criterios diagnósticos de la 10.ª revisión del International Statistical Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems (ICD-10). Se analizan variables sociodemográficas, clínicas y de función pulmonar. Resultados: Un 36% de pacientes con EPOC estable tienen comorbilidad psiquiátrica, pero en el 76% de los casos se desconocía dicho diagnóstico. Presentan un trastorno de ansiedad pura el 19%, depresión aislada el 9,8% y un trastorno mixto de ansiedad y depresión el 7,3% de los pacientes. En el análisis multivariante las variables predictoras son: edad más joven, mayor nivel de estudios, falta de apoyo domiciliario, mayor índice de BODE y mayor número de agudizaciones. La curva ROC del modelo muestra un AUC de 0,765 (p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones: En la EPOC, una mayoría de pacientes con comorbilidad psiquiátrica no son identificados. Los trastornos de ansiedad son más frecuentes que la depresión, en base a un diagnóstico mediante entrevista estructurada. Los pacientes más jóvenes y con mayor nivel de estudios tienen más riesgo de de padecer ansiedad o depresión. Otros factores predictivos son: un mayor índice BODE, más agudizaciones y la falta de apoyo domiciliario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;52(3): 151-157, mar. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149914</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelo predictivo de ansiedad y depresión en pacientes españoles con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica estable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
