<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-34373</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pshysical self-perception profile: psychometric properties of the Spanish version, and validity of the physical self-perception hierarchical structure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this paper is to study the psychometric properties of Physical Self-Perception Profile -PSPP- in its Spanish translation, and to analyse the validity of the hierarchical structure of physical self-perceptions. Two samples of teenagers from the Valencian Community were used. The first sample was composed by 474 subjects (15 to 17 years old) and a second sample of 51 subjects (14 to 19 years old) was used in order to study the temporal stability of the PSPP&#146;s scores. The results obtained showed that not method effects associated to the answer scale of PSPP were observed, and that the internal consistency and temporal stability of PSPP dimensions were good. Confirmatory factor analyses informed that sport competence and physical condition were together in the same dimension, and that the other three dimensions were replicated. Structural equation modelling supported the Fox and Corbin&#146; model (1989) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balaguer, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Atienza, Francisco Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fox, Kenneth</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar las propiedades psicométricas del Perfil de Autopercepción Física -PSPP- en la traducción española, y analizar la validez de la estructura jerárquica de las autopercepciones físicas. Se utilizaron dos muestras de adolescentes de la Comunidad Valenciana, una primera muestra de 474 sujetos (15-17 años), y una segunda muestra de 51 sujetos (14-19 años), con la que se analizó la estabilidad temporal de las puntuaciones del PSPP. Los resultados muestran que no se presentan efectos de método asociados a la escala de respuesta del PSPP y que la consistencia interna y estabilidad temporal de las dimensiones de este instrumento son adecuadas. Los análisis factoriales confirmatorios muestran que las dimensiones competencia en el deporte y condición física se agrupan en una sola dimensión, respetándose la estructura de las otras tres dimensiones. Los modelos estructurales apoyan el modelo propuesto por Fox y Corbin (1989) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);16(3): 461-467, ago. 2004. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-34373</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El perfil de autopercepción física: propiedades psicométricas de la versión española y análisis de la estructura jerárquica de las autopercepciones físicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
