<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137362</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Practical use complementary and integrative no stress occupational treatment: an integrative review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To synthesize the knowledge production related to the use of Integrative and Complementary Practices (PIC) in the treatment of occupational stress. Method: Integrative Review, which had as its guiding question: what is the production of knowledge related to the use of PIC in the treatment of occupational stress published between 2003 and 2013?. The data was collected in the Lilacs and Medline databases using combinations of the following descriptors: "stress" with "complementary therapies", "floral medicines", "mind-body therapies", "sensory therapies through arts", "spiritual therapies, and "therapies under study". Results: 48 articles were selected. The sorting of titles, summaries, reading assessment, and evaluation of complete texts were subsequently performed in stages. Out of all selected articles, 07 articles were analyzed and the following categories built: PIC as stress reducing therapies and other diseases; the use of PIC in the treatment of occupational stress; and Credibility in the use of PIC. Conclusions: The integrative complementary practices have been used not only to reduce stress but also in reducing levels of anxiety and depressive symptoms, and relief of pain and binge eating. The main PIC mentioned were: MSBR, CBRS, Kouk Sun Do, acupuncture, meditation, controlled breathing, yoga, and polarity therapy. The major cited reasons for its use were: reaching spiritual well-being and serenity, mood and sleep improvement, and compassion for others (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Seva Llor, Ana Myriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llapa Rodriguez , Eliana Ofelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lisboa Gois, Cristiane Franca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomes da Silva, Gilvan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Montesinos, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopes Neto, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Sintetizar la producción de conocimiento relacionado al uso de Prácticas Integradas y Complementarias (PIC) en el tratamiento del estrés laboral. Método: Revisión integradora, que tuvo como pregunta guía: ¿cuál es la producción del conocimento de las PIC relacionada al tratamiento del estrés laboral en el período de 2003 a 2013?. Para recolectar los datos se utilizaron las bases de datos Lilacs y Medline, utilizando la combinación de los descriptores "estrés" con "terapias complementarias", "medicamentos florales", "terapias mente-cuerpo", "terapias sensoriales a través de las artes", "terapia espiritual" y "terapias en estudio." Resultados: Se seleccionaron 48 artículos. Posteriormente se realizó por etapas la selección por los títulos de los artículos, evaluación de los resúmenes y el análisis y lectura de los textos completos. Del total, 07 artículos fueron analizados y construídas las categorías: Las PIC como tratamientos para reducir el estrés y otras enfermedades; El uso de las PIC en el tratamiento del estrés y La credibilidad en el uso de las PIC. Conclusiones: Las PIC vienen siendo utilizadas no sólo para reducir el estrés, sino también en la reducción de los niveles de ansiedad, síntomas depresivos, alivio del dolor y en la compulsión alimentaria. Las principales PIC mencionado fueron: MSBR, CBRS, Kouk Sun Do, la acupuntura, la meditación, respiración controlada, el yoga y la terapia de polaridad. Citadas como las principales razones de su uso: el alcance del bienestar espiritual, serenidad, mejor estado de ánimo, la compasión por los demás y para mejorar el sueño (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;14(39): 291-303, jul. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137362</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso de prácticas integradas y complementarias en el tratamiento del estrés ocupacional: una revisión integradora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36276</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
