<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146130</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal outcomes of prematurity and birth weight according to maternal caffeine consumption</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: identify whether there is an increased risk of adverse perinatal outcomes, like prematurity or decreased weight in newborns, associated with caffeine consumption during the first half of pregnancy in pregnant women of our population. Methods: transversal study carried out in 1 175 patients from Virgen de las Nieves University Hospital of Granada (Spain). Information about caffeine consumption during first half of gestation and perinatal outcomes was obtained by personal interview, medical records and telephone call after delivery. The average caffeine intake was calculated from meals and drinks included in a validated questionnaire. Results: there was no difference in caffeine consumption in pregnant women with birth weight &amp;#8805;2 500 g and &lt;2 500 g, or in pregnant women with newborns appropriate for gestational age and small for gestational age, or in pregnant women with term and preterm delivery. When studying the birth weight as a dependent variable, adjusted for confounding variables, a significant association (p &lt;0.05) with decreased birth weight was found (-87.7; 95% CI -159.8, -15.6 g) for caffeine consumption in the fourth quartile (115.01-650 mg/day). Conclusions: there is no relation between caffeine intake and low birth weight, small for gestational age or prematurity, but a decrease in birth weight of mothers who consume large amounts of caffeine is observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Natalia Del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olmedo-Requena, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Ruiz, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Moleón, José Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bueno-Cavanillas, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mozas, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: identificar si existe un aumento del riesgo en resultados perinatales adversos de prematuridad y disminución del peso de los recién nacidos asociados al consumo de cafeína durante la primera mitad del embarazo en gestantes de nuestra población. Métodos: estudio transversal llevado a cabo en 1.175 gestantes del Hospital Universitario Virgen de las Nieves de Granada (España). La información sobre el consumo de cafeína durante la primera mitad del embarazo y los resultados perinatales estudiados se obtuvieron mediante entrevista personal, consulta de la historia clínica y llamada telefónica tras el parto. La ingesta media de cafeína se calculó a partir de las comidas y bebidas incluidas en un cuestionario validado. Resultados: no hubo diferencias en el consumo de cafeína en gestantes con recién nacidos de peso &amp;#8805;2.500 g y &lt;2.500 g ni en gestantes con recién nacidos adecuados a la edad gestacional y pequeños para la edad gestacional, ni en gestantes con parto a término y pretérmino. Al estudiar el peso del recién nacido como variable dependiente, ajustada por las variables de confusión, se encontró una asociación significativa (p &lt;0,05) con la disminución del peso al nacer (-87,7; 95% CI -159,8, -15,6 g) para el consumo de cafeína en el cuarto cuartil (115,01-650 mg/día). Discusión: no hay relación entre el consumo de cafeína y el nacimiento de recién nacidos de bajo peso, pequeños para la edad gestacional o prematuros, pero sí se observa una disminución del peso del recién nacido de madres que consumen mayores cantidades de cafeína (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(6): 2658-2664, dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146130</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resultados perinatales de prematuridad y peso del recién nacido según el consumo de cafeína de la gestante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2143^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7405^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
