<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104757</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Front of pack nutrition labelling: between marketing and public health policies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The increase of the evidences that link some dietary factors to the development of chronic diseases such as obesity, diabetes and heart disease, has generated numerous strategies to guide the food selection of the consumer. The front of pack nutrition labelling is an initiative to present concise and clear nutritional information. There are currently different systems of front of pack nutrition labelling; some include symbols, while others include numerical scores or graphic schemes to communicate the overall nutritional quality of a food product. This diversity of systems creates confusion in the consumer because each system has different nutritional criteria. Currently, there is no single, generally accepted system to a global level. A proposal for the design of the front of pack labeling is to select the nutrients that are considered priorities in the light of local public health, either because their consumption is excessive or because the population has deficiencies, but also taking into account what is understandable by the consumer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dorantes Ugalde, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naranjo Modad , Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El aumento de evidencia de que algunos factores dietarios están asociados con el desarrollo de enfermedades crónicas como la obesidad, diabetes y enfermedad del corazón ha generado numerosas estrategias para orientar la selección de alimentos del consumidor. El etiquetado frontal de alimentos es una iniciativa para presentar información nutricional relevante deforma concisa y clara al frente de los empaques. Actualmente existen diferentes sistemas de etiquetado frontal, algunos comprenden símbolos, otros incluyen calificaciones numéricas o esquemas gráficos para comunicar la calidad nutricional de un producto. Esta diversidad de sistemas de etiquetado frontal crea confusión entre los consumidores porque cada sistema tiene diferentes criterios nutricionales. Actualmente no existe un sistema de etiquetado frontal que sea de aceptación general a nivel global. Una propuesta para diseñar el etiquetado frontal es seleccionar los nutrimentos que se consideren prioridades de salud pública locales, ya sea porque su consumo es excesivo o bien porque la población tiene deficiencias, pero considerando lo que sea entendible por el consumidor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;31(3): 52-61, sept.-dic. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104757</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Etiquetado frontal: entre la mercadotecnia y las políticas de salud pública</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3273</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5654^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
