<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75858</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-1641</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospital managers and internal communication: a pending subject</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Conclusions. A tendency towards higher levels of satisfaction with the Internal Communication inthe smaller hospitals was observed.The phenomenon can be explained by the fact that face-to-facecontact between the management levels and the staff is easier is the smaller hospitals. Small size ofthe hospital favors the use of personal type formal channels. All of the above indicates the importanceof developing well-established formal channels in the Communication Plans to assure that theinformation arrives to defined receptors in the clearest possible way(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>March, Joan Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Olivia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto, María Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Danet, Alina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Conclusiones. Se observa una tendencia a un mayor grado de satisfacción con la comunicacióninterna en los hospitales de 500 camas o menos que en los grandes. Ello puede explicarse por el hechode que en los hospitales más pequeños es más fácil el contacto directo entre la dirección y los profesionales.El menor tamaño del hospital favorece la utilización de canales formalizados de carácterpersonal.Todo ello indica la importancia de desarrollar canales formales bien establecidos en los planesde comunicación para que la información llegue a los públicos definidos y lo haga de la formamás clara posible(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. adm. sanit. siglo XXI;7(1): 165-182, ene.-mar. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75858</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los directivos hospitalarios y la comunicación interna: una asignatura pendiente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10749</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5513</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
