<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113531</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-7240</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between ruminations and emotional distress in patients newly diagnosed with cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Cancer is a strong psychological  stressor, generating emotional distress among  patients. Rumination is an information  processing mode that increases the vulnerability  to such distress. However, rumination has not  been appropriately studied in cancer patients.  This research examines the relationship between  rumination and anxiety/depression symptoms  among recently diagnosed cancer patients. Method: A sample of 71 recently diagnosed  cancer patients was assessed through the   Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale, the  Ruminative Responses Scale, the MOS Social  Support Survey and a clinical interview. Correlations between ruminations (and its  subscales of brooding and reflection), social  support, clinical and socio-demographic   variables and emotional distress (both anxiety  and depression) were analyzed. Multiple  regression models were performed, in order  to determine the specific contribution of each  variable in the explanatory model. Results: Anxiety symptoms correlated  with ruminations, social support, sex and   age. Depression symptoms correlated with  ruminations and social support. Multivariate  models show that anxiety symptoms were  associated with both rumination subscales and  sex. Depression symptoms were associated  with the brooding subscale. Discussion: Ruminations are associated  with higher levels of anxiety and depression  symptoms among recently diagnosed cancer  patients. Rumination become an important   therapeutic target in prevention of psychological distress associated to both diagnosis and  treatment initiation. Longitudinal research  should be carry out in order to determine the  predictive value of ruminations for psychological distress (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hoyuela, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Blanch, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Priede, Amador</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrán, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El cáncer actúa como un potente estresor psicológico, generando malestar emocional en los pacientes. Los modos de  procesamiento de la información basados en  rumiaciones constituyen un importante factor  de vulnerabilidad para la aparición de dicho  malestar. Sin embargo, las rumiaciones no han  sido convenientemente estudiadas en pacientes con cáncer. El presente estudio analiza la  relación existente entre rumiaciones y los síntomas ansiosos y depresivos en pacientes recién diagnosticados de cáncer.  Método: Se evaluó una muestra de 71 pacientes oncológicos recién diagnosticados mediante la Escala de Ansiedad y Depresión Hospitalaria, la Escala de Respuestas Rumiativas, la  Escala MOS de Apoyo Social y una entrevista  clínica. Se analizaron las correlaciones entre  rumiaciones, apoyo social, variables sociodemográficas y clínicas, y malestar emocional  (tanto ansiedad como depresión). Se realizó  un análisis de regresión múltiple con el fin de  determinar las contribuciones específicas de  cada variable en el modelo explicativo. Resultados: La sintomatología ansiosa correlacionó con rumiaciones, apoyo social, sexo  y edad. La sintomatología depresiva correlacionó con rumiaciones y apoyo social. En el  análisis multivariado la sintomatología ansiosa  se asoció con las dos subescalas de rumiaciones y con el sexo, mientras que los síntomas  depresivos se asociaron con la subescala de  reproches. Conclusiones: Las rumiaciones se asocian  con una mayor presencia de síntomas ansiosos   y depresivos en pacientes con un diagnóstico  reciente de cáncer, pudiendo constituir una  diana terapéutica clave para la prevención del  malestar emocional asociado al diagnóstico e  inicio del tratamiento. Estudios longitudinales  deben determinar el verdadero valor predictivo de las rumiaciones sobre el malestar emocional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicooncología (Pozuelo de Alarcón);10(1): 131-140, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113531</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre rumiaciones y malestar emocional en pacientes recién diagnosticados de cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3729</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
