<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156210</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sanitarian conditions and care in the Paraguayan war</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To analytically identify, in the periodical El Centinela, news related to the sanitary conditions and care towards the wounded in the Paraguay war. Method: Serial history approach three news fragments were used to illustrate the sanitary conditions and care towards the wounded. Results: The hostile sanitary conditions where the practice of care, compress with rips of skirts of women to stop the bleeding and the use of medicinal and nutritional marijuana were one of the methods used for care. Conclusion: There wasn&#146;t the pretense of deepen the sanitary conditions and care to injured in action but carried that El Centinela periodical has regular daily richness of war, which allows somehow reassemble, even minimally, the history of care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rocha, Juliane Aguiar da</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nassar, Pedro Ruiz B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porto, Fernando Rocha</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguiar, Simone</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ataide, Anna Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Identificar, analíticamente, en el periódico El Centinela, las noticias relacionadas con las condiciones sanitarias y los cuidados prestados a los heridos en la guerra del Paraguay. Método: Estudio en la abordaje de la historia serial. Fueron utilizados tres fragmentos de noticias para ilustrar las condiciones sanitarias y los cuidados prestados a los heridos. Resultados: Las condiciones sanitarias hostiles dónde se ocurrió la práctica del cuidado, vendajes con rasgos de las faldas de las mujeres para estancar la sangre y el uso de la coca medicinal y nutricional fueron una de las formas se utilizadas en el cuidado. Conclusión: No se ha pretendido profundizar en las condiciones sanitarias y los cuidados prestados a los heridos en combate, pero se demostró que periódico El Centinela tiene la riqueza diaria de la guerra, lo que permite de alguna manera, volver a montar, aunque sea mínimamente, la historia del cuidado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(45): 44-51, mayo-ago. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156210</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condiciones sanitarias y los Cuidados prestados en la Guerra del Paraguay</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50135</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35135</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
