<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96725</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of malocclusion, functional and oral habits alteration in a school student population: Tarragona and Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Etiology of malocclusion may be multifactor and difficult to classify during the development of the individual. The aim of this study is to identify the malocclusion characteristics in a school student population and find the possible relation with functional and oral habit alteration. Material and method: 1270 individuals representative of the school population of Catalonia were studied: 596boys and 674 girls between 6 and 14 years. Information was obtained through medical records and questionnaires. A mixed observational-descriptive transversal study has been done in the period between 2006 and 2007 that was selected by a non-probabilistic convenience sampling. Interexamination calibration was performed. Results: 1051 school children were included in the study with a mean age of 9.32 years. 72.8% presented as Angle Class I, 19.0% and 5.2% Class II / 1 and II / 2, respectively and 2.9% Class III. Nail biting habit was the most frequent habit with 46.4%. The highest level of functional limitation was tonsils hypertrophy with 21.2%.There is a statically significant relationship between sagittal malocclusion and respiration type and tongue mobility, and between horizontal malocclusion and digital suction and tongue mobility (p&lt;0.05). Conclusions: The diagnosis of functional disorders and oral habits can be a warning of the presence of malocclusion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ustrell Torrent, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, VJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sentís Vilalta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: La etiología de la maloclusión puede ser multifactorial y difícil de clasificar durante el desarrollo del individuo. Los objetivos del estudio son conocer las características de la maloclusión y su posible relación con las alteraciones funcionales y los hábitos orales. Métodos: Se estudió a 1.270 individuos representativos de la población escolar de Cataluña; 596 niños y 674 niñas de entre 6 y 14 años. Se obtuvo información mediante registros clínicos y cuestionarios. Se trata de un estudio observacional descriptivo mixto transversal, llevado a cabo entre 2006 y 2007 a través de un muestreo no probabilística de conveniencia. Se ha realizado el calibrado de los examinadores. Resultados: Fueron incluidos 1051 escolares con una edad media de 9,32 años. El 72,8% presenta según Angle Clase I, 19,0% y 5,2% Clase II/1 y II/2 respectivamente y 2,9% Clase III. El hábito onicofagia fue el más frecuente con un 46,4%. El mayor nivel de limitación funcional fue la hipertrofia amigdalar con un 21,2%.Existe relación estadísticamente significativa entre maloclusión sagital y tipo de respiración y movilidad lingual y entre maloclusión horizontal y tiempo de succión digital y movilidad lingual (p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones: El diagnóstico de alteraciones funcionales y de hábitos orales puede advertir de la presencia de maloclusión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;27(2): 75-84, mar.-abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96725</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la maloclusión, alteraciones funcionales y hábitos orales en una población escolar: Tarragona y Barcelona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6335</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8483^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12952^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
