<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92315</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Greater adherence to mediterranean diet is not associated with better metabolic control in patients with type 1 diabetes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: The objective of the present study is to evaluate the level of adherence to the Mediterranean diet model in a group of patients with type diabetes 1 and to determine whether a higher level of adherence to a Mediterranean diet is associated with a better metabolic control or vascular risk factors. Material and methods: A descriptive study was conducted on 132 patients with type diabetes 1 and a mean age 33.7 ± 11.7 years. Adherence to the Mediterranean diet was evaluated by means of a validated questionnaire that provided a score between 0 and 14. The clinical, anthropometric and metabolic parameters analysed were compiled by means of personal interviews; a study of the clinical history and analytical results measured for metabolic control. Results: The mean adherence to the Mediterranean diet scored 8.9 ± 1.9 points, with 59% of the patients having a score of 9 points or lower. Significant differences in adherence to the Mediterranean diet were not found for any of the clinical, anthropometric or analytical parameters analysed. Patients with a higher level of adherence to the Mediterranean diet did not have more favourable lipid profiles, or lower levels of glycated haemoglobin, or less microvascular complications. Conclusions: Most patients with type diabetes 1 evaluated in our study showed a level medium-low level of adherence to the traditional Mediterranean diet model. Higher adherence to the Mediterranean diet was not associated with better metabolic control or other vascular risk factors(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortego, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez, José Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carral, Florentino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ayala, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El objetivo del presente estudio es evaluar el nivel de adhesión al modelo de dieta mediterránea en un grupo de pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 y analizar si un mayor nivel de adherencia a la dieta mediterránea se asocia con un mejor control metabólico y de factores de riesgo vascular. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional descriptivo realizado en 132 pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 de 33,7 ± 11,7 años de edad media. La adhesión a la dieta mediterránea fue evaluada mediante cuestionario validado que proporciona una puntuación entre 0 y 14. Los parámetros clínicos, antropométricos y metabólicos analizados han sido recopilados mediante entrevista personal, estudio del historial clínico y extracción analítica orientada a la evaluación del control metabólico. Resultados: La adhesión media a la dieta mediterránea fue de 8,9 ± 1,9 puntos; el 59% de los pacientes presentó una puntuación igual o inferior a 9 puntos. No se encontraron diferencias significativas en la adhesión a la dieta mediterránea por ninguno de los parámetros clínicos, antropométricos ni analíticos analizados. Los pacientes con mayor nivel de adhesión a la dieta mediterránea no presentaban perfiles lipídicos más favorables, menores niveles de hemoglobina glucosilada ni una menor prevalencia de complicaciones microvasculares. Conclusiones: La mayoría de los pacientes con diabetes tipo 1 evaluados en nuestro estudio muestran un nivel medio-bajo de adhesión al modelo tradicional de dieta mediterránea. La mayor adhesión a la dieta mediterránea no se asoció a un mejor control metabólico ni de otros factores de riesgo vascular(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;27(3): 88-94, mayo-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92315</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La mayor adhesión a la dieta mediterránea no se asocia a un mejor control metabólico en pacientes con diabetes tipo 1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3944^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8230^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
