<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055398</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic principles of robotic surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The evolution of surgical therapy has been vertiginous, from the classical principles of open surgery to laparoscopy and currently to robotic surgery, in which the principles of robotic engineering have been successfully applied to the surgeon&#146;s daily work. The development of minimally invasive surgery, initially led by conventional laparoscopy, was a fertile field for the development of surgical techniques with the robot. The use of automatized systems for surgery is not as new as one could think, but the robots today participating in the main operative rooms worldwide are an example of the newest and most advanced available technology. Urologyhas become the leading surgical speciality in the application of technologies for diagnosis and treatment of its diseases, and robotic surgery is not an exception. We present our vision about the state of the art in automatizedsurgery, in the setting of its close relationship with conventional laparoscopic surgery, which originatedit</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Octavi A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Salas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evolución de la terapéutica quirúrgica ha sido vertiginosa y desde los principios clásicos de la cirugía a cielo abierto la evolución ha llevado a través de la laparoscopia a la actual cirugía robótica, en la cual, se ha logrado la aplicación exitosa de los preceptosde ingeniería robótica al quehacer diario del cirujano.El desarrollo de la cirugía mínimamente invasiva, inicialmente liderado por la laparoscopia convencional, constituyó terreno fértil para el desarrollo de técnicas quirúrgicas con el uso del robot. El uso de sistemas automatizadosen la cirugía, no es tan novedoso como se pudiese pensar, sin embargo los robots que hoy en día participan en los quirófanos de los centros a nivel mundial,constituyen el ejemplo de la tecnología más novedosay avanzada disponible. La Urología se ha erigido como la especialidad quirúrgica líder en la aplicación de la tecnología para el diagnóstico y resolución de los aspectos clínicos que le competen, y la cirugía robótica no es una excepción. Presentamos nuestra visión de la vigente cirugía automatizada, en el marco de su estrecharelación con la cirugía laparoscopia convencional que la originó</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;60(4): 357-362, mayo 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055398</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases laparoscopicas de la cirugia robotica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32597^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19341^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
