<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162343</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complications of endoscopic skull base surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Major complications associated with endoscopic approaches are the same as those associated with traditional skull base approaches. The most frequent are cerebrospinal fluid leaks, tension pneumocephalus, bleeding, cerebrovascular accidents and, more rarely, infectious complications and osteoradionecrosis. These complications may be caused by technical errors, deficient assessment, technical failure or unexpected problems. The present article describes the possible complications and their solutions. Special emphasis is placed on skull base reconstruction and the Hadad-Bassagasteguy naso-septal flap as a major advance in the resolution of postoperative cerebrospinal fluid leaks (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Snyderman, Carl H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kassam, Amin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prevedello, Daniel M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Massegur, Humbert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrau, Ricardo L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mintz, Arlan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las complicaciones mayores asociadas a los abordajes endoscópicos no son distintas de las asociadas a los abordajes tradicionales de la base de cráneo. Las más frecuentes son la fístula de líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR), neumoencefalocele a tensión, sangrado perioperatorio, accidentes cerebrovasculares y, más raramente, complicaciones infecciosas, osteorradionecrosis. Estas complicaciones pueden ser debidas a errores técnicos, errores de valoración, fallos tecnológicos o a la aparición de un problema insospechado. En el artículo se exponen las posibles complicaciones y su solución. Se hace especial hincapié en la reconstrucción de la base de cráneo y se describe el colgajo nasoseptal de Hadad-Bassagasteguy como un avance muy significativo en la resolución de las fístulas de LCR postoperatorias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;58(supl.1): 106-113, oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162343</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones en cirugia endoscópica de la base de cráneo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4757^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32869^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32869^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10206^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5538^s22043</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4757^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
