<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046993</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Early defibrillation in the community: breaking barriers to save lives</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is considered that in Spain, every year, we have more than 24,500 out-of-hospital cardiac arrests. Around 85% of these are secondary to ventricular fibrillation, with possibility of reversion in more than 90% if defibrillation is performed in the first minute of arrhythmia. However, if we delay this defibrillation, survival possibilities disappear in a few minutes. Clinical advances in last decades have not achieved satisfactory results in the treatment of cardiac arrest as survival rates at hospital discharge do not exceed 7%. Aware of this situation, the International Scientific Societies are recommending decreasing time to defibrillation, advising, at best, a time less than five minutes between the 112-call (emergency) and adequate electric discharge. Development of automated defibrillators in Emergency Medical Systems and their use by «first responders» of «non-health care» emergency services (police, fire fighters, etc) contribute to reach this objective. Because of this, Emergency Medical Systems are modifying their assistance strategies, to implement the early defibrillation as «key to survival». Literature showed the effective value of automated defibrillators in the public areas but their efficiency level is less than that reached with the Emergency Services. Efficiency depends on multiple factors such as type of installation, accessibility level to emergency medical services or incidence rate of sudden cardiac arrest. Thus, their introduction should be preceded by a cost-effectiveness study. Effectiveness of automated defibrillators at home, where up to 80% of cardiac arrest are produced, has still not been evaluated. Nevertheless, in the USA, its marketing with this indication has been authorized</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Fernández, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Vela, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perales-Rodríguez de Viguri, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se estima que en España se producen, cada año, mas de 24.500 paradas cardíacas extrahospitalarias (PC). Hasta el 85% de estas paradas están ocasionadas por una fibrilación ventricular y más del 90% podrían revertirse si se realizara una desfibrilación en el primer minuto, pero si ésta se retrasa las posibilidades de sobrevivir desaparecen en muy pocos minutos. A pesar de los avances de las últimas décadas no se han logrado unos resultados satisfactorios en el tratamiento de la PC, de forma que la tasa de supervivencia, al alta hospitalaria, no suele superar el 7%. Ante esta situación las Sociedades Científicas internacionales recomiendan que se acorte el retraso en la realización de la desfibrilación, aconsejando, como óptimo, un tiempo menor de 5 minutos entre la llamada al 112 y la descarga eléctrica. La incorporación de los desfibriladores semiautomáticos (DESA) en los Servicios de Emergencias Médicas (SEM) y su utilización por «primeros intervinientes» de los servicios de emergencias «no sanitarios» (policías, bomberos, etc.) contribuye a alcanzar este objetivo. Por ello, los SEM están modificando sus estrategias asistenciales para incorporar la desfibrilación temprana, como la «llave para la supervivencia». La literatura ha validado como efectiva la utilización de los DESA en los espacios públicos, pero su nivel de eficiencia es menor que el alcanzado con su uso por los Servicios de Emergencias. Su eficiencia depende de múltiples factores como el tipo de instalación, el nivel de accesibilidad para el SEM o la tasa de incidencia de muertes súbitas. Por ello su implantación debe estar precedida de un estudio coste-efectividad. Aún no está evaluada la efectividad de la utilización de los DESA en el hogar, que es donde se produce hasta el 80% de las PC. No obstante, en EE.UU. se ha autorizado su comercialización con esta indicación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);30(5): 223-231, jun. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046993</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La desfibrilación temprana en la comunidad: romper barreras para salvar vidas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3275</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15100^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
