<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107943</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Celedonio Calatayud-Costa and the birth of the specialty, the Spanish Society of Medical Radiology, and the journal: the beginning of a century of Spanish Radiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dr. Celedonio Calatayud-Costa, an eminent Spanish radiologist, electrical engineer, researcher, and co-founder of the Spanish Society of Electrical Engineering and Medical Radiology, was also the founder of the Spanish Journal of Electrical Engineering and Medical Radiology. The journal, the first journal dedicated specifically to the incipient specialty of electrology, from which radiology would later develop, was the official publication of that primordial Society, and was thus the first antecessor of Radiología, which is today the official journal of the Spanish Society of Medical Radiology. This article analyzes the figure of Dr. Calatayud, based on the scant information available about him, in the centennial of the publication of his journal. Criticized by some and eulogized by others, knowledge about this controversial figure is essential to any understanding of the beginnings of the specialty and its scientific publication in Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Santos, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puyalto de Pablo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Fernández, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Dr. Celedonio Calatayud Costa, eminente radiólogo español, electrotécnico, investigador y cofundador de la Sociedad Española de Electrología y Radiología Médica, fue también el fundador de la Revista Española de Electrología y Radiología Médica. La revista, la primera específicamente dedicada a la incipiente especialidad de la electrología, de la que después se desarrollará la radiología, fue la publicación oficial de aquella Sociedad primordial y, por lo tanto, la primera antecesora de Radiología, hoy revista oficial de la Sociedad Española de Radiología Médica. Este artículo analiza la figura del Dr. Calatayud, partiendo de la escasa información que de él se dispone, en el centenario de la edición de su revista. Criticado por algunos, destacada su figura y labor por otros, se trata de una figura controvertida sin la que es imposible entender los comienzos de la especialidad y su publicación científica en España(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);54(6): 539-548, nov.-dic.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Celedonio Calatayud Costa y el nacimiento de la especialidad, la Sociedad Española de Radiología Médica y la revista: el comienzo de un siglo de Radiología española</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24850^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24850^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29531^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
