<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90618</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thymic uptake of 18FFDG following radioiodine ablation therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a 47 year-old woman with a history of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. During the course of her disease, we performed various 18FFDG PET/CT that identified several significant incidental findings. First, we incidentally identified a hypermetabolic nodule in the left thyroid lobe, whose final diagnosis was differentiated thyroid carcinoma. Second, metabolic activity was visualized in the thymus secondary to ablative treatment with radioiodine. This uptake disappeared in subsequent studies. Several papers have reported thymic rebound following chemotherapy but we have found only one case report of 18FFDG uptake after radioiodine treatment. On the other hand, this case is of interest because it supports the benefit of studying the hypermetabolic thyroid nodules incidentally detected on the PET/CT performed for other reasons(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Uña Gorospe, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello García, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Gimeno, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albalá González, M. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas Negro, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sequera Rahola, M. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Allende Riera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 47 años con antecedente de linfoma no Hodgkin. En el transcurso de su enfermedad se le realizan varias PET/TAC con 18F-FDG que muestran varios hallazgos incidentales significativos. En primer lugar, encontramos incidentalmente un nódulo hipermetabólico en el lóbulo tiroideo izquierdo, cuyo diagnóstico definitivo fue de carcinoma papilar. En segundo lugar, se observó actividad metabólica en timo secundaria al tratamiento ablativo de restos tiroideos con radioyodo, que desapareció en los estudios posteriores. Se han publicado múltiples artículos acerca de la hiperplasia tímica tras quimioterapia, pero sólo hemos encontrado un caso descrito de captación de 18F-FDG tras radioyodo. Por otra parte, este caso es de interés ya que apoya la conveniencia de estudiar los nódulos tiroideos hipermetabólicos detectados incidentalmente en la PET/TAC(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;30(5): 314-316, sept.-oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90618</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Captación de 18F-FDG en timo tras terapia ablativa de restos tiroideos con 131I</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14340^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2334^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33386^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14349^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14340^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14338^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14340^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14338^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
