<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146508</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">BET inhibitors. The odd compound (+)-JQ1</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The serendipitous discovery of (bromodomain extra-terminal) (BET) inhibitors, especially of the BRD4 bromodomain inhibitors, has allowed modulation of gene transcription with epigenetic drugs. This is the case of protooncogen c- MY C and other genes involved in carcinogenesis and different disfunctions. These drugs, that include the compound (+)-JQ1, have shown their potencial as anticancer agents, immunomodulators, male contraceptives, antiviral, or heart failure chemopreventive agents, among others. In this review we analyze their discovery, structure, mechanism of action and future perspectives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Avendaño, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El descubrimiento fortuito de los inhibidores BET (bromodomain extra-terminal), y en especial de los inhibidores del bromodominio BRD4, ha permitido modular con fármacos epigenéticos la transcripción del protooncogén c-MY C, entre otros genes implicados en la carcinogénesis y otras disfunciones. Estos fármacos, entre los que se encuentra el compuesto (+)-JQ1, han mostrado su potencial como anticancerosos, inmunomoduladores, anticonceptivos masculinos, antivirales, o agentes preventivos del fallo cardíaco. En esta revisión se analiza su descubrimiento, estructura, mecanismo de acción y sus perspectivas futuras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;81(3): 214-220, 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146508</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inhibidores BET. El singular compuesto (+)-JQ1</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55206^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29089^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29089^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29089^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29093^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38372^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22884^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29093^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7336^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
