<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140985</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pain and dementia of people living in a nursing home</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pain is prevalent, sub diagnosed and sub treated in people with dementia or other mental disorders Aim: To identify the prevalence of pain and its relation with sociodemographic, clinical and functional variables of 80 residents in a unit of long stay (LSU) in the centre of France. Methods: Elaboration of an orientation script for data collection of sociodemographic, clinical and functional variables. Register of pain. Results: The prevalence of pain is 70% of the residents in a LSU. Conclusion: It´s an aged population, mainly women, multipharmacology and with multi diseases, pain and minor awareness of themselves. It´s necessary formative procedure to help formal and informal caregivers to identify pain in those who do not verbalize it and in order to understand deviate behaviour caused by  pain in those with cognitive deterioration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carneiro, Constancia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pestana, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sotto Mayor, Margarida</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valente, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reis, Gorete</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dolor es prevalente, infradiagnosticado e infratratado en las personas con diagnóstico de demencia u otros trastornos mentales. Objetivo: identificar la prevalencia del dolor y su relación con las variables sociodemográficas, clínicas y funcionales de las 80 personas residentes en una unidad de larga estancia (ULE) del centro de Francia. Métodos: elaboración de un guion orientador para la recogida de datos de variables sociodemográficas, clínicas y funcionales. Registro de dolor. Resultados: El dolor tiene una prevalencia del 70% en los residentes de la ULE. Conclusión: población envejecida, sobre todo del sexo femenino, polimedicada, con pluripatología, dolor y menor conciencia de sí misma. Son necesarias medidas formativas que ayuden a los cuidadores formales e informales a identificar el dolor en las personas que no lo verbalizan y a comprender las alteraciones de comportamiento resultantes del dolor en las personas con deterioro cognitivo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);26(1): 23-27, mar. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140985</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dolor y demencia en las personas que viven en una unidad de larga estancia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
