<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165523</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metacognitive skills in students of the Specialization Course in Family Medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The educational process in modern societies requires personal initiatives, both in the educational and the work context, and thus it is important for people to develop and regulate their cognitive competences throughout learning processes. Aim. To describe the metacognitive skills of students taking the Specialisation in Family Medicine Course, in a centre in the state of Sonora. Subjects and methods. A cross-sectional study was conducted to evaluate the development of metacognitive skills in all the students enrolled in the Specialisation in Family Medicine Course, at a centre in Ciudad Obregón, Sonora. The metacognitive skills inventory was applied after previously validating it and determining its reliability by means of a pilot test. Descriptive statistics, chi squared and Kruskall-Wallis were applied. Results. Of the 36 students (63.9% females), with a mean age of 28.7 ± 1.9 years, 28 (78.8%) presented a high level of development in metacognitive skills, with a mean of 200.79, 203.13, 200.75 and 201.75 points for the first, second and third years and overall, respectively (p = 0.834; Kruskall-Wallis). Conclusions. No differences are observed in the overall development of their metacognitive skills or in their subscales, among students in the three academic years at the residence. In the future, instruments that evaluate the student&#146;s degree of social desirability of will have to be considered with the aim of controlling this bias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Heredia, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Gastélum, Norma A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Acevedo, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Cázares, José A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Félix-Álvarez, Carlos A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Morales, Cruz M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reynoso Arenas, M Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El proceso educativo en las sociedades modernas necesita iniciativas personales, tanto en el contexto educativo como en el laboral, por lo que es importante que la persona desarrolle y regule sus competencias cognitivas durante los procesos de aprendizaje. Objetivo. Describir las habilidades metacognitivas en alumnos del Curso de Especialización en Medicina Familiar, en una sede del estado de Sonora. Sujetos y métodos. Se realizó un estudio transversal para evaluar el desarrollo de las habilidades metacognitivas en el total del censo de los alumnos adscritos al Curso de Especialización en Medicina Familiar, de una sede en Ciudad Obregón, Sonora. Se aplicó el inventario de habilidades metacognitivas, el cual se validó y se determinó su fiabilidad a través de una prueba piloto. Se aplicó estadística descriptiva, chi al cuadrado y Kruskall-Wallis. Resultados. De los 36 alumnos (63,9% de sexo femenino), con una edad media de 28,7 ± 1,9 años, 28 (78,8%) presentaron un desarrollo alto de habilidades metacognitivas, con una media de 200,79, 203,13, 200,75 y 201,75 puntos para el primer, segundo, tercer año y global, respectivamente (p = 0,834; Kruskall-Wallis). Conclusiones. No se observaron diferencias en el desarrollo global de las habilidades metacognitivas, ni en sus subescalas, entre los tres años académicos del alumnado de la residencia. En el futuro, se tendrán que considerar instrumentos que evalúen el grado de deseabilidad social del alumno con el fin de controlar dicho sesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);20(4): 177-181, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165523</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Habilidades metacognitivas en alumnos del Curso de Especialización en Medicina Familiar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13421^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
