<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62306</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE: To determine possible variations in plasma ;;levels of melatonin in patients sedated with propofol ;;administered in continuous infusion. ;;PATIENTS AND METHODS: Healthy patients receiving ;;spinal anesthesia for lower limb orthopedic surgery were ;;randomized to 2 groups in this prospective study: group A ;;patients were sedated with intravenous propofol infused at ;;a rate of 3 to 4 mg·kg-1h-1 and group B underwent surgery ;;without sedation. Data from these groups were compared ;;with data from 2 other groups. Group C data, from healthy ;;volunteers who did not undergo surgery or sedation, were ;;compared with baseline values. Group D data were ;;theoretical reference values for plasma melatonin levels ;;taken from the literature, for comparisons at baseline and ;;in the range of hypnosis. Hormone levels were determined ;;by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay at baseline, at 10 ;;and 60 minutes after the start of sedation, and 90 minutes ;;after withdrawal of sedation. ;;RESULTS: Twenty patients were enrolled. No significant ;;between-group differences were detected at baseline (P&gt;.269), ;;60 minutes after starting sedation or 90 minutes after ;;withdrawing it (P&gt;.347 and P&gt;.057 respectively). Values were ;;significantly different between group B and groups A and D ;;10 minutes after starting sedation with propofol (P&lt;.001). ;;CONCLUSIONS: Plasma levels of melatonin increased; during administration of propofol in continuous perfusion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Salván, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riquelme Osado, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bardina Pastor, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas Roca, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Castro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Alcantud, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS: Determinar posibles variaciones en losniveles plasmáticos de melatonina en pacientes sometidosa sedación con propofol en perfusión continua.PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: Estudio prospectivo aleatorio enpacientes sanos sometidos a anestesia espinal para cirugíatraumatológica de miembros inferiores y separadosen dos grupos: (A) sedación con propofol (3-4 mg Kg-1 h-1, i.v.) y (B) sometidos a cirugía sin sedación. Se realizó lacomparación de estos grupos con otros dos: (C) no sometidoni a cirugía ni a sedación (sólo una muestra basal envoluntarios sanos), para control de valores basales, y (D)curva teórica con los valores de melatonina plasmáticarecogidos en la literatura, tanto basales como en rangohipnótico. La determinación de los valores de la hormonase realizó mediante ELISA, tanto los basales, como alos 10 y 60 minutos tras iniciarse la sedación y 90 minutostras ser retirada la misma.RESULTADOS: Incluimos 20 pacientes. No apreciamosdiferencias en los valores basales (p&gt;0,269), tras 60minutos después de iniciar la sedación, ni 90 minutostras retirar la misma (p&gt;0,347 y p&gt;0,057 respectivamente).Apreciamos diferencias significativas entre los gruposA y D respecto al B (p&lt;0,001) en el minuto 10 trasiniciar la sedación con propofol.CONCLUSIONES: Observamos un aumento de melatoninaplasmática durante la administración de propofol enperfusión continua (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;54(8): 469-474, oct. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62306</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24841^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10669^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7170^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
