<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142183</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hepatitis vaccine among Primary Care personnel</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AIM. To know the prevalence of those who are vaccinated and protected against the hepatitis B virus (HBV), to estimate the risks they have at their work and describe antibody markers, considering 14 professional categories, gender, age, seniority and workplace. METHOD. A cross-sectional observational study conducted in 2003 in a study population of 550 health care site workers in Palencia. Source of information: self-completed questionnaire. Main variables: correctly vaccinated (three doses of 20 micrograms of HBsAg, with a regime of 0, 1, 6 or 0, 1, 2 months), protected against the HBV (correctly vaccinated with postvaccination anti-HBs antibodies &gt; 10 IU) and risk perceived by the worker in his/her work activity (values from 0 to 9). The statistical analysis of the data was conducted with EPIIN- FOV.6. RESULTS. A total of 50.45% participated and 59.1% (CI 95%, 53.3-64.9) were correctly vaccinated. Responsive subjects: 35.1% (CI 95%, 29.5-40.7%). Arithmetic mean of perceived risk: 5.36 (CI 99%, 5.28-5.44), there being high values (7-9) in odontologists, nursing assistants and nurses, and middle values (4-6) in doctors, cleaning staff and midwives. CONCLUSIONS. The prevalence of vaccinated subjects found is higher than in other similar studies; possibly one third of the population might not be vaccinated and more than 40% could be candidates for vaccination. In conclusion, more antibody controls must be recorded and informative campaigns made on hepatitis B, mainly aimed at high-risk non-health care staff and at male health care workers who are over 45 and have been practicing in rural areas for more than 20 years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Calvo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Rodríguez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVOS. Conocer la prevalencia de vacunados y protegidos contra el virus de la hepatitis B (VHB), estimar el riesgo que perciben en su actividad laboral y describir marcadores serológicos, distribuidos por catorce categorías profesionales, sexo, edad, antigüedad laboral y centro de trabajo. MÉTODO. Estudio observacional y transversal realizado en 2003. Población de estudio: 550 trabajadores de los centros de salud de Palencia. Fuente de información: cuestionario autoaplicable. Variables principales: vacunado correctamente (tres dosis de 20 mg de HBsAg en pautas 0-1-6 o 0-1-2 meses), protegido contra el VHB (vacunado correctamente con anticuerpos anti-HBs posvacunal &gt; 10 UI) y riesgo percibido por el trabajador en su actividad laboral (valores de 0-9). El análisis estadístico de los datos se realizó con EPIINFO V.6. RESULTADOS. Participación: 50,45%. Vacunados correcta- mente: 59,1% (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 53,3%- 64,9%). Protegido: 35,1% (IC del 95%, 29,5%-40,7%). Media aritmética del riesgo percibido: 5,36 (IC del 99%, 5,28-5,44), con valores altos (7-9) en odontólogos, auxiliares de enfermería y enfermeros y valores medios (4-6) en médicos, personal de limpieza y matronas. CONCLUSIONES. La prevalencia de vacunados hallada es más alta que en otros estudios similares, una tercera parte de la población podría no estar vacunada y más de un 40% sería vacunable. Se concluye que hay que registrar más controles serológicos y ampliar las campañas informativas sobre hepatitis B, dirigiéndose sobre todo al personal no sanitario en riesgo y al personal médico, varones mayores de 45 años con más de 20 de antigüedad y que ejercen en el medio rural (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);35(1): 2-9, ene. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142183</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vacuna de hepatitis B entre personal de Atención Primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16843</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6664^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
