<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62169</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of health-related quality of life in clinical practice: Subjectivity in evidence</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incorporation of subjective elements provided by the patient to medical practice constitutes a new bridge between two historical movements of human culture: naturalism and rationalism. In recent years, medical sciences have identified these movements as patient-centered medicine and evidence-based medicine.By revisiting the paradigms of medicine, theories of causality, doctor-patient relationship models, bioethical principles and examples of clinical studies, their role and meaning has been revised. The applicability for neuroendocrinology has been demonstrated by validating therapeutic results with measurement of health-related quality of life. The need to incorporate the patient&#146;s subjective perception poses a challenge that, when accepted, can advance the understanding and care of human beings &#151;ultimately rational, thinking subjects, and therefore subjective&#151; as our species has been defined (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Resmini, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, Camelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Webb, Susan M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barahona, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ybarra, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, María Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La incorporación de elementos subjetivos aportados por el paciente en la práctica constituye un nuevo puente entre dos corrientes históricamente pendulares de la cultura humana: naturalismo y racionalismo. En las ciencias médicas de los últimos años, estas corrientes se identifican en la medicina centrada en el paciente y en la medicina basada en la evidencia. Revisando los paradigmas de la medicina, las teorías de causalidad, los modelos de relación médico-paciente, principios de bioética y con ejemplos de estudios clínicos, estudiamos su lugar y su significado. Desde la neuroendocrinología, con la validación de resultados terapéuticos mediante la medición de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud, mostramos su aplicabilidad. La necesaria incorporación de la percepción subjetiva del paciente plantea un desafío que, asumido, puede contribuir con un paso más hacia la comprensión y el cuidado del sujeto humano, en última instancia materia pensante, luego subjetiva, como ha sido definida nuestra especie (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;56(6): 331-336, jul.-ago. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62169</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida relacionada con la salud, su lugar en la práctica clínica: lo subjetivo en la evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28600</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11344^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200908</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
