<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054018</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contact allergy to propolis in beekeepers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Some toothpastes, cosmetics and ointments contain propolis, a bee product, and it is increasingly popular as a dietary supplement. Although propolis is known to cause contact allergy, there have been no studies of the prevalence of this.                 Objectives: This study aimed to determine the prevalence of contact allergy to propolis in beekeepers and any relationship between propolis allergy and environmental and physical and mental health characteristics in this group.                 Subjects and methods: A specially developed instrument which included a validated questionnaire on emotional stability was included in the issues of three German beekeeping journals sent to subscribers in a number of regions (potential readership 35,000). A reference group also completed questionnaire.                 Results: 1051 questionnaires were returned and 37 cases of allergic reactions to propolis were reported (3.6 %). Only 10 of the 37 (27 %) beekeepers had recognised the allergy before participating in this study. Propolis contact allergy was significantly associated with lung diseases and other allergic reactions. Only some affected beekeepers protected their hands more while working with bees and showed significantly greater emotional instability than those not sensitised to propolis.                 Conclusions: Contact allergy to propolis is common among beekeepers, but they do not seem to recognise the problem or protect themselves properly</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Georgi, R von</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hackethal, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Münstedt, K</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hellner, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Winter, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Algunas pastas de dientes, cosméticos y pomadas contienen propolis, un producto de las abejas, que esta teniendo un popular incremento como suplemento alimenticio. Aunque el propolis es conocido como causante de alergia de contacto, no hay estudios sobre la prevalencia de esto. Objetivos. Este estudio está dirigido para determinar la prevalencia de la alergia de contacto al propolis en apicultores y la relación entre alergia al propolis y ambiente, y las características físicas y mentales de este grupo. Controles y métodos. Un instrumento especialmente desarrollado que incluía un cuestionario validado sobre estabilidad emocional, se incluyó en la edición de tres revistas Alemanas de apicultores, enviado a los suscriptores de un número de regiones (35.000 potenciales lectores). El cuestionario también lo completó un grupo de referencia. Resultados. Retornaron 1.050 cuestionarios que reportaron 37 casos de reacciones alérgicas a propolis (3,6%). Sólo 10 de los 37 (27%) apicultores habían reconocido la alergia antes de participar en este estudio. La alergia de contacto al propolis estuvo asociada significativamente con enfermedad pulmonar y otras reacciones alérgicas. Solamente algunos apicultores protegían sus manos cuando trabajaban con las abejas y mostraron una mayor significativa inestabilidad emocional que los no sensibilizados al propolis. Conclusiones. La alergia por contacto al propolis es común entre apicultores, pero ellos no parece que reconozcan el problema y se protejan adecuadamente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);35(3): 95-100, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054018</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alergia de contacto al propolis en apicultores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11861^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3894^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5998</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11861^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1535^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
