<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152241</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The influence of a congested fixture calendar on physical performance in elite soccer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper is to analyze the impact of playing a high amount of minutes in competition during the season on elite soccer performance. Distances covered at various speeds and the time spent in highintensity activities by 68 players that completed the entire match in the FIFA World Cup Brazil 2014 were examined. A k mean analysis classified the players according to the number of minutes played throughout the season: high, medium and low amount of minutes. Additional variables such as the scoreline, quality of the opponent and playing position were included. Data were examined through linear regression analysis. Overall, the results suggested that playing a high amount of minutes during the season does not affect physical performances in elite soccer. Central Midfielders covered higher total distances and distances covered at high speed than the other playing positions (p&lt; 0.01). Winning or losing match status was not associated with changes on the physical performance profiles of the players. These results could be used by coaches and analysts to improve the design of assignment and the team and players performance assessment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lago-Peñas, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-López, Maite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo consiste en analizar el impacto de disputar una alta carga de minutos de competición a lo largo de una temporada sobre el rendimiento físico en el fútbol de elite. La distancia recorrida a distintas velocidades y el porcentaje de tiempo realizando actividades de alta intensidad por 68 jugadores que disputaron la Copa Mundial de Brasil 2014 de la FIFA fueron analizados. Un análisis de cluster clasificó a los jugadores en tres grupos dependiendo del número de minutos disputados a lo largo de la temporada: alta, media y baja carga de competición. El marcador, el nivel del oponente y el puesto específico de los jugadores se incorporaron en el análisis como variables de control. Los datos fueron analizados mediante de un análisis de regresión lineal. En general, los resultados sugieren que jugar una alta carga de minutos de competición durante la temporada no afecta negativamente al rendimiento físico de los jugadores. Los mediocentros recorrieron una distancia total y a alta intensidad mayor que el resto de puestos específicos (p&lt; 0,01). Tener el marcador a favor o en contra y la fortaleza o debilidad del oponente no modificó significativamente el rendimiento físico de los jugadores. Estos resultados podrían ser utilizados por entrenadores y analistas para mejorar el diseño de tareas y la evaluación del rendimiento de los equipos y de los jugadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;16(1): 287-294, ene. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152241</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de un calendario sobrecargado de partidos sobre el rendimiento físico en el fútbol de élite</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29745</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
