<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052263</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease on activities of daily living: results of the EIME multicenter study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to determine the impact of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) on activities of daily living in a large group of patients in Spain who responded to a specific questionnaire. A second aim was to explore the practical utility of the questionnaire and determine which variables could be used to identify "fragile" patients or patients in greater need of attention. To do this, we examined the relationship between questionnaire results and clinical variables, lung function measurements, socioeconomic status, and validated quality of life questionnaires.         Methods: We conducted an observational, descriptive, multicenter, cross-sectional study in which 227 respiratory specialists from all over Spain collected data from 1057 patients with COPD. Each patient was given a specific questionnaire containing 7 items that measured the extent to which COPD affected different aspects of their lives. The patients rated each item on a scale of 0 to 2, depending on the level of impact. Total possible scores, thus, ranged from 0 to 14, and patients with a score of 9 or higher were classified as fragile. We then explored the relationship between questionnaire results and clinical variables, socioeconomic status, spirometric values, and quality of life as measured by the St George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ).                 Results: We studied 1057 patients (95.2% male) with a mean (SD) age of 67 (9) years and a mean predicted forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) of 41.8% (13.3%). The mean questionnaire score was 6.3 (3.1). The activities that were affected most were sport and leisure, habitual physical activity, and sex life (major impact reported by 52.5%, 30.3%, and 20.2% of patients, respectively). We found a correlation between questionnaire scores and known disease severity markers such as SGRQ scores, dyspnea, number of exacerbations, and FEV1 in liters. Patients included in the fragile category were older and had a lower socioeconomic status.                 Conclusions: COPD impact questionnaire scores correlated well with SGRQ scores and the usual clinical variables and lung function measurements for evaluating disease severity (dyspnea, FEV1, and exacerbations). The questionnaire could, therefore, be a useful tool for identifying fragile patients who, in addition to having poorer clinical status and lung function measurements, have a lower socioeconomic status</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle, Miriam</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Gutiérrez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miravitlles, Marc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gobarttd, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizamos el estudio con el propósito de conocer, a través de un cuestionario específico, el impacto de la enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica (EPOC) sobre las actividades de la vida diaria en un grupo amplio de pacientes en España. Asimismo estudiamos su relación con parámetros clínicos, funcionales y socioeconómicos, y con escalas validadas de calidad de vida, para evaluar su utilidad en la práctica habitual y determinar qué variables pueden definir a los pacientes "frágiles" o que requieren una mayor atención.                 Métodos: Se ha realizado un estudio observacional, descriptivo, multicéntrico y transversal, con la participación de 227 neumólogos de toda España, que incluyó a pacientes con el diagnóstico de EPOC. A todos éstos se les pasó un cuestionario específico con 7 preguntas que medían el impacto de la enfermedad sobre aspectos de la vida diaria Las respuestas se valoraron de 0 a 2, según el grado de afectación, lo que supone un intervalo entre 0 y 14 unidades. Definimos al paciente como "frágil" si presentaba valores iguales o mayores de 9 en el cuestionario de impacto. Se evaluó la relación entre la escala de impacto y variables clínicas, situación socioeconómica, espirometría y calidad de vida medida con el cuestionario específico St. George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ).                 Resultados: Estudiamos a 1.057 pacientes (un 95,2% varones), con una edad media (± desviación estándar) de 67 ± 9 años y volumen espiratorio forzado en el primer segundo (FEV1), expresado en porcentaje, del 41,8 ± 13,3%. La puntuación media del cuestionario de impacto fue de 6,3 ± 3,1. Las actividades con mayor afectación fueron deporte y ocio, actividad física habitual y vida sexual (mucha afectación en el 52,5, el 30,3 y el 20,2% de los pacientes, respectivamente). Encontramos relación entre la puntuación del cuestionario y parámetros conocidos de gravedad (SGRQ, disnea, número de agudizaciones y FEV1 expresado en litros). Los pacientes definidos como frágiles tenían mayor edad y menor nivel tanto cultural como económico.                 Conclusiones: El cuestionario de impacto de la EPOC se correlaciona bien con los clásicos parámetros clínicos y funcionales de valoración de la gravedad de la enfermedad (disnea, FEV1 y exacerbaciones) y con el cuestionario de calidad de vida relacionada con la salud SGRQ. Así pues, podría ser un instrumento útil para identificar un perfil de paciente frágil, que presenta, además de una peor situación clínica y funcional, una situación socioeconómica más desfavorecida</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;43(2): 64-72, feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052263</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la EPOC en la vida diaria de los pacientes. Resultados del estudio multicéntrico EIME</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16843</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
