<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-29447</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Anoxic encephalopathy. Clinical description, prognosis and neuroimaging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To describe the clinical profile (neuropsychological, psychopatological, functional and neuroimaging), as well as the evolution of patients with anoxic encephalopathy. Patients and methods. Nine patients with anoxic encephalopathy attending our Service were included in the study. All patients were assessed with a broad range of neuropsychological tests, checklists of psychopathological symptoms, and several functional scales. A CT/MRI or a positron emission tomography (PET) were performed in five patients. Five patients were admitted to a multidisciplinary rehabilitation program. Results. All patients showed problems in orientation, executive functions, verbal learning an immediate and long-term verbal memory, in association with diffuse cognitive changes in other functions. Psychopathologically, all patients showed apathy-indifference, and eight subjects showed anosognosia. All subjects have an important dependence in daily activities. CT/MRI were normal or showed subcortical changes whereas the PET showed a predominantly cortical hypometabolism with specifical patterns. There were no significance improvements after rehabilitation in treated patients. Conclusion. In the absence of a unique clinical profile, our patients with anoxic encephalopathy showed similarities in their symptoms (diffuse cognitive deficits with predominance of mnesic and executive impairments; presence of apathy and anosognosia; complete functional dependence; and poor response to the rehabilitation). Functional neuroimaging could be a useful tool for a better understanding of these encephalopaties (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Describir las características clínicas (neuropsicológicas, psicopatológicas, funcionales y de neuroimagen), así como la evolución clínica de pacientes que han sufrido una encefalopatía anóxica. Pacientes y métodos. Se incluyeron nueve pacientes con encefalopatía anóxica que fueron atendidos en nuestro servicio.La evaluación se compuso de: 1) valoración neuropsicológica (orientación, atención, aprendizaje, memoria, praxis, gnosias, funciones ejecutivas, lenguaje e inteligencia general); 2) valoración psicopatológica (síntomas neuropsiquiátricos, conciencia de enfermedad); 3) valoración funcional (Barthel, FIM-FAM). A todos se les realizó RM, TCoPET. Cinco pacientes fueron admitidos en un programa de rehabilitación multidisciplinar. Resultados. Todos los pacientes presentaban una importante alteración en la capacidad de orientación, funciones ejecutivas, aprendizaje, memoria inmediata y, especialmente, memoria a largo plazo. En el resto de las funciones cognitivas, la heterogeneidad era mayor. Psicopatológicamente, todos mostraban apatía, y ocho de los nueve mostraban anosognosia. Funcionalmente, todos los sujetos tenían una importante dependencia en las actividades de la vida diaria. Las pruebas de neuroimagen (TC/RM) fueron normales o mostraron lesiones subcorticales, mientras que el PET mostró una afectación predominantemente cortical con patrones específicos. Apenas se apreciaron mejorías significativas tras el proceso rehabilitador en los pacientes tratados. Conclusiones. Si bien parece no existir un patrón clínico único típico de la encefalopatía anóxica, sí parecen existir características comunes (afectación cognitiva difusa con predominio de alteración de la memoria y de las funciones ejecutivas, presencia de apatía y anosognosia, dependencia funcional completa y escasa respuesta a la rehabilitación). Las pruebas de neuroimagen funcional son una herramienta útil para una mejor comprensión, y valoración pronóstica y terapéutica de esta patología (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(2): 111-117, ene. 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Encefalopatía anóxica. Descripción clínica, pronóstico y neuroimagen</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Simó Guerrero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirivella Garrido, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noé Sebastián, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferri Campos, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-29447</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
