<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88925</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Wistar rats as an experimental animal model for use with gynecological pelvi-trainers in surgical resident physicians</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe a new animal model for training resident physicians in gynecological endoscopy. The surgery and training exercises are performed in live, anesthetized, Wistar rats in a pelvitrainer for gynecological endoscopy. The pelvitrainer is used to practice dissection, cutting, electrocoagulation, mobilization of structures in the abdominal cavity, subtotal hysterectomy with double anexectomy, extraction of the surgical specimen in a bag, and knotting to close the surgical wound. Twelve hours of training are sufficient for third-year resident surgeons to master the movements required to perform these techniques in humans (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herráiz Esteban, Néstor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boíllos Calvo, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Hiraldo, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ramos, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nassar Melic, Nadia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Burillo, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos nuevos ejercicios de entrenamiento endoscópico ginecológico en modelo animal (rata Wistar) para formación de los residentes en esta disciplina quirúrgica. Las intervenciones y los ejercicios de adiestramiento se efectuarán en una rata Wistar viva y anestesiada, introducida en un entrenador pélvico endoscópico ginecológico. A través del mismo se realizarán en la rata las prácticas de disección, coagulación, corte, movilización de estructuras de cavidad abdominal, histerectomía subtotal con anexectomía bilateral, extracción de pieza en bolsa y anudado para cerrar la herida abdominal. Con 12h de trabajo un residente de obstetricia y ginecología en su tercer año conseguiría el dominio de los movimientos necesarios para realizarlos en humanos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);54(6): 325-329, jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88925</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La rata Wistar como modelo animal experimental, para el adiestramiento laparoscópico de residentes con entrenadores pélvicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7226^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
