<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048237</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pharmacological treatment neuromuscular impairments in critically ill patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The use of drugs for treating neuromuscular impairments that present in the patient admitted to the Intensive Care Unit is virtually inexistent. The use of intravenous immunoglobulins for managing polyneuropathy of the critically ill patient (PCIP) is supported by no evidence. More important is prophylactic therapy, as is the administration of insulin perfusion to prevent hyperglycemia that is associated to increased development of PCIP. New data suggest that the protective mechanism of this perfusion, which normalizes glucose levels, is achieved through the modulation of endothelial dysfunction and lowering levels of asymmetrical di-methyl arginine (ADMA). As for myopathy of the critically ill patient or conditions with prolonged neuromuscular blockade, treatment consists in avoiding the use of several drugs known to be associated with development of these conditions, such as muscle relaxants and aminoglycosides. In relation to acute flaccid paralysis -an infection caused by the Western Nile Virus, anecdotic cases have been reported of improvement with the use steroids or interferon, although routine management remains to be established (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Leyba, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El empleo de fármacos para tratamiento de las alteraciones neuromusculares que se presentan en el enfermo ingresado en una Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos es prácticamente inexistente. El empleo de inmunoglobulinas por vía venosa para el tratamiento de la polineuropatía del paciente crítico (PPC) no aporta ninguna evidencia para su uso. Más importancia tiene el tratamiento profiláctico, como es el caso de la administración de una perfusión de insulina para prevenir la hiperglucemias que seasocian a un mayor desarrollo de la PPC. Nuevos datos inducen a pensar que el mecanismo protector de esta perfusión, normalizando los niveles de glucosa se hacen modulando una disfunción endotelial y a unos menores niveles de dimetilarginina asimétrica (ADMA). Con respecto a la miopatía del paciente crítico o a los cuadros de bloqueo neuromuscular prolongado, el tratamiento consiste en evitar el empleo de diversos fármacos que se sabe se asocian al desarrollo de estas entidades como son los corticoides, los relajantes musculares y los aminoglucósidos. Por lo que respecta a la parálisis aguda flácida -infección por el virus del oeste del nilo se han comunicado casos anecdóticos de mejoría con el empleo de corticoides o de interferón, pero su tratamiento rutinario queda aún por establecer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(supl.3): 114-117, 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048237</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento farmacológico de las alteraciones neuromusculares en el paciente crítico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9660^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15304^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22210^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33110^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
