<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058793</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Integral management in the emergency area and coordination with primary care services</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To assess the impact of a unique management model combining the different emergency areas included in a Department of Health on the activity of an emergency department (ED) and the results of developing a Center for Integrated Health (CIH) which acts as a link between emergency attention at continued attention points (CAP) and the ED. Methods: Over a 2-year period from April 2003 to 2005 we performed two separate studies in the Department of Health. The first descriptive study evaluated different elements necessary to provide emergency assistance in an integrated system. The second study assessed the usefulness of the CIH (before-after study). Results: The number of emergency department visits in the area of influence decreased by 30% in the ED since the Center for Integral Health (CIH) started to work. This percentage was equivalent to the increase in the number of visits to the CIH (34%). The emergency assistance curve of growth diminished from 135 000 patients in 2003 to 116 085 patients in 2005. Conclusions: The unique healthcare management model improves the use of the available resources in order to satisfy the patient care needs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz López, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán Soria, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bermejo, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trescoli Serrano, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarazona Ginés, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mínguez Platero, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar el impacto que tiene un modelo único de gestión que integra las distintas áreas de urgencias de un Departamento de Salud sobre la actividad de un servicio de urgencias hospitalario (SUH), así como la repercusión de la creación de un centro se salud integrada (CSI) que actúa como eslabón intermedio entre la asistencia urgente que se presta en los puntos de atención continuada (PAC) y el SUH. Método: Se estructurarán dos subestudios en el ámbito del Departamento de Salud en el periodo de dos años a partir de abril de 2003. En primer lugar, estudio descriptivo de los distintos elementos para avanzar hacia un sistema integrado de prestación de servicios urgentes. En segundo lugar, la valoración de la implantación del CSI (estudio evaluativo antes-después). Resultados: Tras la creación del Centro de Salud Integral (CSI) se observa un descenso de asistencia en el SUH de pacientes de su zona de influencia (30%). El descenso directamente se corresponde con el porcentaje de aumento que ahora acude inicialmente al CSI (34%). Se observa inversión en la curva de crecimiento de asistencia urgente hospitalaria (116.085 personas durante 2005 frente a una estimación de 135.000). Conclusiones: La gestión única de los servicios asistenciales conlleva un mejor aprovechamiento de los recursos en la búsqueda de satisfacer las necesidades actuales del usuario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);20(1): 8-14, feb. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058793</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestión integral del área de urgencias y coordinación con atención primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
