<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148517</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Regulation of the calcium sensing receptor. Influence of secondary hyperparathyroidism</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The parathyroid glands have a great sensitivity to small changes in the extracellular ionic calcium. The calcium-sensing receptor (CaR) is a G protein-coupled receptor that responds to extracellular ionic calcium changes activating several intracellular signaling systems (phospholipases C, A2 and D) finally inhibiting the PTH secretion. In addition to calcium, there are some other agonists and modulators such as the Mg2+, spermine, amyloid &amp;#946;-peptides, a variety of aminoacids, especially aromatic aminoacids and ionic strength. In the uraemia, the sensitivity of the parathyroid glands to calcium is altered and higher values of calcium are necessary to suppress the PTH. In the secondary hyperparathyroidism the CaR expression is reduced. It has been found a negative correlation between cellular proliferation and the expression of the CaR in hyperplasic glands. Despite it is a calcium receptor, the expression of the CaR does not seem to be regulated by calcium and there is some controversy about the role of calcitriol regulating its expression. On the other hand, the phosphorous induces hyperplasia of the parathyroid gland increasing the cellular proliferation and a decrease of the CaR expression (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Martín, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Suárez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cannata Andía, JB</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las glándulas paratiroides tienen una gran sensibilidad a pequeños cambios en el calcio iónico extracelular. El receptor sensor de calcio (CaR) es un receptor acoplado a proteínas G que es capaz de responder a incrementos en el calcio extracelular activando una serie de señales intracelulares (fosfolipasas C, A2 y D) y cuyo resultado final es la inhibición de la secreción de PTH. Además del calcio, existen otros agonistas y moduladores del CaR como el Mg, espermina, péptidos amilodes &amp;#946;, ciertos aminoácidos, especialmente los aminoácidos aromáticos y la fuerza iónica. En la uremia la sensibilidad de las glándulas paratiroides al calcio está alterada, necesitando concentraciones más altas del mismo para suprimir la PTH. En el hiperparatiroidismo secundario la expresión del CaR se encuentra reducida. En glándulas hiperplásicas se ha observado una correlación negativa entre la proliferación celular y la expresión del CaR. A pesar de ser un receptor de calcio, la expresión del CaR no parece estar regulada por el calcio y existe una cierta discrepancia sobre si el calcitriol es capaz de regular su expresión. Por otro lado, el fósforo provoca una hiperplasia de la glándula paratiroides incrementando la proliferación celular y un descenso en la expresión del CaR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;23(supl.2): 7-11, 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148517</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regulación del receptor sensor de calcio. Influencia del hiperparatiroidismo Secundario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7851^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2151^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31906^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8448^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7141^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7851^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28261^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23827</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10171</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d600^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10494^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24316^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10469^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7172^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11186^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28856^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38268</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33891</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200300</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
