<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148347</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychoanalysis in times of technoculture: some reflections on the fate of the body in virtual space</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The author notes the increasing presence of techno-culture an cyberspace in contemporary life. Starting from the already controversial Freudian opposition between factual reality and psychic reality (with virtual elements by definition), she questions the psychic influence of the virtual worlds offered by the internet and cyberspace. She explores the complexity of some of these, such as Second Life and various other programs for experimentation in which the protagonist may inhabit different bodies or avatars in the virtual world. She presents the experience of an analytic process with a patient who, of his own accord, first makes use of videos and chat rooms, which he brings to his analyst as material, to later move on to virtual experiences with visual contact with others, and finally to contact in factual reality. She analyzes the significance for the patient of these progressive exchanges in coming to terms with and developing aspects of his body image and sexual identity. The author puts forward the world of cyberspace as a potential space for experimentation and progressive psychic elaboration and suggests that it might be considered in psychoanalytic processes as useful material for psychic growth and maturation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lemma, Alessandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La autora constata la creciente presencia en la vida contemporánea de la tecnocultura y el ciberespacio. Partiendo de la ya polémica contraposición freudiana entre la realidad fáctica y la realidad psíquica (con elementos virtuales por definición), se pregunta por la influencia psíquica de los mundos virtuales que ofrecen internet y el ciberespacio. Se adentra en la complejidad de algunos de ellos, como Second Life o diferentes programas de investigación en que el protagonista puede habitar diferentes cuerpos o avatares en el mundo virtual. Presenta la experiencia de un proceso analítico con un paciente que motu proprio hace uso primero de vídeos y chats que va llevando como material a su analista, para más adelante pasar a experiencias virtuales con contacto visual con otros, y finalmente a contactos en la realidad fáctica. Analiza la trascendencia para el paciente de estos intercambios progresivos para asumir y desarrollar aspectos de su imagen corporal e identidad sexual. La autora propone el mundo del ciberespacio como un espacio potencial para la experimentación y progresiva elaboración psíquica y que podría ser considerado en los procesos psicoanalíticos como material de utilidad para el crecimiento y la maduración psíquica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(75): 167-188, 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148347</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El psicoanálisis en tiempos de la tecnocultura: algunas reflexiones sobre el destino del cuerpo en el espacio virtual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55091^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55091^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55091^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34589^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34589^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55091^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33139^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27466^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27466^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
