<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154535</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fixed-dose combination fluticasone propionate/formoterol for the treatment of asthma: a review of its pharmacology, efficacy and tolerability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The fixed-dose combination fluticasone propionate/formoterol (FPF) is a novel combination of a widely known and used inhaled glucocorticoid (IGC) and a long-acting &amp;#946;2-adrenergic agonist (LABA), available for the first time in a single device. This fixed-dose combination of FPF has a demonstrated efficacy and safety profile in clinical trials compared with its individual components and other fixed-dose combinations of IGC/LABA and is indicated for the treatment of persistent asthma in adults and adolescents. FPF is available in a wide range of doses that can adequately cover the therapeutic steps recommended by treatment guidelines, constituting a fixed-dose combination of GCI/LABA that is effective, rapid, well tolerated and with a reasonable acquisition cost. Various assessment agencies of the Spanish Autonomous Communities consider this combination to be an appropriate alternative therapy for asthma in the primary care setting (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Entrenas Costa, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ginel Mendoza, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintano Jiménez, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La combinación a dosis fija de fluticasona propionato/formoterol es una nueva combinación de un glucocorticoide inhalado y un agonista &amp;#946;2-adrenérgico de acción larga ampliamente conocidos y utilizados, disponibles por primera vez en un mismo dispositivo. Esta combinación a dosis fija de fluticasona propionato/formoterol ha demostrado su perfil de eficacia y seguridad en distintos ensayos clínicos frente a sus componentes individuales y otras combinaciones a dosis fijas de glucocorticoide inhalado/agonista &amp;#946;2-adrenérgico de acción larga, y está indicada para el tratamiento del asma persistente en adultos y adolescentes. Fluticasona propionato/formoterol está disponible en un amplio rango de dosis, que permite cubrir adecuadamente los escalones terapéuticos recomendados por las guías terapéuticas, y constituye una combinación a dosis fija de glucocorticoide inhalado/agonista &amp;#946;2-adrenérgico de acción larga eficaz, rápida, bien tolerada y con un coste de adquisición razonable. Esta combinación ha sido posicionada por los distintos organismos evaluadores de las comunidades autónomas como alternativa terapéutica adecuada para el asma en el ámbito de la atención primaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);42(supl.1): 2-9, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154535</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Combinación a dosis fija de fluticasona propionato/formoterol fumarato para el tratamiento del asma: una revisión de la farmacología, eficacia y tolerabilidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d321^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d325^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6082^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4419^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55859^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
