<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156446</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Safe intravenous administration in pediatrics: A 5-year Pediatric Intensive Care Unit experience with smart pumps</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To estimate the impact of smart pump implementation in a pediatric intensive care unit in terms of number and type of administration errors intercepted. Design: Observational, prospective study carried out from January 2010 to March 2015 with syringe and great volumen infusion pumps available in the hospital. Setting: A tertiary level hospital pediatric intensive care unit. Participants: Infusions delivered with infusion pumps in all pediatric intensive care unit patients. Interventions: Design of a drug library with safety limits for all intravenous drugs prescribed. Main variables: Users&#146; compliance with drug library as well as number and type of errors prevented were analyzed. Results: Two hundred and eighty-three errors were intercepted during 62 months of study. A high risk drug was involved in 58% of prevented errors, such as adrenergic agonists and antagonists, sedatives, analgesics, neuromuscular blockers, opioids, potassium and insulin. Users&#146; average compliance with the safety software was 84%. Conclusions: Smart pumps implementation has proven effective in intercepting high risk drugs programming errors. These results might be exportable to other critical care units, involving pediatric or adult patients. Interdisciplinary colaboration is key to succeed in this process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Galindo, AC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manrique Rodríguez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Llamazares, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo Álvarez, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Calvo, MM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanjurjo Sáez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Estimar el impacto de la implantación de bombas de infusión inteligentes en una unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátricos en cuanto al número y tipo de errores de administración interceptados Diseño: Estudio observacional, prospectivo, realizado de enero de 2010 a marzo de 2015 con las bombas volumétricas y de jeringa disponibles en el hospital. Ámbito: Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Pediátricos de un hospital general de tercer nivel. Participantes: Todas las infusiones programadas con bomba de infusión en los pacientes ingresados en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Pediátricos. Intervenciones: Elaboración de una biblioteca de fármacos con límites de seguridad a través de la cual se programarían todas las infusiones intravenosas prescritas. Variables principales: Se analizó la adherencia a la biblioteca de fármacos y el número y tipo de errores evitados según las alarmas generadas en el sistema. Resultados: Se interceptaron 283 errores reales de programación durante los 62 meses que duró el estudio. En el 58% de los errores estuvo implicado un fármaco de alto riesgo, como agonistas y antagonistas adrenérgicos, sedantes, analgésicos, bloqueantes neuromusculares, opiáceos, potasio e insulina. Durante este período, la adherencia media de los usuarios al software de seguridad fue del 84%. Conclusiones: La implantación de bombas de infusión inteligentes ha demostrado ser eficaz en la intercepción de errores de programación relacionados con fármacos de alto riesgo. Esta herramienta es susceptible de implantarse en otras unidades de pacientes críticos, tanto adultos como pediátricos. La colaboración multidisciplinar es clave para el éxito del proceso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);40(7): 411-421, oct. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Administración segura de medicamentos intravenosos en pediatría: 5 años de experiencia de una Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Pediátricos con bombas de infusión inteligentes (AU)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19209^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23699^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17212</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
