<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119777</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perceived stress by medical residents performing emergency guards in two hospitals of Madrid and determination of stress biomarkers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: to study the relationship between perceived stress by resident physicians (MIR) guards performing emergency and biomarkers of stress in two hospitals in Madrid. Material and Methods: a retrospective cross-sectional study of MIR second to fifth year who were on duty emergency during 2012-2013. Underwent medical examination (ME), and given two validated questionnaires: Goldberg about anxiety/depression (as well in the initial ME) and perceived stress 10 (PSS- 10). After medical guard and before 10 am, blood tests (for cortisol and other biomarkers of stress) and blood pressure were performed. Results: The prevalence of perceived stress measured by PSS- 10 was 94.68 % in the 94 MIR included. The high perceived stress was associated with the number of guards (OR 3.359, 95% CI 1.208 to 10.189, p = 0.0207), and actual anxiety/depression (OR 1.447, 95% CI 0.623 to 2.270, p = 0.0007), while not previous anxiety/depression Conclusions: MIR working in emergency guards showed a high level of perceived stress in our study. No association between perceived stress and stress biomarkers evaluated were found. It has been proposed preventive solutions regarding to training about conflictive situations in the beginning of the medical residency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mahíllo Fernández, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa Zabala, Kelman L de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero Borrego, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deschamps Perdomo, Ambar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo Bals, Mª Teresa del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la posible relación entre estrés percibido por médicos internos residentes (MIR) que realizan guardias de Urgencias en dos hospitales de Madrid y biomarcadores de estrés. Material y métodos: Estudio transversal retrospectivo en MIR de segundo a quinto año que realizaban guardias de Urgencias durante 2012-2013. Se les realizó un reconocimiento médico (RM), administrándoseles dos cuestionarios validados: el de Goldberg para ansiedad/ depresión (también se incluyeron los resultados del cuestionario de Goldberg del RM inicial) y percepción de estrés 10 (PSS-10). Se les realizó una extracción de sangre para análisis de cortisol y otros biomarcadores de estrés así como toma de tensión arterial al salir de guardia (antes de las 10 de la mañana). Resultados: La prevalencia de percepción de estrés medida por PSS-10 fue de 94,68% en los 94 MIR reclutados. La mayor percepción de estrés se relacionó con el número de guardias (OR 3,359, IC 95% 1,208-10,189, p=0,0207) y la ansiedad/depresión en el momento actual (OR 1,447, IC 95% 0,623-2,270, p=0.0007), aunque no con la ansiedad/depresión al inicio de su contratación. Conclusiones: Los MIR que realizaban guardias de Urgencias presentaron un alto nivel de percepción de estrés en nuestro estudio. No se encontró una asociación entre percepción de estrés y  los biomarcadores de estrés considerados. Se proponen medidas preventivas de formación en manejo de situaciones conflictivas para los MIR al inicio de su programa de especialidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;23(1): 238-245, mar. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrés percibido por médicos residentes que realizan guardias de urgencia en dos hospitales de Madrid y determinación de biomarcadores de estrés</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16370</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8671^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
