<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045167</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Monitorins of vancomycin plasma levels in patients undergoing hemodialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to confirm whetherpatients undergoing dialysis and treated with vancomycin 1g/week or 500 mg/48 hours reach optimum plasma levels (10-25 mcg/ml).Method: Thirty two patients were included with a total numberof 34 infectious events. The most commonly used dose was 1g/week (67.6% of infectious events), versus 500 mg/48 hours(32.4%). Low ultrafiltration membranes were used more frequently(64.7%) than high ultrafiltration membranes (35.3%).Vancomycin was infused over an one-hour period during thelast hour of the hemodialysis session and plasma samples weredrawn prior to the beginning of the session. Samples were analyzedusing fluorescent polarization immunoassays.Results: Mean concentration results for the total populationdid not reach optimum values (10-25 mg/ml). In the group receiving500 mg/48 hours, optimum mean values were not reachedin any of the determinations, whereas in the group receiving 1g/week, optimum values were reached in the fourth determination.Mean plasma levels of the antibiotic were bellow optimumvalues, regardless the type of membrane used, either low or highultrafiltration.Conclusions: Based on the above results, we recommendtitration of the vancomycin dose in this group of patients and theadministration of a loading dose of 20 mg/kg during the last hourof the hemodialysis session, followed by a maintenance dose of 7mg/kg after each session, as well as the monitoring of the druglevels in this group of patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Reyes, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franquelo, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, M . V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallego, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pizarro, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo del estudio es confirmar que los pacientesen hemodiálisis y en tratamiento con vancomicina, recibiendodosis de 1 g semanal o 500 mg/48 horas, alcanzan niveles plasmáticosóptimos (10-25 mcg/ml).Método: Se incluyeron 32 pacientes sobre un total de 34 episodiosde infección. La dosis más utilizada fue la de 1 g/semana(67,6% de los episodios de infección), frente a la de 500 mg/48horas (32,4%). Las membranas más frecuentemente empleadasfueron las de baja ultrafiltración (64,7%) frente a las de alta ultrafiltración(35,3%).La administración de vancomicina se realizó en infusión de unahora, durante la última hora de la sesión de hemodiálisis y lasmuestras plasmáticas se extrajeron antes del inicio de la sesión.Las muestras fueron analizadas por inmunoanálisis de polarizaciónde fluorescencia.Resultados: Los resultados de concentración promedio parala población total no alcanzaron en ningún momento los valoresóptimos (10-25 mg/ml). En el grupo que recibió 500 mg/48horas los valores promedio óptimos no se alcanzaron en ningunade las determinaciones y en el grupo de 1 g/semanal sólo sealcanzaron dichos valores en la cuarta determinación. Los nivelesplasmáticos promedio del antibiótico están por debajo de los valoresóptimos independientemente del tipo de membrana, baja oalta ultrafiltración, empleada.Conclusiones: A la vista de los resultados recomendamosmodificar las dosis de vancomicina en este grupo de pacientes yadministrar dosis de carga 20 mg/kg durante la última hora de lasesión de hemodiálisis y posteriormente dosis de mantenimientode 7 mg/kg después de cada sesión, así como monitorizar losniveles del fármaco en este grupo de pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;29(6): 354-358, nov.-dic. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045167</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización de las concentraciones plasmáticas de vancomicina en pacientes en hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23504^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28582^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23497^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
