<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107572</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk behaviors in patients with sleep apnea syndrome: explorative study in complex and dynamic situations of simulated traffic</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: A large consensus exists within the scientific community with regard to the existence of a high incidence of traffic accidents in people with Sleep Apnea Hypopnea Syndrome (SAHS). However, some aspects of this relationship are still in need of clarification. It has not been possible to show the likely cause of this large rate of accidents, there are possible uncontrolled, confounding factors, and some of the evaluation instruments used have low ecological validity. The goal of the study was to analyze risk behavior during driving in patients with SAS, in a virtual reality setting with simulated traffic. Material and methods: Evaluation of risk driving behavior was carried out using the Honda Riding Trainer simulator. The participants were 12 patients diagnosed with SAS, treated with  continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP), and 12 matched controls. Daytime somnolence, mental fatigue, and levels of activation during the tests, were also evaluated in both groups through the use of questionnaires. Results: Although patients with SAHS showed higher daytime somnolence, they did not exhibit more risk driving behaviors than the control group. There were no differences in mental fatigue  or levels of activation during the simulation. Conclusion: Unlike the results found in classical studies, when the evaluation is carried out with more ecological tools and the duration of the tests is much shorter, the performance of patients with SAS treated with CPAP does not differ from that of the control group. These findings  support the use of CPAP as well as the testing of drivers using virtual simulations in order to obtain a driver&#146;s license, especially in high risk populations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Di Stasi, L. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Piedra, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buela Casal, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Catena, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Existe un amplio consenso sobre la existencia de una mayor incidencia de accidentes de tráfico en personas con síndrome de apneas&amp;#8209;hipopneas del sueño (SAHS). Sin embargo, algunos aspectos de esta relación están aún por dilucidar. No se ha podido demostrar cuál es la causa probable de esta mayor accidentalidad, existen posibles factores de confusión no controlados  y algunos instrumentos de evaluación utilizados poseen una baja validez ecológica. El objetivo del estudio fue analizar la conducta de riesgo en conducción de pacientes con SAHS enun entorno vial virtual realista y con tráfico simulado. Material y métodos: Se evaluó la conducta de riesgo en la conducción mediante el simulador  Honda Riding Trainer, en 12 pacientes diagnosticados de SAHS, tratados con presión positiva  continua (CPAP), y 12 controles emparejados. También se evaluaron, a través de cuestionarios, la somnolencia diurna en los dos grupos y la fatiga mental y los niveles de activación durante la prueba. Resultados: Aunque los pacientes con SAHS mostraban una mayor somnolencia diurna, no se han mostrado más arriesgados que los controles durante la conducción. No hubo diferencias en fatiga mental o niveles de activación durante la simulación. Conclusiones: A diferencia de los resultados encontrados en los estudios clásicos, cuando la  evaluación se realiza con herramientas más ecológicas y la duración de las pruebas es más breve, la ejecución de los pacientes con SAHS tratados con CPAP no difiere de la de los controles. Estos hallazgos apoyan el uso de la CPAP y respaldan la inclusión de pruebas de simulación virtuales para obtener o prorrogar el permiso o licencia de conducir, sobre todo, en poblaciones de riesgo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;15(3): 78-84, jul.-sept. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107572</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conductas de riesgo en pacientes con síndrome de apneas¿hipopneas del sueño: estudio exploratorio en situaciones complejas y dinámicas de tráfico simulado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7148^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34202^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19132^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12721</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23893</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
