<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83210</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral anticoagulant treatment: initiation, adjustment and use precautions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The drugs with oral anticoagulant activity which up to today are approved aredrugs that require special handling due to their characteristics pharmacokineticsand pharmacodynamics. They correspond to the dicoumarin group, whosemechanism of action is interfering with the metabolism of vitamin K-dependentfactors. There are experts groups&#146; guidelines with the objective of providingstandards to improve safety of this treatment given the difficulties inherent inits characteristics. The future expects to be promising waiting for new antithrombotic,some of them already approved for other indications, with a betterpharmacological profile different to dicoumarin drugs, especially because theydon&#146;t require follow-up analytical controls and the practical absence of druginteractions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrasco Expósito, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los fármacos con actividad anticoagulante oral aprobados hasta el día de hoyprecisan de un especial manejo por sus características farmacocinéticas y farmacodinámicas.Corresponden al grupo de los dicumarínicos, cuyo mecanismode acción resulta de la interferencia en el metabolismo de los factores vitaminaK-dependientes. Existen guías de grupos de expertos con el objetivode facilitar unas normas para mejorar la seguridad de este tratamiento, dadaslas dificultades inherentes a sus características. El futuro se espera prometedorcon nuevos antitrombóticos, algunos de ellos ya aprobados para otras indicaciones,con un mejor perfil farmacológico que los diferencia de los dicumarínicos,especialmente porque no precisan controles analíticos y por la prácticaausencia de interacciones farmacológicas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(1): 17-20, ene.-feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83210</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con anticoagulantes orales: inicio, ajuste y precauciones en su utilización</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14308^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15261^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1752^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
