<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61843</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mental illness and road safety</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Psychiatric disorders, either due to their psychopathology or the drug treatments required, may lead to changes in perception, information processing and integration, and psychomotor activity which may disturb and/or interfere with the ability to drive safely. Method. This study assesses competence to drive in a sample of psychiatric outpatients, with a driver's license, who drove regularly. This ability was assessed with the accredited LNDETER 100 battery, an electronic assessment unit measurement, in different clinical situations. Results. Only 24 of the 120 patients passed the four tests required to obtain or renew a driver's license, and 80% failed in at least one of the required tests. None of the patients studied had notified the traffic authorities or the examination centers that they had a psychiatric condition that could affect safe driving. No patient stopped driving, although 10% of them admitted that their ability to drive was somewhat deteriorated. Conclusions. Psychiatric patients with altered psychomotor performance should be a concern for psychiatrists and general practitioners regarding their competence to drive vehicles. Clinical, ethical and legal aspects of our findings are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Castresana, C. de las</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Álvarez, E. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los trastornos psiquiátricos, bien por su psicopatología o por los tratamientos farmacológicos que precisan, pueden producir cambios en la percepción, en el procesamiento e integración de la información y en la actividad psicomotora que pueden alterar y/o interferir con la capacidad para una conducción segura. Método. El presente estudio valora la competencia para la conducción de vehículos de una muestra de pacientes psiquiátricos ambulatorios, con licencia de conducir y que conducen asiduamente, que cumplimentaron la batería psicotécnica computarizada homologada LNDETER 100 en diferentes situaciones clínicas. Resultados. De los 120 pacientes estudiados, únicamente 24 superaron las cuatro pruebas requeridas para la concesión o renovación del permiso de conducción, mientras que el 80% fracasó en al menos una de las pruebas exigidas. Ninguno de los participantes en el estudio declaró su enfermedad o su tratamiento a las autoridades de tráfico, ni a los centros de reconocimiento existentes. Ningún paciente dejó de conducir, aunque un 10% de ellos consideró que su capacidad estaba en algún modo deteriorada. Conclusiones. Los pacientes psiquiátricos con un funcionamiento psicomotor alterado deben ser una preocupación para los psiquiatras y médicos generales en precisión de su competencia para la conducción de vehículos. Se discuten las consideraciones clínicas, éticas y legales de los hallazgos del estudio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;37(2): 75-81, mar.-abr. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad mental y seguridad vial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12034^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1339^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14111</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1340^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35475</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
