<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140042</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comanagement with Internal Medicine in a Gynecology Department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. There has been an increase in the age and complexity of patients hospitalized in gynecology departments, which has affected the work of gynecologists. We studied the effect of comanagement (CM) with Internal Medicine (IM) on hospital stay among gynecology inpatients. Material and methods. We compared patients aged &amp;#8805; 14 years old discharged from the gynecology department in 2013 who underwent CM with IM with patients who did not undergo CM and who were discharged in 2012. We analyzed age, emergency admission, surgery yes/no, administrative weight, number of diagnoses, the Charlson comorbidity index (CCI), hospital stay, fallecimiento, and readmissions. Results. In 2013, we observed increases of 20.6% in the number of diagnoses and of 46.2% in the CCI. The adjusted length of stay was reduced by 0.5 days (95% CI 0.2 to 0.7; p &lt; 0.001). Conclusions. CM with IM is associated with a decrease in length of stay in gynecology, in line with that observed in other surgical departments (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rebollar Merino, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agudo Alonso, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Ruiz, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Castro, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbero Allende, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Las pacientes hospitalizadas en Ginecología están aumentando su edad y complejidad, dificultando la labor de los ginecólogos. Estudiamos el efecto de la asistencia compartida (AC) con Medicina Interna (MI) sobre la estancia hospitalaria de las enfermas ingresadas en Ginecología. Material y método. Comparamos las pacientes &amp;#8805; 14 años dadas de alta de Ginecología en 2013, con AC con MI, con las del 2012, sin AC. Analizamos edad, ingreso urgente, cirugía sí/no, peso administrativo, número total de diagnósticos, índice de comorbilidad de Charlson (ICh), estancia hospitalaria, fallecimiento y reingresos. Resultados. En el año 2013 observamos incrementos del 20,6% en el número de diagnósticos y del 46,2% en el ICh. La estancia media ajustada se redujo en 0,5 días (IC 95% 0,2 a 0,7; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones. La AC con MI se asocia a una disminución de la estancia media en Ginecología, en línea con lo observado en otros servicios quirúrgicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);58(7): 307-310, ago.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140042</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asistencia compartida (comanagement) con Medicina Interna en el Servicio de Ginecología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7553^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16765</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10553^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10553^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
