<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147154</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-2597</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Developmental coordination disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Over several years, many children without severe neurological comorbidity having suboptimal motor development or motor difficulties in specific areas such as visomotor coordination or balance were labels as 'clumsy,' with 'dyspraxia' or 'minor motor disorders.' In 1994, this type of disorder was unified under the term 'developmental coordination disorder.' However, it continues to be a little known condition and is often underdiagnosed. It is estimated that 5-8% of school age children could have developmental coordination disorder, with a greater predominance in the male gender. This risk is significantly greater in premature children, even in those without apparent neurological sequels. The clinical manifestations are determined by the combination of an alteration in propioception, motor programming and sequential motor activity. This entails difficulties in different motor areas that affect the daily life activities, academic performance and self esteem. There are specific diagnostic tools for their detection. The clinical course without specific treatment generally leads to the chronification of the motor disabilities, so that the early diagnosis and treatment is of special importance in these children (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paz Fernández, JA de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Conde Guzón, PA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mata Zubillaga, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regueras Santos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante varios años, muchos niños sin comorbilidad neurológica grave que presentaban un desarrollo motor subóptimo o con dificultades motrices en áreas específicas como la coordinación visomotora o el equilibrio eran etiquetados como 'torpes', con 'dispraxia' o 'trastornos motores menores'. En 1994, este tipo de trastornos se unificaron bajo el término único de 'trastorno del desarrollo de la coordinación'; sin embargo, actualmente sigue constituyendo una patología poco conocida y a menudo infradiagnosticada. Se estima que entre un 5-8% de niños en la etapa escolar podrían tener trastorno del desarrollo de la coordinación, con un mayor predominio en el sexo masculino. Este riesgo es significativamente superior en los niños prematuros, incluso en aquellos sin secuelas neurológicas aparentes. Las manifestaciones clínicas vienen determinadas por la combinación de una alteración en la propiocepción, la programación motora y la actividad motora secuencial, lo que conlleva dificultades en diferentes áreas motrices, que repercuten en las actividades de la vida diaria, el rendimiento académico y la autoestima. Existen herramientas diagnósticas específicas para su detección. La evolución clínica sin tratamiento específico suele ser la cronificación de las disabilidades motrices, por lo que el diagnóstico y el tratamiento precoz resultan de especial interés en estos niños (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Bol. pediatr;55(234): 247-253, abr. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147154</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastorno del desarrollo de la coordinación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7410^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34332^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12033^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33528^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
