<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144063</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of tibolone on dendritic spine density in the rat hippocampus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Oestrogen deficiency produces oxidative stress (OS) and changes in hippocampal neurons and also reduces the density of dendritic spines (DS). These alterations affect the plastic response of the hippocampus. Oestrogen replacement therapy reverses these effects, but it remains to be seen whether the same changes are produced by tibolone (TB). The aim of this study was to test the neuroprotective effects of long-term oral TB treatment and its ability to reverse DS pruning in pyramidal neurons (PN) of hippocampal area CA1. Methods: Young Sprague Dawley rats were distributed in 3 groups: a control group in proestrus (Pro) and two ovariectomised groups (Ovx), of which one was provided with a daily TB dose (1 mg/kg), OvxTB and the other with vehicle (OvxV), for 40 days in both cases. We analysed lipid peroxidation and DS density in 3 segments of apical dendrites from PNs in hippocampal area CA1. Results: TB did not reduce lipid peroxidation but it did reverse the spine pruning in CA1 pyramidal neurons of the hippocampus which had been caused by ovariectomy. Conclusions: Oestrogen replacement therapy for ovariectomy-induced oestrogen deficiency has a protective effect on synaptic plasticity in the hippocampus (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar Zavala, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán-Campos, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padilla-Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ríos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Cintra, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El hipoestrogenismo produce estrés oxidativo (EO) y cambios en las neuronas del hipocampo (H) y reduce la densidad de las espinas dendríticas (ED). Estas alteraciones repercuten en la respuesta plástica del H. La terapia de sustitución intraperitoneal con estrógenos revierte estos efectos, pero no se sabe si ocurre lo mismo con la tibolona (TB). El objetivo fue comprobar los efectos neuroprotectivos de la TB administrada por vía oral a largo plazo y su capacidad para revertir la poda de ED de las neuronas piramidales (NP) del CA1 del H. Métodos: Ratas Sprague Dawley jóvenes: distribuidas en 3 grupos: control en proestro (Pro) y 2 grupos ovariectomizados (Ovx), uno suplementado con dosis diaria de TB (1 mg/kg), OvxTB, y otro con vehículo (OvxV), por 40 días. Se analizaron la peroxidación de lípidos y la densidad de las ED en 3 segmentos de la dendrita apical de las NP del CA1 del H. Resultados: La TB no redujo la peroxidación de lípidos en el H, pero recuperó la poda de espinas en las NP del CA1 del H, producida por la ovariectomía. Conclusiones: La terapia de sustitución estrogénica en el hipoestrogenismo por ovariectomía tiene un efecto protector (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;30(7): 401-406, sept. 2015. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la tibolona en la densidad de las espinas dendríticas en el hipocampo de la rata</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38425^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23743^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53420^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23534</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d843</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28573</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6783^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5059^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
