<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100627</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-5967</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychoanalysts´ interventions in child psychoanalysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The different manners of intervention which the psychoanalist may use when working with children are discussed throughout this paper, under the premise that we are dealing with a subjet in the process of structuration. The different languages children use are described as well as the different complaints the parents make when seeking professional advice and the ways in which psychoanalytical work with children and their parents can take place. A line is drawn between interpretations a d structuring interventions(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Janin, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">A lo largo de este artículo se desarrollan las diferentes modalidades de intervención del psicoanalista en el trabajo con niños partiendo de la premisa de que se opera sobre un sujeto en estructuración. Se describen los diferentes lenguajes que los niños emplean y se exponen tanto las diversas formas que toma la consulta como los modos del trabajo psicoanalítico con los niños y sus padres. Se hace una distinción entre interpretaciones e intervenciones estructurantes(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psiquiatr. psicoter. niño adolesc;(53): 49-56, ene.-jun. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100627</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las intervenciones del psicoanalista en psicoanálisis con niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2698^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201200</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
