<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167074</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of a new Practicum model. Challenge and opportunity to form in advanced roles in the Nursing Degree</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of the Nursing Education is to train nurses with skills, attitudes, aptitudes and knowledge to enable them to develop their function in an efficient manner. An increasing demand of nurses more competent to a data-management system, to use new technologies and application of complex interventions on different places of nursing care, is requested. To respond to this demand, the Escuela Superior de Ciencias de la Salud Tecnocampus (ESCST), has been emphasized for an advanced and integrative Practicum Model in accordance with the theoretical and practical training, that it enables students to have an holistic view. Not just of specific pathologies, but also the assistance processes by means of form of itinerary. The work that is presented has the aim to make know this model and which are evaluation tools that are used during the development for the assessment of student's practical training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Raya, Lorena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosell, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chabrera, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Ruiz, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de la educación en Enfermería es formar profesionales con actitudes, habilidades y conocimientos necesarios para llevar a cabo sus funciones de manera eficiente. Cada vez hay mayor demanda de profesionales de enfermería más competentes para el manejo de información, uso de nuevas tecnologías y aplicación de intervenciones complejas en el cuidado de las personas en diferentes entornos de cuidado. Para dar respuesta a esta demanda, desde la Escuela Superior de Ciencias de la Salud Tecnocampus, se apuesta por modelo de Practicum avanzado más integrador y acorde a la formación teórica y práctica, que permita al estudiante una visión holística, ya no tanto de las patologías concretas, sino de los procesos asistenciales en forma de itinerarios. El trabajo que aquí se presenta tiene el objetivo de dar a conocer este modelo y las herramientas evaluadoras del estudiante utilizadas durante el mismo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;26(1/2): 91-95, ene.-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167074</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo de un nuevo modelo de Practicum. Reto y oportunidad de formar en roles avanzados en el Grado de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30653</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53787^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
