<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79519</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract: Out-patient intensive treatment programme for children and adolescents with severs mental disorders. This paper exposes the functioning of the treatment programme for children and adolescents with severe mental pathology, which started at Gijon (Spain) three years ago. It describes the organization of the team, the internal functioning and the work done with children, families and related health and educational services. The authors describe in detail each of the steps of attendance, process and also share some of the experiences and conclusions they arrived to (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Pascual, Henar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales Herrera, Carmen de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedreira, Josué</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hacemos una exposición del  funcionamiento del programa de tratamiento intensivo que se puso en marcha en Gijón hace 3 años, para niños y adolescentes con trastornos mental grave. Hablamos sobre la organización del equipo, el funcionamiento interno y el trabajo que realizamos con los niños, los padres, y los dispositivos sanitarios y educativos implicados. Describimos cada uno de los pasos de la atención recibida en nuestro programa .Compartimos algunas de las experiencias y conclusiones a las que vamos llegando (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(12): 71-78, nov. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79519</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa ambulatorio del tratamiento intensive para niños y adolescents con trastornos mental grave</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d300</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
