<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057484</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Synovial sarcoma of the mandible. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Synovial sarcoma is an unusual soft tissue        tumour of the head and neck. It is extremely rare on the mandible.        Case presentation: We present here a case of a 74        year-old man previously diagnosed and treated of jaw osteosarcoma.        Five years later the patient showed a neoplasm        recurrence on the remaining mandibular condyloid, extending        to the temporal bone. The diagnosis with light microscopy,        immunohistochemical staining, and ultrastructure was        monophasic synovial sarcoma. The characteristic chromosomal        translocation t(x;18) was founded on the cytogenetic        study, confirming the diagnosis of local recurrence of synovial        sarcoma. The previous biopsy was misdiagnosed. Conclusions:        The monophasic synovial sarcoma needs a differential        diagnosis with other neoplasms. More than 50% of        the cases shows recurrence and have a high rate of distant        metastases. Adequate tissue sampling, immunohistochemical,        ultraestructural and characteristic chromosomal translocation        findings are necessary for diagnosis</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Ruiz, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álava, Enrique de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-González, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enguita, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballestín, Claudio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meizoso, Telma</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El sarcoma sinovial es un tumor de partes        blandas poco frecuente en cabeza y cuello y excepcional        en la mandíbula. Presentación del caso: Presentamos un        caso de un paciente de 74 años previamente diagnosticado y        tratado de osteosarcoma mandibular, que muestra una tumoración        en el remanente mandibular con extensión infratemporal.        El diagnóstico con microscopía óptica, técnicas        inmunohistoquímicas y ultraestructura fue de sarcoma sinovial        monofásico. Se realizó estudio genético para la traslocación        t (x;18) que resultó positiva, confirmándose el diagnóstico        de recidiva local por sarcoma sinovial. La biopsia        previa estaba erróneamente diagnosticada. Conclusiones:        El sarcoma sinovial monofásico requiere diagnóstico diferencial        con otras entidades. Es una tumoración que recidiva        en más de la mitad de los casos y presenta un riesgo elevado        de metástasis. Su diagnóstico exacto necesita un buen        procesamiento tisular, técnicas inmunohistoquímicas,        ultraestructurales y estudio genético</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;40(3): 188-191, jul.-sep.2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057484</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sarcoma sinovial intramandibular. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31919^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
