<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046078</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Volume determinations of the whole prostate and of the adenoma by transrectal ultrasound: correlation with surgical specimen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: We evaluated whether preoperative transrecta ultrasound (TRUS) mesaurements of the transition zone (TZ) and        total prostate volumen predict real prostatic weight.        Material y Methods: We compare estimated TRUS volumes with surgical specimen weight, in surgically treated patients with        localized prostate cancer (group A, n=33) or benign prostatic hyperplasia (group B, n=37).        The volume was calculated by the ellipsoid formula. Both measurements were compared with surgical specimen weight, assuming        1 as specific prostate weight.        Results: Group A: mean prostate measured volume was 38,6 cc. (SD 22,7), mean RP specimen weight was 54,2 g (SD 27,2)        (p=0,001). Total estimated prostate volume underestimated prostatectomy specimen weight by 29%. In order to adequate the estimated        volume to the specimen weight, we calculated the formula: estimated prostate weight=0,95 x prostatic measured volume        + 17,657 (p=0,005).        Group B: mean TZ measured volume was 62,8 cc. (SD 23,3), mean adenomectomy specimen weight was 79,9 g (SD 45,9)        (p=0,001). TZ estimated volume underestimated adenomectomy specimen weight by 21%. In order to adequate the estimated        volume to the specimen weight, we calculated the formula: estimated TZ weight=1,67 x TZ measured volume - 24,768 (p=0,04).        Conclusions: We found significative differences between TRUS measured volumes and real weight of surgical specimen. These        differences could be corrected by simple formulas that allow to minimize the observed underestimations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabello Benavente, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jara Rascón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz Amo, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monzó, J. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Subirá Ríos, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lledó García, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Díez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la fiabilidad de la ecografía transrectal (ECOTR) en la medición del volumen prostático total y de la zona        transicional (ZT) y buscar coeficientes de correlación capaces de mejorar la equiparación entre ambas medidas y el peso real prostático.        Material y Métodos: Comparamos los volúmenes estimados mediante ECOTR con el peso de la pieza quirúrgica en pacientes        con cáncer prostático localizado (grupo A, n=33) o HBP (grupo B, n= 37) sometidos a cirugía. El volumen se calculó mediante la        fórmula del elipsoide. Ambas medidas se comparan con el peso de la pieza quirúrgica, asumiendo el peso específico próstatico        igual a 1.        Resultados: Grupo A: volumen prostático medio medido fue 38,6 cc. (DE 22,7), peso medio de la pieza de PR fue 54,2 g (DE        27,2) (p=0,001). El volumen prostático total estimado infravaloró el peso de la pieza de prostatectomía un 29%. Calculamos la        fórmula para adecuar el volumen medido al peso real: peso estimado=0,95 x volumen medido prostático + 17,657 (p=0,005).        Grupo B: volumen medio de ZT medido fue 62,8 cc (DE 23,3), peso medio de la pieza de adenomectomía fue 79,9 g (DE 45,9)        (p=0,001). El volumen estimado del adenoma infravalora el peso de la pieza de adenomectomía un 21%. Calculamos la fórmula        para adecuar el volumen medido al peso del adenoma: peso estimado=1,67 x volumen medido ZT - 24,768 (p=0,04).        Conclusión: Encontramos diferencias significativas entre los volúmenes medidos por ECOTR y el peso real de la pieza quirúrgica.        Estas diferencias pueden ser corregidas utilizando unas sencillas fórmulas, que permiten minimizar las infraestimaciones        observadas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(2): 175-180, feb. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046078</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Correlación ecográfico-anatómica de la medición del volumen prostático total y de la zona transicional mediante ecografía transrectal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37562^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11913^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11910^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
