<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74916</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malignant phyllodes tumor (cystosarcoma phyllodes) of the breast with lipoblastic differentiation. Radiographical and histological study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Malignant phyllodes tumour is anuncommon neoplasm in the breast. Liposarcomatous differentiationof the stromal component raises new differentialdiagnoses. Material and methods: We report a case ofmalignant phyllodes tumour of the breast with extensiveliposarcomatous differentiation. Results: We describe theimaging studies and histological features of the lesion anddiscuss the differential diagnosis. Conclusions: Extensivesampling, together with systematic study, is necessary for acorrect diagnosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nieto Parra, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Gomez, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Machín, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el tumor filodes maligno es una neoplasiamamaria infrecuente, poco específica en las pruebas deimagen. La diferenciación del componente estromal a liposarcomaplantea nuevos diagnósticos diferenciales. Materialy método: presentamos un caso de tumor filodesmaligno de mama con extensa diferenciación a liposarcomadel componente estromal. Resultados: describimos loshallazgos radiológicos, ecográficos e histológicos de lalesión comentando los diagnósticos diferenciales. Conclusiones:Sólo el muestreo y estudio sistemáticos conducirána un diagnóstico certero en este tipo de neoplasias heterogéneas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;42(3): 230-234, jul.-sept.2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74916</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor filodes maligno (cistosarcoma filodes) mamario con diferenciación lipoblástica. Estudio radiológico e histológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31056^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8254^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31817^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31817^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31056^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8254^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
