<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63175</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: 30-50% of pediatric patients with the diagnosis of lower urinary tract infection (UTI) have vesicoureteral reflux (VUR). The endoscopic treatment of VUR has become one of the main therapeutic tools and its success has been traditionally related to the grade of VUR. Nevertheless, in each of the VUR grades different grades of ureteral dilation may be observed. The aim of the study is to evaluate the influence of ureteral dilation rate in the cure rate after endoscopic treatment. Methods: From a total of 632 renal units with reflux treated endoscopically, we review the first four years (1996-1999). After discarding patients with secondary VUR (neurogenic bladder, ureteral duplication) 70 patients enter the study (a total of 105 renal units with reflux). Voiding cystourethrograms (VCUG) were evaluated by means of a double blind study, grading ureteral dilation of all patients in three grades: mild-normal, moderate and severe. We performed comparisons between the cure rates of first endoscopic injection in the three grades of ureteral dilation. Results: After the evaluation of VCUG in the double blind study, from 105 renal units with reflux in the study, three had grade I VUR, 12 grade II, 64 grade III, and 26 grade IV. After grading ureteral dilation there were 45 with mild-normal grade, 44 moderate and 16 severe. The comparison of cure rates for grade III and IV VUR without considering the grade of ureteral dilation did not show statistical significance. Nevertheless, we found statistically significant differences between the cure rates of each grade of ureteral dilation: when considering all renal units with reflux treated, considering all grade III and IV VUR, and considering only grade III reflux. Conclusions: The international classification of VUR as a prognostic factor for the success of endoscopic treatment does not considered differences between same degree refluxes. The results observed demonstrate that grade of ureteral dilation must be evaluated in conjunction with grade of reflux at the time of making prognosis about the success of endoscopic treatment of VUR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molina Vázquez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Somoza Argibay, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vela Nieto, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El 30-50% de lo pacientes pediátricos diagnosticados de infección del tracto urinario inferior (ITU) presenta Reflujo Vésicoureteral (RVU). El tratamiento endoscópico del RVU se ha convertido en una de sus principales armas terapéuticas y su éxito se ha relacionado tradicionalmente con el grado de RVU. Sin embargo en cada uno de los grados de RVU se pueden observar distintos grados de dilatación ureteral. En este estudio pretendemos estudiar la influencia del grado de dilatación ureteral en la curación endoscópica del RVU. Métodos: De un total de 632 unidades renales refluyentes (URR) tratadas endoscópicamente; realizamos una revisión de los primeros 4 años (1996-1999). Tras descartar los pacientes con RVU secundario (vejiga neurógena, duplicidad) entraron en el estudio 70 pacientes (un total de 105 URR). Mediante un estudio de doble ciego se valoraron las cistografías miccionales (CUMS), se graduó la dilatación ureteral de todos los pacientes en tres grados: leve-normal, moderada y severa. Realizamos diversas comparaciones entre los porcentajes de curación tras la 1ª inyección endoscópica en los tres grados de dilatación ureteral. Resultados: Tras la valoración de las CUMS mediante el estudio doble ciego; de las 105 URR estudiadas, 3 presentaban RVU de grado I, 12 de grado II, 64 de grado III y 26 de grado IV. Tras graduar la dilatación ureteral había 45 con grado leve-normal, 44 moderada y 16 severa. Al comparar los porcentajes de curación de los RVU de grado III con los de grado IV, sin considerar el grado de dilatación ureteral, no se encontró significación estadística. Sin embargo sí encontramos diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre los porcentajes de curación de cada uno de los grados de dilatación ureteral: al considerar todas las URR tratadas, al considerar únicamente los RVU de grado III y IV y al considerar sólo los reflujos de grado III. Conclusiones: La Clasificación Internacional del RVU como factor pronóstico del éxito del tratamiento endoscópico pasa por alto diferencias entre reflujos del mismo grado. Los resultados observados demuestran que el grado de dilatación ureteral debe ser valorado conjuntamente con el grado de reflujo a la hora de pronosticar el éxito del tratamiento endoscópico del RVU (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;61(2): 185-190, mar. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63175</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15123^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1775^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4149^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
