<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041197</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-3465</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Celiac disease in a patient with ataxia of unknown origin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Gluten sensitivity is a state of hightened inmunologicalresponsiveness triggered by the ingestion ofgluten in genetically susceptible individuals. This inmunologicaldisorder is expressed by the finding ofantitransglutaminase and antigliadin autoantibodies.Although neurological disorders, mainly ataxia, arecommon in this patients, only 16% of them havegastrointestinal symptoms. We report a case of a2year-old child with ataxia for the previous weeks.No neuroimaging, neurophysiological nomnetabolicaldisorders were found. Nevertheless antigliadinand antitransglutaminase autoantibodies were detectedand a gluten-free diet was introduced. ln thefollowing weeks was noticed a clinical improvementand the autoantibodies levels were lower</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Pardo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomo Atance, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polanco Allué, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Bermejo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Pascual, S. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camarero Salce, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La sensibilidad al gluten es un estado de hiperrespuestainmunológica desencadenada por la ingestade gluten en sujetos con predisposición genética.Esta alteración inmunológica viene expresadapor la determinación de anticuerpos antitransglutaminasay antigliadina. Aunque las alteraciones neurológicas,sobre todo la ataxia, son frecuentes enestos pacientes, sólo el 16% tienen síntomas digestivos.Se recoge el caso de una niña de dos añoscon ataxia desde las semanas previas. No se encontraronalteraciones en las pruebas de neuroimagen,ni en las neurofisiológicas ni en las metabólicas.Se encontraron autoanticuerpos antigliadina yantitransglutaminasa positivos y se inició una dietasin gluten. En las semanas posteriores se produjouna mejoría clínica y los niveles de autoanticuerposeran más bajos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediátrika (Madr.);25(6): 272-276, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041197</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad celíaca en paciente con ataxia de origen desconocido</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1267^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6044^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1329^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2481^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
