<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-107166</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Evaluation of results in psychosocial rehabilitation is difficult for several reasons: the procedure is done through different strategies and programs, working on many areas at the same time, the objectives are individualized, the course of the disease varies; and many variables affect the generalization and maintenance of results. However there is evidence that the psychosocial rehabilitation improves the psychosocial funcioning, integration into community resources, cognitive performance, selfesteem and quality of life of people with mental illness, as well as increasing adherence to mental health services and reduce the number of admissions in hospital and cost of care. Objective. T he aim is to assess if there are significant changes after a year of intervention in psychosocial rehabilitation with 74 people attending a Center for Psychosocial Rehabilitation, in variables such as symptoms, cognitive performance, social skills and attitudes toward the disease. Method. We compared the results after one year of intervention, through an assessment made at the beginning and repeated one year later. We focus on the intervention programs used. Results. Significant differences were observed in areas related to anxiety, depression, self esteem, general psychopathology, and expressive and conversational skills, problem-solving ability and some cognitive measures. No significant changes in attitudes towards illness, assertiveness skills, and psychotic symptoms. Conclusions. T he psychosocial rehabilitation produces benefits, which suggest the importance of implementing these interventions in the community. Research needs to identify which patients benefit from treatment and which components of the psychosocial rehabilitation are most effectives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil Sanz, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Modamio, M del M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrieta Rodríguez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bengoechea Seco, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La evaluación de resultados en rehabilitación psicosocial (RPS) se hace difícil por diversos motivos: la intervención se realiza mediante diferentes estrategias y programas; se trabaja sobre numerosas áreas al mismo tiempo; los objetivos se individualizan; las manifestaciones y evolución de la enfermedad varían; y numerosas variables repercuten en la generalización y mantenimiento de resultados. No obstante existe evidencia de que la RPS mejora el nivel de funcionamiento, la integración en recursos comunitarios, el rendimiento cognitivo, la autoestima y la calidad de vida de las personas con enfermedad mental, además de aumentar la adherencia a los servicios de salud mental y reducir el número de hospitalizaciones y coste de cuidado. Objetivo. Valorar si hay cambios significativos tras un año de intervención en RPS con 74 personas que acuden a un Centro de Rehabilitación Psicosocial, en variables como la sintomatología, el rendimiento cognitivo, las habilidades sociales y las actitudes hacia la enfermedad. Método. Se realiza una evaluación al inicio de la intervención y pasado un año, comparando resultados. Se señalan los programas de intervención utilizados. Resultados. Se observan diferencias significativas en las pruebas que valoran ansiedad, depresión, autoestima, psicopatología general, habilidades conversacionales y expresivas, capacidad de resolución de problemas y algunas medidas cognitivas. No se observan cambios en actitudes hacia la enfermedad, habilidades asertivas, y sintomatología positiva y negativa. Conclusiones. E l hecho de que la RPS produzca ganancias sobre el bienestar y funcionamiento del paciente justifica las intervenciones realizadas. Se evidencia la necesidad de identificar qué pacientes son los que más se benefician del tratamiento, hacer una valoración a más largo plazo, y estudiar cada una de las intervenciones por separado para ver qué componentes son los más efectivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(210): 329-340, oct.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-107166</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de resultados  tras un año de intervención en un CRPS</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3188^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32795^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
