<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105036</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fat grafting: variables that influence the viability of the adipocyte and mesenchimal stem cells</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Though adipose tissue grafts have been used for decades in last century, the technique has been considered as slightly usefull provided that the graft was tending to reabsorption. It was Coleman who introduced a system of a traumatic harvesting-processing-infiltration that increased the percentage of survival of the graft  obtaining positive similar results in its application  all over the world. Nonetheless, publication of unlike results in the literature regarding survival of the graft with different percentages of reabsorption and the discovery of stem cells in the adipose tissue, have led to the accomplishment of numerous research works directed to understanding the biology of the fat graft, the role of the stem cells in this process  and the influence that the different steps for transplantation have on the cellular viability. We present a review of the scientific literature about the theme to bring together the available information about these controversies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Benito Ruiz, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Si bien los injertos de tejido adiposo se han venido utilizando durante décadas a lo largo del siglo pasado, la técnica se venía considerando como poco útil dado que el injerto tendía a la reabsorción. Fue Coleman quien introdujo un sistema de obtención-procesamiento-infiltración a traumático que aumentó el porcentaje de supervivencia del injerto y la obtención de resultados positivos similares en su aplicación en todo el mundo. Aún así, la publicación de resultados dispares en la literatura respecto a la supervivencia del injerto, con diferentes porcentajes de reabsorción y el descubrimiento delas células madre en el tejido adiposo, han llevado a la realización de numerosos trabajos de investigación encaminados a comprender la biología del injerto de tejido adiposo, a estudiar el papel de las células madre en este proceso y la influencia que sobre la viabilidad celular tienen los distintos pasos a los que los cirujanos plásticos sometemos al tejido adiposo para su trasplante. Hemos hecho una revisión de la literatura científica al respecto para reunir la información disponible sobre estas controversias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;37(4): 311-318, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105036</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Injertos de tejido adiposo: variables que influyenen la viabilidad del adipocito y de las células madre mesenquimales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32332^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29995^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37572^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33583^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
