<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76415</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Parotidectomies in benign parotid tumours: "Sant Pau" surgical extension classification</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and goals: At present different options co-exist for treating a benign tumour of the parotid gland, which has led to some confusion about the extent of resection performed in each case. In an effort to improve this situation, we created a classification system to define the areas removed. We started using this classification in July, 2006, and this article reviews its applicability and usefulness. Methods: We analyzed 44 patients who underwent surgery for clinically benign tumours of the parotid gland in our department between July, 2006, and December, 2008. In all resections, our classification was applied, dividing the parotid gland into five areas: I (lateral superior), II (lateral inferior), III (deep superior), IV (deep inferior), V (accessory). Results: The classification was easily applied and has presented no practical problem in the 44 patients operated. When analyzing the areas excised in surgery, the most common surgery was lateral inferior partial parotidectomy (removal of area II) in 47% of the cases. Lateral parotidectomy (removal of areas I and II) was the next most frequent, with 14 cases (33%). The remaining 20% was distributed among the other options. Conclusions: Our classification system appears to be a simple and easy way to define the surgery performed in each case, which simplifies the description of the resection performed, even in unusual resections (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orús, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Jacinto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quer, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>León, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sañudo, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: En la actualidad coexisten diferentes opciones para tratar un tumor benigno de la glándula parótida, lo que ha llevado a una cierta confusión sobre la extensión de la resección que se realiza en cada caso. Para intentar mejorar dicha información, se creó en nuestro servicio un sistema de clasificación por áreas para definir la parte extirpada. Se empezó a utilizar en julio de 2006 y en este artículo se revisa su aplicabilidad y utilidad. Métodos: Se analizan 44 pacientes operados en nuestro servicio de tumores clínicamente benignos de la glándula parótida, en el periodo comprendido entre julio de 2006 y diciembre de 2008. A todas las resecciones se les aplicó el sistema de clasificación de nuestro centro, que divide la parótida en 5 áreas: I (lateral craneal), II (lateral caudal), III (profunda craneal), IV (profunda caudal), V (accesoria). Resultados: La clasificación ha sido de fácil aplicación y no ha presentado ningún problema práctico en los 44 pacientes operados. Al analizar las áreas resecadas en la cirugía, destaca el alto porcentaje (47%) de parotidectomías laterales parciales caudales (resección del área II). La parotidectomía lateral (resección áreas I&#150;II) ha sido la segunda en número con 14 casos (33%). El 20% restante se ha repartido entre las demás opciones. Conclusiones: El sistema de clasificación por áreas ha permitido definir con claridad la cirugía realizada en cada caso y ha permitido explicar de forma fácil la resección realizada, incluso en aquellos casos de resecciones poco habituales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;61(1): 1-5, ene.-feb. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Parotidectomías en tumores benignos: clasificación «Sant Pau» de la extensión de la resección</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3979</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d243^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22602^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31876^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10496^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
