<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136644</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The importance of an ophthalmologic examination in patients with juvenile idiopathic arthritis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Uveitis occurs within the first year of arthritis onset in 73% of patients with juvenile idiopathic arthritis (JIA) considered at risk. The intraocular inflammation is characterized by an insidious onset and a silent and chronic clinical course capable of producing significant visual loss due to complications such as: cataract formation, secondary glaucoma, maculopathy and optic neuropathy. The absence of initial signs and symptoms, along with a deficient ophthalmic monitoring produce a delay in diagnosis with serious consequences. It has been estimated that 47% of JIA patients at risk for developing uveitis are legally blind (20/200 or worse) at least in one eye at the time of their first visit to the ophthalmologist. To reduce ocular complications and improve their visual outcome, it is necessary that rheumatologists refer all patients recently diagnosed (within the first month) with JIA for an ophthalmic evaluation, and maintain periodical follow-up visits based on classification and risk category of the disease (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-García, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La uveítis ocurre dentro del primer año del inicio de la artritis en hasta el 73% de los pacientes con artritis idiopática juvenil (AIJ) considerados en riesgo. La inflamación intraocular se caracteriza por un inicio insidioso y un curso clínico silencioso y crónico, capaz de producir pérdida visual significativa debido a complicaciones como: formación de cataratas, glaucoma, maculopatía y neuropatía óptica. La ausencia de signos y síntomas oculares iniciales, aunado a una deficiente monitarización oftalmológica, producen un retraso diagnóstico de graves consecuencias. Se ha reportado ceguera legal (20/200 o peor) en al menos un ojo en hasta el 47% de aquellos pacientes en riesgo para desarrollar uveítis durante la primera visita oftalmológica. Para reducir las complicaciones oculares y mejorar el pronóstico visual, es necesario referir inmediatamente a pacientes recién diagnosticados con AIJ por el reumatólogo a evaluación oftalmológica y mantener visitas periódicas de seguimiento basadas en la clasificación y la categoría de riesgo de la enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);11(3): 133-138, mayo-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136644</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia de la evaluación oftalmológica en pacientes con artritis idiopática juvenil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28259^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1177^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20181^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
