<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044793</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-0599</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retinosis pigmentosa and psychosis: with regard to a clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The retinosis pigmentosa is a degenerative disease that affect the retina, producing a progressive reduction of the vision. There isn´t a principal aetiological theory, existing a hereditary important component. This disease relates to diverses systemics syndromes, being observed an association with psychosis. This association presents a greater prevalence to the observed in other medical entities, being able to come to 25% of the patients diagnosed of Usher´s syndrome (retinosis pigmentosa, deafness and mental retardation). The reasons of this greater prevalence are not definite, suggesting a major vulnerability towards the psychosis. In this work present a clinical case of a 20-year-old patient, diagnosed of retinosis pigmentaria, that develops a psychotic episode</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peddrós Roselló, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La retinosis pigmentaria es una enfermedad degenerativa que afecta a la retina, produciendo una progresiva reducción de la visión. No existe una teoría etiológica única, existiendo un componente hereditario importante. Esta enfermedad se relaciona con diversos síndromes sistémicos, observándose una asociación con la psicosis. Esta asociación presenta una prevalencia mauor a la observada en otras entidades médicas, pudiendo llegar al 25% de los pacientes diagnosticados de síndrome de Usher (retinosis pigmentaria, sordera y retraso mental). Las causas de esta mayor prevalencia no se encuentran definidas, sugiriendo una mayor vulnerabilidad hacia la psicosis. En este trabajo se presenta un caso clínico de un paciente de 20 años, diagnosticado de retinosis pigmentaria, que desarrolla un episodio psicótico</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psiquiatr;22(1): 32-34, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044793</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Retinosis pigmentaria y psicosis: a propósito de un caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27800^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27800^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37285^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37285^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37285^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27800^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37285^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27800^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
