<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048406</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Small cell neuroendocrine tumour of the bladder: with reference to a case and bibliographical revision</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The small cell neuroendocrine tumour is an infrecuent neoplasia, with    inmunohistochemistry being the key to diagnosis. We present a new case making reference to treatment    and its evolution there after.    Material and methods: The clinic, diagnosis and treatment of this tumour is described. Bibliographical    revision follours.    Conclusions: The neuroendocrine tumour of small cell is an infrecuent neoplasia, in which the    inmunohistochemistry study is key in the diagnosis. The differential diagnosis includes the high    degree diferentiation transitionals cells carcinoma and primary and secondary linfoma. The standard    treatment is based on chemotherapy plus surgery</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pujol Obis, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villar Sordo, V del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogueras Gimeno, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo López, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrón Penón, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lahoz Tornos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: El tumor neuroendocrino de célula pequeña es una neoplasia infrecuente,    siendo el estudio inmunohistoquímico clave en el diagnóstico. Aportamos un nuevo caso, hacemos    referencia al plan de tratamiento y evolución en los primeros meses tras el mismo.    Material y métodos: Se describe la clínica, diagnóstico y tratamiento de este tumor. Revisión bibliográfica.    Conclusiones: El tumor neuroendocrino de célula pequeña es una neoplasia infrecuente, en la que    el estudio inmunohistoquímico es clave en el diagnóstico. El diagnóstico diferencial incluye el carcinoma    de células transicionales de alto grado y el linfoma primario y secundario. El tratamiento estándar    se basa en quimioterapia más cirugía</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(8): 835-838, sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048406</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor neuroendocrino vesical de célula pequeña: a propósito de un caso y revisión bibliográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2338^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2971^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2338^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23438^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29961^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32808^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7802^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28169^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8855^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15152^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5143^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
