<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86694</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infantile convulsions with mild gastroenteritis: epidemiological and clinical characteristics and outcome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To analyse the epidemiological, clinical and developmental characteristics of a group of children with seizures associated with mild gastroenteritis in order to facilitate the diagnostic suspicion of the condition in daily clinical practice. Patients and methods. We conducted a retrospective review of the medical records of 24 patients who were admitted to hospital between January 2001 and December 2008 because they presented seizures associated with mild gastroenteritis: epidemiological, clinical and developmental data were collected. Results. The mean age at diagnosis was 18.1 months. The female/male ratio was 2.8. The interval between the gastroenteritis  and the seizure was 3.8 days. The mean rectal temperature in the seizure was 37.1 °C. The mean number of seizures per hospitalisation was 2.2. Seizures were brief (90.6% &lt;= 5 min) and 96.8% of them were recorded as generalised. Rotavirus antigenemia in faeces was positive in 55.2% of cases. Lab findings, including the cerebrospinal fluid study, were normal. The electroencephalogram, in an immediate post-seizure situation, showed generalised and/or focal paroxysmal activity in four patients. The mean follow-up time was 4.2 years. The mean age of the group is currently 5.7 years, with normal development and level of schooling. Five patients (20.8%) had recurrences coinciding with new bouts of gastroenteritis. One patient, with a history of maternal epilepsy, was later diagnosed with focal epilepsy, and whether it  can be related with the earlier presentation of seizures associated with mild gastroenteritis or not is debatable. Conclusions. Seizures in children associated with mild gastroenteritis are a well-differentiated convulsive syndrome. Prognosis is excellent, but a relatively important percentage of cases tend to have recurrences if there is a new diarrhoeic process (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Durá Travé, Teodoro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souto Hernández, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molins Castiella, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera Albesa, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yoldi Petri, Mª Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar las características epidemiológicas, clínicas y evolutivas de un grupo de pacientes con convulsiones infantiles asociadas a gastroenteritis leve, para facilitar su sospecha diagnóstica en la práctica clínica diaria. Pacientes y métodos. Se han revisado retrospectivamente 24 historias clínicas de pacientes hospitalizados, entre enero de 2001 y diciembre de 2008, por presentar convulsiones asociadas a gastroenteritis leve: se recogieron datos epidemiológicos,  clínicos y evolutivos. Resultados. La edad media al diagnóstico era de 18,1 meses. La relación mujer/varón era de 2,8. El intervalo entre la gastroenteritis y la convulsión fue de 3,8 días. La temperatura media rectal en la crisis era de 37,1 °C. El número medio de convulsiones por hospitalización fue de 2,2. Las convulsiones eran breves (90,6% &lt;= 5 min) y el 96,8% de ellas se registraron como generalizadas. La antigenemia de rotavirus en heces fue positiva en el 55,2% de los casos. Los resultados  analíticos, incluido el estudio de líquido cefalorraquídeo, fueron normales. El electroencefalograma, en situación poscrítica inmediata, mostraba actividad paroxística generalizada y/o focal en cuatro pacientes. El tiempo medio de seguimiento ha sido de 4,2 años. Actualmente, la edad media del grupo es de 5,7 años, con un desarrollo y escolarización normales.  Cinco pacientes (20,8%) tuvieron recidivas coincidiendo con nueva gastroenteritis. Un paciente, con antecedentes de epilepsia materna, fue diagnosticado posteriormente de epilepsia focal, y es discutible su relación con la presentación anterior de convulsiones asociadas con gastroenteritis leve. Conclusiones. Las convulsiones infantiles asociadas a gastroenteritis leve constituyen un síndrome convulsivo bien diferenciado.  Su pronóstico es excelente, pero un porcentaje relativamente importante tiende a recidivar si presenta unnuevo proceso diarreico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;51(1): 12-18, jul. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86694</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Convulsiones infantiles asociadas a gastroenteritis leve: características epidemiológicas, clínicas y evolutivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31778^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13024^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13024^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
