<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-69855</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ectopic thyroid tissue is a rare abnormality caused by the failure of the thyroid gland to migrate from the foramen cecum to its final pretracheal position. The mostfrequent sites of ectopic thyroid tissue are lingual and sublingual. In most patients, the ectopic tissue is the only source of functioning thyroid. Ectopic thyroid maybe asymptomatic or may produce variable symptoms. We describe 2 cases of ectopic thyroid (sublingual and precricoidal). Both patients had hypothyroidism and localsymptoms. We review the clinical features, diagnosis and treatment of this entity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Elviro Peña, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Bolaños, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavón de Paz, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivar Roldán, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montoya Álvarez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tiroides ectópico es una alteración congénita infrecuente, consecuencia de la migración defectuosa del tiroides desde el agujero ciego (foramen caecum) hasta su posición final pretraqueal. La localización más frecuente del tejido tiroideo ectópico es lingual y sublingual. En la mayoría de los casos el único tejido tiroideo que queda suele ser ectópico. Puede serasintomático o con clínica variable. Presentamos 2 casos de tiroides ectópicos (sublingual y precricoideo). Los 2 casos asociaban hipofunción tiroidea y síntomas locales. Revisamos la clínica y el manejo diagnóstico y terapéutico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(9): 504-507, nov. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-69855</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14450^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3431^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
