<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126891</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical and therapeutic differences in neuro-ophthalmological involvement secondary to syphilis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. There are many forms of neuro-ophthalmological involvement secondary to syphilis, and not all of them are well known. Our aim is to determine the clinical and therapeutic differences in these patients. Case reports. Our sample included eight patients diagnosed with an ocular and neuro-ophthalmological disorder due to syphilis over the years 2012 and 2013. Five of them presented uveitis, pan-eveitis being the most frequent, with three cases. Two cases presented papilloedema and another displayed retrobulbar optic neuropathy. A total of 62.5% were diagnosed with neurosyphilis, the presence of which was related with compromise of the optic nerve (p = 0.035). None of them gave positive for VDRL in cerebrospinal fluid and they were diagnosed by the presence of FTA antibodies together with high protein levels in cerebrospinal fluid, lymphocytic pleocytosis or intrathecal synthesis of antibodies. In the absence of uveitis, diagnosis was delayed by a mean time of 2.6 months (p = 0.047). All the patients, except one who required a vitrectomy, progressed favourably with intravenous antibiotic therapy. Conclusions. In cases of neuro-ophthalmological compromise, whether inflammatory or non-inflammatory, the physician must bear syphilis in mind as a potential causation in order to avoid delays in the diagnosis, since early well-tailored treatment can prevent permanent loss of sight(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernando Quintana, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcia Alejos, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Burillo, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Martínez, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Pérez, Desiré</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rubio, Sebastián</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Existen múltiples formas de afectación neurooftalmológica secundaria a sífilis, no siempre bien conocidas. Nuestro objetivo es conocer las diferencias clínicas y de tratamiento en estos pacientes. Casos clínicos. Se incluyeron ocho pacientes diagnosticados de afectación ocular y neurooftalmológica por sífilis durante los años 2012 y 2013. Cinco presentaron uveítis, siendo la panuveítis la forma más frecuente, con tres casos. Dos casos presentaron papiledema, y otro, neuropatía óptica retrobulbar. Un 62,5% fue diagnosticado de neurosífilis, cuya presencia se relacionó con la afectación del nervio óptico (p = 0,035). Ninguno de ellos presentó positividad para VDRL en el líquido cefalorraquídeo, y se diagnosticaron por la presencia de anticuerpos FTA junto con hiperproteinorraquia, pleocitosis linfocitaria o síntesis intratecal de anticuerpos. En ausencia de uveítis, se produjo un retraso diagnóstico medio de 2,6 meses (p = 0,047). Todos los pacientes, salvo uno que precisó vitrectomía, evolucionaron favorablemente con antibioterapia intravenosa. Conclusiones. En casos de afectación neurooftalmológica, inflamatoria y no inflamatoria, el clínico debe tener en cuenta la sífilis como potencial etiología para evitar un retraso diagnóstico, puesto que un adecuado tratamiento precoz puede evitar una pérdida de visión permanente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;59(6): 264-268, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias clínicas y terapéuticas de la afectación neurooftalmológica secundaria a sífilis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5231^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27865^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27728^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9683^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2527^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
