<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79973</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Should epidural analgesia still be a routine technique in pain units?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Epidural analgesia has become a routine process in the peri-operative management of surgical patients which has been extended from the operating rooms and high dependency units to hospital wards. The irruption into this new scenario has improved post-surgical analgesia with acceptable safety margins, and has secured a predominant place in the analgesia guidelines of Acute Pain Units (APU). Epidural analgesia with local anaesthetics and opioids, compared to systemic with opioids, has historically been more effective, with a decrease in complications due to the reduction in surgical stress and the improved cardiorespiratory function. However, as well as these these advantages, epidural analgesia also has some disadvantages such as lowering of blood pressure or urinary retention, along with potentially serious ones arising from neurological damage caused by epidural haematoma, infection or direct injury of the nerve tissue. Although its advantages have been consistent and solid, it does seem to be the case today. The advances made in minimally invasive surgery, with earlier hospital discharge, together with multimodal strategies, are leading to the re-establishment of the use of techniques such as epidural and a re-evaluation of its indications. The latest evidence leads us to believe that epidural analgesia has reached its limit in the treatment of post-surgical pain and will begin to lose ground with the introduction of equally effective techniques, with less complications and secondary effects. This will be a slow process in which it must be assured that the alternative analgesics really give better results as regards efficacy, safety, tolerability and quality of recovery from the perspective of the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caba, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La analgesia epidural se ha convertido en una técnica rutinaria en el manejo perioperatorio de los pacientes quirúrgicos que se ha extendido fuera de los quirófanos y de las unidades de alta dependencia hacia las salas de hospitalización. La irrupción en este nuevo escenario ha mejorado la analgesia postoperatoria con aceptables márgenes de seguridad, lo que le ha servido para colocarse en un lugar predominante entre las pautas analgésicas de las Unidades de Dolor Agudo (UDA). La analgesia epidural con anestésicos locales y opioides frente a la sistémica con opioides ha presentado históricamente una superior eficacia analgésica, y una disminución de complicaciones derivadas de la atenuación del estrés quirúrgico y de la mejora en la función cardiorrespiratoria. Sin embargo, frente a estas ventajas la analgesia epidural también presenta inconvenientes como la hipotensión arterial o la retención urinaria, junto a las potencialmente graves derivadas del daño neurológico ocasionado por un hematoma epidural, una infección o una lesión directa del tejido nervioso. Si sus ventajas han resultado consistentes y fundamentadas, en este momento no lo parecen tanto. El avance que ha supuesto la cirugía mínimamente invasiva con altas más precoces, junto al desarrollo de estrategias multimodales, está conduciendo a un replanteamiento de la utilización de técnicas como la epidural y a una reevaluación de sus indicaciones. Las últimas evidencias nos inducen a pensar que la epidural probablemente haya tocado techo en el tratamiento del dolor postoperatorio y comenzará a perder terreno frente a otras técnicas igualmente efectivas, con menores complicaciones y efectos secundarios. Este será un proceso lento en el que deberá quedar asegurado que las alternativas analgésicas ofrecen realmente mejores resultados en cuanto a eficacia, seguridad, tolerabilidad y calidad de la recuperación desde la perspectiva del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;17(4): 206-212, mayo 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Se debe mantener la analgesia epidural como técnica de base en la UDA?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d778^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19211^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
