<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053549</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Overweight and obesity in female cleaning and office staff in Vizcaya (Basque Country)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Data on height and weight, using a standardized approach, were obtained from the medical examinations performed        among female cleaning (n=512) and office workers (n=249) employed by municipal governments in Vizcaya (Basque Country).        Weight tended to remain within the normal range until 47 years of age; thereafter, the prevalence of being overweight        and obese women increased. In general, the prevalences of being overweight, and obesity were higher among cleaners, who        also showed a quicker onset of weight imbalance with respect to office workers. The risk of being, overweight and obese        increased with age, and was statistically significant in the 41-46 year age group (overweight: odds ratio, [OR]=2.39; 95%        confidence interval, [95% CI]=1.10-5.21; obesity: OR=3.04; 95%CI=1.10-8.44). Afterwards, the risk decreased, mainly for        obesity (OR=0.70; CI95%:0.33-1.49). This decreased risk among cleaners 47 years of age or older could be explained by        early resignation from the workplace of obese cleaning workers</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prado Méndez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aurrekoetxea, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Durante los reconocimientos médicos laborales de 2003 se midió el peso y la talla en una muestra de 512 limpiadoras y        249 administrativas de ayuntamientos de Bizkaia utilizando balanza electrónica y estadiómetro estandarizados y calibrados.        En las administrativas se observa peso adecuado hasta los 47 años, aumentando posteriormente la prevalencia de sobrepeso        y obesidad. En general, las limpiadoras presentan mayor prevalencia de sobrepeso y obesidad y desequilibrio ponderal más        rápido y progresivo que las administrativas. Esta diferencia es significativa en el intervalo de 41-46 años (sobrepeso: odds        ratio OR=2,39, intervalo de confianza 95%, IC95%1,10-5,21; obesidad: OR=3,04, IC95% 1,10-8,44). Sin embargo, a partir        de esta edad el riesgo se invierte, especialmente para obesidad (OR=0,70, IC95%:0,33-1,49). La disminución del riesgo en        limpiadoras mayores de 46 años podría explicarse por un abandono precoz del trabajo de las limpiadoras obesas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);10(2): 81-84, abr.-jun. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053549</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sobrepeso y obesidad en mujeres trabajadoras de la limpieza y administrativas de Bizkaia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6950^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
