<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048035</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endovascular repair of bilateral arteriovenous femoral fistula following catheterization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION. The increasing number of cardiac catheterizations for diagnosis and/or treatment of coronary disease has raised the incidence of vascular complications. This incidence is not high in case of postcatheterization arteriovenous fistulae (1%). CASE REPORT. A 64 year-old man with the following clinical backgrounds: cigarette-smoker, dyslipemia, arterial hypertension, chronic bronchopathy and chronic ischemic cardiopathy, underwent coronary revascularisation 18 years ago; two coronary stent grafts were placed one year ago. He was referred to our department because of sudden onset of short distance intermittent claudication immediately after a diagnostic cardiac catheterization. Arteriography showed a left external iliac artery short occlusion and a bilateral femoral arteriovenous fistula. The patient underwent repair of these lesions by using endovascular techniques without complications. CONCLUSIONS. There are three risk factors for the development of postcatheterization arteriovenous fistulae: those related to the patient, the procedure and the anticoagulation. In selected patients, endovascular repair is less aggressive than open surgery and offers excellent short- and medium-term results</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riera Del Moral, Luis Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáez Martín, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leblic Ramírez, Israel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Stefanov Kiuri, Stefan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garzón Moll, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Heredero, Álvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Nistal, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera de Cubas, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El aumento del número de cateterismos cardíacos para el diagnóstico y el tratamiento de la patología cardíaca se ha acompañado de un incremento en la incidencia de complicaciones vasculares. Las fístulas arteriovenosas tras cateterismo tienen una incidencia escasa (1%). Caso clínico. Varón de 64 años con antecedentes de tabaquismo, dislipemia, hipertensión arterial, broncopatía crónica y cardiopatía isquémica crónica que precisó revascularización quirúrgica hace 18 años y angioplastia con implantación de dos stents hace un año. Fue remitido a nuestro servicio por claudicación intermitente a cortas distancias en el miembro inferior izquierdo de aparición brusca tras realización de cateterismo de control. El estudio arteriográfico demostró la presencia de una oclusión segmentaria de la arteria ilíaca externa izquierda y sendas fístulas arteriovenosas en ambos sectores femorales. El paciente fue intervenido de dichos hallazgos mediante técnica endovascular sin complicaciones perioperatorias. Conclusiones. Se distinguen tres tipos de factores de riesgo en el desarrollo de las fístulas arteriovenosas tras cateterismo: relacionados con el paciente, con el procedimiento y la anticoagulación en relación con éste. La reparación endovascular supone un procedimiento menos agresivo que la cirugía convencional en pacientes seleccionados, que ofrece excelentes resultados a corto y medio plazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;58(4): 335-340, jul.-ago. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048035</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reparación endovascular de fístula arteriovenosa femoral bilateral tras cateterismo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15055^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30853^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23275^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
