<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87170</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Development of Lennox-Gastaut syndrome in adulthood</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Lennox-Gastaut syndrome (LGS) is an epileptic encephalopathy that starts in childhood and has an unknown pathophysiological mechanism. Studies on the progress of LGS reveal a poor prognosis. Patients and methods. A retrospective study of 1629 patients with epilepsy was conducted. Patients included in the study were those with an age of onset during childhood, tonic seizures and atypical absences (who might also suffer from other types of seizures); electroencephalogram (EEG) showing generalised slow spike-wave and generalised fast activity; mental  retardation and a follow-up time of at least 10 years. Results. The sample consisted of 12 patients, 9 of whom were males. Follow-up time: 20 years. Onset of seizures: 3 years. Cryptogenic LGS: 67%; symptomatic: 33%. Frequency of the seizures at onset: daily (83.3%) or weekly (16.7%). Types of seizures: tonic and atypical absences (100%); drop-attacks (83%); generalised tonic-clonic (75%); myoclonias (41.7%); partial (8.3%) and pseudo-epileptic (8.3%). EEG with slow background activity, generalised slow spike-wave and generalised fast activity: 100%. Fifty percent of the patients had at least one epileptic status. They used an average of 7.5 different  antiepileptic drugs. At the end of the follow-up 33% were suffering from seizures on a daily basis; 17% were weekly and 42% monthly. A total of 8.3% were free from seizures. All of them were following combination therapy: 17% in bitherapy and 83% with an average of 3.8 drugs (range: 3-5). A total of 92% suffered from severe or very severe mental retardation. Fifty percent required neuroleptic drugs due to behavioural disorders. Conclusions. Despite the fact that the diagnosis of LGS is serious, we observed a decrease in the number of seizures after  several years of development, although the antiepileptic combination therapy remains constant. The mental retardation and behavioural disorders lead to a poor functional prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Rodríguez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón González, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Carriles, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Temprano Fernández, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salas Puig, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El síndrome de Lennox-Gastaut (SLG) es una encefalopatía epiléptica de inicio en la infancia con mecanismo fisiopatológico desconocido. Los estudios sobre la evolución del SLG demuestran un mal pronóstico. Pacientes y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de 1.629 pacientes con epilepsia. Se incluyó a los pacientes con edad de inicio en la infancia, crisis tónicas y ausencias atípicas (los cuales podían sufrir además otros tipos de crisis); electroencefalograma (EEG) con punta-onda lenta generalizada y actividad rápida generalizada; retraso mental y tiempo de seguimiento de al menos 10 años. Resultados. Muestra de 12 pacientes, 9 de ellos varones. Tiempo de seguimiento: 20 años. Inicio de las crisis: 3 años. SLG criptogénico: 67%; sintomático: 33%. Frecuencia de las crisis al inicio: diaria (83,3%) o semanal (16,7%). Tipos de crisis: tónicas y ausencias atípicas (100%); drop-attacks (83%); tonicoclónicas generalizadas (75%); mioclonías (41,7%); parciales (8,3%) y pseudoepilépticas (8,3%). EEG con actividad de fondo lenta, punta-onda lenta generalizada y actividad rápida  generalizada: 100%. El 50% de los pacientes tuvo al menos un estado epiléptico. Usaron una media de 7,5 antiepilépticos distintos. Al final del seguimiento sufrían crisis diarias el 33%; semanales, el 17%, y mensuales, el 42%. El 8,3% estaba libre de crisis. Todos seguían politerapia: el 17% biterapia y el 83% con un promedio de 3,8 fármacos (rango: 3-5). El 92% padecía un retraso mental grave o muy grave. El 50% precisó neurolépticos por trastorno del comportamiento. Conclusión. A pesar de que el pronóstico del SLG es grave, observamos una disminución en el número de crisis al cabo de unos años de evolución, si bien la politerapia antiepiléptica es una constante. El retraso mental y los trastornos del comportamiento  provocan un pronóstico funcional malo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;52(5): 257-263, mar. 2011. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87170</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del síndrome de Lennox-Gastaut en la edad adulta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d31669</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30326^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4736^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
