<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043311</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Variability in the management of acute myocardial infarction in the ARIAM registry in the year 2002</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. Analyze the differences in the management of acute myocardial infarction (AMI) between the different regional communities of the hospitals participating in the ARIAM registry during the year 2002. Design. Hospital based multicenter, national registry of patients admitted to cardiology intensive care units (CICU) due to suspicion of acute coronary syndrome. Scope. CICU of 80 Spanish hospitals in 14 regional communities. Patients or participants. All the patients from the ARIAM registry in the 2002 whose cause of hospitalization is AMI of less than 24 hours evolution are included. Interventions. None. Variables of principal interest. Demographic variable, background, symptoms, delays and site of initial action, use of diagnostic and therapeutic techniques, stay time and morbidity-mortality were recorded. The cases were grouped by geographic areas that correspond to the different regional communities of Spain. Differences were analyzed with the variation coefficient (VC).Results. A total of 6,820 patients were included. Basal characteristics were similar, except for the presence of diabetes as risk factor (VC: 21%). Excessive variation coefficients corresponded to way of access to health care system (061: 29%), site fibrinolysis was done (community: 155%, emergency service: 120%), fibrinolytic type (rTPA: 78%), interhospital delays (door-to-needle: 24% and door-to-balloon: 39%), use of primary percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty (PTCA) (122%), conduction of coronariography (75%) and treatment with anti-IIb/IIIa (34%). Global mortality in the CICU was 8.0%, with a 16% VC. Conclusions. There are differences in the management of AMI between the different regional communities studied, especially in that regarding prehospital care and the use of revascularization techniques. However, no significant differences are found in the study population regarding short term result</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Quintana, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colmenero Ruiz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez Parejo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina Toral, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo de Hoyos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Bueno, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alcántara, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Bailén, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar las diferencias en el manejo del infarto agudo de miocardio (IAM) entre las distintas comunidades autónomas de los hospitales participantes en el registro ARIAM durante el año 2002. Diseño. Registro multicéntrico nacional de base hospitalaria de pacientes ingresados en Unidades de Cuidados Intensivos Cardiológicos (UCIC) por sospecha de síndrome coronario agudo. Ámbito. UCIC de 80 hospitales españoles de 14 comunidades autónomas. Pacientes o participantes. Se incluyen todos los pacientes del registro ARIAM del año 2002 cuyo motivo de ingreso hospitalario es IAM de menos de 24 horas de evolución. Intervenciones. Ninguna Variables de interés principales. Se registraron variables demográficas, antecedentes, clínicas, retrasos y lugar de actuación inicial, uso de técnicas diagnósticas y terapéuticas, tiempos de estancia y morbimortalidad. Se agruparon los casos por áreas geográficas que corresponden a las diferentes comunidades autónomas de España. Se analizaron las diferencias mediante el uso del coeficiente de variación (CV). Resultados. Se incluyeron 6.820 pacientes. Las características basales fueron similares, salvo para la presencia de diabetes como factor de riesgo (CV: 21%). Los CV excesivos correspondieron al modo de acceso al sistema sanitario (061: 29%), lugar de realización de la fibrinolisis (extrahospitalaria: 155%, urgencias: 120%), tipo de fibrinolítico (rTPA: 78%), retrasos intrahospitalarios (puerta-aguja: 24% y puerta-balón: 39%), uso de angioplastia coronaria transluminal percutánea (ACTP) primaria (122%), realización de coronariografía (75%) y tratamiento con anti-IIb/IIIa (34%). La mortalidad en UCIC global fue del 8,0%, con un CV de 16%. Conclusiones. Existen diferencias en el manejo del IAM entre las distintas comunidades autónomas estudiadas, especialmente en lo concerniente a la atención prehospitalaria y el uso de las técnicas de revascularización. Sin embargo, en la población estudiada, no se traducen en diferencias significativas respecto al resultado a corto plazo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);29(8): 420-429, nov. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043311</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad en el manejo del infarto agudo de miocardio en el registro ARIAM en el año 2002</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28096^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24519^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
