<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122144</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infiltration efficiency ozone lumbar paravertebral and trigger point treatment as adjuvant in patients with chronic low back pain and sciatica chronic myofascial pain syndrome or isolated accompanied by other diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: After the first episode of low back pain, recurrence persists for a year or more in 25 to 60 %, affecting economically active population, causing disability and 80 % absenteeism. Objective: To evaluate the effectiveness of the use of ozone injection technique with paravertebral lumbar and trigger points along the drug treatment and rehabilitation in patients with  chronic low back pain and sciatica due to chronic pain syndrome myofascial isolated or accompanied other pathologies. Methods: A non-probability, experimental type double-blind controlled. We studied 43 patients (22 experimental and 21 control). The experimental group received lumbar paravertebral ozone trigger points and more drug treatment and rehabilitation.  The control group received drug treatment and rehabilitation.Was applied in both groups VAS, Oswestry and measuring the degrees of flexion of the trunk at the beginning, two and four weeks after initiation of therapy.  Results: The application of ozone and lumbar paravertebral and trigger points along the drug treatment and rehabilitation in the management of patients with chronic low back pain and sciatica, compared to just drug treatment and rehabilitation, was more effective, with statistical significance (p &lt;  0.05) to decrease the intensity of pain (90.5 %), functional disability (90.5 %) and increased degrees of trunk flexion (85.7 %) versus 40.0, 70 and 75 %, respectively, at four weeks after initiation of treatment. It is evident improvement in patients  with MDS or accompanied isolated lateral recess syndrome, facet syndrome, disc herniation varying degrees except the central extrusion. Conclusions: The ozone infiltration paravertebral lumbar and trigger points along the drug treatment and rehabilitation  was more effective, to reduce pain and functional disability and increase the degrees of trunk flexion early in patients with chronic low back pain and sciatica due to chronic isolated oraccompanied by other conditions that cause back pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva Jiménez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baíz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Posterior al primer episodio de dolor lumbar, la recurrencia persiste durante un año o más en el 25 al 60 %, afectando a población económicamente activa, causando discapacidad y en 80 % ausentismo laboral.  Objetivo: Evaluar el grado de eficacia del uso de la técnica de infiltración con ozono paravertebral lumbar y en puntos gatillos junto al tratamiento farmacológico y rehabilitador, en pacientes con dolor lumbar crónico y lumbociatalgia crónica debido al síndrome doloroso miofascial (SDM) aislado o acompañado de otras patologías. Métodos: Estudio no probabilístico, de tipo experimental controlado, doble ciego. Se estudiaron 43 pacientes (22 experimental  y 21 control). El grupo experimental recibió ozono paravertebral lumbar y en puntos gatillos más tratamiento farmacológico y rehabilitador. El grupo control recibió tratamiento farmacológico y rehabilitador. Se aplicó en ambos grupos la escala de EVA, Oswestry y la medición de los grados de flexión del tronco al inicio, dos y cuatro semanas posterior al comienzo del tratamiento. Resultados: La aplicación de ozono paravertebral lumbar y en puntos gatillos, junto al tratamiento farmacológico y rehabilitador, en el manejo de pacientes con dolor lumbar y lumbociatalgia crónica, comparado con solo tratamiento farmacológico y rehabilitador, resultó ser más eficaz, con significancia estadística (p &lt; 0,05) para disminuir la intensidad del dolor (90,5 %), la incapacidad funcional (90,5 %), y aumentó los grados de flexión del tronco (85,7 % versus 40,0, 70 y 75 %) respectivamente, a las cuatro semanas posteriores al inicio del tratamiento. Se evidencia mejoría en pacientes con SDM aislado o acompañado de síndrome de receso lateral, síndrome facetario, grados variables de hernia discal excepto la extrusión central.  Conclusiones: La infiltración de ozono paravertebral lumbar y en puntos gatillos junto al tratamiento farmacológico y rehabilitador resultó ser más eficaz, para disminuir el dolor e incapacidad funcional y aumentar los grados de flexión del tronco  precozmente en pacientes con dolor lumbar crónico y lumbociatalgiacrónica debido al SDM aislado o acompañado de otras patologías que originan dolor lumbar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;21(1): 23-38, ene.-feb. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122144</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la infiltración de ozono paravertebral lumbar y en puntos gatillos como coadyuvante del tratamiento en pacientes con dolor lumbar crónico y lumbociatalgia crónica en el síndrome doloroso miofascial aislado o acompañado de otras patologías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30665^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12966^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10311^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9401^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
