<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86795</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Caffeine as a preventive drug for Parkinson&#146;s disease: epidemiologic evidence and experimental support</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and development. Prospective epidemiologic studies performed in large cohorts of men (total: 374,003 subjects) agree in which the risk of suffering Parkinson&#146;s disease diminishes progressively as the consumption of coffee and other caffeinated beverages increases. In the case of women (total: 345,184 subjects) the protective effect of caffeine is only observed in menopausal women which do not receive estrogen replacement therapy. Studies with models of acute parkinsonism in rodents have shown that caffeine reduces the loss of nigrostriatal dopaminergic neurons induced with the neurotoxins 6-hidroxidopamine and 1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine, effect that seems to be mediated  through blockade of A2A adenosine receptors. Recently, it was shown that male rats treated with moderate doses of caffeine (5 mg/kg/day) during six months, followed by a withdrawal period of at least two weeks, developed a greater resistance to the catalepsy induced with the dopaminergic antagonist haloperidol, which was possibly mediated by an increase of dopaminergic transmission in the corpus striatum. Conclusions. More studies are needed to demonstrate unequivocally that caffeine prevents the degeneration of dopaminergic neurons in animal models of moderate, chronic, and progressive parkinsonism, since it could lead to the discovery of  more effective drugs for the prevention of aging-related degenerative diseases of the central nervous system (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Góngora Alfaro, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y desarrollo. Los estudios epidemiológicos prospectivos realizados en grandes cohortes de varones (total: 374.003 sujetos) coinciden en que el riesgo de padecer la enfermedad de Parkinson disminuye progresivamente cuanto mayor es el consumo de café y otras bebidas con cafeína. En el caso de las mujeres (total: 345.184 sujetos), el efecto protector de la cafeína sólo se observa en las mujeres con menopausia que no reciben terapia de reemplazo con estrógenos. Estudios con modelos de parkinsonismo agudo en roedores han mostrado que la cafeína reduce la pérdida de las neuronas  dopaminérgicas nigroestriatales inducida con las neurotoxinas 6-hidroxidopamina y 1-metil-4-fenil-1,2,3,6-tetrahidropiridina, efecto que parece estar mediado a través del bloqueo de los receptores A2A de adenosina. Recientemente se demostró que las ratas macho tratadas con dosis moderadas de cafeína (5 mg/kg/día) durante seis meses, seguida de un período de abstinencia de cuando menos dos semanas, desarrollaron una mayor resistencia a la catalepsia provocada con el antagonista dopaminérgico haloperidol, posiblemente mediada por un aumento de la transmisión dopaminérgica en el cuerpo estriado. Conclusiones. Se necesitan más estudios para demostrar inequívocamente que la cafeína previene la degeneración de las neuronas dopaminérgicas en modelos animales de parkinsonismo moderado, crónico y progresivo, pues ello podría  conducir al descubrimiento de fármacos más eficaces para la prevención de las enfermedades degenerativas del sistema nervioso central asociadas con el envejecimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;50(4): 221-229, feb. 2010. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86795</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La cafeína como un fármaco preventivo de la enfermedad de Parkinson: evidencias epidemiológicas y sustrato experimental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8950^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2143^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32116^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201002</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
