<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125824</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bilateral endogenous ophthalmitis due to Candida glabrata after complicated bariatric surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: A 43 year-old female presented with decreased visual acuity in the right eye. «Snowball-like» retinal lesions were found in both eyes on examination. Due to a lack of improvement with intravitreal antifungal empirical treatment, vitreous culture was performed and Candida glabrata was isolated. The patient then received intravitreal amphotericin B, as well as systemic treatment with caspofungin and amphotericin B lipid complex. Discussion: Endogenous fungal endophthalmitis is a sight-threatening condition. There are few reports of Candida glabrata endogenous endophthalmitis. Treatment regimens for Candida endophthalmitis include combinations of systemic and/or intravitreal antifungals, as well as vitrectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pizango, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buendia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lujan, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tejeda, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Mujer de 43 años presenta disminución de agudeza visual en ojo derecho. En la evaluación, se encuentran lesiones retinianas «en bolas de nieve» en ambos ojos. En ausencia de mejoría con tratamiento empírico antifúngico intravítreo, se realiza cultivo de vítreo y se halla Candida glabrata. La paciente recibe anfotericina B intravítrea y tratamiento sistémico con caspofungina y anfotericina B complejo lipídico. Discusión: La endoftalmitis endógena fúngica es una afección ocular grave. Existen escasos artículos de endoftalmitis endógena por Candida glabrata. Los regímenes de tratamiento para endoftalmitis por Candida incluyen combinaciones de antifúngicos sistémicos o intravítreos, así como vitrectomía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(7): 282-285, jul. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125824</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endoftalmitis endógena bilateral por Candida glabrata posterior a cirugía bariátrica complicada</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28297^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54215</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36630^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
