<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70155</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retrospective, descriptive, observational study of treatment of multiple actinic keratoses with topical methyl aminolevulinate and red light: results in clinical practice and correlation with fluorescence imaging</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Actinic keratosis (AK) is one of the most common skin diseases seen in clinical practice. In the last 5 years, several studies assessing the efficacy of photodynamic therapy in the treatment of multiple AKs have been published. Objective. We aimed to assess the clinical outcomes of photodynamic therapy in patients with multiple AKs and the correlation of those outcomes with fluorescence imaging. Material and methods. In this retrospective, descriptive, observational study of 57 patients treated in our hospital with photodynamic therapy for multiple AKs, we recorded age, sex, and lesion site (face, scalp, and dorsum of the hands). All patients were treated in the same way: methyl aminolevulinic acid (Metvix®) was applied for 3 hours and the skin then irradiated with red light at630 nm, 37 J/cm2, for 7.5 minutes (Aktilite®). The response, remission duration, tolerance, number of sessions, and fluorescence images were recorded by site. The X2 test was used to assess between-site differences and the correlation between fluorescence imaging and clinical response. Results. The greatest improvements were obtained for facial lesions; these required fewer sessions and remission lasted longer than lesions at other sites. The treatment was best tolerated on the dorsum of the hands. The fluorescence area and the reduction in intensity on applying treatment were found to be strongly and significantly correlated with the extent of clinical response. Conclusions. Overall, the outcomes of treatment of multiple AKs with photodynamic therapy are better for the face than for the scalp and dorsum of the hands. Fluorescence imaging may be an effective tool for predicting response to treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Harto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ronco, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaén, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marquet, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-García, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Guarino, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Las queratosis actínicas (QA) son una de las patologías cutáneas más frecuentes en la práctica clínica. En los últimos 5 años se han publicado varios estudios que evaluaban la eficacia de la terapia fotodinámica (TFD) en el tratamiento de múltiples QA. Objetivo. Evaluar los resultados de la TFD de múltiples QA por localizaciones y su correlación con la imagen de fluorescencia. Material y métodos. Realizamos un estudio retrospectivo, descriptivo y observacional de los pacientes tratados por múltiples QA con TFD en nuestro hospital. Se describe la edad, el sexo y la localización de las lesiones (cara, cuero cabelludo y dorso de las manos) de los 57 pacientes. Se trató a todos los pacientes usando los mismos parámetros: ácido metilaminolevulínico (MAL, Metvix®) ocluido tres horas e irradiación con luz roja de 630 nm, 37 J/cm2, 7,5 minutos (Aktilite®). Se describe la respuesta, período de remisión, tolerancia, número de sesiones y la fluorescencia según localizaciones. Con la prueba Chi-cuadrado se evalúan las diferencias entre localizaciones y la correlación de la imagen de fluorescencia con la respuesta clínica. Resultados. En la cara se obtiene mayor grado de mejoría, se requieren menor número de sesiones y mayores períodos de remisión que en el resto de las localizaciones. El dorso de las manos es la zona mejor tolerada. Existe una correlación alta y significativa entre el área de fluorescencia y su disminución al aplicar el tratamiento, con el grado de respuesta clínica. Conclusiones. Los resultados en el tratamiento de múltiples QA con TFD son mejores, globalmente, en la cara que en el cuero cabelludo y en el dorso de manos. El diagnóstico de fluorescencia puede ser una herramienta eficaz para predecir la respuesta al tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;99(10): 779-787, dic. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70155</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio retrospectivo, descriptivo y observacional del tratamiento de queratosis actínicas múltiples con metilaminolevulinato tópico y luz roja: resultados en la práctica clínica y correlación con la imagen de fluorescencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12592^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7809^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d633^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7345^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7809^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11207^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12917^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12917^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
