<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052209</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outpatient management of malignant pleural effusion using a tunneled pleural catheter: preliminary experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Inpatient management of malignant pleural effusion includes the placement of a conventional thoracostomy tube for drainage and talc slurry pleurodesis and/or a surgical approach consisting of video-assisted thoracoscopic talc insufflation. Both techniques require prolonged hospital stays of up to 1 week. Unfortunately, life expectancy in patients with this disease does not usually exceed 6 months, and so the primary aim of any palliative intervention intended to improve quality of life should be to avoid hospital admissions and to relieve pain as far as possible.     Of the few outpatient alternatives to hospital management the most frequently used is repeated thoracentesis. We describe the outpatient management of malignant pleural effusion by placement of a tunneled pleural catheter in a patient with stage IIIB lung adenocarcinoma. In our opinion, the use of this catheter offers a viable alternative to conventional therapy and is better tolerated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campo, Arantza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armendáriz, Ana Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaide, Ana Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lacunza, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seijo, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zulueta, Javier J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El manejo hospitalario del derrame pleural maligno incluye la colocación de un tubo de toracostomía convencional, drenaje y esclerosis mediante talcaje, y/o el abordaje quirúrgico mediante videotoracoscopia. Ambas técnicas requieren ingresos prolongados, de hasta una semana de duración. Lamentablemente, la esperanza de vida en pacientes con esta enfermedad no suele superar los 6 meses, motivo por el que toda intervención paliativa destinada a mejorar la calidad de vida debe tener como objetivo primordial el evitar, en la medida de lo posible, el ingreso hospitalario y aliviar el dolor.         Hay pocas alternativas ambulatorias al manejo hospitalario. De ellas, la toracocentesis de repetición es la más frecuentemente utilizada. Describimos el uso de un catéter tunelizado en el manejo ambulatorio del derrame pleural maligno de un paciente con adenocarcinoma de pulmón en estadio IIIB. Consideramos que este catéter ofrece una alternativa viable y mejor tolerada que el tratamiento convencional</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;42(12): 660-662, dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052209</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo ambulatorio del derrame pleural maligno mediante colocación de un catéter de drenaje tunelizado. Experiencia preliminar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11425^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23183^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27990^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
