<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054789</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Osteocalcin in serum, saliva and gingival crevicular fluid: their relation with periodontal treatment outcome in postmenopausal women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Osteocalcin levels have been postulated as a marker of inhibition of bone formation. The aim of the pre-sent study was to assess plasma, saliva and GCF levels of osteocalcin and correlate them with periodontal treatmentoutcome in postmenopausal women.Methods. Thirty-nine postmenopausal women (57.8 ±8.5 years old) were recruited for the study. Periodontal examinationof all women was carried out and plaque, bleeding on probing, probing depth (PD), and clinical attachment level (CAL)were recorded. Serum, saliva and gingival crevicular fluid osteocalcin were measured. Then, periodontal treatment wascarried out. Six months after the first appointment a second periodontal examination was carried out.Results. Mean PD and mean CAL decreased significantly at second appointment in the group with serum osteocalcinconcentration &lt; 10 ng/ml (15.8 ±15.8% and 15.3 ± 21.2% respectively; p &lt; 0.05). Mean PD decreased significantly atsecond appointment in the groups with saliva osteocalcin concentration &lt; 3 ng/ml (17.1 ± 15.9%; p &lt; 0.05) and 3 &#150; 7ng/ml (16.2 ± 18.1%; p &lt; 0.05).Conclusions. Low serum osteocalcin concentration is associated to a significantly higher percentage of decrease in PDand CAL after periodontal treatment in postmenopausal women. Low saliva osteocalcin concentrations are significantlyassociated to a higher percentage of decrease in PD</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martinez Sahuquillo, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bullon, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chandler, Lucy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez Cano, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Egea, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Los niveles de osteocalcina se han propuesto como marcador de la inhibición de la formación ósea. El propósito de este trabajo es determinar las concentraciones de osteocalcina en plasma, saliva y fluido crevicular correlacionándolo con el resultado del tratamiento periodontal en mujeres postmenopáusicas. Pacientes y métodos. El estudio se realizó en treinta y nueve mujeres postmenopáusicas (57.8 ±8.5 años de edad). El examenperiodontal incluyó el control de placa, el sangrado al sondaje, la profundidad de sondaje (PS) y la pérdida de inserción(CAL). Se determinaron los niveles de osteocalcina en suero, saliva y fluido crevicular. A continuación se llevó a cabo el tratamiento periodontal. Pasados seis meses tras la primera cita se llevó a cabo un segundo examen periodontal.Resultados. Las medias de la PS y del CAL disminuyeron significativamente en el segundo examen periodontal en elgrupo de mujeres con osteocalcina en suero &lt; 10 ng/ml (15.8± 15.8% y 15.3± 21.2%, respectivamente; p &lt; 0.05). La PSmedia disminuyó significativamente en el segundo exámen en los grupos con concentraciones de osteocalcina en saliva&lt; 3 ng/ml (17.1± 15.9%; p &lt; 0.05) y 3 &#150; 7 ng/ml (16.2 ± 18.1%; p &lt; 0.05). Conclusiones. Los niveles bajos de osteocalcina en suero se asocian significativamente a un mayor porcentaje de disminuciónde la PS y del CAL tras el tratamiento periodontal en mujeres postmenopáusicas. Las bajas concentraciones de osteocalcina en saliva se asociaron significativamente a un mayor porcentaje de disminución de la PS</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);12(3): E193-E197, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054789</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteocalcina en serum, saliva fluido crevicular gingival: su relación con el tratamiento en mujeres posmenopaúsicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24820^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24820^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6027^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10701^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12838^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31200^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10709^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
