<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158210</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Strategies for coping with ocuppational stress in Nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Nursing Staff is a group exposed to high levels of occupational stress. Coping strategies act as mediator variables between the stress perceived and its negative consequences, such as the Burnout Syndrome. The objectives of this article are to define the concept of coping strategies and their classification, to expose the empirical evidence found in nursing research, and to describe the main interventions for their development. Said interventions are: specific workshops or programs for the development of adaptive coping strategies (based on clinical simulation), and strengthening social support, relaxation techniques, change in wrong cognitions, and briefing sessions or meetings. Said interventions should be promoted from universities and healthcare institutions, because this would not only make it easier for nursing professionals to alleviate and minimize the negative consequences of occupational stress, but would also improve their daily clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arrogante, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El personal de Enfermería es un colectivo expuesto a altos niveles de estrés laboral. Las estrategias de afrontamiento actúan como variables mediadoras entre el estrés percibido y sus consecuencias negativas, como el síndrome de burnout. El artículo tiene como objetivos definir el concepto de estrategias de afrontamiento y su clasificación, exponer la evidencia empírica encontrada en la investigación enfermera y describir las principales intervenciones para su desarrollo. Dichas intervenciones son: los talleres o programas específicos para el desarrollo de estrategias de afrontamiento adaptativas (basados en la simulación clínica) y el fortalecimiento del apoyo social, las técnicas de relajación, el cambio de cogniciones erróneas y las sesiones o reuniones informativas. Desde las universidades y las instituciones sanitarias se deberían promover dichas intervenciones, ya que no solamente facilitaría a los profesionales enfermeros amortiguar y minimizar las consecuencias negativas del estrés laboral, sino que mejoraría su práctica clínica habitual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(10): 71-76, dic. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158210</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estrategias de afrontamiento al estrés laboral en Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9926</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28574</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
