<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156887</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frequency of single nucleotide polymorphisms and alpha-synuclein haplotypes associated with sporadic Parkinson&#146;s disease in the Mexican population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Parkinson&#146;s disease (PD) is a common neurodegenerative disease which begins in adulthood. Its incidence in Mexico is estimated to be 40-50 cases per 100,000 inhabitants/year and is the fourth reason for medical care in the National Institute of Neurology and Neurosurgery. The protein alpha-synuclein, SNCA, plays a key role in the pathology of PD, and its polymorphisms have been associated with an increased risk of developing the disease. Aim. To evaluate the risk of PD represented by the polymorphisms rs2619364, rs2619363, rs2736990, rs7684318, rs17016074, rs356219, rs356220 and rs356203 of SNCA in a sample of Mexican subjects. Subjects and methods. Altogether 171 patients diagnosed with PD and 171 gender- and age-paired controls were assessed by means of real-time polymerase chain reaction, and a statistical analysis was performed to determine the association between the polymorphisms and the disease. Results. The SNCA variants rs356220, rs356203, rs7684318 and rs2736990 were associated with the disease and form two haplotypes with a high risk of developing sporadic PD in the Mexican population. Conclusions. Variations in SNCA are a risk factor for the development of PD and can act as specific genetic biomarkers as a diagnostic support tool in sporadic PD for Mexican mestizo patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dávila-Ortiz de Montellano, David J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monroy-Jaramillo, Nancy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yescas-Gómez, Petra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fresán, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Violante, Mayela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La enfermedad de Parkinson (EP) es una entidad neurodegenerativa común de inicio en la etapa adulta. Su incidencia en México se estima en 40-50 casos por 100.000 habitantes/año y constituye la cuarta causa de atención médica en el Instituto Nacional de Neurología y Neurocirugía. La proteína alfa-sinucleína, SNCA, es clave en la patología de la EP y sus polimorfismos se han asociado a un riesgo aumentado de desarrollarla. Objetivo. Evaluar el riesgo que representan los polimorfismos rs2619364, rs2619363, rs2736990, rs7684318, rs17016074, rs356219, rs356220 y rs356203 de SNCA en una muestra de sujetos mexicanos para la EP. Sujetos y métodos. Se evaluaron 171 pacientes con diagnóstico de EP y 171 controles pareados por sexo y edad mediante reacción en cadena de la polimerasa en tiempo real, y se realizó un análisis estadístico para determinar la asociación de los polimorfismos con la enfermedad. Resultados. Las variantes rs356220, rs356203, rs7684318 y rs2736990 de SNCA están asociadas a la enfermedad y forman dos haplotipos de riesgo elevado para desarrollar EP esporádica en la población mexicana. Conclusiones. Las variaciones en SNCA son un factor de riesgo para desarrollar EP y pueden ser biomarcadores genéticos específicos para pacientes mestizos mexicanos como herramienta de apoyo diagnóstico en la EP esporádica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;63(8): 345-350, 16 oct., 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156887</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Frecuencia de polimorfismos de nucleótido único y haplotipos de alfa-sinucleína asociados con la enfermedad de Parkinson esporádica en población mexicana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51166^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51166^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51166^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19180^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34583^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34583^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10489^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51166^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
