<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154026</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality indicators in vascular disease: National multicentre pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is growing interest in evaluating the quality of vascular care. The quality indicators are the tool to measure this. Different international vascular scientific societies are developing initiatives to monitor the most frequent surgical procedures. Objectives: The Quality Group of the Spanish Society of Angiology and Vascular Surgery considered it of interest to begin developing a basic structure of indicators in our Society. To this end, it was proposed to select 4-5 vascular diseases and 1-2 indicators of these processes, thus demonstrating that this initiative is feasible and can lead to useful results to improve the quality of our daily work. Material and methods: Seventeen Spanish Vascular Surgery Units were selected, together with 5 of the most common diseases and two key indicators for each: abdominal aortic aneurysms, peripheral arterial disease, extracranial carotid disease, venous thrombosis and arteriovenous fistulas for haemodialysis. Practice guidelines, consensus documents and published studies of great scientific importance were used to select the indicators (key performance indicators). Through expert consensus process indicators were selected. Results: The results showed a great variability between centres, few of them being impossible to quantify, because of the absence of computer databases to be able to analyse them. The specific details of each indicator are fully described in this article. Conclusions: This report has allowed us to show that the development of quality indicators is feasible, useful, and a valid opportunity to improve. As in other international scientific societies and after this positive experience, we should increase these indicators and create a national database to monitor them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Cañibano, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Espada, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Veiguela, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Florit López, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morata Barrado, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellmunt Montoya, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Desde hace más de una década ha surgido un interés creciente por evaluar la calidad de la atención sanitaria que prestamos. Los indicadores de calidad son la medida instrumental de esa calidad asistencial. Diferentes sociedades científicas internacionales están desarrollando iniciativas para monitorizar sus procesos quirúrgicos más frecuentes. Objetivos: El Grupo de Calidad de la Sociedad Española de Angiología Cirugía Vascular consideró que sería de interés empezar a desarrollar una estructura básica de indicadores dentro de nuestra sociedad. Para ello se propuso como objetivo seleccionar 4-5 patologías vasculares frecuentes y elaborar 1-2 indicadores de esos procesos, para de esta forma demostrar que esta iniciativa es factible y puede dar lugar a unos resultados útiles para mejorar la calidad de nuestro trabajo diario y poder hacer «benchmarking» europeo. Material y métodos: Se seleccionaron 17 Servicios de Cirugía Vascular, 5 de las patologías más frecuentes y 2 indicadores clave por cada una de ellas: aneurismas de aorta abdominal, patología arterial periférica, patología carotídea extracraneal, trombosis venosa profunda y fístulas arteriovenosas para hemodiálisis. Para seleccionar los indicadores clave (key performance indicators) se recurrió a las guías de práctica clínica, documentos de consenso y estudios publicados de gran relevancia científica. Por consenso de expertos se escogieron preferentemente indicadores de proceso y se elaboró una ficha para la recogida uniformada de información. Resultados: Los resultados mostraron una gran variabilidad entre los centros, siendo alguno de ellos imposible de cuantificar, dada la ausencia de bases de datos informatizadas que permitieran su análisis. Los detalles concretos de cada indicador se describen exhaustivamente en el contenido de este artículo. Conclusiones: Este trabajo nos ha permitido mostrar que la elaboración de indicadores de calidad es factible, útil y una oportunidad de mejora válida. Como en otras sociedades científicas internacionales, y después de esta positiva experiencia, deberíamos ampliar estos indicadores y crear una base de datos nacional para monitorizarlos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;68(4): 285-291, jul.-ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154026</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicadores de calidad en patología vascular: estudio piloto multicéntrico nacional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29873^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29873^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
