<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131709</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Osteosarcoma and ATR-16 syndrome: Association or coincidence?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ATR-16 syndrome is due to alterations on chromosome 16p13.3, and is usually accompanied by alpha-thalassemia, mild-moderate mental retardation, dysmorphic facial features, skeletal and genitourinary malformations. There are no references of the combination of ATR-16 syndrome and osteosarcoma in the literature. Osteosarcoma usually has a complex karyotype, characterized by a high degree of heterogeneity of chromosomal aberrations, among which is the involvement of chromosome 16. We report a case of a patient with ATR-16 syndrome diagnosed with femoral osteosarcoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Regueiro García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saborido Fiaño, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome ATR-16 se debe a alteraciones en el cromosoma 16p13.3 y se caracteriza por  -talasemia, retraso mental leve-moderado, rasgos faciales dismórficos, malformaciones genitourinarias y esqueléticas. No hay hasta el momento actual ninguna referencia bibliográfica sobre asociación con osteosarcoma. l osteosarcoma se presenta generalmente con un cariotipo complejo, caracterizado por un   lto grado de heterogeneidad de aberraciones cromosómicas, entre las que ocasionalmente se ha encontrado la afectación del cromosoma 16. resentamos un caso clínico de un paciente con síndrome ATR-16 diagnosticado de osteosarcoma  femoral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): e189-e191, ene. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131709</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteosarcoma y síndrome ATR-16, ¿asociación o coincidencia?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24403^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7150^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
