<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-145599</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Norton Scale as predictor of health-related quality of life in institutionalized elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: A low Norton Scale (NS) score predicts pressure ulcer risk and several adverse outcomes in the elderly. On the other hand, health-related quality of life (HRQOL) is an indicator with clinical and predictive utilities. The aim was to assess the relationship between NS and HRQOL, in a gender analysis. Method: Fifty-one women and 39 men, institutionalized and aged &amp;#8805; 65 years, were evaluated through personal interview and medical records. The NS, HRQOL &#150;with EuroQol-5D&#150;, age, body mass index, falls, use of psychoactive drugs, cognitive function and Charlson, Barthel and Tinetti indexes, were assessed. Two regression models were developed, with EuroQol-5D as dependent variable. Results: The NS showed the same score in both sexes, with a median (interquartile range) value of 19 (2). Women presented a worse HRQOL, with an EuroQol-5D = 0.78, whereas it was 0.87 in men (P = .02). The NS score was correlated with HRQOL in women (r = 0.57; P &lt; .001) but not in men (r = 0.15;P = .36). After adjusting for confounders, the NS showed a beta value of 0.54 (P = .02) in women and beta = 0.35 (P = .14) in men. Conclusions: The NS has shown to be the strongest factor on HRQOL in women, regardless of age, comorbidity and the rest of covariates. Conversely, the relationship was weaker and non-significant in men (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pariente-Rodrigo, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Expósito, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Román, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo-Fernández, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado-Amores, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Una puntuación baja en la Escala de Norton (EdN), además de señalar el riesgo de aparición de una úlcera por presión, parece ser pronóstica de otros eventos adversos en el anciano. Por otro lado, la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) es un indicador con utilidades clínicas y, asimismo, predictivas. El objetivo ha sido analizar la relación entre la EdN y la CVRS en un análisis diferenciado por género. Método: Cincuenta y una mujeres y 39 varones de &amp;#8805; 65 años, institucionalizados, fueron estudiados mediante entrevista personal y registros médicos. Fueron evaluadas la EdN y la CVRS &#150;mediante el cuestionario EuroQol-5D&#150;, además de la edad, el índice de masa corporal, las caídas, el consumo de psicotropos, la función cognitiva, y los índices de Charlson, Barthel y Tinetti. Se elaboraron 2 modelos de regresión, con el EuroQol-5D como variable dependiente. Resultados: La EdN mostró el mismo resultado en ambos sexos, con un valor de mediana (rango intercuartílico) de 19 (2). Las mujeres refirieron una peor CVRS, con un EuroQol-5D = 0,78, frente a 0,87 en los varones (p = 0,02). La EdN se correlacionó significativamente con la CVRS en las mujeres (r = 0,57; p &lt; 0,001), pero no en los varones (r = 0,15; p = 0,36). Con el ajuste multivariante, la EdN presentó un valor beta = 0,54 (p = 0,02) en las mujeres y beta = 0,35 (p = 0,14) en los varones. Conclusiones: La EdN ha sido la variable de mayor impacto sobre la CVRS en las mujeres, siendo dicha asociación independiente de la edad, la comorbilidad y el resto de las variables analizadas. En los varones, la relación fue más débil y no alcanzó la significación estadística (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);25(6): 312-318, nov.-dic. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-145599</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Escala de Norton como predictor de la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud en el anciano institucionalizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5991^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28417</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
