<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125760</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The construction of the metaphor through transferential interpretation in a narcissistic patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the typical cure of patients with a neurotic organization, the patient settles into the metaphor of the encounter withour difficulties. The patient recognizes a current meaning in transferential interpretation that owes its existence to the meaning that it acquired in his chilhood past. The otherness of the analyst and her analytic function is recognized and signified by the patient. In patients with a narcissistic organization, the world said and heard in the analytic encounter move away from the metaphor to acquired a literal meaning that exaggerates the affect linked to it. The otherness of the analyst ad her analytic function lack a metaphorical representation in the patient´s psychic reality. In this work, the author, using the word of the analyst as a vehicle, proposes a modification in the typical cure thar allows, in the psychic reality of the narcissistic patient, the establishment of the metaphor of the psychoanalytic encounter. Using metapsychological concepts sucha as  transference, countertransference and the intersubjective bond of a narcissistic nature, and with the metaphoric use of the Winnicottian concepts of space and transitional object, the author suggests the possibility of recreating the representation of a transitional space that can be used by patient as a transitional object. A recreation undertaken within the traditional setting of a typical cure. The particularities of this recreation are also described, as is its repercussion in the founding and maintenance of the typical cure, and its influence on transferential, countertransferential, and tranfero-countertransferetial phenomena and their inherent limitations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Serrano Lindes, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la cura tipo, de pacientes con una organización neurótica, el analizado se instala, sin dificultades, en la metáfora del encuentro. Reconoce en la interpretación transferencial un sentido y significado actual que debe su existencia al sentido y al significado que adquirió en su pasado infantil. La alteridad del analista y su función analítica es reconocida y significada por el analizado. En pacientes con una organización narcisista, la palabra dicha y escuchada en el encuentro analítico se aleja de la metáfora para adquirir un sentido y significado literal que sobredimensiona el afecto a ella vinculado. La alteridad del analista y su función analítica carecen de una representación metafórica en la realidad psíquica del analizado. En este trabajo, la autora, empleando como vehículo la palabra del analista, plantea una modificación de la cura tipo que permita, en la realidad psíquica del paciente narcisista, el establecimiento de la metáfora del encuentro psicoanalítico. Utilizando conceptos metapsicológicos como transferencia, contra transferencia y vínculo intersubjetivo de naturaleza narcisista, y apoyándose en el empleo metafórico de los conceptos wuinnicottianos de espacio y objeto transicional, sugiere la posibilidad de recrear la representación de un espacio transicional que pueda ser utilizado por el analizado como un objeto transicional. Una recreación efectuada dentro del encuadre tradicional de la cura tipo. Así mismo, se describen las particularidades de esta recreación, su repercusión positiva en la instauración y mantenimiento de la cura tipo, su influencia sobre los fenómenos transferenciales, contratransferenciales y transfero-contratransferenciales y sus inherentes limitaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(53): 127-143, ene.-abr. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125760</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La construcción de la metáfora a través de la interpretación transferencial en el paciente narcisista</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10554^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33190</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
