<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89317</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Secular acceleration of weight, height and BMI. Cross-sectional and longitudinal Spanish studies on growth 2008</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cross-sectional and longitudinal growth studies have recently been conducted in Spain. Between 1999 and 2002, weight and vertex-heel length were evaluated in 9,362 new-borns (4,884 males, 4,478 females), 26-42 weeks of gestational age. Age increase in these values compared with previous Spanish studies (1987-1992) and sexual dimorphism were observed. Between 2000 and 204, height, weight and body mass index were evaluated in 32,064 subjects 816,607 males, 15,457 females) from birth to adulthood. A secular trend of growth was observed compared to data obtained 20 years ago, with a higher increase in BMI values above the 50 th percentile. A longitudinal growth study of 458 healthy subjects (223 boys, 235 girls) born between  1978 and 1982 yielded pubertal growth and maturity standards for each of the five pubertal maturity groups. Adult height was similar to that reported by European and American studies, but lower than that reported for German, Swedish and Netherlands populations. In males, BMI was higher than in other European population and near to the USA population. In females, BMI was similar to European populations and lower than in the USA population (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Siguero, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yeste, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobradillo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En España recientemente han finalizado estudios de crecimiento transversales que permiten evaluar la antropometría neonatal de recién nacidos prematuros y a término, y el crecimiento postnatal de niños y adolescentes. Además, disonemos de estudios longitudinales que permiten evaluar el crecimiento puberal diferenciado para cada grupo madurador. El peso y longitud al nacer fueron evaluados (1999-2002) en 9.362 recién nacidos, 26-42 semanas de edad gestacional, observándose dimorfismo sexual y un incremento en ambos parámetros respecto a estudios previos (1987-1992) particularmente en el grupo de recién nacidos pretérmino. El peso, talla e IMC fueron evaluados (2000-2004) en 32.064 niños y adolescentes (16.607 varones y 15.457 mujeres) de 0-24 años de edad, observándose aceleración secular en los tres parámetros respecto a estudios realizados hace 20 años. El incremento ponderal fue excesivo respecto al de talla, para los valores  del IMC superiores al percentil 50. El estudio longitudinal (458 sujetos: 223 varones,235 mujeres, nacidos entre 1978 y 1982) permitió obtener patrones de crecimiento y de maduración puberal diferenciados para cada uno de los cinco grupos maduradores. La talla adulta en ambos estudios, es similar a la reportada en estudios europeos y americanos, aunque inferior a la alemana, sueca y holandesa. En varones el IMC fue superior al observado en países europeos y próximos al reportado en EE.UU. En mujeres el IMC fue similar al de países europeos e inferior al reportado en EE.UU (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;65(3): 184-189, mayo-jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89317</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aceleración secular de peso, talla e IMC. Estudios españoles transversales y longitudinales de crecimiento 2008</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6278</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
