<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99520</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Results from the application of a quality management system in the community pharmacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Oxidative stress is an uncontrolled oxidation process of biological structures, triggering by free radicals, which cause damage and death cell. Many evidences implicate oxidative stress in the pathogenesis of neurodegenerative diseases such as Alzheimer and Parkinson. Compounds with antioxidant capacity may prevent from oxidative damage because of the inhibition of free radical production. More than 160 diterpenes have been identified and isolated from aerial parts of Sideriti sspp. These compounds are largely responsible for the anti-inflammatory, antioxidant and digestive activities, reason why these species are used in traditional Mediterranean medicine. To evaluate the neuroprotective effect of the diterpenes andalusol, conchitriol and lagascatriol, isolated from Sideriti sspp. aerial parts, against oxidative stress induced by hydrogen peroxide in the human astrocytoma U373 MG cell line. The possible protective effect of the diterpenes against the damage induced by hydrogen peroxide has been evaluated using MTT assay. The free radical scavenging capacity of these compounds has been studied using DPPH method. Results of the present study demonstrated that the diterpenes andalusol, conchitriol y lagascatriol (5 and 10 &amp;#956;M) protect U373 MG cells from hydrogen peroxide toxicity, which is due to in part to the antioxidant capacity of these compounds. Itis suggested that these diterpenes could exert a beneficial effect in the prevention of neurodegenerative diseases associated to oxidative stress. These future studies will be focused on a deepening of action mechanism(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Serranillos, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Burgos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomino, O. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carretero, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estrés oxidativo es un proceso de oxidación no controlado de las estructuras biológicas, desencadenado por radicales libres, que produce daño y muerte celular. Numerosas evidencias implican al estrés oxidativo en la patogénesis de enfermedades neurodegenerativas como Alzheimer o Parkinson. Compuestos con capacidad antioxidante pueden prevenir el daño oxidativo al inhibir la producción de radicales libres. Más de 160 diterpenos han sido identificados y aislados de las partes aéreas de Sideritis spp. A ellos se atribuyen en gran medida actividades antiinflamatorias, antioxidantes y digestivas por las cuales se utilizan estas especies en la medicina tradicional mediterránea. El objetivo de este estudio es evaluar el efecto neuroprotector de los diterpenosandalusol, conchitriol y lagascatriol, aislados de las partes aéreas de Sideritis spp. frente al estrés oxidativo inducido por peróxido de hidrógeno en la línea celular U373MG de astrocitoma humano. El posible efecto protector de los diterpenos frente al daño provocado por peróxido de hidrógeno ha sido evaluado mediante el ensayo de MTT. La capacidad de captación de radicales libres de los compuestos se ha estudiado mediante la técnica del DPPH. Los resultados del presente estudio demuestran que los diterpenos andalusol, conchitriol y lagascatriol (5 y 10 &amp;#956;M) protegen a las células U373 MG de la toxicidad del peróxido de hidrógeno, lo que se atribuye en parte a la capacidad antioxidante de dichos compuestos. Se sugiere que estos diterpenos podrían ejercer un efecto beneficioso en la prevención de enfermedades neurodegenerativas asociadas al estrés oxidativo. Estudios futuros irán encaminados a una profundización de su mecanismo de acción(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;51(supl.3): 617-627, jul. 2010. graf, ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99520</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuroprotección mediada por diterpenos aislados de Sideritis spp. frente al estrés oxidativo en astrocitos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34314^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30204^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5744^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5744^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32116^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4285^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4285^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32116^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32116^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4285^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32116^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4285^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
