<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111276</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fine-cut tobacco: a priority for public health and consumer advocacy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To study whether fine-cut tobacco poses a problem for public health and consumer affairs. Methods We analyzed up to 70% of the fine-cut tobacco market in Spain. Regarding public health, the contents of nicotine, tar and carbon monoxide were analyzed and compared with levels in conventional cigarettes. Concerning consumer affairs, the labeling of samples was checked. Results The contents of nicotine, tar and carbon monoxide reached values of 70%, 85% and 84%, respectively. These values are higher than those allowed in conventional cigarettes. A total of 67% of the samples analyzed did not show nicotine and tar contents on the labeling. None of the labels showed carbon monoxide contents. The presence of labeling per se did not guarantee sufficient information for consumers. Conclusions Fine-cut tobacco is a problem in both public health and consumer affairs. Solutions are required to resolve both problems (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ysa Valle, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hebert Jiménez, Céline</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campo San Segundo, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons Carlos-Roca, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Calduch, Tania</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Valorar si el tabaco de liar supone un problema en materia de salud pública y consumo. Métodos Se estudia el 70% del mercado español. En materia de salud pública, se analizan los contenidos de nicotina, alquitrán y monóxido de carbono del humo, y se comparan con los de los cigarrillos convencionales. En materia de consumo, se examina el etiquetado. Resultados Los contenidos de nicotina, alquitrán y monóxido de carbono alcanzan valores de hasta el 70%, el 85% y el 84%, respectivamente, más de lo permitido para los cigarrillos convencionales. El 67% de las muestras no indican los contenidos de nicotina y alquitrán, y el 100% el monóxido de carbono. A pesar de la existencia de etiquetado, éste no garantiza una información suficiente al consumidor. Conclusiones El tabaco de liar supone un problema tanto en materia de salud pública como en consumo. Por ello, sería necesaria alguna medida que permita resolver esta cuestión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;26(3): 267-269, mayo-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111276</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tabaco de liar: una prioridad de salud pública y consumo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51522</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51519</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14415^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
