<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68193</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study was designed to evaluate the effects of three non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) with varying cycloxygenase selectivities on the small intestinal biochemical composition, function and histology during 1, 2-dimethylhydrazine (DMH) administration. Sprague Dawley male rats were divided into five different groups viz: Group 1 (control, vehicle treated), Group 2 (DMH-treated, 30 mg/kg body weight/week in 1 mM EDTA-saline, subcutaneously), Group 3 (DMH + aspirin-60 mg/kg body weight), Group 4 (DMH + celecoxib-6 mg/kg body weight), Group 5 (DMH + etoricoxib-0.64 mg/kg body weight). After six weeks of treatment, brush border membrane was isolated from the jejunum segment of all the groups and changes in the associated enzymes such as sucrase, lactase, maltase, alkaline phosphatase, membrane lipid composition, fluorescence polarizations of diphenylhexatriene, pyrene excimer formation, histological changes and surface characteristics were studied. The results indicated a significant alteration in the enzyme activity as well as changes in the structure and function of the intestine in the presence of the pro-carcinogen, DMH, which suggests the possible chemopreventive efficacy of NSAIDs against the intestinal cancer (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nath Sanyal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Singh Kanwar, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mittal, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente estudio se diseñó para evaluar los efectos de tres fármacos antiinflamatorios no esteroideos (AINE) con diferente selectividad por la ciclooxigenasa sobre la composición bioquímica, la función y la histología del intestino delgado durante la administración de 1,2-dimetilhidracina (DMH). Se distribuyó a ratas macho Sprague Dawley en grupos distintos: Grupo 1 (control, tratado con vehículo), Grupo 2 (tratado con DMH, 30 mg/kg de peso /semana en 1 mM de EDTA-salino, subcutáneo), Grupo 3 (DMH + aspirina-60 mg/kg de peso), Grupo 4 (DMH + celecoxib-6 mg/kg de peso), Grupo 5 (DMH + etoricoxib-0,64 mg/kg de peso). Tras seis semanas de tratamiento, se aisló la membrana en cepillo de un segmento del yeyuno en todos los grupos y se estudiaron los cambios en las enzimas asociadas tales como sucrasa, lactasa, maltasa, fosfatasa alcalina, en la composición lipídica de la membrana, las polarizaciones de fluorescencia del difenilhexatrieno, la formación del excímero pireno, los cambios histológicos y las características de la superficie. Los resultados indican una alteración significativa de la actividad enzimática así como cambios en la estructura y función del intestino en presencia del procarcinógeno DMH, lo que sugiere la posible eficacia quimio-preventiva de los AINE frente al cáncer de intestino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;23(5): 439-448, sept.-oct. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68193</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33401^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9059^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27938^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30408^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7577^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7576^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
