<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84788</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-6982</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Iodine uptake in the chest in the follow-up of well-differentiated thyroid cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Differentiated thyroid cancer is a disease having a very good prognosis when treated adequately. Ablation treatment with 131I is frequently adjunct to surgery in these patients since it improves survival. Radioiodine whole-body scan is one of the imaging modality of choice in the follow-up of patients with this kind of pathology. After ablation treatment of the thyroid gland, any radioiodine accumulation in a non-physiological location usually means the presence of functioning metastasis. Recognition of potential false-positives is essential to avoid unnecessary exposure to further radiation from repeated therapeutic doses of radioactive iodine. We report a case of uptake in the chest due to bronchiectasis, potentially masquerading as pulmonary metastasis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Balsa Bretón, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elviro Peña, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alonso, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vásquez Tineo, S. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillejos Rodríguez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Valle, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariana Monguía, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pey Illera, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paniagua Correa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Paulini, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Penín González, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cáncer diferenciado de tiroides es una enfermedad con muy buen pronóstico si se trata adecuadamente. El tratamiento ablativo con 131I frecuentemente se asocia al tratamiento quirúrgico en estos pacientes ya que mejora la supervivencia, y el rastreo corporal total con 131I es una de las modalidades de diagnóstico de elección en el seguimiento de esta enfermedad. Tras tratamiento ablativo del tejido tiroideo, cualquier depósito del radiotrazador en una localización no fisiológica representa habitualmente la presencia de metástasis. Así pues, será fundamental el reconocimiento de cualquier posible falso positivo con el fin de evitar la radiación innecesaria debida a tratamientos inadecuados. Presentamos un caso clínico de captación torácica por bronquiectasias que puede malinterpretarse como metástasis pulmonar(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Med Nucl;30(1): 24-28, ene.-feb. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84788</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Captación torácica de 131I en el seguimiento del cáncer diferenciado de tiroides</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6191^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14342^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14349^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6191^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22696^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14349^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2320^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
