<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-80979</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-0921</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Decrease of the capacity of informal support to elderly and family network and scarce increase of formal support network require other methods and strategies to study this issue. The analysisof social network can be useful to analyze available social resources for disabled elderly. Material and methods: Descriptive research dated was made between November 29 and July 1 2008. The information was obtained from interviews supported by computer to 40 disabled elder. Results: 80% of disabled elderly (Egos) was more than 75 years, 42.5% lived alone; almost half of Alters (individuals of the environment of the elderly) were retired and belonged to same generationthan elderly. Density and cohesion of social network, mediated for stock of capital social, influenced positively on subjective perception of health and had an effect in Capital Social stock too to favor good auto-perception of health indirectly. Conclusions: Personal networks model defines with more clearly than other analysis techniques the kinds of support provided to elderly and allow to asses the contribution of the whole social network to disabled elderly (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gaete, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivera, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La disminución de la capacidad de apoyos informales al anciano en la red familiar básica y el tímido aumento de las redes formales de atención hacen necesario tener en cuenta metodologías que hagan hincapié en la potencialidad de los recursos sociales que poseen los ancianos dependientes. Material y métodos: Investigación descriptiva comprendida entre el 29 de noviembre de 2007 y el 1 de julio de 2008. La información se obtuvo a partir de entrevistas asistidas por ordenador a 40 ancianos dependientes. Resultados: Un 80% de los ancianos dependientes (Egos) tenía más de 75 años, un 42,5% vivía solo; casi la mitad de los Alteris (personas del entorno del sujeto estudiado) estaban jubilados y eran de lamisma generación que los Egos. La densidad y la cohesión de las redes sociales, controlados por elstock de Capital Social, tenían una influencia positiva sobre la percepción subjetiva de salud. Además también repercutía en el stock de Capital Social, de tal forma que favorecía indirectamente la buena autopercepción de la salud. Conclusiones: El modelo de redes personales define con más nitidez que otras técnicas de análisis los tipos de ayuda que se procuran al anciano y permite medir la contribución de toda la red social al apoyo, real y potencial, de la persona pendiente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. multidiscip. gerontol;19(3): 121-129, jul.-sept. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-80979</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación del modelo de redes personales al estudio de los ancianos dependientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10011^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3878</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
