<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153403</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7198</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The unprecedented legal implications that non-therapeutic genetic manipulation in pre-implantation embryonic state points out demand a, until now, unexplored approach, which, at the same time, requires the redefinition and extension of legal-binding status of traditional categories of law related to constitutional, restorative, criminal and international law. ln this paper, l will identify and define a juridical framework to regulate non-therapeutic genetic manipulation in pre-implantation embryonic state, specifically when that manipulation introduces deteriorations, disabilities or illnesses, which imply objective harms for a new subject of rights who should be considered in the juridical map: the future person. ln addition, I intend to remedy the existing legal vacuum and loopholes in this matter by proposing to update, expand and deepen international legal systems through the juridical re-categorization of non-therapeutic genetic manipulation and the concept ot legal existence of the person (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valdés Meza, Erick</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El rasgo jurídico inédito que la manipulacion genética no terapéutica en estado embrionario despliega, exige un abordaje jurídico-procedimental, hasta ahora inexplorado que, a la vez, demanda la redefinición y ampliación de la estatura legal vinculante de categorías tradicionales del derecho positivo y que alcanzan las fronteras del derecho constitucional, de familia, reparatorio y penal. En este artículo busco demostrar la necesidad de definir un marcojuridico para regular la manipulación genética no terapéutica en estado embrionario preimplantacional que introduce desmejoras o discapacidades que redundan en perjuicios objetivos para un nuevo sujeto de derechos que debiera ser considerado en el mapa juridico: la persona futura. Por ello, pretendo subsanar el vacio legal existente, proponiendo actualizar, ampliar y profundizar los ordenamientos jurídicos iberoamericanos, a través de la recategorizacion jurídica de la manipulación genética no terapéutica y la emergencia de un nuevo sujeto de derechos: la persona futura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. derecho genoma hum;(43): 123-159, jul.-dic. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153403</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bioderecho y sujeto de derechos. Recategorización jurídica de la manipulación genética no terapéutica en estado embrionario pre-implantacional y del concepto de existencia legal de la persona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29177^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5957^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38821^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38858</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6958^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5957^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1720^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1720^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
