<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-039173</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Visualization and validation of nasal bone and nuchal translucency as ultrasound markers of aneuploidies</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the value of assessment of fetal nasal bone and nuchal translucency as chromosomal markers in early pregnancy. Subjects and methods: We performed an observational cross-sectional study in 434 pregnant women with 466 fetuses. To evaluate the presence or absence of nuchal translucency and nasal bone, ultrasound scans performed between weeks 11 and 14 respectively were studied. Results: In 60 (12.9%) fetuses, the presence or absence of the nasal bone could not be confirmed. Fetal nasal bone had a sensitivity of 0% and a specificity of 97.5% with poor positive and negative likelihood ratios. Nuchal translucency had a sensitivity of 100% and a specificity of 98.7%, with excellent likelihood ratios. Conclusions: More precise methodology is required for the systematic application of nasal bone assessment as a marker of trisomy 21. Nasal bone should be considered together with maternal age, nuchal translucency and blood test to increase the accuracy of screening</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ariza, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabeu, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sellers, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la capacidad de visualización del hueso nasal y de la translucencia nucal junto con su validación y utilidad clínica como marcadores de cromosomopatía en gestaciones tempranas. Sujetos y métodos: Se diseñó un estudio observacional y transversal en 434 gestantes, con un total de 466 fetos, en exploración ecográfica entre las semanas 11 y 14 para la evaluación de la translucencia nucal y el hueso nasal. Resultados: En 60 (12,9%) fetos nos fue imposible concluir la presencia o ausencia del hueso nasal. El hueso nasal presentó una sensibilidad del 0% y una especificidad del 97,5%, con malos cocientes de probabilidad positivos y negativos. La translucencia nucal obtuvo una sensibilidad del 100% y una especificidad del 98,7%, con excelentes cocientes de probabilidad. Conclusiones: Debe establecerse una metodología más precisa para la aplicación sistemática del hueso nasal como marcador de trisomía 21. Debería utilizarse, en relación con la edad materna, la translucencia nucal y la bioquímica para aumentar la sensibilidad del cribado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);48(7): 319-326, jul. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-039173</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Visualización y validación del hueso nasal y la translucencia nucal como marcadores ecográficos de aneuploidías</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9490^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11732^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32869^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
