<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79195</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hypothermia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A deep understanding about the causes and situations which predispose a patient to hypothermia can prevent its progression and the emergence of complications which present life-threatening risks and can lead to irreversible organ deterioration. The distinct degrees of hypothermia require a diagnosis and a distinct therapeutic treatment which share common pillars based on: the need to employ general measures which counterarrest the deterioration of those organs caused by heat loss; and the use of internal or external reheating methods which vary due to the degree of hypothermia and the hemodynamic stability of the patient. In moderate or severe cases, a nurse&#146;s role, as one who collaborates in patient treatment, requires paying special attention to strict monitoring of vital constants, neurological, metabolic and cardio-respiratory signs, as well as collaborating in various therapeutic procedures. As a nursing diagnosis, hypothermia refers to those situations in which a nurse&#146;s professional competence capacitates he/she to carry out actions which resolve that prejudicial situation a patient faces(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Iriarte, Antxon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanca Marín Fernández, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz Mendía, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;33(1): 55-62, ene. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79195</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La hipotermia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1858^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1858^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3694^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3694^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
