<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141669</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Musculoskeletal system pathology in aids patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: to study by means of Magnetic Resonance the different processes that can affect the musculoskeletal system in AIDS patients. Material and methods: We studied 22 AIDS patients who presented musculoskeletal system pathology. The affected area underwent simple X-Ray and MR. The MR study was performed using a 1 Tesla magnet. T1 and T2 weighted echo spin sequences, as well as sequences of short TI inversion recovery (STIR). In nine cases, intravenous gadolinium was used at a dose of 0.2cc / kg. The study plane was selected depending on the location of the lesion and surface coils were used when appropriate. In those patients showing pathology which was removed from the appendicular skeleton, the principal magnet was used as both transmitter and receiver. In one case, an On-Line Tomography (CT) was also carried out. The evaluated data were: a) localization; b) bony erosion; c) soft-tissue mass; d) articular effusion; e) cartilaginous changes; f) T1 and T2 signals, and g) gadolinium enhancement. A diagnosis was made on the basis of biopsy or clinical culture, and evolution. Results: Spinal cord alterations were the most frequent, being found in 13 cases. Twelve were caused by spondylodiscitis, 10 by tuberculosis, one by staphylococcal infection and one by candidiasis. In all cases, there appeared disk damage, as well as bone marrow signal alterations in the affected area and disks with soft-tissue. In the nine cases in which gadolinium was used, the disk, vertebral plates and soft-tissue mass heterogeneously enhanced, demonstrating an abscess with ring enhancement, and a central necrotic area in one case. In one patient, a spinal cord alteration due to non-Hodgkin's lymphoma was observed. In six cases, there was observed an infectious arthritis -- two in coxofemoral joints, three in knees and one in a glenohumeral joint. Isolated germs were staphylococcal in three cases -- one being Mycobacterium tuberculosis, another being M. kansasii and the third identified as Candida. In all cases, there was observed joint effusion, synovial thickening, joint cartilage damage and bony erosions. We found one case of myositis in the right anterior thigh muscle in which Streptococcus was isolated, one case of femoral bone infarction, and one case showed signs of lymphoma in the fibula. Conclusions: The spinal cord is that anatomical area of the musculoskeletal system most frequently affected in AIDS patients. It is primarily of the lumbar column, with tuberculous spondylodiscitis being the most common cause. Infectious arthritis is also commonly found in such patients, with a wider range of such related germs being present (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Bolado, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grande, Domingo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gorriño, Olatz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabala, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oleaga, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecumberi, Iñigo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar mediante resonancia magnética (RM) los diferentes procesos que pueden afectar al sistema musculosquelético en pacientes con sida. Material y métodos: Se han estudiado 22 pacientes con sida que presentaban patología del sistema musculosquelético. Se realizó radiografía simple del área afectada y RM. El estudio de RM se realizó con un imán de 1 Tesla. Se emplearon secuencias eco del epín (SE) potenciadas en T1 y T2 y secuencias de inversión recuperación (STIR). En nueve casos se utilizó gadolinio intravenoso a una dosis de 0,2 ml/kg. El plano de estudio se seleccionó dependiendo de la localización de la lesión y se emplearon bobinas de superficie en los casos susceptibles de ello y en aquellos pacientes en los que la patología estaba alejada del esqueleto apendicular se empleó el imán principal como transmisor y receptor. En un caso se realizó además estudio con tomografía computarizada (TC). Los datos evaluados fueron: a) localización; b) erosión ósea; c) masa de partes blandas; d) derrame articular; e) afectación cartilaginosa; f) señal en T1 y T2, y g) realce con gadolinio. Se llegó el diagnóstico por cultivo, biopsia o clínica y evolución. Resultados: La afectación más frecuente fue la de la columna (13 casos). Doce casos fueron espondilodiscitis, 10 por tuberculosis, una por Staphylococcus y una por Candida. En todos los casos existía una erosión de los platillos vertebrales, una alteración de la señal de la médula ósea de la zona afectada y del disco con masa de partes blandas. En los nueve casos en los que se empleó gadolinio el disco, los platillos vertebrales y la masa de partes blandas se realzaban de forma heterogénea demostrándose un absceso con realce en anillo y una zona necrótica central únicamente en un caso. En un paciente se demostró una de afectación de la columna por un linfoma no hodgkiniano. En seis casos se demostró una artritis infecciosa, dos en articulación coxofemoral, tres en rodilla y uno en articulación glenohumeral. Los gémenes aislados fueron Staphylococcus en tres casos, Mycobacterium tuberculosis en uno, M. kansasii en uno y Candida en uno. En todos los casos existía derrame articular, engrosamiento sinovial, afectación del cartílago articular y erosiones óseas. Encontramos un caso de miositis en el músculo recto anterior del muslo en la que se aisló Streptococcus; un caso de infarto óseo en el fémur y uno de linfoma en el peroné. Conclusiones: El área anatómica del sistema musculosquelético afectada con más frecuencia en pacientes con sida es la columna, fundamentalmente la columna lumbar, siendo la espondilodiscitis tuberculosa la causa más común. Es frecuente encontrar también en estos pacientes artritis infecciosas, siendo en estos casos el espectro de gérmenes implicados más amplio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);45(3): 125-132, mayo 2003. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141669</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología del sistema musculosquelético en pacientes con sida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29364^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7414^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200305</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
