<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163583</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Food selectivity in autism espectrum disorders: a sistematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a neurodevelopmental disorder, with can lead to eating disorders such as food selectivity. The hypothesis of this systematic review of observational studies is that children and adolescents with ASD are more selective than those with typically developing (TD). The goal was to assess the connection between the presence of ASD in children and adolescents under 18 years old, and the selectivity and food consumption. Methods: A bibliographical research was carried out in PubMed/MEDLINE 2.0 from January 2010 to December 2014. The search strategy of original studies was done by combining several terms of ASD and dietary habits. Results: A total of 465 studies were obtained. Finally, 11 studies were selected. These studies show that both children and adolescents with ASD tend to choose foods with high energy density such as juices, sugary drinks and snacks, and have a low consumption of fruits and vegetables as well as fish and dairy. Conclusions: Food selectivity is most common in children and adolescents with ASD than those with TD, which could affect their nutritional status. This should be taken into account after diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorente García, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pineda López, Olga</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Siles Sánchez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cándido Fernández-Cao, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arija Val, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El trastorno del espectro autista (TEA) es un desorden del neurodesarrollo, que puede conllevar problemas alimentarios como la selectividad alimentaria. La hipótesis de esta revisión sistemática de estudios observacionales es que los niños y adolescentes con TEA son más selectivos que los de desarrollo típico (DT). El objetivo fue valorar la relación entre la presencia del TEA en niños y adolescentes menores de 18 años y la selectividad y consumo alimentario. Métodos: Se ha realizado una búsqueda bibliográfica en PubMed/MEDLINE 2.0 desde enero del 2010 hasta diciembre del 2014. La estrategia de búsqueda de artículos originales fue realizada combinando varios términos del TEA y de hábitos dietéticos. Resultados: Se obtuvo un total de 465 artículos. Finalmente, 11 artículos fueron seleccionados. Los estudios muestran que los niños y adolescentes con TEA suelen escoger alimentos de elevada densidad energética, como zumos, bebidas azucaradas y snacks, y realizan un bajo consumo de frutas y verduras, así como de pescado y lácteos. Conclusiones: La selectividad alimentaria es más frecuente en los niños y adolescentes con TEA que en los de DT, lo que podría influir en su estado nutricional. Esto se debería tener en cuenta tras el diagnóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;21(2): 13-19, abr.-jun. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163583</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Selectividad alimentaria en los trastornos del espectro autista: una revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28032^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34570^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56096^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
