<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163020</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Substance use or abuse, internet use, psychopathology and suicidal ideation in adolescents?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Substance and Internet use or abuse, psychopathology and suicidal ideation appear to be related. The aim of this study is to investigate the association between use of psychotropic substances, inadequate Internet use, suicidal ideation and other psychopathological symptoms within the adolescent population. The present study was carried out as part of the Saving and Empowering Young Lives in Europe (SEYLE) project, funded by the European Union. The sample is composed of 1026 adolescents aged between 14 and 16 years from 12 state schools in Asturias (530 men and 496 women). This study adds to the possibility of knowing whether the SEYLE data is confirmed in a relatively isolated and recession hit province of Spain. In the present study the following consumption rates were obtained: a) alcohol 11.89% in males and 7.86% in females; b) tobacco: 4.15% and 5.44 % in males and females respectively; c) other drugs: 6.98% in males and 4.44% in females; d) maladaptive or pathological Internet use: 14.53% and 20.77% in males and females respectively. The variables that predict suicide ideation in the logistic regression model were: previous suicide attempts, depression, maladaptive or pathological Internet use, peer problems and alcohol consumption (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Mesa, Eva M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bobes, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wasserman, Danuta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarchiapone, Marco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Portilla, M Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Alvarez, Leticia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bousoño, Matilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Al-Halabí, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido, Marlen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carli, Vladimir</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burón, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bousoño, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáiz, Pilar Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hoven, Christina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galván, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias, Celso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso o abuso de sustancias o internet, la psicopatología y la ideación suicida parecen estar relacionadas. El objetivo del presente estudio es investigar la asociación en población adolescente entre consumo de sustancias potencialmente adictivas, uso inadecuado de internet, psicopatología e ideación suicida. El estudio forma parte del proyecto europeo Saving and Empowering Young Lives in Europe (SEYLE). La muestra está compuesta por 1026 adolescentes con edades comprendidas entre 14 y 16 años procedentes de 12 centros escolares públicos del Principado de Asturias (530 varones y 496 mujeres). El presente trabajo aporta la posibilidad de conocer si los datos generales del proyecto SEYLE varían en una zona relativamente aislada y socioeconómicamente en recesión. Las tasas obtenidas de consumo de las distintas sustancias y de uso de internet fueron: a) alcohol: 11,89% en varones y 7,86% en mujeres; b) tabaco: 4,15% y 5,44% en varones y mujeres respectivamente; c) otras drogas: 6,98% en varones y un 4,44% en mujeres; d) uso de internet desadaptativo o patológico: 14,53% y 20,77% en varones y mujeres respectivamente. Se ha observado que las variables con capacidad predictiva sobre las conductas suicidas fueron: tentativas suicidas previas, síntomas depresivos, uso desadaptativo o patológico de internet, problemas con los compañeros y consumo de alcohol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);29(2): 97-104, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163020</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso y abuso de sustancias psicotrópicas e internet, psicopatología e ideación suicida en adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30236^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
