<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98009</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The evolution of Military Health in Valencia during the Spanish Civil War (1936-1939)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Precedents and purposes: After the military insurrection of July 18, 1936 the Republican Army remained partially dismantled, affecting Military Health. In case of Valencia, it was assumed rapidly by Sanitary Popular Committee, a revolutionary organism that led the sanitary response of Valencia to the Civil War. Later, the Republican Government proceeded to recover power throghout centralizing measures, as the militarization of some hospitals. At this the time an authentic Military Health returned to be articulated. The aim of this work is to study the evolution of Military Health in Valencia, one of the most important republican zones. Material and method: Documentation generated by the abundant hospitals installed in the city of Valencia is analyzed, studying as well changes that took place after militarization of some  sanitary centers. This information has been consulted in the File of the County Council of Valencia. Results: Military Health in Valencia during the Spanish Civil War went through several stages, as it evolved from initial improvisation to later organization. Conclusions: A bidirectional relation is established between the degree of Military Health organization and troop&#146;s efficiency (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Munayco Sánchez, A. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Ferrandis, X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivos: Tras la insurrección militar del 18 de julio de 1936 el Ejército de la República quedó parcialmente desarticulado, resultando afectada la Sanidad Militar. En el caso de Valencia, ésta fue asumida rápidamente por el Comité Sanitario Popular, un organismo revolucionario que lideró la respuesta sanitaria de Valencia a la Guerra Civil. Posteriormente, el Gobierno Republicano procedió a recuperar el poder a través de medidas de carácter centralizador, como fue la militarización de algunos hospitales. Fue entonces cuando volvió a articularse una auténtica Sanidad Militar. El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar la evolución de la Sanidad Militar en Valencia, una de las zonas republicanas más importantes. Material y métodos: Se analiza la documentación generada por los abundantes hospitales instalados en la  ciudad de Valencia, estudiando los cambios que se produjeron tras la militarización de algunos centros sanitarios. Esta información ha sido consultada en el Archivo de la Excma. Diputación Provincial de Valencia. Resultados: La Sanidad Militar en Valencia durante la Guerra Civil española atravesó varias etapas, evolucionado desde la improvisación inicial a la posterior organización. Conclusiones: Se establece una relación bidireccional entre el grado de organización de la Sanidad Militar y la efectividad de la tropa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;67(4): 383-389, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus, graf, btab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La evolución de la Sanidad Militar en Valencia durante La Guerra Civil Española (1936-1939)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9075^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15259</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28438^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6928^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51708</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
