<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63844</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aging of the population increases the possibility of attending to problems related to cognitive functioning in Primary Care. In spite of the obstacles existing for the diagnosis of these disorders in Primary Care, this may fundamentally be a clinical condition in which interdisciplinary participation of all the professionals involved, adequate coordination between levels and firm involvement of the social-health care institutions are recommended. There is currently no evidence to recommend systematic screening. Early diagnosis that is based on signs of suspicion in the cognitive, behavioral and functional areas of life is the best option. Syndromic diagnosis is based on information compiled from the patient's medical history, the neuropsychological examination (abridged version) and physical examination. The diagnosis could be complemented with information from the etiological symptoms, the functional situation, the clinical evolution, the socio-family assessment and the degree of work overload to the caregiver. The objective is to draw up an individual care plan based on pharmacological and non-pharmacological interventions addressed not only to the patient but also to his/her caregiver and the surrounding setting</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riu Subirana, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Rodríguez, V. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrieta Antón, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El envejecimiento poblacional incrementa la posibilidad de atender problemas relacionados con el funcionamiento cognitivo en Atención Primaria. A pesar de los obstáculos existentes para el diagnóstico de estos trastornos en este nivel asistencial, este es posible al ser un proceso fundamentalmente clínico, en el que se recomienda el trabajo interdisciplinar de todos los profesionales implicados, la adecuada coordinación entre niveles y la decidida implicación de las instituciones sociosanitarias. No existen evidencias para recomendar el cribado sistemático. El diagnóstico temprano, a partir de los signos de sospecha en las áreas cognitiva, comportamental y funcional, constituye la mejor opción en el momento actual. El diagnóstico sindrómico se basa en los datos recogidos en la historia clínica, la exploración neuropsicológica abreviada y la exploración física. Se recomienda completar el diagnóstico hasta obtener los datos de sospecha etiológica, situación funcional, estadio evolutivo, valoración sociofamiliar y grado de sobrecarga del cuidador. El objetivo es la elaboración del plan de cuidados individualizado que se basa en intervenciones farmacológicas y no farmacológicas, dirigidas no solo al paciente, sino también al cuidador y a su entorno</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(2): 87-90, feb. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63844</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25123</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2850^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200802</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
