<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86462</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Muscle characteristics and anaerobic and aerobic maximal power in competence cyclists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A group of Venezuelan cyclists from the Lara State selection, aged 20 ± 2 years, formed by 9 males and 5 females, wasstudied. Seven of them were long-distance cyclists, 4 sprinters and 4 middle-distance cyclists. Maximal aerobic power(VO2 max) was evaluated, as well as lactacid (Wingate test) and alactacid power (vertical jump test). A quadriceps musclebiopsy was taken for muscle fiber classification, assessment of capillaries and determination of the enzymes citrate synthase (CS), ß-hydroxacil-CoA-dehydrogenase (HAD) and lactic dehydrogenase (LDH). The male group showed higher values in all tests, except in fatigue index, which was similar to the female group. CS muscle levels were higherin men, but there were not differences in fiber area and capillarity compared to females. The highest percentage in typeI fibers was found in the long-distance cyclists (63±7 %), also the most elevated CS level (29.2±5.5 &amp;#956;mol/min.gr) and the highest capillary density (417±31 capillaries/mm2). Middle-distance cyclists showed the highest proportion of IIafiber type (50±5 %). There was a direct correlation between CS level and Watts/Kg in the jumping test (r=.55), in the HAD level and mean power/Kg in Wingate test (r=0.69), and between LDH level and the all the results of the Wingatetest (r=0.52 to r=0.60).In conclusion, in this group of cyclist, aerobic and anaerobic power tests seemed to be more related to muscle changes due to training that to muscle fiber type proportions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Noelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alexander, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Sonia H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera, Alvaro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Subiela, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jimeno, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se estudiaron 15 ciclistas de la selección del Estado Lara de Venezuela, 9 del sexo masculino y 5 del femenino, de 20± 2 años. Siete eran fondistas, 4 semifondistas y 4 velocistas. La potencia aeróbica fue evaluada por el consumo máximo de oxígeno (VO2 max), la potencia anaeróbica lactácida por la prueba de Wingate y la potencia anaeróbica alactácida por la prueba del salto vertical. Se practicó biopsia del músculo cuadriceps para la clasificación de los tipos de fibras, evaluación de los capilares y determinación de las enzimas citrato sintetasa (CS), ß-hidroxiacil-CoA-deshidrogenasa(HAD) y deshidrogenasa láctica (LDH). El grupo masculino alcanzó mayores valores en todas las pruebas, excepto en el índice de fatiga en el que no difirió del grupo femenino. El músculo mostró niveles más altos de CS en los hombres y fue similar en área de las fibras y en capilaridad respecto a las mujeres. Los fondistas mostraron mayor proporción de fibras tipo I (63±7 %), mayor nivel de CS (29,2±5,5 &amp;#956;mol/min.gr) y mayor densidad capilar (417±31capilares /mm2). Los mediofondistas presentaron mayor porcentaje de fibras tipo IIa (50±5 %). Se encontró correlación entre la CS y los Watts/kg en la prueba del salto (r=0,55), entre la HAD y la potencia promedio/kg en Wingate (r=0,69)y entre la LDH y los resultados de Wingate (r=0,52 a r=0,60).En conclusión, las potencias aeróbica y anaeróbica de los ciclistas del grupo estudiado parecen estar más relacionadas con los efectos del entrenamiento en el músculo, que con su composición miofibrilar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;24(119): 168-178, mayo-jun. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86462</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Carazterísticas musculares y potencia anaeróbica y aeróbica máximas en ciclistas de competición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32981^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4877^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4877^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52940^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23556^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9334^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32981^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32128^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
