<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30892</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Descriptive study of behavioural disorders in mild cognitive impairment</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Blasco, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu Català, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu Catalá, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fages, EM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introduction. Mild cognitive impairment (MCI) is defined as an abnormality in cognitive function not provoking a noticeable disability in activities of daily living in the affected person. In a group of patients with MCI, we propose to observe and to quantify the presence of behavioral disorders, using the neuropsychiatric inventory (NPI). Patients and methods. NPI is a known instrument in evaluation of this kind of disorders in patients with dementia, and it is a semi structured interview with a relevant informer or relative to the patient. NPI was applied to a series of 100 cases (61 women and 39 men) of MCI, diagnosed as usual in our settings. Mean age was 74.3 ± 10 years, and mean MEC (Spanish modified version of MMSE) 25.57 ± 4.2 (over a maximum of 35 points). Results. Most prevalent disorder was depression, in 36 % of cases, and other frequent findings were irritability (35%), anxiety (24%) and apathy (19%). In some cases, agitation (4%), abnormal motor behavior (3%) and delusions (1%) were detected. Hallucination, desinhibition and euphoria or elation were not detected in this series. Conclusion. Data show a certain similarity with occidental culture environment, globally considered. The presence of behavioral and psychological disorders in patients with MCI could be a marker for later development of dementia. NPI can be a usable tool when detection and evaluation of these symptoms is required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;38(4): 323-326, feb. 2004. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30892</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio descriptivo de los trastornos conductuales en el deterioro cognitivo leve</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1545</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
