<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146701</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What is hidden behind the Baking Tray Task? Study of sensibility and specificity in right-hemispheric stroke patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Tham and Tegnér proposed the Baking Tray Task (BTT) as a fast simple assessment test for detecting spatial negligence. However, very few studies have examined its validity as a diagnostic test. Aim. To analyse the diagnostic validity of the BTT by measuring its specificity and sensitivity in a sample of subjects with right hemisphere strokes. Subjects and methods. Forty-eight patients with right hemisphere vascular lesions were distributed in two groups (negligence group, n = 35; non-negligence group, n = 13) according to the scores obtained in a battery of visuospatial examination tests. The participants&#146; performance on the BTT was compared with that of a healthy control group (n = 12). Results. The results showed a high level of sensitivity of the BTT, but low specificity. The performance on the BTT of eight of the 13 members of the non-negligence group was suggestive of negligence. Conclusions. The BTT has proved to be a sensitive test for the detection of spatial negligence. Yet, based on its low specificity, its use alone as a single diagnostic test is not recommended (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peña Casanova, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enseñat, Antònia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Molina, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio López, Celeste</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Carrión, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Fernández, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig Rovira, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Tham y Tegnér propusieron el Baking Tray Task (BTT) como una prueba de evaluación rápida y simple para la detección de negligencia espacial. No obstante, apenas existen estudios que hayan examinado su validez como prueba diagnóstica. Objetivo. Analizar la validez diagnóstica del BTT, midiendo su especificidad y sensibilidad, en una muestra de sujetos con ictus hemisféricos derechos. Sujetos y métodos. Cuarenta y ocho pacientes con lesiones vasculares hemisféricas derechas distribuidos en dos grupos (grupo negligencia, n = 35; grupo no negligencia, n = 13) en función de las puntuaciones obtenidas en una batería de exploración visuoespacial. La ejecución de los participantes en el BTT se comparó con un grupo control sano (n = 12). Resultados. Los resultados mostraron una alta sensibilidad del BTT, pero una baja especificidad. Ocho de los 13 integrantes del grupo no negligencia obtuvieron un rendimiento en el BTT sugestivo de negligencia. Conclusiones. El BTT se muestra como un test sensible para la detección de la negligencia espacial. Sin embargo, basándonos en su baja especificidad, no es recomendable su uso aislado como prueba única de diagnóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;61(12): 543-549, 16 dic., 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146701</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué se esconde tras el Baking Tray Task? Estudio de sensibilidad y especificidad en sujetos con ictus hemisférico derecho</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53994^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9674^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1951^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53994^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36435</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
