<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109319</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic performance and factorial structure of the Beck Depres-sion Inventory&#150;Second Edition (BDI-II)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study had to aims. The first aim was to analyze the diagnostic performance of the Spanish version of the Beck Depression Inventory&#150;Second Edition (BDI-II) in a sample of patients with psychological disorders. The second aim was to examine whether the one- and two-factor solutions previously found for the BDI-II in similar samples are replicable, and, if it is so, to analyze the independent contribution of the general factor and the two specific factors to the variance of the BDI-II. The BDI-II, along with the mood disorder module of the Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV Axis I disorders, Clinical Version (SCID-I VC) and a clinician-administered checklist for depressive symptoms, were administered to a Spanish sample of 322 adult outpatients with a variety of psychological disorders. Taking as a criterion the clinical diagnosis based on the SCID-I VC and the checklist for depressive symptoms, the BDI-II showed an accept-able diagnostic performance to discriminate between patients with major depressive disorder and those without depression. Factor analyses suggested that the BDI-II assess a general depression dimension composed of two related factors (somatic and cognitive symptoms), but these factors hardly explained any additional variance beyond accounted for by the full-scale score (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Vera, María Paz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tenía dos objetivos. Primero, analizar el rendimiento diagnóstico de la versión española del Inventario de Depresión de Beck-II (BDI-II) en una muestra de pacientes con trastornos psicológicos y, segundo, examinar si las soluciones unifactoriales y bifactoriales del BDI-II encontradas previamente en muestras similares son replicables y, de ser así, analizar la contribución relativa del factor general y de los dos factores específicos a la varianza del BDI-II. El BDI-II, junto con el módulo de los trastornos del estado de ánimo de la Entrevista Clínica Estructurada para los Trastornos del Eje I del DSM-IV (SCID-I VC) y un listado de cotejo de síntomas depresivos completado por el clínico, fueron aplicados a una muestra española de 322 pacientes adultos ambulatorios con diversos tras-tornos psicológicos. Tomando como criterio el diagnóstico clínico basado en la SCID-I VC y el listado de cotejo de síntomas depresivos, el BDI-II demostró un rendimiento diagnóstico aceptable para discriminar entre pacientes con trastorno depresivo mayor y pacientes sin depresión. Los análisis factoriales indicaron que el BDI-II mide una dimensión general de de-presión compuesta por dos factores relacionados (somático y cognitivo), pero estos factores apenas explicaban varianza adicional más allá de la puntuación global (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;29(1): 66-75, ene.-abr. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109319</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rendimiento diagnóstico y estructura factorial del Inventario de Depresión de Beck-II (BDI-II)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51593^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51593^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
