<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76486</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The psychological contract in the Public Administration: rights and obligations of the public employee from his or her own perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper examines the contents and status of the psychological contract in a sample of697 employees in a Public Administration organization. Results show that employees perceive that the organization makes promises at a moderate level (3.6 &#150;range 1-7) and keeps them at a similar level (3.7) whereas they perceive themselves making promises and keeping them at higher levels (5.6 and 5.8 respectively). Employer promises have been found to be more diverse as compared to employee promises: three different types of promises for the employers (well being, wages, job security, and participation in decision making) and only one type for the employees &#150;grouped into the same factor. Significant gender differences have been obtained for the employers&#146; perception of promise making and keeping (higher perception for males) although no differences were found in equity perception. Significant differences were also found concerning the type of contract &#150;promises and their fulfillment concerning salary and job security are perceived higher by permanent employees whereas temporary employees perceive more equity in the relationships. Finally between rank differences were found in well-being in the workplace, participation in decision making, the three employer fulfillment factors above mentioned, fairness and trust. Theoretical and practical implications are finally discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gracia, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mañas, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peiró, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo estudia el contenido y estado del contrato psicológico en una muestra compuesta por 697 trabajadores pertenecientes a una organización de la Administración Pública española. Los resultados muestran que los empleados perciben que la organización realiza las promesas consideradas en un nivel medio (3.6 en una escala con rango de 1 a 7) y presenta un grado de cumplimiento similar (3.7) mientras que las promesas realizadas por los empleados alcanzan niveles más elevados (5.6), según sus propias percepciones al igual que su cumplimiento (5.8). También se observa una mayor diversificación de la percepción de los tipos de promesas del empleador (agrupadas en: bienestar laboral, salario y estabilidad, y participación en la toma de decisiones) que en las del empleado (agrupadas en un único factor). Se han obtenido diferencias significativas en percepciones de promesas y cumplimiento en función del sexo (los varones presentan generalmente niveles más elevados en lo que se refiere a los empleadores) aunque no hay diferencias en las percepciones de equidad. En función del tipo de contrato, las promesas relativas al salario y a la estabilidad laboral muestran resultados mas elevados en los permanentes, aunque es mayor la percepción de equidad en los temporales. Finalmente, se han obtenido diferencias significativas en función del nivel jerárquico en el factor &#147;bienestar laboral&#148; y &#147;participación en la toma de decisiones&#148; de obligaciones del empleador, en los tres factores relativos al cumplimiento del empleador, en justicia y en confianza. Todos estos resultados se discuten y analizan señalándose las implicaciones teóricas y prácticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);23(3): 389-418, 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76486</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El contrato psicológico en la Administración Pública: derechos y obligaciones del empleado público desde su propia perspectiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12831</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37687^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36443</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51571</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
