<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135901</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of the epidemiological method in determining preventive measures: pesticide poisoning</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To confirm a chlorpyrifos and cipermetrina poisoning in a workplace, to identify causes in this process and to determine preventive measures. Methods: A retrospective and prospective longitudinal designs accounting for four months of follow-up. Cases were identified with two questionnaires through a personal interview among study population and with the measurement of erythrocyte cholinesterase (ChE) changes. We determined environmental and surfaces of presence pesticides and investigated the methods of application and preventing measures. To confirm the outbreak we compared symptoms incidence and temporal distribution between study and reference population. Results: There were 49 cases with irritative symptoms among a 65 study persons. Symptoms showed up with an outbreak pattern beginning the first exposure day. A 80.0% of the exposed population presented irritative symptoms the next week from application and a 9.7% of the reference population; related to neurotoxic symptoms a 72% in front of a 12%. Five hours exposure risk was higher 2.6 (IC 1.2-5.6) than that of 0-2 hours. High chlorpyrifos and cipermetrina concentration was identified in surfaces and environment. ChE changes among cases followed the known pattern: a decrease following a slight increase later on. Conclusions: We confirmed biocides intoxication&#146;s outbreak existence in a workplace and we identified the causes that contributed to its extension and intensit (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Molinero, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pañella, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maldonado, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Confirmación de un brote de intoxicación por clorpirifos o cipermetrina después de un tratamiento realizado con Matul HQ en un centro de trabajo de atención al público, identificación del proceso causal y determinación de medidas preventivas. Métodos: Se utilizó un diseño longitudinal retrospectivo y prospectivo con cuatro meses de seguimiento. Se identificaron los casos mediante dos cuestionarios administrados por entrevista personal a toda la población de estudio y la determinación en sangre de los cambios en la Acetilcolinesterasa Intraeritrocitaria. Se analizó la presencia de biocidas en ambiente y superficies y se investigó el proceso de aplicación y las medidas preventivas. Para la confirmación del brote se utilizó la comparación de incidencias con una población de referencia. Resultados: Se identificaron 49 casos con síntomas irritativos en una población de 65 personas (75,4%). La aparición de síntomas mostró un patrón de brote de inicio en el primer día de la exposición. El 80% de los expuestos presentaron síntomas irritativos la semana siguiente a la aplicación frente a un 9,7% en la población de referencia, y el 72% frente al 12% para los síntomas neurotóxicos. Existió un mayor riesgo de afectación (RR= 2,6 (IC 95% 1,2-5,6)) para los expuestos a más de 5 horas en el centro que para los expuestos 0-2 horas. Se identificaron clorpirifos y cipermetrina en ambiente y superficies. Conclusión: Se confirmó la existencia de un brote de intoxicación por biocidas, con mayor riesgo a mayor exposición. Las medidas de prevención de estos accidentes deberán tener en cuenta las características del local, sistemas de climatización, tiempo de permanencia en el ambiente del producto, actividad laboral e información que reciben los individuos sobre los riesgos para su salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);5(4): 151-158, oct.-dic. 2002. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135901</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del método epidemiológico en la determinación de medidas de prevención: Una intoxicación por biocidas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11471^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50301</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51562</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
