<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-92736</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interdisciplinary boarding of the health and the disease: Contributions to the nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present paper has as object to be introduced in the old discussion initiated in the Seventies by the medical Anthropology and more ahead, by the Sociology about the differences that exist between planning&#146;s of the health and the disease that have been defined by the medical or biomedical knowledge and the planning that have been constructed by the own knowledge of the communities or the groups from their cultural heaps and the material conditions in which they live. The previous thing, like a map course that nursing task must consider, like discipline that tries to take care of the experience of health in a context that cannot be defined as neutral, but is influenced by the culture, the policy and the economy of a society in a historical moment dice. By this, some of the considerations with respect to the importance for the discipline appear of considering the constructions surroundings to the health and the disease of the care subjects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Laza Vásquez, Celmira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas Martínez, Fernando José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El artículo tiene como objeto introducirse en la discusión iniciada los años setenta por la Antropología médica y más adelante, por la Sociología sobre las diferencias que existen entre las conceptualizaciones de la salud y la enfermedad definidas por el saber médico o biomédico y las construidas por el saber propio de las comunidades o colectivos desde sus acervos culturales y las condiciones materiales en las que viven. Lo anterior, como un derrotero que debe tenerse en cuenta en el quehacer de Enfermería, como disciplina que cuida la experiencia de salud en un contexto que no se puede definir como neutro, sino influenciado por la cultura, la política y la economía de una sociedad en un momento histórico dado. Además, se presentan algunas de las consideraciones respecto a la importancia para la disciplina de tener en cuenta las construcciones en torno a la salud y la enfermedad de los sujetos de cuidado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;18(1): 37-41, ene. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-92736</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Abordaje Interdisciplinario de la Salud y la Enfermedad: Aportes a la Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28448</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3487</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28564</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200901</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
