<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85244</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Preliminary results on dietary fibre intake in Spain and health benefits associated to soluble fiber intake</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Many studies have found an association between dietary fiber intake and a protective effect against a number of chronic diseases such as colon cancer, cardiovascular diseases, constipation and obesity, among other. However, fiber intake in western countries are low, distant from recommended values. Methods: In this ecological study, total dietary fiber consumption, soluble and insoluble, in Spanish households has been estimated and its association with morbidity and morbidity data for selected diseases in the period 2004-2008. Results: Average total fiber intake in Spanish households during the study period was 16.24 ± 0.15 g/day, below recommended intakes for dietary fiber. A negative correlation (p &lt; 0.05) was observed between total fiber and insoluble fiber intake and mortality for ischaemic heart disease (myocardial infarction), cardiac failure and stroke. No significant correlation was found with soluble fiber intake. Conclusions: Consumption of foods rich in fiber is adequate for the prevention of different chronic diseases, particularly foods rich in insoluble dietary fiber, such as cereals and pulses(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Roso Calvo de Mora, Baltasar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Olleros Conde, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Muchos estudios relacionan el consumo de fibra dietética (FD) con la protección contra numerosas enfermedades crónicas, como cáncer de colon, enfermedades cardiovasculares, el estreñimiento y la obesidad, entre otros. Sin embargo, las ingestas de FD en los países occidentales son bajas y bastante alejadas de los valores recomendados. Método: Se ha estudiado el consumo de FD total, soluble e insoluble en los hogares españoles y su relación con la morbimortalidad por algunas enfermedades durante el periodo 2004-2008. Resultados: El consumo medio de FD total en los hogares españoles durante el periodo estudiado fue 16,24 ± 0,15 g/día, mucho menor que las ingestas de FD recomendadas. Se ha observado una correlación negativa (p &lt; 0,05) entre el consumo de FD total e insoluble con la mortalidad por infarto de miocardio, insuficiencia cardíaca y enfermedades cerebrovasculares. No se ha encontrando correlaciones significativas con el consumo de FD soluble Conclusiones: El consumo de alimentos ricos en fibra es adecuado para la prevención de diferentes enfermedades degenerativas, especialmente el consumo de alimentos ricos en fibra insoluble, como los cereales o las leguminosas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;16(3): 147-153, jul.-sep.2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85244</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Avance de resultados sobre consumo de fibra en España y beneficios asociados a la ingesta de fibra insoluble</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23550</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50324</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50311</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2560^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
