<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051528</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0367</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Illness and falling ill in psychiatry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In current clinical psychiatry the aims is to have well founded physiopathological references and valid target symptoms with reliably classifiable elements on which to base a general theory of psychiatric illness. Nevertheless there is some confusion over the meaning and implication of this for psychiatric illness and the process of falling ill, in terms of theoretical constructs and their repercussions in clinical practice. As a contribution to psychitric theory, we tackle the facts and values bound up in the terms psychiatric illness and falling psychiatrically ill, bearing in mind both their objective and subjective aspects, the social references of variations in symptoms and the consequent modifications in taxonomy and evaluation</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lillo Roldán, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina León, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Díaz, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La clínica psiquiátrica actual aspira a poseer referentes fisiopatológicos fundados y síntomas diana válidos y fiables de sus elementos clasificables y que llo sea la base de su teoría general del enfermar psiquiátrico. Sin embargo, existe confusión entre lo que significa y representa ello para la enfermedad y para el enfermar psiquiátrico, como constructos teóricos y sus repercusiones en la clínica. En este sentido se aborda, como una contribución a la teoría psiquiátrica, los hechos y valores que conllevan los términos enfermedad y enfermar psiquiátrico, teniendo en cuenta las vertientes objetivas y subjetivas de los mismos, las referencias sociales de la variabilidad sintomática y las modificaciones que ello produce en los órdenes taxonómicos y evaluativos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. psiquiatr;69(3): 159-170, jul.-sept. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051528</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermar y enfermedades en psiquiatría</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23899</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36377^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
