<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90952</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rhupus: report of 4 cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present the clinical and serological characteristics of four patients with rhupus (Simon&#146;s definition). The 4 patients with rhupus presented ACR criteria for SLE as well as for RA, ANA positive with titers ranging from 1/80 to 1/5,250, and positive anti-DNA, with the predominance of symmetrical erosive polyarthritis. We found anti-CCP positivity and high titers in 3 of the 4 patients, and positive antiphospholipid antibodies in 2 (anticardiolipin and LA), without manifestation of antiphospholipid syndrome. One patient presented renal affection, and 2 subcutaneous nodules. The 3 patients with RA preceded the manifestations of SLE by an average of 7.7 years. Two patients were refractory to conventional DMAR in combination, requiring biologic and mycophennolate mofetil(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pair, Sergio Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benavente, Emilio Pablo Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos las características clínicas y serológicas de cuatro pacientes con diagnóstico de rhupus (definición de Simon). Presentaban criteriosACRtanto para LEScomopara AR, factor antinuclear (FAN) positivo a títulos desde 1/80 a 1/5.250 y anti-DNAn positivo, predominandocomomanifestación clínica una poliartritis simétrica erosiva. Se halló anti-CCP positiva y a títulos altos en 3 de los 4 pacientes y anticuerpos antifosfolípidos en 2 (anticardiolipina y anticoagulante lúpico), sin manifestación de síndrome antifosfolípido. Sólo un paciente presentó compromiso renal y 2 nódulos subcutáneos. En 3 de los pacientes el diagnóstico de AR precedió a las manifestaciones de LES en un promedio de 7,7 a&#152;nos. La mitad fue refractaria a fármacos antirreumáticos modificadores de la enfermedad (FAME) convencionales en combinación y requirió biológicos y micofenolato mofetil(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);7(5): 333-335, sep.-oct.2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rhupus: descripción de 4 casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3258^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8356^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1184^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32355^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1174^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32355^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
