<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164013</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-7615</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">'Overcome a bad shot&#146;: an ethnographic study of young people experiencing acute alcohol intoxication in an emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The current pattern of intensive recreational use of alcohol leads sometimes excesses favoring the support of young people in the emergency department. The objective of this research was to study the experience and perspective of young people after an acute alcohol intoxication. This is an ethnographic study carried out in an emergency department of a hospital in the city of Granada (Spain) by purposive sampling with 95 young people. We develop a qualitative content analysis. Our results show that youth served often consider their experience with AAI as a &#145;bad shot&#146; that is necessary to go and forget. They justified this AAI with causes unrelated to alcohol abuse (have not eaten, bad luck, diabetes, etc.). The urgency department is the last therapeutic measure to reverse the adverse effects of AAI and do not consider stop drinking, although most of the consulted youth recognized that they need to moderate the alcohol consumption. We discuss the findings providing ideas to make interventions in the emergency departments more sensitive to the needs of young people and the organization of health services (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romo-Avilés, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos-Marcos, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-García, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarragona-Camacho, Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marquina-Márquez, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad, el patrón recreativo de consumo intensivo de alcohol conlleva, en ocasiones, que los jóvenes terminen en los servicios de urgencias. El objetivo de esta investigación ha sido estudiar la experiencia y perspectiva de jóvenes tras una intoxicación etílica aguda. Se trata de un estudio etnográfico llevado a cabo en el servicio de urgencias de un hospital de la ciudad de Granada (España) mediante un muestreo intencional con 95 jóvenes. Se realizó un análisis de contenido cualitativo. Nuestros resultados muestran que los jóvenes atendidos suelen considerar su experiencia con una intoxicación etílica como un «mal trago» que hay que pasar y olvidar. Justifican dicha intoxicación con razones no relacionadas con el consumo abusivo de alcohol (no habían comido, mala suerte, padecer diabetes, etc.). El servicio de urgencias es la última medida terapéutica para revertir los efectos adversos de una intoxicación etílica aguda y no consideran, tras su experiencia, dejar de beber, aunque la mayoría de la muestra consultada puso de manifiesto la necesidad de moderar el consumo de alcohol. Los resultados se discuten proporcionando ideas para poder realizar intervenciones en los servicios de urgencias que sean adecuadas a las necesidades de las personas jóvenes y la organización de los servicios sanitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. drogodepend;42(2): 11-26, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164013</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">&#145;Pasar el mal trago&#146;: un estudio etnográfico de jóvenes que experimentan una intoxicación etílica aguda en un servicio de urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d439^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d439^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35514^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
