<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149240</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Doppler ultrasound study and venous mapping in chronic venous insufficiency</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Chronic venous insufficiency of the lower limbs is very prevalent. In recent decades, Doppler ultrasound has become the method of choice to study this condition, and it is considered essential when surgery is indicated. This article aims to establish a method for the examination, including venous mapping and preoperative marking. To this end, we review the venous anatomy of the lower limbs and the pathophysiology of chronic venous insufficiency and explain the basic hemodynamic concepts and the terminology required to elaborate a radiological report that will enable appropriate treatment planning and communication with other specialists. We briefly explain the CHIVA (the acronym for the French term &#147;cure conservatrice et hémodynamique de l&#146;insuffisance veineuse en ambulatoire&#148; = conservative hemodynamic treatment for chronic venous insufficiency) strategy, a minimally invasive surgical strategy that aims to restore correct venous hemodynamics without resecting the saphenous vein (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Solís, MF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Carriazo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez de las Heras, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mármol Vázquez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La insuficiencia venosa crónica (IVC) de las extremidades inferiores es una enfermedad muy prevalente. La ecografía Doppler se ha establecido en las últimas décadas como el método de elección en el estudio de esta patología, por lo que resulta imprescindible ante una eventual indicación quirúrgica. El objetivo de este trabajo es establecer una metodología en la exploración, incluyendo la realización de cartografía y el marcaje prequirúrgico. Para ello revisaremos la anatomía venosa de los miembros inferiores y la fisiopatología de la IVC explicando los conceptos hemodinámicos básicos y la terminología necesarios para la realización de un informe radiológico que permita una adecuada planificación terapéutica y comunicación con otros especialistas. Explicaremos brevemente la estrategia CHIVA (cura hemodinámica de la insuficiencia venosa ambulatoria), método quirúrgico mínimamente invasivo que tiene como objetivo restaurar la hemodinámica venosa sin extirpar la vena safena (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);58(1): 7-15, ene.-feb. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149240</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la insuficiencia venosa crónica mediante ecografía Doppler y realización de cartografía venosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15096^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12878^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14854^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12878^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1290^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31992^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15095^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1290^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1290^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15096^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1290^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31992^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14854^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
