<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149044</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Specif language disorders: their diagnosis. Classification and study using magnetoencephalography</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Specific language disorder (SLD) is defined as a disorder in which language is slow and retarded with respect to the patient's chronological age, and which is not related to a sensory-auditory or motor deficit or to a pervasive development disorder; in other words, structural and functional neurological developmental disorders must be excluded. After many studies and attempts to reach an agreement, specific language disorders have been broadly classified into two groups: specific expressive language disorder and specific receptive-expressive language disorder. Aims. Our objective was to study SLD using magnetoencephalography (MEG) in order to look for epileptiform manifestations in precise language areas. Patients and methods. We studied a sample made up of 11 patients with SLD, one of whom had LandauKleffner syndrome and one with cryptogenic-type SLD. The criteria used were age-dependent autism exclusion tests and specific language tests for SLD. The MSI technique was carried out on all the patients, by magnetic resonance and MEG. Results. A characteristic pattern is obtained for SLD in the form of irregular spike and polyspike-wave discharges in bilateral frontal channels. The dipoles were situated mainly in the left perisylvian areas. Conclusions. The study of specific language disorders using MEG enables us to identify the SLD included in a proposed classification as primary-type specific language disorder, cryptogenic-type specific language disorder and secondary-type type specific language disorder, like Landau-Kleffner síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valls Santausana, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosendo Moreno, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perich Alsina, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maestú, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Yunta, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvadó Salvadó, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Morales, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palau Baduell, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trastorno específico del lenguaje (TEL) se define cono un trastorno del lenguaje lento y retrasado respecto su edad cronológica, que no tenga relación con un déficit sensorioauditivo, motor ni trastorno generalizado del desarrollo, es decir, deben excluirse las alteraciones neurológicas estructurales y funcionales del desarrollo. Los trastornos específicos del lenguaje, después de largos estudios y consenso se han clasificado en dos grandes grupos: el trastorno específico del lenguaje expresivo y el trastorno específico del lenguaje receptivo-expresivo. Objetivo. Estudiar los TEL mediante magnetoencefalografía (MEG) con el fin de encontrar manifestaciones epileptiformes en áreas precisas del lenguaje. Pacientes y métodos. Muestra formada por 11 pacientes que presentaban TEL, uno que presentaba síndrome de Landau-Kleffner y uno con TEL de tipo criptogenético. Los criterios utilizados han sido tests dependientes deedad para exclusión de autismo y tests específicos del lenguaje para TEL. A todos los pacientes se les practicó la técnica MSI, mediante resonancia magnética y MEG. Resultados. Se obtiene un patrón característico para los TEL en forma de descargas de punta y polipunta-onda irregular en canales frontales bilaterales. Los dipolos se sitúan predominantemente en áreas perisilvianas izquierdas. Conclusión. El estudio de los trastornos del lenguaje mediante la MEG nos permite identificar los TEL considerados en una propuesta de clasificación como trastorno específico del lenguaje de tipo primario, trastorno específico del lenguaje de tipo criptogenético y trastorno específico del lenguaje de tipo secundario, como el síndrome de Landau-Kleffner (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;40(supl.1): s115-s120, 15 ene. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149044</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos específicos del lenguaje: diagnóstico, tipificación y estudios con magnetoencefalografía</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
