<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050770</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Natural history of and risk factors for idiopathic atrial fibrillation recurrence (FAP Registry)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The natural history of idiopathic atrial fibrillation is not well understood. The aim of this study was to investigate the frequency of and risk factors for disease recurrence. Methods. The study involved 115 patients with a first episode of paroxysmal atrial fibrillation of unknown origin who were included the FAP registry, which contains data from 11 district hospitals in Catalonia, Spain. All patients underwent comprehensive clinical, laboratory, electro-cardiographic and echocardiographic investigations at baseline and were followed up periodically every 6 months to identify the occurrence of new symptomatic episodes and their complications. Results. During a mean follow-up period of 912 (445) days, 32 (27.8%) patients experienced recurrence of atrial fibrillation. Those who experienced recurrence had a significantly higher left ventricular ejection fraction (P=.023) and smaller end-systolic volume (P&lt;.001), and they were more likely to consume alcohol regularly (P=.013). Cox regression analysis confirmed that these variables had independent prognostic value. In contrast, the occurrence of syncope during the initial episode was associated with a lower likelihood of recurrence (P=.017). Conclusions. The risk of recurrence of idiopathic atrial fibrillation was high, and was enhanced by moderate alcohol consumption and increased left ventricular activity, probably of sympathetic origin. This trend was less marked in paroxysmal atrial fibrillation of vagal origin</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poblet, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Menor, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro-López, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Planas, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Oliva, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La historia natural de la fibrilación auricular (FA) primaria o idiopática tiene aspectos poco conocidos. El objeto del estudio fue describir la frecuencia y los factores determinantes de las recurrencias. Métodos. Se estudió a 115 pacientes atendidos en su primera crisis de FA paroxística sin causa conocida incluidos en el «registro FAP», en el que participan 11 centros comarcales de Cataluña. Se les practicó un estudio clínico, analítico, electrocardiográfico y ecocardiográfico exhaustivo y fueron seguidos periódicamente cada 6 meses para detectar la aparición de nuevas crisis sintomáticas y sus complicaciones. Resultados. Durante el seguimiento de 912 ± 445 días de promedio, 32 (27,8%) pacientes presentaron una recidiva de la fibrilación auricular. Los pacientes con recurrencias tenían una fracción de eyección más elevada (p = 0,023), un menor volumen telesistólico (p &lt; 0,001) y eran con mayor frecuencia consumidores habituales de alcohol (p = 0,013). El análisis de regresión de Cox confirmó el valor predictivo independiente de estas variables. En cambio, la presencia de lipotimias en el episodio agudo se asoció con una menor tendencia a recidivar (p = 0,017). Conclusiones. La fibrilación auricular idiopática mostró una notable tendencia a las recidivas, favorecida por el consumo moderado de alcohol y el aumento de la actividad ventricular, probablemente de origen simpático. La tendencia fue menor en la fibrilación paroxística de origen vagal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(11): 1106-1112, nov. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050770</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Historia natural y factores de riesgo de recurrencia de la fibrilación auricular primaria (Registro FAP)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13955^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22102^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
