<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-105764</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">General anaesthesia and obstetric bleeding in caesarean section. One year's experience in a university hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Obstetric haemorrhage is an important worldwide cause of morbidity and mortality. General anaesthesia for caesarean section is rarely used. Our goal is to analyse the incidence, causes and risk factors associated with general anaesthesia for caesarean section, and the prevalence of obstetric haemorrhage (HO), its risk factors and predictors of post-caesarean HO together with the use of blood in our hospital population. Methods. A retrospective study was conducted on all caesarean section discharge reports from PACU in 2008. Results. General anaesthesia was required in 12.4% of the patients. Epidural catheter failure as a cause of general anaesthesia was infrequent (2.8%) and within the recommended standards. Conclusions. The most frequent indications for caesarean section under general anaesthesia included mainly life-threatening emergencies, and the most important risk factors for general anaesthesia, including coagulation disorders, bleeding in the third trimester, foetal distress and severe pre-eclampsia. General anaesthesia is a risk factor for transfusion, as is abruptio placentae, placenta previa and pre-eclampsia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Montenegro, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guasch, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schiraldi, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La hemorragia obstétrica es una causa frecuente de mortalidad y morbilidad en el mundo. La anestesia general es cada vez menos frecuente para la cesárea. Nuestro objetivo es analizar la incidencia, causas y factores de riesgo asociados a la anestesia general en la cesárea, y la prevalencia de hemorragia obstétrica (HO), sus factores de riesgo y los predictores de HO poscesárea junto al uso de hemoderivados en la población de estudio. Material y métodos. Se ha realizado un estudio retrospectivo de los informes de alta de la URPA durante el año 2008. Resultados. El 12,4% de nuestras pacientes requirieron anestesia general. El fallo del catéter epidural como causa de anestesia general, fue poco frecuente (2,8%) y dentro de los estándares recomendados. Conclusiones. Las indicaciones de cesárea más frecuentes bajo anestesia general incluyeron principalmente urgencias vitales, que coincide con los factores de riesgo de anestesia general más significativos (alteraciones de la coagulación, hemorragia del tercer trimestre, riesgo de pérdida de bienestar fetal y preeclampsia grave). La anestesia general es un factor de riesgo de transfusión, como también lo es las alteraciones de la placentación y la preeclampsia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;59(8): 415-422, oct. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-105764</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anestesia general y hemorragia obstétrica con transfusión en la cesárea. Experiencia durante un año en un hospital universitario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51443</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6622^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
