<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116479</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional somatic symptoms in a Spanish sample: Psychopathology and educational styles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Although there are many studies on functional somatic symptoms (FSS), there are few conducted with Spanish samples. The aim of this study was to assess the prevalence of frequent functional somatic symptoms in a Spanish sample, and to look for relationships with psychopathology and parenting styles. Patients and methods: The sample consisted of 672 participants from 6 to 8 years-old attending primary school in the region of Osona (Catalonia, Spain). The parents reported on the presence of FSS in children, school absence, paediatric visits; psychiatric symptoms, and parenting styles. Children who complained of frequent somatic symptoms (four or more in the previous fortnight) were compared with children who did not complain. Results: A total of 429 of the 672 (63.8%) children had at least one physical complaint during the two weeks prior to the study. Almost one quarter (162, 24.1%) of the participants had frequent FSS. Significant relationships were found with, separation anxiety, social phobia, and visits to the paediatrician. A small effect of overprotection/control parenting style on FSS was observed. Conclusions: Functional somatic symptoms are common in a Spanish sample of children between 6 to 8 years-old. These children may be considered a risk group for future emotional distress. It is also important for future research to clarify the nature of the relationship between overprotection and FSS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Claustre Jané, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serra, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bonillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Muchos investigadores han estudiado los síntomas somáticos funcionales (SSF). Sin embargo, hay pocos estudios con muestras españolas. El objetivo de la investigación fue calcular la prevalencia de síntomas somáticos funcionales frecuentes en una muestra española de niños y verificar asociaciones con psicopatología y estilos educativos. Pacientes y métodos: La muestra estuvo formada por 672 participantes de 6 a 8 años inscritos en la escuela primaria de la comarca de Osona (Cataluña, España). Los padres informaron sobre la presencia de los SSF en los niños, ausencias escolares, visitas pediátricas, síntomas psiquiátricos y estilos educativos. Los niños que manifestaron SSF frecuentes (4 o más en la última quincena) han sido comparados con los que no los presentaban. Resultados: De los 672 participantes, 429 (63,8%) manifestaron por lo menos una queja física en las 2 semanas previas al estudio; 162 (24,1%) niños han presentado SSF frecuentes. Se hallaron asociaciones significativas con ansiedad de separación, fobia social y visitas al pediatra. También se observó un pequeño efecto del estilo educativo sobreprotección/control sobre los SSF. Conclusiones: Los SSF son comunes en una muestra española de niños de 6 a 8 años. Dichos niños pueden ser considerados un grupo de riesgo para estrés emocional. Los resultados también sugieren la necesidad de futuras investigaciones que permitan clarificar la relación entre la sobreprotección de los padres y los SSF (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);79(2): 101-107, ago. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116479</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas somáticos funcionales en una muestra española: psicopatología y estilos educativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13384^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23905^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
