<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96422</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social reputation, psychosocial adjustment and adolescent peer victimization at the school context</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to analyse the relationship among adolescent&#146;s social reputation &#150;perceived and ideal-, peer victimization at the school context and some specific psychosocial adjustment variables such as life satisfaction, loneliness, depressive symptomatology and self-esteem. The sample was composed of 1319 adolescents aged from 11 to 16 years old. Structural equation modeling was carried out to examine the direct and indirect effect of social reputation on peer victimization. Results obtained indicated social reputation was related both directly and indirectly to peer victimization. The indirect effects suggested self-esteem, depressive symptomatology and loneliness mediated the relationship between the adolescent&#146;s social reputation and peer victimization. Finally, these results and their implications were discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cava, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Musitu, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Buelga, Sofía</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del presente trabajo fue analizar las relaciones entre la reputación social del adolescente &#151;percibida e ideal&#151;, la victimización entre iguales en el contexto escolar y determinadas variables de ajuste psicosocial, como la satisfacción con la vida, la autoestima, la sintomatología depresiva y la soledad. La muestra estuvo formada por 1319 adolescentes de edades comprendidas entre los 11 y los 16 años. Se utilizó un modelo de ecuaciones estructurales para analizar el efecto directo e indirecto de la reputación social en la victimización entre pares. Los resultados obtenidos indicaron que la reputación social del adolescente se relaciona tanto directa como indirectamente con la victimización escolar. Los efectos indirectos sugirieron que la autoestima, la sintomatología depresiva y la soledad median la relación entre la reputación social del adolescente y la victimización escolar. Finalmente, se discutieron estos resultados y sus implicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;28(1): 180-187, ene.-abr. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96422</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reputación social, ajuste psicosocial y victimización entre adolescentes en el contexto escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1538</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1538^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
