<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66133</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The pineal gland is an unpaired, central structure that develops at the expense of an invagination of the central ventricular cavity. Classically, it has been compared to a pineapple, hence its name. Its structure is essentially histological, it being formed by pinealocytes and glial cells. Its primaryfunction is melatonin synthesis and secretion. Melatoninseems to be related to many actions, such as circadianrhythm synchronization, promoting sleep, body thermoregulation, action on the immune system, puberal development, osteogenesis, metabolic actions and digestive protective effect; it has also been linked with the pathogenesis of the psychiatricdisorders: depression and degenerative diseases. Becauseof the relationship of melatonin in regards to moodstates and their potential contribution to depression, the studies conducted on the effect of antidepressants on the pineal gland are varied</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez de la Cruz, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo García, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Chamorro, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodilla Rodilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maestre Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Garcés, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La glándula pineal es un cuerpo impar y central que se desarrolla a expensas de una invaginación de la bóveda del ventrículo medio. Clásicamente ha sido comparada a una piña, de ahí su nombre. Su estructura histológica fundamental está formada por los pinealocitos y células de la glía. Su función principal es la síntesis y secreción de melatonina. La melatonina parece estar relacionada, en contra de lo que se pensaba, con múltiples acciones como sincronización circadiana, promoción del sueño, termorregulación corporal, acciónsobre el sistema inmune, desarrollo puberal, osteogénesis, acciones metabólicas y efecto protector digestivo; también ha sido relacionada con la patogenia de los desórdenes psiquiátricos: depresión y enfermedades degenerativas. Debido a la relación de la melatonina sobre los estados de ánimo y su posible contribución a los estados depresivos, son variados los estudios realizados sobre el efecto de los antidepresivossobre la glándula pineal</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);34(4): 183-192, abr. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66133</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d935^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8718^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2881^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11303^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28186^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
