<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165257</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-2927</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality and customer loyalty: A segmentation analysis in low-cost fitness center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Quality and loyalty have been studied in fitness centers, mainly in the relationship between them and with other variables. In a few cases, studies have been carried out to analyze the profiles of clients who perceived these variables better. For this reason the study aimed to segment customers of low-cost fitness centers according to the perception of quality and loyalty. The sample consisted of 8462 clients (4303 women and 4159 men) from low-cost fitness centers. Analysis of variance and two - stage clustering were performed. The results showed four clusters in which there were significant differences in the perception of quality and loyalty. These findings show the importance of knowledge of the characteristics of sports consumers (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grimaldi-Puyana, Moisés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Oliver, Antonio Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gálvez-Ruiz, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, Jerónimo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Gavira, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La calidad y la fidelidad han sido estudiadas en los centros de fitness, mayormente en la relación que tienen entre ambas y con otras variables. En pocos casos se han realizado estudios que analicen los perfiles de clientes que mejor perciben dichas variables. Por esta razón el estudio tenía por objetivo segmentar a los clientes de centros de fitness low-cost según la percepción de calidad y fidelidad. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 8462 clientes (4303 mujeres y 4159 hombres) de centros de fitness low-cost. Se realizó análisis de la varianza y de conglomerados bietápico. Los resultados mostraron cuatro clústers en los que existieron diferencias significativas en la percepción de la calidad y la fidelidad. Estos hallazgos muestran la importancia del conocimiento de las características de consumidores deportivos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ars pharm;26(supl.3): 17-22, 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165257</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La calidad y la fidelidad del cliente: Un análisis de segmentación en centros de fitness low-cost</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3277^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
