<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113324</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Histology of submandibular gland tumours, 10 years&#146; experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: There are few reports focused on neoplasms in the submandibular gland because they are uncommon and are frequently grouped with the other salivary glands tumours. In the classical studies, the proportion of malignancy reported in these cases is around 50%. Objectives: Determining the proportion of malignancy, the most frequent histological types, the gender distribution and average age at diagnosis in patients with submandibular gland neoplasms who were treated in our hospital from 2000 year to 2010. Methods: A retrospective review of our department database of the patients who underwent surgery for submandibular gland neoplasm in a ten-year period was performed. Results: Twenty-two patient records were included, in which 19 (86%) patients presented benign disease and 3 were of a malignant type (adenocarcinoma, well-differentiated epidermoid carcinoma, follicular lymphoma). Two of the 3 cases of malignant neoplasms were in men. Conclusions: A greater proportion of benign neoplasm was found in submandibular tumours. The most frequent benign tumour is the pleomorphic adenoma. Women are more commonly affected (76%). Benign tumours appear in younger patients than do malignant ones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bravo-Escobar, Gerardo Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo-Ventura, Bertha Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Becerril-Ramírez, Perla Bernice</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prado-Calleros, Héctor Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pombo-Nava, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Hay pocos trabajos enfocados a neoplasias de glándulas submandibulares porque son poco comunes y se les agrupa con otras glándulas salivales. En los estudios clásicos se reporta que los tumores malignos en esta localización representan alrededor del 50%. Objetivos: Reportar la proporción de malignidad en pacientes con neoplasia de glándulas submandibulares y tipos histológicos más comunes que se trataron en nuestro hospital del año 2000 al 2010, así como la proporción por sexo y edad de presentación. Métodos: Se realizó una revisión retrospectiva de la base de datos de nuestro servicio de los pacientes que fueron atendidos en 10 años por neoplasia de glándula submandibular. Resultados: Se atendieron 22 pacientes con neoplasias de glándula submandibular, 19 (86%) de tipo benigno y tres malignos (adenocarcinoma, carcinoma epidermoide bien diferenciado y linfoma folicular), edad promedio en patología benigna: 40 años y 55 años en malignos. Hubo predominio del sexo femenino (76%), sin embargo dos de tres casos de neoplasia maligna se presentaron en el sexo masculino. Conclusiones: La mayoría de las neoplasias de glándula submandibular son benignas. El tumor benigno más frecuente es el adenoma pleomorfo. Las mujeres son afectadas con mayor frecuencia. Los tumores benignos se presentan en pacientes más jóvenes que los malignos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;62(6): 432-435, nov.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Histología de tumores de glándulas submandibulares. Experiencia de 10 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22683^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31876^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
