<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86723</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Quality of life and multiple sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Health-related quality of life (HRQoL) is a complex concept in which evaluation of physical, emotional and social domains of health are included. Since chronic diseases has raised, the importance of HRQoL evaluation has increased, overall in patients with multiple sclerosis (MS) whose HRQoL has shown to be worse than in other chronic diseases. Aim. To review the information available about the HRQoL in patients with MS to provide an overview of the current situation. Development. Previously performed clinical trials identified the main factors related to the HRQoL: physical factors  (sensitive/motor deficits, fatigue, pain, sexual/bladder dysfunction), psychological factors (depression, anxiety, cognitive disturbances, coping strategies) and social factors (family/social relationships, work activity). The inclusion of HRQoL questionnaires in the patients&#146; follow-up is a relevant issue to optimize its treatment, making easier treatment decision and improving adherence, as well as to reduce the inconveniences derived from medication such as adverse events.  Conclusions. HRQoL evaluation is really complex in patients with MS, being difficult to identify the main domains that impact on HRQoL. However, its regular evaluation provides essential information to improve the symptomatic treatment, increase the adherence to treatment and modify the immunomodulating treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olascoaga, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La calidad de vida relacionada con la salud (CVRS) es un concepto complejo en el que se engloba la valoración de los dominios físicos, emocionales y sociales de la salud. Con el aumento de la prevalencia de pacientes con enfermedades crónicas progresivas, la valoración de la CVRS ha cobrando importancia, especialmente en pacientes con esclerosis múltiple (EM), en los que la CVRS se ha mostrado como una condición más deteriorada que en otras enfermedades crónicas. Objetivo. Realizar una revisión de la información disponible sobre la CVRS de los pacientes con EM, que permita ofrecer una visión global de la situación actual. Desarrollo. Los estudios realizados han logrado identificar los principales factores relacionados con la CVRS: factores físicos (alteraciones motoras/sensitivas, fatiga, dolor, problemas sexuales/urinarios), factores psicológicos (depresión, ansiedad, pérdida de funciones cognitivas, actitud frente a la enfermedad) y factores sociales (alteración de relaciones sociales/familiares, actividad laboral). La incorporación de cuestionarios de CVRS en el seguimiento de los pacientes constituye una herramienta para optimizar su tratamiento, facilitando la selección de la terapia, mejorando la adhesión y  reduciendo los inconvenientes de la medicación, como la presentación de efectos adversos. Conclusiones. La CVRS es un aspecto sumamente complejo de analizar en pacientes con EM ya que resulta difícil identificar los dominios específicos que interfieren en mayor medida. No obstante, su valoración periódica proporciona información esencial para mejorar el tratamiento sintomático, incrementar la adhesión al tratamiento y modificar el tratamiento  inmunomodulador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;51(5): 279-288, sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86723</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calidad de vida y esclerosis múltiple</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
