<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161353</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Chronic ischaemic heart disease in the elderly</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is the aim of this manuscript to take into account the peculiarities and specific characteristics of elderly patients with chronic ischaemic heart disease from a multidisciplinary perspective, with the participation of the Spanish Society of Cardiology (sections of Geriatric Cardiology and Ischaemic Heart Disease/Acute Cardiovascular Care), the Spanish Society of Internal Medicine, the Spanish Society of Primary Care Physicians and the Spanish Society of Geriatrics and Gerontology. This consensus document shows that in order to adequately address these elderly patients a comprehensive assessment is needed, which includes comorbidity, frailty, functional status, polypharmacy and drug interactions. We conclude that in most patients medical treatment is the best option and that this treatment must take into account the above factors and the biological changes associated with aging (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Abu-Assi, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidán, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Sellés, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Huelgas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calderón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo pretende tener en cuenta las peculiaridades y características específicas de los pacientes ancianos con cardiopatía isquémica crónica desde una perspectiva multidisciplinar, con la participación de la Sociedad Española de Cardiología (secciones de Cardiología Geriátrica y Cardiopatía Isquémica/Cuidados Agudos Cardiovasculares), la Sociedad Española de Medicina Interna, la Sociedad Española de Médicos de Atención Primaria y la Sociedad Española de Geriatría y Gerontología. En este documento de consenso se detalla cómo el abordaje de estos enfermos de edad avanzada exige una valoración integral de la comorbilidad, la fragilidad, el estado funcional, la polifarmacia y las interacciones medicamentosas. Concluimos que en la mayoría de los pacientes el tratamiento médico es la mejor opción y que, a la hora de programarlo, se deben tener en cuenta los factores anteriores y las alteraciones biológicas asociadas al envejecimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);43(2): 109-122, mar. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161353</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cardiopatía isquémica crónica en el anciano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37619</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4421^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d798^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28628^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
