<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128968</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4603</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Methodology for competency-based education in a student with Moebius syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study is the result of experience in applying the model of competency-based education in a student with Moebius syndrome, which consists of congenital paralysis leading to a lack of control of facial expressions and lateral eye movements. We present our experience with a student with Moebius syndrome, which required the teaching faculty to design strategies to develop the student's learning(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moratalla Isasi, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Romero, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio que presentamos es el resultado de la experiencia con el modelo de educación basada en competencias a un estudiante con síndrome de Moebius. Presentamos una experiencia real con un estudiante con dicha enfermedad que consiste en una parálisis congénita que no le permite controlar las expresiones faciales ni el movimiento lateral ocular. Esta situación diversa plantea al profesorado un replanteamiento didáctico para el desarrollo del aprendizaje(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. logop. foniatr. audiol. (Ed. impr.);30(4): 174-179, oct.-dic.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128968</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metodología para trabajar competencias con un estudiante con síndrome de Moebius</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5235^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8037^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7984^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5258^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13957</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
