<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10820</identifier>
<setSpec>0376-7892</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of description and treatment of most frequent congenital anomalies in hand</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and Objective. This review paper aims to provide an introduction to the vast group of congenital hand anomalies, focusing on the 3 most common entities seen in daily practice, namely: simple syndactyly and radial polydactyly, predominantly one or the other according to the population and publications, and about 1 per 2000 live births; and trigger thumb, which incidence is difficult to calculate, but it is estimated in 3 per 1000 live births. Our aim is to dump the experience of more than 27 years of our Service in these 3 entities, with the respective sub-classifications used which guided us the treatment indication and surgical techniques in each type of anomaly.  Methods. We conduct a revision of casuistry from a personal data base from 2005 to 2016; and for older patients, between 1998 and 2006, we consulted and electronic data base at the Plastic Surgery Unit of the Pediatric Hospital Juan P. Garragan, Buenos Aires, Argentina, combined with registries (1987-2000) and completed with the present electronic system of clinical records of the hospital (2014-2016).  Besides, through a literature review, we look about the 3 most frequent pathologies that we found at our consultory: simple syndactyly, radial polydactyly, and trigger thumb.  Results. The total number of surgical procedures on congenital pathology of the hand operated on at our Unit between 1998 and 2015 was 622.  Thanks to our literature review we found a new classification of congenital hand anomalies, based on the part of the body and the predominantly involved axis.  Conclusions. In congenital pathologies of the hand, primary focus is surgical treatment to improve hand function without losing the cosmetic-aesthetic concept that must accompany us at all times (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dogliotti, Andrés A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y Objetivo. Este trabajo de revisión intenta aportar una introducción al vasto grupo de las anomalías congénitas de la mano enfocada en las 3 entidades más habituales en la consulta diaria, a saber: la sindactilia simple y la polidactilia radial, predominando una o la otra de acuerdo a la población y las publicaciones, y siendo su frecuencia de aproximadamente 1 por cada 2000 nacidos vivos; y el pulgar en resorte, cuya frecuencia es difícil de estimar pero se calcula que está en torno a los 3 por cada 1000 nacidos vivos.  Nuestro objetivo en el presente trabajo es volcar la experiencia de más de 27 años de nuestro Servicio en estas 3 entidades, con las respectivas subclasificaciones utilizadas que nos guían en la indicación del tratamiento y las conductas quirúrgicas a seguir en cada tipo de anomalía. Material y Método. Para la recogida de nuestra casuística recopilamos la información sobre pacientes de una base de datos personal desde 2005 a 2016; y para los pacientes más antiguos, entre 1998 a 2006, consultamos una base de datos electrónica del Servicio de Cirugía Plástica y Quemados del Hospital de Pediatría Juan P. Garrahan, en Buenos Aires, Argentina, combinada con los registros de fichas (1987-2000) y complementada con el actual sistema de historias clínicas electrónicas del hospital (2014 a 2016). Llevamos a cabo también una revisión de la literatura sobre las 3 patologías que con más frecuencia vemos en consulta: el dedo en resorte congénito, la sindactilia congénita y la polidactilia radial. Resultados. El número de procedimientos quirúrgicos en casos con patología congénita de mano operados en nuestro Servicio entre 1988 y 2015 fue de 622.  Gracias a la revisión de la literatura encontramos una nueva clasificación de las anomalías congénitas de la mano basada en el sector y el eje predominantemente involucrado.  Conclusiones. En las patologías congénitas de la mano resulta primordial enfocar el tratamiento quirúrgico hacia la mejora de la función de la mano, sin perder de vista el concepto cosmético-estético que debe acompañarnos en todo momento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. plást. ibero-latinoam;43(supl.1): s97-s106, sept. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10820</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de la descripción y tratamiento de las anomalías congénitas más frecuentes de la mano</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
