<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125662</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-5934</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Response predictive factors for electroconvulsive therapy in depression</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) is one of the main treatments for depression. However, there is a lack of consensus on the variables that determine the successful response to ECT. This review focuses on current studies of the predictive factors of ECT response in depressed patients. A systematic search was conducted using the Medline database and the references of previous reviews. A total of 25 relevant articles published between 1996 and 2013 were selected. As positive predictors were identified: ageover 65 years, homozygous Val/Val for the enzyme catechol-O-methyltransferase, the severity of the episode, suicidal ideation, and increased baseline scores in items of dysphoria on the Montgomery and Asberg Depression Rating Scale. Treatment resistance, chronic state of the disorder, and comorbidity with personality disorders would be negative response predictors to ECT. This review was unable to demonstrate the association with psychotic symptoms, melancholic symptoms or angiotensin converting enzyme polymorphisms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojo Rodes, J. Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monserrat Díez, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hurtado Ruiz, M. Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcoverro Fortuny, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia electroconvulsiva (TEC) es uno de los principales tratamientos en la depresión. No obstante, existe una falta de consenso respecto a las variables que determinan la respuesta satisfactoria a TEC. Esta revisión se centra en los estudios actuales de los factores predictivos de respuesta a TEC en pacientesdiagnosticados de trastorno depresivo. Se realizó una búsqueda sistemática en la base de datos Medline  y en las referencias bibliográficas de las revisiones previas. Se seleccionaron 25 artículos relevantes publicados entre 1996 y 2013. Se identificaron como factores predictivos positivos: la edad mayor de 65 a&#152;nos, homocigosis Val/Val para la enzima catecol-O-metiltransferasa, la severidad del episodio depresivo, la ideación suicida y puntuaciones pretratamiento elevadas en ítems de disforia en la Montgomery and Asberg Depression Rating Scale. La resistencia al tratamiento, la cronicidad del trastorno y la comorbilidad con desórdenes de personalidad serían factores predictivos negativos de respuesta a TEC. Esta revisión no puede concluir que haya asociación respecto a la sintomatología psicótica, la melancólica o a determinados polimorfismos de la enzima convertidora de angiontensina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psiquiatr. biol. (Ed. impr);21(2): 72-79, mayo-ago. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125662</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictivos de respuesta a la terapia electroconvulsiva en la depresión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4637^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3886^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31868^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
