<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98283</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-755X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Playing is a topic of interest concerning both normal children and children with Down syndrome. In fact, playing is an essential tool to let the psychological development of children unfold and it is also a key element in the teaching-learning process. This study outlines the psychological intervention with two children suffering Down syndrome using playing and toys as key elements to stir psychological development. Results show a substantial improvement in the psychological development of both children, especially in the areas of language, socialization, cognitive functions, gross and fine motor skills, and self care. Moreover, their emotional behavior changed notoriously and social interaction both with their family and their mates improved significantly, getting more and more involved in social events (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Damián Diaz, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El juego es tema de interés tanto para niños normales como para niños con Síndrome de Down como herramienta indispensable para desplegar el desarrollo psicológico de los niños y como elemento indispensable del proceso de enseñanza-aprendizaje. En este estudio se presenta la intervención psicológica de dos niños con Síndrome de Down utilizando el juego y los juguetes como elementos indispensables entre otros, para mejorar y avanzar en su desarrollo psicológico. Los resultados muestran ganancias sustanciales en ambos niños en el desarrollo psicológico considerando las áreas de lenguaje y socialización, cognoscitivas, motoras gruesas y finas y autocuidado, además su comportamiento emocional se transformo notablemente y la interacción social entre sus familiares y compañeritos evolucionó de manera positiva involucrándose cada vez más en los episodios sociales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. educ. (Madr.);13(2): 133-149, jul.-dic. 2007.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98283</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La importancia del juego en el desarrollo psicológico infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11416^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11417^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
