<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-84726</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body fat and poor diet in breast cancer women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Breast cancer is the most common cancer in women worldwide. Differences in breast cancer incidence suggest a significant role of environmental factors in the aetiology: obesity, central adiposity, excess body fat and some dietary factors have been suggested as risk factors. This pilot study aimed to analyse the pattern of nutritional status, body fat, and the usual dietary intake among women diagnosed with breast cancer, consecutively referred to the Radiotherapy Department of the University Hospital Santa Maria. Patients and methods: Throughout 2006, 71 consecutive women with breast cancer were included. Evaluations: weight (kg) &amp; height (m), determined with a SECA® floor scale + stadiometer to calculate body mass index (BMI), waist circumference, percentage body fat with bipolar hand-held bio-impedance analysis (BF-306®), Food Frequency Questionnaire validated for the Portuguese population to assess the usual dietary intake. Frequency analysis and Mann-Whitney U test were used to evaluate prevalence and associations. Results: Mean age was 60 ± 12 (36-90) years. Invasive ductal carcinoma was the most frequent histology (68%), p &lt; 0.05. Most patients were in stage I (30%) or stage IIA (25%) of disease vs IIB (10%), IIIB (4%), IV (4%) or others (21%), p &lt; 0.05. Regarding nutritional status, 82% were overweight/obese; 89% of patients had a %body fat mass above the maximum limit of 30% vs only 8 (11%) with %body fat within normal range (p &lt; 0.002); 62% pts had a waist circumference &gt; 88 cm (prevalence analysis: p &lt; 0.04), and 61% of pts had gained weight after diagnosis. Univariate analysis did not show any association between histology, BMI, %body fat and waist circumference; by multivariate analysis there was an association between higher BMI, %body fat &amp; aggressive histologies (p &lt; 0.005). Food frequency analysis showed a low intake of vegetables and wholegrain cereals rich in complex carbohydrates (sources of fibre and phytochemicals), of fatty fish &amp; nuts, primary sources of n-3 PUFA's and a high intake of saturated fat; more aggressive histologies were correlated with low intake of green leafy vegetables (p =0.05) and n-3 fatty acids food sources (p = 0.01). Conclusions: Our findings show a vast prevalence &amp; homogeneous pattern of overweight/obesity, excessive body and abdominal fat, as well as weight gain after diagnosis, combined with diets deficient in protective nutrients. Further investigation is warranted as cancer rates in Portugal continue to increase (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camilou, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguel, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amaral, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ravasco, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mehdad, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Monteiro Grillo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: el cáncer de mama es el cáncer más frecuente en mujeres en todo el mundo. Las diferencias en la incidencia de cáncer de mama sugieren un papel significativo de los factores ambientales en su etiología: se han propuesto la obesidad, la adiposidad central, el exceso de grasa corporal y algunos factores dietéticos como factores de riesgo. El propósito de este estudio piloto fue analizar el patrón del estado nutricional, la grasa corporal y consumo dietético habitual en mujeres diagnosticadas de cáncer de mama y remitidas de forma consecutiva al Servicio de Radioterapia del Hospital Universitario de Santa María. Pacientes y métodos: A lo largo de 2.006, se incluyeron 71 mujeres consecutivas con cáncer de mama. Evaluaciones: peso (kg) &amp; talla (m), determinados mediante una báscula + estadiómetro SECA® para calcular el índice de masa corporal (IMC), la circunferencia de la cintura, el porcentaje de grasa corporal con el análisis bipolar manual de bioimpedancia (BF-306®), el cuestionario Food Frequency Questionnaire validado en versión portuguesa para evaluar el consumo dietético habitual. Se emplearon el análisis de frecuencia y la prueba U de Mann-Whitney para evaluar la prevalencia y las asociaciones. Resultados: la edad media fue 60 ± 12 (36-90) años. La histología más frecuente fue el carcinoma ductal invasivo (68%), p &lt; 0,05. La mayoría de las pacientes estaba en estadio I (30%) o estadio IIA (25%) de la enfermedad frente a los estadios IIB (10%), IIIB (4%), IV (4%) y otros (21%), p &lt; 0,05. Con respecto al estado nutricional, el 82% tenía sobrepeso / obesidad; el 89% de las pacientes tenía un % de grasa corporal por encima del límite máximo de 30% frente a sólo (11%) con un % de grasa corporal dentro del rango normal (p &lt; 0,002); 62% pacientes tenían una circunferencia de la cintura &gt; 88 cm (análisis de prevalencia: p &lt; 0,04) y 61% de ellas había ganado peso tras el diagnóstico. El análisis univariado no mostró asociación alguna entre la histología, el IMC, el % de grasa corporal ni la circunferencia de la cintura; mediante el análisis multivariado se mostró una asociación entre un mayor IMC, el % de grasa corporal e histologías agresivas (p &lt; 0,005). El análisis de frecuencia de alimentos mostró un consumo bajo de vegetales y cereales integrales ricos en complejos carbohidratados (fuentes de fibra o histoquímicos) o de ácidos grasos de pescados o frutos secos, fuentes primarias de ácidos grasos poliinsaturados n-3 y un consumo elevado de grasas saturadas; las histologías más agresivas se correlacionaban con un consumo bajo de verduras (p = 0,05) y de fuentes de ácidos grasos n-3 (p = 0,01). Conclusiones: nuestros hallazgos muestran una amplia prevalencia y un patrón homogéneo de sobrepeso/obesidad, y una cantidad excesiva de grasa corporal y abdominal, así como de ganancia de peso tras el diagnóstico, junto con deficiencias dietéticas en nutrientes protectores. ¡Se requiere investigación adicional puesto que las tasas de cáncer siguen aumentando en Portugal! (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(3): 456-461, mayo-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-84726</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grasa corporal y mala alimentación en mujeres con cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27771</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d280</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
