<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051368</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-2841</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the origins, there was a necessary relationship between the registers of nosology and epidemiological activity. The MBDS is one the more complete systems of information. It´s the more typical of hospital discharge. In order to making it, is essential to codify the clinical processes. the MBDS was initially employed to value the assistance output with fidelity, however raises some epidemiological applications. In this use it has some profits, like account many data, standarization, widely established, computerization and economy. The main applications are to know the pathology attended, incidence, their comparison, to confront with another sources of information, description of characteristics of patients and the comorbility, recovery for specific researches, evaluation of procedures, estimation of nosocomial infection rates and avoidable hospitalization, and detection of drug-related adverse effects. Some limitations and obstacles are cited in this field</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Asensio, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde los orígenes, hubo una necesaria relación entre lo registros de casuística y la actividad epidemiológica. Uno de los más completos sistemas de información es el CMBD, el más típico al alta hospitalaria. Para su confección es básico el proceso de codificación. El CMBD se ha empleado inicialmente para valorar equitativamente la producción asistencial. No obstante, se suscitan algunos usos de carácter epidemiológico, gozando de las ventajas de gran acopia de datos, estandarización, amplia difusión, informatización y economía. Se repasan los más significativos aspectos de investigación: episodios atendidos, incidencia, comparabilidad de la misma, comparación con otras fuentes de datos, estudio de la comorbilidad, descripción de las características de los pacientes, recuperación para estudios específicos, estudios de la demanda asistencial, evaluación de procedimientos, evaluación de la infección nosocomial, detección de efectos adversos a medicamentos y evaluación de la hospitalización innecesaria. Se hace referencia a las dificultades y limitaciones en estos usos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. prev;12(3): 7-12, jul.-sept. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051368</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El CMBD al alta hospitalaria como herramienta de la investigación epidemiológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28585</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
