<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050557</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic gastrectomy for gastric adenocarcinoma. Long-term results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: the objective of our paper is to report on thelong-term results of patients with gastric cancer treated by mini-invasivesurgery with "intention-to-treat" laparoscopy.Patients and methods: between June 1993 and January2006, 130 patients comprising 94 men and 36 women with gastricadenocarcinoma were prospectively selected by two surgical teams inthree hospitals based on a prior agreement (CHU Charleroi, Belgium,Centre Hospitalier de Luxembourg and Zumárraga Hospital,Spain). Patients with adenocarcinoma of the cardia were excluded.Mean age of patients was 68 years (range, 37-85 years).Results: post-operative mortality within 60 days of operationwas 6 patients; 109 patients were therefore properly followed upfor an average of 49 months (range, 2-153 months).Average survival time for 10 non-resected patients was 4.5months. Average survival rate for all 14 palliatively resected patientswas 6.9 months. Actuarial 5-year survival rate for R0-typesurgery was 35%. Global actuarial 5-year survival rate after resectivesurgery was 31%.Conclusions: laparoscopic gastrectomy with any kind of lymphadenectomyis a major but safe operation with acceptable mortalityand morbility rates in patients with advanced gastric cancer,usually in poor general condition. Laparoscopic gastrectomy forlocally advanced cancers is equivalent to laparotomy as far aslong-term oncological results are concerned</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Azagra, JS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goergen, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simona, P de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clamares de Lama, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Echenique Elizondo, MM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rico Selas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibáñez Aguirre, JS</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Erro Azcárate, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Elola-Olaso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el objetivo del presente artículo es analizar losresultados a largo plazo de los pacientes con cáncer gástrico tratadosmediante un abordaje laparoscópico miniinvasivo como unaherramienta quirúrgica con la &#147;intención de tratar por laparoscopia&#148;.Pacientes y métodos: entre junio de 1993 y enero de 2006,130 pacientes, 94 hombres y 36 mujeres, portadores de un adenocarcinomagástrico fueron seleccionados de forma prospectivapor dos equipos quirúrgicos en tres centros hospitalarios previoacuerdo (CHU de Charleroi, Bélgica/Centre Hospitalier de Luxemburgo;y el Hospital de Zumárraga, País Vasco, España). Fueronexcluidos los pacientes con adenocarcinoma de cardias y losadenocarcinomas de muñón gástrico. La edad media de los pacientesfue de 68 años (37-85 años).Resultados: la mortalidad postoperatoria a 60 días fue de 6pacientes; 109 pacientes fueron sometidos a un seguimiento oncológicomedio de 49 meses (2-153 meses). La media de supervivenciaobservada en los 10 pacientes no resecados fue de 4,5 meses.La media de supervivencia observada en los 14 pacientesresecados paliativamente fue de 6,9 meses. La supervivencia actuariala 5 años observada tras exéresis de tipo R0 fue del 35%.La supervivencia actuarial global a 5 años de los pacientes resecadosfue del 31%.Conclusiones: la gastrectomía laparoscópica asociada a cualquiertipo de linfadenectomía es una intervención importante perosegura, con tasas de morbi-mortalidad aceptables en pacientescon cáncer gástrico avanzado que frecuentemente presentan unmal estado general. Los resultados oncológicos a largo plazo de lagastrectomía laparoscópica por cáncer gástrico avanzado son similaresa los obtenidos por vía laparotómica</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;98(7): 491-500, jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050557</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gastrectomía laparoscópica por adenocarcinoma gástrico. Resultados a largo plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5884^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8374</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13662^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
