<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149894</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospital variation in anastomotic leakage after rectal cancer surgery in the Spanish Association of Surgeons project: The contribution of hospital volume</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This multicentre observational study aimed to determine the anastomotic leak rate in the hospitals included in the Rectal Cancer Project of the Spanish Society of Surgeons and examine whether hospital volume may contribute to any variation between hospitals. Methods: Hospital variation was quantified using a multilevel approach on prospective data derived from the multicentre database of all adenocarcinomas of the rectum operated by an anterior resection at 84 surgical departments from 2006 to 2013. The following variables were included in the analysis; demographics, American Society of Anaesthesiologists classification, use of defunctioning stoma, tumour location and stage, administration of neoadjuvant treatment, and annual volume of elective surgical procedures. Results: A total of 7231 consecutive patients were included. The rate of anastomotic leak was 10.0%. Stratified by annual surgical volume hospitals varied from 9.9 to 11.3%. In multilevel regression analysis, the risk of anastomotic leak increased in male patients, in patients with tumours located below 12 cm from the anal verge, and advanced tumour stages. However, a defunctioning stoma seemed to prevent this complication. Hospital surgical volume was not associated with anastomotic leak (OR: 0.852, [0.487-1.518]; P=.577). Furthermore, there was a statistically significant variation in anastomotic leak between all departments (MOR: 1.475; [1.321-1.681]; P&lt;0.001). Conclusion: Anastomotic leak varies significantly among hospitals included in the project and this difference cannot be attributed to the annual surgical volumen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Biondo, Sebastiano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Codina, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roig, José Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciga, Miguel Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Enríquez-Navascués, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espín, Eloy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Granero, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El objetivo de este estudio observacional multicéntrico fue determinar la tasa de dehiscencia anastomótica en los hospitales que participan en el Proyecto del Cáncer de Recto de la Asociación Española de Cirujanos y evaluar si había diferencias atribuibles al volumen quirúrgico entre los hospitales que participan en él. Métodos: La variación interhospitalaria se cuantificó mediante un estudio multinivel realizado con una base de datos prospectiva de los pacientes operados por un adenocarcinoma de recto con una resección anterior en 84 hospitales, entre marzo de 2006 y diciembre de 2013. En los análisis se incluyeron: las variables demográficas, la clasificación de la American Society of Anaesthesiologists, la utilización de un estoma de derivación, la localización y el estadio del tumor, la administración de tratamiento neoadyuvante y el volumen quirúrgico anual del hospital. Resultados: Se analizó a 7.231 pacientes operados consecutivamente. La tasa de dehiscencia anastomótica fue del 10,0%. Los porcentajes de dehiscencia de los hospitales, estratificados por el volumen quirúrgico annual, variaron entre el 9,9 y el 11,3%. En el análisis de regresión multinivel el sexo masculino, los tumores localizados por debajo de 12 cm medidos desde el margen anal y los estadios T avanzados favorecieron la aparición de la dehiscencia, mientras que la presencia de un estoma de derivación la previno. El volumen quirúrgico anual del hospital no se asoció con la dehiscencia (OR: 0,852; [0,487-1,518]; p = 0,577). Además, se observó una variación significativa de la tasa de dehiscencia entre los hospitales (MOR: 1,475; [1,321-1,681]; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusión: La dehiscencia anastomótica varía de forma estadísticamente significativa entre los hospitales incluidos en el proyecto, y esta diferencia no se puede atribuir al volumen quirúrgico anual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);94(4): 213-220, abr. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Variabilidad interhospitalaria de la dehiscencia anastomótica en el Proyecto del Cáncer de Recto de la Asociación Española de Cirujanos: La influencia del volumen quirúrgico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55468</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29640</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23288</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22831</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51280</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12424^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55775</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
