<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165410</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiac resynchronization therapy: a clinical perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac resynchronization therapy improves hemodynamics and symptoms in patients with advanced heart failure and ventricular dyssynchrony. The results of numerous studies of cardiac resynchronization in patients with advanced heart failure (i.e., New York Heart Association class III or IV) who have a wide QRS complex and who are receiving optimal medical therapy have consistently demonstrated significant improvements in quality of life, exercise capacity and cardiac function and a significant reduction in the number reaching the combined endpoint of mortality or hospitalization due to all causes. Clearly, the management of heart failure requires multidisciplinary collaboration between heart failure specialists, electrophysiologists and surgeons. However, up to 30% of patients may not benefit from this type of therapy. New markers of dyssynchrony, such as echocardiographically guided measurement of ventricular asynchrony, are currently being investigated with the aim of identifying responders more accurately. At present, the efficacy of cardiac resynchronization therapy is undergoing further study in other groups of patients who may benefit: those with atrial fibrillation (potentially 20% to 30% of patients with severe heart failure), those with dyssynchrony secondary to conventional right ventricular pacing, and those in NYHA class II. Cardiac resynchronization therapy has been shown to reduce morbidity and mortality in patients with advanced heart failure and a wide QRS complex who remain symptomatic despite optimal medical therapy. It should, therefore, be offered routinely to eligible patients with heart failure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pulpón, Luis A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Violeta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cavero, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado, Juan F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia de resincronización cardíaca produce mejoría sintomática y hemodinámica en pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca avanzada y asincronía ventricular. Los resultados de diferentes estudios han demostrado de forma consistente que la resincronización produce mejoría significativa de la calidad de vida, capacidad de ejercicio y de la función cardíaca, objetivándose una reducción significativa de la mortalidad total y del número de hospitalizaciones en pacientes tratados con insuficiencia cardíaca avanzada, en clase funcional de la New York Heart Association (NYHA) III o IV a pesar de tratamiento médico óptimo y de un complejo QRS ancho. Claramente, el tratamiento de la insuficiencia cardíaca requiere, en el momento actual, una colaboración multidisciplinaria entre los clínicos especialistas en insuficiencia cardíaca, electrofisiólogos y cirujanos. Sin embargo, hasta el 30% de los pacientes puede no beneficiarse de esta terapia. Se están investigando nuevos marcadores de asincronía, como la determinación de asincronía guiada por ecocardiografía, en un intento de mejorar la identificación de los respondedores. Actualmente se está investigando el beneficio de la terapia de resincronización en otros grupos de pacientes que potencialmente se podrían beneficiar de ella, como aquellos en fibrilación auricular (aproximadamente el 20-30% de los pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca severa), asincronía secundaria a estimulación convencional derecha, o en clase II de la NYHA. En pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca avanzada y complejo QRS ancho que permanecen sintomáticos a pesar de recibir tratamiento médico óptimo, la terapia de resincronización ha demostrado una reducción de la morbimortalidad. Por tanto, actualmente debería considerarse de forma sistemática en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);5(supl.B): 53-59, 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165410</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resincronización cardíaca: punto de vista del cardiólogo clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54223^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2353^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2068^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4630^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
