<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104909</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral cavity paracoccidioidomycosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Paracoccidioidomycosis (PCM) or South-american Blastomycosis is the most important systemic mycosis in Latin America, is relatively common in Brazil, Venezuela, Colombia, Ecuador and Argentina. Sporadic cases can also be seen in some other countries, which is a rare progressive and fatal if not treated. It has been regarded as a multifocal disease with oral lesions as the prominent feature. It is caused by a dimorphic fungus, Paracoccidioides brasiliensis, which mainly affects the skin, lymph nodes, lungs and mucous membranes, oral, nasal and gastrointestinal. Depending on the specific immunity of the host, the infection can take many forms and affects one or more organs, becoming a serious and potentially fatal disease. It is very important for health professionals worldwide have knowledge about Paracoccidioidomycosis because sometimes the disease only manifests itself many years after you have left the endemic area. To provide useful information about the diagnosis and treatment of disease A case report of case of male patient 48 years old from a rural area of Brazil Oath, presenting multiple painful ulcers on the gums and palate of 3 months duration, referred to chronic smoking history, clinical examination extraoral lesions are discarded in other intraoral examination bodies and multiple ulcers were observed necrotic and granulomatous background located on the gums and palate. We performed an incisional biopsy of the lesion and the material was sent for pathologic examination. The pathology report confirmed the clinical impression of Paracoccidioidomycosis. The patient was treated with the use of sulfamethoxazole + trimethoprim - 800/60 mg/day, orally every 12 hours for 30 days. The oral lesions disappeared completely and the patient remains under control in the service (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vergara Hernández, CI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Caballero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antunes Freitas, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreira, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La paracoccidioidomicosis (PCM) o blastomicosis suramericana es la micosis sistémica más importante de América latina que es relativamente común en Brasil, Venezuela, Colombia, Ecuador y Argentina. Los casos esporádicos también pueden verse en algunos otros países, la cual es progresiva y con un infrecuente desenlace fatal si no es tratada a tiempo. Se considera como una enfermedad multifocal, con lesiones orales como la característica prominente. Es causada por un hongo dimórfico, Paracoccidioides brasiliensis, que afecta principalmente la piel, los ganglios linfáticos, los pulmones y membranas mucosas oral, nasal y gastrointestinal. Dependiendo de la inmunidad específica del huésped, la infección puede asumir muchas formas y afecta a uno o varios órganos, llegando a ser una enfermedad grave y potencialmente fatal. Es muy importante para los profesionales de la salud de todo el mundo tener conocimiento acerca de la Paracoccidioidomicosis porque a veces la enfermedad sólo se manifiesta muchos años después de que haya abandonado la zona endémica. Para proporcionar información útil sobre el diagnóstico y tratamiento de la enfermedad se presenta caso clínico de un paciente masculino de 48 años de edad procedente de una zona rural de Juramento Brasil, por presentar múltiples úlceras dolorosas en encía y paladar de 3 meses de evolución; refiere antecedentes de fumador crónico, al examen clínico extraoral se descartan lesiones en otros órganos y al examen intraoral se observan múltiples úlceras con fondo necrótico y granulomatoso localizadas en encía y paladar. Se realizó una biopsia incisional de la lesión y el material fue enviado para estudio anatomopatológico. El informe histopatológico confirmó la impresión clínica de Paracoccidioidomicosis. El paciente fue tratado con el uso de sulfametoxazol + trimetoprima - 800/60 mg/día, vía oral, cada 12 horas durante 30 días. Las lesiones bucales desaparecieron completamente y el paciente continúa bajo control en el servicio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;28(1): 11-16, ene.-feb. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104909</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paracoccidioidomicosis en cavidad oral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10413^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24903^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9373^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10414^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
