<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91290</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orthorexia: from a healthy concern to a pathology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The tendency to worship the body and eating disorders are evidentfacts in today&#146;s Western countries in which people have putinto their minds that having a good physical appearance and enjoyinga good health are the formula to reach happiness andas a result people feel attracted towards all healthy activities andproducts. Hand in hand with that comes an eating disorderknown as orthorexia. This disease is characterised by an excessivefocus on eating healthy foods. The prevalence of thisdisorder is currently unknown in Spain as it a rather rare andnew phenomena. Some specialist estimate that from 0.5 to 1%of their total number of visits have been with orthorexic patients.The disorder is based on sociocultural factors as the hypothesisto get completely natural products in today&#146;s modernsocieties is practically nil.This fixation has a direct impact on the emerging association betweenmental problems and endocrine disorders. This paperdepicts the problem from its origin and establishes its prevalenceand the groups at risk. It also describes the characteristicsand effects of this &#147;addiction&#148; to the consumption of healthyfoods (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Medina, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La tendencia de culto al cuerpo y trastornos alimentarios sonhechos evidentes en la sociedad occidental actual, en la que seha interiorizado que un buen aspecto físico y salud son sinónimosde felicidad y por extensión, las personas se sientenatraídas por todas las actividades y productos saludables. Dela mano viene un emergente trastorno alimentario: la ortorexia,donde se manifiesta una preocupación patológica por ladieta sana. En España, actualmente, se desconoce la prevalenciade este trastorno ya que es un fenómeno muy novedoso,aunque algunos especialistas apuntan que entre sus visitashan tenido entre un 0,5 y 1% de pacientes ortoréxicos. El trastornose da fundamentalmente por factores socioculturales, yaque la hipótesis de conseguir alimentos totalmente naturalesen las &#147;sociedades modernas&#148; son casi nulas, incidiendo en laemergente proyección de los problemas mentales en trastornosendocrinos. El presente artículo analiza el problema desdesus orígenes, así como la prevalencia y grupos de riesgo, parapasar a ver las características y efectos de esta adicción (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;12(6): 14-19, jul. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ortorexia: de sana inquietuda patología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32738^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23944^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
