<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113547</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The child in the survival chain: A useful intervening party. Study on a simulation scenario</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiac arrest is a major health problem in the Western world. As a result of that, institutinons have developed programs that allow early action since the collapse, including telephone-directed cardiopulmonary resuscitation and population training. This study assesses the capacity as a first responder for children aged 8-12 years (4º-5º-6º primary education) to follow telephone-directed cardiopulmonary resuscitation without prior knowledge, the impact of training on the quality of resuscitation maneuvers and relationship with anthropometric variables. We performed an observational and quasi experimental simulation scenario with a sample of 158 children. No child reached 80% effectiveness of compressions. After the training, records improve p&lt;0,05, the percentage of students able to make any effective compressions were 28,57% compared with the initial registration (12%) p&lt;0,004, four pupils of 6º achieved efficiency above 80% and four pupils of 4º above 56% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cobos Malo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cepero García, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu Gracia, S. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pelay Barcelona, M. Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón Ramas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belenguer Sancho, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La parada cardiaca representa un problema sanitario en el mundo occidental; como consecuencia se han desarrollado programas que permiten una pronta actuación desde el colapso, entre ellos se encuentra la RCP guiada telefónicamente y la formación a la población. El trabajo valora la capacidad como primer interviniente de niños con edades comprendidas entre 8-12 años (4º-5º-6º educación primaria) para seguir indicaciones de RCP telefónicas sin conocimientos previos, el impacto de la formación sobre la calidad de las maniobras de reanimación y la relación con variables antropométricas. Se realizó un estudio observacional y cuasi-experimental sobre un escenario de simulación con una muestra de 168 niños, en la que ningún niño alcanzó el 80% de efectividad de las compresiones. Tras la formación mejoran los registros p&lt;0,05, el porcentaje de alumnos capaces de realizar alguna comprensión efectiva pasó del 12% al 28,57% p&lt;0,004, cuatro alumnos de 6º consiguieron efectividad por encima del 80% y cuatro de 5º por encima del 56% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;68(3): 226-233, mayo-jun. 2012. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113547</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El niño en la cadena de supervivencia ¿Un interviniente útil? Estudio sobre un escenario de simulación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6475^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30213^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5527^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33168</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
