<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153957</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Outbreak of Trichophyton tonsurans ringworm in a health area of the Community of Madrid (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Trichophyton tonsurans is a dermatophyte fungus that can cause ringworm outbreaks. In our health area in September 2013, two cases of T. tonsurans ringworm were diagnosed in children who lived in a Children's Centre. Aims. To determine the origin and extent of the outbreak. Methods. Mycological cultures of scalp and skin samples from the contacts of the diagnosed cases were performed, as well as environmental samples from the Children's Centre. The patients started with a treatment for their ringworm, and an environmental disinfection of the centre was performed. Results. Twelve cases of ringworm were detected, along with three asymptomatic scalp carriers of T. tonsurans among 20 children in the Centre. The index case was a resident in whose family, that had just returned from their country of origin, Nigeria, three cases of ringworm were diagnosed. From November 2013 to February 2014 another five cases of ringworm were diagnosed among schoolmates of three cases from the Children's Centre. Conclusions. The antifungal treatment of the children resulted in the mycological and clinical resolution, and from February to November 2014 no other cases of ringworm by T. tonsurans in the same health area were diagnosed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Velasco-Rodríguez, Manuel José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Regodón-Domínguez, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aragón, Andrés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durán-Valle, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Garcés, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. Trichophyton tonsurans es un hongo dermatofito que puede dar lugar a epidemias de tiña. En septiembre de 2013 fueron diagnosticados en nuestra área sanitaria dos casos de tiña por T. tonsurans en niños que convivían en un centro infantil. Objetivos. Conocer el origen y la extensión del brote. Métodos. Se realizaron cultivos micológicos de muestras de cuero cabelludo y piel de los contactos de los casos detectados, y de muestras ambientales del centro infantil. Se inició el tratamiento de los pacientes y la desinfección ambiental del centro. Resultados. Se identificaron doce casos de tiña y tres portadores asintomáticos de T. tonsurans en el cuero cabelludo entre los 20 menores residentes del centro infantil. El caso índice fue un residente del centro en cuya familia, que acababa de regresar de su país de origen, Nigeria, se detectaron tres casos de tiña. Desde noviembre de 2013 a febrero de 2014 se diagnosticaron otros cinco casos de tiña en compañeros de colegio de tres casos del centro infantil. Conclusiones. El tratamiento resolvió clínica y micológicamente los casos, y entre marzo y noviembre de 2014 no se diagnosticó ningún otro caso de tiña por T. tonsurans en la misma área sanitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;33(2): 126-128, abr.-jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153957</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemia de tiña por Trichophyton tonsurans en un área sanitaria de la Comunidad de Madrid (España)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24966^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7819^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2397^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14649^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14392^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14392^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2397^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14392^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7274^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54398^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14392^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14392^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
