<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114834</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Situational leadership in nursing in a health institution in Bucaramanga, Colombia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction In nursing, it is crucial to know the leadership style required in each situation to act as a leader. The clinical nurse must have an effective leadership style that suits the situations presented during the performance of their functions, in order to achieve the objectives in the care of the patient and family. Objectives To describe the situational leadership styles present in nurses in hospital departments, including intensive care, according to the theory of Hersey and Blanchard and to determine the relationship between leadership styles and occupational variables. Methodology A cross-sectional descriptive study was conducted on a sample population of 107 nurses working in clinical areas of hospital and intensive care in two health institutions. The Dr. Herman Bachenheimer situational leadership tool was applied to nursing staff. Results The nurses at the hospital area (61) and intensive care (46) have mainly a guide-leadership style (35.4%), followed by a participative style (33.9%) and manager-style (27.9%). Delegation leadership style (2.8%) was not present in clinical nurses. There is no significant relationship between leadership styles and the time working in the institution. A statistically significant relationship was found between leadership styles and length of management experience in the clinical area (P = .011). Conclusions The predominant leadership style of hospital nurses is to guide, and for intensive care nurses it is participatory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres-Contreras, Claudia Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción Para el trabajo de enfermería es determinante conocer el estilo de liderazgo que se maneje en cada situación para desempeñar la función de líder. La enfermera asistencial debe tener un estilo de liderazgo eficaz que se adapte a las situaciones presentadas en el desempeño de sus funciones para alcanzar los objetivos propuestos en la atención al paciente y a su familia. Objetivos Describir los estilos de liderazgo situacional presentes en las enfermeras de los servicios de hospitalización y cuidados intensivos según la teoría de Hersey y Blanchard y determinar la relación entre los estilos de liderazgo y las variables laborales. Metodología Estudio descriptivo de corte transversal, cuya población y muestra fueron 107 enfermeras que laboran en área clínica de los servicios de hospitalización y cuidados intensivos de 2 instituciones de salud. Se utilizó el instrumento de liderazgo situacional Dr. Herman Bachenheimer aplicado al personal de enfermería. Resultados Las enfermeras de hospitalización (61) y cuidados intensivos (46) presentan principalmente un estilo de liderazgo guiar (35,4%), seguido del estilo participativo (33,9%) y directivo (27,9%). El estilo delegativo (2,8%) no está presente en las enfermeras clínicas. No existe relación significativa entre los estilos de liderazgo y el tiempo de estar laborando en la institución. Se encontró relación estadísticamente significativa entre los estilos de liderazgo directivo y el tiempo de experiencia en el área clínica, evidenciado por una p de 0,011. Conclusiones El estilo de liderazgo predominante en las enfermeras de hospitalización es guiar y en las enfermeras de cuidados intensivos es participativo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);23(4): 140-147, jul.-agos. 2013. tab, ima</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114834</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Liderazgo situacional en enfermeras de una institución de salud de Bucaramanga (Colombia)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8035</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9924^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3137</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
