<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154590</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Diagnostic and prognostic efficiency of 24-hour Holter monitoring in patients with syncope</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Syncope is a common condition and complex to diagnose. The yield of the 24h-Holter ECG in this context has not been clearly defined. The aim of this study was to evaluate its diagnostic and prognostic capacity in these patients. Patients and method: Retrospective study of 6,006 consecutive patients sent to our unit for 24h-Holter ECG monitoring for syncope. We registered the diagnostic findings and abnormal findings potentially related to an arrhythmic cause of syncope. The prognostic endpoint was a combination of death or the need for device implantation (pacemaker or defibrillator) within one year. Results: 242 patients (4%) presented diagnostic findings and 472 (7.9%) had some abnormal findings. In 328 cases device implantation was necessary within one year, but up to 66% of these patients did not have any relevant findings on the Holter monitoring. A total of 564 patients presented the combined event, including 36.8% of patients with diagnostic findings and 8.2% without them. Conclusions: 24h-Holter ECG monitoring presents a limited diagnostic and prognostic yield in unselected patients with syncope (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bouzas Mosquera, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barbeito Caamaño, Cayetana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Broullón, Francisco J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Fernández, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez García, Nemesio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Rodríguez, José Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes y objetivo: El síncope es una entidad frecuente y con un diagnóstico complejo. El rendimiento del Holter-ECG 24h en este contexto no está bien definido. Nuestro objetivo fue evaluar su capacidad diagnóstica y pronóstica en estos pacientes. Pacientes y método: Estudio retrospectivo de 6.006 pacientes consecutivos remitidos a nuestra unidad para la realización de Holter-ECG 24h por síncope. Se registraron los hallazgos diagnósticos y aquellos hallazgos anormales potencialmente relacionados con una causa arrítmica de síncope. El objetivo pronóstico fue un combinado de muerte o necesidad de implante de dispositivo (marcapasos o desfibrilador implantable) a un año. Resultados: En total, 242 pacientes (4%) presentaron hallazgos diagnósticos y 472 (7,9%) tuvieron algún hallazgo anormal. En 328 casos fue necesario el implante de un dispositivo a un año, pero hasta un 66% de estos enfermos no tenían ningún hallazgo relevante en el Holter. Un total de 564 pacientes presentaron el episodio combinado, incluyendo el 36,8% de pacientes con hallazgos diagnósticos y el 8,2% sin hallazgos diagnósticos. Conclusiones: El Holter-ECG 24h presenta un rendimiento diagnóstico y pronóstico limitados en pacientes no seleccionados con síncope (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);147(4): 148-150, ago. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154590</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rendimiento diagnóstico y pronóstico del registro Holter de 24horas en pacientes con síncope</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30763^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10326^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29417^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13955^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6484^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
