<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89582</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assesment versus grading in the new European Higher Education Area (EHEA), an ethical-critical approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The European Convergence process is a major change affecting most of European states, by introducing new elements in order to harmonize its policies. In terms of education, there are significant changes in educational systems, especially those concerning university studies. In this frame, new educational methodologies in nursing studies have started to develop through pilot experiences in different European universities. In this article, one of these particular experiences, developed by the University of Almería (Spain) is described, especially in terms of objectivity and considering exams as an exclusive assessment methodology. After an exhaustive review of this topic, and due to the unspecificity of reliable tools for assessing knowledge, as well as attitudes and skills, we propose an ethical-critical review of the assessment concept, from a practical rationality that goes far beyond positivist and utilitarian aspects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Granero Molina, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Sola, Cayetano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera Manrique, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El proceso de Convergencia Europea es un cambio que afecta a la mayoría de los estados europeos, introduciendo elementos que tienden a armonizar sus políticas. En materia de educación las modificaciones de los sistemas educativos son significativas, y esencialmente en los estudios universitarios. Inmersos en este proceso, el empleo de nuevas metodologías educativas en Enfermería se desarrolla a través de experiencias piloto en distintas universidades europeas. A través de un estudio de revisión, se reflexiona sobre una de estas experiencias desarrolladas en la Universidad de Almería (España), atendiendo esencialmente a la objetividad y el empleo del examen como metodología exclusiva de evaluación del alumno. Tras una revisión exhaustiva sobre el tema, y ante la inespecifidad de instrumentos que midan fiablemente conocimientos, pero sobre todo actitudes y habilidades; se plantea una revisión ético-crítica del concepto de evaluación desde una racionalidad práctica que se separa de los aspectos positivistas y utilitaristas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(1): 37-41, ene.-mar. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89582</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación frente a calificación en el nuevo Espacio Europeo de Educación Superior (EEES), una reflexión ético-crítica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36363</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14893^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5160</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
