<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114989</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Experience of the care of nurses to the person in the process of death</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The objective of this study is to understand how nurses experience the care of the person in the process of death and dying. Method: Phenomenological study with fourteen nurses of the unit of long-stay patients and of the medical clinic of a general hospital, through phenomenological interview, after approval by the Ethics in Research Committee, Protocol No. 031/2010. The phenomenological analysis went through the steps of description, reduction and understanding. Results: It was unveiled the suffering in face of death in the daily work, death as a remarkable experience and the existential void in face of death. Conclusion: The nurses unveiled in their testimonies anxiety, fear and death as a remarkable experience that makes nurses reveal the difficult acceptance and existential vacuum (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guedes Fontoura, Elaine</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Oliveira Santa Rosa, Darci</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio es comprender como las enfermeras vivencian el cuidado a la persona en el proceso de morir. Método: estudio fenomenológico con catorce enfermeras de la unidad de pacientes de larga duración y de la clínica médica de un hospital general, a través de entrevista fenomenológica, posterior aprobación por el Comité de Ética en Investigación. El análisis fenomenológico pasó por las etapas de descripción, reducción y comprensión. Resultados: fueron desvelados el sufrimiento ante de la muerte en el cotidiano laboral, la muerte como una experiencia inolvidable, y el vacío existencial ante de la muerte. Conclusión: Las enfermeras mostraron ansiedad, miedo y la muerte como una experiencia inolvidable, revelando la difícil aceptación y el vacío existencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;22(1/2): 25-29, ene.-jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114989</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vivencia de las enfermeras ante los cuidados en el proceso de muerte</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9912^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
