<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165745</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pressure ulcers and moisture associated skin damage prevalence in the Burgos University Hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: Determine the prevalence of pressure ulcers (PU) and moisture associated skin damage (MASD) at Burgos University Hospital. Identify lesions and their characteristics. Identify the risk assessment surveys of PU recorded in the health record and the use of prevention devices. Identify nursing records related to PU and MASD. Methods: Transversal descriptive observational study, by direct observation of each patient and review of their health record. Conducted between February 23rd and March 10th, 2015. Results: The study population was 404 patients. 195 lesions were identified: 24 MASD and 171 PU. The resulting prevalences were 5.69% for MASD and 21.53% for PU. 93,56% of PU were stages I and II. The most common anatomic sites were: elbow (28,07%), heel (22,8%), ear (18,12%) and sacrum (11,11%). Using the Norton scale, PU risk was assessed in 164 patients (48.59%), with 46 patients (28.05%) exhibiting medium to high risk levels. 31 patients had additional prevention devices (7.67%), while 29 patients (7.17%) with identified risk had no device. Conclusions: The resulting prevalence of PU is high due to increased detection of mild stages. Conducting risk assessment of PU to all hospitalized patients is advised. Likewise it is pertinent to increase training in detection and prevention of the milder stages (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Real López, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Romero, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capa Santamaría, Sheila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesia García, Elena de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez Estébanez, M Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santamaría González, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Hernantes, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la prevalencia de úlceras por presión (UPP) y lesiones cutáneas asociadas a la humedad (LESCAH) en el Hospital Universitario de Burgos. Identificar las lesiones y sus características. Identificar las valoraciones del riesgo de padecer UPP registradas en la historia clínica y el uso de dispositivos de prevención. Identificar los registros de Enfermería relacionados con las UPP y LESCAH. Metodología: Estudio observacional descriptivo transversal, mediante inspección directa de cada paciente y revisión de la historia clínica. Realizado entre el 23 de febrero y el 10 de marzo del 2015. Resultados: La población estudiada fue de 404 pacientes. Se identificaron 195 lesiones: 24 LESCAH y 171 UPP. Las prevalencias resultantes fueron 5,69% para las LESCAH y 21,53% para las UPP. El 93,56% de las UPP pertenecen a los estadios I y II. Las localizaciones anatómicas más frecuentes fueron: codo (28,07%), talón (22,8%), oreja (18,12%) y sacro (11,11%). Se encontró registro de la valoración del riesgo mediante escala de Norton en 164 (48,59%) pacientes, presentando riesgo entre medio y muy alto, 46 (28,05%) pacientes. Contaban con algún dispositivo de prevención adicional 31 (7,67%) pacientes, mientras que 29 (7,17%) pacientes, con riesgo detectado, carecían de él. Conclusiones: La prevalencia resultante de UPP es elevada debido a la mayor detección de estadios leves. Se aconseja la realización de valoración del riesgo de padecer UPP a todos los pacientes ingresados. Así mismo, se considera necesario aumentar la formación en detección y prevención de los estadios más leves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);28(2): 103-108, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165745</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de úlceras por presión y lesiones cutáneas asociadas a la humedad en el Hospital Universitario de Burgos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33939^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6965^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13264^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
