<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-102964</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Information competence in nursing and other health professionals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The activities of health professionals, whether from the aspect of the student, and later in clinical practice, research or education, are intensive in information. Internet has become the most dynamic means to find and retrieve biomedical information since the emergence of computerized databases. There are two factors driving this development of informational competence: the first one is the need to perform successfully in the "information and knowledge scene", the second one is the emergence of the practice of medicine and evidence-based nursing. Informational competence has a repercussion on the quality of documentary production and quality of care. The present article describes the basic elements that make up informational competence for health professionals grouping them into three sections: knowledge, skills and attitudes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lleixà-Fortuño, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Martínez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto-de la Fuente, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albacar-Ribóo, Nùria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Internet se ha convertido en el medio más dinámico para encontrar y recuperar información biomédica desde la eclosión de las bases de datos automatizadas. Las actividades de los profesionales de la salud, ya sean desde la faceta del estudiante, y después en la práctica clínica, la investigación o la educación, son intensivas en información. Dos grandes motores impulsan el desarrollo de la competencia informacional: el primero es la necesidad de desempeñarse exitosamente en la "sociedad de la información y el conocimiento"; el segundo, la emergencia de la práctica de la medicina y enfermería basadas en la evidencia. La competencia informacional tiene repercusiones en la calidad de la producción documental y en la calidad asistencial. En el presente artículo se describen los elementos básicos que componen la competencia en información para los profesionales de la salud agrupados en tres bloques: conocimientos, habilidades y actitudes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;20(4): 257-261, oct.-dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-102964</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Competencia informacional en enfermería y otros profesionales de la salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19081</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9927^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30349^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19131^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
