<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159408</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-1342</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Spherical subjective refraction with a novel 3D virtual reality based system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To conduct a clinical validation of a virtual reality-based experimental system that is able to assess the spherical subjective refraction simplifying the methodology of ocular refraction. Methods: For the agreement assessment, spherical refraction measurements were obtained from 104 eyes of 52 subjects using three different methods: subjectively with the experimental prototype (Subj.E) and the classical subjective refraction (Subj.C); and objectively with the WAM-5500 autorefractor (WAM). To evaluate precision (intra- and inter-observer variability) of each refractive tool independently, 26 eyes were measured in four occasions. Results: With regard to agreement, the mean difference (±SD) for the spherical equivalent (M) between the new experimental subjective method (Subj.E) and the classical subjective refraction (Subj.C) was &amp;#8722;0.034 D (±0.454 D). The corresponding 95% Limits of Agreement (LoA) were (&amp;#8722;0.856 D, 0.924 D). In relation to precision, intra-observer mean difference for the M component was 0.034 ± 0.195 D for the Subj.C, 0.015 ± 0.177 D for the WAM and 0.072 ± 0.197 D for the Subj.E. Inter-observer variability showed worse precision values, although still clinically valid (below 0.25 D) in all instruments. Conclusions: The spherical equivalent obtained with the new experimental system was precise and in good agreement with the classical subjective routine. The algorithm implemented in this new system and its optical configuration has been shown to be a first valid step for spherical error correction in a semiautomated way (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ondategui-Parra, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero, Carles</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badiella, Llorenç</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pujol, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aldaba, Mikel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilaseca,  Meritxell</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar una validación clínica de un sistema experimental basado en realidad virtual, capaz de evaluar la refracción subjetiva esférica simplificando la metodología de la refracción ocular. Métodos: Para evaluar la concordancia, se obtuvieron mediciones de la refracción esférica de 104 ojos pertenecientes a 52 sujetos, utilizando tres métodos diferentes: subjetivamente con el prototipo experimental (Subj.E) y la refracción subjetiva clásica (Subj.C); y objetivamente con el autorrefractómetro WAM-5500 (WAM). Para evaluar la precisión (variabilidad intra e inter-observador) de cada herramienta refractiva, de forma independiente, se midieron 26 ojos en cuatro ocasiones. Resultados: Con respecto a la concordancia, la diferencia media (±DE) para el equivalente esférico (M) entre el nuevo método subjetivo experimental (Subj.E) y la refracción subjetiva clásica (Subj.C) fue de &amp;#8722;0,034 D (±0,454 D). El 95% correspondiente a los Límites de la Concordancia (LoA) fue de (&amp;#8722;0,856 D, 0,924 D). En relación a la precisión, la diferencia media intra observador para el componente M fue de 0,034 ± 0,195 D para Subj.C, 0,015 ± 0,177 D para WAM y 0,072 ± 0,197 D para Subj.E. La variabilidad inter observador reflejó peores valores de precisión, aunque fueron clínicamente válidos (inferiores a 0,25 D) en todos los instrumentos. Conclusiones: El equivalente esférico obtenido con el nuevo sistema experimental fue preciso y guardó consonancia con la rutina subjetiva clásica. El algoritmo introducido en este nuevo sistema, y su configuración óptica, han demostrado ser un avance válido para la corrección del error esférico de modo semi-automático (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>J. optom. (Internet);10(1): 43-51, ene.-mar. 2017. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159408</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Refracción subjetiva esférica utilizando un nuevo sistema 3D basado en realidad virtual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6531</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55091^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55091^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12451^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24366^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
