<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043654</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Erythrocytic aggregation in the physiopathogenesis of diabetic microangiopasthic skin lesions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Diabetes can produce significant skin lesions. Some of them are linked to microcirculatory changes (diabetic dermopathy, pigmentary purpura, erythrosis, erysipela-like erythema, facial rubeosis, and perionychial telangiectases). There is increasing evidence that hemorheological abnormalities play a definitive role in diabetes mellitus. Consequently, the present study analyzed red blood cell aggregation in diabetic patients with and without skin lesions. Patients and method: Eighty-six type 1 and type 2 diabetic patients of both sexes and similar ages, with (28) and without (58) skin lesions and 20 healthy controls underwent clinical, dermatological and hemorheological studies. Red blood cell aggregation was measured using direct microscopic observation and the recorded digitized images were numerically processed through the aggregate shape parameter (ASP). ANOVA, Student's t-test and the chi-square test were employed. Results: Diabetic patients with skin lesions had longer disease duration than those without and their ASP (0.692 ± 0.066) significantly exceeded that of controls (0.288 ± 0.134) (p = 0.65 was higher in those with cutaneous lesions than in those without (80% versus 45%, p = 0.006). Conclusions: Red blood cell aggregation may participate in the development of diabetic microangiopathy and in the appearance of the above-mentioned dermatologic lesions</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carrera, LI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>D'Arrigo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Foresto, P. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Etchepare, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>D'ottavio, A. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La diabetes puede producir importantes lesiones cutáneas; algunas microangiopáticas (dermopatía diabética, púrpura pigmentaria, eritrosis, eritema símil erisipela, rubeosis facial y telengiectasias periungueales). Existe creciente evidencia de que las anormalidades hemorreológicas desempeñan un papel definido en esta enfermedad. En consecuencia, este trabajo analiza la agregación eritrocitaria en pacientes diabéticos con y sin lesiones cutáneas Pacientes y método: Se estudió clínica, dermatológica y hemorreológicamente a 86 pacientes con diabetes tipos 1 y 2, de ambos sexos y edades similares, con lesiones cutáneas (28) y sin ellas (58), y 20 controles sanos. La agregación eritrocitaria se midió mediante observación microscópica directa y procesamiento numérico de las imágenes digitalizadas recogidas a través del llamado Parámetro de Forma de los Agregados (ASP). Los datos se analizaron con ANOVA y las pruebas de la t de Student y de la *2. Resultados: El tiempo de evolución de los pacientes diabéticos con lesiones cutáneas fue más prolongado y su ASP (0,692 ± 0,066) excedió significativamente el de los controles (0,288 ± 0,134) (p = 0,65 fue superior en aquéllos que presentaban lesiones cutáneas (el 80 frente al 45%; p = 0,006). Conclusiones La agregación eritrocitaria puede participar en el desarrollo de la microangiopatía diabética y en la aparición de las citadas lesiones dermatológicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;53(4): 242-245, abr. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043654</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La agregación eritrocitaria en la fisiopatogenia de las lesiones cutáneas microangiopáticas diabéticas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4990</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3948^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31417^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
