<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137616</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Esophagogastric pathology in morbid obese patient: Preoperative diagnosis and influence in the selection of surgical technique</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Given the difficulty in accessing to the excluded stomach after gastric bypass and the increase in gastroesophageal reflux after sleeve gastrectomy, it is justified to perform a preoperative fibrogastroscopy. The influence of the fibrogastroscopy (FGS) findings in the therapeutic approach is analyzed. Patients and methods: A retrospective study of preoperative FGS findings is performed, from 04/06 to 12/12. The influence of the FGS results on the surgical technique selection, in the endoscopic or medical treatment and its relation to gastric fistula is analyzed by means of multivariate regression (confounding factors: Age, body mass index, arterial hypertension, diabetes mellitus, antiplatelet therapy, surgical technique (bariatric surgery, sleeve gastrectomy). Results: Three hundred thirty one patients are included: 32.6% biopsy of gastric lesion; 27% gastritis; 18.1% hiatal hernia; 3% metaplasia; 0.6% Barrett esophagus; 2.1% esophagitis; 0.3% dysplasia; 0.3 Schatzky´s ring; 1.5% incompetent cardia; 2.4% duodenitis; 0.3% gastric erosions; 0.6% gastric xanthoma; 1.8%, gastric polyp; 1.6% duodenal ulcer; 0.6% papulo-erosive gastritis; 0.6% esophageal papilloma; 0.3% submucosal tumor. Helicobacter pylori+ 30.2% (triple therapy eradication in all patients). The FGS findings led to a variation in the surgical technique or to the completion of endoscopic treatment in 22.2% of cases. The gastric lesions did not influence the development of gastric fistula. Independent prognostic factors of fistula: Sleeve gastrectomy (7.9% vs. 2.7%; p = 0.02; OR: 1.38 IC95: 1.01-1.87) and the body mass index &gt; 50 kg/m2) (6.7% vs. 2.2%; p = 0.04; OR: 3.7 IC95: 1.12-12.4). Conclusions: The diagnosis of gastroesophageal disease through preoperative FGS motivated variations in the therapeutic approach in 52% of patients, so we consider essential to include the preoperative FGS in bariatric surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estévez Fernández, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Fernández, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Turnes Vázquez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Santos, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mariño Padín, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la dificultad de acceso al estómago excluido tras el bypass gástrico (BG) y el empeoramiento del reflujo gastroesofágico tras la gastrectomía vertical (GV) justifican la fibrogastroscopia (FGS) preoperatoria. Se analiza la influencia de los hallazgos de FGS en la actitud terapéutica. Pacientes y métodos: estudio retrospectivo de hallazgos de FGS previa a cirugía bariátrica desde 04/06 a 12/12. Influencia del resultado FGS en la selección de la técnica quirúrgica y en el tratamiento médico o endoscópico; y su relación con la fístula gástrica mediante regresión multivariada (factores de confusión: edad, índice de masa corporal, hipertensión arterial, diabetes mellitus, tratamiento antiagregante, técnica quirúrgica (bypass gástrico o gastrectomía vertical). Resultados: se incluyen 331 pacientes: 32,6% biopsia de lesión gástrica; 27% gastritis. 18,1% de hernia de hiato; 3% metaplasia, 0,6% Barret, 2,1% esofagitis, 0,3% displasia, 0,3 anillo de Schalzsky, 1,5% de cardias incompetente, 2,4% de duodenitis, 0,3% erosiones gástricas, 0,6% xantoma gástrico, 1,8%, pólipos gástricos, 1,6%, úlcera duodenal, 0,6% gastritis papuloerosiva, 0,6% papiloma esofágico, 0,3% tumor submucoso. Helicobacter pylori+ 30,2% (triple terapia añadida en todos). Variación de técnica quirúrgica o tratamiento endoscópico debido a FGS 22,2%. Las lesiones gástricas no influyeron en el desarrollo de fístula gástrica. Factores pronósticos independientes de fístula: GV (7,9% vs. 2,7%; p = 0,02; OR: 1,38 IC95: 1,01-1,87) y el índice de masa corporal (IMC) &gt; 50 kg/m2 (6,7% vs. 2,2%; p = 0,04; OR: 3,7 IC95: 1,12-12,4). Conclusiones: el diagnóstico de patología esofagogástrica mediante FGS preoperatoria motivó variaciones en la actitud terapéutica del 52% de los procedimientos, por lo que consideramos imprescindible incluir la FGS en el preoperatorio de la cirugía bariátrica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;107(7): 408-412, jul. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Patología esofagogástrica en el obeso mórbido: diagnóstico preoperatorio e influencia en la selección de la técnica quirúrgica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5884^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19272^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5897^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5897^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
