<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72579</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale for Children and Adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this study was to analyze the component structure and reliability of the Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale for Children and Adolescents, self-report version (LSAS-CA-SR), in a Spanish community population. The sample was made up of 422 students from elementary and high schools, aged between 10 and 17 years. Exploratory factor analysis isolated one component for the Anxiety subscale and one component for the Avoidance subscale. Medium-strong associations were found between the total score and subscale scores. LSAS-CA-SR scores had stronger associations with instruments of social anxiety. Internal consistency for the Fear subscale was .91, and for the Avoidance subscale, it was .89. Gender and age effects were assessed for LSAS-CA-SR scores. Effect sizes for age and gender and interaction of age and gender were very low on both the Fear and the Avoidance subscales. There were significant differences between female and male means on the Fear subscale. The findings suggest that the LSAS-CA-SR is reliable and valid (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olivares, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Pina, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-García, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar la estructura factorial y la fiabilidad de la Escala de Ansiedad Social para Niños y Adolescentes de Liebowitz en su versión autoinforme (LSAS-CA-SR), en una muestra comunitaria española de 422 estudiantes entre 10 y 17 años. El análisis factorial exploratorio aisló un componente para la subescala de ansiedad y un componente para la subescala de evitación. Las correlaciones entre la puntuación total y las puntuaciones de las subescalas fueron de medias a elevadas. Las puntuaciones de la LSAS-CA-SR obtuvieron correlaciones elevadas con otras medidas de ansiedad social. La consistencia interna en la subescala de miedo fue de 0,91, y en la subescala de evitación de 0,89; los tamaños del efecto para la edad y el género y su interacción fueron bajos en ambas. Sin embargo, se encontraron diferencias significativas entre varones y mujeres en la subescala de miedo. Los hallazgos sugieren que la adaptación de la LSAS-CA-SR es fiable y válida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);21(3): 486-491, jul.-sept. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72579</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La Escala de Ansiedad Social de Liebowitz para Niños y Adolescentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
