<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-21359</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Approximation to the cost of pharmacological treatment of rheumatoid arthritis in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To study the direct cost derived of utilization of pharmaceutical compounds in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis(RA). Material and methods: A prospective study with 150 patients (125 women/25 men) suffered of RA was carry out in Galicia-Spain public hospital. The mean age was 60,2 years , with a mean lengthy of disease of 11,2 years (1-53); the 64,4% come from rural areas. A personal interview was made with a complete registry of all data: demographic, activity score (ESR, Swollen joints), radiological status, functional class (ACR), extrarticular manifestations and co-morbid diseases. Such data was accomplished with all the medications employees with a calculation of monthly or annual cost for the different therapeutic groups and a final total cost. The statistical study was made with Excel´s (Microsoft) and the Analysis Tool Pack. Results: The 53% of patients was in functional class I and 52% in radiological stage I or II (Steinbrocker) whereas 16 patients was considered in remission. Non-steroideal ant-inflammatory drugs (NSAID) were used in the 82.7% of patients with a monthly cost of 12.71 &amp;#128; (1.10-80). Corticosteroids at low doses were used in 90.7% with a monthly cost of 5.17 &amp;#128; (1.24-33.7). The Disease Modifying Anti-rheumatic Drugs (DMARD) was used in 94% of cases, the most common methotrexate and association of two or more in 21%. The mean monthly cost for a single DMARD was 3,63 &amp;#128; and for two, 13.75 &amp;#128;. Gastroprotection and therapy for co-morbid diseases was employee in 80% and 95% of cases, with a monthly cost of 36,9&amp;#128; and year cost of 568.6 &amp;#128;, respectively. The study included 23 patients under treatment with anti-TNF therapy with a monthly mean cost of 933.8 &amp;#128;. For pharmaceuticals exclusively for RA, annual cost was 342.8 &amp;#128; excluding anti-TNF therapy, but with wide variation (6.4-2.910). If we include all patients with anti-TNF therapy, gastro-protection and co-morbid situations in a calculation, the mean cost was 2,587 year. The most important cost was found in patients with 50-70 years-old and existing a good correlation between the final burden and use of medications for co-morbid conditions, gastro-protection, use of anti-TNF, age, lengthy of disease between 5-10 years and number of swollen joints, but not radiological stage. Conclusions: The economic burden for pharmaceuticals used in RA is very variable depending of some variables, including the proper disease and other related conditions. The most important cost occur in case of use of anti-TNF therapy. In the most frequent conditions, gastro-protection and therapy for co-morbid diseases lead the 62% of total annual burden, followed by the use of DMARD and in a minor load, the NSAIDs and corticosteroids (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Arán Ediciones, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Estudiar el coste directo derivado de la utilización de fármacos en el tratamiento de la artritis reumatoide (AR) en España. Material y métodos: Un estudio prospectivo de 150 pacientes (125 mujeres/25 varones) con AR se realizó en un hospital público de la Comunidad de Galicia. La edad media fue de 60,2 años, con un tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad de 11,2 años (1-53); el 64,4 por ciento de los pacientes procedía de medio rural. Se realizó entrevista personal con registro completo de todos los datos: demográficos, actividad de la enfermedad (VSG, número de articulaciones inflamadas), estadio radiológico, estadío funcional (ACR), manifestaciones extrarticulares y enfermedades concomitantes, así como el coste mensual o anual y coste total final, según correspondiese. El estudio estadístico se realizó con el paquete Excel (Microsoft) y la herramienta Analisis Tool Pack del mismo. Resultados: El 53 por ciento de los pacientes estaban en clase funcional ACR I y 52 por ciento en estadio radiológico I o II de Steinbrocker. 16 pacientes estaban en remisión. El 82,7 por ciento de los pacientes usaban algún antinflamatorio no esteroideo, con un coste mensual de 12,71&#128; (1,10-80,1 &#128;); Estaban recibiendo corticoides el 90,7 por ciento, con un coste mensual 5,17 &#128; (1,24-33,7 &#128;).Un 94 por ciento empleaban algún fármaco de acción lenta (FARAL), el más común de ellos, metotrexato y tratamiento combinado con más de un FARAL el 21 por ciento. El coste medio mensual para uso de un solo FARAL, en general MTX, fue de 3,63 &#128;. El uso de combinaciones de 2 de estos fármacos supone 13,75 &#128;/mes. El 80 por ciento de todos los pacientes usaban alguna vez fármacos gastroprotectores con un coste mensual medio de 36,9 y para otras patologías concomitantes recibían tratamiento con algún fármaco a lo largo de un año el 95 por ciento, cuyo coste sumado al de la gastroprotección supone por paciente y año 568,6 &#128;. Se han incluido 23 pacientes que recibían anti-TNF, con un coste mensual medio de 933,8 &#128;. El coste medio anual para una AR en fármacos exclusivos para artritis fue de 342,8 &#128; sin el empleo de anti-TNF, aunque con amplias variaciones (6,47-2910 ). Con la inclusión de fármacos para enfermedades concomitantes, gastroprotección y aquellos que usan anti-TNF, el coste anual por paciente es de 2.587 &#128;. El mayor gasto farmacéutico se produce en edades entre 50 y 70 años. Hemos encontrado una buena correlación entre un mayor coste total y el uso de fármacos para otras enfermedades diferentes de la artritis, el uso de gastroprotección, el uso de anti-TNF, la edad, el grupo de tiempo de evolución de la enfermedad de 5 a 10 años, el número de articulaciones inflamadas, pero no así el estadio radiológico. Conclusiones: La carga económica por consumo de fármacos en la AR es muy variable dependiendo de varias variables que incluyen la propia enfermedad y otras condiciones relacionadas. El mayor coste aparece con el uso de terapia anti-TNF. En los casos más frecuentes, la gastroprotección y la terapia para la comorbilidad suponen el 62 por ciento del gasto total anual, seguido por el uso de FARAL, y en menor medida por antinflamatorios y corticoides (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;20(3): 114-121, mar. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aproximación al coste del tratamientofarmacológico en la artritis reumatoide en España</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Caamaño Freire, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mera Varela, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-21359</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30355</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32355</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
