<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164156</identifier>
<setSpec>1577-0354</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hydrogymnastics training program on physical fitness in elderly women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to evaluate the effect of a hydrogymnastics training program on physical fitness in 26 elderly women (experimental group n=16, control group n=10). The physical fitness was determined by the senior fitness test protocol, the hydrogymnastics consisted in aerobic exercise at 50%-60% of maximum heart rate, 5 times a week in a period of 12 weeks. ANOVA 2x2 as statistical test was used, indicating statistically significant interaction (p=0.052) between groups and measurements on test strength endurance in the legs by squatting on chair in 30 s, agility test 2.4 meters was significant interaction (p&amp;#8804;0.01) between groups and measures, testing aerobic capacity test step 2 minutes (p=0.02) and six minutes walk indicated significant interaction between groups and measurements (p=0.50), the results shown that hydrogymnastics in the elderly women participants was effective improving endurance, strength and agility mainly in legs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moncada-Jiménez, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Martínez, PY</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Meza, EI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martin Dantas, EH</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hall López, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Bertruy, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se evaluó un programa de entrenamiento de hidrogimnasia sobre las capacidades físicas en 26 adultas mayores (grupo experimental n=16, grupo control n=10), determinadas mediante el protocolo senior fitness test, la hidrogimnasia fue 5 veces por semana por 12 semanas, con ejercicios aeróbicos del 50%-60% de la FCmáx. Se utilizó ANOVA 2x2, indicando interacción significativa (p=0.052) entre grupos y mediciones en la prueba de resistencia a la fuerza en extremidades inferiores, la prueba de agilidad de 2.4 metros tuvo interacción significativa (p&amp;#8804;0.01) entre grupos y mediciones, las pruebas de capacidad aeróbica step test de 2 minutos (p=0.02) y caminar 6 minutos indicaron interacción significativa entre grupos y mediciones (p=0.50); Se infiere que la hidrogimnasia en las adultas mayores participantes es eficaz en la mejora de las capacidades físicas principalmente aeróbicas, de resistencia a la fuerza y agilidad de miembros inferiores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. int. med. cienc. act. fis. deporte;17(66): 283-298, jun. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164156</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programa de entrenamiento de hidrogimnasia sobre las capacidades físicas de adultas mayores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6324^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
