<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-112754</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Group psychotherapeutic approach in schizophrenia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present study attempts to reflect theoretically on a group experience conducted over several years with schizophrenic patients, in the logical context of combined treatment (psychiatric drugs, psychotherapy, rehabilitation therapies). The creation of a therapeutic group space for the treatment of patients diagnosed with schizophrenia carries with it the implicit notion that these patients meet to articulate and integrate in a shared way their experiences as schizophrenic patients, their experiences resulting from the various kinds of therapeutic attention, and obviously their individual life experiences. In this sense group psychotherapy constitutes the basic element and support of the experiences that these patients encounter during the process of their illness (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silvestre García, Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Ordás Álvarez, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ingelmo Fernández, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo trata de reflexionar teóricamente sobre una experiencia grupal, realizada durante varios años con pacientes esquizofrénicos. Lógicamente, siempre en el contexto de un tratamiento combinado de los pacientes (psicofármacos, psicoterapia, terapias rehabilitadoras). La creación de un espacio terapéutico grupal para el tratamiento de estos pacientes diagnosticados de esquizofrenia lleva implícita la idea de que estos pacientes puedan reunirse para poder estar, articular e integrar las experiencias de forma compartida, tanto las inherentes a la propia patología esquizofrénica, como las procedentes de los diferentes contextos terapéuticos en los que son atendidos y, obviamente, las experiencias vitales de cada cual. En este sentido, la psicoterapia grupal constituiría el elemento básico y el soporte de las experiencias que estos pacientes realizan a lo largo de su proceso de enfermedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;33(118): 289-300, abr.-jun.2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-112754</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propuesta de un enfoque dinámico grupal para el tratamiento combinado de los trastornos esquizofrénicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12946</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
