<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058360</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Frozen section in urological oncology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The indications of Frozen section diagnosis (FS) in surgery due to urologic neoplasia are quite specific, and this        explains the fact that they amount to a mere 7.3% of the FSs performed in general hospitals. This also makes the        precise knowledge of their usefulness necessary, and thus we are submitting the present review.        Generally speaking, FS is not warranted to identify the nature of a tumoral mass, with the following exceptions:        1) Renal masses of a doubtful parenchymal origin, or in the urinary tract: 2) In testicular neoplasias, when        the possibility of a conservative treatment arises; 3) Determination of the presence of a prostate adenocarcinoma        in an organ donor with high serum PSA; but even in these circumstances its need is widely controversial.        Intraoperative determination of surgical margins is particularly useful in: 1) Partial nephrectomies (it may be        limited to inspection after dyeing the margin with Indian ink - bed freezing is very seldom needed); 2) Urethral        margins in women with total cystectomies and orthotopic substitution; 3) In partial penectomies (always studying        the urethral margin and the cavernosal and spongiosal corpora margins).        The study of the nodes is a widely debated issue, and except for those cases in which unexpectedly increased        node size is found, systematic FS is indicated neither of the bladder nor of the prostate. The situation regarding        penis carcinoma is different, as in the groups with intermediate and high risk of node metastasis, even though        there is around 16% - 18% of false negatives FS is recommended, particularly of radioisotope-marked sentinel        nodes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santaularia, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algaba, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villavicencio Mavrich, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arce, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las indicaciones de la biopsia intraoperatoria (BI) en las cirugías por neoplasias urológicas son muy concretas,        esto explica que sólo representen un 7´3% de las BI en los hospitales generales y motiva que se conozca de        una forma precisa su utilidad, siendo éste el motivo la revisión que presentamos.        En términos generales no está justificada la BI para identificar la naturaleza de una masa tumoral, a excepción        de: 1) Las masas renales con dudas sobre el origen parenquimatoso o en vías urinarias. 2) En las neoplasias        testiculares cuando se plantea la posibilidad de un tratamiento conservador. 3) La determinación de la presencia        de un adenocarcinoma de próstata en un donante de órganos con PSA sérico elevado, pero incluso en estas circunstancias        hay amplia discusión sobre su necesidad.        La determinación intraoperatoria de los márgenes quirúrgicos es especialmente útil en: 1) Las nefrectomías        parciales (puede limitarse a la inspección habiendo pintado con tinta china el margen y sólo muy ocasionalmente        se precisa congelación del lecho). 2) El uretral en mujeres con cistectomías totales y sustitución ortotópica. 3)        En las penectomías parciales (estudiando siempre el margen uretral y el de los cuerpos cavernosos y esponjoso).        El estudio de los ganglios es un tema ampliamente debatido y salvo en casos del hallazgo de un inesperado        aumento del tamaño ganglionar no está indicada la BI sistemática ni en vejiga ni en próstata. Otra es la situación        en el carcinoma de pene ya que en los grupos de riesgo intermedio y alto de metástasis ganglionar, aunque haya        de un 16% a un 18% de falsos negativos se recomienda BI, especialmente de los ganglios centinelas marcados con        radioisótopos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;31(9): 945-956, oct. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058360</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La biopsia intraoperatoria en patología oncológica urológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14115^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10605^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10605^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
