<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128193</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bowel ischaemia and cocaine consumption; case study and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Amongst others, cocaine consumption has a detrimental effect in the vascular supply to the mesenteric area causing abdominal ischemic changes. Early recognition of these changes and adequate treatment are essential to avoid serious complications and possible death of the patient from sepsis. Case report: In this case study, the subject is a 40-years-old gentleman presenting with acute abdominal pain due to multiple ischemic changes in both small bowel and sigmoid loops. The patient required emergency surgical intervention consisting of bowel resection and anastomosis. The pathologic analysis of the segment showed transmural necrosis and necrotizing phlebitis caused by the ingestion of drugs or toxic agents. The patient later confirmed the habitual consumption of cocaine. Discussion: The increase in cocaine consumption and other recreational toxins substructed from erythroyilon coca alcaloids amongst young people have generated a large number of admissions to Hospital Accident and Emergency Departments with patients complaining of acute abdominal pain. In many of these cases, surgical intervention is required and in some cases patients will sadly die without a proper diagnosis. Some of the most common effects of cocaine and its compounds includes; hollow viscus perforation, gastro-intestinal bleed, and other vascular problems such as enteritis and ischemic colitis. It appears clear that there is a great need for an advance history taking of these patients and their habit to cocaine and other drugs together with a urine test for drug screening. These together with a suspicion of a non- occlusive ischemic bowel caused by the effects of cocaine in young adults with no cardiac risk factors will guide clinicians and establish, and plan the correct treatment for these categories of patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Alberca, Carmen María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Olías, Coral de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega Ruiz, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balbuena García, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho Ramírez, Alonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Arias, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Najeb, Assad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Vieira, almudena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Durán, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Godoy, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: entre los efectos nocivos del consumo de cocaína se incluyen los producidos a nivel de la vascularización mesentérica, instaurándose en forma de cuadros abdominales isquémicos de potencial gravedad que, si no son diagnosticados y tratados adecuada y precozmente, conllevan complicaciones serias e incluso a la muerte por sepsis. Caso clínico: presentamos el caso de un hombre de 40 años que fue intervenido de urgencias por abdomen agudo secundario a isquemia segmentaria múltiple de asas de delgado y sigmoides. Se realizó resección intestinal y anastomosis. La anatomía patológica del segmento describió hallazgos compatibles con necrosis transmural y flebitis necrotizante producida por el efecto de drogas o tóxicos; el paciente confirmó el consumo previo y habitual de cocaína. Discusión: la difusión entre la población generalmente joven, del consumo de este y de otros tóxicos derivados de los alcaloides de la Erythroyilon coca, ha condicionado un incremento de las consultas en urgencias por dolor abdominal agudo; generalmente, en muchos de estos casos, los pacientes se intervienen quirúrgicamente sin diagnóstico o lo que es más grave, fallecen sin el mismo. Entre los efectos adversos a nivel gastrointestinal de la cocaína y sus derivados, se encuentran la perforación de víscera hueca, la hemorragia digestiva, y los problemas vasculares en forma de enteritis y colitis isquémica. Sería aconsejable un interrogatorio minucioso sobre el consumo de cocaína y otras drogas o la solicitud de su presencia en orina, y la sospecha clínica de una isquemia intestinal no oclusiva originada por cocaína en aquellos adultos jóvenes sin factores de riesgo cardiovascular, sobre todo con vistas a planificar el correcto tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;106(5): 354-358, mayo 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Isquemia intestinal y consumo de cocaína; presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8818^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33538^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24501^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8818^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3070^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8818^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32031^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
