<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76270</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Decentralizing review sessions for patients who have undergone an oral anticoagulant treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Therapeutic use of oral anticoagulants began some fifty years ago. In the past decade, we have witnessed a large increase in the number of people who undergo oral anticoagulant treatment. A correct applied control on these patients, whether that control be carried out in a hospital setting or in a primary health care center, has been demonstrated to be effective in preventing serious complications; this fact taken into account with the improved life quality gained by avoiding displacements and inconveniences makes it obvious to conclude that decentralization benefits all concerned. There are various models available to use to manage oral anticoagulant treatment. In this analysis, the authors deal with the management carried out from a primary health care center, which contacts patients after their dosis has been adjusted and validated by a hematologist at the Torrecárdenas Hospital Complex. As their hypothesis, the authors of this study plan to demonstrate the possibility of decentralizing the reviews of patients undergoing oral anticoagulant treatment, thereby avoiding trips in order to control and adjust their treatment. This is a non-random clinical study whose study group has been chosen by means of a non-probability criteria. This study lasted 12 months. The subjects were chosen from patients undergoing oral anticoagulant treatment registered in the hematology service&#146;s data base at the Torrecárdenas Hospital Complex in Almeria. Applied protocol for being included in this study was decentralization of coagulation. The study sample included 38,097 patients. This study included commentaries by the patients receiving this treatment as a fundamental element to prove its effectiveness(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cañadas Núñez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tobías Manzano, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortuño Moreno, M. Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galdeano Rodríguez, Nicolás</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Rivas, Alicia María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Picón, Josefa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Arrabal, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alarcón Gómez, Inmaculada Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El uso terapéutico de los anticoagulantes orales (ACO) se inició hace más de cincuenta años. En la última década estamos asistiendo a un fuerte incremento de la población sometida a tratamiento con anticoagulación oral (TAO). Un correcto control, independientemente de que sea en el ámbito hospitalario o en atención primaria ha demostrado eficacia en la prevención de complicaciones graves; si a esto unimos la calidad de vida ganada al evitar desplazamientos e incomodidades, es obvio pensar que la descentralización nos beneficia a todos. Existen varios modelos de gestión del TAO. En este estudio se aborda el manejo desde atención primaria, contactando tras el ajuste de dosis y validación por parte del hematólogo del Complejo Hospitalario Torrecárdenas. Como hipótesis se pretende demostrar la posibilidad de descentralizar las revisiones de los pacientes sometidos al mismo, evitando desplazamientos para el control y ajuste de su tratamiento. Se trata de un estudio clínico no aleatorizado con elección del grupo intervención de manera no probabilística a criterio. Duración del mismo: doce meses. Población: pacientes sometidos a anticoagulación oral registrados en la base de datos del servicio de hematología del Complejo Hospitalario Torrecárdenas (Almería). Intervención aplicada: «descentralización del control de coagulación». El espacio muestral es de 38.097 personas. En este trabajo se ha incluido la voz del usuario como parte fundamental de la eficiencia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;32(11): 728-734, nov. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76270</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descentralización de revisiones en pacientes sometidos a Tratamiento con Anticoagulación Oral (TAO)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29491^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23547^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36313</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16763^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
