<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129067</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of a child health prevention and promotion telephone service before its introduction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate a telephone-information service on health issues for children before its implementation. To determine the overall assessment of the service and quality of the information available from the perspective of a potential user population. Methods. Design: Simulation of a telephone call to the telephone service and further evaluation using qualitative techniques. Setting: Primary and special care in the city of Granada. Participants: Parents, who were not health professionals, of children between 0 and 14years old, resident in Andalusia and recruited from both primary care and hospitals throughout the city of Granada. A comprehensive assessment of service and quality of information offered through interviews and focus groups. The number of participants was established on two criteria: evaluation of the whole range of information provided by the telephone service; response saturation. Results. The overall service assessment was positive, emphasising the quick and easy access to information, time saving and confidence building. The information received was described as clear, easily understood and expressed in a respectful tone. To improve the service it has been suggested that the calls be free and that the range of information topics available should be extended. Conclusions. The methodology used is novel, as most telephone services are evaluated after they have been put in place and without the participation of the future users(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gijón Sánchez, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March Cerdá, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Toyos, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto Rodríguez, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Corral, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero Carretero, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar, antes de su puesta en marcha, un servicio telefónico de información sobre temas de salud pediátricos. Conocer la valoración global del servicio y de la calidad de la información que oferta desde la perspectiva de la población potencialmente usuaria. Método. Diseño: simulación de una llamada telefónica al servicio y valoración posterior con técnicas cualitativas. Emplazamiento: atención primaria y especializada de la ciudad de Granada. Participantes: padres y madres de niños/as entre 0 y 14 años y residentes en Andalucía que no fuesen profesionales sanitarios, localizados a través de servicios de atención primaria y hospitalaria de la ciudad de Granada. Se estudió la valoración global del servicio y la calidad de la información ofertada mediante entrevistas y grupos focales. El número de participantes se estableció con base en dos criterios: evaluación de toda la batería de información elaborada para el servicio telefónico y saturación del discurso. Resultados. La valoración global del servicio fue positiva, destacándose el fácil y rápido acceso a la información, el ahorro de tiempo y la tranquilidad que infunde. La información recibida fue calificada de clara, de fácil comprensión y expresada en un tono respetuoso. Para mejorar el servicio se propone que las llamadas sean gratuitas y que se amplíen los temas sobre los que solicitar información. Conclusiones. La metodología usada es novedosa ya que la mayoría de los servicios telefónicos se evalúan una vez puestos en marcha y sin contar con la participación de los públicos potenciales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;26(3): 168-173, mayo-jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129067</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un servicio telefónico de prevención y promoción de salud infantil antes de su puesta en funcionamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2710^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6444^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
