<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040344</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Balloon angioplasty for native coarctation in children: immediate and medium-term results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The use of balloon angioplasty to treat native aortic coarctation in pediatric patients is controversial. Our aims were to report our experience with this technique and to compare retrospectively the immediate and medium-term results obtained during 2 distinct time periods. Subjects and method. 53 patients who underwent balloon angioplasty for native coarctation were divided into 2 groups: (A) those treated between 1985-1988 (n=26); and (B) those treated between 1993-2003 (n=27). Follow-up data were available for all patients. Results. The immediate result was good (i.e., pressure gradient, &lt;20 mmHg) in 18/26 patients in group A (69.2%) and 22/27 (81.5%) in group B. On follow-up, the recoarctation rate was similar in both groups: 33% in group A and 25.6% in group B. Group A patients with recoarctation were referred for surgery, whereas group B patients underwent a second angioplasty (either balloon or stent). At the end of follow-up, angioplasty had been successful in 62% (16/26) of patients in group A vs 85% (23/27) in group B. The incidence of serious complications was lower in group B (4%) than group A (19.2%), as was the incidence of aneurysm: 4% in group B vs 15% in group A. Conclusions. Balloon angioplasty is an effective alternative to surgery for the treatment of native, localized aortic coarctation. Better selection of suitable patients, use of low-profile catheters, and improved patient care can reduce the incidence of complications. Repeat angioplasty (either balloon or stent) in cases of recoarctation has improved results with this technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Ruiz, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro, María C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Felipe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerro, María J del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La angioplastia percutánea de la coartación nativa en la edad pediátrica es una técnica controvertida. El objetivo de este estudio es aportar nuestra experiencia con esta técnica, y comparar retrospectivamente los resultados obtenidos en 2 períodos distintos. Sujetos y método. Los 53 pacientes tratados con angioplastia se dividieron en 2 grupos: a) tratados entre 1985 y 1988 (n = 26), y b) tratados entre 1993 y 2003 (n = 27). Se realizó seguimiento en todos.Resultados. La angioplastia fue inicialmente efectiva (gradiente &lt; 20 mmHg) en 18/26 pacientes del grupo A (69,2%), y en 22/27 (81,5%) en el grupo B. Presentaron recoartación el 33% del grupo A y el 25,6% del grupo B. Los pacientes recoartados del grupo A fueron derivados a cirugía, mientras que en 5 pacientes del grupo B se realizó una segunda angioplastia. Al final del seguimiento, se había conseguido una angioplastia efectiva en el 62% (16/26) en el grupo A frente al 85% (23/27) en el grupo B. La incidencia de complicaciones graves fue menor en el grupo B (4%) que en el A (19,2%), así como la de aneurismas (grupo B: 4%; grupo A: 15%). Conclusiones. La angioplastia percutánea es una alternativa eficaz en el tratamiento de la coartación nativa, circunscrita. La mejor selección de los casos, la utilización de balones de menor perfil y la optimización de los cuidados generales puede disminuir la incidencia de complicaciones. La aplicación de una segunda angioplastia (simple o con stent) en los casos de recoartación ha mejorado los resultados de esta técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;58(9): 1054-1061, sept. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040344</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Angioplastia con balón de la coartación nativa en la edad pediátrica: resultado inicial y a medio plazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30956^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1022^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
