<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-71819</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Besides reducing blood pressure, it is important to think about the blood pressure variability that hypertensive patients may present. Indeed, studies suggest that target organ damage is greater in hypertensive people with high blood pressure variability. The purpose of the present study was to determine the blood pressure variability in patients who had not been treated with antihypertensive medication, as well as its relationship with the glomerular filtration. Patients and method: We included 702 patients with clinical indication for 24h ambulatory blood pressure monitoring. Results: 43.6% of patients had high variability of the blood pressure. These patients had greater levels of 24-h systolic blood pressure, diurnal and night blood pressure and a lower glomerular filtration. The main factors associated with high blood pressure variability were age, years from diagnosis of arterial hypertension, systolic blood pressure and a glomerular filtration smaller than 60ml/min. Conclusions: A high variability of blood pressure is frequent among hypertensive patients. Since it is not possible to perform ambulatory blood pressure measurement in all them, we should mainly suspect it in old patients and in those with reduced glomerular filtration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Alonso, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mediavilla García, Juan Dieg</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Expósito Ruiz, Manuela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arroyo Nieto, Ascensión</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Torres, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: en pacientes hipertensos, además de reducir la presión arterial, debemos plantearnos la variabilidad de presión arterial que ellos presentan, dado que algunos estudios demuestran lesión de órgano diana en pacientes con variabilidad alta. El propósito de este estudio fue determinar la variabilidad de la presión arterial en pacientes hipertensos tratados y no tratados y su relación con el filtrado glomerular. Pacientes y método: se incluyó en el estudio a 702 pacientes con indicación clínica para monitorización ambulatoria de la presión arterial (MAPA) de 24h. Resultados: el 43,6% presentó variabilidad alta. Estos pacientes tenían mayores valores de presión arterial sistólica de 24h, diurna y nocturna, y menor filtrado glomerular. Los factores principales asociados con variabilidad alta fueron la edad, los años de evolución de la hipertensión, la presión arterial sistólica clínica y, sobre todo, un filtrado glomerular&lt;60ml/min. Conclusiones: la variabilidad elevada es frecuente entre hipertensos. Dado que no es posible realizar MAPA a todos ellos, sí debemos sospecharla en pacientes de más edad, con más años de evolución de la hipertensión y con filtrado glomerular reducido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);132(5): 180-183, feb. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-71819</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d32339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
