<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78960</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are the questionnaires currently used in the treatment of the smoking habit useful?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Evaluate the utility of the questionnaires in the evaluationof the profile of the patient who smokesPatients and methods: Analytic study in smokers who request treatmentin a smoking cessation unit during the period of 2004/2006. Studyvariables: gender, age, daily cigarette consumption, psychodrug consumption,background of anxiety/depression, previous attempts to quite,compliance, physical dependence (Fagerström test), psychological dependence(Glover-Nilsson test), motivation grade (Richmond test) and anxietytrait (STAI-R questionnaire). Abstinence is considered to be successfulwhen, according to the intention to treat criterion, it is continuedand validated with cooximetry (expired carbon monoxide 10 ppm). Theresults are expressed as proportions and absolute frequencies or qualitativevariables and as means ± standard deviation for quantitative variables.Results:Atotal of 683 smokers who requested treatment in the SmokingCessation Unit were analyzed. Of these, 601 initiated group therapyand only a clinical history was obtained in 82. The smokers whodid not initiate treatment were less motivated regarding those who did.The test scores were: Fagerström test: 6.13 ± 2.27; Richmond test: 7.71± 1.58, and Glover-Nilsson test 21.62 ± 6.50. The patients with previousattempts were more motivated and had less physical dependence. In thesame way, a lower score on the Fagerström test was related with goodcompliance and with being abstinent at one month and 3 months (p 0.05).Conclusions: The utility of the Fagerström test, both in the diagnosisand in prognostic value, is confirmed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marqueta Baile, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beamonte San Agustín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gargallo Valero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nerín de la Puerta, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Muro Franco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Valorar la utilidad de los cuestionarios en la evaluacióndel perfil del paciente fumador.Pacientes y métodos: Estudio analítico en fumadores que solicitantratamiento en una unidad de tabaquismo a lo largo del período2004/2006. Variables de estudio: sexo, edad, consumo de cigarrillos diarios,consumo de psicofármacos, antecedentes de ansiedad/depresión,intentos previos de cesación, cumplimentación, dependencia física (testde Fagerström), dependencia psicológica (test de Glover-Nilsson), gradode motivación (test de Richmond) y ansiedad rasgo (cuestionarioSTAI-R). Se consideró éxito a la abstinencia, según el criterio de intenciónde tratar, continuada y validada con cooximetría (monóxido decarbono espirado &amp;#8804; 10 ppm). Los resultados se expresan como proporcionesy frecuencias absolutas para las variables cualitativas, y comomedias ± desviación estándar para las variables cuantitativas.Resultados: Se han analizado 683 fumadores que solicitaron tratamientoen la Unidad de Tabaquismo, 601 iniciaron terapia grupal y 82únicamente realizaron la historia clínica; los fumadores que no iniciarontratamiento estaban menos motivados con respecto a los que sí lohicieron. Las puntuaciones de los test fueron: test de Fagerström: 6,13± 2,27; test de Richmond: 7,71 ± 1,58, y test de Glover-Nilsson 21,62 ±6,50. Los pacientes con intentos previos estaban más motivados y teníanmenos dependencia física. Del mismo modo una puntuación menoren el test de Fagerström se relacionó con buena cumplimentacióny con estar abstinente al mes y 3 meses (p &amp;#8804; 0,05).Conclusiones: Se confirma la utilidad del test de Fagerström, tantoen el diagnóstico como en su valor pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;10(2): 56-62, abr.-jun. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Son útiles los cuestionarios utilizados actualmente en el tratamiento del tabaquismo?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12036^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
