<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166330</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Temporary cardiac pacing. Pacing after cardiac surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Temporary transvenous cardiac pacing is the treatment of choice when continuous temporary cardiac pacing is required, for example, as a bridge until a bradyarrhythmia has resolved or until permanent pacemaker implantation. Generally, right ventricular pacing is sufficient except under very special hemodynamic conditions, such as cardiogenic shock due to right ventricular myocardial infarction or obstructive hypertrophic cardiomyopathy with atrioventricular block. Transcutaneous cardiac pacing is the most appropriate technique for use in emergencies that require the support of cardiac pacing and for the majority of prophylactic applications, thereby avoiding, in these latter cases, the potential complications associated with the intravenous approach. In addition to contributing to the treatment of the conduction abnormalities that frequently occur after cardiac surgery, temporary post-surgery cardiac pacing also plays an important role in helping to increase heart rate-dependent cardiac output and in reducing or preventing postoperative atrial fibrillation. In patients who have left ventricular dysfunction and a wide QRS complex before surgery, it is advantageous to implant temporary leads in the left ventricle so that biventricular pacing can be implemented if necessary. There is some controversy about when is the most appropriate time for deciding to implant a permanent pacemaker, and this decision has to be taken individually for each patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Coma Samartín, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carbonell de Blas, Raúl</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño Ruiz, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estimulación cardiaca temporal transvenosa es la modalidad de elección cuando se precisa estimulación cardiaca temporal continua, ya como puente a la resolución de la bradiarritmia o al implante del marcapasos definitivo. Generalmente es suficiente estimular el ventrículo derecho, salvo en situaciones hemodinámicas muy especiales como son el shock en el infarto de ventrículo derecho o la miocardiopatía hipertrófica obstructiva con bloqueo auriculoventricular. La estimulación cardiaca transcutánea es la más adecuada para solventar las situaciones de emergencia que requieren un soporte de estimulación cardiaca y en la mayoría de las profilácticas, con lo que en estas últimas se evita las potenciales complicaciones de la endovenosa. La estimulación epicárdica temporal tras la cirugía cardiaca, además de la contribución al tratamiento de las frecuentes alteraciones posquirúrgicas de la conducción, tiene un importante papel en la contribución al gasto cardiaco dependiente de la frecuencia y en la reducción o prevención de la fibrilación auricular postoperatoria. En los pacientes con disfunción ventricular izquierda y complejo QRS ancho preoperatorio, es deseable dejar implantados unos electrodos temporales en el ventrículo izquierdo, para poder realizar estimulación biventricular si fuese necesario. La decisión del momento más adecuado para la implantación de un marcapasos definitivo tras cirugía cardiaca es materia de controversia y debería ser individualizado para cada paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);7(supl.G): 54g-68g, 2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166330</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estimulación cardiaca temporal. Estimulación tras cirugía cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d53678^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14290^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2348^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6480^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1289^s22022</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6480^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
