<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141184</identifier>
<setSpec>2173-9242</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Thrust technique C3 in neck pain: modifications of the pressure pain threshold</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Chronic cervical pain is located posterior to the neck (from the neck to the interscapular zone) for more than 12 weeks, with a higher incidence in the female sex. This chronic pain can be associated with periods of invalidating exacerbation, which can occur with variable frequency and duration. There is a wide variety of treatments applicable in patients with chronic cervicalgia, although there is little evidence regarding their efficacy. Objective: To determine the effect of manipulation of C3 on the Pressure Pain Threshold (PPT) in the trigger points (TP) of the sternocleidomastoid muscles (SCM) and in the spinous process of C3 in patients with chronic mechanical cervicalgia. Material and methods: We performed a randomized, double-blind clinical trial with pre and post intervention measurements in the control and experimental groups. The analyzed sample size was 60 patients (n=60). A digital dynamometer was used to measure the pressure pain threshold (PPT) of PG1 of the SCM muscles and in the spinous process of C3. Results: No significant changes were found between the control and experimental groups in relation to the pressure pain threshold in the PG of the SCM muscles (p=0.769 right SCM; p=0.082 left SCM). There were also no statistically significant differences in UDP in the spinous process of C3 (p=0.777). Conclusions: The manipulation of C3 does not cause statistically significant changes in the PPT in the SCM muscles or in the spinous process of C3. In both groups, there is an increase in the pain threshold in the post-intervention measurement, which is greater in the experimental group at the trigger point of the left SCM muscle and in the spinous process of C3 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz Gómez, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliva Pascual-Vaca, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caraballo Camacho, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palanco Parreño, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez Vera, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El dolor cervical crónico se localiza a nivel posterior del cuello (desde la nuca hasta la zona interescapular) durante más de 12 semanas, teniendo mayor incidencia en el sexo femenino. Este dolor crónico puede asociarse a periodos de reagudización invalidante, que pueden ocurrir con frecuencia y duración variables. Existe una amplia variedad de tratamientos aplicables en pacientes con cervicalgia crónica, aunque existe escasa evidencia sobre la eficacia de los mismos. Objetivos: Determinar el efecto de la manipulación de C3 sobre el umbral de Dolor a la Presión (UDP) en los puntos gatillos (PG) de los músculos esternocleidomastoideos (ECOM) y en la apófisis espinosa de C3 en pacientes con cervicalgia mecánica crónica. Material y métodos: Se realizó un ensayo clínico aleatorizado, doble ciego con mediciones pre y post intervención en el grupo control y experimental. El tamaño muestral analizado fue de sesenta pacientes (n=60). Se utilizó un dinamómeto digital para medir el umbral de dolor a la presión (UDP) del PG1 de los músculos ECOM y en la apófisis espinosa de C3. Resultados: No se encontraron cambios significativos entre los grupos control y experimental en relación al umbral del dolor a la presión en los PG de los músculos ECOM (p=0,769 ECOM derecho; p=0,082 ECOM izquierdo). Tampoco hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el UDP en la apófisis espinosa de C3 (p=0,777). Conclusiones: La manipulación de C3 no provoca cambios estadísticamente significativos en el UDP en los músculos ECOM ni en la apófisis espinosa de C3. En ambos grupos se aprecia un incremento del umbral de dolor en la medición posterior a la intervención, que es mayor en el grupo experimental en el punto gatillo del músculo ECOM izquierdo y en la apófisis espinosa de C3 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. J. Ost. Clin. Rel. Res;9(2): 35-41, mayo-ago. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141184</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Técnica de thrust C3 en cervicalgias: modificaciones del umbral del dolor a la presión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33863^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29646</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54522^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32948^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36281^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36281^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2614^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36281^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52443^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36281^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36281^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30624^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36281^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
