<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050361</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Acute effects of high intensity strength training in female players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">the acute responses to training involve how the body responds to one bout of exercise, the chronic adapatations to training mark how the body responds over time to the stress of repeated exercise bouts. The purpose of this investigation was to examine acute effects of high intensity strength training. The sessions of strength training (independent variable) involved 4 sets/3 repetitions with a range of rest 3´- 5´between exercise, 2 days per week. 12 women (19-21 yrs) participated in the study, sport sciences students and athletes of sports velocity-strength, these women competed in middle or lower levels of competition. The dependent variables measured were: 1 maximum repetition (1RM) (kg); force production (Nw) and velocity (m/s) in two exercises: bench press and semi-squat. We realized 3 testing sessions (pretest, postest1, postest2). The high intensity strength training caused significantly improve in all variables tested (p&lt;0.05). Exist a significant improves inlower extremity in comparison with upper extremity (p&lt;0.05). We reported before and after 3 maximum voluntary contractions of the leg extensors an increase 23.23% inpostest 1 and 27.43% inpostest 2 and an increase 2,16% inpostest 1 and 9.09% inpostest 2 of the arm extensors due to increase in neuromuscular activation, but we suggested it has validity with middle and low trained athletes in speed-strength. So, this study have suggested that inclusion of a set squats with 3 RM load in a warm-up might result in improve performance in activities dominated by the power output. It was concluded that acute effects of high intensity strength training is advantageous for increasing power output in athletes of middle or lower level of competition</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Ravé, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Coll, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las respuestas agudas al ejercicio determinan como el organismo responde a una sesión de entrenamiento, mientras que cuando se repite en el tiempo se produce adaptación crónica. El objetivo de este estudio es comprobar las adaptaciones agudas al entrenamiento de fuerza utilizando cargas concentradas de alta intensidad (variable independiente), dos días a la semana durante 2 semanas con una semana de descanso entre microciclos de trabajo. 12 mujeres, estudiantes de ciencias de la actividad física y el deporte (19-21 años) que practican deportes de tipo combinado de fuerza-velocidad a niveles medios y bajos de competición, realizaron los siguientes ejercicios al 90-100% de IRM (4 series, 3 repeticiones con un descanso entre ellas de 3´- 5´). Se realizaron 3 sesiones de evaluación (pretest, postest 1 y postest 2). Las variables dependientes medidas fueron: 1 repetición máxima (IRM) expresada en KG; producción de fuerza (Nw) y velocidad (m/s). Se realizaron 3 sesiones de evaluación (pretest, postest 1 y postest 2). Los resultados muestran como el entrenamiento de fuerza de cargas concentradas de alta intensidad provoca mejoras significativas entre las variables medidas tanto en press de banca como en semisquat (p0.05). Después de las sesiones, se produjo un incremento del miembro inferior del 23,23% en postest 1 y de un 27,43% en postest 2, así como un incremento del 2,16% y del 9,09% de los extensores de brazo respectivamente. Por lo tanto concluimos que la utilización de un protocolo de cargas concentradas de alta intensidad, dos días a la semana durante 2 semanas con una semana de descanso entre microciclos de trabajo provoca mejoras significativas en la producción de fuerza máxima en deportistas femeninas de niveles medios y bajos de competición</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;23(114): 283-290, jul.-ago. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050361</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Respuestas agudas al entrenamietno de fuerza máxima en deportistas femeninas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d228^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5178^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34326</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
