<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75480</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stroke rehabilitation: Care model. Recommendations of the Spanish Society of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, 2009</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectivesThe Spanish Society of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation has elaborated a document of good clinical practice recommendations on the care model in stroke rehabilitation based on the clinical experience and consensus of the authors and reference clinical practice guides.Search strategyThe search was focused on clinical practice guides and articles related with the care model in stroke rehabilitation in the MEDLINE, EMBASE and COCHRANE DATABASES from January 2004 to January 2009.Selection of studiesRandomized clinical trials, meta-analyses, systematic reviews and review articles on the care model in stroke rehabilitation were selected.Synthesis of resultsThe stroke rehabilitation program is a complex procedure that requires a multidisciplinary approach. Its key elements are early initiation, adequate intensity, periodic evaluation and active participation of the patients and caregivers.ConclusionsRehabilitation care under the responsibility of a multidisciplinary team, coordinated by a medical specialist in rehabilitation with adequate levels of organization and experience of the professionals should be assured on all health and socio-health care, hospital or community levels(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iñigo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bori, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernabeu, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flórez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viosca, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Forastero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lizarraga, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López de Munaín, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Déniz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gentil, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juan, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Junyent, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duarte, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soler, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miguéns, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Montes, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Máñez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrión, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomino, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivosLa Sociedad Española de Medicina Física y Rehabilitación elabora un documento de recomendaciones de buena práctica clínica sobre el modelo asistencial en la rehabilitación (RHB) del ictus basadas en la experiencia clínica y el consenso de los autores y las guías de práctica clínica de referencia.Estrategia de búsquedaLa búsqueda se centra en guías de práctica clínica y artículos relevantes sobre el modelo asistencial en la RHB del ictus en las bases de datos MEDLINE, Embase y Cochrane Databases desde enero de 2004 hasta enero de 2009.Selección de estudiosSe seleccionan ensayos clínicos aleatorizados, metaanálisis, revisiones sistemáticas y artículos de revisión sobre el modelo asistencial en la RHB del ictus.Síntesis de resultadosEl programa rehabilitador del ictus es un proceso complejo que requiere un abordaje multidisciplinario, siendo elementos claves el inicio precoz, la intensidad adecuada, la evaluación periódica y la participación activa de pacientes y cuidadores.ConclusionesEn todos los niveles de atención sanitaria y sociosanitaria, hospitalaria o comunitaria se debe asegurar la atención de RHB a cargo de un equipo multidisciplinario, coordinada por un médico especialista en RHB con adecuados niveles de organización y experiencia de los profesionales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);44(1): 60-68, ene.-mar.2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75480</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Rehabilitación del ictus: modelo asistencial. Recomendaciones de la Sociedad Española de Rehabilitación y Medicina Física, 2009</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12467^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11243^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11243^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13339^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
