<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043463</identifier>
<setSpec>0556-6177</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Myocardial regeneration: future at reach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The last few years have witnessed a growing interest in regenerative therapy of the failing heart by cell transplantation. Initial studies with skeletal myoblasts were conducted more than 10 years ago. However, the potential of bone marrow derived cells has more recently led to a flurry of experimental studies generating overall positive but occasionally conflicting results. The ethics of initiating clinical trials with stem cells in patients with heart failure has been questioned. Although laboratory research attempts to overcome a number of questions surrounding the usefulness and safety of cell therapy, the accumulated body of evidence warrants implementation of clinical trials. The earliest of these have now documented the feasibility of cell therapy. It is now appropriate to conduct safety and efficacy studies which, if carefully done, should allow assessment of the extent to which this concept of regenerative therapy can be made a clinical reality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barba, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herreros, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegría, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abizanda, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gavira, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Caro, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prósper, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Arnau, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Ilzarbe, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En los últimos años hemos asistido a un interés creciente por eltratamiento de la insuficiencia cardíaca mediante el trasplante decélulas madre. Mientras que los estudios con células madre de músculo(mioblastos) se iniciaron hace mas de 10 años, la posibilidadde que las células madre de la médula ósea tengan un enorme potencialde diferenciación y proliferación han estimulado la investigacióncon otros tipos de células madre. Estos estudios experimentales handemostrado, en no pocas ocasiones, resultados contradictorios loque ha llevado a posturas enfrentadas en cuanto a la ética de iniciarestudios clínicos. Creemos que es adecuado tratar de ofrecer unavisión crítica sobre la utilización de las células madre en la insuficienciacardíaca. Quizá la pregunta mas difícil de contestar en estemomento es, si la realización de ensayos clínicos esta justificado ono a la luz de los conocimientos actuales o si por el contrario debemosadquirir un conocimiento mucho más preciso de la posibleeficacia de este tipo de tratamiento y de los mecanismos que justificandicha eficacia, antes de siquiera iniciar los estudios en humanos.En nuestra opinión existen suficientes evidencias que justifican eldesarrollo de ensayos clínicos a pesar de que, sin duda, existenmuchos interrogantes que debemos resolver mediante estudios experimentalesen animales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Med Univ Navarra;49(3): 62-68, jul.-sept. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043463</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regeneración miocárdica: el futuro al alcance de la mano</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9398^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6473^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36525^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12460</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
