<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134444</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictors of adherence to the Mediterranean diet from the first to the second trimester of pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Although changes in eating patterns may occur during gestation, predictors of these changes have not been explored. This study aimed to identify predictors of adherence to the Mediterranean diet (MD) from the first to second trimester of pregnancy. Methods: A prospective study was conducted with 102pregnant women aged 18-40, from the city of Porto, Portugal. Socio-demographic and lifestyle characteristics were assessed through a questionnaire. Food consumption was assessed with a three-day food diary completed during the first and second trimesters. Participants were categorized according to their change in adherence to the MD into the negative change group (i.e., women who had low adherence in each trimester or had high adherence in the first trimester and then low adherence in the second) and the positive change group (i.e., women who had high adherence in both trimesters or had low adherence in the first trimester and then high adherence in the second). Conditional stepwise logistic regression models were performed to assess the potential predictors of negative MD change. Results: Among the 102 women, 39.2% had negative change from the first to the second trimester. The logistic model&#146;s results show that being married (OR=0.26,95%CI: 0.10, 0.76) and having a higher intake of vegetables in the first trimester (OR=0.17, 95%CI: 0.10, 0.43) were associated with lower odds of having a negative change in adherence to the MD from the first to second trimester. Conclusion: Marital status and vegetable consumption seem to be associated with a lower occurrence of negative change in adherence to the MD from early to middle pregnancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santos, Paula Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mota, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreir, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abreu, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montenegro, Nuno</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreira, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Rute</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Aunque los cambios en los patrones pueden ocurrir durante la gestación, predictores de estos cambios no han sido exploradas. Este estudio pretende identificar predictores de la adhesión a la dieta mediterránea (DM) desde el primer al segundo trimestre del embarazo. Metodología: Se realizó un estudio prospectivo con 102 embarazadas de edad 18-40, de la ciudad de Oporto, Portugal. Se evaluaron las características socio-demográficas y de estilo de vida a través de un cuestionario. Consumo de alimentos se evaluó con un diario de alimentos de tres días concluido durante los primeras y segundo trimestres. Los participantes fueron categorizados según su cambio en la adhesión a la DM en el cambio negativo (es decir, las mujeres que tenían poca adhesión en cada trimestre o tenido alta adhesión en el primer trimestre y luego baja adhesión en el segundo) y el grupo de cambio positivo (es decir, las mujeres que tenían alta adhesión en ambos trimestres o tenía baja adhesión en el primer trimestre y luego elevada adhesión en el segundo). Modelos de regresión logística stepwise condicional se realizaron para evaluar los posibles predictores de la variación negativa de DM. Resultados: Entre las 102 mujeres, 39,2% tenían cambio negativo del primer al segundo trimestre. Los resultados model´s logística muestran que estar casada (OR = 0,26, IC95%: 0,10, 0,76) y tener una mayor ingesta de verduras en el primer trimestre (OR = 0,17, IC95%: 0,10, 0,43) se asociaron con menor probabilidad de tener un cambio negativo en la adhesión a la DM del primer al segundo trimestre. Conclusiones: Estado civil y el consumo de vegetal parecen estar asociado con una menor ocurrencia de cambio negativo en la adhesión a la MD desde temprano a medio embarazo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(3): 1403-1412, mar. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134444</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los predictores de la la dieta mediterránea desde el primero hasta el segundo trimestre del embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11704</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30663</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37653^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52506</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29499</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11707</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
