<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-63033</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Translational research is a new discipline which incorporates aspects from both basic science and clinical investigation. As a result it requires training and resources which are not always available in laboratories or clinical departments. For this reason institutions which combine both clinical and basic research, such as universities, basic science centre sand major hospitals, are the ideal institutions to perform this type of research. Over the past 40 years, Hospital Clinic in Barcelona, have been significant with the most marked changes in the following areas; the creation of clinical units which replaced the former cathedrae, the availability of grants for post residents, sabbaticals, the Foundation Clinic for Biomedical Investigation and finally the inauguration of IDIBAPS, Institut d'investigacions Biomediques August Pi y Sunyer. During more recent years the hospital has undergone major reorganization dividing it into Institutes and Centres. The scientific production of the past few years has continued to grow, not just in the number of articles published but also the number of articles published in high ranking Journals. Results show that IDIBAPS equals some of the best research and investigational institutions in the western world (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodés, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación trasnacional es una nueva disciplina que incorpora aspectos de ciencia básica e investigación clínica y, por tanto, requiere entrenamiento y recursos que no se suelen encontraren los laboratorios o en departamentos clínicos. Es por ello que los institutos donde se combinan ambos tipos de investigación como universidades, centros de investigación básica y hospitales de alto nivel asistencial, son las instituciones ideales para realizar este tipo de investigación. En el Hospital Clínica de Barcelona se ha producido un cambio en el transcurso de los últimos 40 años. Este cambio ha venido marcado por varios hechos, a destacar la creación de los servicios clínicos que substituyeron a las antiguas cátedras, la creación de los servicios de medicina, las becas post-residencia, los años sabáticos, la Fundación Clínica para la Investigación Biomédica y finalmente la puesteen marcha del Institut d'Investigacions Biomèdiques August Pi i Sunyer (IDIBAPS). En los últimos años  es importante destacar también la reorganización del hospital en institutos y centros. La producción científica en estos últimos años se ha mantenido en alza, tanto en número de publicaciones como del impacto de las revistas en las que se publica. El IDIBAPS ha alcanzado unos resultados similares a los obtenidos por los mejores institutos de investigación del mundo occidental (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);10(4): 202-208, dic. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-63033</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17571^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
