<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048383</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of diet and ppar alfa2 and Beta2 - adrenergic receptor genes on energy metabolism and body composition in obese women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the effect of diet and PPAR&amp;#947;2 and b2-adrenergic receptor genes on energy metabolism and body composition in obese women. Material and methods: 60 obese women, aged 34.59 ± 7.56 years were studied at the Department of Physiology and Nutrition at Navarra University. Anthropometric, biochemical,metabolic and molecular evaluations were carried out, and the women were submitted to short-term and longterm hypocaloric diets, varying the macronutrients. The groups were formed according to gene polymorphism, as follows: Pro12Pro(PPAR&amp;#947;2)/Gln27Gln (b2-adrenergic receptor genes) - A, Pro12Pro (PPAR&amp;#947;2)/Gln27Glu (b2- adrenergic receptor genes) - B, Pro12Pro (PPAR&amp;#947;2)/Glu27Glu (b2-adrenergic receptor genes)-C and Pro1Ala (PPAR&amp;#947;2)/Gln27Glu (b2-adrenergic receptor genes) - D. Results: In group A, fat oxidation was correlated positively with body mass index (BMI), but an increase in fat and saturated fatty acids (SFA) in the diet did not reflect in increased oxidation. In group B, total fat and SFA intake did not lead to fat oxidation increase. In group C, fat and complex carbohydrates (CHO) resulted in lower fat oxidation, and long-term increase of monounsaturated fatty acid (MUFA) intake resulted in increase of CHO oxidation and smaller weight loss. In group D, greater energy expenditure was obtained after diet high in SFA in a short-term, and fat basal and postprandial oxidation correlated positively with its intake. Hypocaloric diet high in polyunsaturated fatty acid (PUFA) resulted inincrease of fat oxidation. Conclusions: Polymorphism in PPAR&amp;#947;2 gene resulted in increased fat oxidation, regardless of genotype of b2- adrenergic receptor gene. It is recommended control of the total intake of fats and SFA in Pro12Pro/Gln27Gln and Pro12Pro/Gln27Glu, and complex CHO and MUFA in Pro12Pro/Glu27Glu. In Pro12Ala/Gln27Glu, AGPI intake can result in greater body weight loss (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, JAM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cecon, PR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bressan, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosado, EL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martins, MF</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluación del efecto de la dieta y de los genes PPAR&amp;#947;2 y b2-adrenérgico en el metabolismo energético y la composición corporal de mujeres obesas. Material y métodos: Fueron seleccionadas 60 mujeres obesas de 34,59 ± 7,56 años en el Departamento de Fisiología y Nutrición de la Universidad de Navarra. Se realizó evaluaciones antropométricas, bioquímicas, metabólicas y moleculares, sobre dietas en corto y largo plazo (hipocalórica), variando los macronutrientes. Los grupos fueron formados según el polimorfismo de los genes, siendo Pro12Pro(PPAR&amp;#947;2)/Gln27Gln(b2-adrenérgico) - A, Pro12Pro(PPAR&amp;#947;2)/Gln27Glu(b2-adrenérgico) - B, Pro12Pro(PPAR&amp;#947;2)/Glu27Glu(b2-adrenérgico) - C y Pro12Ala(PPAR&amp;#947;2)/Gln27Glu(b2-adrenérgico) - D. Resultados: En el grupo A, la oxidación de grasas se correlacionó positivamente con el índice de masa corporal (IMC), pero el aumento en la ingesta de grasas y ácidos grasos saturados (AGS) no reflejó en aumento de su oxidación. En el grupo B, la ingesta de lípidos totales y AGS no resultó en aumento de la oxidación de lípidos. En el grupo C, la ingesta de lípidos y hidratos de carbono (HC) complejos resultaron en menor oxidación de grasas, y el aumento en los ácidos grasos monoinsaturados (AGMI) en largo prazo resultó en aumento de la oxidación de HC y menor pérdida de peso. El grupo D, obtuvo mayor utilización energética trás la dieta rica en AGS en corto prazo, y la oxidación basal y postprandial de grasas correlacionó positivamente con su ingesta. La Nutridieta hipocalórica rica en ácidos grasos polinsaturados (AGPI) resultó en aumento de la oxidación de grasas.  Conclusiones: Se supone que el polimorfismo en el gen PPAR&amp;#947;2 reflejó en aumento de la oxidación de grasas,independiente del genotipo del gen b2-adrenérgico. Recomiéndase el control de la ingesta de grasas totales y AGS en Pro12Pro/Gln27Gln y Pro12Pro/Gln27Glu, y de HC complejos y AGMI en Pro12Pro/Glu27Glu. En Pro12Ala/Gln27Glu la ingesta de AGPI puede resultar en mayor pérdida de peso corporal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(3): 317-331, mayo-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048383</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efecto de la dieta y de los genes PPAR alfa2 y beta2 - adrenérgico en el metabolismo energético y en la composición corporal de mujeres obesas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
