<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056826</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of endoscopic ultrasonography in the localization of pancreatic neuroendocrine tumours: report of 2 benign insulinomas</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Insulinomas are neuroendocrine tumors that usually present as fasting hypoglycemia. Diagnosis is based on clinical suspicion followed by confirmation of endogenous hyperinsulinism and tumoral localization. Nevertheless, localization cannot always be achieved with routine imaging techniques, in which case invasive imaging techniques are required. We present 2 cases of insulinomas that were not identified by conventional imaging techniques but were successfully identified by endoscopic ultrasonography (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catalá, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Hervás, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedro, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Real, José T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente, Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ascaso, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmena, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabater, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argüello, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los insulinomas son tumores neuroendocrinos que se manifiestan por episodios de hipoglucemia de ayuno. El diagnóstico se basa en la sospecha clínica, que debe ir seguida de la demostración de hiperinsulinismo y la localización tumoral. Sin embargo, la localización no siempre es posible con las técnicas de imagen habituales, por lo que se debe recurrir a otras más complejas. Presentamos 2 casos de insulinomas cuya localización tumoral no fue posible con técnicas de imagen convencionales, pero sí con ultrasonografía endoscópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(6): 335-339, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de la ultrasonografía endoscópica para el diagnóstico de localización de tumores neuroendocrinos pancreáticos: presentación de 2 insulinomas benignos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7181^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33097^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7510^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31255^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
