<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037874</identifier>
<setSpec>0303-8874</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laryngeal tuberculosis masquerading as carcinoma. Report of one case and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the introduction of antituberculous medications, the incidence of laryngeal tuberculosis (LTB) has decreased. However, it is a fact the increasing number of cases of pulmonary or extrapulmonary TB mainly caused by the Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome. We report the clinical case of a 72 years old male with dysphonia secondary to LTB which masqueraded a carcinoma. It's certain diagnosis was the histopathologic exam of the biopsy obtained by microsurgery. There was a residual TB in lung after a complete study of Internal Medicine Department</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Palomino, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trinidad Ruiz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pardo Romero, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pimentel Leo, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blasco Huelva, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino Rivero, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde la introducción de los fármacos tuverculostáticos, la incidencia de tuberculosis (TBC) laríngea ha disminuido. Sin embargo, es un hecho el aumento del número de casos de TBC pulmonar o extrapulmonar debidos principalmente al SIDA. Presentamos el caso clínico de un varón de 72 años con disfonía debida a TBC laríngea que simulaba un carcinoma y cuyo diangóstico de confirmación fue el examen histopatológico de la biopsia obtenida tras microcirugía. A nivel pulmonar existía una TBC residual tras estudio completo por parte del Departamento de Medicina Interna</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Otorrinolaringol Ibero Am;32(1): 47-53, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tuberculosis laríngea simulando carcinoma. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27877^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27877^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8009^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27877^s22058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28150^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
