<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106518</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparison of dynamic contour tonometry, Goldmann and pneumotonometer in ocular hypertension patients and their relationship to pachymetry and ocular pulse amplitude</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: To determine the relationship between dynamic contour tonometry (DCT), Goldmann applanation tonometry (GAT) and pneumotonometry (PNT) in ocular hypertension patients (OHT) and their relationship to central corneal thickness (CCT) and ocular pulse amplitude (OPA). Methods: Sixty patients (101 eyes) with intraocular pressure (IOP) greater than or equal 21mmHg using GAT and normal appearing optic nerve heads and normal visual fields were included. The following tests were performed simultaneously during a single visit: IOP using DCT, GAT and PNT, OPA using DCT and CCT using ultrasound pachymetry. We studied the difference IOP between these 3 tonometers using Wilcoxon non-parametric test and the effect of CCT on IOP and OPA, as well as the relationship between OPA and IOP using Spearman correlation coefficient. Results: The median PNT IOP was 24mmHg (Inter-quartile range [IQR]: 22-26), median GAT IOP was 22mmHg (IQR: 22-24), and median DCT IOP was 28.2mmHg (IQR: 24.1-30.7). PNT and DCT had higher IOP values than GAT (median 2mmHg and 6.2mmHg, respectively). Mean CCT was 594.5 micrometer (SD 30.0). GAT IOP and DCT IOP showed an increase with increased corneal thickness (r: 0.209; P=0.036 and r: 0.195; P=0.051, respectively). PNT IOP did not change with CCT (r: 0.15; P=0.12). The median OPA was 4.8mmHg (IQR: 3.6-6.1), and significantly increased with GAT IOP (r: 0,38; P&lt;0.001) and with CCT (r:0.287; P=0.004). This association was unclear with IOP PNT and IOP DCT (r: 0.067; P=0.50 and r: 0,17, P=0.08, respectively). Conclusions: DCT and PNT IOP values were higher than GAT IOP measurements in ocular hypertension patients. GAT IOP showed a significant increase with increased corneal thickness. Increased OPA seems to correlate with increased CCT and IOP, particularly if GAT is used(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villafruela-Güemes, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Colás-Tomás, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Del Cura, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clariana-Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdivia-Pérez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la relación entre el tonómetro de contorno dinámico (TCD), Goldmann (TG) y neumotonómetro (NT) en pacientes con hipertensión ocular (HTO) y su relación con el grosor central de la córnea (GCC) y amplitud del pulso ocular (APO). Método: Se han incluido 60 pacientes (101 ojos) con presión intraocular (PIO)mayor o igual 21mmHg con TG y sin alteraciones glaucomatosas en disco óptico y campo visual. Se ha medido la PIO con TG, TCD y NT, la APO con el TCD y el GCC con paquímetro de ultrasonido. Se ha estudiado la diferencia de PIO entre los tres tonómetros mediante el test no paramétrico de Wilconxon y la relación de la APO con el GCC y la PIO con el coeficiente de correlación de Spearman. Resultados: La mediana de PIO con NT fue de 24mmHg (RIC: 22-26), con TG de 22mmHg (RIC: 22-24) y con TCD de 28,2mmHg (rango intercunatílico [RIC]:24,1-30,7). En comparación con el TG la PIO fue mayor con el NT y con el TCD, siendo la diferencia de medianas de 2,0 y de 6,2mmHg respectivamente. La media del GCC fue de 594,5 micrometro (DE 30,0), encontrándose una asociación estadísticamente significativa entre esta y la PIO con TG (r:0,209; p=0,036) y de magnitud similar aunque sin ser significativa con el TCD (r:0,195; p=0,051). No se encuentra asociación entre GCC y NT (r: 0,15; p=0,12). La APO fue de 4,8mmHg (RIC: 3,6-6,1), incrementándose significativamente con la PIO tomada por el TG (r: 0,388; p&lt;0,001) y con el GCC (r: 0,287; p=0,004). Esta relación no fue significativa con el NT y TCD (r: 0,067; p=0,50 y r: 0,17; p=0,08 respectivamente). Conclusiones: Los valores de PIO con TCD y NT son mayores que con TG en pacientes con HTO. La PIO con TG se ve influenciada por el aumento de GCC. El incremento de APO se asocia a un incremento del GCC y de PIO con los tres tonómetros (siendo esta relación solo estadísticamente significativa con el TG)(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;87(12): 401-406, dic. 2012. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106518</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación de tonómetro de contorno dinámico, Goldmann y neumotonómetro en pacientes con hipertensión ocular y su relación con la paquimetría y amplitud del pulso ocular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14455^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7591^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3333^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
