<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043857</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-3465</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Strange chem in respiratory roads. Take care in a pediatric urgency service in a municipal hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The bronchoaspiration of strange chem in childrenless than 3 years old is the accident that occuredfrequently at home. It may cause death at the momentof the accident or could happen inadvertent soas to often weeks, monthes or years may destroythe places where they were lodged. With the objectiveof know the behavior of this accident in the urgencyservice of Santa Cruz del Sur Municipal Hospital,it was carried out a retrospective study to 118children which were attended in an urgency roomcause aspiration of strange chem. It was developeda detail questionary, physic exploration, x-ray of toraxin anteroposterior, lateral position and forced inspirationand expiration. It was also made a broncoscopicexploration under general anaesthesia andcardiorespiratory monitorization with rigid broncoscopicof wolf, so later storz broncoscopic with opticspliers. In all the cases were developed clinic and radiologiccontrols during the first 12 and 24 hours ofintervention.In the investigation predominate the children lessthan 3 years old with a 60,9%, been the boys the moreafected ina 68,6%. The characteristics of strangechem were variables predominant the vegetables,andamong these the dry fruits in 50,0%. The moreaccented symptom was the persistant cought with a 81,3%, along or associated to others less frequentsymptoms such as: A finite sound, respiratory problemsand fever.The mayority of the patients presentedto their hipoventilation admission in a 72,0%; so,respect to the radiology the more frequents signs werethe aerial flytrap by mechanism of valve 61%</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Moya, V. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Santos, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La broncoaspiración de cuerpos extraños en niñosmenores de tres años de edad es el accidenteque ocurre con mayor frecuencia en el hogar. Puedeocasionar la muerte en el momento del accidente opasar inadvertido para dar lugar después de semanas,meses o años, a la destrucción de los sitiosdonde quedaron alojados.Con el objetivo de conocer el comportamiento deeste accidente en el Servicio de Urgencias del HospitalMunicipal de Santa Cruz del Sur, se realizó unestudio retrospectivo a 118 niños que fueron atendidosen el cuerpo de guardia por aspiración de cuerpoextraño. Se hizo anamnesia detallada, exploraciónfísica, radiológico de tórax en posición anteroposterior,lateral y en inspiración y espiración forzada.También exploración broncoscópica bajo anestesiageneral y monitorización cardiorrespiratoria,con broncoscopio rígido de Wolf y posteriormentebroncoscopio Storz con pinzas ópticas. En todos loscasos se realizaron controles clínicos y radiológicosa las 12 y 24 h de la intervención.Predominaron los menores de 3 años con 60,9%,siendo los varones los más afectados en 68,6%. Lascaracterísticas de los cuerpos extraños fueron variablespredominando los vegetales y entre estos losfrutos secos en el 59,0%. El síntoma mas acentuadofue la tos persistente 81,3%, aislada o asociada aotros síntomas menos frecuentes como sibilancia,dificultad respiratoria y fiebre. La mayoría de los pacientespresentaron a su admisión hipoventilación72,0%. En cuanto a la radiología los signos más frecuentesfueron el atrapamiento aéreo por mecanismode válvula 61%</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediátrika (Madr.);26(1): 24-28, ene. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043857</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuerpo extraño en vías respiratorias de niños. Atención en servicio de urgencia de un hospital municipal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12557^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5683^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7220^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2026^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
