<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-141805</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Plan for the elimination of measles and rubella in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The current Plan for the elimination of measles and rubella is made of the Plan for the elimination of measles in Spain, set up in 2001, and the Surveillance protocol of rubella and congenital rubella syndrome in the phase of elimination, established in 2007. The monitoring of the elimination of both diseases conducted from the European Region of World Health Organization (WHO) has been reinforced since 2010. An annual report with information on the situation of measles and rubella in The Member Estates is being requested since 2013. The Ministry of Health, Social Services and Equality nominated a National Committee for Verification of Measles and Rubella Elimination in 2013, for the review and delivery of the requested information. The strategies and activities currently recommended from the WHO European Region, the verification process in Spain, and the steps to follow for the updating of the Plan for the elimination of measles and rubella in Spain are mentioned in this article (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Limia Sánchez, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Plan de Eliminación del Sarampión en España, del año 2001, y el Protocolo de vigilancia de la rubeola y del síndrome de la rubeola congénita en fase de eliminación, del año 2007, componen el actual Plan para la eliminación de ambas enfermedades en España. Desde 2010 se está reforzando el seguimiento de la eliminación del sarampión y la rubeola en la Región Europea de la Organización Mundial de la Salud (OMS), solicitando información anual a los estados miembros sobre la situación del sarampión y la rubeola desde el año 2013. Ese mismo año, a instancias de la OMS, el Ministerio de Sanidad, Servicios Sociales e Igualdad nombró el Comité Nacional de Verificación de la Eliminación del Sarampión y la Rubeola en España para la revisión y envío de la información solicitada. En este artículo se comentan las estrategias y actividades actuales recomendadas por la Región Europea de la OMS, el proceso de verificación en España y los pasos a seguir para la actualización del Plan de eliminación del sarampión y la rubeola en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(4): 393-396, jul.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-141805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Plan para la eliminación del sarampión y la rubeola en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12784^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23113^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12784^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28485^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8626^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35372^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8628^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12786^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54858^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
