<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131665</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Autosomal dominant osteopetrosis: A presentation of 3 cases and a new gene mutation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Osteopetrosis (OP) is a congenital bone disease which is caused by a functional disorder in osteoclasts with inability for normal bone resorption, leading to increased bone mineral density and bone sclerosis. It can be classified into different groups according to their clinical and their genetic characteristics: autosomal recessive with several subtypes (OPTB) or autosomal dominant type 1 or 2 (OPTA1-2). There is a wide clinical variability of the disease, from asymptomatic to lethal in the first months of life, with variable expressivity in the family members. Diagnosis is mainly clinical with genetic confirmation of the OP, and treatment is symptomatic. Three cases of OP are presented, with the discovery of a new gene mutation in LRP5 which caused OPTA1 in one of them (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>de Arriba Muñoz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Janer Subías, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Lozano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labarta Aizpun, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Iñiguez, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez del Pozo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La osteopetrosis (OP) es una rara enfermedad ósea congénita producida por una alteración funcional en los osteoclastos con incapacidad para la reabsorción ósea normal, produciéndose un aumento de la densidad mineral ósea y esclerosis ósea. Puede clasificarse en autosómica recesiva (OPTB) o autosómica dominante (OPTA1-2). Existe una gran variabilidad clínica de la enfermedad, desde asintomática a letal en los primeros meses de vida, con expresividad variable en los miembros de una familia. Su diagnóstico es principalmente clínico con confirmación genética, y el tratamiento es sintomático. Se presentan una serie de casos de OP, con el hallazgo de una nueva mutación en el gen LRP5 causante de OPTA1 en uno de ellos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): e35-e38, ene. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131665</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Osteopetrosis autosómica dominante: a propósito de 3 casos y una mutación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10203^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10203^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10203^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10203^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1873^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10203^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12979^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
