<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163513</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cri du Chat Syndrome: a case report. Clinical and evolutive characteristics</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Cri du Chat syndrome has an incidence of 1/15,000 - 1/50,000 and is caused by a deletion of the chromosome 5p. Affected individuals have a special phenotype, intellectual disability, language delay and a characteristic acute cry in the early stages of their life, although there is a clinical variability according to the extent and location of the deletion. It is very important to begin rehabilitation therapy early to improve learning and communication skills and thus improve quality of life. We report the case of an infant with clinical suspicion of the syndrome at birth that was confirmed by genetic testing. We describe the most characteristic clinical and evolutionary aspects of the syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Orden Rueda, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clavero Montañés, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Gimeno, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa Gómez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz del Olmo Izuzquiza, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berdún Chéliz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome Cri du Chat tiene una incidencia de 1/15.000&#151;1/50.000 y es debido a una delección del cromosoma 5p. Los individuos afectos presentan un fenotipo especial, discapacidad intelectual, retraso del lenguaje junto con un llanto agudo característico en las primeras tapas de su vida, si bien, hay una variabilidad clínica según la extensión y localización de la delección. Es muy portante iniciar una terapia rehabilitadora precozmente ara mejorar sus capacidades de aprendizaje y comunicación y así mejorar su calidad de vida. Se presenta el caso 6 un lactante con sospecha clínica del síndrome al nacimiento confirmándose en el estudio genético. Se describen los aspectos clínicos y evolutivos más característicos del síndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;73(2): 109-111, mar.-abr. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163513</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome Cri du Chat: a propósito de un caso. Características clínicas y evolutivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32938^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2921</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34293^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3428^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3428^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52517^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19107^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
