<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-62039</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparo-endoscopic single site (LESS)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: We present our initial experience in laparo-endoscopic single site (LESS) surgery, through multichannel port, articulated instruments and standard instruments adapted others adapted for the procedures. Materials and methods: Between February and October 2008, 28 LESS surgical procedures with multi-port were performed (Transumbilical simple prostatectomy (PSTU) and transvesical (PSTV), simple nephrectomy (NS), Enterocystoplasty augmentation (ECA) and simple hysterectomy (HS)). The clinical data were collected prospectively and analyzed retrospectively. Was used access device Multichannel (R-Port). The procedures were performed for a single surgeon (RS). The surgical technique was the same route used by conventional laparoscopic. Results: Twenty-eight surgeries were performed: PSTU (01), PSTV (20), NS (01), ECA (01), HS (05). The incision was performed umbilical or infraumbilical. Only one case (nephrectomy) needed it placement of an additional trocar. The average age by procedure was PSTU and PSTV, 67 and 68 year-old (57-89 y) respectively; NS 12 year-old; RCT 20 year-old; HS 46.4year-old (41 &#150; 54 y). The operative time was: PSTU 120 minutes, PSTV 91 minutes (45-210 min); NS 120 minutes; RCT 300minutes; HS 112 minutes (90-160 min). The operative bleeding was PSTU and PSTV 200 cc. and 337 cc (50-1500 cc) respectively; NS 100cc; EAC 100 cc; HS 118 cc (100-160 cc). The complication was haematury in two cases of PSTV, both patients required exploration postoperative endoscopic with satisfactory evolution. Conclusions: LESS is a feasible and reproducible surgical option in uro-gynecologic surgical treatment. Further studies, experience and follow-up will provide an objective assessment of the technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sotelo, Rene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Astigueta, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carmona, Oswaldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrade, Robert De</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez-Salas, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Presentar nuestra experiencia inicial en LESS Surgery (Laparo-Endoscopic Single Site Surgery/Cirugía laparoendoscópica por acceso único), mediante uso de dispositivo multicanal, instrumentos estándar, articulables y otros adaptados para la consecución de los procedimientos. Materiales y métodos: Entre febrero y septiembre del 2008 se realizaron 28 procedimientos quirúrgicos LESS con puerto multicanal: prostatectomía simple transumbilical (PSTU) y transvesical (PSTV), nefrectomía simple (NS), enterocistoplastia de aumento (ECA) e histerectomía simple (HS). Los datos clínicos fueron recopilados de manera prospectiva y analizados retrospectivamente. Se utilizó dispositivo de acceso multicanal (R-Port). Los procedimientos fueron realizados en un centro por un solo cirujano (RS). La técnica quirúrgica empleada correspondió a la misma utilizada por vía laparoscópica convencional. Resultados: Se realizaron 28 intervenciones quirúrgicas: PSTU (01), PSTV(20), NS(01), ECA(01), HS(05). La incisión de acceso fue realizada a nivel umbilical o infraumbilical. Solo un caso (nefrectomía) ameritó uso de trocar adicional de 2 mm. La edad media en años por procedimiento fue: PSTU, 67; PSTV, 68 (57&#150;89); NS, 12; ECA, 20; HS, 46.4 (41&#150;54). El tiempo quirúrgico medio en minutos fue: PSTU, 120; PSTV, 91 (45&#150;210); NS, 120; ECA, 300; HS, 112 (90&#150;160). El sangrado operatorio fue: PSTU, 200cc; PSTV, 337 cc (50-1500); NS, 100cc; EAC, 100cc; HS, 118cc. (100&#150;160). La complicación observada fue hematuria profusa en dos casos de PSTV, ambos pacientes requirieron exploración postoperatoria con evolución satisfactoria. Conclusiones: LESS es una alternativa factible y reproducible en patología uroginecológica de resolución quirúrgica. Mayores estudios, experiencias y seguimiento permitirán la evaluación objetiva de esta técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;33(2): 172-181, feb. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-62039</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Laparo-endoscopia por acceso único: experiencia inicial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14970^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11911^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200902</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
