<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-12803</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-2273</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Central nervous system anomalies. Ultrasound prenatal diagnosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present an abstract about the congenital central nervous system anomalies, and previously a summary of anatomy and embryological development.Anomalies are very well detailed and always accompanied with its echographic image, obtained from our daily experience, and a review of the literature.Also, we have been interested in the prognosis of these anomalies, that will be very useful for the treatments involved</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Alpe Editores, S.A.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un resumen del desarrollo embriológico y de la anatomía del sistema nervioso central, que servirá como base al estudio y revisión de las anomalías congénitas de dicho sistema.Dichas anomalías se exponen detalladamente, con una amplia revisión bibliográfica, y nuestra experiencia, haciendo hincapié en su descripción ecográfica para realizar un diagnóstico correcto.También nos ha interesado, en la medida de lo posible, conocer su pronóstico, lo cual será de gran ayuda en su manejo  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cienc. ginecol;6(2): 62-85, mar. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anomalías del sistema nervioso central. Diagnóstico ecográfico prenatal</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Montalvo, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costales, C. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, M. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-12803</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5426^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9614^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
