<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126848</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biologic therapy in idiopathic inflammatory myopathy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper is to study the most available scientific evidence on the use of biological therapies in patients with idiopathic inflammatory myopathy (dermatomyositis, polymyositis and sporadic body myositis inclusion). In this review the main published studies on the use of biologic agents in patients with myositis are discussed, especially those with an adequate study design, including randomization and control group, and the methodological difficulties inherent to the rarity and heterogeneity of these are discussed complex diseases. The evidence currently available do not allow us to place biological therapies as an established treatment in patients with myositis, although its use is a therapeutic resource to assess given the lack of proven treatments in these entities. It is likely that the publication of future studies, some of them still in progress, contribute to improve this situation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ramos Casals, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selva-O Callaghan, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Grau Junyent, Josep M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este artículo es estudiar la mayor evidencia científica disponible sobre el uso de terapias biológicas en pacientes con miopatía inflamatoria idiopática (dermatomiositis, polimiositis y miositis con cuerpos de inclusión esporádica). En esta revisión se analizan los principales estudios publicados sobre la utilización de fármacos biológicos en sujetos con miositis, especialmente aquellos con un diseño metodológico adecuado, que incluyen asignación aleatoria y grupo control, y se discuten las dificultades metodológicas inherentes a la rareza y heterogeneidad de estas complejas enfermedades. Las evidencias disponibles en la actualidad no permiten todavía situar a las terapias biológicas como un tratamiento consolidado en pacientes con miositis, si bien su utilización constituye un recurso terapéutico a valorar dada la escasez de tratamientos con eficacia probada en estas entidades. Es probable que la publicación de futuros estudios, algunos de ellos todavía hoy en curso, contribuyan a mejorar esta situación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);143(6): 275-280, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126848</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia biológica en pacientes con miopatía inflamatoria idiopática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1716^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9411^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29591^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53366</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28622^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
