<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94499</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medication history taking on admission to a hospital emergency department</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the quality and accuracy of medication histories taken during admission to the emergency department (ED) and to analyze the factors that may be related to the presence of discrepancies. Methods: Descriptive cross-sectional study. Patients over the age of 64 years were enrolled on admission to the hospital from the during the last quarter of 2009. To detect the presence of discrepancies we compared the medication histories taken by a clinical pharmacist to the ones taken by an emergency physician on admission. Regression analysis was used to identify factors associated with the presence of discrepancies. Results: A total of 324 patients (53.4% women) with a mean age of 78.3 years were enrolled. We detected 2928 discrepancies affecting 95.1% (95% confidence interval [CI], 92.7%-97.4%) of the patients. The medication groups with the largest numbers of discrepancies were antiulcer drugs (10.8%), antithrombotic drugs (9.5%), and psycholeptics(7.2%). We detected discrepancies in the recording of 257 high-risk drugs (8.8%) in 33.3% (95% CI, 28.2%-38.5%) of the patients. The only independent variable associated with a higher prevalence of discrepancies was the use of multiple medications (odds ratio, 8.02 (95% CI, 2.79-23.02).Conclusion: Our findings demonstrate that there is ample room for improvement, on medication history taken at ED, and increased cuation should be taken for patients of advanced age and those taking multiple medications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iniesta Navalón, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madrigal de Torres, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñera Salmerón, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gascón Canovas, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbieta Sanz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar la calidad y la precisión de la historia farmacoterapéutica realizada al ingreso en el servicio de urgencias y los factores asociados a la presencia de discrepancias. Método: Estudio transversal descriptivo. Se incluyeron los pacientes mayores de 64 años que ingresaron en el hospital desde el servicio de urgencias durante el último trimestre de 2009. Para determinar la presencia de discrepancias se cotejó la historia farmacoterapéutica realizada por un farmacéutico clínico con la obtenida por el urgenciólogo al ingreso hospitalario. Los factores asociados a de discrepancias se identificaron mediante un análisis de regresión logística univariante con el paquete estadístico SPSS versión 15.0. Resultados: Se incluyeron en el estudio 324 pacientes (53,4% mujeres) con una edad media de 78,3 años. Se identificaron 2.928 discrepancias que afectaron al 95,1%(IC95%: 92,7-97,4%) de los pacientes. Los grupos terapéuticos con mayor número de las discrepancias detectadas fueron los antiulcerosos (10,8%), los antitrombóticos (9,5%) y psicolépticos (7,2%). Se detectaron 257 discrepancias (8,8%) en medicamentos de alto riesgo en el 33,3% (IC95%: 28,2-38,5%) de los pacientes. La polimedicación fue la única variable independiente asociada a una mayor prevalencia de discrepancias [OR: 8,02 (IC95%: 2,79-23,02)].Conclusiones: Nuestros resultados muestran que existe un amplio margen de mejora,en la historia farmacoterapéutica realizada en urgencias, y debe extremarse la precaución en la población anciana y polimedicada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);23(5): 365-371, oct. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94499</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la anamnesis farmacoterapéutica realizada en el servicio de urgencias al ingreso hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53712</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8675^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
