<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91506</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Twenty five years of health reports in Barcelona: a commitment to transparency and a tool for action</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After a quarter century of annual health reports in the city of Barcelona, this study documents the experience and draws some elements that may be useful in other contexts, specifying the analysis on the Health Report of 2008. We show the conceptual framework, the process of preparing the report, sources of information used and the contents.We evaluate the dissemination of the health report, both at the political level, as well as the media, professionals and the public. Furthermore, we examine the impact of the report as a tool for social change and planning(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bartoll, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Borrell, Carme</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Altés, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro, Manel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villalbí, Joan R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pasarín, M. Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo documenta la experiencia de 25 años de informes de salud anuales en la ciudad de Barcelona y extrae algunos elementos que pueden ser útiles en otros contextos, particularizando el análisis en el Informe de Salud de 2008. Se muestra el marco conceptual, el proceso de elaboración del informe, las fuentes de información utilizadas y los contenidos del mismo. Se evalúa la difusión del Informe de Salud de 2008, tanto a nivel político como a los medios de comunicación, a los profesionales y a la ciudadanía. Además se analiza la repercusión del informe como herramienta de cambio social y de planificación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;85(5): 449-458, sep.-oct.2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91506</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Veinticinco años de informes de salud en Barcelona: una apuesta por la transpariencia y un instrumento para la acción</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12070^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12070^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12070^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3184^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d861</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28455^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
