<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038649</identifier>
<setSpec>1698-6946</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mandibular ameloblastoma. A review of the literature and presentation of six cases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Ameloblastoma is a benign odontogenic tumour of epithelialorigin without induction in the connective tissue. In treating thistype of tumour, it is important to assess the clinical type (solid,multicystic, unicystic, peripheral), localisation, and size of thetumour as well as age of the patient. Articles have recently beenpublished with the purpose of providing updated knowledgeand therapeutic approaches to ameloblastoma. We present sixcases of patients with localised mandibular ameloblastoma whowere treated during the last seven years. We present data onclinical appearance, histological characteristics, and therapeuticapproach that was used, which included excision of the lesion,perilesional drilling of the bone, or block resection, accordingto the type of ameloblastoma. Lastly, we analysed follow-upmeasures and the rate of recurrence in these patients. The aim ofthis paper is to review the concepts relating to ameloblastomathat have been published recently and to assess their influence onthe clinical attitude taken when facing this pathology, using ourexperience with ameloblastoma as a starting point to illustratethis discussion</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Lagares, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Guisado, José M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Infante Cossío, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Pérez, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El ameloblastoma es un tumor odontogénico benigno de origenepitelial sin inducción en el tejido conectivo. En el tratamientodel mismo se debe valorar el tipo clínico (sólido y multiquístico,uniquístico, periférico), la localización y el tamaño del tumor,así como la edad del paciente. Recientemente se han publicadoalgunos artículos con el fin de actualizar los conocimientos yactitudes terapéuticas frente al ameloblastoma.Se presentan seis casos de pacientes afectos de ameloblastomaslocalizados en la mandíbula, tratados en los últimos siete años.Se aportan datos acerca de su aparición clínica, sus característicashistológicas, el manejo terapéutico realizado que consistióen la extirpación de la lesión, fresado perilesional del hueso oresección en bloque, según el tipo de ameloblastoma. Finalmenteanalizamos el seguimiento y la aparición de recidivas en lospacientes presentados.El objetivo de este artículo es revisar los conceptos respecto alameloblastoma que se han publicado recientemente y valorarsu influencia en la actitud del clínico a la hora de actuar frentea esta patología, tomando como punto de partida para ilustrarestá discusión la presentación de nuestra experiencia respectoal ameloblastoma</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. oral patol. oral cir. bucal (Internet);10(3): 231-238, mayo-jul. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038649</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ameloblastoma mandibular. Revisión de la literatura y presentación de seis casos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3577^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24273^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
