<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108533</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of hemorrhage in patients with abdominal trauma: application of the European Guidelines for the management of bleeding following major trauma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In patients with traumatic intraabdominal hemorrhage, urgent decisions must be made. Resuscitation measures must often be simultaneously combined with diagnostic actions and measures to control the source of the bleeding. Hemorrhages are usually complicated by coagulation disorders and the presence of acidosis and hypothermia. In these conditions, emergency measures are required that usually involve various specialists. However, given the paucity of the scientific evidence in this field, the intervention protocols differ from one center to another. The European Guidelines for the management of bleeding following major trauma has recently been published. These guidelines review aspects such as evaluation and initial management of bleeding, localization and control of the source of bleeding and replacement of blood products. In addition, recommendations based on the best available evidence to 2008 are made. This review describes the basic aspects of traumatic intraabdominal hemorrhage (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Mondéjar, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pino-Sánchez, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tuero León, Gaspar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Bolaños, Sandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castán Ribas, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El paciente con hemorragia intraabdominal traumática requiere la toma de decisiones con carácter urgente. Con frecuencia habrá que combinar de forma simultánea las medidas de reanimación con acciones diagnósticas y de control de la fuente de la hemorragia. El cuadro hemorrágico suele verse complicado con trastornos de la coagulación y la presencia de acidosis e hipotermia. En estas condiciones son necesarias actuaciones urgentes que generalmente implican a varios especialistas, pero dada la debilidad de la evidencia científica en este campo, las pautas de actuación difieren de un centro a otro. Recientemente se han publicado las Guías Europeas para el manejo del paciente traumatizado sangrante en las que se revisan aspectos como la valoración y el manejo inicial de la hemorragia, la localización y control de la fuente del sangrado y la reposición de hemoderivados. Se elaboran, asimismo, unas recomendaciones basadas en la mejor evidencia disponible hasta 2008. En la presente revisión expondremos los aspectos fundamentales referidos a la hemorragia intraabdominal traumática (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);85(supl.1): 29-34, jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108533</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la hemorragia en pacientes con traumatismo abdominal: aplicación de las Guías Europeas para el manejo del paciente traumatizado sangrante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7215^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28875^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d147^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
