<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045635</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disability and quality of life of stroke survivors: evaluation nine months after discharge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aim. After acute episode, a great number of individuals who survive a stroke have impairmentsthat impede them to carry out with autonomy a set of basic activities of daily life and instrumental activities of daily life. Theclinical evaluation health self perception is a useful element on patient&#146;s recovering process. The purpose of this study was toevaluate post-stroke functional health status and quality of life. Patients and methods. After identification of a cohort ofadmitted patients at a general hospital, those were contacted by phone nine months after discharge. The collected tool sent bymail included the COOP WONCA charts, Frenchay Activities Index, Barthel Index, Rankin scale and a set of sociodemographicvariables. Results. Participants survival rate was of 81%. The physical functioning and the capacity to performdaily activities were the most affected ones, impairing the patients of making a set of basic and instrumental daily activities.The emotional state and health self-perception are also correlated to disability. Conclusions. The results suggest asignificative percentage of stroke survivors maintaining a moderate or severe disability (47.8%) requiring the presence ofcaregiver helping self-care. Collected data enhances that stroke survivors have severe physical dysfunction associated toemotional and psychological disturbances</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ribeiro, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martins, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garret, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Tras el episodio agudo de accidentevascular cerebral (AVC), un gran número de supervivientesse ve afectado por secuelas que impiden llevar a cabo diversas actividadesbásicas o instrumentales de la vida diaria. Junto con laevaluación clínica, la percepción del paciente relativa a su estadode salud constituye una información útil en su proceso de recuperación.El objetivo de este estudio se centró en evaluar la capacidadfuncional y la calidad de vida tras el AVC. Pacientes y métodos.Tras la identificación de una cohorte de pacientes atendidos en unhospital general, se contactó con ellos nueve meses después del altahospitalaria. El instrumento de recogida de datos, enviado porcorreo, integraba la escala de COOP WONCA, el índice de actividadesde Frenchay, el índice de Barthel y la escala de Rankin, ademásde un conjunto de variables sociodemográficas. Resultados. Latasa de supervivencia de los participantes fue del 81%. La aptitudfísica y la capacidad para ejecutar actividades diarias son lasdimensiones físicas más afectadas, que impiden a los pacientes realizarun conjunto de actividades básicas e instrumentales diarias.El estado afectivo-emocional y la autopercepción del estado generalde salud se correlacionan igualmente con la incapacidad física.Conclusiones. Los resultados apuntan a un porcentaje significativode individuos que tras el AVC mantienen una incapacidad moderadao grave (47,8%), lo cual determina la presencia de una segundapersona para colaborar en las actividades de autocuidado. Los datosencontrados son decisivos en cuanto a que los individuos presentandisfunciones físicas graves asociadas a alteraciones emocionalesy psicológicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(11): 655-659, jun. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045635</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incapacidad y calidad de vida del paciente afectado por un accidente vascular cerebral: evaluación nueve meses después del alta hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
