<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153578</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation by the tutor and self-evaluation by Nursing students of learning results during clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to compare and analyze the perception by Nursing Degree Students about achieving the learning results expected during their monitored practices in the basic level, and about the scores assigned by their practice tutors in the evaluation of learning results. Materials and methods: a preliminary observational descriptive study. The study population consisted of Nursing Degree Students from the Centro Universitario San Rafael Lebrija (Madrid) in monitored practices of basic level during the 2015-2016 terms. The scores for their learning results during rotation were collected through two questionnaires for evaluation of competence, self administered by tutors at six weeks into the rotation, and by students at three and six weeks into the rotation. Results: twenty-five students were included. In the self-evaluation by students, the highest mean scores linked to generic competences were obtained by: &#147;Fits in the team: greets others when their shift starts and ends, shows respect, and conveys a collaborative attitude&#148; (9.33 (SD: 0.92) at week 3) and 9.80 (SD:0.65) at week 6). In specific competences, there was a mean score of 9.38 (SD: 0.82) at week 3 and of 9.66 (SD: 0.55) at week 6 in:&#147;Shows respect for the opinions, beliefs and values of patients and relatives, avoiding value judgments&#148;. In the evaluation by tutors (week 6), the mean scores for results were similar to those of students. Conclusions: the scores assigned by tutors, in contrast to the self-evaluated by students, favour a more accurate view of the teaching-learning process; therefore, self-evaluation is a useful tool in order to monitor students&#146; progress (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Visiers Jiménez, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: comparar y analizar la percepción que tienen los estudiantes de Grado en Enfermería sobre la consecución de los resultados de aprendizaje previstos durante la realización de sus prácticas tuteladas de nivel básico, y con las puntuaciones otorgadas por los tutores de prácticas en la evaluación de los resultados de aprendizaje. Material y métodos: estudio preliminar observacional descriptivo. La población de estudio fueron estudiantes de Grado en Enfermería del Centro Universitario San Rafael Lebrija (Madrid) en prácticas tuteladas de nivel básico en el curso 2015-2016. Se recogieron las puntuaciones de los resultados de aprendizaje del rotatorio a través de dos cuestionarios de evaluación de competencias autoadministrados a tutores a las seis semanas de rotación, y a los estudiantes, a las tres y a las seis semanas de rotación. Resultados: se incluyeron a 25 estudiantes. En la autoevaluación del estudiante las mayores puntuaciones medias vinculadas a competencias genéricas las obtuvo: &#147;Se integra en el equipo: saluda y se despide cuando inicia y finaliza el turno, demuestra respeto y transmite actitud colaboradora&#148; (9,33 [DE: 0,92] en semana 3 y9,80 [DE: 0,65] en semana 6). En competencias específicas se obtuvo una media de 9,38 (DE: 0,82) en la semana 3 y de 9,66 (DE:0,55) en la semana 6 en: &#147;Muestra respeto hacia las opiniones, creencias y valores de los pacientes y familiares, evitando juicios de valor&#148;. En la evaluación del tutor (semana 6) las puntuaciones medias de los resultados son similares a las de los estudiantes. Conclusiones: las puntuaciones otorgadas por los tutores encontraste con las autoevaluadas por los estudiantes favorecen a una visión más ajustada sobre el proceso de enseñanza-aprendizaje siendo la autoevaluación una herramienta útil para monitorizarla progresión de los estudiantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(1): 69-70, feb. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153578</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del tutor y autoevaluación de los estudiantes de Enfermería sobre los resultados de aprendizaje durante las prácticas clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3008^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7561^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
