<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118671</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Penile representations in ancient Greek art</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: The presentation of the cult of phallus in ancient Greece and the artistic appearance of the phenomenon on vase figures and statues, as indicative of the significant role of the male genitalia in all fertility ceremonies. METHODS: The examination of a great number of penile representations from the ancient Greek pottery and sculpture and the review of the ancient theater plays (satiric dramas and comedies). RESULTS: Phallus in artistic representation is connected either with gods of fertility, such as the goat-footed and horned Pan or the ugly dwarf Priapus or the semi-animal nailed figures Satyrs, devotees of the god Dionysus accompanying him in all ritual orgiastic celebrations. Phallus also symbolizes good luck, health and sexuality: people bear or wear artificial phalli exactly like the actors as part of their costume or carry huge penises during the festive ritual processions. On the contrary, the Olympic gods or the ordinary mortals are not imaged ithyphallic; the ideal type of male beauty epitomized in classical sculpture, normally depicts genitals of average or less than average size. It is noteworthy that many of these images belong to athletes during or immediately after hard exercise with the penis shrunk. The normal size genitalia may have been simply a convention to distinguish normal people from the gods of sexuality and fertility, protectors of the reproductive process of Nature. CONCLUSIONS: The representation of the over-sized and erected genitalia on vase figures or statues of ancient Greek art is related to fertility gods such as Priapus, Pan and Satyrs and there is strong evidence that imagination and legend were replacing the scientific achievements in the field of erectile function for many centuries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Poulakou-Rebelakou, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tsiamis, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rempelakos, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: La presentación del culto del falo en la Grecia antigua y la aparición artística del fenómeno en figuras de ánforas y estatuas, como indicativo del papel significativo de los genitales masculinos en todas las ceremonias de fertilidad. MÉTODOS: La examinación de un gran número de representaciones fálicas en la cerámica y escultura griega antigua y la revisión de las antiguas obras teatrales (dramas satíricos y tragedias). RESULTADOS: El falo en las representaciones artísticas está conectado a los dioses de fertilidad, como Pan, el dios con pies de chivo y cuernos, o el enano feo Príapo, o los Sátiros, figuras con uñas parecidas a las de los animales, devotos del dios Dioniso que lo acompañan en todas las celebraciones rituales orgiásticas. El falo también simboliza la buena suerte, la salud y la sexualidad: la gente se pone falos artificiales exactamente como los actores, como parte de sus trajes, o lleva penes enormes durante las procesiones rituales festivas. Al contrario, los dioses del Olimpo o los mortales comunes no están representados como itifálicos; el tipo ideal de la belleza masculina resumida en la escultura clásica, normalmente representa genitales de tamaño mediano o aún más pequeño. Es notable que muchas de estas imágenes pertenecen a atletas durante o inmediatamente después de ejercicios duros con el pene reducido. Quizás los genitales de tamaño regular hayan sido sencillamente una convención para distinguir entre la gente común y los dioses de sexualidad y fertilidad, protectores del proceso reproductivo de la naturaleza. CONCLUSIONES: La representación de genitales de gran tamaño o en erección en figuras de ánforas y estatuas en el arte griego antiguo está relacionada con dioses de fertilidad como Príapo, Pan y los Sátiros, y existe una gran evidencia de que la imaginación y la leyenda estaban sustituyendo los logros científicos conseguidos durante muchos siglos en el campo de la función eréctil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(10): 911-916, dic. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118671</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Representaciones fálicas en el arte griego antiguo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12994</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38875</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1160</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
