<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129967</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maxillary second molar with four roots and five root canals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The maxillary second molar usually exhibits 3 roots (2 buccal roots and 1 palatal root), as well as 3 root canals (1 root canal corresponding to each root). Even though it is unusual to find variations in its morphology, it is important to know the possible alterations that could occur if such variations are found, in order to prevent operative accidents. This paper reports a case of endodontic treatment applied to a maxillary second molar with 4 root and 5 root canals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Plasencia Contreras, Hugo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero Bobadilla, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Sánchez, Rodrigo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Magaña, Mariana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Herrera, Dennis Pamela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El segundo molar maxilar comúnmente presenta tres raíces (dos raíces bucales y una raíz palatina) y tres conductos radiculares (un conducto radicular por cada raíz). No obstante, a pesar de que es muy inusual encontrar variaciones en su morfología, es importante conocer las posibles alteraciones que pueden presentarse con el objetivo de evitar accidentes operatorios. En este caso se reporta el tratamiento endodóntico de un segundo molar maxilar con cuatro raíces y cinco conductos radiculares (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);31(1): 33-37, ene.-mar. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129967</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Segundo molar maxilar con cuatro raíces y cinco conductos radiculares</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32617^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55116</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14485^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12764^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12765^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3801^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
