<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045614</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New prognostic and predictive factors in advanced colorectal cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cancer patients often show a clinical tendency to thromboembolic events. This tendency is due to tumor cell-related factors together with the damage of the vascular endothelial exerted by chemotherapy treatment. Gastrointestinal tumors especially contribute to these types of events. More recently, the implication of tumor angiogenesis in clotting/fibrynolisys and plasminogen systems activation has been addressed in cancer patients. Finally, some hemostasis and angiogenesis-related factors such as platelets, von Willebrand factor, fibrinogen, plasminogen activator inhibitor type-1, D dimer, and vascular endotelial growth factor have been highlighted as new potential response and survival predictors in colorectal cancer patients. In this review article, the current evidence supporting the use of these proteins in assessing prognosis in colorectal cancer patients is critically exposed and discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil-Bazo, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Páramo, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Foncillas, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes con cáncer presentan una tendencia a experimentar episodios tromboembólicos. Los tumores gastrointestinales son más susceptibles a este tipo de alteraciones. Recientemente se ha estudiado la participación en el desarrollo angiogénico tumoral de la activación de los sistemas de la coagulación, la fibrinólisis y el plasminógeno. Factores causantes de la activación de estos sistemas como el factor Von Willebrand, el fibrinógeno, el inhibidor del activador de plasminógeno de tipo 1, el dímero D y el factor de crecimiento del endotelio vascular han ganado valor como posibles predictores de respuesta al tratamiento oncológico y como elementos pronósticos de supervivencia en pacientes con carcinoma colorrectal. En esta revisión se analiza la evidencia que avala el uso de estas proteínas en la valoración pronóstica y predictiva del cáncer colorrectal</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(14): 541-548, abr. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045614</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevos factores pronósticos y predictivos en el cáncer colorrectal avanzado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5453</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24373^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11392^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9582^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6641^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
