<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046874</identifier>
<setSpec>0301-0546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effectiveness of nebulized furosemide added to nebulized salbutamol in children with acute asthma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Nebulized furosemide has been shown to be protective against bronchoconstricting stimuli. Methods: To investigate whether inhaled furosemide would exhibit an additional therapeutic effect in children with acute asthma we performed a double-blind, placebo-controlled study in which patients with acute asthma attack were randomized to receive either nebulized salbutamol (0.15 mg/kg) plus nebulized furosemide (10 mg/m²) or nebulized salbutamol (0.15 mg/kg) plus nebulized saline as placebo. In all patients, clinical asthma scores (CAS) were determined before and after drug administration. Peak expiratory flow rates (PEFR) were measured by a peak flow meter. Results: CAS and PEFR improved in both groups with nebulized salbutamol treatment. The CAS changed from 3.56 ± 2.13 to 2.06 ± 1.84 (p = 0.0001) in the study group and from 4.44 ± 2.63 to 2.56 ± 1.86 (p = 0.0003) in the control group. PEFR increased from 177.50 ± 65.88 to 221.88 ± 66.05 L/min in the first group (p = 0.0001) and from 183.13 ± 51.73 to 218.13 ± 60.25 in the second group (p = 0.0001). Conclusion: Adding nebulized furosemide to nebulized salbutamol in pediatric patients experiencing an acute asthma attack did not produce greater improvement in clinical (p = 0.3829) or spirometric (p = 0.3839) parameters than nebulized salbutamol alone</dc:description>
<dc:creator>K&amp;#1472;l&amp;#1472;ç, Mehmet Ya&amp;#351;ar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ceran, Ömer</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nuho&amp;#287;lu, Ça&amp;#287;atay</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: Se ha demostrado que la furosemida nebulizada protege frente a estímulos broncoconstrictores. Métodos: Con objeto de investigar si la furosemida inhalada tedría un efecto terapéutico adicionesl en niños con crisis de asma, un grupo de pacientes escogidos aleatoriamente, con crisis de asma recibieron bien salbutamol nebulizado (0.15 mg/kg) más furosemida nebulizada (10 mg/m²) bien salbutamol nebulizado (0,15 mg/kg) más solución salina como placebo. Se trata de un estudio doble ciego controlado con placebo. Antes y después de administrar los medicamentos, todos los pacientes se evaluaron clínicamente mediante un test de puntuación. Con un medidor de flujo se valoró el pico de flujo espiratorio (PEFR) a todos los pacientes. Resultados: La puntuación clínica y el PEF mejoraron en ambos grupos tratados con salbutamol. En el grupo en estudio, la puntuación clínica cambió de 3.56 ± 2.13 a 2.06 ± 1.84 (p=0.0001), y en el grupo control con placebo cambió de 4.44 ± 2.63 a 2.56 ± 1.86 (p=0.0003). El PEFR aumentó de177.50 ± 65.88 a 221.88 ± 66.05 L/min en el primer grupo (p=0.0001) y de 183.13 ± 51.73 a 218.13 ± 60.25 en el segundo grupo (p=0.0001). Conclusión: La adición de furosemida nebulizada al salbutamol nebulizado en pacientes pediátricos con crisis aguda de asma, no supone una ventaja para la mejoría de los parámetros clínicos (p=0.3829) ni del PEF (p=0.3839) frente al uso de salbutamol nebulizado solo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Allergol Immunopathol (Madr);34(2): 54-58, mar. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la furosemida nebulizada añadida al salbutamol nebulizado en los niños con crisis de asma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32858^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32858^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32858^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5801^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5801^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d423^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d423^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32388</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d423^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1257^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2021^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
