<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161023</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of nutritional status in patients with psychiatric disorders in a hospital unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There is little evidence regarding the nutritional status of patients with mental disorders (psychiatric illness). It is known that they are at higher risk of dying from cardiovascular disease and pose a higher likelihood of having diabetes, hypertension, dyslipidemia, and being overweight. Objective: Assess, in a hospital unit, the nutritional status of patients according to their psychiatric disorder. Material and Methods: An observational, comparative, and cross-sectional study was performed on 76 patients hospitalized with mental disorders (psychiatric illness). Anthropometric (weight, height, BMI, waist circumference), biochemical (seric albumin and blood glucose), clinical (administered drugs and gastrointestinal function), and dietary (energy and nutrient consumption) indicators were evaluated. Comparisons were made through Chi-square test, Student test and one-way ANOVA. Results: Patients, men and women are overweight, with a tendency of weight gain during hospitalization, particularly higher in the men. BMI did not differ in the comparison of mental disorders (psychiatric illness) (p = 0.13). Patients showed fasting glucose (71.9 ± 14.5 mg / dl) at levels close to the lower limit and albumin levels (3.0 ± 1.6 g / dL) below the minimum recommended range. The use of typical antipsychotics such as risperidone (30%), olanzapine (30%) and quetiapine (28%), predominated. Constipation was identified in 31.6% of patients. We observed that patients ingest 88.2% of the diet provided; with a consumption of 2032.7 ± 350.9 kcal / day (range 1108.2 - 2815.6 kcal / day). The average daily nutrient intake was 104 g of protein, 45.8 g of lipids, and 297.5 g of carbohydrates. Discussion: Patients with mental disorders (psychiatric illness) showed a state of malnutrition evidenced by overweight with risk of escalating to obesity during hospitalization; and malnutrition determined by the levels of albumin in their blood. It is known that pharmacological treatments used for these diseases induce an increase in appetite and decrease satiety, with consequent weight gain. The results are consistent with those reported on the increased risk of dying from cardiovascular disease displayed in these patients compared with the rest of the population. Conclusion: Patients with psychiatric illness are overweight; albumin values indicate malnutrition and energy and nutrient consumption that exceed your recommended daily requirement. No statistically significant differences in the nutritional status of patients were identified according to their mental disorders (psychiatric illness) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Ortiz, María Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ramírez, Brenda Yadira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jasso Molina, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existe poca evidencia en relación al estado nutricio del paciente con trastornos psiquiátricos, se sabe que presentan una probabilidad mayor de presentar sobrepeso, diabetes, hipertensión arterial, dislipidemia y mayor riesgo de morir por enfermedad cardiovascular. Objetivo: Evaluar el estado nutricio de los pacientes de acuerdo a su trastorno psiquiátrico, en una Unidad Hospitalaria. Material y Métodos: Se realizó un estudio observacional, comparativo, transversal en 76 pacientes hospitalizados con trastornos psiquiátricos. Se evaluaron indicadores antropométricos (peso, estatura, IMC, circunferencia de cintura), bioquímicos (albúmina y glucosa sanguínea), clínicos (fármacos y función gastrointestinal) y dietéticos (consumo energético y nutrimental). Se hicieron comparaciones por prueba Chi cuadrada, T de student y Anova de una vía. Resultados: Los pacientes, hombres y mujeres presentan sobrepeso, con una tendencia al aumento de peso durante la hospitalización, mayor en el grupo de los hombres. El IMC no fue diferente en la comparación por enfermedad psiquiátrica (p=0.13). Los pacientes presentaron glucosa en ayuno (71.9 ± 14.5 mg/dl) en niveles cercanos al límite inferior y albúmina (3.0 ± 1.6 g/dL) por debajo del rango mínimo recomendado. Predominó el uso de antipsicóticos atípicos como la Risperidona (30%), Olanzapina (30%) y Quetiapina (28%). Se identificó estreñimiento en un 31.6% de los pacientes. Se observó que los pacientes ingieren el 88.2% de la dieta proporcionada; con un consumo de 2032.7±350.9 kcal/día (rango 1108.2 - 2815.6 kcal/día). El promedio de consumo diario de nutrimentos fue de 104 g proteína, 45.8 g de lípidos y 297.5 g de hidratos de carbono. Discusión: Los pacientes con trastornos psiquiátricos presentaron un estado de mala nutrición evidenciado por sobrepeso con riesgo de incrementar a obesidad durante la hospitalización; y desnutrición determinada por sus niveles de albúmina en sangre. Se sabe que los tratamientos farmacológicos que se usan para estas enfermedades inducen aumento del apetito y disminución de la saciedad, con el consecuente aumento de peso. Los resultados son congruentes con lo reportado sobre el riesgo incrementado de morir por enfermedades cardiovasculares que presentan estos pacientes comparados con el resto de la población. Conclusión: Los pacientes con enfermedad psiquiátrica presentan sobrepeso; valores de albúmina que indican desnutrición y un consumo energético y nutrimental que excede su requerimiento diario recomendado. No se identificaron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el estado nutricio de los pacientes según el trastorno psiquiátrico que presentan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;37(1): 24-33, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161023</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del estado nutricio en pacientes con trastornos psiquiátricos en una unidad hospitalaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
