<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152088</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-0852</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Disorders specifically associated with stress: A case-controlled field study for ICD-11 mental and behavioural disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">As part of the development of the Eleventh Revision of International Classification of Diseases and Related Health Problems (ICD-11), the World Health Organization Department of Mental Health and Substance Abuse is conducting a series of case-controlled field studies using a new and powerful method to test the application by clinicians of the proposed ICD-11 diagnostic guidelines for mental and behavioural disorders. This article describes the case-controlled field study for Disorders Specifically Associated with Stress. Using a vignette-based experimental methodology, 1,738 international mental health professionals diagnosed standardized cases designed to test key differences between the proposed diagnostic guidelines for ICD-11 and corresponding guidelines for ICD-10. Across eight comparisons, several proposed changes for ICD-11, including the addition of Complex PTSD and Prolonged Grief Disorder, produced significantly improved diagnostic decisions and clearer application of diagnostic guidelines compared to ICD-10. However, several key areas were also identified, such as the description of the diagnostic requirement of re-experiencing in PTSD, in which the guidelines were not consistently applied as intended. These results informed specific revisions to improve the clarity of the proposed ICD-11 diagnostic guidelines. The next step will be to further test these guidelines in clinic-based studies using real patients in relevant settings (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Keeley, Jared W</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matsumoto, Chihiro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maercker, Andreas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perkonigg, Axel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roberts, Michael C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reed, Geoffrey M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Evans, Spencer C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lovell, Anne M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rousseau, Cécile</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gureje, Oye</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sharan, Pratap</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brewin, Chris R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cloitre, Marylène</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Como parte del desarrollo de la onceava versión de la Clasificación Internacional de Enfermedades y Problemas de Salud Relacionados (CIE-11), la Organización Mundial de la Salud está conduciendo una serie de estudios de campo de casos controlados utilizando un novedoso y potente método para evaluar la aplicación por parte de clínicos de las guías diagnósticas para los trastornos mentales y del comportamiento. Este artículo describe el estudio de campo de casos controlados para los Trastornos específicamente relacionados con el estrés. Con base en una metodología experimental de viñetas, 1.738 profesionales de la salud mental diagnosticaron casos estandarizados específicamente diseñados para evaluar diferencias clave entre las guías propuestas para la CIE-11 y las que les corresponden en la CIE-10. Diversos cambios propuestos para la CIE-11, incluyendo la adición del TEPT complejo y del Trastorno por duelo prolongado, produjeron mejores decisiones diagnósticas en comparación con la versión previa del manual. Sin embargo, se identificaron también áreas en las que las guías no se aplicaron de manera consistente, como el requisito diagnóstico de re-experimentación para el TEPT, lo que informó revisiones específicas para mejorar las guías diagnósticas, que serán evaluadas en futuros estudios basados en la clínica con pacientes reales en escenarios relevante (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. clin. health psychol. (Internet);16(2): 109-127, mayo-ago. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152088</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos específicamente relacionados con el estrés: estudio de campo de casos controlados para la CIE-11</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28405^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13703^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
