<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113755</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ginger as an alternative method to alleviate nausea and vomiting during pregnancy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nausea and vomiting during gestation (NVG) are a common disorder during the first weeks of pregnancy, and sometimes continue beyond week 20. Typically they don&#146;t entail any severe health problems for the pregnant woman and her future child, but they represent a distressing disorder which may interfere in her daily life. There is an increasing trend for pregnant women to use &#147;natural remedies &#147;in order to avoid possible side effects by usual medications. Ginger has proven to be a safe and effective alternative to alleviate nausea and vomiting in pregnant women, as long as it is used in recommended doses, and taking into account the specific medical record of each woman, in order to avoid possible drug interactions and side effects which may have an impact on other conditions suffered by the pregnant woman. It is necessary to encourage studies about safety and efficacy of said treatments in pregnant women, because these medicinal plants are often ingested without the information required for their efficacy and safety (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conde Puertas, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roque Martínez, Maricruz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Herrerías, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las náuseas y los vómitos durante la gestación (NVG) son un trastorno común durante las primeras semanas de embarazo y en ocasiones se prolongan más allá de la semana 20. Normalmente no revisten gravedad para la salud de la embarazada y su futuro hijo/a, pero supone un trastorno angustiante que puede interferir en su vida cotidiana. Cada vez son más las embarazadas que recurren al uso de los &#147;remedios naturales&#148; para evitar los posibles efectos secundarios delos medicamentos habituales. El jengibre ha demostrado ser una alternativa segura y eficaz para paliarlas náuseas y vómitos en la embarazada, siempre y cuando se utilice en las dosis recomendadas y teniendo en cuenta el historial médico particular de cada mujer, a fin de evitar posibles interacciones medicamentosas y efectos secundarios que pudieran influir en otras patologías presentes en la gestante. Se debe fomentar la realización de estudios acerca de la seguridad y efectividad de dichos tratamientos en mujeres embarazadas, ya que en numerosas ocasiones la ingesta de las plantas medicinales se hace sin la información necesaria para que sea efectivo y seguro (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;16(5): 50-53, jun. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El jengibre como método alternativo para paliar las náuseas y vómitos durante el embarazo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38641^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34155</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
