<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127556</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia: Clinical and therapeutic approaches</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia (bvFTD) is the most frequent presentation in the clinical spectrum of frontotemporal dementia (FTD) and it is characterised by progressive changes in personality and conduct. Major breakthroughs in molecular biology and genetics made during the last two decades have lent us a better understanding of this syndrome, which may be the first manifestation in many different neurodegenerative diseases. Development: We reviewed the main epidemiological, clinical, diagnostic and therapeutic  aspects of bvFTD. Most cases manifest sporadically and the average age of onset is 58 years. Current criteria for bvFTD propose three levels of diagnostic certainty: possible, probable, and definite. Clinical diagnosis is based on a detailed medical history provided by family members and caregivers, in conjunction with neuropsychological testing. Treatments which have been used in bvFDT to date are all symptomatic and their effectiveness is debatable. New drugs designed for specific molecular targets that are implicated in frontotemporal lobar degeneration are being developed. Conclusions: BvFDT is a frequent cause of dementia. It is a non-specific syndrome associated with heterogeneous histopathological and biomolecular findings. The definition of clinical subtypes complemented by biomarker identification may help predict the underlying pathology. This knowledge, along with the development of drugs designed for molecular targets, will offer new treatment possibilities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Matarrubia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matías-Guiu, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matías-Guiu, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Ramos, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La variante conductual de la demencia frontotemporal (DFT vc) es el síndrome clínico más frecuente de las demencias frontotemporales (DFT) y se caracteriza por una alteración progresiva de la personalidad y la conducta. En las últimas 2 décadas, los avances en biología molecular y genética han contribuido a un mayor conocimiento de esta entidad, que puede ser el modo de presentación de diferentes enfermedades neurodegenerativas. Desarrollo: Se revisan los principales aspectos epidemiológicos, clínicos, diagnósticos y terapéuticos de la DFT vc. La mayoría de los casos son esporádicos, iniciándose en torno a los 58 a&#152;nos de media. Los criterios diagnósticos vigentes establecen 3 niveles de certeza diagnóstica: posible, probable y definitivo. El diagnóstico clínico se basa en la anamnesis detallada de familiares, complementada con la realización de test neuropsicológicos dirigidos. Hasta la fecha, los tratamientos empleados son solo sintomáticos y de eficacia controvertida. Se están dise&#152;nando fármacos dirigidos contra dianas moleculares específicas implicadas en la patogenia de las degeneraciones lobares frontotemporales. Conclusiones: La DFT vc es una causa frecuente de demencia. Se trata de un síndrome amplio, heterogéneo desde el punto de vista histopatológico y biomolecular. La definición de subtipos clínicos y la identificación de biomarcadores podrían ayudar a predecir la afección subyacente,lo que junto con el desarrollo de fármacos dirigidos contra dianas moleculares ofrece nuevas posibilidades terapéuticas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;29(8): 464-472, oct. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127556</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demencia frontotemporal variante conductual: aproximación clínica y terapéutica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53512^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3103^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
