<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120341</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Subclinical atheroesclerosis and metabolic sindrome in children</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Metabolic syndrome (MS) in children has been associated to subclinical atherosclerosis as estimated by carotid intima-media thickness (CIMT). Objectives: We aim to ascertain the influence of MS, insulin resistance (IR) and nutritional status on CIMT. Percentiles with an increased risk of CIMT were also explored. Methods: A cross-sectional study of 447 children attending public schools in Santiago, Chile, was performed during years 2009-2011. This sample was selected considering the presence of one or more MS component and IR. Anthropometry and BP were assessed. A blood sample for determination of glycemia, insulinemia and lipids was taken. CIMT was assessed using high resolution ultrasonography with automated software. Pearson correlation, Student's t-test, Chi-squared test, and stepwise logistic regression were computed. Results: Mean age was 11.5 ± 1.0 years old (range 1014); 59% girls; 93% pubertal; 72% excess weight; 24% MS; and 15% IR. Mean values of MS components in children with CIMT &amp;#8805; percentile 75 versus &lt; percentile 75 had differences for systolic BP or diastolic BP &amp;#8805; percentile 90 (BP &amp;#8805; percentile 90) and high density lipoproteins cholesterol &amp;#8804; 40 mg/dL (CHDL &amp;#8804; 40 mg/dL). The logistic regression for CIMT &amp;#8805; percentile 75 only selected BP &amp;#8805; percentile 90 and CHDL &amp;#8804; 40 mg/dL. The logistic regression for CIMT &amp;#8805; percentile 90 did not select independent variables. Conclusions: In this group of children BP &amp;#8805; percentile 90 and CHDL &amp;#8804; 40 mg/dL values were associated to CIMT &amp;#8805; percentile 75. Influences of IR and nutritional status on CIMT were not found (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnaiz, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Godoy, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mardones, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarroel, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, Angélica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barja, Salesa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El síndrome metabólico (SM) en niños se ha vinculado al desarrollo de ateroesclerosis subclínica, estimada por el grosor intimo-medial carotideo (CIMT). Objetivos: Estudiar la asociación del CIMT con los componentes del SM, la resistencia insulínica (RI) y el estado nutricional en escolares, además de explorar puntos de corte asociados a riesgo. Métodos: Estudio transversal de 447 niños asistentes a escuelas públicas de Santiago, Chile (2009-2011), seleccionados por presentar uno o más componentes del SM y RI. Se realizó antropometría y toma estandarizada de presión de arteria braquial, además de muestras de sangre para determinar lípidos glicemia e insulinemia. Se midió el CIMT por ultrasonografía de alta resolución. Se utilizó correlación de Pearson, t de Student, chi cuadrado y regresión logística. Resultados: Edad 11,5 ± 1,0 años (rango 10-14); 59% mujeres; 93% púberes; 72% con exceso de peso; 24% con SM y 15% con RI. Los promedios de los componentes del SM en los niños con CIMT &amp;#8805; percentil 75 vs &lt; percentil 75 tuvieron diferencias para presión arterial sistólica o diastólica &amp;#8805; percentil 90 (PA) y colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de alta densidad &amp;#8804; 40 mg/dL (CHDL). En la regresión logística para CIMT &amp;#8805; percentil 75 fueron seleccionadas PA y CHDL. En la regresión logística para CIMT &amp;#8805; percentil 90 no hubo variables seleccionadas. Conclusiones: En este grupo de niños los niveles de PA y CHDL se asocian con CIMT &amp;#8805; percentil 75. No se encontró asociación con estado nutricional y RI posiblemente por ser una muestra seleccionada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;28(5): 1587-1593, sept.-oct. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120341</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ateroesclerosis subclínica y síndrome metabólico en niños</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55111^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54672</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
