<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90894</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Infiltration of ganglion impar and caudal in the management of traumatic coccydynia refractory to conventional analgesic treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Coccydynia is a term that refers to pain in the region of the coccyx. Most cases are associated with abnormal mobility of the coccyx which may trigger a chronic inflammatory process leading to degeneration of this structure. Non-surgical management remains the gold standard treatment for coccydynia, consisting of decreased sitting, seat cushioning, coccygeal massage, stretching, manipulation, local injection of steroids or anaesthetics, and postural adjustments. Material and methods. A retrospective study of 23 patients who underwent treatment for coccydynia and failed to respond to conservative management. They were treated by radiologically guided infiltration of the ganglion blockade impar and/or caudal blockade with 1% lidocaine 60-80mg triamcinolone. Of these 23 patients, 21 were available for clinical review and completed a questionnaire giving their assessment of the effect of the infiltration of the ganglion impar block and/or caudal block. Results. Good results were obtained in 16 of the 21 patients with coccydynia due to trauma. In five patients the results were moderate or poor, although none described worse pain after the operation. They are no complications after the infiltration. Conclusion. Ganglion impar block and/or caudal block offered satisfactory relief of pain in the majority of patients regardless of the cause of their symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Cerrillo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmerón Vélez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quirante Pizarro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jerez Collado, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortiñas Sáenz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Colomo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La coccigodinia es un término referido al dolor en la región del cóccix. La mayor parte de casos se asocian a una movilidad anormal del cóccix que puede provocar un proceso crónico inflamatorio que conduce a la degeneración de esta estructura. El tratamiento conservador debe ser de elección en este cuadro, y puede consistir en terapias manuales (masajes, estiramiento, manipulación y postural) inyecciones locales de esteroides o anestésicos. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de una cohorte histórica de 23 pacientes con clínica de coccigodinia traumática sin respuesta a tratamiento médico. Se trataron con infiltración del ganglio impar y/o bloqueo caudal con lidocaina 1% y triancinolona 60-80mg bajo control radioscópico. De estos 23 pacientes, 21 estaban disponibles y completaron un cuestionario de evaluación del efecto de la infiltración del ganglio impar el bloque y/o el bloque caudal. Resultados. Se consideraron excelentes los resultados obtenidos en 16 de los 21 pacientes con coccigodinia traumática. En cinco pacientes los resultados eran moderados o pobres, aunque ninguno describiera aumento o empeoramiento del dolor después de las infiltraciones. El procedimiento no se asoció a complicaciones mayores. Conclusión. El bloqueo del ganglio impar y/o el bloqueo caudal conllevó un control del dolor coccígeo en la mayoría de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);55(5): 340-345, sept.-oct. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infiltración del ganglio impar y caudal en el manejo de la coccigodinia traumática rebelde al tratamiento analgésico convencional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8577^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8577^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d774^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d774^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8188^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3079^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3079^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
