<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-65024</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-9476</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The medical diagnosis or comes dice by the doctor who sends to our unit, and is a renal or ureteral litiasis and its different locations. But the diagnosis nurse is very different other, because it is based as opposed to on the conduct of the patient the disease and to the treatment, and in other factors that influence negatively or have the possibility detrimentally of affecting the obtaining of an optimal result of the treatment of shock waves. So that the infirmary performances are carried out by means of a scientific method and the result of the possible most effective treatment, it is necessary to make at first the identification of the alterations that presents the patient, that is to say, make a diagnosis. Later to describe the performances that are due to carry out according to the diagnoses, and finally to make a valuation of the obtained results. Thus, making the scientific method by means of the NANDA, the NIC and the NOC we will make the following diagnoses and performances (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Revueltas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Rodríguez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Cordero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El diagnóstico médico ya nos viene dado por el médico que lo remite a nuestra unidad, y es el de litiasis renal o ureteral y sus distintas localizaciones. Pero el diagnóstico enfermero es otro muy distinto, pues se basa en la conducta del paciente frente a la enfermedad y al tratamiento, y en otros factores que influyen negativamente o tienen la posibilidad de afectar perjudicialmente a la obtención de un resultado óptimo del tratamiento de ondas de choque. Para que las actuaciones de enfermería sean llevadas a cabo mediante un método científico y el resultado del tratamiento sea lo más eficaz posible, hay que hacer en un principio la identificación de las alteraciones que presenta el paciente, es decir, hacer un diagnóstico. Para posteriormente describir las actuaciones que se deben llevar a cabo según los diagnósticos, y finalmente hacer una valoración de los resultados obtenidos. Así, realizando el método científico mediante la NANDA, el NIC y el NOC, haremos los siguientes diagnósticos y actuaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>ENFURO: Rev. Asoc. Esp. A.T.S. Urol;(100): 30-34, oct.-dic. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-65024</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d19270^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19612^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24370^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
