<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74757</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lateral arm flap in oral cavity reconstruction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The availability of easily pliable skin hasallowed the functional reconstruction of oral cavity defects. Althoughthe radial forearm free flap is the most frequently used flap for thereconstruction of surface defects of the oral cavity, the lateral armfree flap may be preferable in some situations.Objectives. The aim of the present paper is to show the advantagesand disadvantages and our indications and results for the lateralarm flap in intraoral reconstruction.Material and methods. This is a prospective work on the use of thelateral arm free flap for the reconstruction of oral cavity defects afterablative surgery. The parameters that have been evaluated are: flapviability, morbidity in the donor site, length of the pedicle, selectionof recipient vessels, complications and functional results in thereconstructed area.Results. The lateral arm flap has been used in primary reconstructionafter ablative surgery for squamous cell carcinoma of the oral cavityin ten patients. One flap was lost because of venous thrombosis.The donor site was repaired by direct closure in 8 cases and a splitthickness skin graft had to be used in 2 cases. Mean pedicle lengthwas 8.75 cm. In 9 cases a favorable functional result was achieved.Conclusions. Fasciocutaneous lateral arm flap allows thereconstruction of oral cavity defects achieving good functional results.Morbidity in the donor site is minimal and, in most cases, directclosure permits the repair of the donor site(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alamillos Granados, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dean Ferrer, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz Masera, J. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrios Sánchez, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Corpas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García de Marcos, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Camacho, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La posibilidad de emplear una piel fácilmenteplegable ha permitido reconstruir defectos de la cavidad oral consiguiendouna gran funcionalidad. Aunque el colgajo radial es el colgajo que se utilizacon más frecuencia para reconstruir defectos de superficie de la cavidad oral,el colgajo lateral de brazo puede ser de elección en algunas situaciones.Objetivos. El objetivo del presente trabajo es mostrar las ventajas e inconvenientesy nuestras indicaciones y resultados del colgajo lateral de brazo enreconstrucción de defectos de la cavidad oral.Material y método. Se trata de un estudio prospectivo sobre la utilización delcolgajo lateral de brazo en la reconstrucción de defectos de la cavidad oraltras cirugía ablativa. Se ha valorado: la viabilidad del colgajo, la morbilidaddel lecho donante, la longitud del pedículo, la selección de vasos receptores,las complicaciones y los resultados funcionales de la zona reconstruida.Resultados. Hemos utilizado el colgajo lateral de brazo en 10 pacientes enreconstrucciones primarias tras cirugía ablativa por carcinoma epidermoidede la cavidad oral. Hubo un caso de necrosis por trombosis venosa. El defectodonante se cerró en 8 casos de modo directo y en 2 con un injerto librede espesor parcial. La longitud media del pedículo ha sido de 8,75 cm. En 9casos el resultado funcional de los pacientes ha sido satisfactorio.Conclusiones. El colgajo fasciocutáneo lateral de brazo permite la reconstrucciónde la cavidad oral consiguiendo buenos resultados funcionales. Ademásla morbilidad de la zona donante es mínima y puede realizarse cierredirecto del defecto cutáneo del brazo en la mayoría de los casos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;30(4): 246-254, jul.-ago. 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74757</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colgajo lateral de brazo en reconstrucción de la cavidad oral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33572^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9247^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
