<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81584</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-6157</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In many patients the aesthetics on the smile are seriously determined because they show excessive gingiva when they smile or have short clinics crowns. This can be because many factors and one of themis the altered passive eruption. The altered passive eruption, also called Delayed passive eruption, happens when the gingival margin is not incisal or occlusaly adequate positioned, in the adult anatomic crown and is not approach to the cement enamel junction. This report shows a case of altered passive eruption where the aesthetics play an important role. We achieved give a harmonious smile to the patient at the end of the surgical treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estela Fabra, Norma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nart, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís, Carols</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Violant, Deborah</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La estética en la sonrisa de muchos pacientes está condicionada. Son pacientes que muestran mucha encía al sonreír y/o poseen coronas clínicas cortas, lo cual se puede deber a múltiples factores, siendo uno de ellos la erupción pasiva alterada. La erupción pasiva alterada, también conocida como erupción pasiva retardada, ocurre cuando el margen gingival se encuentra incisal uoclusalmente mal colocado, en la corona anatómica del adulto y no se aproxima a la unión cemento-esmalte. En este artículo mostramos un caso de EPA en el cual la estética juega un papel importante. Y se logra al final del tratamiento quirúrgico proporcionarle a la paciente una sonrisa armoniosa (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Dentum (Barc.);8(4): 145-148, oct.-dic. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81584</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Alargamiento de corona por erupción pasiva alterada. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30169^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200812</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
