<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99708</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prenatal neuroprotection in preterm neonates. A proposal made by a tertiary hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several recent studies provide evidence that the use of magnesium sulfate as a prenatal neuroprotector administered in imminent preterm delivery reduces the risk of severe neurologic sequelae in newborns. Clinical guidelines from various countries support the implementation of these neuroprotective therapies. The present study provides a review of the problem and of the pertinent literature and describes a protocol for neuroprotection that attempts to reduce neurological morbidity in preterm newborns by using a treatment with proven effectiveness. At the same time we invite other hospitals to join our proposal, contribute improvements, and participate in multicenter studies that would allow us to evaluate in a timely manner the results of this protocol by comparing them with data published in the literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blasco Alonso, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo Zurita, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Arana, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrera Peral, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Mesa, Ernesto</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diversos trabajos publicados en últimos años apoyan que el uso del sulfato de magnesio como neuroprotector antenatal administrado ante la inminencia de un parto pretérmino reduce el riesgo de padecer severas secuelas neurológicas en los recién nacidos. Guías clínicas de actuación de diversos países apoyan la instauración de estos tratamientos neuroprotectores. En nuestro trabajo haremos una revisión del problema, de la bibliografía al respecto y realizaremos una propuesta metódica de un protocolo de neuroprotección dirigido a intentar reducir la morbilidad neurológica de los nacidos pretérmino con una terapia que ya ha demostrado su efectividad. Al mismo tiempo, invitamos a diferentes hospitales a sumarse a nuestra propuesta aportando elementos de mejora y participando en estudios multicéntricos que nos permitan evaluar en un tiempo razonable los resultados de esta actuación cotejándolos con los publicados hasta ahora en la literatura (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);55(4): 165-172, abr. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99708</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neuroprotección antenatal en recién nacidos pretérmino. Propuesta de un centro terciario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38640^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11731^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8453^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10541^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2587^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22228^s22014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28634^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201204</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
