<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164176</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mycobacterium bovis lymphadenitis, an entity to consider</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cattle control measures and milk products pasteurization have made Mycobacterium bovis disease uncommon in our environment. The diagnosis of this disease requires a high index of suspicion based on a detailed medical history and appropriate laboratory tests. Extrapulmonary cases are the main presentation, especially lymphadenitis, for this reason, is recommended to refer to study all the adenopathies with poor evolution, for evaluating de need of a fine-needle aspiration for citologý examination and culture. We report the case of M. bovis lymphadenitis in a 7-year-old girl with adequate response to medical treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Herranz Aguirre, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urriza Ripa, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urriza Yeregui, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñafiel-Freire, DM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Resano Abarzuza, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Niyubahwe, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las medidas de control del ganado y la pasteurización de los productos lácteos han hecho que la enfermedad tuberculosa por Mycobacterium bovis sea infrecuente en nuestro medio. El diagnóstico de esta entidad requiere un alto índice de sospecha, fundado en una historia clínica detallada y pruebas complementarias oportunas. La presentación más frecuente es extrapulmonar, principalmente como linfadenitis, por lo que ante una adenopatía de mala evolución se recomienda remitir al paciente para estudio y valorar la realización de punción aspiración con aguja fina para examen citológico y cultivo. Presentamos un caso de linfadenitis por M. bovis en una niña de siete años que respondió adecuadamente al tratamiento médico (AU9</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;19(74): 147-150, abr.-jun. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164176</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Linfadenitis por Mycobacterium bovis, una entidad a tener en cuenta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8376^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5069^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6250^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9356^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d999^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9356^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24244^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6250^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8376^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
