<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044434</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Malignant glaucoma following combined Ahmed valve implant and phacoemulsification surgery for chronic angle-closure glaucoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Case report: Simultaneous Ahmed valve implant, combined with phacoemulsification cataract surgery, is a useful therapeutic option for patients with chronic angle-closure glaucoma, when conventional filtering surgery fails. This combined approach permits both control of intraocular pressure and early recovery of visual function. We report the results in five patients successfully treated with this combined procedure, two of whom developed early postoperative malignant glaucoma. Discussion: Predisposing anatomic features in patients with chronic angle-closure glaucoma, associated with sudden anterior chamber decompression and increased postoperative inflammation, may facilitate the development of malignant glaucoma following combined glaucoma implant and phacoemulsification surgery</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Sánchez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Feijoó, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrosa, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-de-la-Casa, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pablo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: La cirugía combinada de facoemulsificación con implante valvular de Ahmed es una opción terapéutica útil en pacientes con glaucoma crónico por cierre angular, cuando la cirugía filtrante convencional fracasa. Este abordaje combinado permite tanto el control de la presión intraocular como la temprana recuperación de la función visual. Se presentan los resultados en cinco pacientes tratados con éxito con este procedimiento combinado, dos de los cuales desarrollaron un glaucoma maligno en el postoperatorio inmediato.Discusión: Las características anatómicas predisponentes en los pacientes con glaucoma crónico por cierre angular asociado a la descompresión súbita de la cámara anterior y a una mayor inflamación postoperatoria facilitan la aparición del glaucoma maligno en las cirugías combinadas de implante de drenaje y facoemulsificación</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;80(11): 667-670, nov. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044434</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Glaucoma maligno tras cirugía combinada de implante valvular de Ahmed y facoemulsificación en el tratamiento del glaucoma crónico por cierre angular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24698^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32652^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33880^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200511</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
