<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-19995</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ischemic stroke: transesophageal echocardiographic findings</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Since its initial application in 1976, the transesophageal echocardiogram (TEE) has improved the detection of cardiovascular emboligenic sources. Even though its indication in patients with stroke is still controversial, its use has contributed to the identification of potential embolic stroke sources. Objective. To describe the transesophageal echocardiographic findings in ischemic stroke patients. Patients and methods. We analyzed case-series of 162 TEE performed on a total of 576 ischemic events dated between 01/01/99 to 01/05/01. The required information was collected prospectively in the Stroke Data Bank of the Neurology Department at Policlínico Bancario in Buenos Aires. Results. TEE was carried out in 162 (28.1%) cases. Of theses cases 13% belonged to the clinical subtype TACI, 37% to PACI, 17% to POCI, and 37% to LACI subtype. Pathologic findings corresponded to cardiac level: spontaneous contrast in 29% of the cases, and to aortic level: plaques grade IV in 34% and debris in 13% of the cases. According to the etiology of ischemic stroke, 67 patients had been registered under the diagnosis of lacunar infarct (60 in the anterior region and 7 in the posterior region), 93 had been diagnosed medium and grand artery infarct (73 in the anterior region and 29 in the posterior region), and 2 had remained unclassified. Emboligenic sources were found in 69.5% of TACI, 65% of PACI, 52% of POCI, and 53% of LACI. Conclusions. A high percentage of aortic artheroembolic pathology was detected in the population under study. However, spontaneous contrast was the echocardiographic phenomenon more frequently reported. It is to be pointed out the presence of potential cardiac and/or aortic emboligenic sources in 48% of the population with lacunar infarct (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>César Viguera</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Desde su aplicación inicial en 1976, el ecocardiograma transesofágico (ETE) ha mejorado la detección de fuentes embolígenas (FE) cardiovasculares. Si bien su indicación en pacientes con accidente cerebrovascular (ACV) es todavía controvertida, su utilización ha contribuido a la identificación de fuentes potenciales de ACV embólico. Objetivo. Describir hallazgos por ETE en pacientes con ACV isquémico. Pacientes y métodos. Se analizaron en un diseño de casos en serie, 162 ETE realizados sobre un total de 576 eventos isquémicos ocurridos entre 01/01/99 y 01/05/01. La información se recolectó en forma prospectiva en la Base de Datos de ACV del Servicio de Neurología del Policlínico Bancario de Buenos Aires. Resultados. Se realizó ETE en 162 (28,1 por ciento) casos del total de eventos asistidos. Se presentaron con subtipo clínico TACI (13 por ciento), PACI (37 por ciento), POCI (17 por ciento), LACI (37 por ciento). Los hallazgos patológicos fueron: cardíacos, contraste espontáneo (29 por ciento); aórticos, placas grado IV (34 por ciento), debris (13 por ciento). De acuerdo con la etiología del ACV, 67 pacientes se habían registrado con el diagnóstico de infarto lacunar (60 del territorio anterior y siete del posterior), 93 como infartos de mediana y gran arteria (73 del territorio anterior y 20 del posterior), y dos no clasificables. Se encontró FE en TACI (69,5 por ciento), PACI (65 por ciento), POCI (52 por ciento), LACI (53 por ciento). Conclusión. En la población estudiada se identificó un alto porcentaje de patología ateroembólica aórtica. Sin embargo, el contraste espontáneo fue el fenómeno ecocardiográfico más frecuentemente informado. Hay que resaltar la presencia de potenciales FE, cardíaca o aórtica, en el 48 por ciento de la población con infarto lacunar  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;36(4): 330-334, feb. 2003. graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Accidente cerebrovascular isquémico: hallazgos en ecocardiograma transesofágico</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Lourido, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Melcón, CM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubachin, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gestro, DH</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parisi, VL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rotta Escalante, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Curatolo, LM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carosella, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Lynch, MF</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-19995</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2585</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31496</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
