<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125298</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for the safety preparation of sterile medicines in medical wards</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To develop a recommendations guide about the preparation of sterile medicines in medical wards, and to figure out the current situation of different Spanish hospitals, regarding the preparation of sterile medicines outside the pharmacy. Methods: The autors reviewed the available international guidelines in order to summarize the main quality recommendations. To know about the current situation in Spanish hospitals, a 30 questions survey was designed and spread to 500 different hospitals. Answers were analysed with Survey monkey® platform in the period February-July 2012.Results: Based on the literature review, the authors agreed a recommendations list for the safe preparation of sterile medicines in medical wards, which was structured in 8 sections. Regarding the survey results, 8.4% of the hospitals answered, showing a great variability among centres in the quality requirements for sterile compounding outside the pharmacy. It should be pointed out the lack of assigned areas for drug preparation in wards, the lack of protocols to discern which kind of medicines can be compounded inwards as well as the poor recommendations about garment and aseptic (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López Cabezas, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Salom, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales Cabrera, Ana M. Martín de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávila Pousa, Carmela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Herreros, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pernía López, M. Sagrario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano Blázquez, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila Clérigues, M. Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Elaborar una guía de recomendaciones de preparación de medicamentos estériles en las unidades de enfermería, así como averiguar la situación actual de las condiciones de preparación en distintos hospitales españoles mediante una encuesta. Material y métodos: Se llevó a cabo una revisión bibliográfica de las recomendaciones internacionales publicadas y se elaboró un check-list de criterios de calidad. Para conocer la situación actual en los hospitales españoles, se diseñó una encuesta on-line de 30 preguntas dirigida al personal de enfermería que se ha difundido a 500 centros hospitalarios. Las respuestas auto cumplimentadas en el periodo de estudio (Febrero-Junio 2012), se analizaron con la aplicación Survey monkey®.Resultados: En base a la revisión, los autores consensuaron un listado de recomendaciones para la preparación segura de medicamentos estériles en unidades de enfermería, estructurado en 8 apartados. En cuanto a los resultados dela encuesta, respondieron un 8,4% de los centros, mostrando gran variabilidad en los requerimientos de calidad para la preparación de estériles en las plantas. Es destacable la ausencia de zonas designadas para la preparación en las (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;38(1): 57-64, ene.-feb. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125298</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones para la preparación de medicamentos estériles en las unidades de enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4403^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23106</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10797^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4401^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
