<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143903</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Description of Patients Undergoing Mohs Surgery in Spain: Initial Report on Data From the Spanish Registry of Mohs Surgery (REGESMOHS)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The Spanish registry of Mohs micrographic surgery started collecting data in July 2013. The aim of the registry is to report on the use of this technique in Spain and the outcomes achieved. In the present article, we describe the characteristics of patients and the tumors treated. Material and methods: This is a prospective cohort study of patients treated with Mohs micrographic surgery. The participating centers are hospitals where at least one intervention of this type is performed each week. All patients considered for Mohs micrographic surgery in participating centers are included in the registry except those who have been declared legally incompetent. Results: Between July 2013 and October 2014, data from 655 patients were included in the registry. The most common tumor involved was basal cell carcinoma, and the most common histological subtype was infiltrative basal cell carcinoma. Most of the tumors treated were located on the face or scalp, and the most common site was the nose. Almost 40% of the tumors treated were recurrent or persistent, and preoperative tumor size was similar to that reported in other European studies and in Australia. In total, 45.5% of patients had received previous surgical treatment. Conclusion: The findings are similar to those reported in other studies, and the data collected are useful for assessing whether the results of studies carried out elsewhere are applicable in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Estebaranz, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Redondo Bellón, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén Barona, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Doval, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ciudad Blanco, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barchino Ortiz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanmartín-Jiménez, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Allende Markixana, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcés, JR</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manubens-Mercadé, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toll-Abelló, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>De Eusebio Murillo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Jiménez, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfaro Rubio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Alonso, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Diez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Veiga, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Salas, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Prieto, MÁ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miñano Medrano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En julio de 2013 se inició la recogida de datos del registro español de cirugía micrográfica de Mohs, que describe la aplicación y los resultados de esta técnica en España. En este artículo se describen las características del paciente y de los tumores tratados. Material y métodos: Se trata de un estudio de cohortes prospectivo en el que participan centros en los que se practica al menos una intervención semanal de cirugía micrográfica de Mohs. En cada centro se incluyen todos los pacientes que son valorados para realizar cirugía de Mohs, excepto los declarados judicialmente incapaces. En este artículo describimos las características de los pacientes y los tumores incluidos en la cohorte. Resultados: El número de pacientes incluidos desde julio de 2013 hasta octubre de 2014 es de 655. La mayoría de los tumores cutáneos intervenidos correspondieron a carcinoma basocelular, siendo el infiltrante el subtipo histológico más frecuente. La mayoría de las cirugías se practicaron en tumores localizados en la cara y el cuero cabelludo, siendo la localización más frecuente la nariz. Casi el 40% de los tumores operados son recurrentes o persistentes, y el tamaño tumoral prequirúrgico es similar en nuestro medio al descrito en otros estudios australianos o europeos. Hasta el 45,5% de los pacientes había recibido algún tratamiento quirúrgico previo. Conclusión: Los datos observados son similares a los de otras series publicadas, y son relevantes para poder valorar la aplicabilidad en nuestro contexto de estudios realizados en otros medios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;106(7): 562-568, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143903</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Descripción de los pacientes intervenidos mediante cirugía de Mohs en España. Datos basales del registro español de cirugía de Mohs (REGESMOHS)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29051^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31401^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31401^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31401^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31401^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28210^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2323^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29051^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28210^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29051^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
