<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128826</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cutaneous Infection with Alternaria triticina in a Bilateral Lung Transplant Recipient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a 60-year-old man who was receiving immunosuppressive therapy for a bilateral lung transplant and presented with a crusted, violaceous plaque on the left hand. Based on histopathology and microbiological culture the patient was diagnosed with infection by Alternaria species. Treatment with itraconazole led to complete resolution of the skin lesion. Forty months later he developed four reddish, nodular, skin lesions on the left leg. Analysis of a biopsy from one of these lesions using histopathologic and molecular techniques identified a mold that shared 98% homology with a strain of Alternaria triticina. Alternaria species belong to a group of dematiaceous fungi that cause opportunistic infections in humans. The incidence of these infections is increasing, mainly in transplant centers. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first reported case of a human infection caused by A. triticina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-Vela, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Val-Bernal, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Armesto, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Unda-Villafuerte, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un hombre de 60 años en tratamiento inmunosupresor por un trasplante pulmonar bilateral que presentó una placa violácea costrosa en la mano. Se diagnosticó de infección por Alternaria spp mediante estudio histopatológico y cultivo microbiológico. El tratamiento con itraconazol condujo a la resolución completa de la lesión cutánea. Cuarenta meses más tarde el paciente desarrolló 4 lesiones nodulares rojizas en la pierna izquierda. Las muestras obtenidas de una de las lesiones fueron estudiadas mediante histopatología y técnicas moleculares. La secuencia de ADN que se obtuvo del germen causal mostraba una homología del 98% con una cepa de Alternaria triticina. Las especies de Alternaria forman parte del grupo de hongos que componen las feohifomicosis susceptibles de causar infecciones oportunísticas humanas. La incidencia de estas infecciones está aumentando, sobre todo en centros de trasplante. De acuerdo con nuestra información el presente caso es el primero en el que A. triticina es causante de una infección humana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;105(8): e51-e54, oct. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Infección cutánea por Alternaria triticina en un paciente con trasplante bilateral de pulmón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36513^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8348^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
