<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156974</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Healthcare information retrieval through CUIDEN®</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This fourth article of the series &#145;Update in the search for scientific information&#146; is focused on the CUIDEN® database, managed by the Index Foundation, and considered one of the essential information tools in order to be updated about the scientific developments within the Ibero-American area in terms of healthcare and clinical practice in all its specialties. This database has a free access option under the Registered User mode, CUIDEN®, and another option of access by subscription, CUIDEN® Plus. The objective of this article is to describe the main characteristics and features of this tool, through its different search options: simple, advanced, and by key words. Besides, the differences between the free and the subscription versions are highlighted, so that the user can take into account their specific limitations and advantages at the time of initiating a search for information (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sánchez, Alicia Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero Gómez, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este cuarto artículo de la serie &#145;Puesta al día en la búsqueda de información científica&#146; se centra en la base de datos CUIDEN®. Está gestionada por la Fundación Index y es considerada como una de las herramientas de información fundamentales para estar al día sobre la producción científica generada en el espacio iberoamericano sobre cuidados en salud y temática clínico-asistencial en todas sus especialidades. La base de datos tiene una opción de acceso gratuito bajo modalidad de usuario registrado, CUIDEN®, y otra opción de acceso bajo suscripción, CUIDEN® Plus. El objetivo de este artículo es describir las principales características y funcionalidades de esta herramienta a través de las distintas opciones de búsqueda simple, avanzada y por palabras clave. Además, se destacan las diferencias entre la versión gratuita y la de suscripción, de modo que el usuario pueda tener en cuenta las limitaciones y ventajas de una y otra a la hora de afrontar una búsqueda de información (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;19(7): 65-69, sept. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156974</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La recuperación de información de cuidados a través de Cuiden®</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50230</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28904^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23591^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28994^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
