<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118902</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychopatologic symptoms in Spanish adolescents: relationship with perceived parental styles and self-esteem</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this research was to study the presence of psychopathologic symptoms in a community sample of 935 Spanish adolescents, and its relationship with perceived parental styles and the self-esteem. Numbers of males and females were 489 and 446, respectively. Age ranged from 12 to 18 years (M = 14.84, SD = 1.83). Fourteen High School centers in Murcia and Castilla-La Mancha agreed to participate in the current study. Five of them were randomly selected to collected data. The results showed age-related differences in all variables (the psychopathologic symptoms, self-esteem and perceived parental styles). On the other hand, females showed less psychopathologic symptoms and better perception of parental styles than males. Significant negative correlations were found between self-esteem, psychopathology and some positive dimensions of parental style. The main predictors of adolescent&#146;s mental health were: self-esteem, age, gender, revelation and affect from father and psychological control of mother (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Alcázar, Ana I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosa-Alcázar, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parada-Navas, José L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de esta investigación fue analizar la sintomatología psicopatológica evaluada con el SCL-90-R en una muestra comunitaria de 935 adolescentes españoles y su interacción con el estilo parental percibido y la autoestima. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 489 chicos y 446 chicas de edades comprendidas entre los 12 y 18 años (M = 14.84, DT = 1.83) que cursaban estudios de Educación Secundaria y Bachillerato. Catorce centros de la Región de Murcia y Castilla-La Mancha aceptaron participar en el estudio. De éstos, fueron seleccionados al azar siete teniendo en cuenta la titularidad de los centros (pública y concertada). Los resultados indicaron la existencia de diferencias debidas a la edad en todas las variables medidas (síntomas psicopatológicos, autoestima y percepción de los estilos educativos parentales). Las mujeres presentaron menos niveles de sintomatología y mejor percepción de los estilos educativos. Los resultados de los análisis correlacionales confirmaron relaciones significativas y negativas entre auto-estima y síntomas psicopatológicos y entre algunas dimensiones positivas de los estilos educativos. Los predictores más relevantes y de mayor peso en la salud psicológica fueron: autoestima, edad, sexo, revelación y afecto del padre y control psicológico de la madre (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;30(1): 133-142, ene.-abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118902</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas psicopatológicos en adolescentes españoles: relación con los estilos parentales percibidos y la autoestima</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d297^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
