<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95463</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Basis for the clinical management of fire smoke poisoning &#147;Docohumo Madrid 2010&#148;</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">AbstractPoisoning by smoke is the main cause of morbidity and mortality in fires. Smoke is a mixture of carbonaceous particles suspended in hot air and toxic gases. Of these, carbon monoxide (CO) and primarily hydrocyanic acid (CNH), are those that provoke tissue anoxia.AbstractThe clinical manifestations of smoke poisoning are variables. Some of the potential manifestations could be: eye irritation, sore throat, laryngeal stridor, dysphagia, carbonaceous sputum, cough, dyspnea, laryngospasm, bronchospasm, coronary syndrome, coma, hypoxemia, lactic acidosis, cyanosis and death. In the assessment of these patients the presence of soot in the nose, mouth or sputum suggests serious poisoning. Lactate levels higher than 10mmol/L indicates levels of cyanide major than 40micromole/L. The pulse co-oximetry has assumed an important step forward for the diagnosis, appraisal and monitoring of these patients.AbstractIn the treatment it will be essential to assess the need of an early intubation. The administration of oxygen to the 100% will be essential. As an antidote to the cyanide, the first-choice is the hydroxocobalamin. Its administration has to be early. Its administration criteria are: patient who has inhaled smoke (remnants of soot in the mouth, pharynx or sputum) and has neurological disorder (confusion, coma, agitation, seizures) and also presents one of the following circumstances: bradypnea, respiratory arrest, cardiorespiratory arrest, shock, hypotension, lactate &amp;#8805;8mmol/L or lactic acidosis. Logically, the rest of the management will be conventional depending on symptoms or complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández Frutos,  M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puiguriguer, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burillo Putze, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bajo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer,  A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Climent, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dueñas-Laita, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Felices, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nogué, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ResumenLa intoxicación por humo es la principal causa de morbimortalidad en los incendios. El humo es una mezcla de partículas carbonáceas suspendidas en aire caliente y gases tóxicos. De todos ellos, el monóxido carbono (CO) y fundamentalmente el ácido cianhídrico (CNH) son los que van a provocar la anoxia tisular.ResumenLas manifestaciones clínicas de la intoxicación por humo son variables. Algunas de las manifestaciones potenciales podrían ser: irritación ocular, dolor de garganta, estridor laríngeo, disfagia, esputo carbonáceo, tos, disnea, laringoespasmo, broncoespasmo, síndrome coronario, coma, hipoxemia, acidosis láctica, cianosis y muerte. En la evaluación de estos enfermos la presencia de hollín en nariz, boca o esputo sugiere intoxicación grave. Niveles de lactato superiores a 10mmol/l indican cifras de cianuro mayores de 40micromol/l. La pulsicooximetría ha supuesto un avance importante para el diagnóstico, valoración y seguimiento de estos pacientes.ResumenEn el tratamiento será indispensable valorar la necesidad de una intubación temprana. La administración de oxígeno al 100% será esencial. Como antídoto para el cianuro, el de primera elección es la hidroxicobalamina. Su administración ha de ser precoz. Los criterios de administración son: paciente que ha inhalado humo (restos de hollín en boca, faringe o esputo) y que tenga alteraciones neurológicas (confusión, coma, agitación, convulsiones) y además presenta una de las siguiente circunstancias: bradipnea, parada respiratoria, parada cardiorrespiratoria, shock, hipotensión, láctato &amp;#8805;8mmol/l o acidosis láctica. Logicamente el resto del manejo será convencional en función de síntomas o complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);34(9): 609-619, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95463</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bases del manejo clínico de la intoxicación por humo de incendios «Docohumo Madrid 2010»</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d938^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3506^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23831</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2288^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2091</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7033^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13287^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
