<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96210</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The occupational role of dental conditions among a consecutive sample of Spanish workers</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To assess the occupational impact of the mouth in terms of days of work loss in the last year and theperception of the working performance disturbance because of the oral conditions.Study design. A consecutive sample (n=269) of the Regional Government staff of the province of Granada (Spain) wasrecruited. Participants were asked about work loss related to health problems in the past 12 months, capturing the aetiologicalentities, the frequency of the work absent and the total days loss. Also subjects reported if they believed that mouth affectstheir occupational performance, and if they have perceived difficulties for carrying out work because of the mouth. Data onsociodemographic, behavioural and clinical factors were also gathered. Chi-squared test, Odds ratio (OR) and relative risk(RR) of perceived occupational role were used to quantify the effect of the modulating factors.Results. Almost 40% of individuals were absent from work during the last year spending on average 5.4 days forrecovering. Colds and musculoskeletal pathology were the major causes of sick leave. Dental disease caused short workabsences (4 days on average) only in 2.8% of participants. However most of workers (62.5%) considered mouth to influencetheir occupational performance, mainly because of the pain-related events (61.7%), but only 4.1% of workers reporteddifficulties in carrying out their work in the past 12 months. Females (RR=1.3), participants attending regular dental visits(RR=1.4) and denture wearers (RR=2.5) were shown to have significantly higher risk of perceiving an occupational role ofthe mouth. Those workers reporting that mouth influences their work have significantly poorer oral health than counterparts.Conclusions. Most workers considered that mouth influences their occupational performance but dental disease hasdemonstrated to be a minor occupational cause of sick leave in terms of prevalence and magnitude of work loss(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clemot, Y</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bravo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Valverde, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resultados. Casi el 40% de los participantes declararon haber perdido días de trabajo durante el último año, siendo laduración media de las bajas de 5,4 días. Las principales causas de baja fueron resfriados y patología musculoesquelética. Lasenfermedades dentales produjeron bajas de corta duración (4 días de media) sólo en el 2,8% de los participantes. Sin embargo,la mayoría de los trabajadores (62,5%) consideraban que estas dolencias influenciarían sobre la realización de su trabajo,principalmente por los eventos relacionados con el dolor (61,7%), aunque sólo el 4,1% de los trabajadores refirierondificultades para realizar su trabajo durante los últimos 12 meses. Las mujeres (RR=1,3), los trabajadores que acudían deforma regular a revisiones dentales (RR=1.4) y los trabajadores con dentadura postiza (RR=2,5) mostraron una probabilidadsignificativamente mayor de percibir el impacto de las afecciones orales sobre el trabajo. Los trabajadores que percibían lainfluencia de estas dolencias sobre el trabajo mostraron una salud oral significativamente peor que la del resto.Conclusiones. La mayoría de los trabajadores consideraban que las afecciones orales pueden influir sobre la realizacióndel trabajo, pero en nuestra muestra sólo una mínima parte de las bajas laborales se relacionaban con enfermedades dentales,tanto en términos de frecuencia como de días de trabajo perdidos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);15(1): 30-31, ene.-mar. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96210</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de las condiciones dentales sobre el trabajo en una muestra consecutiva de trabajadores españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9252^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28452</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201203</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
