<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85054</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Searching for legal information in occupational medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Medicine and Law,are branches of knowledge that, rather than being independent of each other, are increasingly interconnected.This affects all medical specialties, but is especially relevant in Occupational Medicine, given its highly regulatednature within a broad legal framework, where on a daily basis the occupational physician participates in administrativeissues that will later have legal relevance. It is necessary, therefore, for occupational physicians to familiarize themselveswith searches of the legal literature and related databases, in a manner similar to how they search the medical literatureusing databases such as the prestigious PubMed(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torres Alberich, José Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente-Herrero, M. Teofila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López González, Ángel Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Medicina y el Derecho son ramas del conocimiento que, lejos de caminar de una forma independiente, son cadavez materias más interconectadas. Este hecho, que en Medicina afecta a cualquiera de las especialidades médicas, es deespecial trascendencia en Medicina del Trabajo puesto que es la única especialidad regulada en su composición y funcionamientopor un amplio marco legislativo y donde el profesional de la medicina toma parte día a día en actuaciones administrativasde relevancia jurídica posterior. Conviene pues familiarizarse con la búsqueda jurídica y jurisprudencial enMedicina del Trabajo a través de los portales jurídicos con acceso a bases de datos, como ya se hace de forma habitual enla búsqueda bibliométrica y bibliográfi ca a través de los portales médicos, entre los que sin duda es PubMed el referente(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);13(2): 94-97, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85054</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La búsqueda jurídica y jurisprudencial de apoyo en Medicina del Trabajo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7772</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33619^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9972^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
