<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74871</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-0316</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The polytraumatic patient is, beyond all doubt, an important problem in public health. Every year people have thousands of accidents from which many people get permanently injured or may even die. The emergency care of this kind of patient should be effective and conducted by a team trained in emergency situations. Objectives: 1) To show and to describe the polytraumatic patient's profile; 2) to unify the professionals' viewpoint in the polytraumatic patient's care; and 3) to update de polytraumatic patient's protocol. Materials and methods: Observational prospective analysis from January to April 2007 from 26 polytraumatic patients performed shortly after the trauma. Results: The participants were 19 male and 7 female (median 23 years). The average time in Emergency Department was 3,9 hours. Approximately 75% of them were assisted by the Prehospital Emergency Care. The traffic accident by two-wheeled vehicles were 32%. The presence of a traumatic head injury was 50%. The interhospitalary transfer was 40% and the Hospital Vall d'Hebron was our reference center. About 0,3% of the patients died in the Fundación Hospital Asil de Granollers. Conclusions: The profile of the patient treated in the Fundación Hospital Asil de Granollers was a young male (19-25 years) with a traumatic head, thoracic and extremities injury. The most common accident mechanism was a motorcycle accident and all of them received treatment at the accident site. The length of primary hospital stay was 3,9 hours and after that, the patients were transferred and followed up in the Hospital Vall d'Hebron in Barcelona. It's important to put in place an interdisciplinary protocol for the activation and care of the polytraumatic patient, and reviewing the 1996 protocol is a good way to start(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tolosa, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araya Cruz, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maciá Pajares, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Jiménez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mora Acosta, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seda, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rozas, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: 1) Presentar y describir el perfil y los procedimientos llevados a cabo en los pacientes que acuden al Servicio de Urgencias con criterio de activación del protocolo de paciente politraumatizado; 2) unificar los criterios de actuación de todos los profesionales que intervienen en la asistencia para acelerar la atención inicial, diagnóstico y tratamiento de los mismos; 3) conocer qué técnicas, pruebas y actuaciones que se realizan con mayor frecuencia en un paciente politraumatizado; y 4) actualizar el protocolo de actuación al paciente politraumatizado existente en el centro desde 1996. Material y método: Se ha realizado un estudio observacional prospectivo en el que se incluyeron a 26 pacientes visitados en el Servicio de Urgencias con criterio de activación del protocolo de politrauma durante los meses de enero a abril de 2007. Se analizaron las siguientes variables: filiación, edad, sexo, atención prehospitalaria, tiempos de actuación, maniobras extra- e intrahospitalarias, constantes vitales, mecanismos lesionales, derivaciones y destinos, pruebas complementarias, tipos de traumatismos y medicación. Resultado: Se visitaron un total de 19 hombres y 7 mujeres, con una media de edad de 23 años y una permanencia en Urgencias de 3,9 horas. El 75% de los pacientes fue asistido por el equipo de Extrahospitalaria. El 32% de los accidentes sucedió en vehículos de 2 ruedas. El 50% presentaba TCE (traumatismo craneoencefálico). El 40% fue derivado al Hospital Vall d&#146;Hebron como centro de referencia. Un 0,3% fueron éxitus en el Servicio de Urgencias. Conclusiones: El perfil del paciente politraumatizado asistido en Urgencias es un varón de entre 19 y 25 años, con traumatismo craneoencefálico y traumatismo en extremidades y tórax, producido por accidente de motocicleta. Su primera asistencia es realizada por el servicio de asistencia extrahospitalario y su destino una vez visitado y estabilizado será traslado al Hospital Vall d&#146;Hebron para la realización de pruebas o ingreso. Es necesario unificar los criterios de actuación de diferentes profesionales frente a una misma situación(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Puesta día urgenc. emerg. catastr;9(2): 110-114, abr.-jun. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74871</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Experiencia de atención al paciente politraumatizado en Urgencias del Hospital General de Granollers</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6931^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15345^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34373^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22947^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4710^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34373^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
