<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-12012</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Stability of auditory thresholds in the first 5 weeks following stapedectomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To assess repeatability of audiological test performed every week during the first month post-stapedectomy, audiometry was performed to 21 patients with otosclerosis (mean age 37.8 years, S.D. 9.29), every week, during the 2 weeks prior to stapedectomy and during the first 5 weeks and at week 12 after stapedectomy. Repeatability of the audiological test was evaluated comparing the difference between the audiological evaluations performed before the surgery and the difference between each consecutive pair of audiological evaluations after the surgery, using Bland &amp; Altman method and ANOVA, allowing for 5% of significance. Before the surgery, audiological thresholds, using head phones, were repeatable for low (125-500 Hz), mid (500-2000 Hz) and high (2000-8000 Hz) frequencies in 95% of the patients. After the surgery, repeatability of air conduction thresholds for the low frequency band was evident from the 2nd week, for the mid frequency band was evident from the 3rd week and for the high frequency band from the 4th week. The gain observed at week 5 after surgery was similar to the gain observed at week 12. In conclusion, in this study, stable air conduction auditory thresholds were obtained during the first month after stapedectomy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para identificar la repetibilidad de la audiometría tonal durante el primer mes post-operatorio de estapedectomía, a 21 pacientes con diagnóstico de otosclerosis (edad media de 37,8 años, D.E. 9.29) se les efectuaron estudios audiológicos semanales durante 2 semanas antes de la estapedectomía y durante las primeras 5 semanas y a la semana 12 después de la cirugía. La repetibilidad se evaluó comparando la diferencia entre los estudios pre-estapedectomía versus la diferencia entre cada par de estudios consecutivos post-estapedectomía. El análisis se efectuó con el método de Bland y Altman y ANOVA con significancia del 5 por ciento. Antes de la estapedectomía, los umbrales auditivos por vía aérea para las frecuencias bajas (125-500 Hz), medias (5002000 Hz) y altas (2000-8000 Hz) fueron repetibles en el 95 por ciento de los casos. Después de la estapedectomía, la diferencia entre pares de estudios fue similar a la identificada antes de la cirugía a la semana 2 para las frecuencias bajas, a la 3 para las medias y a la 4 para las altas. La ganancia auditiva por vía aérea fue similar en los estudios efectuados a las semanas 5 y 12. Concluimos que los umbrales auditivos por vía aérea pueden identificarse desde el primer mes después de la cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;53(5): 321-325, mayo 2002. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estabilidad de los umbrales de audición durante las primeras 5 semanas post-estapedectomía</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Castillo Mendoza, S. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morín Murillo, GL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zepeda López, EG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bello Mora, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jáuregui Renaud, K</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-12012</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10218</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1869</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1306</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13588</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
