<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129952</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessmetn of retinal nerve fiber layer thickness, cup/disc ratio, mean desviation and visual field index in cases of recent conversión to perimetric glaucoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose. Assessand compare Retina Nerve Fiber Layer (RNFL) thickness, Cup/Disc Ratio(C/D), Mean deviation (MD) and Visual field index (VFI) in recent cases ofconversion to perimetric glaucoma. Methods. Cross sectional study. The authors studied 62 patients, 15 unilateral initial perimetric glaucoma(G/P), 11 cases of recentunilateral conversion to perimetric glaucoma (CR/P)and 36 glaucoma suspects patients (P/P).Visual fields and OCT images were obtained every 6 to 12 months. RNFL thickness, C/D, MD, VFI and the rate and difference between superior and inferior cuadrants RNFL thickness with their corresponding pre-perimetric fellow eye cuadrants were computed. Results. (P/P) group RNFL thickness differences between superior and inferior cuadrants with corresponding cuadrants from their fellow eyes were &lt; 14% (&lt;14 micras), while in (CR/P) were &gt; 19% and in (G/P) &gt; than 23% with &gt;26 micras of difference. When we compare to a pre-perimetric fellow eye cuadrant classified as borderline/pathologic, visual field defects could appear with minimum RNFL thickness differences (3-5%). Conclusión. Conversion to perimetric glaucoma occurs when certain thresholds are crossed. These limits could be estimated with SD-OCT.A 13-19% RNFL thickness decrease of superior or inferior cuadrants could produce visual field defects appearance.Knowledge of these clinical settings could be helpful in glaucoma management (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Guardiola, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antón, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Banegas, S. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas González, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar el Espesor de la Capa de Fibras Nerviosas de la Retina(ECFNR), Índice excavación/papila(E/P), Desviación media(DM) e Índice de Función Visual(VFI)enojos con reciente conversión perimétrica y compararlos con sus adelfos pre- perimétricos. Método. Estudio transversal.Se estudiaron 62 pacientes, 15 con glaucomainicial perimétrico unilateral(G/P), 11 con reciente conversión perimétrica unilateral(RC/P)y 36pacientes con sospecha de glaucoma( P/P), todos con adelfo pre-perimétrico.Cada 6-12 meses se obtuvieron imágenes con elTomógrafo de Coherencia Óptica (SD-OCT) yPerimetría Computarizada Convencional. Se determinó el ECFNR, E/P, DM y VFIde cada ojo y el cocientey la diferencia de ECFNR delos cuadrantes superior e inferior de cada ojo con los cuadrantes de su adelfo pre-perimétrico. Resultados. En el grupo (P/P) las diferencias de ECFNR en ambos cuadrantes con sus homólogos adelfosnormalesfueron&lt; del 14%con &lt;14 micras de diferencia. Mientras que en el grupo (CR/P) fueron &gt; del 19%con &gt;23 micras de diferencia y en el grupo (G/P)&gt; 23.2% con &gt;26micras de diferencia.Cuando comparamos con un adelfo pre-perimétrico pero con cuadrante Borderline/Patológico, puede haber conversión campimétricacon mínimas diferencias deECFNR 0-5%. Conclusión. La conversión perimétrica se presenta al traspasar límites que podemos calcular con el SD-OCT. Una disminución de 13-19% del ECFNR del cuadrante superior o inferior en comparación con su homólogo adelfo (verde según la base de normalidad del OCT) produciría comienzo de la expresión campimétrica. El conocimiento de estos escenarios clínicos puede ser útil en el manejo de la progresión del glaucoma (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;4(2): 81-87, abr.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación del espesor de la capa de fibrras nerviosas de la retina, índice excavación/papila, desviación media e índice de función visual en ojos con reciente conversión perimétrica, comparación con sus adelfos pre-perimétricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9605^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52973^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
