<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149368</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Keratinophilic fungi in soils of parks of Corrientes city, Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The soil is a natural reservoir of keratinophilic fungi, which are a small but important group of filamentous fungi, some of which typically develop on keratinized tissues of living animals. There are numerous species of saprophytic fungi with recognized keratinophilic abilities, and several studies have been undertaken in order to link their presence to possible human disease. Aims. To know the biota of geophilic fungi in general and of keratinophilic fungi particularly in soils from two public parks. Methods. Soil samples from two public parks of Corrientes city, Argentina, were studied during two seasons, using the hook technique and serial dilutions for fungal isolation. Results. Using the hook technique, 170 isolates were classified into 17 genera and 21 species, among which it is worth mentioning the presence of Microsporum canis. Shannon index for keratinophilic fungi in autumn was 2.27, and 1.92 in spring. By means of the serial dilutions technique, 278 fungi isolated were identified into 33 genera and 71 species. Shannon index in autumn was 3.9, and 3.5 in spring. Conclusions. The soils studied have particularly favorable conditions for the survival of pathogens and opportunistic geophilic fungi for humans and animals (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giusiano, Gustavo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bojanich, María Viviana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sarmiento, María Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Basualdo, Juan Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mangiaterra, Magdalena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes. El suelo es el reservorio natural de hongos queratinofílicos que constituyen un pequeño pero importante grupo de hongos filamentosos; algunos de ellos se desarrollan típicamente sobre tejidos queratinizados de animales vivos. Hay numerosas especies de geohongos saprobios con habilidades queratolíticas reconocidas y son varios los trabajos realizados con el fin de vincular su presencia a la posible enfermedad humana. Objetivos. Conocer la biota de geohongos en general y la de aquellos queratolíticos en particular en suelos de dos parques públicos. Métodos. Las muestras se tomaron de suelos de dos parques públicos de la ciudad de Corrientes, Argentina, durante dos estaciones del año. Para el aislamiento de los hongos se usaron las técnicas del anzuelo queratínico y la de las diluciones. Resultados. Mediante la técnica del anzuelo se aislaron 170 cepas que se clasificaron en 17 géneros y 21 especies, entre las que merece destacar la presencia de Microsporum canis. El índice de Shannon de hongos queratolíticos fue medio, siendo en otoño (2,27) más alto que en primavera (1,92). Con la técnica de diluciones seriadas se obtuvieron 278 cepas que se clasificaron en 33 géneros y 71 especies; el índice de Shannon fue más alto en otoño (3,9) que en primavera (3,5). Conclusiones. Los suelos estudiados presentan condiciones particularmente favorables para la supervivencia de geohongos patógenos y oportunistas para el hombre y los animales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;33(1): 7-12, ene.-mar. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149368</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hongos queratinofílicos en suelos de parques de la ciudad de Corrientes, Argentina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51794^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1241^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1241^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7802^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24421^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9052^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13371</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54353</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
