<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60530</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are all analogue combinations equal?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The huge improvement in the therapeutic arsenal for HIVinfection has led to HIV becoming a chronic disease. Likeus, our patients are aging and their life expectancy isclose to that of the general population. Consequently, weneed safe, easily administered drugs with interactionsthat can be controlled and the least possible impact onhighly prevalent comorbidities such as atherosclerosis orcoinfection with hepatotropic viruses. Drugs should fitthe patient&#146;s lifestyle without affecting quality of life and,above all, be free of effects leading to stigma, such aslipoatrophy, a major concern for most recently diagnosedpatients. The choice of the two nucleoside analoguereverse transcriptase inhibitors used at the start ofantiretroviral therapy should be based on carefulevaluation of the abundant data accumulated on all thesedetermining factors which are heralding a new era in thecontrol of HIV infection. Thus, in this scenario, thymidineanalogues have been relegated to alternative use. Fixeddosecombinations of tenofovir and emtricitabine(TDF/FTC) or abacavir and lamivudine (ABC/3TC) are thebackbone of choice when initiating antiretroviral therapy.Direct comparative data are still scarce but suggestsimilar virological efficacy, with highly preliminary datasuggesting some disadvantages associated with the useof ABC/3TC. After excluding patients at risk ofhypersensitivity to ABC, both combinations are welltolerated, but TDF/FTC is associated with a better lipidprofile. Recent data from the Data Collection on AdverseEvents of Anti-HIV drugs (DAD) study show anunexpected association of ABC with increasedcardiovascular risk and thus more detailed studies arerequired(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miralles Álvarez, Celia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La impresionante mejora en el arsenal terapéutico hahecho real la posibilidad de convivir crónicamente con elvirus de la inmunodeficiencia humana. Nuestrospacientes, como nosotros, están envejeciendo y suesperanza de vida se aproxima a la de la población dereferencia. Por ello se necesitan fármacos seguros, fácilesde tomar, con interacciones controlables y con el menorimpacto posible sobre comorbilidades de granprevalencia, como la aterosclerosis o la coinfección porvirus hepatotropos.Fármacos que se adapten al estilo de vida del paciente sinafectarle en su calidad y libres, sobre todo, de efectosestigmatizantes como la lipoatrofia, que supone hoy unagran preocupación para la mayoría de los pacientes dereciente diagnóstico.La elección de la pareja análogos de nucleósidosinhibidoresde la transcriptasa inversa (ANITI) al inicio deltratamiento antirretroviral (TAR) debe sustentarse en laevaluación cuidadosa de los ya muchos datosacumulados acerca de todos estos determinantes que yaestán configurando una nueva era en el control de lainfección.Así, en este escenario, los análogos timidínicos han sidorelegados a un uso alternativo. Las combinaciones a dosisfijas de tenofovir (TDF) y emtricitabina (FTC) o abacavir(ABC) y lamivudina (3TC) son el ®backbone» electivo aliniciar el TAR.Los datos comparativos directos aún son escasos, peroapuntan a una eficacia virológica similar, con algún datode desventaja, muy preliminar del ABC/3TC. Aunque, trasexcluir a los pacientes con riesgo de hipersensibilidad aABC, ambos ®combos» son muy bien tolerados, elTDF/FTC se asocia a un mejor perfil lipídico. Los recientesdatos del DAD que muestran una inesperada asociacióndel ABC con el incremento del riesgo cardiovascularprecisan estudios en profundidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;26(supl.8): 38-44, jun. 2008. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Son iguales todas las combinaciones de análogos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32626^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35395^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14322^s22003</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9892^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37260^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
