<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124296</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The experience of confronting breast cancer being a nurse. an opportunity for personal growth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article is the testimony of the breast cancer experience when the sufferer is both the patient and also, by profession, a nurse. First it explains the objective reality of cancer. Using this as a starting point, the testimony reflects upon this past experience and highlights the factors which influenced the strategies adopted to face the process of experiencing breast cancer from a positive point of view. Following these reflections there is a summary of what have been the benefits and losses of this experience. The conclusion the author reaches is that what she has lived through has been, on reflection, mainly positive and that, although it seemed difficult, at the time she learned and grew personally as a result of the experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mata Blasco, María Luisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo es un testimonio de la experiencia del cáncer de mama cuando en la misma persona se aúnan las condiciones de enfermera y de paciente. En él se expone, en primer lugar, la realidad objetiva del cáncer y, a partir de este punto, con la perspectiva del tiempo pasado, se analizan los factores que influyeron en la adopción de estrategias para afrontar positivamente el proceso de vivir el cáncer de mama. Seguidamente, se describe la reflexión sobre las pérdidas y las ganancias derivadas de la experiencia. Por último, la autora concluye que lo vivido le ha dejado un saldo positivo y que lo que a priori parecía una difícil vivencia se ha transformado en una oportunidad de aprendizaje y crecimiento personal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(7/8): 497-500, jul.-ago. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124296</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La experiencia de afrontar el cáncer de mama siendo enfermera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9912</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8192</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201408</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
