<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-24121</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A new device for measuring contrast sensitivity with and without glare</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose/Method: To measure the photopic contrast sensitivity, with and without glare, by means of a new instrument. Seventy eight right eyes of 49 young adults and of 29 adults subjects between 35 and 55 years were studied. Contrast sensitivity was measured with the Contrast Glaretester CGT-1000 (Takagi, Japan) that determines the contrast threshold by means of an automated strategy for 6 spatial frecuencies. Results/Conclusions: The values of contrast sensitivity were similar to those obtained with other clinical tests. Contrast sensitivity, without and with glare, decreased significantly with the age. However, glare did not modify the contrast sensitivity under photopic conditions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Audiovisual y Marketing, S.L.</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo/Método: Valorar la sensibilidad al contraste fotópica, sin y con deslumbramiento con un nuevo instrumento. Se estudiaron 78 ojos derechos de 49 adultos jóvenes y de 29 adultos entre 35 y 55 años. La sensibilidad al contraste se midió con el Contrast Glaretester CGT-1000 mediante una estrategia automatizada de reconocimiento para seis frecuencias espaciales. Resultados/Conclusiones: Los valores de sensibilidad al contraste fueron semejantes a los obtenidos con otros tests clínicos. El aumento de la edad disminuyó significativamente la sensibilidad al contraste sin y con deslumbramiento. Sin embargo, el deslumbramiento no modificó la sensibilidad al contraste fotópica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;78(6): 331-334, jun. 2003.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevo instrumento para medir la sensibilidad al contraste sin y con deslumbramiento</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Langa Moraga, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Carrasco, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puell Marín, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benítez del Castillo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ramos, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-24121</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15189</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10972</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21037</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
