<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132288</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-6221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The incidence and severity of retinopathy of prematurity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. In the present work, we plan to meet the current incidence and severity of retinopathy of prematurity in the Vigo University Hospital Complex (CHUVI). aterial and Methods. Retrospective study of all preterm infants between  2006 and 2010 and subjected to screening for ROP. We performed a descriptive analysis and an association study to assess the incidence and severity of ROP in our area. Results. We observed an overall incidence of ROP similar to universal baseline studies, the CRYO-ROP and ETROP, however the number of treated cases is a bit lower than other published series. These differences  ay be due to the subjective component that has the indicated diagnosis and treatment of this disease as well as the bureaucratic structure available in each hospital. Conclusions. The majority of children included in screening for ROPad some degree of disease, but only 6% are severe enough to require eye treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Campo-Gesto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campos García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Mediante el presente trabajo, nos planteamos conocer la incidencia actual y la gravedad de la Retinopatía del Prematuro en el complejo hospitalario universitario de Vigo (CHUVI). Material y Métodos. Estudio restrospectivo de todos los recién nacidos prematuros entre los años 2006 y 2010 y sometidos a despistaje para ROP. Se realiza un análisis descriptivo y un estudio de asociación para valorar la incidencia y la gravedad de la ROP en nuestro área. Resultados. Se observa una incidencia global de ROP similar a los estudios de referencia universal, el CRYO-ROP y el ETROP, sin embargo el número de casos que reciben tratamiento es un poco inferior que el de otras series publicadas. Estas diferencias pueden ser debidas al componente subjetivo que tiene el diagnóstico y la indicación de tratamiento de esta enfermedad así como a la estructura burocrática disponible en cada centro hospitalario. Conclusiones. La mayor parte de los niños incluídos en el cribado para OP tenían algún grado de enfermedad, pero sólo un 6% tienen la gravedad  suficiente para precisar tratamiento ocular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. oftalmol;3(4): 193-199, oct.-dic. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Incidencia y Gravedad de la retinopatía del prematuro</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19399^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
