<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-131704</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Imported dengue: An emerging arbovirosis in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dengue is caused by one of 4 serotypes of dengue virus. Only imported cases have been reported in Spain. The main clinical findings are fever and exanthema, although there may be severe forms, particularly in secondary infections. Five children with a primary, non severe dengue infection are presented. The diagnosis was based on clinical suspicion and epidemiological history, and confirmed by immunochromatography and ELISA tests. The outcome was favourable in all cases. It is important to consider this diagnosis in international travellers that present with fever within the 14 days of returning from an endemic area, in order to get an early diagnosis, adequate treatment and a good prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García López Hortelano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Geldres, T. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mellado Peña, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baquero Artigao, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montero Vega, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Quintana, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El dengue es causado por uno de 4 serotipos del virus dengue. En España, solo se han comunicado casos importados. Las manifestaciones clínicas más frecuentes son fiebre y exantema, aunque puede haber formas graves, especialmente en infecciones secundarias. Presentamos a 5 niños con dengue no grave, infección primaria, diagnosticados por sospecha clínica y antecedente epidemiológico mediante inmunocromatografía y ELISA. Evolución favorable en todos los casos. Es importante considerar este diagnóstico en todo viajero internacional que presenta fiebre dentro de los 14 días tras volver de un área endémica, para un diagnóstico precoz, un adecuado tratamiento y un buen pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);82(1): e165-e169, ene. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-131704</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dengue importado: arbovirosis emergente en Espa&#152;na</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13195^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33342^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33342^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33342^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33342^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1106^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1106^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1106^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33342^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1106^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1106^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
