<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94446</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">How to give an oral presentation at a scientific event</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The research process inevitably requires that its findings be communicated, which can be done in writing or in the form of an oral presentation at scientific meetings. Besides the quality of the research and its outcome, results can be effectively reflected in scientific communications or they can be unintelligible, thus devaluating the whole process.Knowing about the basic principles of public communication, analysing the type of audience the presentation is directed to, and implementing some basic technical guidelines in the structure and format in which the message is transmitted, will help the communicator to meet the standards of research quality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Riestra Rodríguez, M. Rosario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oltra Rodríguez, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El proceso de investigar pasa ineludiblemente por comunicar los hallazgos obtenidos y esto puede hacerse tanto por escrito como de formaoral en reuniones científicas. Independientemente de la calidad de la investigación y de los resultados, estos pueden verse eficazmente reflejados en la comunicación o ser ininteligibles y desvirtuarse todo el proceso. Conocer los principios básicos de la comunicación en público,analizar el tipo de auditorio al que se dirige y contemplar unas normas técnicas mínimas en la estructura y formato en que se transmite el mensaje colaborarán a que la comunicación esté a la altura de la calidad dela investigación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;11(8): 67-72, oct. 2008. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94446</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cómo realizar adecuadamente una presentación oral en un acto científico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22412^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54358^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50136</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
