<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110605</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Educational intervention to introduce an emergency department hyperglycemia treatment protocol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To assess an emergency department (ED) educational intervention leading to implementation of a hyperglycemia treatment protocol. Our hypothesis was that the ED educational intervention would increase use of basal bolus therapy for hospital management of hyperglycemia. Methods: Quasi-experimental pre-post intervention study comparing unmatched groups. Patients treated before and after the intervention were selected consecutively. All were over the age of 18 years and admitted from the ED with a diagnosis oftype-2 diabetes and a blood sugar level over 180 mg/dL. The variables analyzed were percentage of patients in each group treated with basal-bolus therapy, and the degree of glycemic control (days until blood sugar levels were brought under control, mean blood sugar levels, and number of hyperglycemic [&gt;180 mg/dL], and hypoglycemic [&lt;60 mg/dL] episodes).Results: A total of 96 patients (preintervention, 45; postintervention, 51) were included. The use of basal-bolus therapy (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcalde López, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliete Blanco, M. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Javierre Loris,  M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Povar Marco,  J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Usieto López, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parrilla Herránz,  P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar el efecto una intervención educativa en el servicio de urgencias (SU)dirigida a implementar un protocolo de tratamiento de la hiperglucemia. La hipótesis de partida fue que la intervención educativa dirigida a los profesionales del SU permitiría aumentar el uso de la pauta basal-bolo en el tratamiento de la hiperglucemia hospitalaria. Método: Estudio cuasi-experimental con un grupo de control no equivalente, pre/post intervención formativa. Se seleccionaron dos grupos de pacientes (pre y post intervención) mediante muestreo consecutivo, mayores de 18 años y hospitalizados desde el SU con diagnóstico de diabetes tipo 2 e hiperglucemia mayor de 180 mg/dl. Las variables de resultado analizadas fueron la proporción de pacientes tratados con pauta basal-bolo y el grado de control de la glucemia [días transcurridos hasta el control de la (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);25(1): 43-46, feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110605</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención educativa para implantar un protocolo de tratamiento de la hiperglucemia en urgencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22523^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51554</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7500^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
