<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051923</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relation between brachial artery flow-mediated dilation and the ankle-brachial index in patients with peripheral arterial disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Measurement of brachial artery flow-mediated dilation (BAFMD) using ultrasonography was        tested in our laboratory to determine endothelial dysfunction in patients with peripheral arterial disease (PAD). Our        experience shows that this dysfunction does not determine the severity of the disease. The ankle-brachial index (ABI) is        a classic marker of PAD associated with its severity. Aim. To determine the BAFMD and the ABI in patients with PAD.        Patients and methods. The BAFMD and ABI were determined in patients with symptomatic PAD, which had been        confirmed haemodynamically and/or angiographically with an ABI &lt; 0.9. Both cardiovascular risk factors and treatments        are considered. Results. A total of 72 patients aged 65.36 ± 7.7 years were recruited for the study, 27.5% of whom had        critical ischaemia. BAFMD was 5.49 ± 0.43% and the Spearman correlation coefficient was r &lt; 0.001 (p &lt; 0.05). No        statistically significant differences were found between the BAFMD in the group with an ABI &lt; 0.3 (percentile 5) and the        one with a higher index. No significant differences were observed in the ABI values in the groups with a BAFMD above        and below 1.35% (percentile 5). Conclusions. There is no direct relation between the ABI and the BAFMD, which lends        support to our hypothesis that endothelial dysfunction is a predisposing factor for the development of PAD, but does not        determine its severity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Haro Miralles, Joaquín de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flórez González, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Maldonado, Francisco José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Aguilar, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>March García, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Acín García, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La medida ecográfica de la dilatación de la arteria braquial mediada por flujo (DABMF) se ha        validado en nuestro laboratorio en la determinación de la disfunción endotelial en pacientes con enfermedad arterial        periférica (EAP). Según nuestra experiencia, esta disfunción no es determinante de la gravedad de la enfermedad. El        índice tobillo-brazo (ITB) es un marcador clásico de EAP asociado a su gravedad. Objetivo. Determinar la relación de        la DABMF y el ITB en pacientes con EAP. Pacientes y métodos. Determinamos la DABMF y el ITB en pacientes con EAP        sintomática, demostrada hemodinámica y/o angiográficamente con ITB &lt; 0,9. Se recogen los factores de riesgo cardiovascular        y los tratamientos. Resultados. Se reclutó un total de 72 pacientes con edad de 65,36 ± 7,7 años, de los que un        27,5% presentaba isquemia crítica. La DABMF fue de 5,49 ± 0,43%; el coeficiente de correlación de Spearman es r &lt;        0,001 (p &lt; 0,05). No existieron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en la DABMF entre el grupo con ITB &lt; 0,3        (percentil 5) y el de índice mayor. Tampoco existió en los valores de ITB de los grupos con DABMF mayor y menor a        1,35% (percentil 5). Conclusiones. No existe relación directa entre el ITB y la DABMF, lo que corrobora nuestra hipótesis        de que la disfunción endotelial es un factor predisponente para el desarrollo de la EAP, pero no determinante en su        gravedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;59(1): 55-61, ene.-feb. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051923</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación de la dilatación de la arteria braquial mediada por flujo y el índice tobillo-brazo en pacientes con enfermedad arterial periférica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1136^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12461^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29897^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1941^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d856^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1941^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200702</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
