<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116960</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After initiating a neuraxial analgesia for labor pain, there are a few techniques that can be used for its maintenance. The methods used for the maintenance of analgesia, can be classified into two major groups: "top up" techniques and techniques to prevent recurrence of pain (to prevent breakthrough pain). Labor pain is dynamic and can be variable during labour so that anesthesiologists should be able to reach a tailored analgesia and every woman in labor, to facilitate a memorable and pleasant birth experience. Medical technology has evolved to allow us these goals and requirements and provide women a painless, safe and more natural childbirth. New management labor analgesia systems, allow individualized regimens. Programmed intermittent boluses reduce local anesthetic consumption and the incidence of breakthrough pain. Further studies are needed to definitively demonstrate that the incidence of instrumental delivery is confirmed to be decreased and by how much. The costs of these technologies would be justified if confirmed improved obstetric and analgesics (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Schiraldi, Renato</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz Rodríguez, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guasch Arévalo, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Después de iniciar una analgesia neuroaxial para el dolor del trabajo de parto, hay muchas técnicas que pueden utilizarse para el mantenimiento de la misma. Los métodos usados para este mantenimiento de la analgesia, se pueden clasificar en dos grandes grupos: técnicas de &#147;top up&#148; y técnicas que previenen la recurrencia del dolor. El dolor del parto es algo dinámico, personal y cambiante, así que los anestesiólogos, debemos hacer lo posible por llegar a una analgesia a la medida de cada parturienta, para facilitar que el nacimiento sea una experiencia memorable y agradable. La tecnología médica ha evolucionado para permitirnos posiblemente atender mejor estos requerimientos y llegar a proporcionar a las mujeres un parto sin dolor, seguro y más natural. Los nuevos sistemas de administración de analgesia en el parto permiten individualizar los regímenes a medida. Los bolos programados intermitentes reducen el consumo de anestésico local y la incidencia de dolor irruptivo. Se necesitan más estudios para ver si la incidencia de parto instrumental se confirma que disminuye y en qué cuantía. Los costes de estas tecnologías quedarían justificados si se confirma la mejora de resultados obstétricos y analgésicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;23(3): 11-12[3], jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116960</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actualización en el mantenimiento de la analgesia en el parto: PCEA, bolos intermitentes o programados, etc</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3708^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34540^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d788^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
