<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89174</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Occupational disease in a mutual insurance company in the year before the legistlative change</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The new Panel of Occupational Diseases was published in Spain on November 10th 2006, establishing new criteria for notification and registration. Aims and purposes: To assess and quantify the occupational  diseases among the labour population covered by the &#147;ASEPEYO&#148; mutual insurance company over the last year before the legislative change, and to describe their main features. Methods: Descriptive study of the cases of occupational disease declared by &#147;ASEPEYO&#148; over the year  2006. Results: Over the year 2006 there was an occupational disease incidence of 171 cases per 100,000 workers, representing a total number of 3,824 cases of medical leave-associated occupational disease. 99% of the cases were classed as mild. 89.5% of the reported cases were classed among the occupational diseases caused by physical agents. Conclusions: Over the year 2006, a decrease as  compared to preceding years is evident. Most of the cases were mild, and physical agents were the main cause (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ortiz de Salazar, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Manzano, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Barreiro, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Fernández, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bizighescu, Magda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El 10 de noviembre de 2006, se publica el nuevo cuadro de EE PP en España, estableciéndose nuevos criterios de notificación y registro. Objetivo: Cuantificar las EE PP de la población trabajadora cubierta por la mutua ASEPEYO durante el último año previo al cambio  legislativo, y describir sus principales características. Metodología: Estudio descriptivo de los casos de enfermedad profesional declarados por la mutua ASEPEYO en el año 2006. Resultados: Durante el año 2006, se observó una incidencia de 171 nuevos casos por cada 100.000 trabajadores, que constituye un total  de 3.824 casos de EE PP con baja. El 99% de los casos fueron leves. El 89,5% de los casos declarados pertenecen al grupo de EE PP causadas por agentes físicos. Conclusiones: Se observa en 2006 una disminución de casos con respecto a años anteriores. La mayoría de   los casos presentan un pronóstico leve y la patología por agentes físicos es la más frecuente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;17(1): 36-44, abr. 2008. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89174</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Situación de la enfermedad profesional en una mutua, en el año previo al cambio legislativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29063^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16373^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200804</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
