<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120943</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bone scintigraphy and secondary osteomalacia due to nephrotoxicity in a chronic hepatitis B patient treated with tenofovir</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tenofovir is a nucleotide analogue used for the treatment of chronic hepatitis B and HIV infection. The safety of tenofovir is high but it has been described that tenofovir produces tubular toxicity and Fanconi's syndrome in some HIV-infected patients. To our knowledge this is the first documented case of bone involvement in Fanconi's syndrome in a patient treated with tenofovir for chronic hepatitis B without HIV coinfection. Bone scintigraphy has proven to be very useful for the diagnosis of secondary osteomalacia. Normalization of the bone scan after the withdrawal of the drug and the decline in alkaline phosphatase and phosphate serum levels reinforce the cause-effect relationship (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Samaniego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Martínez, MV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pirogova, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gallardo, FG</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tenofovir es un análogo de nucleótido que se utiliza para el tratamiento de la hepatitis B y de la infección por VIH. La seguridad del fármaco es muy alta, pero se ha descrito que en algunos pacientes VIH produce toxicidad tubular y síndrome de Fanconi. En nuestro conocimiento este es el primer caso en el que se documenta afectación ósea en síndrome de Fanconi en una paciente tratada con tenofovir por hepatitis B. En este contexto la gammagrafía ósea ha resultado ser de gran utilidad para el diagnóstico de osteomalacia secundaria. La normalización de la gammagrafía ósea y de los valores séricos de fosfato y fosfatasa alcalina tras la retirada del fármaco refuerza la relación causa-efecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);33(2): 103-105, mar.-abr. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120943</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gammagrafía ósea y oseteomalacia secundaria a nefrotoxicidad en una paciente con hepatitis B tratada con tenofovir</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1867^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9897^s32387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33343^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10198^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10198^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5302^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53982^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
