<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128285</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Integration of Mechanical, Structural and Electrical Imaging to Understand Response to Cardiac Resynchronization Therapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives There is extensive controversy exists on whether cardiac resynchronization therapy corrects electrical or mechanical asynchrony. The aim of this study was to determine if there is a correlation between electrical and mechanical sequences and if myocardial scar has any relevant impact. Methods Six patients with normal left ventricular function and 12 patients with left ventricular dysfunction and left bundle branch block, treated with cardiac resynchronization therapy, were studied. Real-time three-dimensional echocardiography and electroanatomical mapping were performed in all patients and, where applicable, before and after therapy. Magnetic resonance was performed for evaluation of myocardial scar. Images were postprocessed and mechanical and electrical activation sequences were defined and time differences between the first and last ventricular segment to be activated were determined. Response to therapy was defined as a reduction in left ventricular end-systolic volume 15% after 12 months of follow-up. Results: Good correlation between electrical and mechanical timings was found in patients with normal left ventricular function (r2=0.88; P= .005) but not in those with left ventricular dysfunction (r2=0.02; P=not significant). After therapy, both timings and sequences were modified and improved, except in those with myocardial scar. Conclusions: Despite a close electromechanical relationship in normal left ventricular function, there is no significant correlation in patients with dysfunction. Although resynchronization therapy improves this correlation, the changes in electrical activation may not yield similar changes in left ventricular mechanics particularly depending on the underlying myocardial substrate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Silva, Etelvino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mont, Lluis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andreu, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doltra, Adelina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sitges, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berruezo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brugada, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bijnens, Bart</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: Debido a la controversia existente al determinar si la terapia de resincronización cardiaca corrige asincronía eléctrica o mecánica, el objetivo del estudio es determinar si hay correlación entre las secuencias eléctricas y mecánicas y si la cicatriz miocárdica tiene un impacto relevante. Métodos Se estudió a 6 pacientes con función ventricular izquierda normal y 12 pacientes con disfunción del ventrículo izquierdo y bloqueo de rama izquierda tratados con terapia de resincronización cardiaca. Se realizaron ecografías tridimensionales en tiempo real y cartografías electroanatómicas de todos los pacientes, antes y después de dicha terapia, así como una resonancia magnética para evaluar la cicatriz miocárdica. Se posprocesaron las imágenes, se definieron secuencias de activación mecánica y eléctrica y se determinaron diferencias temporales entre el primer y el último segmento del ventrículo izquierdo. Se consideró respuesta a la terapia una reducción del volumen telesistólico del ventrículo izquierdo &amp;#8805; 15% a los 12 meses. Resultados: Se encontró buena correlación entre tiempos eléctricos y mecánicos en pacientes con función ventricular normal (r2 = 0,88; p = 0,005), pero no en aquellos con disfunción (r2 = 0,02; p = no significativa). Después de optimizar el dispositivo, se modificaron y mejoraron los tiempos y las secuencias, excepto los de aquellos con cicatriz miocárdica. Conclusiones: A pesar de la estrecha relación electromecánica en ventrículos normales, no hay una correlación significativa en los pacientes con disfunción ventricular. Aunque la terapia mejora esta correlación, los cambios en la activación eléctrica no pueden producir cambios similares en la mecánica del ventrículo izquierdo, sobre todo en función del sustrato miocárdico subyacente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;67(10): 813-821, oct. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Integración de la imagen mecánica, estructural y eléctrica para entender la respuesta a la terapia de resincronización cardiaca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53678</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54223^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54283^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201410</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
