<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-041414</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A life skills training programme evaluation in Costa Rica</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The need to evaluate a prevention programme developed under the paradigm of life skills, led to the design of an investigative strategy by means of which information was analysed on the performance of a sample of adolescents in a number of life skills (decision making, face-to-face relationships, communication, stress handling, self-esteem, peer pressure) and on drug use, before and after the application of the Trazando el Camino Programme on a Costa Rican student population in 2001. In order to achieve the proposed objective, a pretest-posttest design was used, within a quasi-experimental framework. A sample of 1897 young students completed a questionnaire in the pretest and 920 in the posttest. The results were interesting insofar as both the group where the programme was applied as well as the control group showed significant improvements in self-esteem, stress management, peer pressure and communication. This could be interpreted in respect of the typical evolution of adolescents during this period. It is also probable that the young people in both groups were exposed to additional preventive influences which were outside the knowledge and control of the researchers. It is considered that the evaluation period of the programme should be longer, with the aim of ascertaining its possible long-term effects, an objective of some importance as this programme is being implemented over the long term</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ugalde, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bejarano, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Desirée</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La necesidad de evaluar un programa de prevención desarrollado bajo el paradigma de las habilidades para vivir, llevó a diseñar una estrategia investigativa mediante la cual se analizó información acerca del desempeño de una muestra de adolescentes en una serie de dominios (toma de decisiones, relaciones interpersonales, comunicación asertiva, percepción de amenazas, autoestima, presión de grupo) y sobre consumo de drogas, antes y después de la aplicación del programa denominado Trazando el Camino a una población estudiantil costarricense en el año 2001. Para el logro del objetivo propuesto se trabajó con un diseño pretest-postest, dentro de una modalidad de investigación cuasi- experimental. Se aplicó un instrumento de medición a una muestra de 1879 en el pretest y a otra de 920 jóvenes estudiantes en el postest. Los resultados obtenidos son de interés, en la medida en que tanto en el grupo al cual se le aplicó el programa, como aquel que operó como grupo de comparación, se registraron mejoras significativas en la autoestima, manejo del estrés, presión grupal y comunicación. Esto puede interpretarse en función de la evolución propia de los adolescentes en este período. También es probable que los jóvenes, en ambos grupos, estuviesen expuestos a influencias preventivas adicionales, que escaparon al conocimiento y manejo de los investigadores. Se considera que el período de evaluación del programa debería ser mayor, con el propósito de conocer sus posibles efectos en el largo plazo, situación de importancia en la medida que los programas mismos tengan permanencia en el tiempo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);17(1): 71-80, ene. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-041414</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de un programa escolar en Costa Rica basado en habilidades para vivir</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
