<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-144181</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Admissions Service</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In the present article we describe the activity of the admissions service on the day of the terrorist attacks, 11 March, 2004. Firstly, we try to describe the objectives and lines of intervention that we believe should be covered by our service. Subsequently, we describe how we organized ourselves into teams in order to organize and synchronize activities as effectively as possible. The difficulties that arose during the course of the day in performing some our functions are discussed. Next, we report the sequence of interventions that were carried out from the morning of 11 March until the last victim of the terrorist attack was discharged. The article concludes with an overall evaluation of the activity performed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oria, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Sampelayo, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicario, Domitila</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintanilla, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este trabajo describimos el desarrollo de las actuaciones del Servicio de Admisión durante el día de los atentados terroristas, 11 de marzo de 2004. En primer lugar intentamos describir los objetivos y líneas de actuación que consideramos debíamos cubrir desde nuestro servicio. A continuación, relatamos cómo nos organizamos en grupos de trabajo a fin de intentar coordinar las actividades y sincronizarlas de la forma más efectiva posible. Asimismo, se explican las dificultades que fueron surgiendo a lo largo del día en relación con el cumplimiento de algunas de nuestras funciones. Seguidamente referimos la secuencia de las acciones que se ejecutaron desde el inicio de la jornada hasta el día en que se dio de alta la última víctima del atentado. Se concluye el trabajo con una valoración del conjunto de actuaciones que se llevaron a cabo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(supl.1): 48-48, mar. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-144181</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Servicio de Admisión</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d289^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d289^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d289^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d289^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10537^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d289^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d289^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35430^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10537^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10549^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10549^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10549^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10537^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
