<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152589</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Center of pressure displacements in individuals with Down syndrome during a bipedal position</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate body balance of adults with Down syndrome based on the analysis of their centre of pressure behaviour. Method. Cross-sectional case control-study. Twelve individuals with Down syndrome and twelve without Down syndrome took part in the study. All the participants were tested under two conditions on a force plate: i) static with eyes open and ii) static with eyes closed. Centre of pressure signals were analyzed in time domain. Non-parametric contrasts were used for statistical analysis. Results. Statistical differences between groups were found in anteroposterior range, anterior-posterior force and medio-lateral force (p &lt; 0.05). Within-groups comparisons showed poorer results in eyes closed conditions for both groups. Conclusion. Individuals with Down syndrome involved in the present study showed deficits in balance control when compared with people without Down syndrome. The obtained data are not conclusive. The participation of the different systems which control balance in people with Down syndrome remains unknown (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabeza-Ruiz, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beas-Jiménez, JD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro-Lemus, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Centeno-Prada, RA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Valorar el equilibrio de adultos con síndrome de Down a través del estudio del desplazamiento del centro de presiones. Método. Estudio transversal de casos y controles. Doce sujetos con síndrome de Down y 12 sin síndrome de Down formaron parte del estudio. Todos los participantes realizaron 2 pruebas sobre plataforma dinamométrica: i) estática con ojos abiertos y ii) estática con ojos cerrados. Las señales del centro de presiones fueron analizadas en el dominio temporal. Se utilizaron contrastes no paramétricos para el análisis estadístico de los datos. Resultados. Los resultados mostraron diferencias significativas entre-grupos en las variables rango anteroposterior, fuerza anteroposterior y fuerza medio-lateral (p &lt; 0.05). Las comparaciones intragrupos mostraron peores resultados en las pruebas con ojos cerrados en ambos grupos. Conclusión. En el presente trabajo las personas con síndrome de Down presentaron un control del equilibrio mermado al compararlo con sujetos sin síndrome de Down. Los datos obtenidos no son concluyentes para determinar cuál de los sistemas involucrados en el control del equilibrio es el responsable de estos resultados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;9(2): 62-66, jun. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152589</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desplazamiento del centro de presiones en personas con síndrome de Down en bipedestación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4634^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13530^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52443^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52443^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
