<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128603</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Affective regulations, symbolization processes and Materna Subjectivity in mother-child play</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The study of affects and their regulation is linked to the psychic structuration, and it is a central research field in psychoanalysis. A research project is presented on: parental reflective functioning studied through deep interviews to mothers and through the detailed analysis of videotaped mother-child play interactions. The conclusions are in connection with Winnitcott´s  theory about the two foundational moments in the psychic structure: the achievemente of &#147;the capacity to be alone in the presence of another person&#148; (which can be seen in our study in the transition from a dyadic affective regulation to infant´s self-regulation), and &#147;playing together in a relationship&#148; (which can be seen in our results in the strong correlation between mother-child convergence during a play situation, and the rise of the complex symbolic play sequences). This study contributes giving tools for the early intervention with infants and their families, through an approach which includes the complex interaction between: maternal subjectivity, baby´s building of psychic structure, and the continuous interactive display between the baby and its environment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vernengo, María Pía</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duhalde, Constanza</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huerin, Vanina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schejtman, Clara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laplacette, Juan Augusto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Silver, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vardy, Inés</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteve, María Jimena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio de los afectos y su regulación está ligado a la estructura psíquica y es de interés en el psicoanálisis actual. Se presenta una investigación que explora el funcionamiento reflexivo parental a través de entrevistas en profundidad a las madres y el despliegue interactivo lúdico madres-niño a través del análisis minucioso de interacciones videofilmadas. Las conclusiones se relacionan con el planteo de Winnicott acerca de los momentos fundantes en la estructuración psíquica: lograr la capacidad de &#147;estar a solas en presencia de otro&#148; (que en nuestros estudios involucra el pasaje de la regulación efectiva didáctica a la autorregulación) y &#147;jugar juntos en una relación&#148; (encuentro de subjetividades que en nuestros resultados se expresió en la fuerte asociación entre convergencia madre-niño en el juego y aumento de secuencias de juego simbólico complejo). Este trabajo brinda herramientas para intervenir tempranamente con infantesy sus familias desde un enfoque que incluya la compleja intrincación entre subjetividad materna, tiempos de estructuración psíquica del bebé y el momento a moento del despliegue interactivo observable entre el bebé y su entorno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(71): 283-304, ene.-abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128603</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Regulación afectiva, procesos de simbolización y subjetividad maternal en el juego madre-niño</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9226^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
