<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050777</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular regenerative medicine at the crossroads. Clinical trials of cellular therapy must now be based on reliable experimental data from animals with characteristics similar to human's</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is now over 4 years since early reports of murine models raised high expectations that bone marrow cell transplantation to the postischemic myocardium could produce physiologically significant myocardial regeneration. In quick succession, a flurry of publications documented the capacity of a variety of other types of adult cell to produce similar results. These publications were all controversial from the start because none addressed the mechanisms involved in the differentiation of transplanted cells. In addition, each report raised at least as many questions as it answered. Despite these obvious weaknesses, the first phase-I clinical trials were started immediately without any further animal experimentation. Today the results of more than a dozen trials are already in the public domain but we still do not have a single piece of solid data documenting whether any of the approaches used is capable of regenerating contractile cells in the human myocardium. This is one of the main reasons why the controversy over the effectiveness of this therapeutic approach is becoming increasingly heated. Moreover, skepticism about the efficacy, and even the feasibility, of inducing clinically relevant myocardial regeneration has increased to the point where it threatens the future of this nascent field. The present situation in myocardial generation contrasts sharply with that in neural regeneration. Although there is a solid and extensive body of knowledge on the origin, phenotype, and regulatory mechanisms of neural stem cells, the first clinical trials have only recently been started. To move this field forward it is necessary to distinguish between the procedures needed to establish «proof-of-concept» and those that have the potential for widespread clinical application. In addition, the technique must be implemented in such a way that it continues to add to existing knowledge. It is our belief that, if the necessary information is to be acquired, we need: a) significantly more extensive experimental data from animals whose anatomical and physiological characteristics are similar to human's, including data on, for example, dose-effect relationships, the best form of administration, and the duration of therapeutic responses; and b) better understanding of the molecular mechanisms that determine whether cardiac stem cells and transplanted cells will either remain as stem cells or differentiate. In summary, if we are to progress systematically in this area, we need better understanding of myocardial biology. Without it, we run the risk of holding back the field for decades, as happened with the first human heart transplants and with trials of gene therapy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ellison, Georgina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torella, Daniele</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nadal-Ginard, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hace ya 4 años que las primeras publicaciones de trabajos realizados en roedores crearon grandes expectativas sobre el potencial del trasplante de células de la medula ósea para producir una regeneración del miocardio con relevancia fisiológica. Rápidamente, en algunas publicaciones adicionales se documentó la capacidad de otras células del adulto para producir efectos semejantes. Todas estas publicaciones fueron controvertidas desde el principio porque ninguna de ellas aclaraba los mecanismos de la diferenciación de las células trasplantadas. Es más, cada uno de estos trabajos dejaba al menos tantas preguntas abiertas como las que contestaba. A pesar de estas deficiencias, los primeros ensayos clínicos de fase I se empezaron inmediatamente sin ninguna experimentación animal adicional. En la actualidad se han publicado los resultados de más de una docena de ensayos clínicos y todavía no hay una sola evidencia convincente que documente si los protocolos utilizados pueden regenerar células miocárdicas contráctiles en el miocardio humano. Ésta es una de las principales razones por las que la controversia sobre la efectividad de este tratamiento es cada día más vitriólica. El escepticismo acerca de la efectividad e incluso del potencial de la regeneración miocárdica clínica ha llegado a un nivel que amenaza el futuro de este campo en su infancia. La situación de la regeneración miocárdica contrasta claramente con la del campo de regeneración neuronal. A pesar de la extensa y sólida documentación sobre el origen, el fenotipo y los mecanismos reguladores de las células madre neurales, los primeros ensayos clínicos apenas se han iniciado recientemente. Para progresar en este campo es necesario distinguir entre los procedimientos necesarios para establecer una «prueba de concepto» y los que tienen el potencial de una amplia aplicación clínica. Además, el método de implementación debe permitir una acumulación progresiva de conocimientos. Según nuestra opinión, para obtener la información requerida necesitamos: a) mucha más información procedente de animales cuya anatomía y fisiología sean relevantes para los humanos, incluidas la relación dosis/efecto, el modo óptimo de administración, la duración del efecto, etc., y b) un mejor conocimiento de los mecanismos moleculares que permiten mantener la «troncalidad frente a la diferenciación de las células madre cardiacas y/o de las células trasplantadas». En conclusión, necesitamos entender mejor la biología del miocardio para avanzar en este campo de forma sistemática. De otra forma corremos el peligro de retrasar este campo durante décadas, como ocurrió con los primeros trasplantes de corazón y los ensayos de tratamiento genético</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;59(11): 1175-1189, nov. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050777</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Medicina regenerativa cardiovascular en la encrucijada. Es urgente basar los ensayos clínicos sobre terapia celular en datos sólidos obtenidos en animales experimentales relevantes para los humanos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37572^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55362^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12460^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
