<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049300</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-invasive diagnosis of erectile dysfunction due to venous leak using Doppler ultrasound</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The most common pathogenic mechanism causing erectile dysfunction has its origins in a    vascular disorder. To date, in the diagnosis of erectile dysfunction due to venous leak, only invasive diagnostic tests, such    as cavernosometry and cavernosography, have been available, and such methods naturally entail a potential iatrogenic    risk for patients. Case report. A 38-year-old male with vascular erectile dysfunction due to venous leak (dysfunction of the    corporal veno-occlusive mechanism), diagnosed using only Doppler ultrasonography and the penile index in our noninvasive    vascular diagnosis clinic. Conclusions. Haemodynamic examination using Doppler ultrasound recording of the    cavernous arteries has now become the preferred test for diagnosing erectile dysfunction in the arterial phase, and more    so since the incorporation of intracavernous administration of vasoactive drugs. Likewise, many authors also consider    it to be the preferred method for evaluating the corporal veno-occlusive mechanism (or venous phase) and it has    gradually substituted dynamic tests such as cavernosography and cavernosometry</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano-Vilardell, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Manuel-Rimbau, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera-Vázquez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino-Mairal, O. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgués-Gasión, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torreguitart-Mirada, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El mecanismo patogénico más frecuente de la disfunción eréctil es el de origen vascular. Hasta la    fecha, en el diagnóstico de la disfunción eréctil por fuga venosa, únicamente se disponía de pruebas diagnósticas invasivas,    como la cavernosometría y la cavernosografía, con un riesgo potencial de yatrogenia para los pacientes. Caso clínico.    Varón de 38 años de edad con disfunción eréctil de origen vascular por fuga venosa (disfunción del mecanismo corporovenooclusivo),    diagnosticado únicamente mediante eco-Doppler e índice peneano en nuestro gabinete de diagnóstico vascular    no invasivo. Conclusiones. La exploración hemodinámica mediante eco-Doppler de las arterias cavernosas, sobre todo    desde la incorporación de la administración intracavernosa de fármacos vasoactivos, ha pasado a considerarse como la    prueba de elección en el diagnóstico de disfunción eréctil en la fase arterial. De la misma forma, muchos autores también    la consideran de elección en la valoración del mecanismo corporovenooclusivo (o fase venosa) y ha desplazado de forma    paulatina a pruebas como la cavernosografía y la cavernosometría dinámicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;58(6): 501-504, nov.-dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diagnóstico no invasivo mediante eco-Doppler de la disfunción eréctil por fuga venosa</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7231^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8657^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19636^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19636^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23623^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15068^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
