<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138299</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rapid Disability Rating Scale-2 in Alzheimer's disease: NORMACODEM project data</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">INTRODUCTION: The study aimed to investigate the Rapid Disability Rating Scale-2 (RDRS-2) in Alzheimer's disease (AD). Test retest reliability, internal consistency, data of discriminant validity of the scale, correlations with other functional and cognitive measures were analyzed. MATERIAL AND METHODS: 451 subjects were assessed: 254 healthy controls, 86 with cognitive impairment but no dementia (CIND) and 111 subjects diagnosed of AD. Total and subscales scores of the RDRS-2 were obtained. The total score is the sum of three subscales: activities of daily living, disability, and special problems. To establish its correlation with other functional scales and cognitive instruments, the following tools were applied: Blessed Dementia Rating Scale (BDRS), Interview for the Deterioration of Daily Living in Dementia (IDDD), Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale-Cognitive (ADAS-Cog) and the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE). STATISTICAL ANALYSIS: lineal multivariate regression analysis. Crossvalidation. ROC curves. Intraclass coefficient. Cronbach's alpha and Pearson's Correlation coefficient. RESULTS: RDRS-2 scores by group were the following (mean and SD): Controls (18.95; 1.64), CIND (20.61; 2.88), and AD (28.96; 9.07). Results from regression analysis 282 demonstrated absence of influence of sociocultural variables such as age and education in RDRS-2 scores. Correlations with other instruments were as following: BDRS, r=0.820; IDDD, r=0.882; ADAS-Cog, r=0.762, and MMSE, r=0.742. Intraclass coefficient was 0.86 and Cronbach's alpha was 0.91. For the RDRS-2 the best cutoff score was 21 (82.88% sensitivity and 88.8% specificity). Area under the ROC curve was 0.92. CONCLUSIONS: The Spanish adaptation of the RDRS-2 is free of sociocultural influence, and shows very adequate data on internal consistency and stability. Although not specifically designed for its use in AD it correlates highly and significantly with other functional scales as well as with the degree of cognitive impairment in AD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monllau, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sol, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña-Casanova, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Böhm, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blesa, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, G</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El propósito del presente artículo fue el estudio de la Rapid Disability Rating Scale-2 (RDRS-2) en la enfermedad de Alzheimer (EA). Se analiza la fiabilidad testretest, la consistencia interna, la validez discriminativa de esta escala y el grado de correlación con otras escalas funcionales y cognitivas. Material y métodos. Se estudiaron 451 sujetos: 254 controles sanos, 86 casos de deterioro cognitivo sin demencia (DSD) y 111 sujetos afectos de EA. Se obtuvieron las puntuaciones de los diversos apartados de la escala de RDRS-2. La puntuación total de la RDRS-2 es la suma resultante de tres subescalas: actividades de la vida diaria, grado de discapacidad y problemas especiales. A fin de poder establecer su correlación con otras escalas funcionales y tests cognitivos se aplicaron la Blessed Dementia Rating Scale (BDRS), Interview for Detererioration of Daily Living in Dementia (IDDD), la subescala cognitiva del Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale (ADASCog) y el Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE). Estudio estadístico: regresión lineal multivariable. Validación cruzada. Curvas ROC. Coeficiente de correlación intraclase. Coeficiente alfa de Cronbach. Coeficiente de Pearson. Resultados. Las puntuaciones obtenidas de la RDRS-2 (media y DE) fueron las siguientes: controles (18,95; 1,64), DSD (20,61; 2,88) y EA (28,96; 9,07). La regresión lineal multivariable demostró que la puntuación de la RDRS-2 no está influenciada por factores socioculturales, tales como la edad o la escolaridad. Se objetivaron las siguientes correlaciones: BDRS, r=0,820; IDDD, r=0,882; ADAS-Cog, r=0,762, y MMSE, r=0,742. El coeficiente de correlación intraclase fue de 0,86 y el coeficiente alfa de Cronbach de 0,91. El punto de corte más equilibrado de la RDRS-2 fue 21 (sensibilidad: 82,88 %, y especificidad: 88,8 %). El área bajo la curva ROC fue de 0,92. Conclusiones. La presente versión en lengua castellana de la RDRS-2 no está influenciada por factores socioculturales, presenta gran fiabilidad test-retest y consistencia interna. Aunque no fue diseñada específicamente para usarla en la EA, se correlaciona de forma significativa con otras escalas funcionales y además existe una buena correlación con el grado de deterioro cognitivo presente en pacientes con EA (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(6): 282-288, jul.-ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138299</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio de la Escala de Evaluación Rápida de Discapacidad-2 (Rapid Disability Rating Scale-2) en la enfermedad de Alzheimer: datos del proyecto NORMACODEM</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8779</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33119</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9673^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d545^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
