<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66630</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Thyrotropin secreting adenomas (TSHomas)account for less than 1% of all pituitary adenomas and are a rare cause of hyperthyroidism. Most cases correspond to macroadenomas, microadenomas beingexceptional. Differential diagnosis should be made with resistance to thyroid hormones. The first line treatment is transphenoidal surgery. When surgery is unsuccessful, somatostatin analogues are a therapeutic alternative. We report a patient with a TSH-secreting microadenoma. The microadenoma was resected through the transsphenoidal route. Because surgery was unsuccessful, medical therapy with somatostatin analogue was initiated. Currently, 9 years later, the patient continues to be under treatment with somatostatin analogue therapy, which has controlled the hyperthyroidism and tumoral growth. We describe successful long-term treatment of a TSH-oma with somatostatin analogue therapy when surgery is unsuccessful (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Illán Gómez, Fátima</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orea Soler, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Saura, Herminia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz Tafalla, M. Soledad</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual Díaz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores hipofisarios secretores de tirotropina (tirotropinomas) son menos del 1% de los adenomas hipofisarios y una causa rara de hipertiroidismo. La mayoría se diagnostica como macroadenoma, y los microadenomas son excepcionales. Debe hacerse el diagnóstico diferencial con la resistencia a las hormonas tiroideas. El tratamiento de elección es la adenomectomía transesfenoidal. Si fracasa, los análogos de somatostatina son una alternativa terapéutica. Presentamos a una paciente con un microadenoma productor de tirotropina en quien se practicó una adenomectomía transesfenoidal. Tras el fracaso de la cirugía, se inició tratamiento con un análogo de somatostatina. En laactualidad, después de 9 años, la paciente continúa el tratamiento y el hipertiroidismo y el crecimiento tumoral están controlados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;55(6): 270-273, jun. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66630</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22676^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11344^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7160^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22697^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
