<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-151698</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A review of the dissociative disorders: from multiple personality disorder to the posttraumatic stress</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this paper we review the idea of dissociation, dissociative disorders and their relationship with the processes of consciousness. We will deal specifically with multiple personality disorder and posttraumatic stress disorder. Both polarize the discussion of diagnostic categories with dissociative symptoms. This review compares the initial ideas (one century old) with the current scenario and emerging trends in research, which are relating cognitive processes and dissociative phenomena and disorders from a neuroscientific approach. We discuss the ideas on dissociation, hypnosis and suicide associated with these disorders. There seems to be a lack of consensus as to the nature of dissociation with theoretical, empirical and clinical implications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero-López,  Modesto J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo trata la idea de disociación, los trastornos disociativos y su relación con los procesos de conciencia. Se centra en el trastorno de personalidad múltiple y el trastorno de estrés postraumático, desde la perspectiva del diagnóstico y del tratamiento. Ambos grupos de trastornos polarizan el debate sobre las categorías diagnósticas con síntomas disociativos. Se revisan las ideas sobre disociación, hipnosis y suicidio asociadas a estos trastornos. Parece darse una falta de consenso en cuanto a la naturaleza misma de la disociación con implicaciones teóricas, empíricas y clínicas. Completa esta revisión la comparación desde sus inicios, hace poco más de un siglo, con el panorama actual y las nuevas tendencias en las investigaciones que desde las neurociencias están relacionando los procesos cognitivos con los fenómenos y trastornos disociativos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;32(2): 448-456, mayo 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-151698</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una revisión de los trastornos disociativos: de la personalidad múltiple al estrés postraumático</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4274^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7167^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54296</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13701^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
