<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124822</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-1285</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of burning mouth. New trends</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this review will tackle treatment SBA. Because the exact etiopathogenesis is unknown, treatment is directed toward symptom management. The aim is: Treat the processes associated with burning mouth or eliminating local irritants (snuff, alcohol, spicy foods and acidic beverages, cutting edges, xerostomia, dysgeusia, parafunctions, bruxism, chewing or sucking mucous, oral parafunctional habits, mechanical irritation, unadjusted dentures or allergies to dental materials) as these can increase the burning. Prevent and treat disease or disorder of the oral mucosa. On the other hand should be treated and/or remit psychopathological processes. Just listen carefully to the patient and explain the reason for their discomfort usually calm the patient and reduce the symptoms so a periodic assessment every 6 months is advised. The treatment is based on four therapeutic possibilities: Dental: locally conservative and hygienic (polish-rounded cusps or sharp edges; make prosthetic treatment, the use of physical barriers such as gels or dental dams); Pharmacological, Psychological: depression and anxiety play an important role in modulating pain perception, have been demonstrated in these patients alterations of the central nervous system and the peripheral nervous system so that the use of antidepressants have been justified psychoactive drugs, including topical clonazepam (Rivotril®) with a 50% improvement in symptoms. Given the poor results in the treatment of the condition have been proposed a number of Alternative treatments to try to control it, which have apparent beneficial results: infrared, low level laser applied in the area reported by the patient, with herbal medicine analgesic and antidepressant effects, with improvement in 52% of patients, aloe vera, acupuncture and cognitive-behavioral treatment to help reduce anxiety. Given that neither treatment is definitive or universal, we can conclude that there are effective treatments some cases, but many others are still looking for a method to be effective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>De Luca Monasterios, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de Rivera, Campillo ME</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la presente revisión, abordaremos el tratamiento del SBA. Dado que desconocemos con exactitud la etiopatogenia, el tratamiento suele orientarse hacia el manejo de los síntomas. Se pretende: Tratar los procesos relacionados con ardor bucal eliminando los factores locales o irritantes (tabaco, alcohol, comidas picantes y bebidas ácidas, aristas cortantes, xerostomía, disgeusia, parafunciones, bruxismo, mordisqueo o succión de mucosas, hábitos parafuncionales orales, irritación mecánica, prótesis desajustadas o alergia a materiales dentales) ya que estos pueden aumentan el ardor. Prevenir y tratar alteraciones o lesiones sobre la mucosa bucal. Por otro lado se deben tratar y/o remitir procesos psicopatológicos. El hecho de escuchar con atención al paciente y explicarle el motivo de sus molestias suele calmar al paciente y disminuir los síntomas por lo que se aconseja una evaluación de forma periódica cada 6 meses. El tratamiento se basa en cuatro posibilidades terapéuticas: Odontológico: local-conservador e higiénico (pulir-redondear cúspides o aristas cortantes; realizar tratamiento protésico, la utilización de barreras físicas como geles o protectores dentales); Farmacológicos, Psicológicos: la depresión y la ansiedad desempeñan un papel importante en la modulación de la percepción del dolor, se han evidenciado en estos pacientes alteraciones del sistema nervioso central y del sistema nervioso periférico por lo que el uso de fármacos psicoactivos antidepresivos se han justificado, entre ellos el clonacepam tópico (Rivotril®), con una mejoría del 50% de los síntomas. Dados los escasos resultados obtenidos en el tratamiento del cuadro, se han propuesto una serie de tratamientos Alternativos para intentar controlarlo, los cuales han tenido aparentes resultados beneficiosos: infrarrojos, el láser de baja intensidad aplicado en la zona referida por el paciente, la fitoterapia con efectos analgésicos y antidepresivos, con mejoría del 52% de los pacientes, el aloe vera, la acupuntura y el tratamiento cognitivo-conductual que ayuda a reducir la ansiedad. Teniendo en cuenta que ninguno de los tratamientos es definitivo ni universal, podemos concluir que existen tratamientos eficaces para algunos de los casos, pero en otros muchos se sigue buscando un procedimiento que resulte eficaz (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av Odontoestomatol;30(3): 139-143, mayo-jun. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124822</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento del ardor bucal y de la boca seca. Nuevas tendencias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15386^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36294^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7676^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19609^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10090^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2086^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
