<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89577</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors of the caregiver that influence the fulfillment of the elegant basic ones of the humbled user</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The number of postrados users it increases; only one part of the cares that they require is provided by the sanitary professionals, most are being taken care of in its familiar and communitarian surroundings, being from it, often, cares inadequate. Objective: To associate factors of the caregiver with the fulfillment of the basic cares of the postrado user. Methodology: Quantitative, descriptive, analytical, corelational study of cross section. Population of study: 98 caregiver pertaining to Centers of Health of Chillán- Chile. Results: I determine that most of the caregiver of postrados users, they moderately fulfill the cares basic that the patient needs, present/display an intense overload and exists evidence to affirm that the factors of the informal caretaker that influence in the fulfillment of the basic cares they are: age, schooling, time in charge of the patient and nontransmissible chronic diseases without anxiety symptoms (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Luengo Martínez, Carolina Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araneda Pagliotti, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Espinoza, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El número de usuarios postrados va en aumento; sólo una parte de los cuidados que requieren es proporcionada por los profesionales sanitarios, la mayor parte están siendo atendidos en su entorno familiar y comunitario, resultando de ello, muchas veces, un cuidado inadecuado. Objetivo: asociar factores del cuidador familiar con el cumplimiento de los cuidados básicos del usuario postrado. Metodología: estudio cuantitativo, descriptivo, analítico, correlacional de corte transversal. Población de estudio: 98 cuidadores familiares pertenecientes a Centros de Salud de Chillán-Chile. Resultados: se determinó que la mayoría de los cuidadores familiares de usuarios postrados, cumplen moderadamente los cuidados básicos que necesita el paciente, presentan una sobrecarga intensa y existe evidencia para afirmar que los factores del cuidador familiar que influyen en el cumplimiento de los cuidados básicos son: edad, escolaridad, tiempo a cargo del paciente y enfermedades crónicas no transmisibles sin síntomas de ansiedad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;19(1): 14-18, ene.-mar. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89577</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores del cuidador familiar que influyen en el cumplimiento de los cuidados básicos del usuario postrado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32193^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6858^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
