<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152336</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7709</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalencia of diabetic neuropathy signs in a simple of type 2 diabetics from the Health Area of Ferrol</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is actually estimated that diabetic complications have millionaire costs. The American Diabetes Association believes that in 2007 direct and indirect costs of Diabetes Mellitus were about 174 billion dollars in the U.S. One of the risk factors identified by the ADA involved in the development of the diabetic foot syndrome is diabetic neuropathy. Its complex diagnosis is due in part to the very few symptoms displayed and because of the little attention payed in the clinical examination. All these factors difficult its early diagnosis and in consequence setting up an appropriate treatment and a new healthy lifestyle avoiding long-term complications. For these reasons new simple, inexpensive, ambulatory diagnostic tools are necessary. In this cross-sectional study the authors have identified diabetic neuropathic signs (sensory and autonomic signs) using the graduated Rydel-Seiffer tuning fork and a new visual test (Neuropad®) based on the assessment of the foot sweat glands function in 181 type 2 diabetic patients (according to ADA criteria). Furthermore, prevalence of three cardiovascular risk factors was evaluated: arterial hypertension, hypertriglyceridemia and a pathological ankle brachial index. Prevalence of neuropathic signs using the graduated Rydel-Seiffer tuning fork was 79%. In contrast, using Neuropad® test the prevalence of sudomotor dysfunction compatible with peripherical affection of the autonomic nervous system was 64,6%. In the whole sample, we have found a high prevalence of cardiovascular risk factors associated with Diabetes Mellitus: 60,7% prevalence of arterial hypertension, S7,4% prevalence of hypertriglyceridemia and a 68,5% prevalence of pathological ankle brachial index (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bellido, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mantiñán, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellido, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mosquera, Abián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreira, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vale, María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las actuales cifras hablan de costes millonarios para el tratamiento de las complicaciones de la Diabetes Mellitus (DM). Concretamente, la Asociación Americana de Diabetes (ADA) estima que en 2007 los costes directos e indirectos derivados de la DM en EE.UU ascendieron a 174 billones de dólares. De entre los factores de riesgo identificados por la ADA implicados en el desarrollo del pie diabético la neuropatía diabética periférica (NDP) se ha revelado como una afección de difícil diagnostico debido en gran parte a la escasez de sintomatología con que se presenta. Este hecho sumado a la poca atención que generalmente se le presta en la exploración clínica dificulta su pronta identificación y en consecuencia retrasa el tratamiento y la modificación de hábitos que eviten a largo plazo complicaciones mayores. Por estos motivos son cada Vez mas necesarias nuevas herramientas de diagnóstico precoz que puedan ser empleadas ambulatoriamente en la consulta.  En el presente trabajo los autores han identificado signos de neuropatía diabética (componente sensitivo y autónomo) en una muestra de 181 diabéticos tipo 2 según criterios de la ADA de 2004 pertenecientes al Área Sanitaria de Ferrol empleando el diapasón graduado Rydel Seiffer y un nuevo test Visual (Neuropad®) de Valoración de la función sudoral del pie. Además se ha evaluado la presencia de tres factores de riesgo cardiovascular asociados a la diabetes mellitus tales como hipertensión arterial, hipertrigliceridemia y un índice tobillo-brazo patológico. La prevalencia de dé&amp;#64257;cit de sensibilidad vibratoria utilizando el diapasón graduado Rydel Seiffer fue del 79%, en tanto que mediante el test Neuropad® las cifras de prevalencia de disfunción sudoral compatible con la afectación periférica del sistema nervioso autónomo fut: del 64,6%. En el total de la muestra se ha hallado una elevada prevalencia de factores de riesgo cardiovascular asociados a la diabetes mellitus: hipertensión arterial (60,7%), hipertrigliceridemia (57,4%) e índice tobillo-brazo patológico (68,5%) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Peu;31(4): 182-188, oct.-dic. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152336</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de signos de neuropatía diabética en una muestra de diabéticos tipo 2 del Área Sanitaria de Ferrol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13926^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13926^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13926^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53218^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11462^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13926^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53218^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3952^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
