<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055090</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional support in patients with open abdomen</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: We have designed a protocol to evaluate the        tolerance, effectiveness and the nutritional support in        post-surgical patients with an open abdomen.        Patients and methods: We have made a prospective        descriptive study of patients submitted to surgery and        left with an open abdomen with a Bogotá bag, and have        received nutritional support. The patients who have        stayed for less than 4 days with the open abdomen where        excluded. A group received total parenteral nutrition        (TPN) with mixtures all in one; another group received        enteral nutrition (EN) through a needle catheter        jejunostomy (NCJ) and a third group received mixed        nutritional support. To evaluate the tolerance to EN,        we have included those patients receiving this type of        nutrition for at least 4 consecutive days without        having diarrhea or pain. A jejunostomy catheter was        placed in all patients by need o puncturing during the        surgical act.        Setting: The Surgical Department I of Ángel Larralde        University Hospital, I.V.S.S. Valencia - Venezuela, during        the period from May 2002 to May 2005.        Results: 24 patients entered the study, 46% recived        mixed nutritional support (Enteral and Parenteral),        33% exclusively TPN, and 31% exclusively EN. 75% have        evolved favorably, discharged to their home in good        general condition; 25% died from multiple organ failure        due to severe sepsis.        About nutritional support, 66% of the patients did        not present complications; 21% of those receiving TPN        presented hyperglycemia; and 13% of those receiving        EN presented diarrhea. About EN effectiveness, 69% of        the patients have reached 80% of the estimated caloric        objective within days 4-5 from the beginning of formula        administration.        Conclusions: The integral care of the patients with an        open abdomen, added to a nutritional support regimen        tailored to each patient&#146;s condition can help decreasing the hypermetabolic response, as well as moridity and        mortality</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guedez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velázquez G, JO</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cadenas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas U, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbistazu, JP</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: El soporte nutricional es fundamental en        los pacientes con trauma severo para disminuir los efectos        de la respuesta inflamatoria sistémica y el hipermetabolismo.        Se diseñó un protocolo para evaluar la tolerancia        y eficacia y del soporte nutricional, así como la        evolución clínica en los pacientes post-operados con abdomen        abierto.        Pacientes y métodos: Se realizó un estudio descriptivo,        prospectivo de pacientes intervenidos quirúrgicamente a        quienes se les dejó el abdomen abierto con bolsa de Bogotá        y recibieron soporte nutricional. Fueron excluidos        del estudio aquellos pacientes que permanecieron menos        de 4 días con el abdomen abierto. Un grupo recibió nutrición        parenteral total (NPT) con mezclas tres en uno,        otro grupo recibió nutrición enteral a través de yeyunostomía        con aguja y catéter y un tercer grupo recibió soporte        nutricional mixto.        Ambiente: Servicio de Cirugía I del Hospital Universitario        Ángel Larralde. IVSS Valencia (Venezuela). Período        del estudio entre mayo del 2002 a mayo del 2005.        Resultados: Ingresaron 24 pacientes al estudio, 46%        recibió soporte nutricional mixto (enteral y parenteral),        33% exclusivamente NPT y 31% exclusivamente nutrición        enteral. 75% evolucionaron favorablemente egresando        al domicilio en buenas condiciones generales, 25%        fallecieron debido a falla múltiple de órganos por sepsis        severa.        En relación al soporte nutricional, 66% de los pacientes        no presentaron complicaciones, de los que recibieron        nutrición parenteral 21% presentaron hiperglicemia y        de los que recibieron nutrición enteral 13% presentaron        diarrea. En cuanto a la eficacia de la nutrición enteral        69% de los pacientes alcanzaron el 80% de la meta calórica estimada entre el 4º y 5º día del inicio de la administración        de la fórmula.        Conclusión: El cuidado integral de los pacientes con        abdomen abierto, sumado a un esquema de soporte nutricional        que se ajuste las condiciones de cada paciente        puede ayudar a disminuir la respuesta hipermetabólica        así como la morbilidad y mortalidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;22(2): 217-222, mar.-abr. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055090</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Soporte nutricional en pacientes con abdomen abierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22926^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13886^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
