<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88551</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Paramedian Forehead Flap for the Reconstruction of Extensive Nasal Defects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The Department of Dermatology at Hospital Universitario de Guadalajara in Spain is a referral center for Mohs micrographic surgery. Consequently, we are regularly faced with the problem of repairing large surgical defects on the nose. The paramedian forehead flap is currently one of the techniques of choice for the repair of such defects.                              Materials and methods: We review our experience in the repair of nasal defects using the paramedian forehead flap over the period from 2004 to 2008. We describe the surgical technique, complications, and final results. Results: Ten patients (mean age, 75.1 years) were treated using this flap. Two patients also required cartilage grafts and reconstruction of the internal nasal lining. The most common complications were bleeding (60%) and partial necrosis (10%). The final cosmetic and functional results were considered good or excellent in 90% of cases. Conclusions: The forehead flap continues to be one of the best options for the closure of surgical defects of the nasal pyramid larger than 2 cm. Adequate knowledge and careful application of the technique allows excellent results to be obtained with few complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Belmar, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juanes, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vergara, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Eusebio, E. de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El Servicio de Dermatología del Hospital Universitario de Guadalajara es un centro de referencia en cirugía de Mohs, por lo que con cierta frecuencia nos vemos enfrentados al problema de la reconstrucción de defectos quirúrgicos nasales de gran tamaño. El colgajo frontonasal paramedial está considerado en la actualidad como una de las técnicas de elección en la reconstrucción de defectos nasales extensos. Material y métodos: Revisamos nuestra experiencia en la reconstrucción nasal mediante el colgajo fronto-nasal paramediano entre los años 2004 y 2008. Describimos la técnica quirúrgica, las complicaciones y los resultados finales. Resultados: Diez pacientes con una media de edad de 75,1 años fueron reconstruidos mediante este colgajo. Un 20% requirió además injertos cartilaginosos y reconstrucción de la cobertura nasal interna. Las complicaciones más frecuentes fueron el sangrado (60%) y la necrosis parcial (10%). Los resultados finales, tanto estéticos como funcionales, fueron considerados buenos o excelentes en el 90% de los pacientes. Conclusiones: El colgajo fronto-nasal sigue siendo una de las mejores alternativas para el cierre de defectos quirúrgicos mayores de 2 cm localizados en la pirámide nasal. El conocimiento de su técnica y su realización cuidadosa permite obtener excelentes resultados con pocas complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;102(3): 197-192, abr. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88551</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Colgajo fronto-nasal paramedial en la reconstrucción de defectos nasales extensos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28200^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35420^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33584^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
