<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142468</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Vitamin D deficiency among children and adolescents with normal nutritional status</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze the prevalence of vitamin D deficiency throughout a natural year in a pediatric population with normal nutrition status. Material and methods: cross sectional clinical and analytical study (calcium, phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase, calcidiol and parathyroid hormone) in 413 caucasian individuals (aged 3.1 to 15.4 years): 227 school children (96 males and 131 females) and 186 adolescents (94 males and 92 females), all of them in a normal nutrition status, during the year 2014. Vitamin D deficiency was defined according to the United States Endocrine Society guidelines. Results: calcidiol levels were lower during spring (25.96 ± 6.64 ng/ml) and reached its maximum level in summer (35.33 ± 7.51 ng/ml); PTH levels were lower in summer (27.13 ± 7.89 pg/ml) and reached maximum level in autumn (34.73 ± 15.38 pg/ml). Vitamin D deficiency prevalence was 14.3% in summer and 75.3% in spring. PTH levels were compatible with secondary hyperparathyroidism in 8 individuals (1.9%). There was a negative correlation between calcidol and PTH levels (p &lt; 0.01). There was not a correlation between body mass index (BMI) and calcidiol. Conclusion: the pediatric population in normal nutrition status shows a high prevalence of vitamin D deficiency during the months of autumn and winter and, especially, in spring; the addition of vitamin supplements and/ or an increase in the ingestion of their natural dietary sources should be considered (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallinas-Victoriano, Fidel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chueca Guindulain, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Berrade-Zubiri, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Durá-Travé, Teodoro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar la prevalencia de la deficiencia de vitamina D a lo largo de un año natural en una población pediátrica con un estado nutricional normal. Material y métodos: estudio transversal clínico y analítico (calcio, fósforo, fosfatasa alcalina, calcidiol y hormona paratiroidea) en 413 sujetos (entre 3,1 y 15,4 años): 227 escolares (96 varones y 131 mujeres) y 186 adolescentes (94 varones y 92 mujeres), de raza caucásica y estado nutricional normal, durante el año 2014. Para definir la deficiencia de vitamina D se han aplicado los criterios de la Sociedad Americana de Endocrinología. Resultados: los niveles de calcidiol eran más bajos en primavera (25,96 ± 6,64 ng/ml) y alcanzaban su máximo nivel en verano (35,33 ± 7,51 ng/ml); mientras que los de PTH eran más bajos en verano (27,13 ± 7,89 pg/ml) y alcanzaban su máximo nivel en otoño (34,73 ± 15,38 pg/ml). La prevalencia de deficiencia de vitamina D era del 14,3% en verano y del 75,3% en primavera. En 8 casos (1,9%) existían cifras de PTH compatibles con hiperparatiroidismo secundario. Existía una correlación negativa entre calcidiol y PTH (p &lt; 0,01). No existía correlación entre IMC y calcidiol. Conclusión: en la población pediátrica con una situacion nutricional normal existe una alta prevalencia de deficiencia de vitamina D en los meses de otoño e invierno y, especialmente, en primavera, y habría que considerar la necesidad de administrar suplementos vitamínicos y/o ingerir mayores cantidades de sus fuentes dietéticas naturales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(3): 1061-1066, sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Deficiencia de vitamina D en escolares y adolescentes con un estado nutricional normal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52504</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15210^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
