<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044413</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Carcinoma of the fallopian tube: a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The case of a 43-years old woman with previous history of mental retardation and major depressive syndrome, consulting for metrorrhagia is presented. At physical examination a right adnexal mass was detected on palpation. Transvaginal echography showed a 3-cavity cyst in right ovary. A surgical intervention with total hysterectomy and dual adnexectomy was performed. Pathological study showed proliferative endometrium, bilateral follicular cysts and well differentiated serous adenocarcinoma located at fallopian tube. The patient refused adyuvant chemotherapy, a close follow-up is ongoing in outpatient Oncology Unit. Then some epidemiologic, etiologic, clinica, diagnostic and therapeutic issues related to this rare tumour are discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Díaz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez Ucelay, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viana Alonso, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos Sánchez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albo Castaño, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marrupe González, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 43 años de edad, con antecedentes personales de retraso mental y síndrome depresivo mayor, que consultó por metrorragias. A la exploración física se palpaba una masa anexial derecha. En la ecografía transvaginal se observó un quiste en el ovario derecho con 3 cavidades. Se decidió realizar intervención quirúrgica, efectuándose una histerectomía total con doble anexectomía. El resultado de la anatomía patológica fue de endometrio proliferativo, quistes foliculares bilaterales y adenocarcinoma seroso bien deferenciado de la trompa de Falopio. La paciente rechazó la realización de tratamiento con quimioterapia adyuvante y se está efectuando un seguimiento estrecho de la misma en las consultas de Oncología. Posteriormente comentamos algunos aspectos epidemiológicos, etiológicos, clínicos, diagnósticos y terapéuticos de esta rara tumoración</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;23(2): 83-85, feb. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un caso de carcinoma de trompa de Falopio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5286^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5286^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30193</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5286^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
