<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115510</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dandy-Walker complex associated with multiple congenital malformations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Dandy-Walker complex is a sporadic congenital malformation of the midbrain dysmorphogenesis that involves a variable degree of anatomical abnormalities mainly in the cerebellum and fourth ventricle. This syndrome can be associated with other malformations. The presence of other anomalies is associated with significantly higher neurological morbidity and neonatal mortality. We report the case of a pregnant Moroccan woman who did not attend the 20th week ultrasound prenatal visit. The third trimester ultrasound scan showed intrauterine growth retardation, Dandy-Walker syndrome, and deformities of the extremities (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Redondo Llorente, M. Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quesada Segura, Gonzalo E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mancha Heredero, Elvira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantos García, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez Camino, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Valdés, Elsa M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El complejo Dandy-Walker es una malformación congénita esporádica originada por una disembriogénesis del cerebro medio, que conlleva un grado variable de alteraciones anatómicas en el cerebelo y el cuarto ventrículo principalmente. Puede estar asociado o no a otras malformaciones. La presencia de otras anomalías se asocia a un aumento significativo de la morbilidad neurológica y la mortalidad neonatal. Presentamos el caso de una gestante marroquí que no acude al control ecográfico de la semana 20, en la ecografía del tercer trimestre se objetiva un retraso de crecimiento intrauterino precoz, síndrome Dandy-Walker y malformaciones en las extremidades (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);56(7): 374-377, ago.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115510</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complejo Dandy-Walker asociado a síndrome polimalformativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3635^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31341^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d664^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5428^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3635^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31341^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3635^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3635^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
