<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118417</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prader-Willi syndrome. Presentation of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We report the case of a term infant of 39+1, born by emergency cesarean section due to suspected fetal distress with an Apgar test 4/6/8 and axial hypotonia with weak reflexes. After 52 days of hospitalization an individualized care plan was developed and applied based on Marjory Gordon's functional patterns model and NANDA domains. We used the NANDA diagnoses, interventions according to nursing interventions classification (NIC), and the expected results as classified by nursing outcomes (NOC). Through the care plan, the identified diagnoses and potential complications were resolved. Progress was slow but favorable, stimulating sucking and achieving a good breastfeeding latch, with an appropriate weight gain, decreased muscle stiffness, and increased response to stimuli (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jiménez Vaquero, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Domingo, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montilla-Pérez, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Lomas, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presenta el caso de un recién nacido a término de 39+1; nació por cesárea urgente por sospecha de pérdida de bienestar fetal, con un test de Apgar de 4/6/8 e hipotonía axial con reflejos débiles. Tras 52 días de ingreso se desarrolló y aplicó un plan de cuidados individualizado basado en los patrones funcionales de Marjory Gordon y dominios NANDA. Se han utilizado los diagnósticos NANDA, las intervenciones según la clasificación de intervenciones de enfermería (NIC) y los resultados esperados según la clasificación de resultados (NOC).A través de este plan de cuidados, se resolvieron los diagnósticos identificados y las complicaciones potenciales. La evolución fue lenta pero favorable, consiguiendo estimular la succión y un buen enganche al pecho, con un adecuado aumento de peso, disminución de la rigidez muscular y mayor respuesta a estímulos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);23(6): 290-297, dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118417</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de Prader-Willi. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32270^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11655^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
