<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-91828</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Bion(r) Activate: Usefulness in individuals with vernal asthenia. Results of an observational study performed in 2010 on a labour population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Asthenia is a frequent symptom in the modern Western societies, and it is not always a symptom or manifestation of an underlying disease. Vernal asthenia might be considered a manifestation of the so-called &#147;seasonal affective disorder&#148;, and is characterized by  seasonal variations in mood and vitality. The possible therapeutic measures proposed range from exposure to light to maintenance of a healthy or health-promoting lifestyle or reducing undue overactivity. We here present the results of an observational study performed  in 2010 with the aim to document the effects of an alimentary complement (BION® Activate) in individuals with vernal asthenia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alberic, X</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La astenia es un síntoma frecuente en la sociedad occidental moderna y no siempre es síntoma o manifestación de alguna enfermedad. La astenia primaveral podría considerarse una manifestación del llamado &#147;trastorno afectivo estacional&#148;, que se caracteriza por variaciones en el estado de ánimo y la vitalidad según   la estación del año. Las soluciones propuestas para su tratamiento abarcan desde la exposición a la luz hasta el mantenimiento de hábitos de vida saludables o el apaciguamiento del ritmo de vida. Presentamos aquí los resultados de un estudio observacional desarrollado en 2010 para documentar los efectos de un complemento  alimentario (BION® Activate) en individuos con astenia primaveral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;20(1): 9-13, abr. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-91828</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">BION® Activate: su utilidad en personas con astenia primaveral. Resultados del estudio observacional en una población laboral en 2010. Conclusiones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1255^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29823^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32687^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201104</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
