<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164261</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Aggressive mandibular tumours in children: reconstruction with titanium plates (report of 3 cases)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Tumours of the facial region in children are rare, but the damage they cause in tissues leads to changes in the development and growth of the face, causing physical, aesthetic and psychological disorders. The histopathological origin of lesions is variable, but they are often locally aggressive, not corresponding to their benign histological appearance. To reach a correct diagnosis is important to determine the clinical and image characteristics presented by each lesion. A proper biopsy must be taken, as well as having a histopathologist with experience in recognising these tumours, since the correct treatment to be performed depends on this. The aim of the treatment is the resection of the lesion, restoring function and facial aesthetics and, where possible, to promote the growth of the defected anatomical structures. This article reports 3 cases of tumours in paediatric patients, rare and of histological different lineages, but with the same local aggressiveness, treated in the high speciality hospital number 71 of the Mexican Security Institute, Torreón, Coahuila, Mexico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mercado Montañez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los tumores de la región facial en niños son poco frecuentes pero el daño que ocasionan en los tejidos modifica el desarrollo y crecimiento de la cara, ocasionando alteraciones físicas, estéticas y psicológicas. El origen histopatológico de las lesiones es variable, pero la conducta local de las mismas suele ser agresiva, no correspondiendo en muchas ocasiones a su «benigna» apariencia histológica. Para llegar a un diagnóstico correcto es importante conocer características clínicas y de imagen que presenta cada lesión, realizar una adecuada toma de biopsia, además de contar con histopatólogos de experiencia en el reconocimiento de estos tumores, ya que de ello depende el correcto tratamiento a realizar. El objetivo del tratamiento es la resección de la lesión, restaurando función y estética facial y de ser posible, favorecer el crecimiento de las estructuras anatómicas afectadas. En este artículo se reportan 3 casos de tumores en pacientes pediátricos, de diferente estirpe histopatológica y de poca frecuencia, pero con la misma agresividad local, tratados en el Hospital de Alta Especialidad (UMAE) 134, del Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social, Torreón, Coahuila, México (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;39(3): 150-155, jul.-sept. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164261</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumores mandibulares de conducta agresiva en pacientes pediátricos reconstruidos con placas de titanio (reporte de 3 casos)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8513^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55068^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31224^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24235^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55068^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31224^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14414^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23942^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8506^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
