<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79151</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adequacy of the preventive treatment of osteoporotic fractures in postmenopausal women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Objective. To assess the adequacy of preventive treatments of osteoporotic fractures in postmenopausal women of our health care area.Material and methodsDesign. Cross-sectional, descriptive study. Primary care setting: Health Care Center Puerto Real. Participants. A total of 310 postmenopausal women receiving treatment with antiresorptive drugs in the year 2008. Main measurements. Adequate pharmacological prescription, if they fulfill any of the following criteria: background of fragility fractures, BMD T score &lt;=&amp;#8722;2.5 and T score from &amp;#8722;2.0 to &amp;#8722;2.5 plus at least one of the following: BMI&lt;19Kg/m2, precocious menopause and background of maternal hip fracture. Use of the first choice drug. We consider it adequate if the drug prescribed was alendronic acid in isolated presentation.ResultsThe treatment adequacy was 25.4% (95% CI: 20.6&#150;30.2), 25.7 % (95% CI: 20.08&#150;30.6) in that originated by the family doctor and 36.5 % (95% CI: 31.2&#150;41.8) in that induced from another specialty (OR 1.685; 95% CI: 0.944&#150;3.010). A total of 56.5% took alendronic acid in isolate presentation, 54% of the prescriptions came from the family doctor and 60% were made from another specialty (OR 1,049; 95% CI: 0.617&#150;1.784). Annual cost for inadequate prescriptions reached 90,740&#128; in our basic health area.ConclusionsThe adequacy of the antiresorptive drug prescriptions is below the desired level. No significant differences were observed in the degree of adequacy between the prescription given by the family doctor and that given in other specialties. The prescription quality is related to the recording of the osteoporosis diagnosis and the origin of the prescription in the clinical history (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lendínez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amaya, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Objetivo. Valorar la adecuación de los tratamientos preventivos de fracturas osteoporóticas en mujeres posmenopáusicas de nuestra zona de salud.Material y métodosDiseño. Descriptivo transversal. Emplazamiento. Atención primaria, Centro de Salud de Puerto Real. Participantes. 310 mujeres posmenopáusicas en tratamiento con fármacos antirresortivo en el año 2008. Mediciones principales. Prescripción farmacológica adecuada, si se cumple alguno de los siguientes criterios: historia de fracturas por fragilidad, DMO T score &lt;=&amp;#8722;2,5 y T score de &amp;#8722;2,0 a &amp;#8722;2,5 más al menos uno de: IMC&lt;19kg/m2, menopausia precoz y antecedente materno de fractura de cadera. Uso del fármaco de primera elección. Consideramos adecuado si el fármaco prescrito fue ácido alendrónico en presentación aislada.ResultadosLa indicación de tratamiento fue del 25,4% (IC 95%: 20,6&#150;30,2), 25,7% (IC 95%: 20,08&#150;30,6) en la originada por el médico de familia y 36,5% (IC 95%: 31,2&#150;41,8) en la inducida desde otra especialidad (OR 1,685; IC 95%: 0,944&#150;3,010). El 56,5% tomaba ácido alendrónico como principio activo único, 54% de las prescripciones originadas por el médico de familia y 60% de las inducidas (OR 1,049; IC 95%: 0,617&#150;1,784). El gasto anual por prescripción inadecuada asciende a 90.740&#128; en nuestra zona de salud.ConclusionesLa calidad de la prescripción de fármacos antirresortivos está por debajo del nivel deseable. No se aprecian diferencias significativas en el grado de adecuación entre la prescripción del médico de familia y la inducida por otras especialidades. La calidad de la prescripción se relaciona con el registro del diagnóstico de osteoporosis y del origen de la prescripción en la historia clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);36(3): 121-127, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79151</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adecuación del tratamiento preventivo de fracturas osteoporóticas en mujeres posmenopáusicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5298^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31161^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
