<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148207</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Simple discrimination training and conditional discrimination response</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The conditional discrimination is a procedure the use of which is widely extended in the EAB (Experimental Analysis of Behavior), especially those known as &#147;Matching to Sample&#148;. Although it has been used with a wide variety of species, the behavior of humans with verbal skills in these kinds of tasks may involve other control variables which are different from the scheduled contingencies of four terms. The aim of this work was to verify if conditional discriminations could be acquired, although reinforcement contingencies did not involve the sample. 109 psychology students, who were divided into three conditions, participated in the study. All of them were exposed to two blocks of training (A and B), with one sample and three comparisons, however, the sample did not really function as a conditional stimulus in 75% of the trials in block B. Simultaneity between sample and comparisons, as well as the requirement of a sample observation response, were manipulated resulting in three different conditions. The results showed no differences between acquisition speed in block A and block B in any condition, which suggests that the behavior of the participants was more controlled by the stimuli configuration than by the reinforcement contingencies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Polín, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La discriminación condicional es un procedimiento cuyo uso está ampliamente extendido en el AEC (Análisis Experimental del Comportamiento), especialmente las denominadas &#147;Igualaciones a la Muestra&#148;. Aunque se ha puesto en práctica con una amplia variedad de especies, el comportamiento de humanos con competencias verbales en este tipo de tareas puede involucrar otras variables de control diferentes a las contingencias de cuatro términos programadas. El objetivo de este trabajo fue comprobar si se podían adquirir discriminaciones condicionales aunque las contingencias de refuerzo no involucrasen a la muestra. Participaron 109 alumnos de psicología que fueron distribuidos en tres condiciones. Todos fueron expuestos a dos bloques de entrenamiento (A y B) con una muestra y tres comparaciones, no obstante, en el 75% de los ensayos del bloque B la muestra no funcionaba realmente como un estímulo condicional. Se manipularon la simultaneidad muestra-comparaciones y el requerimiento de respuesta de observación a la muestra, dando lugar a tres condiciones diferentes. Los resultados no mostraron diferencias entre la velocidad de adquisición del bloque A y del B en ninguna condición, lo que apunta a que el comportamiento de los participantes estaba más controlado por la configuración estimular que por las contingencias de reforzamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;32(1): 250-255, ene. 2016. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148207</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Entrenamiento de discriminación simple y respuesta de discriminación condicional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4252</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37555^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12476</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
