<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118266</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Iodine supplementation during pregnancy and lactation. Position statement of the working group on disorders related to iodine deficiency and thyroid dysfunction of the Spanish Society of Endocrinology and Nutrition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Severe and mild iodine deficiency during pregnancy and lactation affects thyroid function of the mother and neonate as well as the infant's neuropsychological development. Studies performed in Spain confirm that most women are iodine deficient during pregnancy and lactation. Pregnant and breast feeding women and women planning to become pregnant should take iodine supplements (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de Trabajo sobre Trastornos relacionados con la Deficiencia de Yodo y Disfunción Tiroidea de la Sociedad Espa&#152;nola de Endocrinología y Nutrición</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La deficiencia de yodo grave y moderada durante el embarazo y la lactancia afecta a la función tiroidea de la madre y del neonato, así como al desarrollo neuropsicológico del niño. Estudios realizados en España confirman que la mayoría de las mujeres se encuentran en yododeficiencia durante la gestación y la lactancia. Las mujeres embarazadas, las que amamantan a sus hijos y las que planifican su gestación deberían recibir suplementos de yodo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;61(1): 27-34, ene. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118266</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Suplementación con yodo durante el embarazo y la lactancia. Toma de posición del Grupo de Trabajo de Trastornos relacionados con la Deficiencia de Yodo y Disfunción Tiroidea de la Sociedad Española de Endocrinología y Nutrición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7619^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14347^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14348^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16596^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33546^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11688^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
