<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76616</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the utility of a nutrition education program with ealing disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: As eating disorders include both psychological and physiological components, appropriate management of these disorders requires input from a number of disciplines working together in a coordinated manner, following an integrated Programme. The Eating Disorders-Nutrition Education Programme has as its purpose achieving healthier habits and modifying eating behaviour. The Programme should take place as one part of Eating Disorders treatment. Objectives: To determine the efficacy of a Nutrition Education Programme about nutritional state and eating patterns in a group of patients diagnosed with Eating Disorders who follow the usual check-up protocol in the clinic for nutrition and mental health. Material and methods: 89 patients were included, including 5% men. They received individual nutritional education with weekly/fortnightly appointments during a period of 4-6 months. Educational counseling was carried out by a dietician. The mean age of the sample was 24 ± 8 years and the diagnoses were: Anorexia Nervosa Restrictive (ANR) 32.5% Anorexia Nervosa Purgative (ANP) 26.5%, Bulimia Nervosa (BN) 18%, Eating Disorder Not Otherwise Specified (EDNOS) 21% and Binge Eating Disorder (BED) 2%. The average evolution time since the diagnosis was 4.8 ± 5 years. An anthropometric assessment, assessment of daily oral intake, 24-hour dietary recall, and Eating Attitudes Test (EAT26) questionnaires were completed at the first appointment and again at the end of the programme. Results: The mean score of the EAT26 questionnaire was 32 ± 15 initially, and after 4-6 months the score was 23.7 ± 14 (p &lt; 0.001). This change represents a significant improvement in the patients' symptoms after the Programme. Furthermore there were significant differences in the evaluation of the questionnaire by scales and by diagnosis. After 4-6 months, there was a meaningful reduction in episodes of vomiting per week (from 7.5 ± 10 to 1 ± 1.8 p &lt; 0.001) in ANP and BN binge-purging (8 ± 9.7 vs 2.2 ± 3.2 p &lt; 0,01). In addition, a favourable trend in the number of binges per week was observed for both diagnoses. The percentage of subjects that ate less than 4 meals per day decreased from 70% to 19% after the Education Programme (p &lt; 0.001). Some 67% of the patients dedicated a specific time for eating and a 54% started to have complete meals. These results that show a very favourable tendency with respect to the normalization of eating patterns. There was improvement in the intake of dairy products, vegetables, fruits, cereals and oil (p &lt; 0.05). At the beginning, 34% consumed at least 3 of the 6 food groups within the recommended range, but at the end 70% did (p &lt; 0.001). After the nutritional education programme, an important increase in energy ingestion and carbonhydrate consumption took place (p &lt; 0.001), as much with ANR as with ANP. With respect to micronutrients, the ingestion of vitamin B2 significantly increased, as well as folic acid and calcium (p &lt; 0.001) in ANP, and magnesium and calcium (p &lt; 0.001) in ANR. In ANR, we found a significant improvement in nutritional status (p &lt; 0.001). Variables including weight, BMI, muscular circumference of the arm and tricipetal fold were at the limit of significance. Regarding ANP and EDNOS, the initial evaluation demonstrated that they were within normal limits, and they were maintained after nutritional education. In BN, progress towards normalization of BMI took place, increasing from 26.4 ± 6.6 to 25.5 ± 5.7 (-2.3 kg). Conclusions: The Nutritional Education Programme carried out by qualified professionals should be a part of Eating Disorders treatment, along with medical and psychological monitoring and as part of an interdisciplinary, multiprofessional team effort (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Torres, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zurita, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo Rabaneda, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Loria Kohen, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Candela, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lourenço Nogueira, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarino Marin, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bermejo López, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Los Trastornos de la Conducta Alimentaria incluyen componentes psíquicos y físicos, por lo que para un adecuado abordaje de los mismos se debe trabajar dentro de un Programa integral con la participación de diferentes disciplinas. La Educación Nutricional busca la modificación de la conducta alimentaria hacia patrones más saludables y debe formar parte del Programa de tratamiento de esta enfermedad. Objetivo: Determinar el efecto de un programa de Educación Nutricional sobre el estado nutricional y el patrón alimentario de un grupo de pacientes con Trastornos de la Conducta Alimentaria que siguen con el protocolo habitual de seguimiento en consulta de Nutrición y deSalud Mental. Metodología: Se incluyeron 89 pacientes, 5% hombres, que recibieron Educación Nutricional individual con visitas semanales/quincenales por 4-6 meses, llevadas a cabo por una Dietista. La edad media 24 ± 8 años. La distribución por diagnóstico fue: Anorexia Nerviosa Restrictiva (ANR) 32,5% y Anorexia Nerviosa Purgativa (ANP) 26,5%, Bulimia Nerviosa (BN) 18%, Trastorno Alimentario No Específico (TANE) 21% y Trastorno por Atracón (TA) 2%. La media del tiempo de evolución desde el diagnóstico fue de 4,8 ± 5 años. Los pacientes completaban el cuestionario EAT26 (Eating Attitudes Test-26), se realizaba evaluación antropométrica, registro de 24 h y frecuencia habitual de consumo de alimentos en la primera consulta y tras recibir el programa de educación nutricional. Resultados: El valor medio del cuestionario EAT26 fue inicialmente 32 ± 15, tras la intervención fue 23,7 ± 14 (p &lt; 0,001), lo que evidencia cambios significativos en la sintomatología de los pacientes muy positivos. También hubo diferencias significativas en el análisis del cuestionario por escalas y en la evaluación por diagnósticos. Tras los 4-6 meses del programa, disminuyó significativamente el número de vómitos/semana tanto en ANP (7,2 ± 10 vs 1 ± 1,8 p &lt; 0,001) como en BN (8 ± 9,7 vs 2,2 ± 3,2 p &lt; 0,01). También se observó una tendencia favorable en la disminución en el número de atracones/semana para ambos diagnósticos. El porcentaje de pacientes que consumían menos de 4 comidas/día se redujo de un 70% a un 19% (p &lt; 0,001). El 67% de los pacientes logró dedicar un tiempo definido como correcto a comer y un 54% pasó a consumir una comida completa, resultados que muestran una tendencia muy favorable respecto a la normalización del patrón alimentario. Aumentó significativamente el consumo de lácteos, verduras, cereales, aceite (p &lt; 0,001), carnes (p &lt; 0,05) y frutas (p &lt; 0,01). Inicialmente un 34% consumía por lo menos 3 de los 6 grupos de alimentos dentro del rango recomendado, al final lo hizo el 70% (p &lt; 0,001).  Tras la educación nutricional se produjo un incremento significativo en la ingesta energética y en el consumo de hidratos de carbono (p &lt; 0,001) tanto en ANR como en ANP. Respecto a los micronutrientes aumentó significativamente la ingesta de vitamina B2, ácido fólico y calcio (p &lt; 0,001) en ANP y de magnesio y calcio (p &lt; 0,001) en ANR. Se produjo una mejoría significativa en el estado nutricional en ANR (p &lt; 0,001) en las variables peso, IMC y circunferencia muscular del brazo y el pliegue tricipital estuvo en el límite de la significación. Para ANP y TANE su valoración inicial demostraba que se encontraban dentro de rangos de normalidad, situación que se mantuvo tras la educación nutricional. En BN se produjo una evolución hacia la normalización del IMC, que pasó de 26,4 ± 6,6 a 25,5 ± 5,7 (-2,3 kg). Conclusión: Los programas de educación nutricional llevados a cabo por profesionales cualificados y expertos, deben formar parte del tratamiento de los TCA, junto al seguimiento médico y psicológico y dentro del marco de la interdisciplina y el trabajo en equipo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;24(5): 558-567, sept.-oct. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la utilidad de un Programa de Educación Nutricional en Trastornos de la Conducta Alimentaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23802</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
