<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152367</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The relationship between social skills and social anxiety and personality styles/disorders</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The relationship between social skills and social anxiety has been addressed conceptually but studied little empirically. Scarcer still are the studies on the relationship between social skills and personality styles/disorders. This paper uses a sample of mostly university students to find possible relationships between social skills, on the one hand, and social anxiety and personality styles/disorders, on the other. The correlations of the total scores for the instruments of social skills and social anxiety were moderate to high and negative; that is, the lower the social skill, the grater the social anxiety, and vice versa.  This same level of correlation was also obtained by analyzing the specific dimensions of each construct, which shows that there are shared aspects between social skills and social anxiety. Furthermore, the relationship between social skills an personality disorders varies depending on the specific personality style/disorder. Most correlations are negative, except for histrionic, narcissistic, obsessive-compulsive, and antisocial styles/disorders. These results provide support for a significant part of the interpersonal characteristics of each personality disorder (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Irurtia, María Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar, Isabel C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballo, Vicente E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olivares, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La relación entre las habilidades sociales (HHSS) y la ansiedad social (AS) ha sido planteada conceptualmente pero poco estudiada a nivel empírico. Más escasos son los trabajos sobre la relación entre las HHSS y los estilos/trastornos de la personalidad (TTPP). El presente trabajo pretende hallar las posibles relaciones entre las HHSS por una parte, y la AS y los estilos/TTPP,  por la otra, en una muestra mayoritariamente de estudiantes universitarios. Las correlaciones entre las puntuaciones totales de los instrumentos de HHSS y AS fueron de moderadas a altas y negativas, es decir, que a menor habilidad social mayor AS y viceversa. Se obtuvo también este mismo nivel de correlaciones al analizar las dimensiones específicas de cada constructo, lo que muestra que hay aspectos que se comparten entre las HHSS y la AS. Por otra parte, las relaciones entre HHSS y TTPP varían según el estilo/trastorno de personalidad específico. La mayoría de las correlaciones son negativas, excepto para los estilos/trastornos histriónico, narcisista, obsesivo compulsivo y antisocial de la personalidad. Estos resultados ofrecen apoyo a una parte importante de las características interpersonales de cada uno de los trastornos de la personalidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;22(3): 401-422, 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152367</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación de las habilidades sociales con la ansiedad social y los estilos/trastornos de la personalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55704</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d991^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1250</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12030^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
