<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165890</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Modern approach to an old technique: narrative revision of techniques used to locate the epidural space</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since the first description of the epidural technique during the 1920s, the continuous progress of knowledge of the anatomy and physiology of the epidural space has allowed the development of different techniques to locate this space while increasing both the safety and efficacy of the procedure. The most common techniques used today are based on the two main characteristics of the epidural space: the difference in distensibility between the ligamentum flavum and the epidural space, and the existence of negative pressure within the epidural space. However, over recent years, technological advances have allowed the development of new techniques to locate the epidural space based on other physical properties of tissues. Some are still in the experimental phase, but others, like ultrasound-location have reached a clinical phase and are being used increasingly in daily practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guasch Arévalo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kollmann Camaiora, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilsanz Rodríguez, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brogly, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alsina Marcos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde la primera descripción de la técnica epidural en los años 1920, el progreso continuo en el conocimiento de la anatomía y de la fisiología del espacio epidural ha permitido desarrollar diferentes técnicas de localización de este espacio para aumentar tanto la seguridad como la eficacia del procedimiento. Las técnicas más utilizadas hoy en día se basan en las 2 principales propiedades descritas del espacio epidural: la diferencia de distensibilidad entre el ligamento amarillo y el espacio epidural y la existencia de una presión negativa en el espacio epidural. Sin embargo, en los últimos años, la evolución tecnológica ha permitido desarrollar nuevas técnicas de localización basadas en otras propiedades físicas de los tejidos. Algunas de ellas están todavía en una fase experimental, pero otras como las técnicas con ultrasonidos han alcanzado una fase clínica y se está expandiendo su uso en la práctica diaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;64(8): 460-466, oct. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165890</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Visión moderna sobre una técnica antigua: revisión narrativa de técnicas de localización del espacio epidural</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d782^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4904^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d782^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
