<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113866</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">In vitro histomorphometric comparison of periodontal ligament of extracted premolar teeth preserved in different media storage</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The aim of this study was to histologically and morphometrically evaluate the results of different types of storage media for avulsed teeth in the maintenance and preserving the integrity of the periodontal ligament. Material and methods: Experimental study. It was used twenty-three extracted premolars for orthodontic reasons. Preserving methods evaluated were: type &#147;B&#148; and &#147;C&#148; milk, saline and dry environment. A total of five teeth were stored in each storage media for 120 minutes. Three teeth served as controls fixed immediately after extraction representing the entire periodontal ligament. The teeth were fixed, processed and stained with hematoxylin/eosin for histological evaluation by light microscopy. Results: The age of the patients who provided the teeth ranged from 13-17 years. The results of the qualitative assessment showed that saline was the most appropriate storage medium, followed by milk type C and type B. In the statistical analysis there was no statistically significant difference between saline and type C milk. After 120 minutes it was found statistically significant differences between histomorphometric changes in the control group and groups of teeth that were kept in wet conditions and dry. Conclusion: Given the results of this study, saline (group II) and milk type C (Group III) can be considered as the most suitable form of storage of avulsed teeth (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Simancas Pallares, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Caballero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrales Salgado, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prokopowitsch, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El propósito de este estudio fue evaluar histológica y morfométricamente los resultados de diferentes tipos de medios de almacenamiento para los dientes avulsionados en el mantenimiento de la preservación de la integridad del ligamento periodontal. Material y métodos: Estudio de tipo experimental de laboratorio, se utilizaron veintitrés premolares extraídos por motivos ortodóncicos. Los medios de conservación evaluados fueron: leche tipo &#147;B&#148; y tipo &#147;C&#148;, solución salina y medio seco. Un total de cinco dientes fueron almacenados en cada uno de los medios de conservación durante 120 minutos. Otros tres dientes sirvieron como controles fijados inmediatamente después de la extracción representando el ligamento periodontal íntegro. Los dientes se fijaron, procesaron y tiñeron con hematoxilina y eosina para evaluación histológica a través de microscopia óptica. Resultados: La edad de los pacientes que aportaron los dientes osciló entre 13 a 17 años. Los resultados de la evaluación cualitativa mostraron que la solución fisiológica fue el medio de almacenamiento más adecuado seguido de la leche tipo C y tipo B. En el análisis estadístico no hubo diferencia estadísticamente significativa entre los grupos de solución fisiológica y leche tipo C. Después de 120 minutos se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre las alteraciones histomorfométricas del grupo control y los grupos de dientes que se mantuvieron en condiciones de humedad y los secos. Conclusión: Dados los resultados de este estudio, la solución salina (grupo II) y la leche tipo C(Grupo III) pueden considerarse como las formas de conservación más adecuadas de los dientes avulsionados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;25(1): 41-47, abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113866</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comparación histomorfométrica in vitro del ligamento periodontal de premolares extraídos mantenidos en cuatro medios de conservación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10704^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1666^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14477^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d540^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
