<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-149070</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Rosette-forming glioneuronal tumor. A rare neoplasm of the fourth ventricle</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We present a case of a rosette-forming glioneuronal tumour of the fourth ventricle in a 14-year-old with no relevant previous clinical history. The patient presented with hypertensive hydrocephalus and radiology revealed a space-occupying lesion affecting the cerebellar vermis and obstructing the fourth ventricle. The tumour was removed and was seen to have a benign appearance and to be formed of rosette-like structures composed of acidophilic fibrillary material. It was positive for neuronal markers (synaptophysin and enolase) and glial markers (GRAP). The main features of this rare entity are discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ludeña de la Cruz, María Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz Rodríguez-Parets, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Torres, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martinez, Sofía del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascal, Eliseo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Velasco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos un caso de tumor glioneuronal formador de rosetas del iv ventrículo observado en un adolescente de 14 años, sin antecedentes clínicos de interés. El paciente presentó un cuadro de hidrocefalia obstructiva y se le detectó radiológicamente una lesión ocupante de espacio que afectaba al vermis cerebeloso y que obstruía el iv ventrículo. Los hallazgos histopatológicos mostraron un tumor de apariencia benigna, constituido por estructuras rosetoides centradas por un material fibrilar acidófilo. Dicho tumor fue positivo tanto para marcadores neuronales (sinaptofisina y enolasa) como gliales (PGFA). Tras la descripción, se comentan brevemente las principales características de esta rara entidad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;49(1): 66-68, ene.-mar. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-149070</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor glioneuronal formador de rosetas. Ejemplo poco frecuente de neoplasia del IV ventrículo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2590^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55496^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53670^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2590^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12773^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2591^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
