<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055221</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Validation of Doppler ultrasound as the only diagnosis of extracranial carotid stenosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In recent years there has been growing interest to indicate Doppler ultrasound-based carotid        endarterectomy, which thus makes continual validation by the haemodynamic laboratories in Vascular Surgery services        essential. Aims. Our aim was to present a comparison of DU versus a reference test in patients referred to our        laboratory. We also sought to identify the group of patients that allowed the precision of Doppler ultrasound to be used        as a single preoperative diagnostic test. Patients and methods.We studied a sample of 47 patients (94 carotids) who were        referred to our laboratory with suspected significant carotid diseases. A control reference test was carried out in all of        them (arteriography: 78.7%; MR angiography: 21.3%). Results. A duplex-reference test kappa coefficient of 0.89 was        obtained for the whole series. Ten occlusions were detected, which were confirmed with reference tests. The ROC curves        (overall series) for the systolic velocity (SV), diastolic velocity (DV) and the internal/common carotid SV ratio (ISV/        CSV) presented areas of 92.7, 93.4 and 90.5%, respectively. The following cut-off points for severe stenosis were        established: SV: 275 cm/s (sensitivity: 93.3%; specificity: 88.9%); DV: 90 cm/s (sensitivity: 90%; specificity: 94.4%) and        the ISV/CSV ratio: 3.5 (sensitivity: 90%; specificity: 85.2%). The validity of Doppler ultrasound is improved when        patients with severe stenosis or contralateral occlusion are excluded (ROC SV: 97.2%; DV: 97.7%; ISV/CSV ratio: 92.5%).        In the diagnosis of severe stenosis with mild-moderate contralateral stenosis, the kappa value was 0.95. Conclusions.        Carotid duplex is a reliable, valid test for diagnosing extracranial carotid stenosis. It can be used as a single preoperative        diagnosis when the contralateral carotid axis does not present any serious disease and the study is of        sufficiently high quality</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Hervás, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Conejero, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moñux Ducajú, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caridad Morata Barrado, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Hernando, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reina Gutiérrez, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En los últimos años ha crecido el interés por indicar la endarterectomía carotídea basada en        eco-Doppler, por lo que es imprescindible la validación continuada de los laboratorios hemodinámicos de los servicios        de Cirugía Vascular. Objetivos. Presentar la concordancia del eco-Doppler frente a una prueba de referencia en los        pacientes remitidos a nuestro laboratorio. Identificar el grupo de pacientes en los que la exactitud del eco-Doppler        podría emplearse como prueba de diagnóstico único preoperatoria. Pacientes y métodos. Se estudian 47 pacientes (94        carótidas) con sospecha de enfermedad carotídea significativa en pacientes remitidos a nuestro laboratorio. En todos se        realiza prueba de referencia de control (arteriografía: 78,7%; angiorresonancia: 21,3%). Resultados. Se ha obtenido en        el total de la serie un coeficiente kappa de 0,89 dúplex-prueba de referencia. Se detectaron 10 oclusiones, que se confirmaron        con pruebas de referencia. Las curvas COR (serie global) para la velocidad sistólica (VS), velocidad diastólica        (VD) y ratio VS carótida interna/común (VSI/VSC) presentaron las áreas 92,7, 93,4 y 90,5%, respectivamente. Se han establecido        como puntos de corte de estenosis grave los siguientes: VS: 275 cm/s (sensibilidad: 93,3%; especificidad:        88,9%); VD: 90 cm/s (sensibilidad: 90%; especificidad: 94,4%) y ratio VSI/VSC: 3,5 (sensibilidad: 90%; especificidad:        85,2%). La validez del eco-Doppler mejora cuando se excluyen los pacientes con estenosis grave u oclusión contralateral        (COR VS: 97,2%; VD: 97,7%; ratio VSI/VSC: 92,5%). En el diagnóstico de estenosis grave con contralateral levemoderada,        el valor kappa ha sido 0,95. Conclusiones. El dúplex carotídeo es una prueba fiable y válida en el diagnóstico        de la estenosis carotídea extracraneal. Puede utilizarse como diagnóstico preoperatorio único cuando el eje carotídeo        contralateral no presente enfermedad grave y el estudio sea de buena calidad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;59(3): 217-224, mayo-jun. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Validación del eco-Doppler carotídeo como diagnóstico único de la estenosis carotídea extracraneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30211^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23623^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
