<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056115</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">New diagnostic and surgical approach to Mirizzi syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mirizzi&#146;s syndrome is an unusual complication of gallstone disease,    in which a stone impacting in the neck of the gallbladder (Hartmann&#146;s    pouch) compresses the common bile duct. This mechanical obstruction    leads to obstructive jaundice frequently followed by inflammatory changes    and several complications.    We present two patients affected by Mirizzi&#146;s syndrome whose diagnosis    was correct in the preoperative period and approached by laparoscopy.    A case was converted to open procedure due to adhesions in the    Calot&#146;s triangle, and therefore, treated with subtotal cholecystectomy    and choledochorrhaphy over a T tube. In the other case the laparoscopy    access became successful. Both postoperative courses were uneventful.    In this article, suitable diagnostic techniques are analyzed. On the    other hand, we discuss what is the best therapeutic option, with especial    attention to the relevance of endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography    and laparoscopic approach in the management of those patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monsalve Laguna, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano Gil Albarellos, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezali Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno de Marcos, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Beorlegui, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El síndrome de Mirizzi es una variante poco frecuente de colelitiasis    en la que un cálculo impactado en la bolsa de Hartmann comprime la vía    biliar desencadenando una ictericia obstructiva, frecuentemente seguida    de fenómenos inflamatorios y de diversas complicaciones (colecistitis,    colangitis, fístulas etc).    Presentamos dos pacientes con síndrome de Mirizzi, correctamente    diagnosticados en el preoperatorio e intervenidos por vía laparoscópica.    Un caso fue convertido por adherencias en el triángulo de Calot y tratado    con colecistectomía subtotal y coledocorrafia sobre tubo en T de Kher.    En el otro enfermo se pudo completar con éxito el procedimiento. Ambos    postoperatorios cursaron con normalidad.    En el presente artículo, se analizan las técnicas diagnósticas que ayudan    a una identificación precoz del síndrome y se discuten las opciones    terapéuticas más adecuadas en el momento actual, prestando una especial    atención al papel de la colangiopancreatografía endoscópica y del abordaje    laparoscópico en el manejo de estos pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;24(6): 281-284, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056115</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Nuevas posibilidades diagnósticas y terapéuticas en el síndrome de Mirizzi</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38066^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24011^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23188^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
