<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108117</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The intraoperative mini gamma camera in primary hyperparathyroidism surgery</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: The evolution of primary hyperparathyroidism surgical treatment has been improved by the arrival of new techniques that allow for better parathyroid gland tracking. A mini gamma camera has recently been developed that makes it possible to take intraoperative parathyroid gammagraphies. The objective of this study was to evaluate the utility of this technique. Method: We prospectively studied 29 patients with primary hyperparathyroidism, comparing the diagnostic effectiveness of the MGP with the results obtained with preoperative techniques (ultrasound scan plus Tc99m-sestamibi gammagraphy). Results: The sensitivity and specificity of the mini gamma camera was superior to those of the preoperative techniques, applied to the lateral neck as well as to the face of the neck (lateral: 89.6% sensitivity and 96.15% specificity compared to 79.31% and 92.59% respectively; and neck face: sensitivity and specificity 83.33% and 90.91% against 48.39% and 72.73%). Conclusions: The portable mini gamma camera accurately tracks pathologic parathyroid glands. In that sense, it could be useful when considering a radio-guided surgery with minimal parathyroid invasion(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sopena, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sopena, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dalmau, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guallart, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estrems, Paloma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abreu, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La evolución del tratamiento quirúrgico del hiperparatiroidismo primario se ha visto favorecido por la aparición de nuevas técnicas que permiten una mejor localización de las glándulas paratiroides. Recientemente se ha desarrollado una minigammacámara portátil (MGP), que permite realizar gammagrafías paratiroideas intraoperatorias. El objetivo del estudio ha sido valorar la utilidad de esta técnica. Métodos: Estudiamos prospectivamente 29 pacientes con hiperparatiroidismo primario y evaluamos la validez diagnóstica de la MGP comparando los resultados obtenidos con las técnicas preoperatorias (ecografía+gammagrafía Tc99m-sestamibi). Resultados: La sensibilidad y especificidad de la minigammacámara es superior a las técnicas preoperatorias, tanto por lado como por cuadrante del cuello (por lado: sensibilidad del 89,6% y especificidad del 96,15% frente a un 79,31 y 92,59% respectivamente, y por cuadrante: sensibilidad y especificidad del 83,33 y 90,91% versus 48,39 y 72,73%). Conclusiones: La MGP localiza de forma precisa las glándulas paratiroides patológicas, por lo que podría resultar útil al plantear una cirugía radioguiada mínimamente invasiva paratiroidea(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;63(6): 450-457, nov.-dic. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108117</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La minigammacámara intraoperatoria en la cirugía del hiperparatiroidismo primario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24661^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28998</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9092</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50516^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50516^s22008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
