<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058754</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Conjunctivodacryocystorhinostomy with the assistance of diode laser. Endoscopic placement of jones lacrimal tubes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe and assess a surgical technique for cases of complete bicanalicular lachrymal destruction by means of the endoscopic insertion use of the Junes tube with a diode laser to study functionality and complications.                 Patients and method: A descriptive study of a case series with 24 consecutive patients with complete bicanalicular obstruction who underwent conjunctivodacryocystorhinostomy with diode laser. The surgery time, intra-operative and post-operative complications, long-term patency, and need for secondary revision were evaluated.                 Results: Twenty-four consecutive patients were included in the study. All surgical procedures were successfully performed without significant complications. Average operating time was 15 minutes. The length of the tubes used ranged from 17 to 26 mm. Patients were evaluated at 24 hours, 3 weeks, 3 months, and 6 months and then every 6 months. The most frequent post-surgical complication was the downward migration of the tube towards the nasal fossa (37.5 %). Secondary intervention was performed in 6 patients. Success was demonstrated using the fluoresceinic staining test under endoscopic monitoring and represented 37.5 % after the initial surgery and 50 % including revision surgery.                 Conclusions: Laser-guided endoscopic intubation is a speedy and accurate surgical procedure that is well-tolerated during the operation and leaves no scar on the skin surface. However, it is associated with a considerable number of post-surgical complications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Fernández, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alañón Fernández, Félix J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas Lara, Manuela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alañón Fernández, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir y evaluar la cirugía en los casos de destrucción canalicular total, mediante la inserción endoscópica con láser diodo del tubo de Jones para estudiar la funcionalidad y las complicaciones.                 Pacientes y método: Se realiza un estudio descriptivo de una serie de casos consecutivos en 24 pacientes con obstrucción bicanalicular completa, a los que se practica una conjuntivodacriocistorrinostomía con láser diodo. Se valoró los tiempos quirúrgicos, las complicaciones operatorias y postoperatorias, la permeabilidad y la necesidad de reintervenciones.                 Resultados: Se incluyó a 24 pacientes en el estudio. La cirugía se llevo a cabo en todos los pacientes sin complicaciones. El tiempo quirúrgico medio fue de 15 min. Los tamaños de los tubos usados fueron de 17-26 mm. Se efectuaron controles a las 24 h, a las 3 semanas y a los 3 y 6 meses, seguidos de revisiones cada 6 meses. La complicación posquirúrgica más frecuente fue el desplazamiento inferior del tubo hacia la fosa nasal (37,5 %). Se precisó reintervención en 6 casos. Los éxitos demostrados mediante el test de tinción fluoresceínica con control endoscópico fueron un 37,5 % tras una primera intervención y un 50 % si se incluye una segunda reintervención.                 Conclusiones: La intubación endoscópica guiada con láser es una cirugía precisa, rápida, bien tolerada intraoperatoriamente y sin cicatriz cutánea, si bien va asociada a un importante número de complicaciones posquirúrgicas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;59(1): 11-15, ene. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058754</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conjuntivodacriocistorrinostomía con láser diodo. Inserción endoscópica de tubos de Jones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10207^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3252^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22874^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9496^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7944^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200801</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
