<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138342</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Long-term risk os relapses in Tolosa-Hunt syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The reviewed diagnostic criteria of Tolosa- Hunt síndrome (THS) by the International Classification of Headache Disorders (ICHD-II, 2004) includes demonstration of inflammatory changes by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) in the cavernous sinus region as an alternative to biopsy. Careful follow-up is required to exclude other possible causes of painful ophthalmoplegia. It remains unclear for how long such close observation should be extended to assure the diagnosis nor whether THS represents a self-limited condition in the long-term. Case report: An observational study along 13 years of a patient fulfilling current ICHD-II criteria for THS to clarify the natural history of the disorder. Results: We witnessed three episodes, the presenting one causing severe left orbital pain, ipsilateral abducens palsy , and hypoesthesia in the territory of the ophthalmic branch of the trigeminal nerve. Gadolinium MRI showed enhancement of tissue infiltrating the lateral wall of the carotid sinus. A relapse 21 months later caused involvement of left oculomotor and abducens nerves in addition to orbital pain which responded rapidly to steroids. Ensuing remission maintained for up to 11 years concluded in a new relapse again characterized by severe ipsilateral orbital pain and frontal numbness, but no ophthalmoplegia. A gadolinium-MRI did not show enhancement on this occasion despite prompt response to steroids. Conclusion: The risk of relapses in THS and its response to steroids may be maintained for as long as 13 years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Giménez- Román, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillem, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los criterios revisados por la International Classification of Headache Disorders (ICHD-II, 2004) para el diagnóstico del síndrome de Tolosa-Hunt (STH) exigen demostrar cambios inflamatorios en el seno cavernoso mediante imágenes por resonancia magnética (RM) como alternativa a la biopsia, pero se requiere un seguimiento cuidadoso del paciente que permita excluir otras causas de oftalmoplegía dolorosa. No está clara su duración ni si el proceso es autolimitado en el tiempo. Caso clínico. Estudio observacional a lo largo de 13 años de una paciente que cumplía criterios ICHD-II a fin de clarificar la historia natural del proceso. Resultados. Observamos tres episodios: el primero iniciado con intenso dolor orbitario izquierdo, seguido de parálisis ipsolateral del nervio motor ocular externo e hipoestesia en el territorio de la rama oftálmica del trigémino. Una RM con gadolinio mostró captación por un tejido que infiltraba la pared lateral del seno carotídeo. Sufrió una recaída 21 meses después; ocasiona ahora parálisis de los nervios motor ocular común y motor ocular externo izquierdo, además de dolor orbitario, con respuesta rápida al tratamiento esteroideo. Tras una remisión prolongada 11 años, una nueva recaída se caracterizó nuevamente por intenso dolor orbitario y acorchamiento frontal ipsolateral izquierdos, pero no oftalmoplegía. Una RM con gadolinio no mostró realce en esta ocasión pese a una pronta respuesta a los corticoides. Conclusiones. El riesgo de recaídas en el STH se prolonga al menos durante 13 años, manteniéndose una respuesta favorable a los corticoides (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;21(7): 382-385, sept. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138342</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Riesgo de recaídas a largo plazo en el síndrome de Tolosa-Hunt</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34304^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34304^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34304^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34304^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
