<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139288</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Using sevelamer in chronic kidney disease. Beyond phosphorus control</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sevelamer is a calcium-free phosphate binder used in advanced chronic kidney disease (CKD) and in dialysis to control hyperphosphatemia. Several experimental and observational studies and clinical trials have shown that sevelamer has pleiotropic effects that go beyond controlling hyperphosphatemia; these pleiotropic effects include acting on inflammation, oxidative stress, lipid profile and atherogenesis, vascular calcification, endothelial dysfunction and decreasing various uremic toxins. All of these represent the biological basis for the global effect of sevelamer on cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in patients with CKD. In this review, we emphasis these pleiotropic actions of sevelamer and their impact on cardiovascular health, with the experience published after more than 10 years of clinical experience (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rojas-Rivera, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Egido, Jesus</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Osorio, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia-Iguacel, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Parra, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pazmiño Zambrano, Diana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El sevelamer es un captor no cálcico de fósforo que se utiliza en la ERC avanzada y en diálisis para el control de la hiperfosforemia. Varios estudios experimentales, observacionales y ensayos clínicos han mostrado que el sevelamer tiene efectos pleiotrópicos, más allá del control de la hiperfosforemia, incluyendo acciones sobre la inflamación, el estrés oxidativo, el perfil lipídico y la aterogénesis, la calcificación vascular, la disfunción endotelial y la disminución de diversas toxinas urémicas, todo lo cual sería la base biológica de su efecto global sobre la morbilidad y la mortalidad cardiovascular en pacientes con enfermedad renal crónica. En esta revisión, se hace énfasis en estas acciones pleiotrópicas del sevelamer y su impacto en la salud cardiovascular, con la experiencia publicada después de más de 10 años de experiencia clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;35(2): 207-217, mar.-abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso del sevelamer en la enfermedad renal crónica. Más allá del control del fósforo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52631^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11186^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
