<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122530</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Retrograde nailing in a tibial fracture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We describe a case of a severely comminuted type iiia open tibial fracture, with distal loss of bone stock (7 cm), total involvement of the tibial joint surface, and severe instability of the fibular-talar joint. The treatment performed consisted of thorough cleansing, placing a retrograde reamed calcaneal-talar-tibial nail with proximal and distal blockage, as well as a fibular-talar Kirschner nail. Primary closure of the skin was achieved. After 3 weeks, an autologous iliac crest bone graft was performed to fill the bone defect, and the endomedullary nail, which had protruded distally was reimpacted and dynamized distally. The bone defect was eventually consolidated after 16 weeks. Currently, the patient can walk without pain the tibial-astragal arthrodesis is consolidated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Marcano Fernández, F. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí Garín, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fillat Gomá, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valls Mellado, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Vargas, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe un caso de fractura abierta de tibia grado iiia con gran conminución y pérdida distal de stock óseo ( cm) con total afectación de la superficie articular tibial y gran inestabilidad de la articulación peroneo-astragalina. El tratamiento realizado consintió en practicar una exhaustiva limpieza, colocándose un enclavado fresado retrógrado calcáneo-astrágalo-tibial con bloqueos proximales y distales, además de una aguja de Kirschner peroneo-astragalina. Se consiguió el cierre primario de la  piel. A las 3 semanas se procedió al aporte de injerto óseo autólogo de cresta ilíaca rellenando el defecto óseo, a la reimpactación del clavo endomedular que estaba protuido distalmente y a la dinamización distal. Se consiguió la consolidación del defecto óseo en 16 semanas. Actualmente, el paciente deambula sin dolor con la artrodesis tibio-astragalina consolidada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);58(3): 196-199, mayo-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enclavado retrógrado en fractura tibial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33575^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14365^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1883^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
