<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-146952</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Economic evaluation seeks threshold to support decisión-making</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To incorporate economic evaluation into decision-making, we need to know how much a health system is willing and able to invest in a quality-adjusted life year (QALY). In Spain, the figure of &#128;30,000 per QALY as cost-effectiveness (CE) threshold has been widely cited. However, as in most health systems, no value has been formally adopted; mainly because of the arbitrariness, the lack of theoretical and scientific basis, and the controversy around its estimation and what the threshold should represent. Based on a systematic review of empirical studies on the estimation of the CE threshold undertaken by this research team, we conducted a critical appraisal of the state of the art, using a Delphi with the participation of 13 national experts. This paper contributes to assess the research progress on the CE threshold in Spain, to consider its utility in the decision making process supported by economic evaluation, and to propose further research to improve what has been achieved so far (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Trujillo-Martín, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valcárcel-Nazco, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Lorenzo, Borja</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo-Torres, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perestelo-Pérez, Lilisbeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano Aguilar, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para que la evaluación económica pueda ser incorporada en la toma de decisiones se debe conocer cuánto está dispuesto y es capaz de invertir por un Año de Vida Ajustado por Calidad (AVAC) el Sistema Nacional de Salud. En España se ha extendido el uso de 30.000&#128; por AVAC como umbral coste-efectividad (CE) pero, como en la mayoría de los sistemas sanitarios, no se ha adoptado un valor formalmente. Esto se debe en parte a la arbitrariedad, la falta de base teórica y científica para su fijación y la controversia que persiste sobre su estimación y lo que dicho umbral CE debe representar. A partir de una revisión sistemática de trabajos empíricos sobre la estimación del umbral CE realizada por este equipo investigador, se llevó a cabo una valoración crítica del estado del arte utilizando un grupo Delphi con la participación de 13 expertos nacionales. Este artículo contribuye a reflexionar cuánto se ha avanzado en investigación sobre el umbral CE en España, a considerar su utilidad para completar el proceso de toma de decisiones bajo evaluación económica, y a plantear líneas de investigación para mejorar lo logrado hasta la fecha (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;89(6): 537-544, nov.-dic. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-146952</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación económica busca umbral para apoyar la toma de decisiones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32636</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5513^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34589^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4537^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16672^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
