<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108796</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The patient with terminal illness in the acute care hospital: the palliative care advisory team</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To determine the characteristics of palliative inpatient characteristics in an acute care hospital. To analyse the factors that determine the discharge location. Material and method: A descriptive study of patients referred to the Palliative Care Advisory Team between October 2008 and September 2009. The comparison of parametric values was performed using the chi squared test and the Student t-test. Results: A total of 198 patients (74% with cancer) were evaluated, with 19 readmissions. There were 63% men, with a mean age 75±12 years. The mean Barthel index was 25±27 and Palliative Performance Scale (PPS) 42±11. The mean time from assessment to discharge was 3.6±4 days. The most frequent symptoms were asthenia (85.6%), anorexia (72%), xerostomia (67.2%), pain (63.6%), insomnia (57.8%), and dyspnea (52.3%). We (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palomo , Amaya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vargas Torres, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodrigo, Rebeca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiben Pereira, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Conocer el perfil del paciente con enfermedad terminal ingresado en un hospital de agudos. Analizar los factores que determinan la ubicación al alta. Material y método: Estudio descriptivo prospectivo de los pacientes ingresados valorados por equipos de soporte hospitalario del 1 de octubre de 2008 al 30 de septiembre de 2009. Análisis estadístico mediante test de la c2 y t de Student. Resultados: Se realizaron 198 valoraciones, con 19 reingresos. El 63% de los pacientes eran varones, con una edad media ± desviación estándar de 75 ± 12 años. El 74% eran oncológicos. Índice de Barthel medio de 25 ± 27 y Palliative Performance Scale (PPS) de 42 ± 11. El tiempo medio desde la valoración hasta el alta fue de 3,6 ± 4 días. Los síntomas más frecuentes fueron astenia (85,6%), anorexia (72%), xerostomía (67,2%), dolor (63,6%), insomnio (57,8%), disnea (52,3%). Al analizar a los pacientes oncológicos (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;18(1): 14-19, ene.-mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108796</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El paciente con enfermedad terminal en el hospital de agudos: la labor del equipo de soporte hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33200^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12438^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
