<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054856</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ethical and Legal Issues in Child and Adolescent Mental Health Practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this paper is to clarify legal and ethical issues in CAMH practice. A review of main legal    psychiatry text-books, regarding those specific aspects, has been done. Professional secret and those    situations in which it would be broken are main concerns in this field. Legal procedure for psychiatric    hospitalisation, informed consent and medical records are also reviewed. Finally some ethical issues    regarding public and private practice are discussed and some ethical guidelines for CAMH workers are    suggested</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Otero, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Samaniego, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benito, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Payá, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prego, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molino, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El principal objetivo de este artículo es clarificar los aspectos éticos y legales de la práctica en Salud    Mental Infanto-juvenil. Se han revisado los principales textos sobre el tema legal, adaptando las ideas al    campo de la pr áctica con niños y adolescentes. Un tema central es el secreto profesional y aquellas    situaciones en que puede ser violado. También se abordan los aspectos legales de la historia cl ínica, así    como el consentimiento informado y la hospitalización. Por último se han revisado las cuestiones éticas de    la relación entre actividad pública y privada y se sugiere una guía ética de consenso entre los profesionales    de los equipos de SMIJ</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(182): 1-8, oct.-dic. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054856</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aspectos éticos y legales de la práctica en salud mental infanto-juvenil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2716^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3243^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2716^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36470</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d300^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d300^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
