<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113388</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-9483</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of dysfunctional beliefs about sleep on the poor sleep quality reported by patients with fibromyalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Most patients with fibromyalgia (FM) have a significant problem of insomnia, which is usually considered as a simple consequence of pain. Disfunctional beliefs about sleep are one of the main maintenance factors of chronic insomnia. However no studies have analyzed the possible contribution of these beliefs to the sleep problems observed in FM. In the present study, 90 women with FM and 70 healthy women completed several self-report measures about sleep, pain, mood state, and daily functioning. Both groups differed significantly in all the variables. In the clinical group, poor sleep quality correlates with greater pain, depression, anxiety and low level of functioning. In addition, patients with FM showed more disfunctional beliefs about sleep, wich correlate significantly with several measures. Pain intensity, depression and disfunctional beliefs about the consequences of insomnia for health are significant predictors of poor sleep quality. The implications of these findings for current treatment of FM are discussed</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Diener, Fabián N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, M. Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prados, Germán</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Ana I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La mayoría de pacientes con fibromialgia (FM) presenta un notable problema de insomnio, que suele contemplarse como una mera consecuencia del dolor. Uno de los principales factores de mantenimiento del insomnio crónico son las creencias disfuncionales sobre el sueño, aunque ningún estudio ha analizado la posible contribución de dichas creencias a los problemas del sueño observados en la FM. En esta investigación 90 mujeres con FM y 70 mujeres sanas completaron diversas medidas de autoinforme sobre sueño, dolor, estado de ánimo y funcionamiento diario. Se observó que ambos grupos se diferencian de forma significativa en todas las variables, asociándose la peor calidad del sueño del grupo clínico a más dolor, depresión, ansiedad y menor nivel de funcionamiento. Además, las pacientes con FM muestran más creencias disfuncionales sobre el sueño que correlacionan significativamente con diversas medidas. La intensidad del dolor, la depresión y las creencias disfuncionales sobre las consecuencias del insomnio en la salud son predictores significativos de pobre calidad del sueño. Se debaten las implicaciones de los resultados de cara al actual tratamiento de la FM (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicol. conduct;20(3): 699-718, sept.-dic. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113388</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de las cogniciones disfuncionales sobre el sueño en la baja calidad del sueño informada por los pacientes con fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
