<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167629</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To determine the prevalence of atelectasis in cystic fibrosis (CF) in Madrid Community, in order to find predisposing risk factors. Material and methods. A retrospective study in the CF Units of Madrid Community was carried out, of the patients who suffered atelectasis We studied: infections, pulmonary complications and comorbilities, prior and subsequent treatment, the use of broncoschopy and its results; the diagnosis using computed tomography (CT), and the resolution or not the atelectasis. Results. 16 (2,66%) patients has suffered atelectasis (2,66%), 7 males (43,8%) with a mean aged with the first atelectasis was 23,81 ± 11,2 year-old 14 (87,5%) presented chronic bronchial infection (CBI), specially by meticillinsensitive S and P. aeruginosa. Three (18,8%) had suffered allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis (ABPA) and one (6,3%) haemoptysis with embolization. There were no significant differences with prior and subsequent treatment. A bronchoscopy was performed in 10 patients (62,5%): improving in eight cases. A radiological improve was observed using a CT in 10 (62,5%) patients, complete in seven patients. We have found significant differences in FEV1/FVC, FEV1 and FVC, in the evolution of the patients; between the total number of exacerbations of the previous year and the following one. Five (31.25%) had a torpid evolution after the event. Conclusions. Pulmonary function with moderate to severe obstruction and other respiratory complications (ABPA and CBI) may predispose to atelectasis in CF. In addition, this complication worsens exacerbations and pulmonary function (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Máiz Carro, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Martínez, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo Posadas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez Redondo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carpio, CJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Río, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prados Sánchez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Girón Moreno, RM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Sala Walter, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Determinar la prevalencia de las atelectasias en la fibrosis quística (FQ) en la Comunidad de Madrid, con el fin de encontrar factores de riesgo predisponentes. Material y métodos. Se ha llevado a cabo un estudio retrospectivo en las unidades de FQ de la Comunidad de Madrid, de aquellos que habían padecido atelectasias. Se estudiaron: infecciones, complicaciones pulmonares y comorbilidades, tratamiento previo y posterior, el empleo de la fibrobroncoscopia y su respuesta, el diagnóstico mediante tomografía computarizada (TC) y la resolución o no de la atelectasia.  Resultados. 16 (2,66%) pacientes habían padecido atelectasias, siete hombres (43,8%), con una edad media a la primera atelectasia de 23,81 ± 11,2 años. 14 (87,5%) presentaron infección bronquial crónica (IBC), especialmente por S. aureus meticilin-sensible y P. aeruginosa. Tres (18,8%) habían padecido aspergilosis broncopulmonar alérgica (ABPA) y uno hemoptisis (6,3%) con embolización. No hubo diferencias significativas en los tratamientos usados antes y después. En 10 (62,5%) se realizó fibrobroncoscopia, mejorando ocho pacientes. La TC demostró mejoría radiológica en un 62,5%, completa en siete pacientes. Hubo diferencias significativas entre FEV1/FVC, FEV1 y FVC en la evolución de los pacientes; entre el número total de exacerbaciones del año previo y del posterior (p= 0,012) y entre las exacerbaciones graves del año previo y las últimas registradas (p= 0,013). Cinco (31,25%) tuvieron una evolución tórpida tras el evento. Conclusiones. Una función pulmonar con obstrucción moderada-grave, y haber padecido otras complicaciones respiratorias (ABPA y IBC) podrían predisponer a padecer atelectasias en FQ. Además, esta complicación empeora las exacerbaciones y la función pulmonar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;20(3): 79-87, jul.-sept. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167629</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características de las atelectasias como complicación pulmonar en la fibrosis quística</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3568^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1969^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36007^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
