<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78249</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Change in the accesibility of the emergency contraceptive pills and analysis concerning the infl uence on the incidence of sexually transmitted disease</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In Spain they have implemented, the free dispensing of the emergency contraceptive pills in the primary care emergency departments, which allows the rapid and free accessfor the users. Objective: To evaluate the influence that free administration ofemergency contraception in Primary Care has had on its consumption and compare the evolution of consumption of theabove mentioned over time with incidence of sexually transmitted diseases (STDs). Materials and Method: Descriptive observational study Data on the consumption of the emergency contraceptive pill from drugstores and health centres of Obligatorily Declared sexually transmitted diseases were collected over 6 years (2002-2007). Main outcome measures: Annual level of consumption (consumption in number of emergency contraceptive pill boxes per 1,000inhabitants per year, incidence (number of new cases detected in a year), and incidence rate (incidence per 100,000 inhabitants) for syphilis and gonococcal infections. Results: The consumption rate of the emergency contraceptive pill at the beginning of the study (distributed in drugstores) was3.02 versus to 12.44 in the year 2007. The tendency of the consumption rate of the emergency contraceptive pill to increase was found to be significant (p=0.024) and lineally related with the tendency of the syphilis rate to increase. Conclusions: An increased consumption of the emergency contraceptive pill and a probable association with the increase in the occurrence of syphilis was detected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Guerra-García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreales-Cardín, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En España se ha puesto en marcha la dispensación gratuita de la píldora poscoital en los servicios de urgencias de atención primaria, lo que permite el acceso rápido y gratuito a las usuarias. Objetivos: Evaluar la influencia que ha tenido la administración gratuita de la píldora poscoital en atención primaria sobre su consumo, y comparar su evolución con las tendencias evolutivas de la incidencia de infecciones de transmisión sexual(ITS). Material y método: Estudio observacional y descriptivo. Se incluyeron datos de consumo de la píldora poscoital en farmacias y centros de salud e ITS de declaración obligatoria durante un periodo de 6 años (2002-2007). Variables de medida: tasa de consumo anual (consumo en número de envases de píldora poscoital por 1.000 habitantes y año), incidencia (número de nuevos casos acontecidos en un año) y tasa de incidencia(por 100.000 habitantes) para la sífilis e infecciones gonocócicas. Resultados: Tasa de consumo de la píldora poscoital al inicio del estudio (dispensación en oficinas de farmacia) de 3,02 frente a 12,44 en el año 2007. La tendencia al aumento de la tasa de consumo total de la píldora poscoital se relacionó de manera significativa (p= 0,024) y de tipo lineal con la tendencia al aumento de la incidencia de sífilis. Conclusiones: Se detecta un elevado incremento del consume de la píldora poscoital y una probable asociación con el aumento de la incidencia de sífilis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;11(4): 157-162, dic. 2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cambio en la accesibilidad a la píldora poscoital y análisis de la influencia sobre la incidencia en las infecciones de transmisión sexual</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24198^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51446</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3300^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51329</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24320^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3300^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3300^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38343^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38343^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38343^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38343^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24198^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
