<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042232</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Medical Burnout: anxiety and doping process as relevant factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">To date there are not many studies focused on burnout like a process, where both environment and personality variables are considered. The present study had two central aims: to test what variables significantly effect the burnout process, and to clarify the empirical relationship between anxiety, coping styles and burnout. The Maslach Burnout Inventory (Maslach y Jackson, 1986), the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (Spielberger, Gorsuch y Lushene, 1988), the Ways of Coping Checklist (Lazarus y Folkman, 1984) and the Situational Medical Coping (Moreno-Jimenez y Seminotti, 1998) were administered to a sample of 130 physicians who work in eight public hospitals in Madrid. The independent variables were gender, marital status, medical group, clinical experience, age and speciality. Results showed a strong relationship among the dependent variables in gender, medical group and age through the GLM Multivariate MANOVA. A stepwise regression analysis provided relevant results to determine the theoretical situational model in Burnout process</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Seminotti, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrosa Hernández, R. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Jiménez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Carvajal, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morante Benadero, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Actualmente, no existen muchas investigaciones donde se consideren variables tanto ambientales como de personalidad en el estudio del burnout como proceso. La presente investigación plantea dos objetivos centrales: evaluar el nivel de significación de la ansiedad y las estrategias de afrontamiento en el proceso de burnout, y clarificar la relación empírica entre ellas. En una muestra de 130 profesionales médicos de ocho hospitales públicos de Madrid se les administró los cuestionarios Maslach Burnout Inventory (Maslach y Jackson, 1986), State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (Spielberger, Gorsuch y Lushene, 1988), Ways of Coping Checklist (Lazarus y Folkman, 1984) y el Cuestionario de Afrontamiento Médico Situacional (Moreno-Jiménez y Seminotti, 1998). Las variables independientes fueron: género, estado civil, grupo médico, experiencia clínica, edad y especialidad. Los resultados mostraron una relación significativa entre las variables dependientes y el género, grupo médico y la edad mediante análisis multivariante MANOVA. El análisis de regresión por pasos mostró resultados relevantes para determinar un modelo teórico situacional del proceso de Burnout</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;11(1): 87-100, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042232</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El Burnout médico: la ansiedad y los procesos de afrontamiento como factores intervinientes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8671^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
