<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166248</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative case-control study of homocysteine, vitamin B12, and folic acid levels in patients with epilepsy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Increased blood homocysteine levels are a known cardiovascular risk factor. Epileptic patients on long-term treatment with antiepileptic drugs may present higher homocysteine levels and, consequently, a potential increase in cardiovascular risk. Material and methods: We conducted an observational case-control study to compare plasma levels of homocysteine, folic acid, and vitamin B12. Results: Our study included a total of 88 subjects: 52 patients with epilepsy and 36 controls. Epileptic patients showed higher homocysteine levels (P=.084) and lower levels of folic acid (P&lt;.05). Conclusion: Homocysteine levels should be monitored in epileptic patients on long-term treatment with antiepileptic drugs. We suggest starting specific treatment in patients with high homocysteine levels (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Quesada Jiménez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendioroz Iriarte, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulido Fontes, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pulido Fontes, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muruzabal Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El aumento de homocisteína en sangre constituye un conocido factor de riesgo cardiovascular. Los pacientes epilépticos en tratamiento crónico con fármacos antiepilépticos pueden presentar niveles más elevados de homocisteína y, en consecuencia, un potencial aumento del riesgo cardiovascular. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional de casos y controles para la comparación de los niveles plasmáticos de homocisteína, ácido fólico y vitamina B12. Resultados: Se reclutó a un total de 88 sujetos, 52 de ellos epilépticos y 36 controles. Se observó una tendencia a niveles de homocisteína más elevados (p=0,084) en los pacientes epilépticos y unos valores de ácido fólico más bajos (p&lt;0,05). Conclusiones: Por su potencial efecto como factor de riesgo cardiovascular, es importante prestar atención a los niveles de homocisteína en los pacientes epilépticos en tratamiento crónico con fármacos antiepilépticos y en caso de encontrar niveles elevados sugerimos la instauración de tratamiento específico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;32(7): 440-445, sept. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166248</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de los niveles plasmáticos de homocisteína, vitamina B12 y ácido fólico en pacientes epilépticos frente a controles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6866^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33775^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15204^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4907^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5629^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
