<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142290</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Winmedtrad utility to know the smoking addiction prevalence in a reference hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: creating smoke-free workplaces still remains the most implemented action concerning tobacco smoking. WinMedtra is the Andalusian Health Service corporate software for the medical surveillance.  AIM: by using this application, we intend to show its utility in calculating the smoking prevalence in a reference hospital.  Material and Methods: an observational study was performed based on health examinations conducted in 2013 (n = 1672). After extracting data related with the tobacco consumption from WinMedtra, a descriptive and inferential statistics (student, simple anova and Chi-square statistical tests) were performed. We calculated arithmetic means and standard deviations for quantitative variables; and absolute and relative frequencies for qualitative variables. Confidence intervals up to 95% were calculated for the main estimates.  Results: the application allowed us to obtain smoking habits data in the interviewed working population. The smoking prevalence active subjects were 22.8% (95% CI: 20.79%-24.81%); 19.8% were former smokers so 77.2% did not smoke during the period study (95% CI: 75.19% -79.21%). The accumulated smoking intake was higher in the group of men than in that of women (21.08 ± 16.31 versus 15.38 ± 13.28 packs/year) (t: 3.61, p&lt;0.001). Significant differences (p &lt;0.001) were obtained by comparing the average age of nonsmokers and that of smokers, (48.33 ± 9.82 versus 50.55 ± 7.62 years) and former smokers (48.33 ± 9.82 versus 50.65 ± 8.32 years). Regarding occupational status, the highest "Non Smokers" percentage belonged to the resident workers (87%) followed by the chief group (75%). The group of administrative assistants (34.7%) and the supervisors (33.3%) had the highest "Smokers" percentage (Chi-square = 131.23, p&lt;0.001).  Conclusions: the software application may be useful to have an accurate epidemiological knowledge about the magnitude of addictive behavior like smoking in workplaces. We have obtained a lower smoking prevalence compared to the area in our study (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ranchal-Sánchez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Cabello, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérula de Torres, LA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Font, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La creación de lugares de trabajo sin humo sigue siendo la medida de mayor implantación frente al tabaquismo. WinMedtra es la aplicación informática corporativa del Servicio Andaluz de Salud para la Vigilancia de la Salud. Objetivo: Aprovechando dicha aplicación, planteamos mostrar su utilidad para calcular la prevalencia de tabaquismo en un Hospital de referencia. Material y método: Estudio observacional a partir de los exámenes de salud realizados en 2013 (n=1672). Se extrajeron los datos relativos al consumo de tabaco de WinMedtra realizándose una estadística descriptiva e inferencial (prueba «t» de Student, análisis de varianza simple y Ji-Cuadrado). Resultados: La aplicación informática nos ha permitido obtener datos del hábito tabáquico en la población laboral estudiada. La prevalencia de sujetos fumadores activos fue de un 22,8% (IC95%:20,79%- 24,81%) y el 19,8% eran ex fumadores, por lo que el 77,2% no fumaba en el periodo del estudio (IC95%: 75,19%-79,21%). El consumo acumulado fue mayor en el grupo de los hombres que en el de las mujeres (21,08 ± 16,31 versus 15,38±13,28 paquetes-año) (t: 3,61, p&lt;0,001). Conclusiones: La aplicación informática puede ser útil para tener un conocimiento epidemiológico más exacto de la magnitud de conductas adictivas como el tabaquismo en centros de trabajo, obteniéndose en nuestro estudio una prevalencia de tabaquismo activo inferior a la del entorno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;61(239): 172-183, abr.-jun. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142290</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad de winmedtra para conocer la prevalencia del tabaquismo en un hospital de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19243^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10749^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
