<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-98625</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of preventive physiotherapy treatments for back care in children and adolescents. A systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To identify the most effective preventive physiotherapy treatments for back care in children and adolescents and to analyze the methodological quality of the articles. Search strategy A systematic review of controlled trials was conducted in the Cochrane, MEDLINE, PEDro, Web of Science and IME databases. Selection of studies A total de 16 research papers that fulfilled the selection criteria were included, producing 19 independent studies. Results The 19 studies analyzed included treatments with postural hygiene applied independently, combined treatments of postural hygiene and physical therapy exercises and postural hygiene and physical activity. Conclusions Treatment of hygiene postural is that used most frequently by the authors. Combined treatment of postural hygiene and physical therapy exercises is effective for the acquisition of knowledge and behaviors. The methodological quality of the studies is related to the effectiveness of the treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Muñoz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Meca, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Conesa, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Conocer los tratamientos fisioterapéuticos preventivos más eficaces para el cuidado de la espalda en niños y adolescentes y analizar la calidad metodológica de los artículos. Estrategia de búsqueda Se llevo a cabo una revisión sistemática de ensayos controlados en las bases de datos de Cochrane, MEDLINE, PEDro, Web of Science e IME. Selección de estudios y datos Se incluyeron un total de 16 trabajos que cumplieron con los criterios de selección, dando lugar a 19 estudios independientes. Síntesis de resultados Los 19 estudios analizados incluyeron tratamientos con higiene postural de forma aislada, tratamientos combinados de higiene postural y ejercicios fisioterapéuticos e higiene postural y actividad física. Conclusiones El tratamiento de higiene postural es el más utilizado por los autores. El tratamiento combinado de higiene postural con ejercicio fisioterapéutico es eficaz para la adquisición de conocimientos y conductas. La calidad metodológica de los estudios se relaciona con la eficacia del tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);33(6): 262-272, Nov. - Dic. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-98625</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de los tratamientos de fisioterapia preventivos para el cuidado de la espalda en niños y adolescentes. Revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30952^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33365^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
