<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165922</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Benefits of iodized salt for school age child</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Iodine is an essential mineral for the normal function of the human organism. When iodized salt is not employed, the consumption- on most occasions - depends entirely on the foods chosen in the daily diet .The aim of this study was to evaluate the use of iodized salt in households of children between 6 and 12 years of age. Methods: By using a nutritional questionnaire completed by parents about their child&#146;s eating habits, the corresponding information was obtained. In a total population of 312 children from various primary schools in the city of Valencia (Spain), an observational, descriptive cross-study was carried out. The result of which was an exhibit of 245 questionnaires gathered between June and December of 2012. Results: 47, 6% of households always and only use iodized salt whilst 15, 38% of households consume both iodized and non-iodized salt. Conclusions: Almost half of the households employ iodized salt, therefore benefiting from the properties of this mineral and avoiding the serious illnesses which the lack of the mineral can provoke.the Mediterranean diet and also a moderate physical activity, being greater among boys and younger (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Clérigues Bonet, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olaso González, Gloria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallada Regalado, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Gálvez, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gandía Balaguer, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alba Tamarit, Encarnación</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos: El yodo es un mineral imprescindible para el normal funcionamiento del organismo humano. La ingesta de yodo, la mayoría de las veces, es totalmente dependiente de los alimentos elegidos en la dieta diaria cuando no se hace uso de la sal yodada. El objetivo de este trabajo fue estimar el uso de sal yodada en los hogares con niños en edad escolar de entre 6 y 12 años. Métodos: A través de una encuesta nutricional, dirigida a padres que respondían acerca de los hábitos alimentarios de sus hijos, se pudo obtener la información correspondiente. Sobre una población total de 312 niños que cursaban primaria en diferentes colegios de la ciudad de Valencia (España), se realizó un estudio observacional descriptivo transversal del cual se obtuvo una muestra de 245 cuestionarios, recogidos entre junio y diciembre de 2012. Resultados: El 47,6% de los hogares siempre utilizaban algún tipo de sal yodada sin combinar con sal común, mientras el 15,38% de los hogares consumían tanto sal común como algún tipo de sal yodada. Conclusiones: Cerca de la mitad de los hogares hacen uso de la sal yodada, de esta manera pueden beneficiarse de las propiedades que este mineral aporta a la dieta y evitar las importantes enfermedades que la carencia de este mineral provoca en las personas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;23(2): 0-0, abr.-jun. 2017. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165922</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Beneficios del uso de sal yodada en niños de edad escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23461^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23461^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2702^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31384^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16566^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7619^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31384^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
