<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15536</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intermediate filament proteins in developing and adult human dorsal root and sympathetic ganglia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neuronal maturation in the central nervous system, as well as in some cells deriving from neural crest, is accompanied by a swich in the expression of cytoskeletal intermediate filament proteins. Whether this occurs in humans and the exact timing of this change in human dorsal root and sympathetic ganglia are matters still open to debate. The present study was designed to analyze these issues in human embryos (estimated gestational age -e.g.a.- ranging between 6 and 12 weeks), as well as the possible co-expression of more than one intermediate filament protein in both embryos and adults. A panel of commercially available antibodies against vimentin, glial fibrillary acidic protein and neurofilament proteins was used. Glial fibrillary acidic protein was consistently absent in both developing and adult dorsal root or sympathetic ganglia. Conversely, embryonic neurons, satellite glial cells and Schwann cells displayed vimentin immunoreactivity. The number of vimentin immunoreactive neurons decreased progressively, and it was absent from neurons by 12 weeks e.g.a., while it persisted in satellite glial and Schwann cells. By adulthood, the pattern of distribution was identical. The occurrence of neurofilament proteins in peripheral neurons was a regular feature from early developmental stages to adulthood, and a time-dependent increase in the percentage of neurons containing phosphorylated neurofilaments was observed. The present results demonstrate that developing human dorsal root and sympathetic ganglion neurons co-express vimentin and neurofilaments for a short time, but that the intermediate filaments for mature neurons are neurofilaments. Our findings also show that co-expression or a switch in the expression of intermediate filament proteins do not occur in satellite glial cells or Schwann cells, which normally contain vimentin and not glial fibrillary acidic protein (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La maduración neuronal en poblaciones neuronales discretas del sistema central nervioso, así como en algunas células que derivan de la cresta neural es acompañada de un cambio en la expresión de las proteínas citoesqueléticas de filamentos intermedios. El que esto ocurre en los seres humanos y la cronología exacta de este cambio en los ganglios de la raíz dorsal y simpáticos no se ha dilucidado todavía. El presente estudio fue diseñado para analizar estos problemas en embriones humanos (edad gestacional estimada &#150;e.g.e- en el intervalo entre 6 y 12 semanas), así como la posible co-expresión de más de una proteína de filamentos intermedios, tanto en embriones como en adultos. Se utilizó un panel de anticuerpos comerciales frente a la vimentina, a la proteína fibrilar glial ácida, y a las proteínas de los neurofilamentos. La proteína fibrilar glial ácida estaba consistentemente ausente de los ganglios de la raíz dorsal y simpáticos, tanto en el adulto como en embriones en desarrollo. Por el contrario, las neuronas embrionarias, las células gliales satélites y las células de Schwann exhibían inmunoreactividad frente a la vimentina. El número de neuronas con inmunoreactividad para la vimentina descendió progresivamente y este compuesto no se detectaba en las neuronas a una e.g.e. de 12 semanas, mientras que persistía en las células Schwann. Llegada la edad adulta, el patrón de distribución era idéntico. La presencia de proteínas de neurofilamentos en las neuronas periféricas se apreció como una característica consistente a partir de las fases tempranas del desarrollo hasta la edad adulta, observándose un descenso dependiente del tiempo en el porcentaje de neuronas que contenían neurofilamentos fosforilados. Los resultados aquí obtenidos demuestran que las neuronas de los ganglios de la raíz dorsal y simpáticos humanos en desarrollo co-expresan la vimentina y los neurofilamentos durante un periodo corto de tiempo, pero los filamentos intermedios de las neuronas maduras son neurofilamentos. Nuestros hallazgos también muestran que la co-expresión o un cambio en la expresión de las proteínas de los filamentos intermedios no ocurren en las células gliales ni en las de Schwann, las cuales normalmente contienen vimentina y no la proteína fibrilar glial ácida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;5(1): 1-9, mayo 2001. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las proteínas de los filamentos intermedios en los ganglios simpáticos y de la raíz dorsal humana adulta en desarrollo</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Vázquez, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naves, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San José, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Germanà, GP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vega, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteban, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15536</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15150^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13510^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5869^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9666^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7546^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5869^s22023</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13510^s29165</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200105</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
