<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156842</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Photodynamic therapy of a first mandibular molar with chronic apical periodontitis and a permeable inter-mesial isthmus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Photodynamic therapy (PDT) has been shown to exert antimicrobial action. Following conventional chemical-mechanical preparation, PDT reduces the microbial burden in the necrotic tooth. This implies an advantage in cases of necrosis in teeth with complex anatomical features, such as the presence of an isthmus. On the other hand, PDT could constitute an alternative to the use of drugs within the canal of teeth with periapical disease. This study describes the PDT technique using a low-power LED lamp (FotoSan®) as light source and toluidine blue as photosensitizer. A description is provided of the results obtained on combining the technique with conventional endodontic treatment of a first mandibular molar with a permeable isthmus, pulp necrosis and chronic apical periodontitis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Forner, Leopoldo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilar, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almenar, Amelia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llena, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>París, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La terapia fotodinámica (TFD) es un procedimiento terapéutico con capacidad antimicrobiana demostrada en la literatura científica. Esta constatado que su empleo, después de la preparación químico-mecánica convencional, reduce la carga microbiana en el diente necrótico. Esto supone una ventaja en los casos de necrosis en dientes con anatomías complejas, como cuando existe un istmo. Por otro lado, la TFD podría ser una alternativa al empleo de medicaciones intraconducto en los dientes con patología periapical. El propósito de este articulo es describir la técnica de uso de la TDF, empleando una lámpara de diodos LED de baja potencia (FotoSan®) como fuente lumínica y azul de toluidina como fotosensibilizador, y mostrar los resultados de su asociación con el tratamiento endodóncico convencional, en un caso de un primer molar mandibular con istmo permeable, necrosis pulpar y periodontitis apical crónica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);34(1): 32-41, ene.-mar. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156842</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Terapia fotodinámica en un primer molar mandibular con periodontitis apical crónica e istmo intermesial permeable</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22005</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d41^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d41^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14190^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8509^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9153^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
