<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165444</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-208X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nutritional status of patients with gastrointestinal tract neoplasias</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In cancer patients there is a marked metabolic alteration, low food intake, altered nutrient absorption, energy requirement and emotional stress, which trigger in weight loss and malnutrition; to prevent its occurrence or progress is essential to assess the nutritional status. Objective: To make a clinical characterization of patients with gastrointestinal neoplasms hospitalized at the Hospital Universitario Mayor Méderi during the period July 2014 - July 2016, by determining the nutritional status and identification of the nutritional support with the highest prevalence. Methods: Cross-sectional, retrospective study between July 2014 and July 2016. We reviewed 399 patients clinical histories with nutritional assessment, a simple and multiple correspondence analysis for the categorical variables. 384 patients were taken for the multivariate analysis. Results: Of the patients who presented weight loss, 47% had severe loss. The most frequent tumors were stomach (32.1%), colon (24.5%) and rectum (7.3%). The malnutrition diagnosis and the oral nutritional supplement were the most frequent. Moderate and severe caloric protein malnutrition is associated with malignant tumors of the rectum, esophagus, and stomach. Enteral support was associated with malignancy of the esophagus and stomach. Oral support with supplementation is related to the presence of malnutrition. Discussion: The incidence of malnutrition in cancer patients may be between 40% and 80%, depending on the type of tumor, in patients with solid gastrointestinal tumors there is a higher prevalence of weight loss, the present study showed that 60% of the population was malnourished. On the other hand, obesity has been associated with factors that increase cancer risk and mortality, this study showed a relationship between overweight and obesity with liver, gallbladder, colon and rectal cancer. The nutritional intervention in patients with cancer focuses on a high energy intake, which is achieved through different specialized nutritional supports, it is the functionality of the gastrointestinal tract one factors that determine nutritional support. Conclusions: 52% of patients with gastrointestinal neoplasms are valued by the nutrition service. Malnutrition was the most frequent nutritional diagnosis and the support one with the highest prevalence was the oral supplement. Nutritional diagnoses overweight and obesity are associated with tumors of the liver and vesicle (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Valoyes Bejarano, Elizabeth</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Restrepo, Milena Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varila, Maria Alejandra</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinzón Espitia, Olga Lucia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En pacientes oncológicos existe una marcada alteración metabólica, baja ingesta de alimentos, alteración en la absorción de nutrientes, en el requerimiento energético y estrés emocional, que desencadenan pérdida de peso y desnutrición; para prevenir su aparición o progreso es fundamental evaluar el estado nutricional. Objetivo: Realizar una caracterización clínica de pacientes con cáncer del tracto gastrointestinal hospitalizados en el Hospital Universitario Mayor Méderi durante el periodo Julio 2014 - Julio 2016, mediante la determinación del estado nutricional, y la identificación del soporte nutricional de mayor prevalencia. Métodos: Estudio transversal, retrospectivo entre julio de 2014 y julio de 2016. Se revisaron 399 historias clínicas de pacientes con valoración nutricional, se realizó un análisis de correspondencias simples, y múltiples para las variables categóricas. Se tomaron 384 pacientes para el análisis multivariado. Resultados: De los pacientes que presentaron pérdida de peso el 47% tuvo perdida severa. Los tumores de mayor frecuencia fueron estómago (32.1%), colon (24.5%) y recto (7.3%). El diagnóstico de desnutrición y el suplemento nutricional vía oral fueron los de mayor frecuencia. La desnutrición proteico calórica moderada y severa se relacionan con tumores malignos del recto, del esófago y del estómago. El soporte enteral se asoció al tumor maligno de esófago y de estómago. El soporte oral con suplemento se relaciona con la presencia de desnutrición. Discusión: La incidencia de desnutrición en pacientes oncológicos puede estar entre un 40% a 80%, dependiendo del tipo de tumor, en pacientes con tumores sólidos gastrointestinales se presenta una mayor prevalencia de pérdida de peso, el presente estudio evidencio que el 60% de la población cursaba con desnutrición. Por su parte la obesidad se ha asociado con factores que aumentan el riesgo y la mortalidad por cáncer, en este estudio se evidencio una relación del sobrepeso y la obesidad con el cáncer de hígado, vesícula biliar, colon y recto. La intervención nutricional en estos pacientes se enfoca en un aporte energético alto, lo que se logra mediante los diferentes soportes nutricionales especializados, es la funcionalidad del tracto gastrointestinal uno de los factores que determina el soporte nutricional. Conclusiones: El 52% de pacientes con neoplasia del tracto gastrointestinal son valorados por el servicio de nutrición. La desnutrición fue el diagnóstico nutricional más frecuente, el soporte de mayor prevalencia fue el suplemento vía oral. Los diagnósticos nutricionales de sobrepeso y obesidad se asocian a tumores de hígado y vesícula (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr. clín. diet. hosp;37(2): 139-146, 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165444</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado Nutricional de pacientes con neoplasias del tracto gastrointestinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8836^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5911^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32108^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
