<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125586</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychoanalysis of the Faroni syndrome at middle age</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Montero, Guillermo Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">The paper is an attempt at applying psychoanalysis to the novel Juegos de la edad tardía by Luis Landero, in which the authors describes all the characteristics related to the working out of anxieties specific to middle age. The writer begins by making a definition of middle age as from the psychical work generated as a result of incipient signs of aging that take the transience of individual life evident. Taking as a reference Freud´s work On transience the author then continues from a theoretical point of view, enabling us to understand the complexity of both the transition and the crisis of middle &#150;age. Freud, in his previously-mentioned work, suggest different possible courses of working out what is short-lived, courses that act as prototype to formulate three differentiated modalities of passage through middle age. In continuation, the writer details the Faroni Syndrome as such, as one of those pathognomonical modalities of middle age, characterized by the establishment of a double with mixed characteristics of double immortal and double ideal with which the person interacts, trying to advance the expression, elaboration and integration of repressed and dissociated psychical contents, as well as the simultaneous promotion of autoplastic and alloplastic transformations. Following and argumental and biographical synthesis of the character, the paper details the history of child neurosis and identifications, the adolescent bond with middle age, a particular modality of bond with the ideal generated during childhood (afán) and its consequences, the Faroni Syndrome, and the expression of the double during middle age, the visissitudes of the self as the regulator of self steem during middle age, as well as a psychopathological vertex. All of these captions aim to explain what the author denominates the Faroni Syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(44): 233-259, ene.-abr. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125586</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Psicoanálisis del Síndrome Faroni en la mediana edad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22101^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5755</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12035^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
