<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116658</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testosterone deficit syndrome in infertile or subfertile men</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Spermatogenesis is a well defined, complex, long and very orderlyprocess of cellular division and differentiation that is under regulation by endocrine signals (GnRH, LH, Inhibin and FSH): paracrine signals, derived from the interrelation of the various types of cells in the tubules and interstitium (even in a juxtacrine way), and autocrine signals of self communication of the cell with itself. Testosterone plays an essential role in this process. In the testicular tubules, testosterone reaches concentrations 100 times higher than circulating testosterone in the blood stream. From a reproduction point of view, we can find two completely different scenarios in relation to testosterone deficit syndrome with a similar final clinical result: The difficulties of the male to have children. On one side the presence of hypogonadism, which requires a different management depending of the clinical priority and wishes of parenthood of the patient an his partner. On the other side, the opposite situation, the patient who requires or is already under testosterone therapy. In patients with hypogonadotropic hypogonadism, when patient`s clinical priority is fertility, the treatment to restore normal spermatogenesis requires external administration of gonadotropins. Treatment must be prolonged, at least 12-18 months.95% of the cases will have a favorable response, meaning the finding of spermatozoids in ejaculation sperm as a consequence of spermatogenesis restoration (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cruz-Navarro, Natalio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La espermatogénesis es un proceso bien definido, complejo, largo y muy ordenado de división y diferenciación celular, que se encuentra bajo regulación de señales endocrinas (GnRH, LH, Inhibina y FSH); paracrinas, derivadas de la interrelación entre los distintos tipos de células de los túbulos y del intersticio (incluso vía yuxtacrina); y de señales autocrinas, de autocomunicación de una célula consigo misma. En todo este proceso la testosterona juega un papel fundamental. La testosterona en el interior del túbulo testicular alcanza concentraciones 100 veces mayores que la testosterona circulante en torrente sanguíneo. Desde un punto de vista reproductivo podemos encontrar dos escenarios completamente diferentes relacionados con un Síndrome de Déficit de Testosterona (SDT) que darán lugar a un resultado clínico final similar: la dificultad para tener hijos del varón. Por un lado la presencia de un hipogonadismo, que requiere un manejo diferente en función de la prioridad clínica y los deseos de descendencia del paciente y su pareja. Por otro la situación inversa, la de un paciente que requiere o ya está en tratamiento con testosterona. Cuando la prioridad clínica del paciente es la fertilidad, en pacientes con hipogonadismo hipogonadotropo, el tratamiento para restaurar una espermatogenesis normal requiere la administración exógena de gonadotropinas. El tratamiento debe ser prolongado, con una duración de al menos 12-18 meses. En el 95% de los casos se va a obtener una respuesta favorable, entendiendo como tal la aparición de espermatozoides en el eyaculado, consecuencia del restablecimiento de la espermatogénesis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;66(7): 675-683, sept. 2013. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116658</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome SDT en varón infértil o subfértil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7425^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7184^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22015</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
