<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056687</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-6343</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: The present study describes the determination of        the bioequivalence of two different nevirapine tablet formulations        (nevirapine tablets 200 mg, Novatec, as the test formulation vs.        viramune tablets 200 mg, Boehringer Ingelheim, as the reference        formulation).        Method: A single 200 mg oral dose of each preparation was        administered to 11 human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-infected        patients volunteers and their bioequivalence was assessed by comparing        the both plasma nevirapine concentrations-time curves and        others pharmacokinetic parameters.        Results: The pharmacokinetic parameters obtained for each        formulation were the area under the time-concentration curve from        0 to 12 h (AUC0-12) and from 0 to infinity (AUC0&amp;#8722;&amp;#8734;), maximum concentration        (Cmax), and the time at which it occurred (Tmax). These        parameters were determined by high-performance liquid chromatography        (HPLC). No significant differences were observed in        these parameters. The 90% confident interval for the ratio of        means for the lnAUC0-12 T/R (0.92-1.10), lnAUC0&amp;#8722;&amp;#8734; T/R (0.86-1.17)        and lnCmax T/R (0.71-1.38) are within the guideline range of bioequivalence        (0.80 to 1.25 and 0.70 to 1.43). For Tmax the mean of        test formulation is in the range 2.64 ± 0.53 h.        Conclusions: The results show that the formulations were        bioequivalent in the extent and in the rate of absorption</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abreu, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tápanes, R. D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tarinas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: En el siguiente estudio se muestra la determinación        de bioequivalencia de dos formulaciones diferentes de tabletas de        nevirapina (NVP) &#150;tabletas de NVP de 200 mg, de los laboratorios        Novatec, como la formulación de prueba (P) vs. las tabletas de        Viramune® de 200 mg, de Boehringer Ingelheim, como la formulación        de referencia (R)&#150;.        Método: Una dosis única de 200 mg de cada formulación fue        administrada a 11 pacientes-voluntarios infectados con el VIH y        se determinó la bioequivalencia entre ambas formulaciones por        comparación de las curvas de concentración-tiempo y de otros        parámetros farmacocinéticos medidos en plasma de estos pacientes        para ambos productos.        Resultados: Los parámetros farmacocinéticos obtenidos para        cada formulación fueron área bajo la curva de concentración en el        tiempo de estudio e infinita (AUC0-12 y AUC0&amp;#8722;&amp;#8734;), concentración máxima        (Cmax) y tiempo para alcanzar la concentración máxima (Tmax).        Estos parámetros fueron determinados por cromatografía líquida de        alta resolución (HPLC). No se observaron diferencias significativas        en los parámetros para ambas formulaciones. En el intervalo de        confianza de 90% la razón de las medias de lnAUC0-12 P/R (0,92-        1,10), lnAUC0&amp;#8722;&amp;#8734; P/R (0,86-1,17) y lnCmax P/R (0,71-1,38) están dentro        de los rangos establecidos de bioequivalencia (0,80-1,25 ó 0,70-        1,43). Para Tmax, la media de la formulación de prueba se encuentra        dentro del rango 2,64 ± 0,53 h.        Conclusiones: Los resultados muestran que ambas formulaciones        son bioequivalentes en cuanto a la magnitud y velocidad de        la absorción</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm Hosp;31(3): 165-168, may.-jun.2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056687</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bioequivalence study of two nevirapine tablet formulations in human immunodeficiency virus-infected patients</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33411^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d286</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2672^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33411^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33411^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23478</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33075^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33075^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
