<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150125</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical activity assessment in the general population; validated self-report methods</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Self-reported questionnaires have been commonly used to assess physical activity levels in large cohort studies. As a result, strong and convincing evidences that physical activity can protect health are widely recognized. However, validation studies using objective measures of physical activity or energy expenditure (double labelled water, accelerometers, pedometers, etc.) indicate that the accuracy and precision of survey techniques are limited. Physical activity questionnaires could fail in estimating particularly non-vigorous physical activity. They have a disproportionate focus on volitional type exercise (i.e. biking, jogging, and walking), while not capturing the activities of daily living and low to moderate intensity movements. Energy expenditure estimates from these data are not recommended. On the other hand, despite objective tools should be the measurement of choice to assess PA level, self-reported questionnaires remain valid, and have many advantages. i.e. low costs. These kind of recalls are designed and validated for different age groups and provide value and important information, mainly about physical activity pattern. Future studies will require more precision and accuracy in physical activity measurement than those provided by traditional survey methods. We can conclude that probably a mixed approach that combines both the objective and subjective techniques involving novel devices and electronic capture of physical activity questionnaires will be more effective (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ara, Ignacio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales-Barco, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nascimento de Souza, Wyslleny</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Gross, Marcela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aparicio-Ugarriza, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aznar, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mata, Esmeralda</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los cuestionarios auto-administrados han sido comúnmente utilizados en los estudios con grandes cohortes, con el fin de evaluar la actividad física de sus participantes. Como consecuencia de ello, existe una considerable cantidad de evidencias científicas sobre el efecto protector de la actividad física sobre la salud. Sin embargo, los estudios de validación que utilizan métodos objetivos, cómo métodos de referencia o «Gold Standard», para la cuantificación de la actividad física o el gasto energético (el agua doblemente marcada, los acelerómetros, los podómetros, etc.), indican que la precisión de los cuestionarios es limitada. Los cuestionarios de actividad física pueden fallar especialmente al estimar la actividad física no vigorosa, y suelen centrarse de forma específica en el ejercicio planificado (ir en bicicleta, correr, andar,&#133;) y no suelen recoger las actividades de la vida diaria y movimientos de intensidad baja no planificada. Por ello, la estimación del gasto energético a partir de estos datos no es muy recomendable. Por otro lado, y a pesar de que los métodos objetivos deberían ser la primera elección a la hora de evaluar la actividad física, los cuestionarios se mantienen todavía como herramientas válidas y con muchas ventajas. Una de las ventajas es la buena implementación para estudios epidemiológicos y su bajo coste. Además, este tipo de instrumentos están específicamente diseñados y validados para diferentes grupos de edad y proporcionan información valiosa e importante, sobre todo, del patrón de actividad física. Sin embargo, aún son necesarios futuros estudios que investiguen en métodos más precisos para medir la actividad física respecto a la que proporcionan los cuestionarios. Podemos concluir que probablemente un método mixto que combine los métodos objetivos y subjetivos, y que incluya nuevos sistemas y registros electrónicos, sería lo más recomendable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;21(supl.1): 209-214, 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150125</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la actividad física en la población general; cuestionarios validados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36345^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32676^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52426^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6184</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
