<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043973</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-8855</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unifocal cervical spine multiple sclerosis. Demyelinating pseudotumor</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a demyelinizatingdisease with variable clinic, radiologic and even pathologicfeatures. Those cases simulating a neoplastic disease, especiallythe unifocal forms of the spinal chord are very rare.Patients and methods: An autopsy case of unifocal MS ofcervical spinal cord is reported. After clinical and radiologicalexaminations a neoplastic condition was suspected. Diagnosiswas made after microscopic study of autopsy specimens.Results (pathologic diagnosis): After routine histological examinationof cervical spinal cord and by using special techniques(luxol fast blue), demyelinating plaques, lymphocyticand macrophagic perivascular and interstitial inflammatoryinfiltrate were found. Conclusions: The authors propose insuch cases the use of the term «demyelinating pseudotumor».The authors consider necessary to include this clinicopathologicentity in the differential diagnosis of other expansive processesof the CNS and diagnose it using non aggressive techniquesso avoiding an inadequate treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Segura Sánchez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Serrano, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Escudero, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Sanz, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La esclerosis múltiple es una enfermedaddesmielinizante con expresión clínica, radiológica eincluso patológica variables. Los casos que remedan un procesoneoplásico del S.N.C., y los unifocales, especialmentelos medulares, son bastante raros. Métodos: Se presenta uncaso de autopsia de E.M. unifocal de médula cervical, queclínica y radiológicamente se confundió con una neoplasia,llegándose al diagnóstico en el estudio microscópico delmaterial procedente de la autopsia. Resultados: Mediantetécnicas radiológicas adecuadas y/o el estudio del materialprocedente de biopsia en ciertos casos, es posible realizarun diagnóstico precoz del proceso. Conclusiones: Los autoresproponen la definición de Pseudotumor desmielinizante.Y creen necesario considerar la posibilidad de esta entidadclínicopatológica en el diagnóstico diferencial de los procesosexpansivos del S.N.C., y es preciso diagnosticarlamediante la utilización de técnicas no agresivas antes deinstaurar un posible tratamiento inadecuado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. patol;38(2): 125-128, abr.-jun. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043973</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esclerosis múltiple unifocal de médula cervical. Pseudotumor desmielinizante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6255^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1352</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29594^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9296^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
