<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129927</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lateral chest X-rays. Radiographic anatomy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lateral chest views constitute an essential part of chest X-ray examinations, so it is fundamental to know the anatomy on these images and to be able to detect the variations manifested on these images in different diseases. The aim of this article is to review the normal anatomy and main normal variants seen on lateral chest views. For teaching purposes, we divide the thorax into different spaces and analyze each in an orderly way, especially emphasizing the anatomic details that are most helpful for locating lesions that have already been detected in the posteroanterior view or for detecting lesions that can be missed in the posteroanterior view (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pedrosa, C. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Villafañe, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La radiografía lateral forma parte esencial del estudio radiográfico del tórax, y el conocimiento anatómico es fundamental para poder detectar las variaciones que en ella producen las diferentes enfermedades. El objetivo de este trabajo es realizar una revisión anatómica de esta proyección, así como de las principales variantes normales. Para ello, y con fines únicamente didácticos, se ha dividido el tórax en diferentes espacios que se analizarán de manera ordenada, haciendo especial hincapié en los detalles anatómicos que más pueden ayudar a localizar lesiones ya detectadas en la proyección posteroanterior, o a detectar lesiones que pueden pasar desapercibidas en esa proyección (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);56(6): 548-560, nov.-dic. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129927</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Radiografía lateral de tórax. Anatomía radiográfica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10530^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8345^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d727^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8345^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
