<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123255</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Iconographic signs of public recognition of Nursing in Spain: their relevance and significance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Iconographic signs (statues, monoliths and monuments; dedication of streets or other public spaces; philatelic issues, etc..) to express public recognition to nurses and nursing, are realizations arising mainly from virtually the last years of twentieth century. However, they have had to date they deserve consideration in the study of the History of Nursing. This paper seeks to identify those in Spain, cataloging and describing, analyzing with the help of semiotics the degree of perception of their messages and how these signs can be considered relevant and appropriate to achieve the objectives (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ávila Olivares, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los signos iconográficos (estatuas, monolitos y monumentos; dedicación de calles u otros espacios públicos; emisiones filatélicas, etc.) para manifestar el reconocimiento público a las enfermeras y a la Enfermería, son realizaciones en su mayoría surgidas prácticamente a partir de los últimos años del pasado siglo XX. Sin embargo, no han tenido hasta la fecha la consideración que se merecen en el estudio de la Historia de la Enfermería. En este trabajo se trata de identificar los existentes en España, catalogarlos y describirlos, analizando con el auxilio de la semiótica el grado de percepción de sus mensajes y en qué medida estos signos pueden considerarse pertinentes y adecuados para lograr los objetivos propuestos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;18(38): 92-106, ene.-abr. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123255</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los signos iconográficos del reconocimiento público de la Enfermería en España: su importancia y significación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d21070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32415</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
