<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166119</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological characteristics that influence sports injuries of amateur triathletes from Yucatan, Mexico</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this research was to analyze the relation between the psychological characteristics with the sport injuries in amateur triathletes from Yucatan, Mexico. The next instruments were applied: Psychological Inventory of Sports Performance (IPED), Sport Competition Anxiety Test (SCAT), Questionnaire of Perceived causes of Injuries in Triathletes (CPELT) and Self-report of training and injuries features. The sample was composed of 50 triathletes, 33 men (66%) and 17 women (34%) with a mean age of 24.47 in a range of 15 to 48 years. Significant relationships were found in the number of sport injuries with IPED and CPELT factors. Furthermore, the competitive anxiety, coping negative control from IPED and prevention measures factor from CPELT gained a better predictive value for sports injuries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Olmedilla, Aurelio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moo Estrella, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Reyes, Aldo Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este trabajo fue analizar las relaciones entre las características psicológicas con las lesiones deportivas en triatletas amateurs de Yucatán, México. Se aplicaron los siguientes instrumentos: Inventario Psicológico de Ejecución Deportiva (IPED), Sport Competition Anxiety Test (SCAT), Cuestionario de Percepción de las causas de las Lesiones en el Triatleta (CPELT) y Autoinforme de características del entrenamiento y de lesiones. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 50 triatletas, 33 hombres (66%) y 17 mujeres (34%) con una media de edad de 24.47 en un rango de 15 a 48 años. Se encontraron relaciones significativas del número de lesiones con factores del IPED y del CPELT. Además la ansiedad competitiva, el control de afrontamiento negativo del IPED y el factor de medidas preventivas del CPELT obtuvieron un mejor valor de predicción para las lesiones deportivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;26(supl.2): 71-77, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166119</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Características psicológicas que influyen en las lesiones deportivas de triatletas amateurs de Yucatán, México</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d54747^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8990^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14532^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53812^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
