<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049568</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dialectical materialism as fundament of soviet psychology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After the Soviet revolution (1917), the application of the Marxism to the task of building a new society determined the existence of the Soviet psychology, a clearly differentiated tradition and with own personality. The Marxism-Leninism was imposed as ideological mark in which all scientific tentative should necessarily be based. In the years twenty the psychology should be materialistic and starting from the thirty it should also be dialectical. The Soviet psychology was presented this way like a philosophical partisan, committed science and socially with a Marxism-Leninist vision of the society that adopted a dialectical materialistic perspective.In this work we will analyze the fundamental positions of the dialectical materialism as well as their influence in the psychology, which was determined for the changes of the power (you purge, prohibitions, impositions&#133;) that constantly interfered in the life ofthe science in way unpredictable</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zumalabe Makirriain, José María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras la revolución soviética (1917), la aplicación del marxismo a la tarea de construir una nueva sociedad determinó la existencia de la psicología soviética, una tradición claramente diferenciada y con personalidad propia. Se imponía el marxismo-leninismo como marco ideológico en el que necesariamente debía basarse toda tentativa científica. En los años veinte la psicología debía ser materialista y a partir de los treinta también debía ser dialéctica. Así la psicología soviética se presentaba como una ciencia partidista, comprometida filosófica y socialmente con una visión marxista-leninista de la sociedad, que adoptaba una perspectiva materialista dialéctica. En este artículo analizamos los planteamientos fundamentales del materialismo dialéctico así como su influencia en la psicología,claramente determinada por los avatares del poder (purgas, prohibiciones, imposiciones...) que de forma impredecible se entrometía constantemente en la vida de la ciencia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);6(1): 21-50, ene. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049568</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El materialismo dialéctico, fundamento de la psicología soviética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16136</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12021^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14987</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8776</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
