<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156788</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Orally ingestion of krokodil in Spain: report of a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The krokodil use disorder is an addictive pathology with quite severe organic effects, especially at the skin level, that causes severe and degenerative necrosis of blood and muscle tissue. Though this disorder has a low prevalence in Spain, compared to the large number of consumers in other countries such as Ukraine or Russia, its consumption is slowly but gradually expanding in countries of the European Union and America. The simplicity of the process of obtaining the substance from desomorphine, together with its high availability and low cost, contribute toward consumers&#146; self-sufficiency. This article presents the case of a user of krokodil and reviews the clinical symptoms of oral ingestion (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baquero Escribano, Abel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Negre, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carratalá Monfort, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo Orenga, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meca Zapatero, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Haro Cortés, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arnau Peiró, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno por uso de krokodil es una de las patologías adictivas con mayores repercusiones orgánicas, principalmente a nivel cutáneo, produciendo una grave y degenerativa necrosis del tejido sanguíneo y muscular. Se trata de un trastorno con escasa prevalencia en España, frente al elevado número de consumidores en otros países como Ucrania o Rusia, si bien se está produciendo una lenta aunque gradual expansión del consumo en países de la Unión Europea y del continente americano. El sencillo proceso de obtención de la sustancia desde la desomorfina, unido a la elevada disponibilidad y bajo coste, configura el proceso de autoabastecimiento de los consumidores. En este artículo revisamos un cuadro clínico, presentando el caso de un paciente que consume krokodil por vía oral (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);28(4): 242-245, 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156788</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de krokodil por vía oral en España: a propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24888^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24888^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9212^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9212^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9211^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9213^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
