<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-130041</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-3568</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fournier Gangrene. Favourable evolution after multidisciplinary treatment. About a case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Necrotising fasciitis, penile-scrotal gangrene or Fournier Gangrene (FO) consiscs of a serious process characterised by necrosis of che skin and the skin covering tite penis, scrotum and perineum as well as subcutaneous ccli tissue, with a sudden installation and quick evolution. Wc present che case of a 64-year oId male attendcd in our Hospital, who vas admitted with a set of symptoms chat evolved to a coma secondaiy to diabetic ketoacidosis, diagnosed hy GP. He receives a multimodal treatment from a multidisciplinary team, based on energecic surgical approach and a broad-based ancibiocic che rapy. vith a favourable evolution. The data relating to the treatment of our patient are described, presenting the good resulcs obcained with the app!ication of hyperharic oxygen therapy and enzymatic debriding with lyophilised collagen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abril, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Correa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rey Seijo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz del Río, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rial, E. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reguengo, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Fascitis necrotizante, Gangrena peneoescrotal o Gangrena de Fournier (OF) consiste en un grave proceso caracterizado por la necrosis de la piel y tejidos de revestimiento de pene, escroto y periné así como del tejido celular subcutáneo, con una instauración brusca y una evolución fulminante. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 64 años atendido en nuestro Hospital que ingresó con un cuadro que evolucionó a coma secundario a cetoacidosis diabética, siendo diagnosticado de GP. Recibe un tratamiento multimodal por un equipo multidiscipli nario, basado en un abordaje quirúrgico enérgico y una terapia antibiótica amplia, observándose una evolución favorable. Se describen los datos relativos al tratamiento de nuestro paciente, exponiendo los buenos resultados obtenidos con la aplicación de oxigenoterapia hiperbárica y desbridamiento enzimático con colágeno liofilizado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. mil;58(3): 41-44, jul.-sept. 2002. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-130041</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gangrena de Fournier: evolución favorable tras tratamiento multidisciplinario. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32745^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32750^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29340^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3664^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30156^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
