<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160654</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Report of the Neuropediatric section of the Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pediatric Neurology is the pediatric speciality with more request for assitance. In our hospital, Pediatric Neurology unit is composed of four assistant doctors. Three of them have a full employment contract and the other a 75% contract. In this article it is exposed the healthcare activity in both outpatient consultations and in pediatric neurology hospitalization, as well as the relationship with other pediatric specialities. Also it has been described our medical portfolio, highlighting we are a national reference center for pediatric stroke and a national reference center for movement disorders (CSUR). Finally, it has been reported the great growth that our section has experienced in recent years specially in the academic and research fields (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vázquez López, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Herrero, MC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro de Castro, P de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barredo Valderrama, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Neuropediatría es una de las especialidades pediátricas que más demanda genera. En el Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón la Sección de Neuropediatria está compuesta por 4 médicos adjuntos, tres trabajando al 100% en la Sección y uno al 75%. En este artículo se expone la actividad asistencial en consultas externas e interconsultas de hospitalización así como la relación con otras especialidades. Se describe también nuestra cartera de servicios, haciendo énfasis en que somos Centro de Referencia nacional en ictus pediátrico y Centro, Servicio y Unidad de Referencia del Sistema Nacional de Salud (CSUR) en trastornos del movimiento. Por último, se reseña el importante empuje que ha tenido nuestra Sección en los últimos años en los aspectos docente e investigador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;72(6): 375-380, nov.-dic. 2016. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160654</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Memoria de la Sección de Neuropediatría del Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6925^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1327^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6940^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2700^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9262^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
