<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163494</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Competency development and organizational environment for performance of advanced practice by Nursing professionals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to evaluate the degree of development of the competency level of nurses in the Balearic Islands regarding selfperception of individual factors for the development of a practice based on evidence and culture and organizational factors. Method: a descriptive transversal study on the population of the Nursing professionals registered in the Balearic Islands, based on voluntary participation in a self-assessment process through online survey with the Limesurvey® platform. The measurement scales were three scales for overall, specific and advanced competencies in Nursing for the analysis of competency development, as well as the Nursing Work Index in order to measure the organizational environment. Results: six hundred (600) female and male nurses from different healthcare settings completed successfully the survey. The analysis showed overall results of an organizational environment with moderate-low scores, while general and specific competencies showed an acceptable score vs. advanced competencies, with overall low scores. Discussion and conclusions: there is a direct relationship between years in the profession and a worse perception of the organizational setting. On the other hand, and regardless of the healthcare setting, the overall and specific competencies which professionals have when they complete their University studies are maintained in medium-high levels throughout their years in the profession. This is not the case with advanced competencies, which show an overall low score, and have a directly proportional influence by the organisational environment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pedro Gómez, Joan E de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sastre Fullana, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bennasar Veny, Miquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco Mavillard, Ian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Serra, Rosa M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: evaluar el grado de desarrollo del nivel competencial de las enfermeras de las Illes Balears relacionado con la autopercepción de los factores individuales para el desarrollo de una práctica basada en la evidencia y cultura y factores organizacionales. Método: se llevó a cabo un estudio descriptivo transversal sobre la población de profesionales de Enfermería colegiados de las Illes Balears, basado en una participación voluntaria en un proceso de autoevaluación mediante encuesta online sobre la plataforma Limesurvey ®. Las escalas de medida fueron tres escalas de competencias generales, específicas y avanzadas de Enfermería para el análisis del desarrollo competencial, así como el Nursing Work Index para medir el clima organizacional. Resultados: 600 enfermeras y enfermeros de diversos ámbitos asistenciales completaron satisfactoriamente la encuesta. El análisis arrojó resultados globales de un clima organizacional con puntuaciones moderadas-bajas, mientras que los resultados de las competencias generales y específicas puntuaban aceptablemente frente a las competencias avanzadas que puntuaron bajo en general. Discusión y conclusiones: existe una relación directa entre años de profesión y empeoramiento de la percepción del contexto organizacional. Por otro lado, y con independencia del ámbito asistencial, las competencias generales y específicas con las que los profesionales egresan de la universidad se mantienen en niveles medios-altos a lo largo de los años de profesión. No ocurre así con las competencias avanzadas que en general puntúan bajo y se ven influencias de manera directamente proporcional por el clima organizacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(4): 55-60, mayo 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163494</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Desarrollo competencial y clima organizacional para el desempeño de una práctica avanzada de los profesionales de Enfermería</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23790</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32547</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53787^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
