<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-055573</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Granular parakeratosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Granular parakeratosis is a rare entity that results from an acquired disorder of keratinization.Clinically presents as dark erythematous plaques, occasionally pruritic, that usually involve the axilla and other intertriginous areas. The pathology is characteristic and consists of thickening of the stratum corneum with compact parakeratosis and retention of keratohyaline granules, whereas the stratum granulosum is preserved. The etiology is unknown although some factors such as irritating physical or chemical agents have been implicated. Treatment response is variable. We report a new case in a 50-year-old woman with brownish and hyperkeratotic plaques on both axillae, of two years duration, with a compatible pathology that showed a favorable response to tacalcitol</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Polo-Rodríguez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallés-Blanco, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vanaclocha-Sebastiána, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosales-Trujillo, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González de Arriba, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Peralto, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz de Frutos, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La paraqueratosis granular es una entidad poco frecuente que se caracteriza por ser una alteración adquirida de la queratinización. Clínicamente se presenta como placas eritematoparduscas, ocasionalmente pruriginosas, que clásicamente aparecen en la axila y áreas intertriginosas. La histología es característica, donde se observa un engrosamiento de la capa córnea con una paraqueratosis compacta y persistencia de gránulos de queratohialina, mientras que el estrato granuloso se encuentra preservado. La etiología es desconocida, se postula la acción de factores irritantes físicos o químicos. La respuesta al tratamiento es variable. Presentamos un nuevo caso en una mujer de 50 años, con placas marronáceas abollonadas e hiperqueratósicas en ambas axilas, de dos años de evolución y con histología compatible, que presentó una buena respuesta al tratamiento con tacalcitol</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;98(5): 355-357, jun. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-055573</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paraqueratosis granular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10430^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10430^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1377</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4139^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6248^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
