<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153415</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-4007</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Testosterone and attention deficits as possible mechanisms underlying impaired emotion recognition in intimate partner violence perpetrators</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Several studies have reported impairments in decoding emotional facial expressions in intimate partner violence (IPV) perpetrators. However, the mechanisms that underlie these impaired skills are not well known. Given this gap in the literature, we aimed to establish whether IPV perpetrators (n=18) differ in their emotion decoding process, attentional skills, and testosterone (T), cortisol (C) levels and T/C ratio in comparison with controls (n=20), and also to examine the moderating role of the group and hormonal parameters in the relationship between attention skills and the emotion decoding process. Our results demonstrated that IPV perpetrators showed poorer emotion recognition and higher attention switching costs than controls. Nonetheless, they did not differ in attention to detail and hormonal parameters. Finally, the slope predicting emotion recognition from deficits in attention switching became steeper as T levels increased, especially in IPV perpetrators, although the basal C and T/C ratios were unrelated to emotion recognition and attention deficits for both groups. These findings contribute to a better understanding of the mechanisms underlying emotion recognition deficits. These factors therefore constitute the target for future interventions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romero-Martínez, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lila, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya-Albiol, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Diversos estudios hablan de carencias en la descodificación de expresiones emocionales faciales en aquellos sujetos que cometen violencia de pareja (VP). No obstante, no se conocen bien los mecanismos subyacentes al déficit de estas capacidades. A la vista de esta laguna en investigación, hemos intentado establecer si las personas que cometen violencia de pareja (n=18) se diferencian en el proceso de descodificación emocional, capacidad de atención y niveles de testosterona (T), cortisol y cociente T/C, comparados con los controles (n=20), así como analizar el papel moderador del grupo y de las variables hormonales en la relación entre capacidad de atención y proceso de descodificación emocional. Nuestros resultados han demostrado que quienes perpetran violencia de pareja muestran un peor reconocimiento emocional y mayor coste en el cambio de atención que los controles. No obstante, no había diferencias en la atención a los detalles y en las variables hormonales. Por último, la pendiente que predice el reconocimiento emocional a partir de los déficits en el cambio de atención era más pronunciada a medida que aumentaban los niveles de testosterona, sobre todo en los sujetos que perpetran violencia de pareja, aunque el cortisol basal y el cociente T/C no guardaban relación con el reconocimiento de emociones y déficit de atención en ambos grupos. Estos resultados contribuyen a explicar los mecanismos que subyacen a los déficits de reconocimiento de emociones. Estos factores son pues el objetivo de intervenciones futuras (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. psychol. appl. legal context (Internet);8(2): 57-62, jul. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La testosterona y los déficits de atención como posibles mecanismos que subyacen a las carencias en el reconocimiento emocional de los hombres que ejercen violencia contra la mujer en las relaciones de pareja</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51792^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56155^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56155^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56155^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14118^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50239</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
