<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-139906</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Historical Perspective about ISSP from 1968-1985 and the Presidency of Bob Singer (1985-1993)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The functioning of the ISSP Managing Council (MC) during the early years was influenced to some degree by the Cold War. MC members were determined according to their acknowledged expertise and reputation, but also in respect to their country and political representation. Bob Singer was elected to be a member of the MC in 1977 at the congress in Prague. It was the first time that voting at the general assembly meeting was agreed upon for nominating and voting for MC members together with those members designated by the former MC. In 1985 he was elected as the third president of ISSP. A new phase in ISSP started and new goals were established. A more democratic style of communication and interactions among MC members were stimulated, agendas for the MC meetings were well organized, promotion of the ISSP&#146;s mission all over the world was developed, new publications were produced, and new relations with other parts of the world as well as with other organizations were promoted (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pons, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serpa, Sidónio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El funcionamiento del Managing Council (MC) de la ISSP durante sus primeros años se hallaba influenciado por la Guerra Fría. Los miembros del MC se designaban de acuerdo a su reputación y sus conocimientos, pero también según su procedencia y su representación política. Bob Singer fue elegido como miembro del MC en 1977 en el congreso de Praga. Fue la primera vez que se acordó que la votación de la Asamblea General sirviera para nombrar a los miembros del MC, junto con aquellos designados por el anterior MC. En 1985 fue elegido como el tercer residente de la ISSP, iniciándose una nueva fase y se fijaron nuevos objetivos. Se estimuló un estilo más democrático de comunicación e interacción entre los miembros del MC, hubo una mejora organizativa de las agendas de las reuniones del MC, se promocionó la misión de la ISSP alrededor del mundo, se editaron nuevas publicaciones, y se fomentaron nuevas relaciones con otras organizaciones y partes del mundo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;24(2): 361-369, 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-139906</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perspectiva histórica de la ISSP desde 1968 hasta 1985, y presidencia de Bob Singer (1985-1993)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13342^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12022^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201500</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
