<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94299</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Children are sociologists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Recent research has established that young children are quite sensitive to the characteristics of individual informants. They prefer to seek and endorse information from informants with whom they are al-ready familiar or from informants who have proven reliable in the past. We report an elaboration of this line of research in which children&#146;s sensitivity to an informant&#146;s group status is probed. A consistent finding across various procedures is that when preschool children are presented with conflicting claims, one claim made by two or three people and another made by a single person, they agree with the majority. This form of endorsement is especially apparent when members of the majority belong to the same racial group as the child rather than a different racial group. Moreover, this bias toward the majority is extended to individual members of the majority. For example, when children are presented with conflicting claims by two informants, one who previously belonged to the majority and one who did not, they are inclined to endorse the member of the majority. By implication, young children are astute sociologists. They take careful note of the relationships among individuals, particularly relationships of agreement or disagreement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Chen, Eva E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corriveau, Kathleen H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Harris, Paul L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Investigaciones recientes han mostrado que los niños pequeños son muy sensibles a las características de las personas de las que obtienen o reciben información. Prefieren buscar y respaldar la información de los informantes con los que ya están familiarizados o de los que han demostrado ser fiables en el pasado. En este artículo se presenta una serie de trabajos en esta línea de investigación en la que se pone a prueba la sensibilidad de los niños al estatus grupal del informante. A través de distintos procedimientos se ha encontrado, de manera consistente, que cuando los niños de Educación Infantil deben elegir entre dos afirmaciones diferentes, una de ellas propuesta por dos o tres personas, y la otra, por una única persona, los niños están de acuerdo con la mayoría. Este resultado es especialmente evidente cuando los miembros de la mayoría pertenecen al mismo grupo racial que el niño, más que cuando pertenecen a otro grupo racial. Además, este sesgo hacia la mayoría se generaliza a los individuos que la componen. Por ejemplo, cuando los niños se enfrentan a un conflicto entre dos informantes, uno que pertenecía anteriormente a la mayoría y uno que no, se inclinan a seguir al miembro de la mayoría. En consecuencia, se puede decir que los niños son sociólogos astutos que se fijan atentamente en las relaciones entre individuos, especialmente en las relaciones de acuerdo y desacuerdo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;27(3): 625-630, oct.-dic. 2011. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94299</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los niños son sociólogos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d73^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2707^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13304^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2721^s22028</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201110</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
