<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70884</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Organizational commitment is a construct of high interest for psychologists and in general for people involved in human resources. Research has addressed those aspects that conform and maintain it. However, literature reviews show differences in conceptualization and hence in measurement of organizational commitment. This study holds a comprehensive perspective to determine whether the use of most common instruments identifies the dimensions of this construct. Mowday, Steers and Porter&#146;s OCQ Questionnaire (1982) and Meyer, Allen y Smith&#146;s Organizational Commitment Questionnaire (1993) were administered to a sample of 233 workers in two kinds of organizations &#150;one public the other private.52 percent of the subjects were males and 48 percent females. The results show four dimensions:Identification&#150;Implication, Affective Commitment, Continuance Commitment (lack of alternatives) and Normative Commitment. It seemed clear that this construct is mainly an attitude that leads to a sense of attachment and to maintain a consistent behavior to avoid the loss of the benefits provided by the organization. The joint administration of both questionnaires seems to improve the measurement of Organizational Commitment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Betanzos Díaz, Norma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrade Palos, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paz Rodríguez, Francisco </dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El compromiso organizacional es un constructo que presenta gran interés para los psicólogos y aquellos involucrados con el recurso humano. Las investigaciones se han dirigido a determinar aquellos aspectos que lo forman y mantienen, sin embargo hay revisiones teóricas que evidencian que aún hay diferencias en la conceptualización y por tanto en su medición. La presente investigación adoptó una posición integradora ante las diferentes perspectivas de estudio para determinar si la aplicación de los instrumentos más utilizados permite hacer evidente las dimensiones que engloban este constructo. Se aplicó el Cuestionario OCQ de Mowday, Steers y Porter (1982) y el Cuestionario de Compromiso Organizacional de Meyer, Allen y Smith (1993), en una muestra de 233 trabajadores de dos organizaciones: pública y privada, 52% hombres y 48% mujeres. Los resultados muestran cuatro dimensiones: identificación - implicación, compromiso afectivo, compromiso de continuidad (faltade alternativas) y compromiso normativo. Se evidenció que este constructo para la muestra estudiada es principalmente una actitud que le lleva a sentir apego y mantener una conducta consistente para evitar perder los beneficios que la organización le brinda. Ambos cuestionarios aplicados en forma conjunta mejoran la medición del compromiso organizacional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);22(1): 25-43, 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70884</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16629</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16385</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
