<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-1349</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Commentaries on handicap in vestibular diseases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Handicap of the patient with vestibular disease can be measured by means of scales and questionnaires. The utility of a questionnaire developed and validated in Spanish language is commented (CEMPV). The CEMPV consists of 46 questions distributed in three scales (emotional, functional and organic) whose obtained scores are related to diverse degrees of handicap (global, emotional, functional and organic). The CEMPV is self-employed and evaluates the evolution of the patient and allows to accredit the results obtained between different investigators (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sanidad y Ediciones (SANED, S.L.)</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La minusvalía del paciente con enfermedad vestibular puede ser medida mediante escalas y cuestionarios. Se comenta la utilidad de un cuestionario desarrollado y validado en castellano (CEMPV). El CEMPV consta de 46 preguntas distribuidas en tres escalas (emocional, funcional y orgánica) cuyas puntuaciones obtenidas se relacionan con diversos grados de minusvalía (global, emocional, funcional y orgánica). El CEMPV es autoadministrado, evalúa la evolución del paciente y permite homologar los resultados obtenidos entre diferentes investigadores (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;52(2): 169-170, mar. 2001.</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comentarios sobre minusvalía en patología vestibular</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Pardal Refoyo, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-1349</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29638</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24913^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4307^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4307^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
