<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127339</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic splenectomy in hematologic diseases in children.  Analysis of 11-year experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. A common indication for splenectomy in children is hematologic diseases. Indications, clinical course and complications of laparoscopic splenectomy are shown; factors associated with open conversion are analyzed. Methods. Retrospective, longitudinal, descriptive series of laparoscopic splenectomy during 11 years and its long-term follow-up. Results. We studied 88 laparoscopic splenectomies. Average age was 9 years and weight 30 kg. The indication was hemolytic anemia in 77% and thrombocytopenic purpura in 18%. Eleven percent was operated with severe thrombocytopenia and two patients urgently; cholecystectomy was done in 13%. The median surgical time was 180 minutes and bleeding 100 ml. Conversion rate was 5.7% mainly because of persistent bleeding, being risk bleeding greater than 300 ml and the need for red cell concentrate transfusion. The median length of stay was 3 days, longer in those affected by purpura. Three patients developed pneumonia and one, intra-abdominal abscess. Follow-up was 3.6 years average with two late complications. Treatment response was cure in 72%, improvement in 11.3% and failure in 6.8%.Discussion. It is feasible to operate patients under 5 years of age and patients with anemia or thrombocytopenia at the time of surgery without major problems. The conversion rate is low and risk factors for conversion are bleeding more than 300 ml and needing to transfuse erythrocyte concentrate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Dávila-Pérez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bracho-Blanchet, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordorica-Chávez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto-Zermeño, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Portilla, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zalles-Vidal, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Una indicación frecuente de esplenectomía en niños son las enfermedades hematológicas. Se muestran las indicaciones, curso clínico y complicaciones en niños con esplenectomía laparoscópica y se analizan los factores de conversión a cirugía abierta. Material y métodos. Estudio de cohorte, longitudinal, descriptivo de esplenectomía laparoscópica en un periodo de 11 años y su seguimiento a largo plazo. Resultados. Se analizaron 88 esplenectomías laparoscópicas. Edad promedio 9 años y peso 30 kg. La indicación fue anemia hemolítica en el 77% y púrpura trombocitopénica en el 18%. El 11% se operó con trombocitopenia grave y dos pacientes en forma urgente, se hizo colecistectomía en el 13%. La mediana de tiempo quirúrgico fue de 180 minutos con sangrado de 100 ml. Se convirtió el 5,7% por sangrado persistente, siendo los factores de riesgo el sangrado mayor a 300 ml y la necesidad de transfusión de concentrado eritrocitario. La mediana de estancia fue 3 días, superior en los pacientes afectos de púrpura. Tres pacientes desarrollaron neumonía y uno, absceso intra-abdominal. El seguimiento promedio es de 3,6 años con dos complicaciones tardías. Hubo curación con normalización del hemograma y sin necesidad de transfusiones en el 72%, mejoría con necesidad de transfusiones (..) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;27(2): 68-73, abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127339</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Esplenectomía laparoscópica por enfermedades  hematológicas en niños. Análisis de 11 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55043^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14306^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13539^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28630</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12132^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d758^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
