<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-135487</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ergonomic equipment for home mail deliveries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to make a proposal, from a Provincial Medical Service of a national mail company, for the improvement of the ergonomic design of the equipment used by the mail delivery personnel. The proposal is made by request of the staff and is aimed at the State Medical Service to be analysed and transferred to the engineering department so as to be included in the process of equipment updating. It comprehends technical, ergonomic, economic, safety and image aspects. The methodology of the study consisted off an extensive research for information which included a bibliographic compilation, field work, the performance of an epidemiological survey on a sample of delivery personnel and a theoretical bio-mechanical study on the physiological repercussions of the use of different systems of small carts for light transport. The information thus obtained then underwent an analysis by way of brainstorming. The excellent results to this study are: a) the general tendency is to diversify the postmen system of transport; b) the small car propelled by impulsion have higher implantation in the transport activities than the traction propelled. c) the small car propelled by impulsion and the horizontally contain bag adduce weighty advantages dynamics and physiological respect to tractions system and vertical contain bag; d) the elemental requirements to the small car ergonomic of the Spanish postmen are: higher dimension and compartmentation to actual; propelled system by impulsion; contained bag horizontality; and regulation the height to the contained bag and propulsion handle. Thee discussion of the results has allowed to make an equipment proposal which includes five adapted means of transport: motorcycle, bicycle, small carts (three versions), mailbag and knapsack and three types of financial bags, each suitable for different delivery situations. Similarly, it is advisable that the equipment is chosen by the employee and it could be convenient to adapt work regulations accordingly. In addition to being directly useful for the delivery personnel, the study can be used as a model for the development of other studies or ergonomic projects (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estudio tiene como objetivo formular, desde un Servicio Médico Provincial de una empresa de correo de ámbito estatal, una propuesta para mejorar el diseño ergonómico del equipamiento del personal de reparto domiciliario. La propuesta se formula a demanda de los empleados y se dirige al Servicio Médico Estatal, para su análisis y traslado al departamento de ingeniería, a efectos de incorporarla en el proceso de renovación de equipamientos, que contempla, de forma integral, aspectos técnicos, ergonómicos, económicos, de seguridad y de imagen. La metodología de estudio ha consistido en una amplia búsqueda de información bibliográfica, un trabajo de campo, la realización de una encuesta epidemiológica en una muestra de repartidores y un estudio biomecánico teórico, sobre las repercusiones fisiológicas del uso de diferentes sistemas de carros de transporte ligero. La información obtenida se ha sometido a un posterior análisis entre directivos, técnicos y trabajadores. Los resultados más sobresalientes son los siguientes: a) la tendencia general es la de diversar los medios de transporte de los carteros; b) el carro propulsado por sistema de empuje tiene una mayor penetración en las actividades de transporte que el de tracción; c) el carro empujado y la caja horizontal presentan importantes ventajas dinámicas y fisiológicas con respecto a los sistemas de tracción y a las cajas verticales; d) los requerimientos básicos para el carro ergonómico de los carteros españoles son: mayor dimensión y compartimentación que el actual, propulsión por empuje, caja horizontal, y regulación de altura de caja y de asa de propulsión. La discusión de los resultados ha permitido formular una propuesta de equipamiento, que comprende cinco tipos de medios adaptados de transporte: la motocicleta, la bicicleta, el carro (con tres versiones), la cartera valija y la mochila; así como tres tipos de bolsos financieros: la riñonera, la minivalija bandolera y la bolsa adaptada al tórax, adecuados a diferentes situaciones de reparto. Además, se puede recomendar que el equipamiento lo seleccione el propio empleado y que se estudie la conveniencia de adaptar la normativa de trabajo. Finalmente, destacar que el estudio puede servir como modelo de desarrollo de otros estudios o proyectos ergonómicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);3(2): 66-76, abr.-jun. 2000. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-135487</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Equipamiento ergonómico en el reparto domiciliario de correo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4943^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4943^s28898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14578^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29745^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11616^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11616^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11616^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11616^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
