<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-046285</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Combined surgical and endovascular repair of the aortic arch and thoracic aorta</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Thoracic aortic aneurysms and aortic dissections are very serious pathologies that affect an    important number of patients and which are often treated with conservative therapy for fear of the high morbidity and    mortality rate that accompanies their surgical procedures. Endovascular techniques are a less drastic alternative, although    sometimes surgical actions are needed to maintain perfusion in the supra-aortic trunks (SAT). Aim. To present the different    combined (open and endovascular) techniques that are used to treat pathologies of the aortic arch. Development.    Following Balm&#146;s classification, we describe the different possibilities open for extra-anatomical revascularisation of SAT    prior to ligation of their origins and their endovascular occlusion during endovascular treatment of arch pathologies. All    the procedures avoid aortic clamping and the need for a heart-lung bypass machine and some of them even make median    sternotomy unnecessary. Conclusions. The development of endovascular techniques and devices for the thoracic aorta, in    combination with less drastic surgery, can represent an interesting alternative for patients who are not going to benefit    from conventional repairs. Further studies are needed to determine the feasibility of these promising techniques and the    survival rates achieved, since to date our experience is limited to very short series of particular cases, the results of which    are inconsistent</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Garzón-Moll, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera-De Cubas, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Riera-Del Moral, L. F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los aneurismas de la aorta torácica y las disecciones aórticas son patologías muy graves que    afectan a una población importante y que con frecuencia se tratan de forma conservadora por miedo a la morbimortalidad    que acompaña a sus procedimientos quirúrgicos. Las técnicas endovasculares son una alternativa menos radical,    aunque en ocasiones necesita de gestos quirúrgicos para mantener la perfusión de los troncos supraaórticos (TSA). Objetivo.    Presentar las distintas técnicas combinadas abierta y endovascular que se utilizan en la patología del arco aórtico.    Desarrollo. Siguiendo la clasificación de Balm, se exponen las distintas posibilidades de revascularización extraanatómica    de los TSA previa a la ligadura de sus orígenes y la oclusión endovascular de éstos durante el tratamiento endovascular    de la patología del arco. Todos los procedimientos evitan el pinzamiento aórtico y la bomba de circulación extracorpórea,    y algunos de ellos incluso la estereotomía media. Conclusiones. El desarrollo de las técnicas y los dispositivos endovasculares    para la aorta torácica, en combinación con cirugías menos radicales puede ser una alternativa interesante    para aquellos pacientes no subsidiarios de reparaciones convencionales. Serán necesarios más estudios para comprobar    la viabilidad de estas técnicas emergentes y la supervivencia que consiguen, ya que hasta la fecha la experiencia se reduce    a series muy cortas de casos seleccionados cuyos resultados son dispares</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;58(supl.1): S149-S158, 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-046285</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reparación combinada quirúrgica y endovascular del arco aórtico y la aorta torácica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4271^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1018^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30828^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1018^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1019^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30828^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1018^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30828^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30828^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1018^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
