<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161488</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High-sensitivity troponin T assay in asymptomatic high cardiovascular risk patients. The TUSARC Registry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: High-sensitivity troponin T assays (Hs-TnT) have been carried out in selected populations in clinical trials and in registries of the general population with low cardiovascular risk (CVR). The aim of this study was to determine the proportion of individuals with detectable Hs-TnT and the proportion of individuals with elevated Hs-TnT in a Spanish population of asymptomatic individuals with very high CVR, as well as the parameters associated with Hs-TnT elevation. Methods: The study included 690 patients. Hs-TnT detection and Hs-TnT elevation (&amp;#8805;99th percentile value), as well the association of elevated Hs-TnT and clinical, analytical, and treatment data were analyzed. Results: Hs-TnT was analyzed in 646 patients and was detected in 645. Elevated TnT was detected in 212 patients (32.9%). On multivariate analysis, elevated TnT was independently associated with male sex (OR, 2.81; 95%CI, 1.67-4.73; P &lt; .001), older age (OR, 1.06; 95%CI, 1.04-1.09; P &lt; .001), a higher body mass index (OR, 1.07; 95%CI, 1.02-1.12; P &lt; .002), insulin therapy (OR, 1.99; 95%CI, 1.15-3.46; P = .01), history of heart failure (OR, 3.92; 95%CI, 1.24-12.39; P = .02), and estimated glomerular filtration rate calculated by CKD-EPI (OR, 0.96; 95%CI, 0.95-0.97; P &lt; .001). Conclusions: In a Spanish population of asymptomatic individuals at very high CVR, Hs-TnT was associated with older age, male sex, higher body mass index, insulin therapy, history of heart failure, and lower glomerular filtration rate (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villamandos, Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, María Gracia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Héctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Raymondi, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palazuelos Molinero, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: La troponina T ultrasensible (TnT-us) se ha cuantificado en poblaciones de ensayos clínicos y en registros poblacionales de bajo riesgo cardiovascular (RCV). El objetivo del estudio es determinar en qué proporción de la población española asintomática de muy alto RCV se puede cuantificar la TnT-us, qué proporción presenta TnT-us elevada y qué variables se asocian con la presencia de TnT-us elevada. Métodos: Se incluyó a 690 pacientes. Se analizó la detección de la TnT-us y de la TnT-us elevada (&amp;#8805; percentil 99 de referencia) y su asociación con las diferentes variables recogidas. Resultados: Se analizó la TnT-us en 646 pacientes y se detectó en 645. Presentaron TnT-us elevada 212 pacientes (32,9%). En el análisis multivariable, la TnT-us elevada se asoció al sexo masculino (OR = 2,81; IC95%, 1,67-4,73; p &lt; 0,001), mayor edad (OR = 1,06; IC95%, 1,04-1,09; p &lt; 0,001) mayor índice de masa corporal (OR = 1,07; IC95%, 1,02-1,12; p &lt; 0,002), tratamiento con insulina (OR = 1,99; IC95%, 1,15-3,46; p = 0,01), insuficiencia cardiaca previa (OR = 3,92; IC95%, 1,24-12,39; p = 0,02) y filtrado glomerular estimado calculado por la fórmula CKD-EPI (OR = 0,96; IC95%, 0,95-0,97; p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: En una población española asintomática de muy alto RCV, la TnT-us se detectó prácticamente en todos los pacientes, y estaba elevada en un tercio de ellos. La TnT-us elevada se asoció a mayor edad, el sexo masculino, el índice de masa corporal, la insuficiencia cardiaca previa, el tratamiento con insulina y un menor filtrado glomerular (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;70(4): 261-266, abr. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161488</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Troponina T ultrasensible en pacientes asintomáticos de muy alto riesgo cardiovascular. Registro TUSARC</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54008</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33838^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d78^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30693^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
