<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77221</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sex differences in body image, weight control and Body Mass Index of Spanish adolescents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This research paper studied the differences among 21,811 adolescents (between the ages of 11 and 18) in key variables in the development of eating disorders, including the Body Mass Index, the perception of and satisfaction with their body image, and the behaviours used to control weight. In spite of the fact that the girls had a better adjusted BMI and a lesser degree of overweight and obesity, we found that they perceived themselves as being fatter, were less satisfied with body image, and the ones who dieted the most to lose weight. On the other hand, we found that the main reason for boys and girls to diet in an effort to lose weight was not their real body weight, but rather their perception of their own bodies, followed by just how satisfied they were with their bodies. Therefore, important differences are revealed between boys and girls in this article, which must be taken into consideration in the design and development of the various programs that are aimed at the prevention of problems with body image and diet behaviour (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rivera de los Santos, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Rodríguez, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Valverde, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio examinó las diferencias entre 21.811 chicos y chicas adolescentes (11-18 años) en variables clave en el desarrollo de trastornos de la alimentación, como son el Índice de Masa Corporal, la percepción y satisfacción con la imagen corporal y las conductas destinadas a controlar el peso. A pesar de que las chicas tenían una puntuación en el Índice de Masa Corporal más ajustada y presentaban un nivel menor de sobrepeso y obesidad, se encontró que eran ellas las que se percibían más obesas, las que estaban más insatisfechas con su imagen corporal y las que realizaban con más frecuencia dietas para adelgazar. Por otra parte, se encontró que la razón que mueve a chicos y chicas a realizar dietas para adelgazar no es el peso corporal real, sino la percepción que tienen de su cuerpo, en primer lugar, y cómo de satisfechos están con él, en segundo lugar. Por lo tanto, en este artículo se encuentran importantes diferencias entre chicos y chicas, a tener en cuenta en el diseño y desarrollo de los diversos programas que se destinen a la prevención de problemas con la imagen corporal y la conducta de hacer dieta (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);22(1): 77-83, 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77221</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias de sexo en imagen corporal, control de peso e Índice de Masa Corporal de los adolescentes españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10740</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24382^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
