<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74893</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-7937</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emotional intelligence as predictor of academic achievement in university student</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present work hs as its main objective the analysis of the specific contribution of emotionl intelligence to the prediction of academic achievement. The participants were 250 universiy students of technical and humanistic studies. Two test of emotional intelligence were used, the TMMS-24, and the Scutte et al (1998) test, along with the g factor test of Cattell y Cattell, and different global academic results showed that practically null correlations were obseved between the intellectual quotient and the different factors of emotinal intellience evaluated in this stdy. In addiction, the hiearchic regression technique showed significant relations of emotional intelligence measures and some indictors of academic performance, even when the effect of the IQ was controlled. Thses results indicate the independent contribution of emotional intelligente to the explanation or prediciton of academic achievement, herarchic regression(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez Pérez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castejón Costa, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este trabajo tiene como objetivo principal el análisi de la contribución específica de la inteligencia emocional a la predicción del rendimiento académico. Los participantes fueron 250 estudantes universitarios de estudios técnicos y humanísticos. Se emplearon dos pruebas de inteligencia emocional, el TMMS-24 y la prueba de Schutte et al. (1998), junto con el test de factor g de Cattell, y diferentes indicadores globnales de rendimiento académico. Los resultados mostraron la existnecia de correlaciones prácticamente nulas enre le cociente intelectual y los diferentes factores de la inteligenica emocional evaluados en este estudio. Además el análisis de regresión jerárquica ostró relaciones signficativas d elas medidas de inteligencia emocional conalgunos indicadores de rendimiento académico, incluso cuando se controló el efecto del CI. Estos resultados indican la contribución independiente de la inteligenci emocional a la predicción y /o explicación del rendimietno académcio en estudiantes universitarios(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Ansiedad estrés;12(2/3): 393-400, dic. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74893</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La inteligencia emocional como predictor del rendimeinto académico en estudiantes univesitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7528^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7529^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
