<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85200</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostics value of NT-proBNP after heart transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Cardiac transplantation is a widely accepted option for the treatment of end-stage congestive heart failure. In order to identify those patients at risk of short life expectancy, it could be worthwhile to establish an individual prognosis factor. The prognostic and diagnostic values of natriuretic peptides have been studied in different areas of clinical practice. The objective of this study was to evaluate the short-term prognostic ability of NT-proBNP concentration in heart transplantation patients. Materials and methods. The group studied consisted of 50 adult heart transplant patients. NT-proBNP concentration was measured in each patient 15 days after surgery to evaluate the prognostic value at 6 months follow up. Results. The non-survivor patients showed higher NT-proBNP concentrations than survivors, with a median of NT-proBNP concentration on the 15th day post-transplantation of 20632ng/L (IIC: 6183 to 37925ng/L) and 3923ng/L (IIC: 1752 to 6890ng/L) in the non-survivors and the survivors groups, respectively. The hazard ratio of mortality was 8.5 times higher (95% CI: 1.7 to 44.2) in those patients with NT-proBNP concentrations over 7500ng/L on the 15th day post-transplantation (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Prieto García, Belén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Menéndez, Francisco V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Molina, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Avello Llano, Noelia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trasplante cardíaco es una opción terapéutica disponible para algunos pacientes con insuficiencia cardíaca avanzada. Es importante establecer el pronóstico que presentan estos pacientes para poder diferenciar aquéllos con peor expectativa de vida y adoptar medidas adicionales en estos casos. Los péptidos natriuréticos cardíacos han demostrado su utilidad diagnóstica y pronóstica en diferentes enfermedades. El objetivo de este estudio es valorar la utilidad del extremo aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético tipo B (NT-proBNP) postoperatorio en el pronóstico de los pacientes trasplantados cardíacos a corto plazo. Materiales y métodos. determinó la concentración de NT-proBNP a los 15 días postoperatorios en 50 pacientes que recibieron trasplante cardíaco para valorar la utilidad pronóstica de mortalidad a 6 meses de seguimiento. Resultados. Los pacientes que fallecieron mostraron concentraciones de NT-proBNP significativamente superiores que los que sobrevivieron, con una mediana de la concentración de NT-proBNP a los 15 días postrasplante de 20.632ng/l (intervalo interculartílico: 6.183 a 37.925ng/l) frente a 3.923ng/l (intervalo interculartílico: 1.752 a 6.890ng/l) respectivamente. Se observó que el hazard-ratio de mortalidad se multiplica por 8,5 veces (IC del 95%: 1,7&#150;44,2) en el grupo de pacientes con concentraciones de NT-proBNP, cuantificadas a los 15 días postrasplante, superiores al valor discriminatorio de 7.500ng/l (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;3(2): 52-57, abr.-jun. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85200</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico postoperatorio del extremo aminoterminal del propéptido natriurético tipo B en el trasplante cardíaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30431^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52438</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11623</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30431^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33835^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22512^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30572^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
