<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148880</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Interleukins network in rheumatoid arthritis pathophysiology: beyond proinflammatory cytokines</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is a systemic autoimmune disease characterized by synovitis and progressive destruction of the joint cartilage and underlying bone, together with diverse extra-articular manifestations. Cytokines act as soluble effector mediators of the inflammatory process. Therapeutic neutralization with monoclonal antibodies against the pro-inflammatory cytokines TNF-alpha and interleukin 1 (IL-1) has shown a clear efficacy on inflammation and clinical manifestations of RA, although a percentage of patients do not respond. This review covers new relevant cytokines in the RA physiopathology and potential biomarkers of inflammation. The current challenge is to develop biomarkers that enable an earlier diagnosis, as well as prognostic markers and new therapeutic candidates. Combined administration of several of these cytokines could eventually address a personalized treatment approach for each patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Longo, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ramón, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carreño, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La artritis reumatoide (AR) es una enfermedad autoinmunitaria sistémica caracterizada por sinovitis y destrucción progresiva del cartílago articular y hueso subyacente, junto con diversas manifestaciones extraarticulares. Las citocinas actúan como mediadores solubles responsables del proceso inflamatorio. El bloqueo terapéutico mediante anticuerpos monoclonales de las citocinas proinflamatorias factor de necrosis tumoral-alfa y la interleucina 1ha demostrado una clara eficacia sobre la inflamación y las manifestaciones clínicas de la AR, si bien no son eficaces en todos los pacientes. Se presenta una revisión de nuevas citocinas relevantes en la fisiopatología de la AR que representan potenciales biomarcadores inflamatorios de la AR. El reto actual consiste en desarrollar biomarcadores que permitan un diagnóstico más precoz, marcadores pronósticos y nuevos candidatos terapéuticos. La administración combinada de varias de ellas podría permitir una aproximación personalizada de estas terapias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);6(supl.3): 20-24, mar. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148880</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Interleucinas en la fisiopatología de la artritis reumatoide: más allá de las citocinas proinflamatorias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52657^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29460^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31092^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1178^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d920^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13966^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32175^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29487^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
