<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111152</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Priority issues, study designs and geographical distribution in nutrition journals</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The increased number of articles published in nutrition is a reflection of the relevance to scientific community. The characteristics and quality of nutritional studies determine whether readers can obtain valid conclusions from them, as well as their usefulness for evidence-based strategic policies. Objective: To determine the characteristics of papers published in nutrition journals. Method: Descriptive study design. We reviewed 330 original papers published between January-June 2007. From: American Journal of Clinical Nutrition (AJCN), Journal of Nutrition, European Journal Nutrition, European Journal of Clinical Nutrition and Public Health Nutrition. We classified them according to the subjects studied; risk factors, study design and country of origin. Results: Almost half the papers studied healthy people(53.3%). The most frequent illness was obesity (13.9%).Food consumption is the most frequent risk factor (63.3%).Social factors appear exclusively only in 3.6% of the papers. Clinical trials were the most common analytical design (31.8%), mainly in the AJCN (45.6%). Cross-sectional studies were the most frequent type of observational design (37.9%). Ten countries produced over half of the papers (51.3%). The US publishes the highest number of papers (20.6%), whilst developing countries make only scarce contributions to scientific literature on nutrition. Conclusions: Most of the papers had inferential power. They generally studied both healthy and sick subjects, coinciding with the aims of international scientific policies. However, the topics covered reflect a clear bias, prioritizing problems pertaining to developed countries. Social determinants of health should also be considered, along with behavioral and biological risk factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Cantero, MT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Moncada, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Clemente-Gómez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Zapata, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El crecimiento de la producción científica nutricional indica relevancia para la comunidad científica. Las características y calidad de los estudios determinan si sus lectores pueden obtener conclusiones válidas, y su utilidad en la orientación de estrategias políticas basadas en la evidencia. Objetivo: Determinar las características de las publicaciones en revistas de nutrición. Método: Estudio descriptivo. Se revisaron 330 artículos originales publicados entre enero-junio de 2007 en las revistas: American-Journal of Clinical-Nutrition (AJCN), Journalof Nutrition, European-Journal Nutrition, European-Journal of Clinical-Nutrition y Public-Health-Nutrition. Los artículos se clasificaron según los temas estudiados, factores de riesgo, diseño del estudio y país de origen. Resultados: Las personas saludables representan la mitad (53,3%) de la población estudiada. La obesidad fue la enfermedad más frecuente (13,9%). El consumo de alimentos fue el factor de riesgo más frecuente (63,3%). Un 3,6% de artículos consideraron factores sociales. Los ensayos-clínicos fueron los estudios analíticos más comunes(31,8%), principalmente en AJCN (45,6%). Los estudios-transversales más frecuentes fueron observacionales(37,9%). Diez países producen más de la mitad de los artículos(51,3%). Los EEUU publican el mayor número de artículos (20,6%); siendo escasa la contribución de los países en desarrollo. Conclusiones: La mayoría de los artículos presentan poder inferencial. La población estudiada se distribuye entre sana y enferma, coincidiendo con los objetivos de las políticas científicas internacionales. Sin embargo, los temas tratados reflejan un sesgo, dando prioridad a los problemas relativos a países desarrollados. Deberían considerarse determinantes sociales de la salud, junto con factores de riesgo de comportamiento y biológicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;26(4): 784-791, jul.-ago. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111152</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Temas prioritarios, diseño de estudios y distribución geográfica de artículos publicados en revistas de nutrición</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52458^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24517</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
