<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75025</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">In vitro antifungal activity of anidulafungin</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anidulafungin is a new and very useful pharmacological tool for the treatmentof invasive mycoses. The antifungal spectrum of anidulafungin reaches themost common pathogenic fungi. Anidulafungin is especially active against thegenera Candida and Aspergillus. Its antifungal mechanism is based on theinhibition of the ß-1,3-D-glucan synthesis, an essential molecule for the cellwall architecture, with different consequences for Candida and Aspergillus,being anidulafungin fungicide for the former and fungistatic for the latter.This review describes the in vitro antifungal spectrum of anidulafungin basedin the scientific and medical literature of recent years. We can underline thatmost than 99% of Candida isolates are susceptible to &lt;= 2 &amp;#956;g/ml ofanidulafungin. MIC are very low (&lt;= 0.125 &amp;#956;g/ml) for most clinical isolates ofthe species Candida albicans, Candida glabrata, Candida tropicalis andCandida krusei while Candida parapsilosis and Candida guilliermondii isolatesare susceptible to anidulafungin concentrations &lt;= 2 &amp;#956;g/ml. An excellentactivity of anidulafungin has been also described against Aspergillus,Pneumocystis and other fungi. However, its activity is very low againstCryptococcus and the Zygomycetes. The excellent activity of anidulafunginhas made this antifungal a first line therapeutic indication for candidemia andinvasive candidiasis in non-neutropenic patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Eraso, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quindós, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anidulafungina es una nueva y eficaz aportación farmacológica para eltratamiento de las micosis invasoras. La anidulafungina tiene un espectroantifúngico que engloba a los hongos patógenos más comunes yespecialmente a los géneros Candida y Aspergillus. Su mecanismo de acciónse basa en la inhibición de la síntesis de ß-1,3-D-glucano, molécula esencialpara la pared fúngica. Este mecanismo tiene como consecuencia dos tipos deacciones: una acción fungicida contra Candida y una acción fungistáticacontra Aspergillus y otros hongos filamentosos. En esta revisión se describe elespectro antifúngico in vitro de anidulafungina tomando como base los datospublicados en los últimos años. Destaca que más del 99% de los aislamientosde Candida son sensibles a concentraciones menores o iguales de 2 &amp;#956;g/ml deanidulafungina. Dentro de esta sensibilidad in vitro a la anidulafungina, las CMIobservadas son más bajas para Candida albicans, Candida glabrata,Candida tropicalis y Candida krusei mientras que Candida parapsilosis yCandida guilliermondii son sensibles a concentraciones menores o iguales de2 &amp;#956;g/ml. También se ha descrito una actividad excelente frente a Aspergillus,Pneumocystis y otros hongos. Sin embargo, su actividad es prácticamentenula contra Cryptococcus y los zigomicetos. Esta excelente actividadantifúngica hace que la anidulafungina sea una indicación terapéutica deprimera línea para el tratamiento de las candidemias y candidiasis invasorasen pacientes sin neutropenia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;25(2): 83-91, 2008. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75025</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actividad antifúngica in vitro de la anidulafungina</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3471^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52786^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2207^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d943^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5794^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1237^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15401^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
