<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66880</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We want to know the influence of gender factor in the consumption characteristics, social support and evolution in treatment with naltrexone in an opiate addict group. Material and methods. 1.432 patients (83.1% males and 16.9% females) recruited over a 12 year period who successively initiated treatment period years with naltrexone. Retrospective observance study, with design of treatment group without control group. We evaluated the role of gender in retention with the Mantel-Cox test. The differences were analyzed according to the gender with contingency tables. Results. One year retention for all of them was 29.75%, this being 30.92% for men and 23.97% for women. This difference is significant at one year according to the Mantel-Cox test (statistics: 8.38%; gl: 1; signification: 0.0038). Women show less frequency of cocaine use (p=0.011) and less use of intravenous cocaine (p=0.048), lower frequency of consumption of alcohol (p=0.000)and cannabis (p=0.002), a shorter period of heroine abuse(p=0.016) and a higher proportion of them only use heroine (p=0.015). They have less economic independence (p=0.001), their partner is more frequently an addict (p=0.000), they have less help for the treatment from anon-consuming partner (p=0.000).Conclusions. There are outstanding differences with regard to consume characteristics, social support and evolution of the treatment according to the gender (either male or female). Men have better prognosis than women in the population studied. These differences seem to be due to the socio cultural contents of the gender concept (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Madoz-Gúrpide, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ochoa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se quiere conocer la influencia del factor género en las características de consumo, apoyo social y evolución en el tratamiento con naltrexona de un grupo de dependientes de opiáceos. Material y métodos. Mil cuatrocientos treinta y dos pacientes (83,1% hombres y 16,9% mujeres) que sucesivamente y durante 12 años inician tratamiento con naltrexona en la unidad de toxicomanías. Estudio observacional retrospectivo con diseño de grupo de tratamiento sin grupo control. Evaluamos el papel del género en la retención con la prueba de Mantel-Cox. Con tablas de contingencia se analizan las diferencias en función del género. Resultados. La retención al año de iniciarse el tratamiento para el total es del 29,75%, siendo del 30,92% para hombres y del 23,97% para mujeres. Esta diferencia al año es significativa según la prueba de Mantel-Cox (estadístico: 8,38; gl: 1; significación: 0,0038). Las mujeres presentan menor frecuencia de consumo (p=0,011) y uso de la vía intravenosa para cocaína (p=0,048), menor frecuencia de consumo de alcohol (p=0,000) y de cannabis (p=0,002), menor tiempo de consumo de heroína (p=0,016) y mayor proporción consumen sólo heroína (p=0,015). Tienen menor independencia económica (p=0,001), cuentan con mayor frecuencia con pareja consumidora (p=0,000), contando con menor apoyo para el tratamiento de una pareja no consumidora (p=0,000).Conclusiones. Existen diferencias relevantes respecto a las características del consumo, apoyo social y evolución del tratamiento según el género (sea hombre o mujer). Los hombres tienen mejor pronóstico que las mujeres en la población estudiada. Dichas diferencias parecen deberse al contenido sociocultural del concepto género (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;36(4): 197-204, jul.-ago. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66880</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5924</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6715^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9463^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13195</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
