<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110139</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Currarino triad: Different forms of presentation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. We describe our experience in Currarino syndrome (CS) and our clinical findings. methods. Case 1: Newborn female with prenatal diagnosis of myelomeningocele which was confirmed at birth as a lipomyelomeningocele, associated with partial sacral agenesis, horseshoe kidney and complex anorectal malformation with colonic vascular anomaly. Case 2: A 14-month-old male with constipation. The physical examination detected an anal stricture and radiological findings of a presacral lipomeningocele plus teratoma and a partial sacral agenesis. Case 3:An 8-month-old male with recurrent meningitis associated with anterior sacral meningocele and rectal fistula. An anal stricture and hemisacrum were also demonstrated. Results. In case 1, an abdomino-perineal pull-through was performed but it failed because of her colonic vascular anomaly. Nowadays she is 3 years old and has a cecostomy, controls her micturition and is able to walk. Case 2 is two years old with satisfactory flow-up-after the teratoma and meningocele removal plus anal dilation. In case 3 a colostomy was necessary because after mass excision a recto-cutaneous fistula appeared during postoperative period. A ventriculoperitoneal valve implantation due to his hydrocephaly was also performed. Conclusions. The constipation is the most common symptom in the CS. Recurrent meningitis has a high mortality rate (56%) due to rectomeningeal fistula. The most common anorectal malformation is the anal stricture, and the more complex the malformation is, higher will the risk of incontinence be. The success of the management and follow-up is a multidisciplinary responsability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calleja Aguayo, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Elías Pollina, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martínez-Pardo, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bragagnini Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estors Sastre, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fustero de Miguel, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Presentar nuestra experiencia en casos diagnosticados de síndrome de Currarino y sus diferentes formas de presentación. material y métodos. Caso 1: neoanata con diagnóstico prenatal por RM de mielomeningocele confirmado al nacimiento como lipomielomeningocele asociado a atresia ano-rectal alta con vascularización anómala del colon, agenesia parcial sacra y riñón en herradura. Caso 2: varón de 14 meses con clínica de estreñimiento y diagnóstico de estenosis anal, lipomeningocele presacro más teratoma y agenesia parcial sacra. Caso 3: varón de 8 meses con clínica de meningitis de repetición y diagnosticado de estenosis anal, meningocele anterior con fístula rectal y agenesia parcial sacra. Resultados. El caso 1 tras un descenso abdomino-perineal fallido por vascularización anómala es portadora actual de cecostomía y a los 3 años de vida presenta un buen control urinario y de la deambulación. El caso 2, con dos años de vida, evoluciona favorablemente con hábito intestinal normal tras extirpación del teratoma y meningocele más dilatación anal. El caso 3 precisó una colostomía tras extirpación del meningocele con fístula rectal por fístula recto-cutánea en el postoperatorio inmediato y derivación ventriculoperitoneal por hidrocefalia postmeningitis. Conclusiones. Según la bibliografía, la forma de presentación del síndrome de Currarino (SC) puede ser muy variada, siendo lo más frecuente el estreñimiento. La presentación más compleja y con alto índice de mortalidad (56%) es la meningitis de repetición debido a fístulas recto-meníngeas. La malformación ano-rectal más frecuente es la estenosis anal y malformaciones más complejas tienen un alto índice de incontinencia. Es un síndrome que precisa de manejo y seguimiento multidisciplinar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;25(3): 155-158, jul.-sept. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Triada de Currarino: sus diferentes formas de presentación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29458^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4105^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1010^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7572^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
