<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163019</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychiatric comorbidity and plasma levels of 2-acyl-glycerols in outpatient treatment alcohol users. Analysis of gender differences</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alcohol addiction is associated with high psychiatric comorbidity. Objective stratification of patients is necessary to optimize care and improve prognosis. The present study is designed to gain insights into this challenge by addressing the following objectives: a) to estimate the prevalence of psychiatric comorbidities in a sample of outpatients seeking treatment for alcohol use disorder, b) to describe the existence of gender differences and c) to validate 2-acyl-glycerols as biomarkers of alcohol use disorder and/or psychiatric comorbidity. One hundred and sixty-two patients were recruited and evaluated with the semistructured interview PRISM. The presence of psychopathology was associated with a greater number of criteria for alcohol abuse and dependence according to DSM-IV-TR. We found gender differences in psychiatric comorbidity, e.g., mood disorder, as well as in comorbid substance use disorders. The prevalence of lifetime psychiatric comorbidity was 68.5%, with mood disorders the most frequent (37%), followed by attention deficit disorder (24.7%) and anxiety disorders (17.9%). Substance-induced disorders were more frequent in mood and psychotic disorders, whereas the primary disorders were more prevalent in patients with comorbid anxiety disorders. We found that 2-acyl-glycerols were significantly decreased in comorbid anxiety disorders in alcohol dependent patients in the last year, which makes them a potential biomarker for this psychopathological condition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Torrens, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero-Sanchiz, Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Marchena, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponce, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pedraz, Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torre, Rafael de la</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araos, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavón, Francisco Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez de Fonseca, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubio, Gabriel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La adicción al alcohol se asocia con una elevada comorbilidad psiquiátrica que complica el tratamiento, siendo necesaria una fenotipación clínica objetiva de estos pacientes para optimizar la atención y mejorar el pronóstico. El presente estudio aborda este problema mediante los siguientes objetivos: a) estimar la prevalencia y tipos de comorbilidad psiquiátrica de una muestra de pacientes que buscan tratamiento por uso de alcohol, b) describir las diferencias de género en su presentación y c) analizar los valores plasmáticos de 2-acilgliceroles (incluyendo el endocannabinoide 2-araquidonilglicerol), estudiando su posible valor como biomarcador de alcoholismo y/o comorbilidad psiquiátrica. Para ello se reclutaron 162 pacientes evaluados con la entrevista semiestructurada PRISM, para evaluar la presencia de comorbilidad y su carácter primario o inducido. Los resultados obtenidos indican que la presencia de psicopatología se asoció a un mayor número de criterios de abuso y dependencia de alcohol Se encontraron diferencias de género tanto en la comorbilidad psiquiátrica, especialmente en trastornos del estado de ánimo. La prevalencia de comorbilidad psiquiátrica encontrada a lo largo de la vida fue del 68,5%, destacando los trastornos del estado ánimo (37%), y seguidos por el trastorno por déficit de atención (24,7%, monitorizado específicamente por la entrevista WURS) y los trastornos de ansiedad (17,9%). Entre los trastornos del estado de ánimo y psicóticos fueron más frecuentes los inducidos, mientras que en los trastornos de ansiedad los primarios fueron más prevalentes. Además, se encontraron concentraciones disminuidas significativamente de 2-acilgliceroles en pacientes con trastornos de ansiedad comórbidos diagnosticados en el último año (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);29(2): 83-96, 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163019</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Comorbilidad psiquiátrica y valores plasmáticos de 2-acilgliceroles en consumidores de alcohol en tratamiento ambulatorio. Análisis de las diferencias de género</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d34378^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38329^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31511</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d555^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d225^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
