<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051231</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9512</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment with atypical antipsychotics of Gilles de la Tourette syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The optimal treatment of Gilles de la Tourette syndrome (GTS) involves educational and supportive interventions, psychological approaches and pharmacological treatment. Pharmacotherapy, especially with antipsychotic drugs, has been the most effective treatment modality in suppressing severe tics. Current treatment with atypical antipsychotics (risperidone, olanzapine) of children and adolescents with GTS appears to be as effective as traditional antipsychotics, while having fewer side effects. Comorbid conditions as attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD), and learning disorders, can be a source of more distress and impairment than the tics themselves. Drug treatment of OCD includes selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) as sertraline. Objective: The purpose of this study was to assess the efficacy and safety of atypical antipsychotics in the treatment of GTS in children and adolescents. Method: This case study inc1uded four subjects (all boys) with a mean age of 11.00 +- 0.50 years. All subjects met Intemational Classification of Diseases (ICD-l0) criteria for GTS. Three children also had a comorbid OCD. Results: Clinical response, as measured by the Clinical Global Impression (CGI) scale showed improvement and reduction in the severity of motor and phonic tics. The most common side effect was weight gain. Conc1usions: These findings suggest that atypical antipsychotics appear to be effective and safe in diminishing motor and phonic tics frequency and intensity in children and adolescents with GTS</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcaina-Prosper, T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Casares, J. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Añó- Torres, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Penalba, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Rey, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento óptimo del síndrome de Gilles de la Tourette (SGT) incluye intervenciones educativas, de apoyo, psicológicas y tratamiento farmacológico. El tratamiento farmacológico, en especial con fármacos antipsicóticos, es la modalidad de tratamiento más efectiva para suprimir tics graves, El tratamiento actual con antipsicóticos atípicos (risperidona, olanzapina) de niños y adolescentes con SGT parece ser tan efectivo como con los antipsicóticos clásicos, aunque con menos efectos secundarios. Trastornos comórbidos como trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad, trastorno obsesivo-compulsivo (TOC) y trastornos del aprendizaje, pueden ser fuente de mayor malestar y deterioro que los propios tics. El tratamiento farmacológico del TOC incluye inhibidores selectivos de la recaptación de serotonina (ISRS) como sertralina. Objetivo: La finalidad de este estudio fue evaluar la eficacia y seguridad de los antipsicóticos atípicos en el tratamiento del SGT en niños y adolescentes, Método: Este estudio de casos incluía cuatro sujetos (todos varones) con una edad media de 11.00+-0.50 años. Todos los sujetos cumplían criterios de la Clasificación Internacional de las Enfermedades (CIE-lO) para SGT. Tres niños presentaban también un TOC comórbido. Resultados: La respuesta clínica cuantificada según la escala Impresión Clínica Global (ICG) indicaba mejoría y disminución en la gravedad de los tics motores y fónicos. El efecto secundario más frecuente fue el aumento de peso. Conclusiones: Estos hallazgos sugieren que los antipsicóticos atípicos parecen ser efectivos y seguros para reducir la frecuencia e intensidad de los tics motores y fónicos en niños y adolescentes con SGT</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. infanto-juv;22(1): 27-33, ene.-mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051231</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento con antipsicóticos atípicos del síndrome de Gilles de la Tourette</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32618^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33791^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24387^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
