<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88874</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The opinion of psychiatric residents on the training they receive</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The results of a survey carried out by the Spanish National Board for Psychiatric Training among psychiatric trainees in their third and fourth year of training are presented and discussed. The aim of the survey was to know the resident&#146;s opinion and level of satisfaction on the training they had received. The results indicate that the majority of residents had complied with the National Program for Psychiatric Training requirements and that their level of satisfaction was fair. However a small but substantial percentage did not comply adequately with the program, particularly in relation with the training in psychotherapy, research methodology, old age psychiatry, neurology and general medicine. Based on these results the National Board puts forward some recommendations meant for those involved in the training of psychiatrists in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez-Beneyto, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castro-Manglano, Pilar de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peralta-Martín, Victor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Gallego, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montilla-García, José F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gay-Pamos, Euxodia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Torres, Miguel A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kuhalainen-Munar, Alejandro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Ibor, Juan J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutierrez-Fraile, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo-Ruiloba, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se presentan y comentan los resultados de una encuesta llevada a cabo por la Comisión Nacional de Psiquiatría entre los MIR de psiquiatría de tercer y cuarto año. La encuesta tuvo por objeto conocer la opinión de los residentes sobre la formación que recibieron, así como el grado de satisfacción que experimentaron. Los resultados indican que la mayoría cumplieron con los requisitos del Programa Nacional de Formación Psiquiátrica y que su grado de satisfacción fue bueno. No obstante un porcentaje pequeño pero sustancial de residentes no cumplieron el programa de forma adecuada, particularmente en relación con la formación en psicoterapia, metodología de la investigación, gerontopsiquiatría, neurología y medicina general. Basándose en estos resultados la Comisión Nacional expone su opinión y presenta unas recomendaciones dirigidas a las partes interesadas en la formación de los residentes de psiquiatría en España (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;39(3): 174-179, mayo-jun. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88874</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La opinión de los residentes de psiquiatría sobre la formación que reciben</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13308</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4571^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9654^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35120</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12007^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12527^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12075</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
