<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85436</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perinatal mortality assessment in native and immigrant women: influence of exhaustiveness and quality of the registries</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ObjectiveTo analyze the exhaustiveness and reliability of the data on perinatal mortality in two Spanish registries, namely, the National Statistics Institute and the Perinatal Mortality Registry of the Valencian Community and to calculate and compare the perinatal mortality rate (PMR) and its components in native and immigrant women, based on the cases reported to both registries in 2005 and 2006.ResultsFetal and neonatal deaths were substantially underreported in the National Statistics Institute compared with the Perinatal Mortality Registry of the Valencian Community. Moreover, in the National Statistics Institute, some neonatal deaths among the offspring of immigrant women were misclassified as being of Spanish nationality. These two factors distorted the proportion of fetal and neonatal deaths in immigrant women, giving rise to an underestimation of the PMR and its components, since the rates obtained from the Perinatal Mortality Registry of the Valencian Community were higher in immigrant than in Spanish women, particularly among east-European and sub-Saharan women.ConclusionsOur results indicate that both registries are complementary. However, the Perinatal Mortality Registry of the Valencian Community was found to be more exhaustive and to have greater reliability. Our results also suggest the importance of monitoring trends in PMR in the immigrant population in Spain(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Río Sánchez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez, Sol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zurriaga Llorens, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Maside, Aurora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rebagliato Ruso,  Marisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Senchermes,  Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bosch Sánchez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolúmar Montrull, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castelló Pastor, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">ObjetivoRealizar un análisis comparativo de la exhaustividad de los datos sobre mortalidad perinatal en la Comunitat Valenciana recogidos en el Instituto Nacional de Estadística (INE) y en el Registro de Mortalidad Perinatal (RMPCV). Posteriormente, calcular y comparar la tasa de mortalidad perinatal (TMP) y sus componentes en gestantes autóctonas e inmigrantes, tomando como referencia los casos notificados a ambos registros durante 2005 y 2006.MétodosSe definieron los distintos tipos de mortalidad de acuerdo con los criterios establecidos por la OMS. La magnitud de la infradeclaración se analizó calculando las frecuencias y porcentajes de muertes infradeclaradas para el período 2005&#150;2006. Se calcularon y compararon las diversas tasas entre mujeres autóctonas e inmigrantes de los cuatro grupos mayoritarios a partir de ambos registros, así como los intervalos de confianza del 95% para dichas tasas.ResultadosEn el INE existe un importante subregistro de muertes fetales y neonatales. Además, constan neonatos fallecidos de madre extranjera con nacionalidad española asignada. Ambos factores distorsionan la proporción de muertes fetales y neonatales en inmigrantes, y provocan una infraestimación de la TMP y sus componentes en estos colectivos, pues las obtenidas a partir del RMPCV son muy superiores en las mujeres inmigrantes, en particular en las de Europa del Este y las subsaharianas, en comparación con las autóctonas.ConclusionesEn definitiva, nuestros resultados indican que ambos registros son complementarios, pero el RMPCV presenta una mayor exhaustividad y fiabilidad para el cálculo de tasas. Además, sugieren la necesidad de monitorizar la evolución de la TMP en la población inmigrante en España(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(5): 403-409, sep. -oct. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la mortalidad perinatal en mujeres autóctonas e inmigrantes: influencia de la exhaustividad y la calidad de los registros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52870^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5424^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27794^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27794^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4716</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
