<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75404</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of the easy or complicated airway by nonexperts using the AirTraq optical laryngoscope</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To evaluate the utility of the AirTraqoptical laryngoscope in a retrospective case series,assessing indications for use and benefits as well aspossible limitations.PATIENTS AND METHODS: Retrospective study of the first124 patients in whom we used the AirTraq for trachealintubation. Anatomical and demographic variables wererecorded in addition to preoperative findings onexamination of the airway. Ease in accomplishing themaneuver and quality of the procedure were assessedafter intubation with the AirTraq.RESULTS: The trachea was correctly intubated in97.6% of the patients. Intubation failed in only 3 (2.4%)patients. Laryngoscopic quality was optimal in over95% of the cases. There were few complications or otherevents.CONCLUSIONS: The AirTraq laryngoscope has beenshown to facilitate intubation even when nonexpert staffperform the maneuver in cases in which previousattempts at laryngoscopy have failed and in which adifficult airway is anticipated. Ease of use and relativesafety make the AirTraq a practical device for a varietyof patient types and clinical settings(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castañeda Pascual, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dorronsoro Auzmendi, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iza López, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Unzué Rico, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo Jaso, e</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Batllori Gastón, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Evaluar la utilidad del laringoscopio ópticoAirtraq®, evaluando sus indicaciones y beneficios, asícomo las posibles limitaciones de su empleo en una serieretrospectiva de pacientes.PACIENTES Y MÉTODOS: Revisión retrospectiva de losprimeros 124 pacientes de nuestro centro cuya intubaciónendotraqueal fue realizada con Airtraq®. Se tuvieronen cuenta variables anatómicas y demográficas delos pacientes, así como la exploración preoperatorio dela vía aérea. Tras la realización de la intubación con Airtraq® se recogieron datos en cuanto a su facilidad demanejo y calidad del procedimiento.RESULTADOS: En un 97,6% de los pacientes se consiguióuna intubación correcta y en sólo 3 (2,4%) pacientesfue imposible. La calidad de la laringoscopia fue óptimaen más del 95% de los casos. Las complicaciones eincidencias fueron mínimas.CONCLUSIÓN: El laringoscopio Airtraq® ha demostradoque facilita la intubación en aquellos casos en losque intentos previos de laringoscopia han sido infructuososy en pacientes con predictores evidentes de víaaérea difícil (VAD), incluso cuando fue empleado porpersonal no entrenado en su uso. La facilidad en suempleo y su relativa inocuidad, lo convierten en unpráctico dispositivo en distintos tipos de pacientes ysituaciones clínicas(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;56(9): 536-540, nov. 2009. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75404</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de la vía aérea fácil y complicada con el laringoscopio óptico Airtraq® en manos inexpertas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7601^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34564^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34564^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7603^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
