<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113805</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-0740</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Weight gain for an uncomplicated birth: limit weight gain by body mass index prior</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: Establish limits of weight gain during pregnancy as body mass index (BMI) before the 12th week to avoid a complicated delivery. Material and methods: A prospective observational study in caucasian primiparous pregnant without underlying diseases, singleton pregnancies to term with cephalic presentation and birth weight of 2,500-4,000 g, assisted in the delivery room at University Hospital Nuestra Señora de la Candelaria, Tenerife, during2009/july-2010/february. It is considered complicated delivery instrumented or cesarean, its cause weight gain during pregnancy and potential confounders: age, smoking, maternal education and epidural administration. The data are summarized with appropriate statics, compare according to their characteristics, stratifying by categories of body mass index we found most sensitive-specific cut-off points for safe weight gain by COR typeII analysis and adjusting for risk factors confounding using logistic regression. Results: It includes 473 pregnant women between 16-46 years,12.7% for underweight, normal weight 53.7%, 23.3% overweight and 10.4% obese and a weight gain of 13.6 ± 5.3 kg, the 33.8% hada complicated delivery. Set to 14.250 kg weight gain for an uncomplicated delivery in the category of underweight, normal weight14.150 kg, overweight 12.750 kg and 10.200 kg for obesity. The risk to suffer a difficult delivery, to overcome these limits is 1.9 (95%CI:1.2 to 2.8), weight gain being the only factor associated with complicated delivery. Conclusion: For an uncomplicated birth pregnant women should not exceed the weight increase established as safe for your BMI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gramage-Córdoba, Laura Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Bellido,  M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre-Jaime, Armando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Asins-Cubells, Adalberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Rodríguez, Salomé</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Establecer los límites de aumento de peso en el embarazo según el índice de masa corporal (IMC) antes de la semana 12 para evitar un parto complicado. Material y métodos: Estudio observacional y prospectivo sobre gestantes caucásicas primíparas, sin enfermedades, con una gestación única a término con presentación cefálica y peso del neonato de 2.500-4.000 g, atendida sen el Paritorio del Hospital Universitario Nuestra Señora de la Candelaria, Tenerife, desde julio de 2009 hasta febrero de 2010. Se considera parto complicado el instrumentado o por cesárea, cuya causa es el aumento de peso durante el embarazo y teniendo en cuenta los posibles factores de confusión: edad, tabaquismo, educación maternal y administración de epidural. Los datos se resumen con estadígrafos apropiados al caso, y se comparan según sus características. Estratificando a las pacientes por categorías de IMC, se hallan los puntos de corte sensible-específicos de un aumento de peso seguro mediante análisis COR tipo II, y ajustándolos riesgos por factores de confusión mediante regresión logística. Resultados: Se incluyeron en el estudio 473 gestantes de 16-46 años de edad, un 12,7% con bajo peso, un 53,7% con normopeso, un23,3% con sobrepeso y un 10,4% obesas, con un aumento ponderal de 13,6 ± 5,3 kg. El 33,8% tuvo un parto complicado. Se establece en14,250 kg la ganancia de peso máxima para un parto sin complicaciones para un bajo peso, en 14,150 kg para un normopeso, en 12,750 kg para sobrepeso y en 10,200 kg para obesidad. El riesgo de sufrir un parto complicado por superar estos límites es de 1,9 (intervalo de confianza del 95%: 1,2-2,8), y la ganancia de peso es el único factor asociado al parto complicado. Conclusión: Para un parto sin complicaciones no debe sobrepasarse el aumento de peso establecido como seguro para su IMC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Matronas prof;14(1): 10-16, ene.-mar. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113805</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ganancia de peso para un parto sin complicaciones: límite de aumento ponderal según el índice de masa corporal previo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7922^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23861</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
