<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75272</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biliary obstruction due to adenocarcinoma of the ampulla of Vater ten years after orthotopic liver transplantation</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Molina Granados, J. F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vida Pérez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrena Baena, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escribano Fernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">The main causes of death in patients with liver transplants are derived from the graft itself. Given the increased survival in this group of patients, the rate of de novo neoplasms in other locations is increasing. We present the case of a 60-year-old man who underwent orthotopic liver transplantation 10 years earlier for terminal cirrhosis caused by hepatitis B. Imaging studies showed dilation of the intra- and extra-hepatic bile ducts with no evidence of lithiasis, anastomotic stenosis, or other biliary complications that are common in patients with liver transplants. The definitive diagnosis was reached by endoscopic retrograde cholangio pancreatography. Adenocarcinoma of the ampulla of Vater should be considered among the causes of biliary obstruction in patients with orthotopic liver transplants (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);51(6): 610-613, nov.-dic. 2009. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75272</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Obstrucción biliar por adenocarcinoma de la papila de Vater en un paciente con trasplante hepático ortotópico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2829^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15072^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29476^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38794^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8287^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200912</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
