<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161615</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The importance of the hospital for the clinical teaching and biomedical research</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of modern hospital is provide to reference population an excellent health care, integrated within social domain and community level, generating knowledge and enhancing the teaching, research and innovation. The teaching hospital should be educated to medicine, nursing and related careers students; to postgraduates (specialists training) and to specialists trained (continous training), The general objective is providing steadily the professional competence of healthcare personnel. The Medicine should be taugh in hospitals, that constitute, in all phases of medical training, their only perform school. In this article is exposed some reflections about the role of the hospitals as training center of the medical personnel; in detail, whom should be instructed, who must be taught, that and how to teach, just like the importance carry out the biomedical research as cosubstantial activity within hospital sector (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Montes, JA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El cometido de un hospital moderno es proveer a la población de referencia una atención de salud excelente, integrada en el ámbito social y comunitario, generándose conocimientos y potenciando la docencia, la investigación y la innovación. El hospital docente debe enseñar a los estudiantes de Medicina y Enfermería y afines, a postgraduados (formación de especialistas) y a especialistas ya formados (educación continuada). El objetivo general es mejorar de forma constante la competencia profesional del personal sanitario. La Medicina debe enseñarse en los hospitales, que constituyen, en todas las etapas del adiestramiento médico, su única escuela práctica. En este artículo, se exponen algunas reflexiones sobre el papel del hospital como centro de formación de personal médico sanitario; en concreto, a quién debe enseñar, quién debe enseñar, qué y cómo debe enseñar, así como la importancia de realizar investigación biomédica como actividad consustancial en el ámbito hospitalario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;20(1): 26-30, 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161615</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Importancia del hospital para la enseñanza clínica e investigación biomédica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9508^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37673^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9508^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17099^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
