<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-97413</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of the results of the 2010 External Quality Control Program of the Spanish Society of Infectious Diseases and Clinical Microbiology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The External Quality Control Program of the Spanish Society of Infectious Diseases and Clinical Microbiology includes controls for bacteriology, serology, mycology, parasitology, mycobacteria, virology and molecularmicrobiology. This article presents the most important conclusions and lessons of the 2010 controls. As awhole, the results obtained in 2010 confirm the excellent skill and good technical standards found inprevious years. However, erroneous results can be obtained in any laboratory and in clinically relevant determinations. The results of this program highlight the need to implement both internal and externalcontrols to ensure maximal quality of microbiological tests (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz de Gopegui Bordes, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosario Ovies, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orta Mira, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gimeno Cardona, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>del Remedio Guna Serrano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Poveda, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El Programa de Control Externo de Calidad de la Sociedad Española de Enfermedades Infecciosas y Microbiología Clínica (SEIMC) incluye las áreas de bacteriología, serología, micología, parasitología, micobacterias, virología y microbiología molecular. En este manuscrito se presenta el análisis de los resultados enviados por los participantes en los controles remitidos durante el año 2010. Los resultados obtenidos confirman de nuevo la buena capacitación general de los laboratorios españoles de microbiología clínica de años anteriores. A pesar de ello, el programa muestra que es posible obtener un resultado erróneo, incluso en determinaciones de gran trascendencia y en cualquier laboratorio. Resaltamos la importancia de complementar el control interno que cada laboratorio lleva a cabo con estudios de intercomparación externos, como los que ofrece el Programa SEIMC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;29(supl.5): 1-7, Dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-97413</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de resultados del Programa Externo de Control de Calidad SEIMC. Año 2010</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13431^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51548</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33124^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25468^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54379^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
