<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036328</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5638</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perfomance of the physiotherapist in the multisensorial stimulation therapy on children with special needs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The figure of the physiotherapist in the educational centres is currently being consolidated, not only for the assistance work they carry out but also for the wide range of actions they can perform. The inter-disciplinary coordination among the different professionals within the educational field (teachers of therapeutic pedagogy, logopedicians, counsellors, etc.) has enabled the physiotherapist to set and propose goals and guidelines concerning the methods of intervention. This article aims to pinpoint the contribution of the physiotherapist to Multisensorial Stimulation Therapy. Our training has allowed us to asquire specific know-how on kinesiology, biomechanics, neurology, physiology, etc., making it possible for us to meet the motoric needs or every student in the most efficient way, and to integrate them within this therapy</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Jaso Margarit, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova Cánovas, I. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diz Fariña, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Campillo Martínez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Hoy en día, la figura del fisioterapeuta en los centros educativos se va afianzando, no solamente por su labor asistencial, sino por la diversidad de actuaciones que puede realizar. La coordinación interdisciplinar con los profesionales del ámbito educativo (profesor especialista en pedagogía terapéutica, logopedas, orientadores, etc.), ha conseguido que el fisioterapeuta elabore y proponga objetivos y orientaciones en los métodos de intervención. Nuestro fín en este artículo es resaltar la aportación del fisioterapeuta en la Terapia de Estimulación Multisensorial. Nuestra formación nos ha permitido adquirir unos conocimientos cinesiológicos, biomecánicos, neurológicos, fisiológicos, etc., que nos permite dar un enfoque más adecuado a la particularidad motórica de cada alumnado e integrarla dentro de esta terapia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Fisioterapia (Madr., Ed. impr.);27(3): 161-166, mayo-jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036328</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actuación del fisioterapeuta en la terapia de estimulación multisensorial en niños con necesidades educativas especiales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4589^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33552^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36319^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11245^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
