<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116380</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Congenital mydriasis as an initial sign of septo-optic dysplasia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Septo-optic dysplasia (SOD)[MIM182230] consisting of a heterogeneous and uncommon condition characterised by the classic triad: optic nerve hypoplasia, abnormalities of pituitary hormone, and defects of the brain midline (including agenesis of the septum pellucidum and/or the corpus callosum; it has also been described associated cortical malformations, it was referred to as SOD plus syndrome).We report the first known case in which the initial diagnostic sign of SOD was a bilateral mydriasis as a manifestation of hypoplasia of both optic nerves, pituitary hypoplasia andcerebral dysgenesis with neuronal migration disorder. We discuss the differential diagnosis of congenital mydriasis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Cano, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Pardo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrascosa-Romero, M. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfaro-Ponce, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La displasia septo-óptica (DSO)[MIM182230] es una entidad heterogénea poco frecuente, caracterizada por la tríada clásica: hipoplasia del nervio óptico, anomalías de las hormonas hipofisarias y defectos de la línea media cerebral (incluyendo agenesia del septumpellucidumy/o del cuerpo calloso; también se han descrito malformaciones corticales asociadas, citado como síndrome DSO plus). Referimos el primer caso clínico conocido, en el que el signo de diagnóstico inicial de DSO fue una midriasis bilateral, como manifestación de hipoplasia de ambos nervios ópticos, hipoplasia hipofisaria y disgenesia cerebral con alteración de migración neuronal. Discutimos el diagnóstico diferencial de la midriasis congénita (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;88(10): 398-402, oct. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116380</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Midriasis congénita como signo inicial de displasia septo-óptica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9624^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10080^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24792^s22013</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36013^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
