<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113770</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of a new model of intensive care medicine upon healthcare in a department of intensive care medicine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives To evaluate a new organizational model in an intensive care unit, with the implementation of early warning systems and a support unit. Design A retrospective, comparative cohort study was carried out. Setting The study was carried out in the Department of Intensive Care Medicine (DICM) of a tertiary hospital (2009-2011), with the comparison of three time periods (P1, P2 and P3) that differed in terms of organization and logistics. Patients We analyzed all patients admitted to the ICU during the study period. Patients from maternal and infant intensive care were excluded. Variables of interest Percentage of patients with stays of under two days, with invasiveness used; readmission to the DICM, type of admission and percentage of stays of longer than one month; APACHE II score, mean stay in the ICU and shift distribution of the admissions. Results We analyzed a sample of 3209 patients (65% males), with a mean age of 58.23 (18.23) years, a mean APACHE II score of 16.67 (8.23), and presenting an occupancy rate of 7.3 (10.3) days in the analyzed period. The ratio APACHE II score/number of beds was 0.69 (0.34) in P1, compared to 0.68 (0.33) in P2 and 0.76 (0.37) in P3 (p&lt;0.001). The intervention surveillance grade (grade 1) was 42% (39-46%) in P1, 40% (37-43%) in P2 and 31% (28-35%) in P3 (p&lt;0.001). The average stay in the ICU ranged from 7.10 days (8.82) in P1to 6.60 days (9.49) in P2 and 8.42 days (12.73) in P3 (p&lt;0.001).Conclusions There has been an increase in the number of patients seen in our DICM, with a decrease in the patients admitted to the conventional ICU. Patients now admitted to the ICU are more seriously ill, require a greater level of intervention, and give rise to an increase in the mean duration of stay in the ICU (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Holanda, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dominguez, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suberviola, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Castro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortiz-Melon, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco-Huelga, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos Evaluar un nuevo modelo organizativo en un servicio de Medicina Intensiva, con la puesta en marcha de servicio extendido y unidad de apoyo. Diseño Estudio de cohortes retrospectivo, comparativo. Ámbito El estudio se realiza en un SMI de un hospital de tercer nivel (2009-2011). Comparando 3 periodos de tiempo (P1, P2 y P3) deferentes en cuanto a organización y logística dentro nuestro SMI. Pacientes Se analizan todos los enfermos que ingresan en el SMI, durante el periodo de estudio. Se excluyen los pacientes del área de cuidados intensivos materno infantil. Variables de interés Porcentaje de enfermos con estancias menores de 2 días, invasividad empleada en los enfermos; reingreso en el SMI, el tipo de ingreso y el porcentaje de estancias superiores a un mes; APACHE II, las estancias medias en la UCI y la turnicidad de los ingresos. Resultados Analizamos una muestra de 3.209 enfermos; La edad media fue de 58,23 (18,23), con un APACHE II medio de 16,67 (8,23), siendo el 65% varones y presentando una estancia media de 7,3 (10,3) días en el periodo analizado. El ratio APACHEII/número de camas fue de 0,69 (0,34) en P1, frente a 0,68 (0,33) de P2 y 0,76 (0,37) en P3 (&lt; 0,001). El grado de intervención de vigilancia (Grado 1) fue del 42% (39-46%) en P1, 40% (37-43%) en P2 y 31% (28-35%) en P3 (&lt; 0,001). La estancia media en UCI varió de 7,10 días (8,82) en P1, 6,60 días (9,49) en P2 y 8,42 días (12,73) en P3 (&lt; 0,001).Conclusiones Se ha producido un aumento del número de pacientes atendidos por nuestro SMI, con un descenso de pacientes que ingresan en las UCI convencionales. Los enfermos que ingresan ahora en la UCI son enfermos más graves, requieren un nivel de intervención mayor y ocasionan un aumento de la estancia media en la UCI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. intensiva (Madr., Ed. impr.);37(1): 27-32, ene.-feb. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113770</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de un nuevo modelo de Medicina Intensiva sobre la asistencia en un servicio de Medicina Intensiva</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7545^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30652</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
