<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85990</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The degree of Knower and compliance with occupational risk prevention measures in the Spanish gastrointestinal endoscopy units is unknown. Aim: 1. To assess compliance with occupational risk prevention measures in GIE units. 2. To determine which factors influence the fulfillment of occupational risk prevention measures. Methods: a validated survey was supplied to 300 GIE units, including questions on: 1. General occupational risk prevention measures; 2. occupational risk prevention measures during disinfection; 3. occupational risk prevention measures during examination. The following Hospital or GIE Unit characteristics were evaluated: Type of hospital according to the Spanish National Health Service; Number of hospital beds; Advanced diagnostic and therapeutic procedures performed and; Centers providing training in the field of endoscopy. Results: response: 196 GIE units (65%). 104 GIE units (53% CI95%: 46-60) fulfill less than 50% of the occupational risk prevention measures studied. The RR of less than 50% of the ORP measures being fulfilled is 1.975 times higher at public hospitals than at private facilities (CI95%: 1.11-3.52). None of the remaining factors analyzed proved to have a significant influence. Conclusions: compliance with occupational risk prevention measures in Spanish GIE units is inadequate and must be improved. Public hospitals in Spain comply with fewer occupational risk prevention measures than their private counterparts(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez del Río, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre-Jaime, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baudet, J. S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la actualidad desconocemos el grado de conocimiento y aplicación de medidas de prevención de riesgos laborales en las Unidades de Endoscopia Españolas. Objetivo: valorar la aplicación de la prevención de riesgos laborales en las unidades de endoscopia y establecer los factores que determinan su cumplimiento. Diseño: se pasó un cuestionario validado a 300 unidades de endoscopia. Se incluían preguntas sobre: Medidas generales de pre - vención de riesgos laborales, medidas de prevención durante la desinfección y medidas de prevención durante las exploraciones. Se valoraron el tipo de hospital en función de su adscripción al sistema público de salud, el tamaño de los hospitales según el número de camas, la realización o no de técnicas avanzadas y la realización de docencia de endoscopia o no. Se estimó el porcentaje de cumplimiento de cada medida con un intervalo de confianza del 95% y se realizó una regresión logística para determinar los factores que determinan su cumplimiento. Resultados: respondieron 196 unidades (65%). 104 (53% CI95%: 46-60) cumplían menos del 50% de las medidas de PRL estudiadas. Los Hospitales Españoles de titularidad pública tienen un RR 1,975 veces mayor (IC95%: 1.11-3.52) de aplicar menos del 50% de las medidas de PRL frente a los privados. El resto de los factores estudiados no mostraron influencia significativa. Conclusiones: la aplicación de medidas de prevención de riesgos laborales en las unidades de endoscopia españolas no es adecuada y debe ser mejorada. Los hospitales públicos cumplen con menor número de medidas que los privados(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;103(2): 83-88, feb. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85990</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevención de riesgos laborales en unidades de endoscopia. Una asignatura pendiente</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32480^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6913^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11926^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10221^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201102</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
