<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81156</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prognostic value of lymph node micrometastases in patients with colorectal cancer in Dukes stages A and B (T1-T4, N0, M0)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: 30% of patients with colorectal cancer (CRC) inDukes stages A and B (T1-T4, N0, M0) present tumor recurrenceand die after 5 years follow up. This unexpectedly poor evolutionmight be attributable to the presence of lymph node micrometastasisundetected in routine examination with haematoxilin-eosine(H&amp;E).Objective: to assess the presence of undetected micrometastasis.Patients and methods: we conducted a retrospective studyof the locoregional lymph nodes in 85 patients operated for CRCin Dukes stages A and B (T1-T4, N0, M0), using immunohistochemistrywith anticytokeratin antibodies AE1/AE3. In this descriptive,inferential bivariant and survival study, we analyzed differentrisk factors, including local infiltration T1/T4, Dukes A/B,number of dissected lymph nodes, vascular invasion, micrometastasis,tumor recurrence and death in the context of the presenceor absence of micrometastases.Results: Dukes stage and neoplastic angioinvasion are influentialin patient prognosis; however, lymph node micrometastaseswere not associated with a poorer outcome of CRC.Conclusions: locorregional lymph node micrometastases detectedwith anticytokeratine antibodies AE1/AE3 in Dukes A andB CRC patients are not associated with reduced survival(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Uribarrena Amezaga, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Uribarrena Echevarría, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fuentes, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Raventós, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: un 30% de los pacientes con cáncer colorrectal(CCR) en estadios A y B de Dukes (T1-T4, N0, M0) presentan recidivatumoral y/o fallecen a los 5 años. Esta inesperada malaevolución, en casos presumiblemente curados podría deberse, entreotras causas, a la presencia de micrometástasis linfoganglionaresno detectadas en el estudio de rutina: hematoxilina-eosina(H&amp;E).Objetivo: determinar si la presencia de micrometástasis linfoganglionaresdetectadas mediante inmunohistoquímica con anticuerposanticitoqueratina AE1/AE3, influyen en la evolución delCCR.Pacientes y métodos: se han estudiado los ganglios linfáticoslocorregionales de 85 pacientes con CCR en estadios A y Bde Dukes (T1-T4, N0, M0), mediante técnicas de inmunohistoquímicacon anticuerpos anticitoqueratinas AE1/AE3, para poner demanifiesto la presencia de micrometástasis. Se ha realizado un estudiodescriptivo, inferencial bivariante y de supervivencia, segúndistintos factores de riesgo, centrado en la presencia o no de micrometástasis.Resultados: hemos observado que el estadio de Dukes y laangioinvasión neoplásica son factores que influyen en el pronósticode estos pacientes. Sin embargo, no se ha demostrado que lapresencia de micrometástasis linfoganglionares se asocie a unapeor evolución en el CCR.Conclusiones: las micrometástasis linfoganglionares locorregionalesdetectadas mediante anticuerpos anticitoqueratinaAE1/AE3, en pacientes con CCR en estadios A y B de Dukes, nose asocian a una menor supervivencia(au9</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;102(3): 176-186, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81156</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor pronóstico de las micrometástasis linfoganglionares en pacientes con cáncer colorrectal en estadios A y B de Dukes (T1-T4, N0, M0)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23595^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8384^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9560^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
