<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79981</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Myocardial perfusion grade, myocardial salvage indices and long-term mortality in patients with acute myocardial infarction and full restoration of epicardial blood flow after primary percutaneous coronary intervention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. The relationship between microcirculatory myocardial perfusion grade (MPG), myocardial salvage and long-term mortality after acute ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) and full restoration of epicardial blood flow by primary percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) remains poorly understood. Methods. This study included 1213 patients with STEMI and Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction (TIMI) grade-3 flow after primary PCI. The MPG was determined and paired scintigraphic studies (before and 7&#150;14 days after the intervention) were performed. The primary outcome was 5-year mortality. Results. The MPG was 0-1 in 217 patients, 2 in 195, and 3 in 801. In patients with an MPG of 0-1, 2 and 3, respectively, the median infarct size was 13% (interquartile range [IQR] 5.6-28%), 12% (IQR 4-27%) and 7% (IQR 1-19%) of the left ventricle, respectively (P&lt;.001), the myocardial salvage index (i.e. the proportion of the initial area at risk that recovered) was 0.44 (IQR 0.22-0.73), 0.46 (IQR 0.25-0.75) and 0.58 (IQR 0.31-0.85), respectively (P&lt;.001), and the Kaplan-Meier estimated 5-year mortality  was 16.6% (i.e. 28 deaths), 15.3% (i.e. 25 deaths) and 7.8% (i.e. 48 deaths), respectively. The odds ratio (OR) for death for an MPG of 0-1 vs. 3 was 2.32 (95% confidence interval [CI] 1.42-3.8; P&lt;.001) and for an MPG of 2 vs. 3, 2.3 (95% CI 1.38-3.85; P=.001). The Cox proportional hazards model identified MPG as independently associated with mortality at 5 years: the hazard ratio for an MPG of 3 vs. 0-2 was 0.65 (95% CI 0.41-0.97; P=.037). Conclusions. In patients with STEMI and TIMI grade-3 flow after primary PCI, suboptimal microcirculatory myocardial perfusion (i.e. MPG &lt;=2) was associated with poorer myocardial salvage, a larger infarct, and higher 5-year mortality than observed in patients whose tissue perfusion was reestablished (i.e. MPG=3) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fusaro, Massimiliano</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ellert, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Schömig, Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kufner, Sebastian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Goedel, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mehilli, Julinda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kastrati, Adnan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ndrepepam, Gjin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tiroch, Klaus</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La relación entre el grado de perfusión miocárdica (GPM), el rescate miocárdico y la mortalidad a largo plazo tras el infarto agudo de miocardio con elevación del segmento ST (IAMEST) y restablecimiento pleno del flujo sanguíneo epicárdico con una intervención coronaria percutánea (ICP) primaria continúa sin conocerse bien. Métodos. Participaron en el estudio 1.213 pacientes con IAMEST y un flujo de grado Thrombolysis in Myocardial Infarction (TIMI) 3 tras la ICP primaria. Se realizaron determinaciones del GPM y dos exploraciones gammagráficas (antes y 7-14 días después de la intervención). La variable de valoración principal fue la mortalidad a 5 años. Resultados. Se observó un GPM de 0-1, 2 o 3 en un total de 217, 195 y 801 pacientes, respectivamente. En los grupos con un GPM 0-1, 2 y 3, los tamaños del infarto (mediana [cuartiles 25-75]) fueron del 13% [5,6%- 28%], el 12% [4%-27%] y el 7% [1%-19%] del ventrículo izquierdo, respectivamente (p &lt; 0,001); los índices de rescate (proporción del área inicial en riesgo que se rescata) fueron 0,44 [0,22-0,73], 0,46 [0,25-0,75] y 0,58 [0,31-0,85], respectivamente (p &lt; 0,001); las estimaciones de Kaplan-Meier de la mortalidad a 5 años fueron del 16,6% (28 muertes), el 15,3% (25 muertes) y el 7,8% (48 muertes); con una odds ratio (OR) = 2,32 (intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 1,42-3,8) (p &lt; 0,001) para GPM 0-1 frente a GPM 3, y OR = 2,3 (IC del 95%, 1,38-3,85) (p = 0,001) para GPM 2 frente a GPM 3. El modelo de riesgos proporcionales de Cox identificó el GPM como factor independiente correlacionado con la mortalidad a 5 años (razón de riesgos = 0,65 [0,41-0,97]; p = 0,037 para el GPM 3 frente a GPM 0-2). Conclusiones. En los pacientes con IAMEST y un flujo de grado TIMI 3 tras una ICP primaria, la reperfusión miocárdica subóptima (GPM &lt;= 2) se asoció a una reducción del rescate miocárdico, un mayor tamaño del infarto y un aumento de la mortalidad a 5 años en comparación con los pacientes con restablecimiento de la perfusión tisular (GPM = 3) (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(7): 770-778, jul. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79981</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Grado de perfusión miocárdica, índices de rescate miocárdico y mortalidad a largo plazo en pacientes con infarto agudo de miocardio y restablecimiento completo del flujo sanguíneo epicárdico tras intervención coronaria percutánea primaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23771^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23771^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23771^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201007</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
