<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142086</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Physical self-concept differences in practitioners and nonpractitioners of physical activity in college students</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present investigation objective was to identify the differences of physical self-concept in regular practitioners and non-practitioners of physical activity in college students. A group of 208 college student between 18 and 31 years participated, of which 49% perform physical activity on a regular basis and 51% do not practice regularly or do not perform any physical activity, and the Physical Self-Concept Questionnaire of Moreno &amp; Cervelló (2005) was applied. In all dimensions of physical self-concept, as well as the general scales of physical self-concept and general self-concept, statistically significant differences were found obtaining p-values below &amp;#945; = .05, this indicates that the physical self-perceptions and general self-perceptions are measured by physical activity, so it sustains the importance of physical activity in the self-concept of college students (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González Hernández, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lara Pot, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuevas Ferrera, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Rivera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presente investigación tuvo como objetivos identificar las diferencias del autoconcepto físico en practicantes regulares y no practicantes de actividad física en estudiantes universitarios. Participaron 208 estudiantes universitarios entre 18 y 31 años de los cuales el 49% realizan actividad física regular y el 51% no practican de forma regular o no realizan ninguna actividad física y se les aplicó el Cuestionario de Autoconcepto Físico (CAF) de Moreno y Cervelló (2005). En todas las dimensiones del autoconcepto físico, así como en las escalas generales de autoconcepto físico y autoconcepto general, se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas al obtener p-valores debajo de &amp;#945;=.05, esto indica que las autopercepciones fí- sicas y las autopercepciones generales están medidas por la actividad física, por lo que se sustenta la importancia que tiene la actividad física en los universitarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;15(2): 27-34, jul. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142086</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Diferencias del autoconcepto físico en practicantes y no practicantes de actividad física en estudiantes universitarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13721^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54263^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1853^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
