<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-154604</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biomarkers of lipid peroxidation in the aqueous humor of primary open-angle glaucoma patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To investigate the lipid peroxidation (PEROX) processes in primary open-angle glaucoma (POAG) patients, and whether this mechanism may be related to disease progression. Material and methods: A prospective, observational, cross-sectional, non-experimental, and analytical study was conducted on a case and a comparison group, consisting of 175 surgical patients divided into: 1) POAG group (GG; n=88) and 2) comparison group of patients with cataracts (CG; n=87). Demographic data, patient characteristics, lifestyle data, as well as ophthalmological examination were registered in an Excel spreadsheet. Biochemical data were obtained by processing the aqueous humor collected at the beginning of surgery. Determination of malondialdehyde/thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (MDA/TBARS) and total antioxidant activity (AAO) was assayed using enzymatic-colorimetric methods in the aqueous humor samples. Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS 15.0 software. Results: Aqueous humor MDA/TBARS levels were significantly higher (P&lt;.001) and the AAO significantly lower (P&lt;.001) in the GG than in the GC. The MDA/TBARS directly correlated with intraocular pressure (IOP) values and the cup-to-disc ratio (CDR). Decreased AAO activity correlated inversely with IOP and CDR. Differences between groups were noticeably higher in the GG as regards obesity, alcohol consumption, anxiety, depression, and sedentary lifestyle. In the multivariate analysis, the variables that showed a better predictive ability were: MDA/TBARS, PIO, AAO, CDR, and depression. Conclusions: The POAG patients have a PEROX background that is reflected in the aqueous humor by variations in MDA/TBARS and AAO. Moreover, both the MDA/TBARS and AAO correlated with IOP values and the CDR. We propose that determination of MDA/TBARS and AAO in the aqueous humor of POAG patients can be used as biomarkers for monitoring the disease, as well the changes in lifestyle and other related risk factors (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piñas García, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinazo Durán, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zanón Moreno, VC</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vinuesa Silva, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández Martínez, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bendala Tufanisco, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lleó Pérez, AV</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Medina, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Investigamos la peroxidación lipídica (PEROX) en el glaucoma primario de ángulo abierto (GPAA) y si este mecanismo puede relacionarse con su progresión. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo observacional, transversal, analítico no experimental de casos y grupo comparativo, con selección de 175 pacientes quirúrgicos, distribuidos en: 1) grupo diagnosticado de GPAA (GG; n=88) y 2) grupo comparativo de pacientes con cataratas (GC; n=87). Se han obtenido datos demográficos, características de los participantes y estilo de vida. Se realizó un examen oftalmológico centrado en GPAA. Se obtuvieron muestras de humor acuoso al principio de la cirugía programada, que fueron procesadas para determinar el malonildialdehído mediante la técnica del ácido tiobarbitúrico y sustancias reactivas (MDA/TBARS) así como la actividad antioxidante total (AAO) por métodos enzimático-colorimétricos. El estudio estadístico se realizó mediante el programa SPSS 15.0. Resultados: El nivel de MDA/TBARS fue significativamente mayor (p&lt;0,001) y la AAO significativamente menor (p&lt;0,001) en el GG que en el GC. El MDA/TBARS correlacionaba directamente con la presión intraocular (PIO) y relación vertical excavación/papilla (CDR). La disminución de la AAO correlacionaba inversamente con la PIO y el CDR. Las diferencias fueron notablemente mayores en el GG para obesidad, hábito alcohólico, ansiedad, depresión y sedentarismo. En el análisis multivariante las variables que presentaron una mejor capacidad predictiva fueron MDA, PIO, AAO, CDR y la presencia de depresión. Conclusiones: Los pacientes con GPAA están tratados mediante procesos de PEROX que se reflejan en el humor acuoso mediante variaciones en MDA/TBARS y AAO que, además, correlacionan con la PIO y el CDR en el curso del glaucoma. Proponemos que la determinación de MDA/TBARS y AAO en el humor acuoso de los pacientes con GPAA puede utilizarse como biomarcadores predictivos, junto con los cambios en el estilo de vida y otros factores de riesgo relacionados, para mejorar el seguimiento de los glaucomatosos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(8): 357-362, ago. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-154604</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Biomarcadores de peroxidación lipídica en el humor acuoso de pacientes con glaucoma primario de ángulo abierto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23743^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28054^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1089^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
