<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-037826</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of C-reactive protein in patients with peripheral arterial disease. Modifications with antiplatelet treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The determination of basal levels of C-reactive protein (CRP) is of    help in cataloguing vascular risk in patients with symptomatic peripheral arterial disease    (PAD). Aims. The aim of this study was to evaluate plasma levels of CRP in a cohort of    patients with PAD and the effect of treatment with antiplatelet drugs (clopidogrel) on CRP    levels, as well as to determine the relationship between CRP and the presence of metabolic    syndrome (MS). Patients and methods. An observational, epidemiological, interventional    prospective, multicentre study carried out on 1455 patients with PAD. Data analysed included    patient records, clinical examination, Ankle brachial indexes and clinical analyses both at the    beginning and after two months&#146; treatment with clopidogrel. CRP was determined with the    standard and ultrasensitive methods (n = 628 patients). Demographic data, cardiovascular    risk factors and previous cardiovascular events were analysed by descriptive statistics. A    t-test was used to analyse the continuous variables, the signed rank test was employed when    the normality hypothesis was not satisfied and chi-squared was utilised for categorical    variables. Results. Statistically significant differences were detected in the figures for CRP    between the initial and final visits in patients with a basal CRP &gt; 3 mg/L according to the    ultrasensitive method (p = 0.001). No statistically significant differences existed in the CRP    values for the population with MS. Conclusions. After two months&#146; treatment, in patients with    PAD, clopidogrel lowered levels of CRP in plasma when they had a basal value above 3 mg/L.    There is no relation between the presence of MS and high basal levels of CRP in patients    with PAD</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Perera-Sabio, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luján-Huertas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cancer-Pérez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puras-Mallagray, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez-Baz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alfayate-García, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La determinación de    los niveles basales de proteína C reactiva    (PCR) ayuda a catalogar el riesgo vascular    en pacientes con arteriopatía periférica sintomática    (APS). Objetivos. Evaluar los niveles    plasmáticos de PCR en una cohorte de    pacientes con APS y la influencia del tratamiento    con antiagregantes plaquetarios (clopidogrel)    sobre los niveles de PCR, y evaluar    la relación entre PCR y la presencia de síndrome    metabólico (SM). Pacientes y métodos.    Estudio de observación, epidemiológico,    prospectivo de intervención y multicéntrico,    de 1.455 pacientes, con APS. Se realiza    historial clínico, exploración clínica, índices    tobillo-brazo y analíticas al inicio, y    tras dos meses de tratamiento con clopidogrel.    La PCR se determinó con los métodos    estándar y ultrasensible (n = 628 pacientes).    Los datos demográficos, factores de riesgo    cardiovascular y eventos cardiovasculares    previos se analizan mediante estadística descriptiva.    Se utiliza un t-test para analizar las    variables continuas, signed rank en caso de    no cumplir la hipótesis de normalidad, y chi    al cuadrado para variables categóricas. Resultados.    Se detectaron diferencias estadísticamente    significativas en las cifras de PCR    entre las visitas basal y final en pacientes    con PCR basal &gt; 3 mg/L según el método    ultrasensible (p = 0,001). No existen diferencias    estadísticamente significativas en las cifras    de PCR para la población con SM. Conclusiones.    Tras dos meses de tratamiento, en    pacientes con APS, el clopidogrel disminuye    los niveles plasmáticos de PCR cuando éstos    están basalmente por encima de 3 mg/L. No    existe asociación entre presencia de SM y niveles    basales elevados de PCR en pacientes    con APS</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;57(1): 5-18, ene.-feb. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-037826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valoración de la proteína C reactiva en pacientes con arteriopatía periférica. Modificaciones con tratamiento antiagregante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22311</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200502</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
