<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165785</identifier>
<setSpec>1578-8423</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Body expression and dance in physical education of secondary and high school</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The Body Expression-Dance is an activity that has proven enriching and formative for all people, and especially for children and young people, for its great creative element, as well as for being one of the most important forms of artistic expression of being human. Recognizing these positive effects in the international literature and in the society itself, the LOMCE collects in the curriculum of the physical education subject in Secondary and High School a block of contents related to it. The purpose of this study has been to check whether teachers actually impart the curriculum contents related to Body Expression-Dance, and if so, the reasons for not doing so. Other variables that may affect the compliance of LOMCE in the Region of Murcia have also been analyzed. The results obtained indicated that only between 9% and 27% of ESO and High School teachers consider that they impart all the contents included in the law, although some contents in each course have a high or very high degree of compliance. The main reason that teachers refer to not impart one or some of these contents of corporal expression is the lack of time in programming, as well as the perception that they do not feel qualified to design and direct these sessions. Other variables such as the gender of the teacher and his/her teaching experience are conditional factors of the degree of fulfilment of these contents in both formative stages (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conesa, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Angosto, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Expresión Corporal-Danza es una actividad que se ha demostrado muy enriquecedora y formativa para todas las personas, y en especial para niños y jóvenes, por su gran elemento creativo, así como por ser una de las formas más importantes de expresión artística del ser humano. Reconocidos estos efectos positivos en la literatura internacional y en la propia sociedad, la LOMCE recoge en el currículum de la asignatura de educación física en Secundaria y Bachillerato un bloque de contenidos relacionados con ésta. El propósito de nuestro estudio ha sido comprobar si los profesores realmente imparten los contenidos establecidos en el currículum relacionados con la Expresión Corporal-Danza, y en su caso, los motivos para no hacerlo. Se han analizado igualmente otras variables que pueden estar afectando al cumpliendo de la LOMCE en la Región de Murcia. Los resultados obtenidos indicaron que únicamente entre un 9% y un 27% de los profesores de ESO y Bachillerato consideran que imparten todos los contenidos recogidos en la ley, aunque algunos contenidos en cada curso llegan a tener un grado de cumplimiento alto o muy alto. El principal motivo al que alude el profesorado para no impartir alguno o algunos estos contenidos de expresión corporal es la falta de tiempo en la programación, así como la percepción de que no se siente cualificados para diseñar y dirigir estas sesiones. Otras variables como el sexo del profesor y su experiencia docente son factores condicionales del grado de cumplimiento de estos contenidos en ambas etapas formativas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cuad. psicol. deporte;17(2): 111-120, jul. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165785</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La expresión corporal y danza en la educación física de secundaria y bachillerato</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d35173</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5278^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3634</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11239^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201707</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
