<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049466</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Pronostic factors on recurrence and progression of superficial bladder cancer. Risk groups (Part I)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: We have carried out a retrospective study on a series of superficial bladder tumours, analyzing the clinical-    pathological factors that can determine the subsequent evolution of the tumour as for recurrence and progression.    Material and Methods: They were revised on the whole 473, of which finally 419 superficial bladder tumours were    useful for the study (223 primary tumours and 196 recurrent). Studies are carried out univariate and multivariate on 24    variables of each tumour referred to the characteristics and to the evolution of the tumour.    Results: We find significant differences in the free time to recurrence, diminishing it in the tumours that recurred in    less than 12 months, in multiple tumours (3 or more tumours) and in bladder dome tumours. Also statistically significant    differences existed when were studied two homogeneous groups of surgeons, while the treatment with bladder instillations    increased it. The time to progression, diminishes in: Tumours that had recurred prematurely (in 6 months),    tumours over 3 cm, high grade tumours and when two groups of surgeons were studied, we also find that the maintenance    therapy with BCG (bacillus Calmette-Guerin) showed a greater time to progression versus induction therapy.    Discussion: The independent factors to explain smaller free time till superficial recurrence were: recurrence in the 1º    year, multiplicity, surgical technique, not employment of bladder washes, treatment with low dose of BCG and use of    intravesical therapy with induction therapy versus maintenance. About the progression, we objectify that the factors with    greater influence in the progression were, recurrence in the first 6 months, grade (grade 2 and grade 3 + Tis) and treatment    with maintenance therapy versus induction</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Escaf Barmadah, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Álvarez, R. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miranda Aranzubia, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Robles, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gómez, J. M. </dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Hemos realizado un estudio retrospectivo sobre una serie de tumores superficiales vesicales, analizando    los factores clínicopatológicos que pueden determinar la evolución posterior del tumor en cuanto a recurrencia y progresión.    Material y Métodos: Se revisaron en total 473 neoplasias vesicales superficiales, de las cuales finalmente 419 fueron    útiles para el estudio (223 tumores primarios y 196 recurrentes). Se realizan estudios uni y multivariante sobre 24 variables    de cada tumor referidas a las características y a la evolución de la neoplasia.    Resultados: Encontramos diferencias significativas en el tiempo libre hasta la recurrencia, que disminuyó en los    tumores que previamente habían recidivado precozmente (&lt;12 meses), en los tumores múltiples (3 o más tumores) y los    localizados en cúpula vesical. Además existieron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el tiempo libre de enfermedad    cuando se compararon dos grupos homogéneos de cirujanos mientras que el empleo de instilaciones vesicales    incrementó dicho tiempo. En cuanto a tiempo hasta la progresión, éste disminuye en tumores que habían recurrido precozmente    (en 6 meses), tumores mayores de 3 cm, tumores de alto grado y según el grupo de cirujanos. Además, encontramos    que la terapia de mantenimiento con BCG (bacilo Calmette-Guerin) demostró un mayor tiempo hasta la progresión    frente al de inducción.    Discusión: Resultaron independientes para explicar menor tiempo libre hasta la recurrencia superficial los siguientes    factores: recidiva en el 1º año, multiplicidad, técnica quirúrgica, no empleo de lavados endovesicales, tratamiento con    dosis bajas de BCG y terapia de inducción frente a mantenimiento. Respecto a la progresión, objetivamos que los factores    con mayor influencia en la progresión fueron: recurrencia en los primeros 6 meses, grado (grado 2 y grado 3 + Tis) y    empleo de terapia endovesical de mantenimiento frente a inducción</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;30(10): 998-1008, nov.-dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049466</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores pronósticos en la recidiva y progresión del cáncer superficial vesical. Grupos de riesgo (Parte I)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9557^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23093^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1774^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
