<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-25900</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Beliefs, coping, and depressive mood state in chronic pain patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study analyses the relationship between pain-related beliefs, coping strategies (self-statements), pain perception, and depressive mood state in chronic pain patients. A theoretical model is proposed and tested with two groups of chronic patients attending two different medical services. The sample was made up of 100 patients from the Rheumatology Unit, and 114 patients from a Pain Clinic. The results suggest that there are differences in the relationships between the different variables studied. A general conclusion is that the pain-related beliefs of patients with chronic pain play a important role on pain perception. However, no significant relationships were found between self-statements and pain. Finally, the pain intensity and the depressed mood are positively correlated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camacho Martel, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anarte Ortiz, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este estudio se analizan las posibles relaciones entre las creencias de dolor, las estrategias de afrontamiento (autoafirmaciones), el dolor percibido y el estado de ánimo deprimido en pacientes con dolor crónico. Se propone un modelo teórico que es contrastado en dos muestras de pacientes que acuden a diferentes servicios médicos para tratar su dolor, concretamente 100 pacientes de Reumatología y 114 de la Unidad del Dolor. Los resultados ponen de manifiesto la existencia de diferencias en cuanto a las relaciones entre las variables estudiadas en pacientes con dolor crónico de diferentes servicios médicos. Como conclusiones generales se destaca que las creencias mantenidas ponlos pacientes influyen sobre la percepción de su dolor, sin embargo, no se encuentran relaciones significativas entre el tipo de autoafirmaciones empleadas y dolor percibido. Finalmente, el dolor que el paciente percibe y el estado emocional deprimido correlacionan positivamente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);15(3): 464-470, ago. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-25900</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Creencias, afrontamiento y estado de ánimo deprimido en pacientescon dolor crónico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24766</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10334^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d714^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
