<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165790</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Generation of a new model of patellar tendinopathy in rats which mimics the human sports pathology: A pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Patellar tendon pathophysiology is not still fully understood. The collection of clinical samples from athletes that could permit the analysis of the tendinopathy progression, especially in the early stages, is difficult. For that reason, the purpose of this study is to develop a new experimental animal model of patellar tendinopathy in rats which mimics the human tendinopathy by in vivo intratendinous collagenase injection in the proximal portion of the patellar tendon. Material and methods: The experimental model used was 8-week-old male Wistar rats (n = 4). The administration of collagenase was performed by ultrasound-guided puncture at the level of the proximal and deep portion of the patellar tendon in anesthetized animals. The tendon lesion was evaluated 48 h after injury by magnetic resonance and then, the animals were euthanized and the patellar tendons were collected for histological evaluation. Results: The collagenase-induced lesion model demonstrated important similarities with the human patellar tendinopathy in the region of the proximal insertion. Conclusions: The experimental model of patellar tendinopathy in rat model induces a degeneration and distortion of the patellar tendon architecture in its proximal portion, which closely mimics to that seen in human patellar tendinopathy, and could represent an excellent preclinical model for the study of new therapies focused on treatment of tendinopathy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Contreras Muñoz, Paola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marotta, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lope, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodasa, Gil</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La fisiopatología de la tendinopatía rotuliana no es del todo conocida. Es difícil obtener muestras clínicas de deportistas que permitan conocer el desarrollo de la tendinopatía, sobre todo en las primeras etapas. Por este motivo, el propósito de este estudio es desarrollar, en una primera fase, un modelo experimental de tendinopatía rotuliana en ratas que simule la tendinopatía humana mediante la aplicación in vivo de colagenasa en la porción proximal del tendón rotuliano. Material y métodos: El modelo experimental utilizado fueron ratas Wistar macho de 8 semanas de edad (n = 4). La administración de colagenasa se realizó, tras anestesia e inmovilización de los animales, mediante punción guiada por ecografía a nivel de la porción proximal y profunda del tendón rotuliano. La lesión tendinosa se evaluó 48 h después de la lesión mediante resonancia magnética, tras lo cual se procedió a la eutanasia de los animales y a la extracción de los tendones rotulianos para su evaluación histológica. Resultados: El modelo de lesión inducida con colagenasa demostró similitud a nivel de la histología con la tendinopatía rotuliana humana en la región de su inserción proximal. Conclusiones: El modelo experimental de tendinopatía rotuliana en ratas induce la degeneración y distorsión de la arquitectura del tendón rotuliano en su porción proximal, situación similar a la observada en la tendinopatía rotuliana humana, y representa un excelente modelo preclínico para el estudio de nuevas terapias enfocadas al tratamiento de la tendinopatía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);52(194): 53-59, abr.-jun. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165790</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Generación de un nuevo modelo de tendinopatía rotuliana en ratas que imita la patología deportiva humana: estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30779^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31206^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1273^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14086^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50477^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
