<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89546</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-7279</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction.&amp;#8194;Childhood and youth psychiatric disorders often require an integrative approach to ensure efficacy. This article describes a multidiscipli­nary treatment paradigm for children and adolescents with mental retarda-tion and other psychiatric disorders.Objective.&amp;#8194;To describe a multimodal treatment paradigm for childhood and youth psychiatric disorders.Methods.&amp;#8194;Series case report. Results.&amp;#8194;A group of 20 patients ages 5 to 29 were admitted to long-term hospitalization to the unit. Seventeen have a diagnosis of mental retardation, one with depressive disorder, and two with personality and behavioral disorders, and according to their functional level 9 of them have an adequate level of function and 11 have some degree of functional compromise. We use a multimodal paradigm of intervention and observed decreased symptoms and in many of them, better social and occupational performance. Moreover, we used the same model in 12 patients admitted to an acute setting, with an average length of stay of 13.8 days, and also found improvement of their symptoms.Conclusions.&amp;#8194;Our multimodal treatment paradigm has significantly improved the complex presentation of our patient population. The challenge is to optimize and ensure continuity of this model (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santacruz Delgado, Andrea</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mideros Meza, Edwin</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santacruz Villota, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mendoza Bermúdez,  Constanza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción.&amp;#8194;La patología infanto-juvenil frecuentemente exige modelos de tipo integrativo que aseguren una mayor eficacia. Presentamos un modelo de atención multidisciplinaria en un Hospital psiquiátrico provincial dirigido a niños y jóvenes con retraso mental y otros diagnósticos psiquiátricos. Objetivo.&amp;#8194;Describir un modelo de intervención multimodal. Método.&amp;#8194;Diseño de serie de casos en el que se describe un esquema de trabajo y enfoque interdisciplinarios. Resultados.&amp;#8194;Un total de 20 pacientes entre los 5 y 29 años están internados actualmente en manejo de larga estancia en nuestra unidad infanto-juvenil, 17 con retraso mental, 1 con trastorno depresivo y los otros 2 con trastornos de personalidad y comportamiento, y según su nivel de desempeño 11 son semifuncionales y los restantes funcionales. Se ha instau­rado un modelo de intervención multi­modal observándose una reducción en su sintomatología psiquiátrica, en muchos un mejor desempeño ocupacional e interacción con su entorno. Además, se han realizado 12 ingresos para hospitalización de menores en fase aguda con un promedio de estancia de 13,8 días en quienes también se ha utilizado este modelo con una adecuada remisión de su sintomatología.Conclusiones.&amp;#8194;El modelo presentado nos ha permitido incidir de manera sinérgica sobre la amplia problemática de nuestros pacientes. Representa un reto para el equipo terapéutico darle continuidad y mayor estructuración a este esquema de intervención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Inf. psiquiátr;(193): 1-1, jul.-sept. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89546</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Una propuesta de tratamiento multimodal en nlos y jóvenes con retraso mental y otros trastornos psiquiátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56095^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8777^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12055^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29494^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
