<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-77674</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-258X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ying-Yang (YY-1) expression and Fas in biopsies of children with type IV lupus nephritis correlates with the clinical condition</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: It has been demonstrated that Fasmediated apoptosis participates in the physiopathology of lupus nephritis, although it is not clear whether it contributes to the development of the tissue damage. Since YY-1 down regulates Fas in cancer cell lines, it is reasonable to consider that this transcription factor may control Fas expression in lupus nephritis. The objective was to determine the correlation between YY-1 and Fas expression in renal biopsies from children with type IV lupus nephritis, and their association with the clinical condition of the patients. Material and methods: Eighteen biopsies from children with type IV lupus nephritis and 5 controls were studied. Fas and YY-1 expression were determined by immunochemistry and quantified by densytometric analysis. The clinical conditions at the moment the biopsy were obtained from the clinical records and the results were analyzed through a one-way ANOVA with p &lt; 0.005. Results: The results of the densytometric analysis showed an inverse relationship between YY-1 and Fas expression. YY-1 was grouped according to the intensity of expression in low, moderate and high and compared with the expression of Fas. The lupus nephritis biopsies, which revealed high expression of YY-1, corresponded to patients with less number of clinical complications, better outcome and fewer alterations on renal function. In contrast, low expression of YY-1 correlated with high Fas expression and worst clinical conditions. Conclusions: The present study suggests that YY-1 regulates Fas expression in lupus nephritis and that it is associated with the clinical outcome of the patients, although further studies are necessary to determine weather it factor may serve as a prognosis factor. This is the first evidence of YY-1 participation in the physiopathology of lupus nephritis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Huerta-Yepez, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Arellano, Berenice</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Solís Vallejo, Eunice</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Bonilla, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Márquez-Marín, Ruben</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Matamoros-Tapia, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes: La apoptosis mediada por Fas participa en la fisiopatología de la nefritis lúpica. Debido a que YY-1 regula negativamente el Fas en líneas celulares de cáncer, es razonable considerar que este factor de transcripción pueda controlar la expresión de Fas en la nefritis lúpica. El objetivo es determinar la correlación de la expresión de YY-1 y Fas en biopsias de niños con nefritis lúpica de tipo IV y su asociación con la condición clínica de los pacientes. Material y métodos: Se estudiaron 18 biopsias de niños con nefritis lúpica de tipo IV y 5 controles. La expresión de Fas y YY-1 se determinó mediante inmunohistoquímica y se cuantificó mediante análisis densitométrico. Se obtuvo información sobre el estado clínico de los pacientes en el momento de la biopsia a partir de los expedientes, y los resultados se analizaron mediante ANOVA de una vía. Se consideró significativo un valor p &lt; 0,005. Resultados: Los resultados del análisis densitométrico muestran una relación inversa entre la expresión de YY- 1 y Fas. Se agrupó YY-1, de acuerdo con la intensidad de su expresión, en baja, moderada y alta para poder compararla con la expresión de Fas. Las biopsias de nefritis lúpica que mostraron alta expresión de YY-1 correspondieron a pacientes con menor número de complicaciones clínicas, mejor desenlace y menor número de alteraciones en la función renal. En contraste, la expresión de YY-1 baja se correlacionó con alta expresión de Fas y peores condiciones clínicas. Conclusiones: En conclusión, el presente estudio indica que YY-1 regula la expresión de Fas en la nefritis lúpica y que se encuentra asociada con el desenlace clínico de los pacientes, si bien son necesarios más estudios para determinar si puede servir como marcador pronóstico. Hasta donde sabemos, ésta es la primera evidencia de que YY-1 participa en la fisiopatología de la nefritis lúpica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Reumatol. clín. (Barc.);3(3): 117-125, mayo-jun. 2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-77674</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La expresión de Yin-Yang-1 (YY-1) y Fas en las biopsias de niños con nefritis lúpica tipo IV se correlaciona con la condición clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19233^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32837^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1731^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50989^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
