<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115497</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intervention for smoking cessation in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in 6 municipal health care centers in Santiago de Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Between 30-70% of patients with COPD caused by tobacco consume remain smoking despite medical advice. In these cases the only measure that can prevent deterioration of pulmonary function and to prolong life is to stop tobacco use. Here are the results of a pilot project done in 2012 by professionals of the COPD control program of six Primary Health Care Centers (PHCC). The strategy was to identify patients, who smoke, provide intensive treatment though counseling and medications. The patients that entered the study, were previously diagnosed COPD clinically and/or by spirometry and were excluded those with unstable medical or psychological conditions and/or current use of alcohol. Six counseling sessions were planned. Drugs were administered to those who smoked &gt;= 10 cigarettes daily. At three PHCCs Varenicline 2 mg was used daily. At three other PHCCs Bupropion 300mg plus Nicotine Gum 4 mg were used daily. The duration of treatment was 3 months. 50 patients average 58.8 years of age range 37-80, 60% being female. Patients showed high degree of addiction 47.7% smoked &gt;= 20 cpd and 64% did so within 30 min after awakening. Average therapy sessions were 8.9 and side effects were 34%, severe in 6%. 3 patients discontinued treatment due to intolerance. 19 patients quit smoking after 6 months (38%). Conclusions. COPD patients are characterized by high degree of addiction. Intensive treatment with medication and psychosocial therapy performed in PCCs by the same professionals whom perform routine check-ups can achieve acceptable results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villena, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salazar, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponce, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urdinola, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Terán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pozo, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Véjar, L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre un 30 y un 70% de los pacientes con EPOC determinado por tabaquismo continúan fumando a pesar del consejo médico. En estos casos la única medida que puede impedir el deterioro de la función pulmonar y alargar la vida es detener el consumo de tabaco. En este artículo se comunican los resultados de un Proyecto Piloto realizado durante 2012 por los profesionales del programa EPOC de 6 consultorios de Atención Primaria de Salud (APS). Se identificaron los pacientes fumadores y se ofreció consejería intensiva y medicamentos a los que fumaban &gt;=10 cigarrillos día. Ingresaron a estudio pacientes con diagnóstico clínico y/o espirométrico de EPOC y se excluyeron aquellos con condiciones médicas o psicológicas inestables y/o consumo actual de alcohol. En 3 centros se usó vareniclina 2 mg/día y en 3 bupropión 300 mg/día más chicle de nicotina de 4 mg. Duración del tratamiento: 3 meses. Ingresaron a terapia 50 pacientes. Edad promedio 58,8, rango 37- 80, sexo femenino 60%. Los pacientes mostraron alto grado de adicción, 47,7% fumaban &gt;=20 cpd y 64% lo hacían antes de 30 min luego de despertar. El promedio de sesiones de terapia fueron de 8,9. Los efectos secundarios de los fármacos se presentaron leves en 17 pacientes (34%) e intensos en 3 (6%), determinando la suspensión del tratamiento. El coste de fármacos por paciente tratado fue de US$ 138. Dejaron de fumar a los 6 meses 19 pacientes (38%). Conclusiones. El paciente con EPOC se caracteriza por alto grado de adicción. El tratamiento intensivo con terapia psicosocial y medicamento realizado en consultorio por los mismos profesionales que los controlan puede obtener resultados aceptables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;15(3): 101-105, jul.-sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115497</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención para cesación tabáquica en pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica en 6 Centros de Salud</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29815^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30220^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9723^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
