<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160680</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-8691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Keeping the focus in mind: focusing in daily clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In this article we pay homage to Eulàlia Torras de Beà, summarizing the presentations that were in the conference held as a tribute to her. The presentations covered a wide spectrum in terms of their content and complementarity: the approach within the public mental health system that has been forced to adapt to increased demand and to the socio-economic precariousness of families and of social safety net systems, the utility of focusing on individual or family interviews for diagnosis, the relationship amongst the patient, his or her family and the therapist to create the focus of treatment and the use of targeting in the treatment of groups (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sala, Jordi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diego, Sergi de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Miró, M Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montaner , Albert</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palau, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En este artículo rendimos homenaje a Eulàlia Torras de Beà, resumiendo las ponencias desarrolladas en su jornada-homenaje. Las ponencias se centraron en la focalización en la clínica infanto-juvenil, aunque abarcaron un amplio espectro, en cuanto a contenidos y complementariedad: un abordaje en la red pública adaptado al incremento de la demanda y precariedad socioeconómica de las familias y sistemas de protección social, la utilidad de la focalización en la entrevista individual o familiar en el diagnóstico, la relación paciente, familia y terapeuta en la construcción del foco y un uso de la focalización en el tratamiento grupal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicopatol. salud ment. niño adolesc;(28): 83-89, nov. 2016.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160680</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Teniendo en mente el foco: la focalización en la clínica diaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12012^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11798</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55387^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11797</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55378</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33540</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
