<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104156</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Characterisation of a CTX-M-15-producing Shigella sonnei in a Spanish patient who had not travelled abroad</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">One hundred and seven Shigella spp. strains were isolated in our laboratory during the years 2000 to2010. One Shigella sonnei harboured the genes that coded the  -lactamases TEM-1 and CTX-M-15, identifying the structure, ISEcp1 + blaCTX-M-15 + orf477, in their genetic environment. The strain also carrieda class 2 integron with the gene cassettes dfrA1 + sat + aadA1. A plasmid group IncI1 ST31 (CC-31)was detected and its mobilization by conjugation was demonstrated. We describe for the (..)  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sáenz, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Seral, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gude, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo-Bezares, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, F. Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">De las 107 Shigella spp. aisladas entre 2000-2010, en una cepa de Shigella sonnei se detectaron los genes codificantes de TEM-1 y CTX-M-15, identificándose la estructura ISEcp1+blaCTX-M-15+orf477. La cepa portaba un integrón de clase 2 con los genes cassettes dfrA1+sat+aadA1. Se detectó un plásmido del grupo IncI1 ST31 (CC-31) demostrando su transferencia por conjugación. Describimos la primera cepa de S. sonnei en nuestra comunidad productora de CTX-M-15 perteneciente a un paciente español que no había viajado al extranjero (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;30(8): 469-471, oct. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104156</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Caracterización de Shigella sonnei portadora de CTX-M-15 en un paciente español sin antecedentes de viaje al extranjero</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4468^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5346^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13142^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11391^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37651^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201210</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
