<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129945</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: We report a case of primary vaginal lymphoma. The clinical presentation was an episode of dysuria and acute urinary retention. We performed a bibliographic review. Methods: Thirty-six year-old patient who consulted in the urology clinic for hesitancy that triggered an episode of acute urinary retention. Physical examination revealed thickening of the vaginal wall. Biopsy was performed and diagnosis of diffuse large B-cell primary vaginal non-Hodgkin&#146;s lymphoma was obtained. Results: Primary lymphomas of the female genital tract are rare. The third most frequent location is vagina. The most common manifestation is vaginal bleeding. Urinary symptoms are rarely the first sign. Diagnosis requires a biopsy. The first choice for treatment is Rituximab- CHOP immuno-chemotherapy. Conclusions: Vaginal lymphoma is a rare disease. Unfrequently, the first clinical manifestations are urinary tract symptoms, and even less acute urinary retention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bejarano Lasunción, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomera Bernal, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Capapé Paves, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Arbej, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso García-Magariño, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Calero, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Aportamos un caso de un linfoma vaginal primario cuya primera manifestación fue un episo-dio de disuria y retención aguda de orina, con revisión bibliográfica. Métodos: Paciente, 36 años. Consulta en urología por disuria inicial que desencadena un episodio de retención aguda de orina. La exploración muestra engrosamiento de la pared vaginal. Se biopsia obteniendo el diagnóstico de linfoma no Hodgkin difuso de células grandes B vaginal primario. Resultados: Los linfomas primarios del tracto genital femenino son infrecuentes. La tercera localización en fre¬cuencia es la vagina. La manifestación más frecuente es el sangrado vaginal. Rara vez son los síntomas urinarios el primer signo. Su diagnóstico es por anatomía patológica. El tratamiento de elección es la poliquimioterapia según el protocolo Rituximab-CHOP. Conclusiones: El Linfoma vaginal es una patología infrecuente. Es raro que la primera manifestación sean sín¬tomas urológicos, más todavía que se presente en forma de retención urinaria aguda (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;67(9): 775-779, nov. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129945</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Disuria y retención aguda de orinacomo primera manifestación de un linfoma vaginal primario. Aportación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29144^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52157^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29271^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19237^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15027^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
