<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138755</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of neurologic function and complications in a retrospective cohort of patients with acute spinal cord injury due to trauma treated with large-dose methylprednisolone</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: Methylprednisolone was used to improve neurologic recovery from spinal cord injury in the National Acute Spinal Cord Injury Studies (NASCIS). Debate over this use led to further research and a 2002 report stating that there was insufficient evidence to support this application as a standard therapy. Our aim was to retrospectively assess this application in a cohort of patients with spinal cord injury. METHODS: Retrospective cohort study of patients admitted to the intensive care unit (ICU) between 1997 and 2007 with a diagnosis of spinal cord injury due to trauma. The patients were grouped according to medical treatment received into a methylprednisolone group and a no-methylprednisolone group. We assessed change in neurologic function on the impairment scale of the American Spinal Injury Association on ICU admission and on discharge. We also recorded medical complications in each group. Cox multiple regression analysis was used to analyze differences between treatments. RESULTS: No significant differences were detected in neurologic outcome on discharge from the ICU (odds ratio [OR], 1.57; 95% confidence interval [CI], 0.69-3.54). The methylprednisolone-treated patients had more medical complications such as hyperglycemia (OR, 5.67; 95% CI, 1.85-17.31) or gastrointestinal bleeding (OR, 19.16; 95% CI, 1.64-223.30) than the patients who did not receive methylprednisolone. CONCLUSIONS: In this retrospective study, methylprednisolone was unrelated to improvement in neurologic outcome after acute spinal cord injury on ICU discharge although the patients treated with this drug were at greater risk of metabolic complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peyró García, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aomar Millán, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortiñas Sáenz, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gerónimo Pardo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Tapia, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calatayud Pérez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: El uso de metilprednisolona para el tratamiento de lesiones traumáticas de médula espinal se utilizó para mejorar la recuperación neurológica en The National Acute Spinal Corel Injury Studies-NASClS. La controversia sobre este protocolo, llevó a investigaciones posteriores y un informe de 2002, lo considera de una evidencia insuficiente para ser considerado un estándar de tratamiento. Nuestro objetivo fue valorar retrospectivamente su aplicación en una cohorte de pacientes con trauma medular. Métodos: Estudio retrospectivo de una cohorte de pacientes ingresados en una unidad de críticos entre 1997-2007 con diagnóstico de lesión de médula espinal traumática. Los pacientes fueron agrupados de acuerdo con el tratamiento médico recibido (grupo metilprednisolona frente a grupo no-metilprednisolona). Se evaluó la variación de la función neurológica mediante la escala ASIA al ingreso y alta, así como la aparición de complicaciones médicas en función del tratamiento con o sin metilprednisobna. Se realizó estudio estadístico mediante regresión múltiple de Cox para el tratamiento o no con el fármaco. Resultados: No hubo diferencias entre grupos de tratamiento en la evolución neurológica al alta de la unidad de cuidados críticos (OR = 1,57, IC 95%: 0,69 a 3,54). El grupo metilprednisolona presentó un aumento de complicaciones médicas como hiperglucemia (OR = 5,67, IC 95%: 1,85-17,31) y hemorragia gastrointestinal (OR = 19,16, IC 95%: 1,64-223,30) en comparación con el grupo no tratado con metalprednisolona. Conclusiones: En este estudio retrospectivo, el uso de metilprednisolona en pacientes con lesión aguda de la médula espinal no se asocia con una mejoría en el resultado de la función neurológica al alta en la unidad de críticos y un mayor riesgo de complicaciones metabólicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;58(10): 583-588, dic. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la lesión neurológica y complicaciones médicas en una cohorte histórica de pacientes con lesión medular aguda traumática  tras tratamiento con megadosis de metilprednisolona</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28621</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22562^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13499^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13502^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
