<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85332</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Children Exposed to Intimate Partner Violence: Towards a Research Based Clinical Intervention</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Abstract. Some 188.000 children (both, little boys and girls) are estimated to be exposed to partner violence in Spain. Research shows evidence for these children showing short and long term emotional and behavioural difficulties, along with trauma symptoms, associated to woman battering &#150;the violence occurring whether during their living together or in the  aftermath of break up. High rates of child physical, emotional, and sexual maltreatment are also documented. Main conclusions from the literature in English are summarised about consequences for children, battering fathers, and battered mothers. From this research evidence, a clinical framework is suggested. Also, a discussion about the status of children  exposed to this violence as secondary or indirect victims is presented along with the need for further statistics and interventions in Spain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Atenciano Jiménez, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Resumen. Se ha estimado en 188.000 la cifra de niñas y niños expuestos a violencia contra la pareja en España. Las investigaciones indican que esta población presenta a corto y largo plazo dificultades emocionales y conductuales, y síntomas de trauma, asociados a los malos tratos contra sus madres, ejercidos durante la relación de pareja y tras la finalización de la misma. Además, un porcentaje elevado de estos menores sufren también maltrato físico, psicológico y sexual. Se presentan las principales conclusiones, basadas en la investigación científica en lengua inglesa, acerca de las consecuencias de la exposición en los menores,  de los maltratadores como padres, y de las mujeres maltratadas como madres. A partir de la evidencia existente sobre esta población, se plantea un marco para la intervención clínica, y se discute su estatus de víctimas secundarias/indirectas, la necesidad de estadísticas e intervenciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;20(3): 261-272, nov. 2009.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Menores Expuestos a Violencia contra la Pareja: Notas para una Práctica Clínica Basada en la Evidencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2696^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33150</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31499^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33199^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200911</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
