<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038733</identifier>
<setSpec>0009-739X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prophylaxis of sternal dehiscence in obese patients through systematic application of robicsek closure</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Sternal deshidence is a relatively frequent complication in median sternotomy and causes high morbidity and mortality in cardiothoracic surgery. Obesity is one of the most important risk factors for sternal infection and deshidence and its prevalence is increasingly frequent in patients undergoing cardiac surgery. The aim of the present study was to assess the clinical benefit of the prophylactic use of robicsek sternal reinforcement in high-risk patients undergoing cardiac surgery. Patient and method. Two hundred ninety ninety consecutive patients who underwent median sternotomy in our center were analysed. The indications for prophylactic sternal reinforcement were severe sternal osteoporosis or a body mass indez (BMI) of &gt;= 30. The technique was used in 105 patients, 54 men and 51 women, with a mean age of 67.7 +/- 9.1 years and a mean BMI of 31.8+/-4.1. Results. None of the patients in the reinforcement group developed non-infectious dehiscence; only one patient (1.7%) in this group showed sternal dehiscence due to osteomyelitis with good response to surgical debridement and intravenous antibiotics. Conclusion. Robicsek reinforcement reduces the incidence of sternal dehiscence in high-risk patients and its prophylactic use should be considered in patients with severe osteoporosis or a BMI of &gt;=30 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paredes-Astillero, Isidro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Serrano-Martínez, Félix</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Crespo, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Fariña, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bustos-Molina, Filadelfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lima-Cañadas, Pedro Pablo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cañas-Cañas, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calleja-Hernández, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Almodóvar, Luis Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porro-Hernández, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz-Martínez, Manuel José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La dehiscencia esternal es una complicación relativamente frecuente de la esternotomía media y que causa gran morbimortalidad en cirugía cardiotorácica. La obesidad se considera uno de los factores de riesgo más importantes de dehiscencia e infección esternal, y su prevalencia cada vez mayor en la población sometida a cirugía cardíaca. En el presente estudio se evalúa el beneficio clínico del uso profiláctico del refuerzo esternal de tipo Robicsek en los pacientes de alto riesgo que son intervenidos de cirugía cardíaca mayor. Pacientes y método. Se analiza a 290 pacientes consecutivos intervenidos mediante esternotomía media en nuestro centro. La indicación de refuerzo profiláctico esternal se estableció en casos de osteoporosis esternal severa o índice de masa corporal (IMC) &gt;= 30, empleándose la técnica en 105 pacientes, 54 varones y 51 mujeres, cuya edad media era de 67,7 ± 9,1 años y con un IMC medio de 31,8 ± 4,1. Resultados. No hubo dehiscencias no infecciosas en el grupo con refuerzo de tipo Robicsek; sólo se produjo un caso (1,7%) de dehiscencia esternal debida a osteomielitis en el grupo reforzado, con buena respuesta a desbridamiento quirúrgico asociado con antibioterapia por vía intravenosa. Conclusión. El refuerzo de tipo Robicsek reduce la incidencia de dehiscencia esternal en los pacientes de alto riesgo y su indicación profiláctica debe ser considerada en casos de osteroporosis severa o IMC &gt;= 30 (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. Esp. (Ed. impr.);78(2): 100-102, ago. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038733</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Profilaxis de la dehiscencia esternal en obesos mediante la aplicación sistemática del cerclaje de tipo Robicsek</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10205^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6500^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13911^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29193</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13635^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
