<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165893</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-9356</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cerebrospinal fluid cutaneous fistula following obstetric epidural analgaesia. Case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cutaneous fistula of cerebrospinal fluid is a rare complication of neuroaxial blockade. We report the case of a parturient in whom an epidural catheter was placed for labour analgesia and 12h after the catheter was removed, presented an abundant asymptomatic fluid leak from the puncture site, compatible in the cyto-chemical analysis with cerebrospinal fluid. She was treated with acetazolamide, compression of skin orifice of the fluid leakage, antibiotic prophylaxis, hydration and rest, and progressed satisfactorily without requiring blood patch (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fedriani de Matos, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Cortés, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintero Salvago, AV</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La fístula cutánea de líquido cefalorraquídeo es una rara complicación de los bloqueos neuroaxiales. Presentamos el caso de una gestante a la que se le colocó un catéter epidural para analgesia de trabajo de parto y que 12h tras la retirada del catéter presentó abundante pérdida asintomática de líquido por la zona de punción, compatible en el análisis citoquímico con líquido cefalorraquídeo. Fue tratada con acetazolamida, compresión del orificio cutáneo de salida de líquido, profilaxis antibiótica, hidratación y reposo, evolucionando de forma satisfactoria sin ameritar parche hemático (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Anestesiol Reanim;64(8): 476-478, oct. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165893</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fístula cutánea de líquido cefalorraquídeo posterior a analgesia epidural obstétrica. A propósito de un caso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d91^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27923^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2594^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31533^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28857^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22234^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
