<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049495</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Personality and pain tolerance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper examine the relationship between a number of personality variables -EPQ-A (Eysenck &amp; Eysenck, 1975), NEO-PI (McCrae and Costa, 1988), STA (Schizotypal personality) and STA (borderline personality, Claridge &amp; Brooks, 1984), with tolerance to experimental pain induced by cold water -cold pressor test, according to the procedure by Staats, Heckmant and Staats (1998). The sample had been previously screened by means of a questionnaire assessing chronic pain, headache, back pain, arthritis, Raynaud syndrome and patients taking medication. Three measures of tolerance to experimentally-induced pain were taken: pain threshold -seconds elapsed from hand immersion in water until first report of pain, pain keeping- seconds elapsed from the onset of pain threshold till hand withdrawal. Correlation, factor analysis and stepwise regression analysis showed a cross effect between anxiety measures -negative pain tolerance, and psychoticism. Along with emotional control, psychoticism was predictor of positive pain tolerance. Paranoid and hardness components of psychoticism seemed to be responsible for a mitigated pain perception</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Collado, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojo, Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrillo, Jesús María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se examina la relación de algunas variables de personalidad -EPQ-A (Eysenck y Eysenck, 1975), NEO-PI (McCrae y Costa, 1988) y STA -personalidad esquizotípica- y STB -personalidad límite-, de Claridge y Broks (1984), con la tolerancia al dolor experimental inducido mediante agua fría (cold pressor test), según el procedimiento de Staats, Heckmat y Staats (1998) en una muestra filtrada mediante un cuestionario sobre dolor crónico, dolores de cabeza, de espalda, artritis, síndrome de Raynaud, y personas bajo medicación. La tolerancia al dolor experimental se evaluó mediante el Umbral de dolor (tiempo en segundos desde la introducción de la mano en el agua hasta el primer informe de dolor). Mantenimiento del dolor (duración en segundos de la inmersión de la mano desde la aparición del umbral hasta su retirada) y Tolerancia al dolor (duración total en segundos de la inmersión de la mano desde su introducción hasta su retirada). Un análisis correlacional, factorial y de regresión por pasos mostraron un efecto cruzado entre medidas de ansiedad (tolerancia negativa al dolor) y psicoticismo, siendo psicoticismo junto con control emocional predictores de tolerancia positiva al dolor. En cuanto a psicoticismo, parece que son sus elementos de naturaleza paranoide y de dureza los que afectan a una percepción atenuada del dolor</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;16(3): 223-236, sept. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049495</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Personalidad y tolerancia al dolor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9686</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30624^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10746^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
