<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042807</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">An evaluation of costs in nephrology by means of analytical accounting system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The analytical accounting is a countable technique directed to theevaluation, by means of pre-established criteria of distribution, of the internal economyof the hospital, in order to know the effectiveness and efficiency of Clinical Units. The aim of this study was to analyze the activity and costs of the Nephrology Departmentof General Hospital of Castellón.Methods: Activity of Hospitalization and Ambulatory Care, during 2003 wasanalysed. Hospitalization discharges were grouped in DGR and the costs per DGRwere determinated.Results: Total costs Hospitalisation and Ambulatory Care were 560.434,9 and146.317,8 Euros, respectively. And the costs of one stay, one first outpatient visit andmaintenance visit were 200, 63, and 31,6 Euros, respectively. Eighty per cent of thedischarges were grouped in 9 DGR and DRG number 316 (Renal Failure) represented30% of the total productivity. Costs of DGR 316 were 3.178,2 Euros and 16%represented laboratory cost and costs of diagnostic or therapeutic procedures.Conclusion: With introduction of analytical accounting and DGR system, theNephrology Departments can acquire more full information on the results and costsof treatment. These techniques permits to improve the financial and economic performance</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calvo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Jaras, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pérez, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La contabilidad analítica es una técnica contable dirigida a la evaluación directa,mediante criterios de reparto preestablecidos, de los hechos económicos internos delhospital, con objeto de conocer los costes y productos de cada uno de los Servicios.El objetivo de este estudio es analizar el coste de los principales productos intermediosy finales elaborados por el Servicio de Nefrología del Hospital General deCastellón, utilizando esta herramienta contable.Se ha analizado la estructura de costes de los Centros de Actividad de Hospitalización(CAH) y Consulta Externa (CACEX). Para ello se han definido tres productosintermedios: Estancia, Primera Visita y Visita Sucesiva, y los productos finales(GRDs) elaborados por el Servicio. La metodología aplicada en los productos finaleses la asignación de costes en función del peso relativo de cada GRD (método «topdown») y posteriormente se añadieron los costes de las distintas exploraciones diagnósticaso terapéuticas realizadas.El coste total del CAH fue de 560.434,9 &#128; y del CACEX de 176.317,8 &#128;. El costede los productos intermedios Estancia, Primera Visita y Visita Sucesiva fueron de200,01, 63,26 y 31,63 &#128;, respectivamente. El 80% de los 232 de episodios de hospitalizaciónse agrupó en 9 GRDs. El GRD más frecuente fue el 316 (InsuficienciaRenal), que representó el 30% de la casuística del Servicio. Su coste ascendió a3.178,2 &#128; y el 16% de este correspondió a las exploraciones diagnósticas y terapéuticas.Podemos concluir que la implantación y desarrollo de la contabilidad analíticaes una necesidad en los Servicios de Nefrología. Esto nos permitirá conocer la estructurade costes de los Servicios, la complejidad de la casuística y por tanto la adecuadaplanificación de los recursos necesarios para atenderla</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;25(5): 543-549, sept.-oct. 2005. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042807</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de costes en un servicio de nefrología mediante la contabilidad analítica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6905^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6925^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10222^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30327</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d70</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3376^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9591^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6905^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6925^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
