<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148011</identifier>
<setSpec>1989-7790</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evolution of ischemic cardiopathy impact on spanish workers on their return to work</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Ischemic cardiopathy is one of the main causes of morbidity and mortality in developed countries. It affects the patients quality of life and interferes with their return to work, thus generating a significant economic cost. The aim of our study is to assess labor conditions of patients who suffered an acute myocardial infarction (AMI), highlighting the factors that could have an impact on their return-to-work time. Materials and methods: Observational retrospective study with patients under 65 years old who suffered an AMI between January 2000 and May 2011. Data concerning clinical, social, demographic and labor circumstances was collected to better understand its relation with the return to work.  Results: A total of 5.067 patients with Coronary Heart Disease (hereinafter referred to as CHD) were selected. 94% of the samples were men, under 54.3 years old. 3679 out of 5067 patients (72. 6%) returned to work after a heart infarct whereas 1261 (24.9%) did not return, obtaining the permanent incapacity to work. Among the clinical and patient factors, the main determinants were age (mostly &lt;50 years), severity of AMI, poor left ventricular function (EF &gt;50% / EF &gt;50%) and revascularization procedures (percutaneous coronary interventions &#150;PCI&#150; and coronary artery bypass graft surgery, CABG). Regarding the economic and job-related factors three variables were found to be the strongest predictors of returning to work: job demands (physically demanding jobs vs. intellectually demanding jobs), incomes and job conditions (self-employment vs. employees). There were no significant differences on the returning-to-work rate between men or women or between sick leave due to an acute coronary syndrome or due to an angina.  We observed that the return-to-work activity increased gradually from 2000-2011 (from rates of 60% in 2000-2002 to over 80% in 2010). This increase is present in all occupational activities as well as in all age ranges.  Conclusion: In our study we observed a gradual increase of patients returning to work in recent years. The variables used to better predict the return-to-work time in a period of sick leave after a CHD episode are categorized as follows: clinic viable like the extent of myocardial damage (LVEF &lt;50%/LVEF &gt;50%) and the revascularization procedures (Percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) or coronary artery bypass graft surgery, CABG), socioeconomic variables related to the kind of job (self-employment vs. employees) and lastly labor conditions like job demands (physical-demanding jobs vs. intellectual-demanding jobs) or age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Inchausti Sánchez, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Bardisa, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Toledo Hervás, Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Muñoz, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramos Ramos, Charo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González López, María Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Ramirez, César</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La cardiopatía isquémica es una de las principales causas de morbimortalidad en los países desarrollados dificultando la vuelta al trabajo de estos pacientes. Pretendemos estudiar la evolución de la incapacidad Temporal y Permanente en trabajadores españoles que causan baja por cardiopatía isquémica, así como analizar las variables que influyen en la reincorporación laboral.  Material y métodos: Estudio observacional retrospectivo de cohortes con pacientes menores 65 años que sufrieron un infarto agudo de miocardio (IAM) entre Enero de 2000 y mayo de 2011. Se recogieron datos clínicos, demográficos, socioeconómicos y laborales para analizar su relación con la reincorporación laboral.  Resultados: Se seleccionaron un total de 5067 pacientes, el 94% varones, y con una edad media de 54,3 años. Un total de 3.679 pacientes (72,6%) se reincorporaron a su actividad laboral tras el infarto, mientras que 1261 (24,9%) obtuvieron la incapacidad laboral permanente. La mayores tasas de incapacidad laboral se observan en los pacientes &gt; 50 años, en los que han sufrido un mayor daño cardiaco (FEVI &lt; 50%), en aquellos con un mayor número de arterias coronarias obstruidas y los que fueron revascularizados mediante cirugía. En cuanto a las variables socioeconómicas se reincorporan menos los trabajadores con salarios más bajos, los trabajadores por cuenta ajena y los que realizan trabajos en los que predomina la carga física y manual frente a las profesiones en que predomina el trabajo intelectual. No encontramos diferencias con respecto a la tasa de reincorporación entre hombres y mujeres o en función del diagnóstico que motivó la baja (síndrome coronario agudo vs. angina).  Observamos que la tasa de reincorporación laboral se ha incrementado de forma progresiva en la última década. (Desde tasas de reincorporación del 60% en el 2000-2002 a tasas superiores al 80% a partir de 2010) Este incremento se observa en todos los sectores ocupacionales como en todos los tramos etarios en los que se distribuye la muestra  Conclusiones: En nuestro estudio se observa un aumento progresivo en los últimos años en el porcentaje de pacientes que se reincorporan al trabajo. Las variables que mejor predicen la reincorporación laboral tras sufrir una baja por cardiopatía isquémica son viables clínicas como la extensión del daño miocárdico (FEVI &lt;50%/FEVI &gt;50%) y el procedimiento de revascularización empleado (percutáneo/cirugía) así como las variables socioeconómicas referentes al tipo de trabajo (autónomo/cuenta ajena), ocupación profesional (carga física/carga intelectual) y la edad del trabajador (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. segur. trab;61(240): 325-341, jul.-sept. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148011</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evolución del impacto de la cardiopatía isquémica en la reincorporación laboral de trabajadores españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9395^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9971^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32027^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30650^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55127^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
