<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-050826</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-9672</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Working place adaptations due to health reasons in the justice department of generalitat de Catalunya (Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The experience of the Occupational Health Service in the Justice Department of the Generalitat de Catalunya (Catalonian        autonomous government) regarding workplace accommodations is described. Between November 1999 and May 2004, a total of        194 workplace accommodations were requested, of which 184 (95%) were considered. The frequency of accommodations, with        respect to a total of 11,974 workers, was 1.5%. Subsequent evaluation of 24 accommodations showed that the recommended        accommodations were implemented in 96% of these cases. Results from this evaluation suggest that workplace accommodations        reduced occupational incapacity and increased subsequent return to work</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Bayarri, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabello Monge, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Fernández, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribó Ferrer, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se describe la experiencia del Servicio de Prevención del Departamento de Justicia de la Generalitat de Cataluña en        relación con las adaptaciones de puesto de trabajo. Durante el periodo de estudio (Noviembre 99 - Mayo 04) se solicitaron        194 adaptaciones de puestos de trabajo por motivos de salud, de las cuales 184 (95%) fueron consideradas. La frecuencia de        adaptaciones realizadas sobre el total de los 11.974 trabajadores en plantilla fue del 1,5%. En una posterior evaluación de 24        casos en los que se recomendaron adaptaciones de las condiciones de trabajo, se observó que en 23 casos se habían adoptado        las medidas preventivas recomendadas, produciéndose en estos trabajadores la reducción de incapacidades temporales y la        facilitación de la reincorporación laboral</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. prev. riesgos labor. (Ed. impr.);9(3): 114-116, jul.-sept. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-050826</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación de las condiciones de trabajo por motivos de salud de los trabajadores: la experiencia en el departamento de justicia de la Generalitat de Catalunya</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30459^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16902^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
