<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100598</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The link between intra-abdominal pressure in peritoneal dialysis and hernias and fugues</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Normal intra-abdominal pressure is equal to atmospheric pressure (zero). In peritoneal dialysis the introduction of intra-peritoneal liquid increases intra-abdominal pressure. In various studies it is recommended that this does not exceed 16-20cm H2O. In addition to possible abdominal discomfort, high intra-abdominal pressure can be linked to problems with the abdominal wall, such as hernias and fugues, and have implications for peritoneal transport and ultrafiltration deficit. The aims of this study were the following: to find out the intra-abdominal pressure levels in the prevalent type of patients in peritoneal dialysis, to assess the factors influencing the values for this pressure and to study the relationship between intra-abdominal pressure and the development of hernias and fugues, retrospectively. A transversal, observational and retrospective study was conducted to measure intra-abdominal pressure in the prevalent, stable patients who had been on peritoneal dialysis for more than three months. Intra-abdominal pressure was measured using the method described by Durand: patient in a supine position, with diurnal peritoneal volume. The final intra-abdominal pressure is the average of the measurements taken during inspiration and expiration, is expressed in cm H2O and the volume drained is specified. Measurements were also taken in sitting and standing positions. 34 patients were studied, 66% of them male, with an average age of 61.2±14 years, 3 with polycystic kidney disease, an average Charlson comorbidity index of 7.9, an average body mass index of 27.4±4.2 and an average of 21±12 months on PD. Average diurnal volume was 1796±385 mL and nocturnal 2100±254 mL. 32% of the patients had a history of abdominal surgery and 5% of hernias, remedied before the start of peritoneal dialysis. The average intra-abdominal pressure lying down was 17.5±4.1cm H2O, with an average volume by body surface of 1141±253ml/m2. 23.5 % had an intra-abdominal pressure of over 20cm H2O. In a sitting position the average was 28±5.5cm H2O and standing up it was 43.7±5.3cm H2O. Patients with an intra-abdominal pressure of &gt; 20cm H2O had a higher percentage of hernias (50% vs 12%) and pericatheter fugues (37% vs. 12%). As the principal conclusions, we would stress that the intra-abdominal pressure levels in our patients were rather higher than in other series. The greater the age, comorbidity and major body mass index, the higher the intra-abdominal pressure. Patients with high intra-abdominal pressure have more episodes of hernias and fugues (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blasco Cabañas, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marquina Parra, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gran Pueyo, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Mejía, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Otero López, Sol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ponz Clemente, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Betancourt Castellanos, Loreley</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La presión intrabdominal normal es igual a la atmosférica (cero). En Diálisis Peritoneal con la introducción del líquido intraperitoneal, la presión intrabdominal aumenta. En varios estudios se aconseja que esta no supere los 16-20 cm. H2O. Además de las posibles molestias abdominales, una presión intrabdominal elevada puede tener relación con los problemas de la pared abdominal, como hernias y fugas y tener implicaciones en el transporte peritoneal y el déficit de ultrafiltración. Los objetivos del presente trabajo fueron: conocer los niveles de presión intrabdominal de los enfermos prevalentes en diálisis peritoneal, valorar los factores que influyen en llos valores de esta presión y estudiar retrospectivamente la relación entre presión intrabdominal y desarrollo de hernias y fugas. Realizamos un estudio transversal, observacional y retrospectivo de valoración de la presión intrabdominal en los enfermos prevalentes, estables, con más de tres meses en diálisis peritoneal. La presión intrabdominal se midió mediante el método descrito por Durand: paciente en decúbito supino, con el volumen peritoneal diurno. La presión intrabdominal final es la media entre las mediciones realizadas durante la inspiración y la espiración, se expresa en cm. de H2O, y se especifica el volumen drenado. También se realizó una medida en sedestación y en bipedestación. Se estudiaron 34 pacientes, 66% varones, edad media de 61.2±14 años, 3 con poliquistosis renal, un índice de comorbilidad de Charlson medio de 7,9, un índice de masa corporal medio de 27.4±4.2 y un tiempo medio en DP de 21±12 meses. El volumen medio diurno fue de 1796±385 mL y el nocturno de 2100±254 mL. Un 32% de los pacientes tenían antecedentes de cirugía abdominal y un 5% de hernias, reparadas antes del inicio de la diálisis peritoneal. La media de presión intrabdominal en decúbito fue de 17.5±4.1 cm. de H2O, y un volumen medio por superficie corporal de 1141±253 ml/m2. Un 23.5 % tenían una presión intrabdominal mayor a 20 cm. de H2O. En sedestación la media fue de 28±5.5 cm. de H2O y en bipedestación de 43.7±5.3 cm. de H2O. Los enfermos con presión intrabdominal &gt; 20 cm. H2O tenían más porcentaje de hernias (50% vs 12 %) y fugas pericatéter (37 % vs. 12 %). Como principales conclusiones, podemos destacar que los niveles de presión intrabdominal de nuestros pacientes son algo más elevados que en otras series. A mayor edad, mayor comorbilidad y mayor índice de masa corporal, la presión intrabdominal es más elevada. Los enfermos con presión intrabdominal elevada presentaron más episodios de hernias y fugas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;15(2): 94-100, abr.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100598</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Relación entre la presión intrabdominal en diálisis peritoneal con las hernias y fugas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6706^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6706^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
