<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052829</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">A training program to improve the memory of children with Down&#146;s syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study starts out from the general agreement about the explicit memory deficits in children with Down&#146;s syndrome. Our aim is to explore the possibilities of the computer as a valuable instrument with which to train memory by teaching cognitive rehearsal strategies. The sample was made up of 40 students with Down&#146;s syndrome and was divided into two research groups: control and experimental. The results show a clear tendency towards memory improvement in the experimental group. These results can be considered indicators of the effectiveness of the intervention. They are also very interesting for education, in the sense that teachers can help the students with Down&#146;s syndrome to improve their memory capacity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Beltrán Llera, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Sánchez, Luz F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Pozuelo, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio parte del consenso generalizado de los déficit de memoria explícita en sujetos con síndrome de Down. En él nos hemos propuesto explorar las posibilidades del ordenador como instrumento significativo para el entrenamiento de la memoria a través de la enseñanza de estrategias cognitivas de tipo repetitivo. En la investigación se ha trabajado con dos muestras de personas con síndrome de Down participantes en un Programa de Nuevas Tecnologías con un total de 40 sujetos. Los resultados muestran una clara tendencia a la mejora en los sujetos del grupo experimental. Estos datos pueden interpretarse como indicadores de la eficacia de la intervención puesta en práctica. Los resultados tienen interés para la educación en el sentido de que los profesores pueden ayudar a los sujetos con síndrome de Down a mejorar su capacidad de memoria</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);18(3): 531-536, ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052829</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Un programa de entrenamiento para la mejora de los déficits de memoria en personas con Síndrome de Down</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8739^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30934^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
