<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-153300</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Management of pediatric central nervous system emergencies: a review for general radiologists</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Teaching objectives. To review the most common and most important diseases and disorders of the central nervous system (CNS) in pediatric emergencies, discussing the indications for different imaging tests in each context. Discussion. In pediatric patients, acute neurologic symptoms (seizures, deteriorating level of consciousness, focal neurologic deficits, etc.) can appear in diverse clinical situations (trauma, child abuse, meningoencephalitis, ischemia&#133;). It is important to decide on the most appropriate neuroimaging diagnostic algorithm for each situation and age group, as well as to know the signs of the most typical lesions that help us in the etiological differential diagnosis. Pediatric patients&#146; increased vulnerability to ionizing radiation and the possible need for sedation in studies that require more time are factors that should be taken into account when indicating an imaging test. It is essential to weigh the risks and benefits for the patient and to avoid unnecessary studies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rebollo Polo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos docentes. Revisar las urgencias pediátricas del sistema nervioso central más frecuentes y relevantes, valorando la indicación de pruebas de imagen en cada contexto. Discusión. La sintomatología neurológica aguda (convulsiones, deterioro del nivel de consciencia, focalidad neurológica, etc.) en el paciente pediátrico puede aparecer en una diversidad de situaciones clínicas (traumatismo, maltrato, meningoencefalitis, isquemia&#133;). Es importante decidir el algoritmo diagnóstico de neuroimagen más adecuado a cada situación y edad, así como conocer la semiología de las lesiones más típicas que nos ayudan en el diagnóstico diferencial etiológico. La mayor vulnerabilidad del paciente pediátrico a la radiación ionizante y la posible necesidad de sedación en los estudios de mayor duración son hechos a tener en cuenta al indicar una prueba de imagen, y siempre es necesario valorar el riesgo/beneficio y evitar la realización de estudios innecesarios (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);58(supl.2): 142-150, mayo 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-153300</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Manejo de los casos de urgencia del sistema nervioso central pediátricos para radiólogos generales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12309^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9615^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3971^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2700^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54668^s37748</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
