<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79358</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic goals in patients with refractory chronic angina</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Refractory angina presents a major clinical challenge for everyday medical practice. Despite the widespread use of statins and improvements in revascularization techniques, a substantial proportion of patients with preserved left ventricular function and no life-threatening arrhythmias remain symptomatic, with severe debilitating angina. Because the rate of major cardiac events in this population is relatively low, the major aim of therapy should be not only to prolong survival but also to improve quality of life. The cornerstone of therapy for all these patients should be the aggressive modification of risk factors using evidence-based treatment, with the aim of stabilizing the disease process and improving overall survival. No opportunity for revascularization should be overlooked. Complementary approaches should be implemented to raise the angina threshold by either reducing oxygen demand or improving hemodynamics to increase myocardial oxygen supply. This review provides an update on therapeutic techniques and goals, and reinforces the need for a multidisciplinary approach to the management of patients with refractory angina (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Scirica, Benjamin M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magnus Ohman, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cohen, Mauricio G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Mario</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La angina refractaria constituye un importante reto clínico para la medicina actual. A pesar del amplio uso de las estatinas y del perfeccionamiento de las técnicas de revascularización, una parte importante de los pacientes con una función ventricular izquierda preservada y sin arritmias con peligro para la vida continúan presentando síntomas, con una angina grave debilitante. Dado que las tasas de eventos cardiacos mayores en esa población son relativamente bajas, las metas principales del tratamiento deben ser no sólo la prolongación de la supervivencia, sino también la mejora de la calidad de vida. La modificación enérgica de los factores de riesgo mediante tratamientos basados en la evidencia, con objeto de estabilizar el proceso de la enfermedad y mejorar la supervivencia, debe constituir el tratamiento de base en todos estos pacientes. No deben pasarse por alto las posibilidades de revascularización. Deben aplicarse estrategias complementarias para elevar el umbral anginoso, ya sea mediante la reducción de la demanda de oxígeno, ya mediante la mejora de la hemodinámica para aumentar el aporte de oxígeno miocárdico. En esta revisión se presenta una actualización sobre las estrategias y las metas terapéuticas y se resalta la necesidad de un enfoque multidisciplinario del tratamiento de los pacientes con angina refractaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;63(5): 571-582, mayo 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79358</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metas terapéuticas en pacientes con angina refractaria crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50504^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d798^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9396^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201005</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
