<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94193</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Noise pollution in primary education public centres of Albacete</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to determine the on going noise level equivalent to the one experienced by a student in his or her daily activity in public primary schools of Albacete.Material and method: cross-sectional descriptive observational study in 11 public primary schools of Albacete. Dependent variable: ongoing noise level equal to that experienced by the student (Leq indBA). Independent variables: school and places in the school. The measurement shave been performed using type 2.226 Bruel &amp; Kjaer sound measurers with tripod. 95% Confidence intervals were calculated. Results: the average noise level equivalent to that in the classrooms of children between the age of three and five had a mean value of 75 dBA, for ages between six and seven it was 66 dBA and for ages between 8 and 11 it was 69 dBA. The sample distribution mean (ages between 3 and 11) was 70 dBA. The average noise level equivalent in the hallway at the end of the school day had a mean value of 71 dBA and 83 dBA in the playground during break.Conclusions: the equivalent on going noise levels obtained exceed the limits established by the current legislation for schools. Therefore,students are exposed to elevated noise during their school activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfaro Espín, Antonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco y López de Lerma, José Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molina Alarcón, Milagros</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Amo Saus, M. Llanos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Alcaraz, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: determinar el nivel sonoro continuo equivalente al que se ve sometido un escolar en su actividad diaria en centros públicos de educación primaria de Albacete. Material y método: estudio observacional descriptivo y transversal en once centros públicos de educación primaria de Albacete. Variable dependiente: nivel sonoro continuo equivalente al que se ve sometido el escolar (Leq en dBA). Variables independientes: colegio y lugares del colegio. Las mediciones se han realizado utilizando medidores de sonido Bruel &amp; Kjaer type 2.226 con trípode. Se calcularon intervalos de confianza para un 95% de seguridad. Resultados: el nivel sonoro medio equivalente en las aulas de los niños con edades entre tres y cinco años tuvo unos valores medios de 75 dBA, para edades de seis a siete años fue de 66 dBA y para edades entre 8 y 11 años fue de 69 dBA. La media de la distribución muestral(de 3 a 11 años) fue de 70 dBA. El nivel sonoro medio equivalente en el pasillo a la salida de los escolares tuvo un valor medio de 71 dBA y de 83 dBA en el patio en el momento del recreo. Conclusiones: los niveles sonoros continuos equivalentes obtenidos superan los límites establecidos por la legislación vigente para centros educativos, por tanto, los escolares están sometidos a sonidos elevados en su actividad escolar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;14(2): 68-71, mar. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94193</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Contaminación sonora en centros públicos de educación primaria de Albacete</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32553^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32436^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32436^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
