<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114820</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology and clinical features of Streptococcus pyogenes bacteremia in Cartagena (Murcia, Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction A gradual increase in severe cases due to Streptococcus pyogenes or Streptococcus beta-hemolytic group A (SGA), has been detected in the last few decades. Methods Retrospective study of bacteremia due to S. pyogenes detected between January 2009 and January 2013 in Cartagena. The annual incidence for severe bacteremia has been estimated. Results Thirteen cases of SGA bacteremia were recorded. The incidence increased from 0.37 in 2009 to 2.5 cases/100,000 inhabitants in 2012. The predominant focus was skin and soft tissue infections (53%). Early mortality was 20%. Conclusion Severe streptococcal disease is rare, but affects individuals with good functional status, and is associated with a high mortality(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz-Vidal, Begoña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jimeno-Almazán, Amaya</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcalde, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Viqueira -Gonzalez, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vera-Méndez, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción En las últimas décadas se ha detectado un incremento progresivo de las infecciones graves producidas por Streptococcus pyogenes o estreptococo beta-hemolítico del grupo A (SGA). Métodos Estudio descriptivo retrospectivo de los 13 casos de bacteriemia por S. pyogenes entre enero de 2009 y enero de 2013 en Cartagena. Se calcula la incidencia anual para la enfermedad grave bacteriémica. Resultados La incidencia se incrementó de 0,37 en 2009 a 2,5 casos/100.000 habitantes en 2012. El foco predominante fue la piel y los tejidos blandos (53%). La mortalidad precoz atribuible fue del 20%. Conclusión Se trata de una patología poco frecuente que afecta a individuos previamente sanos y que se relaciona con una elevada mortalidad(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;31(7): 448-450, ago.-sept. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114820</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología y características clínicas de los episodios de bacteriemia por Streptococcus pyogenes en Cartagena (Murcia)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13677^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30241^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13684^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
