<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-85904</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hot topics in respiratory infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We review the most interesting articles on respiratory infections published in the last trimester of 2009 andin 2010. Notable publications in bronchiectasis were the Guidelines of the British Thoracic Society, as well asseveral articles on the natural course of the process, the impact of exacerbations on the course of the disease,and treatment with inhaled antibiotics. Other notable publications were the SEPAR-SEIMC consensusdocument for the management of tuberculosis and articles on the use of interferon-gamma in the diagnosisof tuberculosis infection. The new recommendations of the Spanish Society of Pneumology and ThoracicSurgery on community-acquired pneumonia have recently been published. Equally important are studies onthe viral etiology of community-acquired pneumonia, the impact of corticosteroid treatment in pneumonia,the duration of antibiotic therapy and preventive measures in both community-acquired and nosocomialpneumonia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Souza-Galvao, M. Luiza de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanquer, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Martínez, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Se efectúa una revisión de los artículos más interesantes de infecciones respiratorias, publicados en el últimotrimestre del año 2009 y en 2010. En cuanto a las bronquiectasias, destacan las Guidelines de la British ThoracicSociety, así como diversos artículos de la evolución natural del proceso y el impacto de las reagudizacionesde ésta, así como del tratamiento inhalatorio antibiótico de las bronquiectasias. Con respecto a la tuberculosis,es recomendable señalar el documento de consenso SEPAR-SEIMC para el manejo de la tuberculosis, así comolas publicaciones sobre la utilización de interferón-gamma en el diagnóstico de infección tuberculosa. Lasnuevas recomendaciones SEPAR de neumonía adquirida en la comunidad (NAC) se han publicado muy recientemente,y junto con ellas destacan estudios de etiología viral de las NAC, impacto del tratamiento corticoideoen las neumonías, duración del tratamiento antibiótico y medidas preventivas de neumonías, tanto comunitariascomo nosocomiales(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;47(supl.1): 41-45, ene. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-85904</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hot topics en infecciones respiratorias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11454^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12561^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11454^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11454^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2017^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201101</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
