<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119724</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Functional magnetic resonance imaging: a critical analysis of its technical, statistical and theoretical implications in human neuroscience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The use of functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) has represented an important step forward for the neurosciences. Nevertheless, it has also been subject to rather a lot of criticism. AIM. To study the most widespread criticism against fMRI, so that researchers who are starting to use it may know the different elements that must be taken into account to be able to take a suitable approach to this technique. Development. The fact that fMRI allows brain activity to be observed makes it a very attractive and useful tool, and its use has grown exponentially since the last decade of the 20th century. At the same time, criticism against its use has become especially fierce. Most of this scepticism can be classified into aspects related with the technique and physiology, the analysis of data and their theoretical interpretation. In this study we will review the main arguments defended in each of these three areas, as well as looking at whether they are well-founded or not. Additionally, this work is also intended as a reference for novel researchers when it comes to identifying elements that must be taken into account as they approach fMRI. Conclusions. Despite the fact that fMRI is one of the most interesting options for observing the brain available today, its correct utilisation requires a great deal of control and knowledge. Even so, today most of the criticism it receives no longer has any solid foundation on which to stand (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tudela, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La utilización de la resonancia magnética funcional (RMf) ha supuesto una gran revolución en el avance de las neurociencias. Pese a ello, ha sido objeto de numerosas críticas. Objetivo. Estudiar las críticas más generalizadas hacia la RMf, de manera que investigadores que se inicien en su uso conozcan los diferentes elementos que hay que tener en cuenta para un acercamiento adecuado a esta técnica. Desarrollo. Su gran atractivo y utilidad a la hora de observar la actividad cerebral han hecho de la RMf una técnica cuyo uso ha crecido exponencialmente desde la última década del siglo XX. Paralelamente, la crítica hacia ella ha sido especialmente feroz. La mayoría de este escepticismo puede clasificarse en aspectos concernientes a la técnica y fisiología, el análisis de los datos y su interpretación teórica. Mediante este trabajo se revisarán los principales argumentos en cada uno de estos tres apartados, así como su adecuación. Adicionalmente, se pretende que este trabajo pueda servir de referencia para investigadores noveles a la hora de identificar elementos que se deban tener en cuenta en su acercamiento a la RMf. Conclusión. Pese a que la RMf constituye actualmente una de las opciones más interesantes para observar el cerebro, es necesario un alto grado de control y conocimiento para su utilización. Aun así, gran parte de las críticas no se sostiene hoy en día (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;58(7): 318-325, abr. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119724</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Resonancia magnética funcional: análisis crítico de sus implicaciones técnicas, estadísticas y teóricas en neurociencia humana</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54669^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1538^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3102^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
