<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155139</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-2399</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of an incident notification system and register in a critical care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To analyse the incident communicated through a notification system and register in a critical care unit. Methodology. A cross-sectional descriptive study was conducted by performing an analysis of the records of incidents communicated anonymously and voluntarily from January 2007 to December 2013 in a critical care unit of adult patients with severe trauma. Study variables: incident type and class, professional reports, and suggestions for improvement measures. A descriptive analysis was performed on the variables. Results. Out of a total of 275 incidents reported, 58.5% of them were adverse events. Incident distributed by classes: medication, 33.7%; vascular access-drainage-catheter-sensor, 19.6%; devices-equipment, 13.3%, procedures, 11.5%; airway tract and mechanical ventilation, 10%; nursing care, 4.1%; inter-professional communication, 3%; diagnostic test, 3%; patient identification, 1.1%, and transfusion 0.7%. In the medication group, administrative errors accounted for a total of 62%; in vascular access-drainage-catheter-sensor group, central venous lines, a total of 27%; in devices and equipment group, respirators, a total of 46.9%; in airway self-extubations, a total of 32.1%. As regards to medication errors, 62% were incidents without damage. Incident notification by profession: doctors, 43%, residents, 5.6%, nurses, 51%, and technical assistants, 0.4%. Conclusions. Adverse events are the most communicated incidents. The events related to medication administration are the most frequent, although most of them were without damage. Nurses and doctors communicate the incidents with the same frequency. In order to highlight the low incident notification despite it being an anonymous and volunteer system, therefore, it is suggested to study measurements to increase the level of communication (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palomino-Sánchez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Ruiz, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo-Pérez, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alted López, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuenca Solanas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Iglesias, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar los incidentes comunicados a través de un sistema de notificación y registro en una unidad de cuidados críticos. Metodología. Estudio transversal descriptivo. Se realizó un análisis de los registros de incidentes comunicados de manera anónima y voluntaria de enero de 2007 a diciembre de 2013 en una unidad de cuidados críticos de pacientes adultos con trauma grave. Variables de estudio: tipo y clase de incidente, profesional que notifica y sugerencias de medidas de mejora. Análisis descriptivo de variables. Resultados. Se comunicaron un total de 275 incidentes, de los cuales el 58,5% fueron eventos adversos. Los incidentes distribuidos por clases: medicación 33,7%; accesos vasculares-drenajes-sondas-sensores 19,6%; aparatos-equipos 13,3%; procedimientos 11,5%, vía aérea y ventilación mecánica 10%; cuidados enfermeros 4,1%; comunicación interprofesional 3%; pruebas diagnósticas 3%; identificación paciente 1,1% y transfusión 0,7%. En el grupo de medicación los errores de administración constituyeron el 62%; en el de accesos vasculares-drenajes-sondas-sensores las vías venosas centrales el 27%; en aparatos y equipos los respiradores un 46,9%; en vía aérea las autoextubaciones el 32,1%. En relación con los errores de medicación el 62% fueron incidentes sin daño. La notificación de incidentes por profesional: médicos 43%; residentes 5,6%; enfermeros 51%; técnicos auxiliares 0,4%. Conclusiones. Los incidentes que más se comunican son eventos adversos. Los sucesos relacionados con la administración de medicación son los más frecuentes, aunque la mayoría no ocasionaron daño. Los enfermeros y médicos comunican incidentes con similar frecuencia. Destaca la baja notificación de incidentes a pesar de ser un sistema anónimo y voluntario, por ello, se sugiere estudiar medidas para aumentar el grado de comunicación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Intensiva;27(3): 112-119, jul.-sept. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155139</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis del registro de un sistema de notificación de incidentes en una unidad de cuidados críticos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36428</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55418^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
