<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-137324</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-248X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: to know the experience of caregivers in palliative care, their opinion about the Andalusian Palliative Care Plan, and their health expectations, highlighting specific actions. Methods: a qualitative design using focused and nominal groups. Six 3-hour workshops were carried out in six Andalusian provinces. Informed consent. Content analysis. Results: 47 participants. The experience of earing after a loved one is painful. It affects caregivers' rest, agenda, family and work, and it leads to stress and suffering. Women value the competent, qualified, humanely close and emphatic assistance received from palliative care professionals. They expect the same attitudes and training from other health professionals in different health services. They demand coordination and communication between levels of care, health and community services, as well as more investigation. A general expectation appears: the need for training on care giving and communication in order to achieve the proper ability to   respond to patients' questions. Female caregivers have an active role in the process of decision making. The most important expectation is the need for improving accessibility to palliative care services. Conclusions: informal caregivers suffer from physical, emotional, social and economical burnout, and this can be reduced and prevented by the health system. It is imperative to improve caregivers' training and support, and to reduce the impact on the quality of life of patients and their families (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cía-Ramos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz-Amores, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carcía-Toyos, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-López, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escudero-Carretero, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Román, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer la experiencia de personas cuidadoras de pacientes en cuidados paliativos (CP), su valoración sobre el Plan andaluz de CP y sus expectativas sanitarias, priorizando acciones a desarrollar. Método: diseño cualitativo con grupo local y nominal. Se realizaron 6 talleres de 3 horas, en seis provincias andaluzas. Consentimiento informado. Análisis de contenido. Resultados: participaron 47 personas. La experiencia de cuidar un ser querido en situación terminal es muy dolorosa. Tiene repercusiones en la vida de quienes les cuidan: en su descanso, tiempo, familia o trabajo; provoca estrés y sufrimiento. Las cuidadoras valoran la atención técnicamente competente, cualificada, cercana y empática de profesionales de CP. Manifiestan expectativa de que profesionales de otros servicios tengan actitudes similares y suficiente formación para atender este tipo de pacientes. Demandan coordinación y comunicación entre niveles asistenciales y entre servicios sanitarios y sociocomunitarios y fomento de la investigación. Es unánime la expectativa de las cuidadoras de formarse en técnicas necesarias para el cuidado y en comunicación para poder responder adecuadamente a las preguntas que les plantea la persona a quién cuidan. En el apoyo a la toma de decisiones, desempeñan un rol activo. La expectativa más priorizada es la mejora en la accesibilidad a los servicios de CP. Conclusiones: las personas cuidadoras sufren desgaste físico, emocional, social y económico que el sistema sanitario puede prevenir y aminorar. Es preciso profundizar en formación y apoyo que reciben y cuidar el impacto en la calidad de vida de pacientes y sus familias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. paliat;17(4): 201-209, jul.-ago. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-137324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Vivencia de personas cuidadoras informales y sus expectativas sobre el Plan Andaluz de Cuidados Paliativos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30727^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50207</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30048^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16836^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
