<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-126589</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-7546</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of a short-term physical exercise program and a hypocaloric diet in lipid profile and body composition of overweight post-menopausal women</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The purpose of this paper is to assess the changes in the body composition and the cholesterol and triglycerides caused by a 6 weeks aerobic and resistance training program and a hypocaloric diet in a group of overweight post-menopausal women. Method. The sample population was made up of 18 post-menopausal women, 9 of them were randomly assigned to the experimental group and the other 9 to the control group. All the women presented more than 12 months of amenorrhea and had an age between 46 and 62 years old. None of them were involved in any physical activity. Results. Significant differences between experimental and control group were found in the variations of the body weight, the body fat mass and the muscle mass. No significant differences were found in the lipid profile. However, the effect size produced in the experimental group related to the control group was moderate for the decrease of the total cholesterol and the low density lipoproteins (LDL). Conclusion. These data suggest that a short-term (6 weeks) aerobic and resistance training program and a hypocaloric diet in overweight postmenopausal women produces substantial improvements in the body composition and a trend to improve the lipid profile. These changes can have a positive impact in the quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vargas, G. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojano, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Analizar los cambios producidos en la composición corporal y, a nivel bioquímico, sobre el colesterol y los triglicéridos, por un programa de ejercicio físico aeróbico y de fuerza de 6 semanas de duración, acompañado de una dieta hipocalórica, en un grupo de mujeres menopáusicas con sobrepeso. Método. La muestra estaba formada por 18 mujeres en la etapa de la menopausia, 9 de las cuales fueron asignadas aleatoriamente al grupo experimental y las otras 9 al grupo control. Todas presentaban más de 12 meses de amenorrea y tenían una edad comprendida entre 46 y 62 años. No realizaban ninguna actividad física. Resultados. Se han encontrado diferencias significativas entre el grupo experimental y el de control en las variaciones experimentadas en la masa, en el componente graso y en el componente muscular. No se han encontrado diferencias significativas en las variaciones experimentadas en el perfil lipídico, si bien el tamaño del efecto producido en el grupo experimental frente al de control fue moderado para la disminución del colesterol total y de las lipoproteínas de baja densidad (LDL). Conclusión. Los resultados obtenidos sugieren que la combinación de un programa de ejercicio físico aeróbico y de fuerza de 6 semanas de duración y una dieta hipocalórica en mujeres menopáusicas con sobrepeso, provoca mejoras significativas en la composición corporal y una tendencia hacia la mejora del perfil lipídico, lo que puede repercutir positivamente en la calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. andal. med. deporte;7(3): 95-100, sept. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-126589</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de una dieta hipocalórica y de un programa de ejercicio físico de corta duración en el perfil lipídico y en la composición corporal de mujeres menopáusicas con sobrepeso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8251^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16525</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4074^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22243^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2181</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
