<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88355</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-3230</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Self-monitoring of blood glucose in diabetes. Historical perspective and technologic evolution</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The appearance of the first capillary blood reagent strip 40 years ago made itpossible for diabetic patients to determine themselves their blood glucose resultat a specific time. A few years later, devices were developed that readthose strips and provided accurate results of the blood glucose. Over time,those devices have improved and have evolved technologically and, as a result,they have today become a tool that enables many people with diabetes toself-manage their condition. In recent years it has become possible to continuouslymonitor blood glucose through sensors implanted subcutaneouslyand capable of offering blood glucose results every few minutes, indicatingtrends and warning of possible hypoglycemia or hyperglycemia. For the future,painless methods for continuous glucose measurement are envisaged whichlinked to insulin infusion pumps and with suitable algorithms will be able toclose the &#147;loop&#148; and keep blood glucose under control in a fully autonomousmanner, in what would be an &#147;artificial pancreas&#148;(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Menéndez Torre, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La aparición de la primera tira reactiva para sangre capilar hace ya 40 añoshizo posible que el propio paciente diabético pudiera conocer el resultado desu glucemia en un momento determinado. Pocos años después se desarrollarondispositivos que leían dichas tiras y aportaban un resultado preciso de laglucemia. Estos dispositivos han ido mejorando y evolucionando tecnológicamente,de forma que en estos momentos constituyen un instrumento que permiteel autocontrol de gran parte de las personas con diabetes. En los últimosaños es posible la monitorización continua de la glucemia con sensores implantadosen tejido subcutáneo, capaces de ofrecer resultados de la glucemiacada pocos minutos, indicar tendencias y avisar de posibles hipoglucemias ohiperglucemias. Para el futuro se vislumbran métodos indoloros de medicióncontinua que, acoplados a infusores de insulina y con algoritmos apropiados,puedan cerrar «el asa» y mantener la glucemia controlada de forma totalmenteautónoma en lo que se podría denominar el «páncreas artificial»(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. diabetol;26(supl.1): s1-s4, abr. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88355</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización de la glucemia en la diabetes. Perspectiva histórica y evolución tecnológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22190^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37656</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201004</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
