<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113903</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nurse managers with management education has any influence in the patient outcomes?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To know the available scientific evidence on the influence of nurse manager training in management on patient outcomes in hospitals. Method: It was conducted a review of the literature available in the databases PubMed, Medline, CINAHL and Cochrane Library. The limits of the search were published articles written in English and / or Spanish in the last 10 years (2002-2012). Results: 207 articles were found and after applying the above limits were reduced to 147. After a first reading of the title and abstract the authors extended the searching to some relevant journals in nursing management area and the technique of snow ball was used. Finally, a total of 56 papers related to the research question were valided. After a close reading of these 56articles, six were selected linking with the aim of this study. Conclusions: It has been detected little evidence in this area of ??nursing. After this review it is suggested to study this issue in the Spanish context in order to cover the need for training of nurse managers with the help of professors in graduate programs at Universities(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Barrio-Linares, Miriam del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la evidencia científica disponible sobre la influencia que tiene la formación de las supervisoras en gestión sobre los resultados de los pacientes en los hospitales. Método. Se ha llevado a cabo una revisión de la literatura disponible en las bases de datos Pubmed, Medline, Cinahl y Cochrane library. Los límites de la búsqueda fueron artículos publicados en los últimos 10 años (2002-2012) escritos en inglés y/o castellano. Resultados. Se obtuvieron un total de 207 artículos que, tras aplicar los límites mencionados, quedaron en 147; tras una primera lectura del título y del resumen se amplió la búsqueda manual en las revistas más relevantes del área de gestión en enfermería y, mediante la técnica de bola de nieve, se consiguió un total de 56 artículos relacionados con la pregunta de investigación. Tras una lectura en profundidad de los mismos se seleccionaron seis estudios que relacionaban, de manera positiva, la formación específica en gestión de las supervisoras con los resultados de los pacientes en los hospitales. Conclusiones. Se detecta una escasa evidencia en esta área de la enfermería. Tras esta revisión se plantea estudiar este tema en el contexto español para poder cubrir la necesidad de formación de las supervisoras, si existe, con ayuda de los docentes de los programas de postgrado de las universidades(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;36(6): 430-439, jun. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113903</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La formación en gestión de las supervisoras ¿Influye en los resultados del paciente?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10751</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9903^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201306</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
