<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157382</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Spanish psoriasis patients&#146; association according to its members: cross-sectional descriptive study of members&#146; opinions of the association&#146;s functions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Patient associations form part of health care systems, but little is known about how their members&#146; view the functionality of these associations and whether they endorse their goals and activities. Objective: To study how the members of the leading Spanish association of patients with psoriasis and their relatives view the group&#146;s functioning. Material and methods: Survey study using a self-administered questionnaire answered by members of the association (total membership, 26 349 persons). The credibility of the association and respondents&#146; confidence in and satisfaction with it were studied and compared with their attitudes toward other agents in the health care system. A Rasch model was used to analyze respondents&#146; ranking of functions. Analysis of variance was used to study between-group differences. Results: A total of 746 members participated (response rate 2.83%). The association&#146;s credibility was rated in second place, after that of specialists who treat psoriasis. Support for the association functions was good (7.53 on a scale of 0 to 10). The function the members rated highest was the raising of societal awareness of psoriasis and its problems. Rated lowest were functions related to personal services for members. Educational level was the only participant factor associated with significant differences in evaluations (P &lt; .05). Conclusions: The psoriasis association contributes by disseminating information about the disease and patient care, and it serves to represent patients. Health professionals and institutions should take the association into account in their efforts to deal with the disease and in designing effective policies (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfonso-Zamora, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribera, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ros, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanch Mur, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-de Paz, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gratacós-Masmitjà, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las asociaciones de pacientes son un elemento más del sistema sanitario, sin embargo en España se desconoce la funcionalidad y el respaldo que tienen según sus propios asociados. Objetivo: Estudiar la funcionalidad de la principal asociación española de pacientes y familiares afectados por la psoriasis según sus propios socios. Material y métodos: Estudio mediante un cuestionario autoadministrado a una muestra de socios y/o simpatizantes (población total = 26.349 personas). Se estudió la credibilidad, confianza y satisfacción y se comparó con otros agentes sanitarios. El cuestionario de funcionalidad se analizó con un modelo de Rasch, y se examinó si había diferencias entre grupos de participantes con la prueba de ANOVA. Resultados: Participaron 746 socios y/o simpatizantes (tasa de respuesta 2,83%). La credibilidad de la asociación se situó tras la de los especialistas que tratan la psoriasis. El respaldo medio a la función de la asociación fue notable (7,53 en una escala de 0 a 10). Según los socios las funciones mejor puntuadas se relacionaban con acciones colectivas para sensibilizar a la sociedad sobre el problema de la psoriasis, en cambio, tuvieron una menor valoración las acciones relacionadas con los servicios de atención personalizada. Solo hubo diferencias significativas (p &lt; 0,05) en el respaldo a la asociación en función del nivel académico de los participantes. Conclusiones: Las asociaciones son unas instituciones que contribuyen a la difusión de información de la enfermedad, que cuidan y representan a los pacientes. Los profesionales de salud e instituciones deberían tenerlas en cuenta para afrontar la psoriasis y diseñar políticas de salud efectivas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;107(9): 751-757, nov. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157382</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Función y respaldo a la asociación de pacientes con psoriasis en España según sus miembros: estudio descriptivo transversal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13036^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12002^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
