<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-94245</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-7310</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Inflammatory Myxohyaline Tumor of the Distal Extremities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Inflammatory myxohyaline tumor of the distal extremities is an extremely rare low-grade sarcoma with a tendency to produce local recurrence after surgical excision, but with a low metastatic potential. We present the case of a 49-year-old woman with a slow-growing asymptomatic tumor on the right pretibial region that was initially considered to be a lipoma. Histopathology revealed the presence of a polymorphic inflammatory infiltrate within a myxoid and hyaline matrix. Interspersed between the inflammatory cells were 3 different populations of neoplastic cells: atypical spindle-shaped cells; bizarre epithelioid cells, some of which were multinucleated and resembled the virocytes or Reed-Sternberg cells; and cells with abundant, vacuolated cytoplasm, similar to lipoblasts. These clinical-pathologic findings led to a diagnosis of inflammatory myxohyaline tumor of the distal extremities. Although the tumor was excised with wide surgical margins, local recurrence developed after 3 months and was treated with re-excision and radiotherapy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Messeguer, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Agusti-Mejias, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lloret, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sabater, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alegre, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tumor mixohialino inflamatorio de las áreas distales de las extremidades (TMHIADE) es un sarcoma de bajo grado de malignidad extremadamente infrecuente, con tendencia a la recurrencia local tras su extirpación quirúrgica, pero con un bajo potencial metastásico. Presentamos el caso de una mujer de 49 años que consultó por una tumoración asintomática de lento crecimiento en la zona pretibial derecha, que inicialmente sugirió el diagnóstico de lipoma. El estudio histopatológico mostró la presencia de un infiltrado inflamatorio polimórfico inmerso en una matriz mixoide e hialina. Entremezcladas entre las células inflamatorias existían varias poblaciones de células tumorales: en primer lugar, unas células atípicas de morfología fusiformes; en segundo lugar, unas células epitelioides bizarras, algunas de las cuales eran multinucleadas y recordaban a los virocitos o células de Reed-Sternberg; por último, unas células de citoplasma amplio multivacuolado que recordaban a los lipoblastos. Estos hallazgos clínico-patológicos permitieron el diagnóstico de tumor mixohialino inflamatorio de las áreas distales de las extremidades. A pesar de que la tumoración se extirpó con márgenes quirúrgicos amplios, presentó una recidiva local tres meses después que fue tratada con nueva extirpación quirúrgica y radioterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Dermosifiliogr;102(6): 456-462, jul.-ago. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-94245</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tumor mixohialino inflamatorio de las zonas distales de las extremidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50469^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31340^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9425^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22071</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31514^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12888^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29849^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
