<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167825</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Risk models for patients with localised renal cell carcinoma</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: We conducted a retrospective analysis of our series to assess the factors that influenced disease-free survival (DFS) and cancer-specific survival (CSS) for patients with localised renal cell carcinoma (RCC). We also created our own risk groups. Material and methods: Between January 1990 and December 2012, 596 patients underwent surgery for localised RCC (clear cell, papillary or chromophobe). Using Cox regression models, we analysed the clinical-pathological variables that influenced DFS and CSS and designed risk groups for DFS and CSS with the variables. Results: The median follow-up for the series was 5.96 years. By the end of the study, 112 patients (18.8%) had a recurrence of the disease, with DFS rates of 82%, 77% and 72% at 5, 10 and 15 years, respectively. The independent factors that influenced DFS in the multivariate study were the following: A Furhman grade of 3-4, haematuria, lymphocytic or vascular invasion, the presence of tumour necrosis and a disease stage pT3-pT4. Furthermore, by the end of the study, 57 patients (9.6%) died due to renal cancer, with CSS rates of 92%, 86% and 83% at 5, 10 and 15 years, respectively. The independent factors that influenced CSS in the multivariate study were the following: A Furhman grade of 3-4, perinephric fat invasion and the presence of tumour necrosis. Conclusions: Factors in addition to the disease stage pT3-pT4 in patients with localised RCC are important, such as the presence of haematuria and lymphocytic or vascular invasion for DFS. A Furhman grade of 3-4 and the presence of tumour necrosis are especially relevant for DFS and CSS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ancizu, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hevia, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velis, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tienza, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Algarra, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Doménech, P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Realizamos un análisis retrospectivo de nuestra serie para evaluar los factores influyentes en la supervivencia libre de enfermedad (SLE) y en la supervivencia cáncer-específica (SCE) en pacientes con carcinoma de células renales (CCR) localizado y realizamos unos grupos de riesgo propios. Material y métodos: Entre enero de 1990 y diciembre de 2012 fueron operados 596 pacientes con CCR localizado (tanto de células claras como papilares o cromófobos). Se analizan las variables clinicopatológicas influyentes en la SLE y en la SCE mediante modelos de regresión de Cox y con ellas se diseñan grupos de riesgo de SLE y de SCE. Resultados: La mediana de seguimiento de la serie es de 5,96 años. Al final del estudio 112 pacientes (18,8%) evidenciaron recidiva de la enfermedad, siendo la SLE del 82%, 77% y 72% a 5, 10 y 15 años respectivamente. Los factores de influencia independiente en la SLE en el estudio multivariado fueron: grado de Furhman III-IV, hematuria, afectación vascular linfática, la presencia de necrosis tumoral y el estadio patológico pT3-pT4. Por otro lado, al final del estudio 57 pacientes (9,6%) fallecieron a causa del cáncer renal, siendo la SCE del 92%, 86% y 83% a 5, 10 y 15 años respectivamente. Los factores de influencia independiente en la SCE en el estudio multivariado fueron: Grado de Furhman III-IV, afectación de la grasa perirrenal y la presencia de necrosis tumoral. Conclusiones: Además del estadio patológico pT3-pT4 en pacientes con CCR localizado son importantes otros factores, como la presencia de hematuria y la afectación vascular linfática para la SLE; y especialmente relevantes el grado de Furhman III-IV y la presencia de necrosis tumoral tanto para la SLE como para la SCE (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;41(9): 564-570, nov. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167825</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelos de riesgo en pacientes con carcinoma de células renales localizado</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2335^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24842</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6566^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7855^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32281</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
