<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125592</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3171</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Shame in books and onthe cough</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The autor based inthe relationship between the feeling of shame and the narcissistic pathology, studies the injurious power of the violent contact with the causative shame truth, that stays split, not repressed. Based on the literature and on the clinic, argues the damage that can produce the truth to ant price, and without the previous development of the necessary defenses that they permit to tolerate it. Propose that the psychoanalysis of the narcissistic disorders, whose fundamental feeling is the shame, it must reflect between the unavoidable obligation of be known itself, and the dangers that said knowledge implies. That is to say it must conciliate the invitation to know of the shrine of Apollo Delfos, with the warnings contained in the traditions and the myths, certainly recorded in our mind, on the danger knowing the truth (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Soriano, J. Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El autor, partiendo de la relación entre el sentimiento de vergüenza y la patología del narcisismo, estudia el poder patógeno del contacto violento con la verdad causante de vergüenza, que permanece escindida aunque no reprimida. Basándose en la literatura y en la clínica, argumenta el daño que puede producir la verdad a cualquier precio, y sin el desarrollo previo de las necesarias defensas para poder tolerada. Propone que el psicoanálisis de los trastornos narcisistas, cuyo afecto fundamental es la vergüenza, debe discurrir entre la inevitable obligación de conocerse a sí mismo, y los peligros que dicho conocimiento implica. Es decir, debe conciliar la invitación a saber del templo de Apolo en Delfos, con las advertencias contenidas en las tradiciones y los mitos, seguramente grabadas en nuestra mente, sobre el peligro de conocer la verdad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicoanál. (Madr.);(45): 103-117, mayo-ago. 2005.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125592</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La vergüenza en los libros y el diván</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4720^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13130</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9484</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12009^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
