<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-040516</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Determination of systemic infections due to mycoplasma in patients with clinically defined amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) is a neurodegenerative disease of unknown origin which hasbeen linked to chronic infections due to intracellular microorganisms. Aims. The purpose of this study was to identify speciesof Mycoplasma in blood samples from patients with clinically defined ALS by means of the polymerase chain reaction (PCR)method in comparison to healthy control subjects. Patients and methods. We conducted a case-control study involving 75participants, 20 of whom were patients with clinically defined ALS and 55 healthy controls. Venous blood samples were takenand processed in the Neuroimmunology Laboratory, where they were submitted to the PCR test for Mycoplasma sp. Results.The patients with ALS were between 35 and 82 years old (mean: 52.5); the ages of the healthy control subjects ranged from 35to 60 years (mean: 44.1). After performing the PCR for Mycoplasma sp. the following results were obtained: among thepatients with ALS, 10 were found to be positive (50%) and 10 were negative (50%), whereas in the control subjects we foundsix positives (10.91%) and 49 negatives (89.09%); these results were statistically significant (p = 0.001). On calculating theestimated risk, an odds ratio of 8167 (CI 95%: 2.4-27.6) was obtained. This indicates that the risk of suffering from ALS, if thePCR test for Mycoplasma sp. is positive, is 8:1. Conclusions. There is a strong link between suffering from a chronic infectiondue to Mycoplasma and developing ALS. Intracellular pathogenic agents such as Mycoplasma can play a role in the genesisof neurodegenerative diseases</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pineda-Olvera, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ordóñez-Lozano, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Río de la Loza, L. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La esclerosis lateral amiotrófica (ELA) esuna enfermedad neurodegenerativa de causa desconocida, que seha relacionado recientemente con infecciones crónicas por microorganismosintracelulares. Objetivo. Identificar especies de Mycoplasmaen muestras de sangre de pacientes con ELA clínicamentedefinida, por medio del método de reacción en cadena de polimerasa(PCR) en comparación con controles sanos. Pacientes y métodos.Realizamos un estudio de casos y controles que incluía a 75participantes, 20 pacientes con ELA clínicamente definida y 55 controlessanos. Se tomaron muestras de sangre venosa y se procesaronen el Laboratorio de Neuroinmulogía, donde se sometieron a laprueba de PCR para Mycoplasma sp. Resultados. Los pacientes conELA tuvieron un rango de edad entre 35 y 82 años (media: 52,5);los sujetos control entre 35 y 60 años (media: 44,1). Después de realizarla PCR para Mycoplasma sp., se obtuvieron los siguientes resultados:en los pacientes con ELA, 10 resultaron positivos (50%) y10 negativos (50%), mientras que en los controles tenemos seispositivos (10,91%) y 49 negativos (89,09%), y se obtuvo significaciónestadística (p = 0,001). Al calcular el riesgo estimado, se obtieneun odds ratio de 8,167 (IC 95%: 2,4-27,6), lo cual indica que elriesgo de padecer ELA, si resulta positiva la prueba de PCR paraMycoplasma sp., es de 8:1. Conclusiones. Existe una fuerte asociaciónentre padecer una infección crónica por Mycoplasma y desarrollarELA. Agentes patógenos intracelulares como Mycoplasmapueden desempeñar una función en la génesis de enfermedades neurodegenerativas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;41(5): 262-267, sept. 2005. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-040516</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Determinación de infecciones sistémicas por Mycoplasma en pacientes con esclerosis lateral amiotrófica clínicamente definida</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2525^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9367^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9367^s32386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d704^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
