<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038579</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidural blockade with ropivacaine for chronic arteriopathies of the lower limbs: a clinical trial</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective:To determine therapeutic effects of epidural blockadewith ropivacaine in patients with chronic arteriopathies ofthe lower limbs.Material and method:Descriptive, prospective and longitudinal study in 58 patientsundergoing epidural blockade with ropivacaine. Wedetermined the degree of motor blockade according toBromage´s scale, the level of sensitive blockade using thepricking method, the degree of analgesia according to thevisual analogical scale (VAS), appearance or changes inpulse rate and changes in skin temperature at the limbs involved,as well as improvement of skin trophic lesions.These determinations were performed 15 and 30 minutesafter the blockade, then at 4-hours intervals during the first 24 hours and subsequently once daily until hospital dischargeand 15 and 30 days afterwards.Results:After the blockade, an immediate relief of pain was observedin 56 patients and all of them recovered the pulserates measured. One month later, pain persisted in 6 patients.Trophic disorders improved in 82.8%, skin lesionsin 86.3% and pulse rate in 91.4%. In more than half of thepatients, skin temperature increased from 3 to 3.9 °C andin some patients it increased in more than 5 °C.Conclusions:The results were satisfactory in 89.6% of patients, sowe conclude that this therapeutic method is effective particularlyfor the management of pain at rest and for the improvementof blood circulation in the limb involved</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santana, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Grosso, N. G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Labrada, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo:Evaluar los efectos terapéuticos del bloqueo epiduralcon ropivacaína en pacientes con insuficiencia arterial crónicade miembros inferiores.Material y método:Estudio descriptivo, prospectivo y longitudinal en 58 pacientesa los que se les realizó bloqueo epidural con ropivacaína.Determinamos grado de bloqueo motor según la escalade Bromage, nivel de bloqueo sensitivo por métododel pinchazo, grado de analgesia por medio de la escala visualanalógica (EVA), aparición o cambios en la intensidad de los pulsos y las modificaciones en la temperatura cutáneade los miembros afectados, así como la mejoría de laslesiones tróficas de la piel. Estas evaluaciones se hicieron alos 15 y 30 minutos siguientes al bloqueo, luego cada cuatrohoras en las primeras 24 horas y posteriormente cadadía hasta el alta, luego a los 15 y 30 días.Resultados:Después del bloqueo se observó mejoría inmediata deldolor en 56 pacientes y todos recuperaron la intensidad delos pulsos explorados. Al mes persistía el dolor en 6 pacientes.Las alteraciones tróficas mejoraron en el 82,8%,las lesiones cutáneas en el 86,3% y los pulsos en el 91,4%.En más de la mitad de los pacientes la temperatura cutánease elevó de 3 a 3,9 °C y en algunos en más de 5 °C.Conclusiones:El resultado fue bueno en el 89,6% de los casos, por loque consideramos que este método de tratamiento es útilsobre todo para el alivio del dolor en reposo y la mejoríaen la circulación del miembro afectado</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;12(2): 86-92, mar. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038579</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Bloqueo epidural con ropivacaína en la insuficiencia arterial crónica de miembros inferiores: ensayo clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1163^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19283^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36500^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
