<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156798</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Complications of double j catheters and their endourological management</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The insertion of a double J catheter (DJ) has widespread, becoming a usual procedure and standard of care in urology. Despite its relative simplicity it is not free from intraoperative risks or problems during the weeks after the implant. Conversely, despite great advances in design of these catheters the ideal material has not been discovered yet, one that is perfectly biocompatible with urine and avoids completely the advent of complications. The range of problems associated with DJs is variable: from mild self-limited dysuria or hematuria to more complex situations with higher risk, such as catheter garanmigration, complete calcification, breakage, obstruction and renal unit loss. The treatment of theses complications must combine maximal efficacy for their resolution with the least possible surgical aggression. Accordingly, the different options of endourological approach become very important and they are the cornerstone for the treatment of the complications associated with ureteral catheters. The objective of this review is to present the main complications derived from the insertion of a DJ, their diagnosis, prevention and treatment, focusing mainly in the different endourological techniques (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Fentes, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La colocación de un catéter doble jota (CDJ) se ha generalizado, pasando a ser una maniobra habitual en la cartera de los servicios de urología. Pese a su relativa sencillez, esta técnica no está exenta de riesgos intraoperatorios o problemas en las semanas siguientes al implante. Por otro lado, pese a grandes avances en el diseño de estos catéteres, no se ha descubierto todavía el material ideal, que sea perfectamente biocompatible con la orina y evite por completo la aparición de complicaciones. El espectro de problemas asociados al CDJ es variable: desde leves cuadros de disuria o hematuria autolimitados, a situaciones más complejas y de mayor riesgo como la migración del catéter, su calcificación completa, rotura, obstrucción y pérdida de la unidad renal. El tratamiento de estas complicaciones debe combinar la máxima efectividad para su resolución con el menor daño o agresión quirúrgica posible. En este sentido, las distintas opciones de abordaje que ofrece la endourología cobran gran importancia y son la piedra angular del tratamiento de las complicaciones asociadas a catéteres ureterales. El objetivo de esta revisión es presentar las principales complicaciones derivadas de la colocación de un CDJ, su diagnóstico, prevención y tratamiento, centrándolo fundamentalmente en las diferentes técnicas endourológicas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;69(8): 527-543, oct. 2016. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156798</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Complicaciones de los catéteres doble jota y su manejo endourológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54279^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23248^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7593^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14919^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6566^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55070^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13901^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28379^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
