<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-045468</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The functional condition of patients following a cerebrovascular accident</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Most patients who suffer a cerebrovascular accident (CVA) belong to the adult-elderly age group.Thus, such patients are likely to display a certain degree of functional compromise as a result of the natural process of aging,regardless of whether they have suffered a CVA or not. Aim. To examine the functional condition of patients with CVA, as wellas that of healthy individuals who have never suffered a stroke. Subjects and methods. An analytical cross-sectional study wasconducted with a control group made up of 82 individuals &#150;41 of whom were CVA patients (G1) and 41 were individuals withno history of CVA (G2)&#150;. These subjects were paired according to sex, age and educational level. Results. The sample waspredominantly made up of females (60%), who were married (70%), with ischaemic CVA (70%), in the right hemisphere of thebrain (56%) and with a primary education (36%). The prevalence rate of patients with severe functional impairment was58.53%, whereas in the control group there were no subjects with this level of deficiency. A relationship was found to exist(p &lt; 0.05) between the functional condition and the variables age and causation of CVA for G1, and also between thefunctional condition and the variable age for the individuals in G2, which indicates that functional compromise is greater inmore elderly subjects. Conclusions. Findings suggest that the functional compromise of patients with CVA is higher than thatof individuals with no history of CVA with the same sex, age and educational level. This clearly shows that there is anassociation between CVA and functional impairment in these patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Araujo da Silva, DL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Da Rocha, VM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azevedo da Costa, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se observa que la población de pacientescon un accidente vascular encefálico (AVE) se concentra de manerapredominante en la franja de edad adulta-anciana. Ante este contexto,se comprueba la posibilidad de que tales pacientes, independientementede haber sufrido un episodio de AVE, muestren una ciertaafectación funcional resultado del proceso de envejecimiento natural.Objetivo. Investigar la condición funcional de los pacientes conAVE, así como de los individuos sanos que no presenten historia clínicade éste. Sujetos y métodos. Estudio transversal de tipo analíticocon un grupo de control compuesto por 82 individuos &#150;41 de ellospacientes con AVE (G1) y 41 individuos sin historia de AVE (G2)&#150;,pareados en cuanto a sexo, edad y nivel de estudios. Resultados.Muestra predominantemente femenina (60%), casada (70%), conAVE de tipo isquémico (70%), hemisferio cerebral derecho (56%) ynivel de estudios primarios (36%). La prevalencia de pacientes condéficit funcional grave fue del 58,53%, mientras que en el grupo decontrol no hubo individuos con este nivel de deficiencia. Se verificóla existencia de relación (p &lt; 0,05) entre la condición funcional y lasvariables de edad y etiología del AVE para el G1 y entre la condiciónfuncional y la variable de edad para los individuos participantes delG2, que indicó un acometimiento funcional mayor entre aquellosindividuos de más edad. Conclusión. Los hallazgos sugieren que laafectación de la función de pacientes con AVE es superior a la de losindividuos sin historia de AVE del mismo sexo, edad y nivel de estudios,lo cual pone en evidencia la asociación entre AVE y deficienciafuncional en estos pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;42(10): 591-595, mayo 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-045468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Condición funcional de los pacientes tras un accidente vascular encefálico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d212</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22101</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28397</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
