<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166417</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of sex on heart transplantation mortality: data from the Spanish National Heart Transplantation Registry</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The incidence of many heart diseases differs between men and women. In addition, the disease course, the number and type of complications and the prognosis can also be very different. The objective of this study was to determine whether sex differences can be observed in heart transplantations performed in Spain. Outcomes in 762 women who underwent heart transplantations in the country between May 1984 and December 2005 were compared with those in 3646 men. The analysis looked at 100 variables, including characteristics of the recipient, the donor, surgery, immunosuppression and the complications occurring during follow-up. The two sexes were compared using univariate and survival analysis. In addition, multivariate analysis was performed for each sex individually. The ratio of men to women who underwent transplantation was 5:1. Typically, women were younger than men (45±18 years vs. 51±14 years; P&lt;.05), had a higher incidence of idiopathic dilated cardiomyopathy (39.8% vs. 31.3%; P&lt;.05) and had fewer cardiovascular risk factors (hypertension 16.2% vs. 23.1%; P&lt;.05, and dyslipidemia 25% vs. 36%; P&lt;.05). Women had more emergency transplants (26.8% vs. 23.4%; P&lt;.05) and developed acute graft failure more frequently (17.4% vs. 13.5%; P&lt;.05). During follow-up, women had a higher incidence of bone complications (15.5% vs. 10.9%; P&lt;.05) and lower incidences of dyslipidemia (38% vs. 45%; P&lt;.05), hypertension (36% vs. 49%; P&lt;.05), gastrointestinal complications (12% vs. 16%; P&lt;.05) and malignancy (9% vs. 12.5%; P&lt;.05). The probability of survival was lower in the short term (P&lt;.05), but similar to that in men in the medium and long term (P=.6). Multivariate analysis identified 14 variables associated with mortality in men, compared with only five in women. In conclusion, important differences were found between men and women who underwent heart transplantation in Spain, but the probability of survival was similar in the two sexes, except in the early stages (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almenar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Muchas enfermedades cardiacas presentan distinta incidencia según el sexo del paciente. También la evolución, el número y el tipo de complicaciones y el pronóstico pueden ser muy distintos. El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar si hay diferencias por sexo en los trasplantes cardiacos realizados en España. Se comparó a 762 mujeres con 3.646 varones trasplantados en España desde mayo de 1984 a diciembre de 2005. Se analizaron 100 variables que incluían características del receptor y del donante, quirúrgicas, inmunosupresión y complicaciones del seguimiento. Se comparó por sexos mediante un análisis univariable y de supervivencia. Se realizó un análisis multivariable de cada sexo. La relación varones:mujeres trasplantados fue 5:1. Las mujeres suelen ser más jóvenes (45 ± 18 frente a 51 ± 14 años; p &lt; 0,05), con mayor incidencia de miocardiopatía dilatada idiopática (el 39,8 frente al 31,3%; p &lt; 0,05) y menos factores de riesgo cardiovascular (hipertensión, el 16,2 frente al 23,1%; p &lt; 0,05; dislipemia, el 25 frente al 36%; p &lt; 0,05). Las mujeres se trasplantan más en situación urgente (el 26,8 frente al 23,4%; p &lt; 0,05) y desarrollan fallo agudo del injerto con más frecuencia (el 17,4 frente al 13,5%; p &lt; 0,05). Durante el seguimiento presentan mayor incidencia de complicaciones óseas (el 15,5 frente al 10,9%; p &lt; 0,05) y menor de dislipemia (el 38 frente al 45%; p &lt; 0,05), hipertensión (el 36 frente al 49%; p &lt; 0,05), complicaciones digestivas (el 12 frente al 16%; p &lt; 0,05) y tumores (el 9 frente al 12,5%; p &lt; 0,05). La probabilidad de supervivencia fue menor a corto plazo (p &lt; 0,05), pero similar a la del varón a medio y largo plazo (p = 0,6). El análisis multivariable mostró 14 variables relacionadas con mortalidad en el varón, por tan sólo 5 en la mujer. En conclusión, hay diferencias importantes entre los varones y las mujeres que se trasplantan en España, pero la probabilidad de supervivencia, a excepción de la etapa precoz, es similar en ambos sexos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);8(supl.D): 49d-54d, 2008. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166417</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia del sexo en la mortalidad por trasplante cardiaco: subanálisis del Registro Español de Trasplante Cardiaco</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2355^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2355^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13113</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29419^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13915</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200800</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
