<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-70368</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A possible complication after surgery is infection. An abscess is an infection localized in the surgical site. We present the case of a patient who was diagnosed with bilateral abscesses in the lymphadenectomy area, around the iliac vessels. Administration of wide spectrum intravenous antibiotics produced no response and image-guided aspiration was performed. This technique proved successful in the treatment of our patient, avoiding the need for open surgery. The major advances achieved in imaging techniques have aided progress in interventional radiology. The combination of gynecology and radiology could provide effective and relatively non-invasive treatments, which were unthinkable until a few years ago (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>González-García, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zornoza-García, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Corona, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luengo-Tabernero, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez-Mayor, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Una posible complicación después de cualquier cirugía es la infección, y el absceso es una forma de infección localizada en el lugar donde se ha trabajado. En el caso que se presenta la paciente fue diagnosticada de abscesos bilaterales en las regiones de las linfadenectomías de los vasos ilíacos. La administración de antibióticos intravenosos de amplio espectro no halló respuesta y se optó por la aspiración guiada por imagen, que consiguió una rápida mejoría de la paciente, evitando someterla a cirugía. Los grandes avances en las técnicas de imagen han facilitado el progreso en radiología intervencionista, y trabajando conjuntamente ginecólogos y radiólogos se podrá optar a tratamientos eficaces y poco invasivos que hasta hace unos años eran impensables (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);35(6): 215-217, nov. 2008. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-70368</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5016^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28157^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8985^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10581^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5016^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23589^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d41^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1464^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23481^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23255^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1464^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23201^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11311^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13781^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13781^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d41^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200811</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
