<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159391</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-0618</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Climatology of Villavieja Spa</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A climatic and bioclimatic study of the spa located in Villavieja village is described in this paper. The climatological analysis has been performed using the data of precipitation, temperature, relative humidity and wind corresponding to the climatological stations of AEMET located near the village of Villavieja, in particular the climatological station of Nules and the principal station of Castellón de la Plana&amp;#8208;Almazora. The monthly mean value and the extreme values have been obtained from the available data, as well as the frequency of climatic parameters exceeding certain thresholds, the long term trends and a set of climatic indices. For the bioclimatic analysis the data of temperature and relative humidity have been used to calculate the climatic comfort indices and the thermal sensation values (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ambrona Rodríguez, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mestre Barceló, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cadenas Cortina, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ballesteros, César</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En el presente trabajo se realiza un estudio climático y bioclimático del Balneario de Villavieja (Castellón). Para llevar a cabo este estudio se han utilizando datos de precipitación, temperatura, humedad relativa y viento, que se han obtenido de las estaciones de AEMET ubicadas en torno a Villavieja, en concreto se han utilizado datos de la estación termopluviométrica de Nules y de la estación completa de Castellón de la Plana&amp;#8208;Almazora. Se han obtenido los valores medios mensuales para cada uno de los parámetros climáticos relevantes, así como los valores extremos, la frecuencia de superación de determinados umbrales, las tendencias a largo plazo y los valores de determinados índices climáticos. Para el análisis bioclimático se han utilizado los datos de temperatura y humedad relativa y se han calculado los índices climatológicos de confort y de sensación térmica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Real Acad Farm;82(5): 108-126, 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159391</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Climatología del Balneario de Villavieja</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15289</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34905</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53349</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15319</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38366^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
