<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157279</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Good weight loss responders and poor weight loss responders after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass: clinical and nutritional profiles</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Bariatric surgery is one of the main treatments for severity obesity, but weight regain after surgery is an important issue. Objectives: To compare the clinical and nutritional profiles of good and poor weight loss responders in the late postoperative period after bariatric surgery. Methods: A cross-sectional study with patients undergoing Roux-en-Y gastric bypass in a University Hospital. Patients were divided into good weight loss responders (GWLR) and poor weight loss responders (PWLR) defined as &amp;#8805; 50% or &lt; 50% excess weight loss (EWL), respectively, at least 2 years post-surgery. Results: The sample included 204 individuals (87.7% women; mean age 50.15 ± 11.1 years; mean time after surgery 67.38 ± 30.76 months). Two years post-surgery, 71.1% were considered GWLR and 28.9% PWLR (mean EWL 72.33% ± 13.86%, and 35.06% ± 12.10%, respectively; p = 0.000). Weight regain was &lt; 10% for 36.3% of patients, 10.1-20% for 36.3%, and &gt; 20% for 21.3%, compared with the lowest post-surgery weight. Among PWLR, 49.0% regained &gt; 20% of the lowest post-surgery weight. GWLR lost most weight at all time points analyzed (p &lt; 0.05). GWLR presented improvement or remission of diabetes, dyslipidemia and hypertension more frequently compared to PWLR (p &lt; 0.05). Eating patterns was similar between GWLR and PWLR (p &gt; 0.05, study&#146;s power 100%). Quality of life improved in 79.5% of the total study sample, with greater improvements in the GWLR (p &lt; 0.05). Conclusions: Greater weight loss correlated with improved remission in comorbidities and better quality of life (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Farias, Gisele</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Heyde, Maria Emilia VD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bettini, Solange C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Thieme, Rubia D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Teixeira, Laila M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Radominski, Rosana B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: la cirugía bariátrica es uno de los principales tratamientos para la obesidad, pero la recuperación de peso después de la cirugía es una cuestión importante. Objetivo: comparar los perfiles clínicos y nutricionales de los buenos y malos respondedores en postoperatorio (PO) tardío de la cirugía bariátrica. Método: estudio transversal con pacientes sometidos a bypass gástrico en Y de Roux en un hospital universitario. La muestra se divide en buenos respondedores (BR) y respuesta deficiente (MR), teniendo en cuenta el porcentaje de pérdida de exceso de peso (PEP) del 50,0%, después de al menos 2 años de PO. Resultados: un total de 204 personas (87,7% mujeres, con una edad media de 50,15 ± 11,1 años y 67,38 ± 30,76 meses después de la operación). Después de 2 años de la operación, el 71,1% se consideraron BR y el 28,9% MR (PEP promedio 72,33 ± 13,86% y 35,06 ± 12,10%, respectivamente) (p &lt; 0,05). La recuperación de peso fue &lt; 10% para el 36,3% de los pacientes, 10,1 a 20% a 36,3% y &gt; 20% a 21,3% en comparación con el menor peso después de la cirugía. Entre MR, el 49,0% recuperó más del 20% del peso más bajo después de la cirugía. El BR perdió la mayor parte de sobrepeso en los diferentes tiempos analizados PO (p &lt; 0,05). El BR mostró mejoría o remisión de la diabetes mellitus, dislipidemia e hipertensión con más frecuencia, en comparación con los MR (p &lt; 0,05). El patrón de dieta fue similar entre la BR y MR (p &gt; 0,05; 100% de la potencia del estudio). La calidad de vida mejoró en el 79,5% del total del grupo, con la mejor evolución en los BR (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusión: la pérdida de peso mayor se correlaciona con la mejora de la remisión de comorbilidades y una mejor calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;33(5): 1108-1115, sept.-oct. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157279</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Buenos y malos respondedores después de bypass gástrico en Y de Roux: perfiles clínicos y nutricionales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22830^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23640^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51221^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
