<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111297</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Knowledge and attitudes as regards living wills between primary and specialised care doctors in the Ferrol health area</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. To evaluate the knowledge, the experience and the attitudes of the health professionals of Primary (PC) and Specialized (SC) Carein our Health Area with respect to Living Wills (LW). Material and method. Descriptive, cross-sectional study, by means of a survey addressed to PC and SC doctors Ferrol (Galicia, Spain) Health Area Results. A total of 120 (42.85%) doctors completed the questionnaire.The professionals self-assessed their level of knowledge with a mean of 3.83 (rank from 0 to 10). Only 21 professionals (17.5%) had objective knowledge of LW, that is to say, they fulfilled the following premises: they had read some pieces of LW legislation, had read an LW document and knew the elements that could figure in it. There were differences that verged on the statistical significance in the objective knowledge between PC and SC doctors (11.7% versus 23.3%, P= .093) and between professionals with under 10 years of professional experience and those with more than 10 years (6.9% versus 21.1%, P=.081). These differences reached statistical significance in some of the items that valued the objective knowledge. A few professionals (28 (23.3%)), had explained to their patients the convenience of having written an LW document, and even fewer (8 (6,7%)) had helped patients with writing one. Conclusions. The knowledge of health care professionals can be clearly improved. The highest deficiency was found between PC professionals and those with less experience. Nevertheless, they showed a favourable attitude towards them(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carballada-Rico, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ameneiros-Lago, Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garrido-Sanjuán, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar los conocimientos, la experiencia y las actitudes de los profesionales sanitarios de Atención Primaria (AP) y Especializada (AE) de nuestra área sanitaria respecto a las instrucciones previas (IP). Material y método. Estudio descriptivo, transversal, por medio de una encuesta dirigida a los médicos de AP y AE del área sanitaria de Ferrol. Resultados. Respondieron 120 médicos (42,85% de respuestas). Los profesionales autopuntuaron su nivel de conocimientos con una media de 3,83 (rango de 0 a 10). Solo 21 (17,5%) tenían conocimientos objetivos sobre las IP, es decir, cumplían las siguientes premisas: habían leído alguna de las leyes sobre IP, habían leído un documento de IP y conocían los elementos que podían quedar recogidos en este. Había diferencias que rozaban la significación estadística en los conocimientos objetivos entre AP y AE (11,7 vs 23,3%, p: 0,093) y entre los profesionales con &lt; de 10 años de ejercicio profesional y aquellos con más de 10 años (6,9 vs 21,1%, p:,081). Estas diferencias alcanzaban la significación estadística en algunos de los ítems que valoraban los conocimientos objetivos. Fueron muy pocos los profesionales que habían expuesto a sus pacientes la conveniencia de tener redactado un documento de IP, solo 28 (23,3%) y menos aún los que habían ayudado al paciente en su redacción, solo 8 (6,7%). En cambio la mayoría de ellos 109 (90,8%) estaban convencidos de su utilidad. Conclusiones. Los conocimientos de los profesionales sanitarios son muy mejorables. El déficit mayor se encontró en los profesionales de AP y aquellos con menos experiencia. Sin embargo, su actitud hacia las mismas es favorable(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;28(2): 109-116, mar.-abr. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conocimientos y actitudes sobre las instrucciones previas de los médicos de Atención Primaria y Especializada del área sanitaria de Ferrol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29008^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29008^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29008^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
