<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99257</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sources of information for parents regarding their children's health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the information that parents are looking for about their children&#146;s health. Material and methods: Descriptive study of the urban population attended at a primary care center by the pediatric services. During a 5-month period, a total of 201 parents came to our consultations and filled out a questionnaire about the information sources that they use regarding their children&#146;s health. Results: 66% of the parents consulted some kind of mass media about health issues. The most widely used are Internet (85%), specialized magazines (36%) and television (18%). 96%of respondents have access to the internet; of these 85% have access at their home. 67% consulted for a medical problem on the Internet during the last year, 93% of these found it helpful. 84% of the parents who had accessed Internet got information through this source about any kind of health problem before and or after visiting the pediatrician or nurse. 45% of the parents were alarmed after reading some medical information in mass media and 65% of these, consulted their doctor or nurse about it. A 98% have more confidence in their pediatrician tha non the Internet. Conclusion: A high percentage of parents have Internet access and uses it to obtain information on health issues about their children. This search is often related to visits by health professionals. Health professionals should be prepared on guiding parents to find information on the Internet(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Bordes, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macias Castellví, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Minguella García, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roqueta del Riego, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castelló Egea, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la información que los padres buscan sobre la salud de sus hijos. Material y métodos: Estudio descriptivo de la población urbana atendida en un centro de atención primaria por el servicio de pediatría. Durante un periodo de 5 meses, un total de 201 padres que acudían a nuestras consultas rellenaron un cuestionario sobre las fuentes de información que utilizan respecto a la salud de sus hijos. Resultados: El 66% de los padres consulta algún medio de comunicación sobre problemas de salud. Los medios más utilizados son Internet (85%), las revistas especializadas (36%) y la televisión (18%). El 96% de respondedores tiene acceso a la red, y de éstos el 85% tiene conexión en casa. El 67% consultó algún problema médico en Internet durante el último año, y de éstos a un 93% le resultó útil. El 84% de los padres que habían consultado Internet en el último año se informaron por este medio de algún problema de salud antes y/o después de visitar a su pediatra/enfermera. Un 45% de los padres se alarmó después de leer alguna información médica en algún medio de comunicación, y un 65% de éstos consultó a su pediatra o enfermera por este motivo. Un 98% confía más en su pediatra que en Internet. Conclusión: Una elevada proporción de padres tiene acceso a Internet y lo utiliza para obtener información sobre temas de salud de sus hijos. Frecuentemente, esta búsqueda está relacionada con las visitas realizadas al personal sanitario. Los profesionales de la salud deberíamos estar preparados para orientar a los padres en la búsqueda de información en la Red(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;69(10): 450-454, nov. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99257</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fuentes de información de los padres respecto a la salud de sus hijos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50099</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52939^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7430^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33921^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54383</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36354</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201111</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
