<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140031</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study on the differences of major pharmaceutical ingredients in different parts and processed medicinal material of Epimedium Brevicornu Maxim in Taihang mountain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to evaluate the medicinal values of different parts of Epimedium brevicornu Maxim. and the effect of processing on major pharmaceutical ingredients in it. The contents of icariin and epimedin C in different parts and processed medicinal material of E. brevicornu in Taihang Mountain were determined with ultrasonic extraction and RP-HPLC. The results indicated that the contents of icariin and epimedin C, respectively 3.4524% and 0.5485%, in the leaf are higher than that in other parts. The contents of icariin and epimedin C, respectively 0.1942 % and 0.1342%, in the stem (include petiole) are the lowest. The contents of these ingredients in the root (include rhizome) are close to that in the leaf. The icariin and epimedin C in all parts of E. brevicornu reduced after processing. The content of icariin in the processed leaf is about 59.5% of that in unprocessed leaves. The effect of prossing on the content of icariin in the stem is unobvious. The content of epimedin C in the processed leaf is about 33.7% of that in unprocessed leaf. The content of epimedin C in the processed stem (include petiole) is about 36.9% of that in unprocessed stem. It is worth to exploit the stem and petiole of E. brevicornu because there are certain contents of pharmaceutical ingredients in them. The firepower should be paid attention to and the temperature should not be very high to avoid the damage on pharmaceutical ingredients in E. brevicornu when process it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Hong-zhi, Chen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zai-you, Jian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gui-fang, Xu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hong-sheng, Wang</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Xi-qiao, Hu</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio pretende evaluar los valores medicinales de diferentes partes de la Epimedium brevicornu Maxim y el efecto de su procesamiento sobre sus principales componentes farmacéuticos. El contenido de icariina y epimedin C en diferentes partes y en material medicinal procesado de Epimedium brevicornu en la montaña de Taihang fue determinado mediante extracción ultrasónica y RP-HPLC. Los resultados indicaron que el contenido de icariina y epimedin C, respectivamente 3,4524% y 0,5485%, en la hoja son mayores que en otras partes. El contenido de icariina y epimedin C, respectivamente 0,1942% y 0,1342%, en el tallo (peciolo incluido) es más bajo. El contenido de estos componentes en la raíz (rizoma incluido) es similar al de la hoja. El contenido de icariina y epimedin C en todas las partes de E. brevicornu se vio reducido después del procesado. El contenido de icariina en la hoja procesada es aproximadamente el 59,5% del de la hoja sin procesar. El efecto del procesado sobre el contenido de icariina en el tallo no es evidente. El contenido de epimedin C en el tallo procesado es de aproximadamente el 33,7% del de la hoja sin procesar. El contenido de epimedin C en el tallo procesado (peciolo incluido) es de aproximadamente el 36,9% de aquel del tallo sin procesar. Vale la pena aprovechar el tallo y peciolo de la E. brevicornu porque hay cierto contenido de componentes farmacéuticos en ellos. Hay que controlar la potencia de fuego y la temperatura no debe ser muy alta para evitar dañar los componentes farmacéuticos de la E. brevicornu (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(2): 913-917, ago. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140031</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio sobre las diferencias de ingredientes farmacéuticos mayor en diferentes partes y procesado medicinal material de epimedium brevicornu maxim en taihang montaña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36754^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36754^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36754^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d433</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2900^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35996^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35996^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2900^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
