<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-142507</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hospital nutritional care: propositions endorsed by the scientific community</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background/objectives: the incidence of hospital undernutrition and its consequences for both the patient and the hospital has demanded procedures that ensure the delivery of good-quality hospital nutritional care. On the basis of literature reports, this study aimed to build a hospital nutritional care propositions that the scientific community later evaluated and endorsed. Methods: forty-one propositions concerning patient clinical nutritional care and hospital food service management by the Hospital Nutrition and Food Service were designed. One hundred professionals, researchers, and professors evaluated the propositions. Agreement with the propositions was analyzed by means of a five-point Likert scale (I strongly disagree; I partially disagree; I have no opinion; I partially agree; I totally agree) associated with each proposition. Agreement was considered to occur when 70% or more of the interviewees agreed (partially or totally) with the proposition. The procedure Proc Corresp of the software SAS 10, version 8, aided descriptive statistics and correspondence analysis. Results: more than 90% of the interviewees completely or partially agreed with 85% (35) of the 41 propositions; between 80 and 90% of the interviewees totally or partially agreed with 15% (6) of the 41 propositions. All the proposed criteria had over 70% agreement (total and partial). The lowest value of total agreement was 70%, attributed to the proposition that suggested patient&#146;s participation in nutritional intervention. Conclusions: the scientific community presented high level of agreement with the hospital nutritional care propositions, which suggested an important consensus about it (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Penaforte, Fernanda Rodrigues de Oliveira</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez-García, Rosa Wanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Japur, Camila Cremonezi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, Edson Zangiacomi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Antecedentes/objetivos: la incidencia de desnutrición hospitalaria y sus consecuencias tanto para el paciente como para el hospital ha exigido procedimientos que aseguren un servicio de atención nutricional hospitalaria de buena calidad. Basado en los informes de la literatura, este estudio tuvo como objetivo construir proposiciones sobre los cuidados nutricionales hospitalarios, que después fueran evaluados y aprobados por la comunidad científica. Métodos: fueron desarrolladas cuarenta y una proposiciones relativas a la atención nutricional clínica del paciente y a la gestión del servicio de alimentación por el Servicio de Alimentación y Nutrición Hospitalaria. Un total de cien profesionales, investigadores y profesores evaluaron las proposiciones. Para analizar si los evaluadores estaban de acuerdo con las proposiciones se utilizó una escala Likert de cinco puntos (estoy en total desacuerdo, estoy parcialmente en desacuerdo, no tengo opinión, estoy parcialmente de acuerdo, estoy totalmente de acuerdo) asociada a cada proposición. Fue considerada concordancia cuando el 70% o más de los evaluadores estaban de acuerdo (totalmente o parcialmente) con la proposición. Para el análisis estadístico fue utilizado el procedimiento Proc Corresp del software SAS 10, versión 8, estadística descriptiva y análisis de correspondencias. Resultados: más del 90% de los entrevistados estaban total o parcialmente de acuerdo con el 85% (35) de las 41 proposiciones; entre el 80 y 90% de los entrevistados estaban total o parcialmente de acuerdo con el 15% (6) de las 41 proposiciones. Todos los criterios propuestos tuvieron más del 70% de concordancia (total y parcial). El menor valor de concordancia total fue del 70%, atribuido a la proposición que sugiere la participación del paciente en la intervención nutricional. Conclusiones: la comunidad científica presentó alto nivel de concordancia con las proposiciones para la atención nutricional hospitalaria, lo que sugiere un importante consenso al respecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(3): 1353-1361, sept. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-142507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Atención nutricional hospitalaria: proposiciones aceptadas por la comunidad científica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5661^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5201</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38344^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10552</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9933^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
