<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123851</identifier>
<setSpec>2174-5544</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Serum endostatins in pre-eclampsia and eclampsia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To compare serum endostatin concentrations in eclamptic, pre-eclamptic and normotensive pregnant women. Materials and method: The study included 30 patients with mild preeclampsia (group A), 30 patients with severe pre-eclampsia (group B), and 30 patients with eclampsia (group C). A control group, consisting of 30 healthy pregnant women of similar age and body mass index to the studiy groups, was selected (group D). Only nuliparous patients were included. Blood samples were collected for serum endostatin determination from all patients before delivery, and from the study groups immediately after diagnosis. Results: Higher values of endostatin were observed in eclamptic patients together with severe pre-eclamptic patients. Lower values were found in mild pre-eclamptic patients. The study groups had significantly higher values of endostatin compared with the control group (P&lt;.05). Linear regression analysis, found that factors that significantly affected plasma endostatin concentrations were uric acid and 24-hour proteinuria. Conclusion: The findings of this study showed that eclamptic and pre-eclamptic patients had higher serum endostatin concentrations than normotensive pregnant women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mejia-Montilla, Jorly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Bolívar, Joel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres-Cepeda, Duly</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Nadia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reyna-Villasmil, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Comparar las concentraciones de endostatina sérica en eclámpticas, preeclámpticas y embarazadas normotensas. Materiales y método: Se incluyó a 30 pacientes con preeclampsia leve (grupo A), a 30 pacientes con preeclampsia grave (grupo B) y a 30 pacientes con eclampsia (grupo C ). El grupo control fue seleccionado por tener edad e índice de masa corporal similares a los de los grupos en estudio y consistió en 30 embarazadas sanas (grupo D). Solo se incluyó a pacientes nulíparas. Las muestras de sangre se recolectaron antes del parto y, en los grupos en estudio, inmediatamente después del diagnóstico para la determinación de endostatina sérica. Resultados: Los valores más altos de endostatina se observaron en el grupo de pacientes eclámpticas junto con las preeclámpticas graves. Se encontraron valores más bajos en las preeclámpticas leves. Los grupos en estudio presentaron valores de endostatina significativamente superiores a los controles (p &lt; 0,05). El análisis de regresión lineal mostró que los factores que afectaban significativamente la concentración plasmática de endostatina fueron el ácido úrico y la proteinuria en 24 h (p &lt; 0,05). Conclusión: Las pacientes eclámpticas y preeclámpticas presentan concentraciones de endostatina sérica más altas que las embarazadas normotensas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Diagn. prenat. (Internet);25(1): 9-14, ene.-jun. 2014.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123851</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Endostatina sérica en preeclampsia y eclampsia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14926^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11662^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38241^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4529^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11946^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
