<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60467</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Blood pH and prolactin levels are lower and correlate in women with vaginal delivery in comparison with those undergoing cesarean section</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction The multiphasic pattern of prolactin (PRL) secretion described during vaginal delivery has not been related to the PRL-inhibiting or -liberating factors that are already known. Objective To determine whether there is a correlation between blood PRL concentrations and pH in women with vaginal delivery compared with those undergoing cesarean delivery. Methods This study included 23 primiparous women, of whom 12 had a vaginal delivery and 11 underwent cesarean delivery. In all patients, seven blood pH and PRL determinations were performed, before and after delivery, from the beginning of the second stage of labor or surgery. Results pH and PRL levels differed between the two groups (p&lt;0.05). In the cesarean delivery group, no changes in pH or PRL concentrations were observed. In the vaginal delivery group, PRL levels were higher 45min after the onset of the second stage of labor and at delivery compared with initial values (p&lt;0.05). Likewise, pH levels were lower 15min after the onset of the second stage until 21min after delivery (p&lt;0.001). A strong correlation was found between pH and PRL at delivery and at 7 and 14min after delivery (p&lt;0.05).Discussion The results of this study confirm the existence of a biphasic PRL secreting pattern during the second stage of labor. This pattern correlates with the reduction in pH levels that occurs during this period (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Chéquer, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quinzaños Fresnedo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carranza Lira, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción El patrón multifásico de prolactina (PRL) que ocurre durante el parto no ha podido relacionarse con factores inhibidores y liberadores de PRL ya conocidos. Objetivo Determinar si hay correlación entre las concentraciones séricas de PRL y el pH sanguíneo en las pacientes que tienen un parto vaginal, en comparación con las que se someten a cesárea. Métodos Se incluyó a un total de 23 mujeres primigestas, de las que 12 tuvieron un parto eutócico y 11 se sometieron a cesárea. A todas ellas se realizaron 7 determinaciones de pH y PRL antes y después del nacimiento, a partir del inicio del segundo peíodo del trabajo de parto o la cirugía, según el caso. Resultados Los valores de PRL y pH fueron diferentes en ambos grupos (p&lt;0,05). En el grupo de cesárea no se observaron cambios en el pH y la PRL. En el grupo de pacientes que tuvieron un parto, los valores de PRL fueron superiores a los 45min del expulsivo y en el momento de parto, comparados con los iniciales (p&lt;0,05). Asimismo, los valores de pH fueron menores a partir de 15min del período expulsivo hasta 21min posparto (p&lt;0,001). Se encontró una fuerte correlación entre el pH y la PRL, en el momento del parto y a los 7 y los 14min posparto (p&lt;0,05).Discusión Se corroboró la existencia de una secreción bifásica de PRL durante el período expulsivo, la misma que se correlaciona con la disminución en los valores de pH que ocurre durante este período (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);36(3): 87-93, mayo-jun. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60467</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los valores de pH y prolactina sanguíneos se correlacionan y son menores en las mujeres que tienen un parto en comparación con las sometidas a cesárea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7014</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1967</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9082^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11821^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37660^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2625^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
