<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-82604</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Fluid intake and dehydration in professional indoor football players depending on the specific position on the field</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectivesDehydration is one of the leading causes of the reduction in physical and mental performance, due to an insufficient fluid intake whilst playing. In team sports, fluid intake and level of dehydration can be influenced by the specific position of player. The objective of this work has been to determine the quantity of fluid intake and level of dehydration of goalkeepers, defenders and forwards.MethodsFluid intake and body mass loss was measured in 3 goalkeepers, 5 defenders and 6 forwards from Elpozo Murcia Fútbol Sala during three official matches in the Liga Nacional de Fútbol Sala (LNFS).ResultsResults showed that goalkeepers drank the least amount of liquid (1205±333.32ml) opposite defenders (1446±735.88ml) and forwards (1747.33±789.28 ml). Goalkeepers and forwards reached the highest dehydration (1.27±0.61% and 1.27±1.1%), followed by defenders (0.56±1.04%). Fluid intake by goalkeepers and forwards was insufficient to compensate for losses caused by sweating, finishing the matches with levels of dehydration which gave rise to a reduction of performance, while defenders maintained their hydration.ConclusionsFluid replacement strategies should be based on individual characteristics of players. It has been shown that there is variability of results within the same sport, even within a specific position(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Jiménez, José Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pellicer, Juan José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yuste Lucas, Juan Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivosLa deshidratación es una de las causas principales de la reducción del rendimiento de los deportistas, debido a una insuficiente ingesta de líquidos durante la práctica. En deportes de equipo, la ingesta de líquido así como el nivel de deshidratación alcanzado por un jugador puede estar influenciado por la posición que ocupe en el campo. El objetivo de este estudio ha sido cuantificar la cantidad de líquido ingerido y el nivel de deshidratación en porteros, defensores y atacantes de fútbol sala durante la disputa de tres partidos oficiales.MétodosLa cantidad de líquido ingerido y el porcentaje de peso perdido fue medido en 3 porteros, 5 defensores y 6 atacantes, pertenecientes a la primera plantilla de Elpozo Murcia Turística Fútbol Sala, durante la disputa de 3 partidos correspondientes a la Liga Nacional de Fútbol Sala.ResultadosLos resultados mostraron como son los porteros quienes menos líquido ingirieron (1.205±333,32ml) frente a defensores (1.446±735,88ml) y atacantes (1.747,33±789,28ml). Porteros y atacantes alcanzaron un porcentaje mayor de pérdida de peso (1,27±0,61% y 1,27±1,1%), seguidos por defensores (0,55±1,1%). La ingesta de líquido en porteros y atacantes fue insuficiente para compensar las pérdidas producidas por sudoración, alcanzando niveles de deshidratación que suponen una reducción del rendimiento, mientras que los defensores mantuvieron niveles de euhidratación.ConclusionesLas estrategias de reposición hídrica deberán estar basadas en las características individuales de cada jugador, puesto que existe gran variabilidad en los resultados dentro de un mismo deporte, e incluso dentro de un mismo puesto específico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);45(166): 69-74, abr.-jun. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-82604</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ingesta de líquidos y deshidratación en jugadores profesionales de fútbol sala en función de la posición ocupada en el terreno de juego</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3694^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5574^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
