<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2321</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-5735</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder: a socio-cultural approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) has become one of the most commonly diagnosed mental disorders in the world. This article takes into account the elements that most of the contemporary studies of this disorder have not examined in great depth. It seeks to address the socio-cultural components surrounding this syndrome, which cannot be reduced to neurobiological or congenital deficits. The concepts of autonomy and self-control within Western individualistic societies allow framing a series of cultural polarities (vice/virtue) where the diagnosis of this disorder and its support in the collective imagination and the prevailing social discourses take place. In addition, these concepts help to understand the possible advantages that this diagnosis may involve. The polarities of parenting style and the concept of school failure are two elements that may contribute to keeping ADHD alive as a child pathology that is being increasingly diagnosed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Londoño Paredes, Diego Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad (TDAH) se ha convertido en uno de los trastornos mentales más diagnosticados en el mundo. Este artículo trata de tomar en consideración elementos que la mayoría de los estudios contemporáneos sobre este trastorno no han examinado en profundidad. En concreto, trata de abordar los componentes socio-culturales que rodean a este síndrome, que no se puede reducir únicamente a déficits neurobiológicos o congénitos. Los conceptos de autonomía y de autocontrol dentro de las sociedades individualistas occidentales permiten enmarcar una serie de polaridades culturales (vicio/virtud) en las que tiene lugar el diagnóstico de este trastorno y su sostenimiento dentro del imaginario colectivo y los discursos sociales predominantes. Asimismo, ayudan a entender las posibles ventajas que conlleva este diagnóstico. Las polaridades del estilo de crianza y el concepto de fracaso escolar son dos elementos que pueden contribuir a mantener vivo el TDAH como patología mayoritariamente infantil de diagnóstico creciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Neuropsiquiatr;37(132): 477-496, jul.-dic. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2321</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El trastorno por déficit de atención con hiperactividad: una mirada socio-cultural</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
