<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93251</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Theoretical models and nursing students: motivational aspects for election in clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The theoretical and philosophical nursing is complex, there are a large number of nursing theories, some difficult to understand, because this usually its practical application is restricted. Aim. To identify the theoretical model of nursing students say they use in clinical practice, the motivation for their choice, and school where they were pursuing their studies. Subjects and methods. Descriptive study. Participants were 105 students doing school practice during the academic year 2006-2007 (of a total population of 108 students). The study variables were the nursing models and theories, the reasons for the choice and demographic variables. Data collection was conducted through a questionnaire completed during their clinical experience. The analysis of data using a thematic analysis of text, categorizing to finally create an explanatory framework. Results and conclusions. The model chosen is mainly that of Virginia Henderson. The motivations for the election as students are used in university education and ease of implementation of the model. It was evident confusion between the terms related to nursing model and methodology (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Parra, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Ruiz, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Rueda, Guadalupe</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abril-Sabater, Dolors</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varez-Pelaez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bardallo-Porras, Lola</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zabalegui-Yárnoz, Adela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás-Sábado, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Donaire, Lidia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El cuerpo teórico y filosófico de enfermería es complejo; existen un gran número de teorías enfermeras, algunas de difícil comprensión, por lo que habitualmente su aplicación práctica se ve restringida. Objetivo. Identificar el modelo teórico de enfermería que los estudiantes dicen utilizar durante las prácticas clínicas, la motivación para su elección, y la escuela universitaria donde estaban cursando sus estudios. Sujetos y métodos. Estudio descriptivo en el que participaron 105 estudiantes (de una población total de 108) que realizaban prácticas de enfermería en el hospital durante el curso 2006-2007. La variables de estudio fueron los modelos teóricos enfermeros, las razones de la elección y variables sociodemográficas. La recogida de datos se llevo a cabo mediante un cuestionario cumplimentado durante su experiencia clínica. El análisis de los datos se realizó mediante un análisis temático de texto, categorizando para crear finalmente un marco explicativo. Resultados y conclusiones. El modelo elegido es principalmente el de Virginia Henderson. Las motivaciones para la elección, según los estudiantes, son su uso en la enseñanza universitaria y la facilidad de ejecución del modelo. Se evidenció confusión entre los términos &#145;modelo conceptual y/o teórico&#146; y &#145;metodología enfermera&#146; (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);14(2): 119-127, jun. 2011. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93251</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Modelos teóricos y estudiantes de enfermería: aspectos motivacionales para su elección durante las prácticas clínicas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4574^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2806</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9152</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
