<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166775</identifier>
<setSpec>1131-3587</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What do the guidelines say?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Antithrombotic treatment of acute coronary syndrome has merited the publication of carefully designed clinical practice guidelines, most notably by the leading cardiologists&#146; associations in Europe and the United States of America. However, their recommendations do not always coincide, not only because of small differences in interpretation of evidence from clinical trials but also because of chronological differences in the publication of the guidelines. The aim of this article was to summarize the information provided by current guidelines on this important topic, which is the focus of this issue of REVISTA ESPAÑOLA DE CARDIOLOGÍA SUPLEMENTOS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salvador Sanz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El tratamiento antitrombótico del síndrome coronario agudo ha merecido la publicación de guías de práctica clínica cuidadosamente diseñadas, lideradas por las asociaciones de cardiólogos más importantes de Europa y Estados Unidos. Sus recomendaciones no siempre coinciden debido no sólo a pequeñas diferencias en la interpretación de la evidencia proporcionada por los ensayos clínicos, sino también a diferencias cronológicas en la publicación de las guías. El presente artículo resume la información proporcionada por las guías actuales sobre el importante tema tratado en este número de REVISTA ESPAÑOLA DE CARDIOLOGÍA SUPLEMENTOS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cardiol. Supl. (Ed. impresa);10(supl.D): 29d-33d, 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166775</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Qué dicen las guías?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23279^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22965^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5478^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52613^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32647^s22006</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27951^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201000</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
