<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134288</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-282X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Introduction of an accreditation system for hospital informed consent forms</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe an accreditation system for informed consent forms (ICF) in a tertiary hospital, as an intervention to improve their quality, and to check the improvements achieved. Material and methods: Following an external evaluation of the ICF quality in a public hospital in Murcia (Spain), an accreditation committee set the ICF requirements and associated procedures. Effectiveness is assessed by comparing two external evaluations carried out by the EMCA Program (2011 and 2013) and based on 19 criteria and a sample of 60 ICF for every public hospital in Murcia Region. Results: To be accredited, every ICF must meet the 19 external criteria plus 5 based on legibility, readability and scientific and technical validity. A form to fill in the contents of every ICF was agreed, which would be reviewed, approved and validated for five years. Before the implementation, 8.2 defects/ICF were detected. The accreditation system obtained an 89% improvement (0.9 defects/ICF) and achieved significant improvements in 18 criteria, 16 of which are benchmarked. Discussion: The accreditation system achieved a substantial improvement in the ICF (obtaining a better result in external evaluations) and guarantees their contents, legibility and readability. This system needs to be extended to other hospitals, since it is not clear whether common ICFs would be suitable. However, this improvement is structural and does not guarantee that the overall information/consent procedure is done properly, thus complementary strategies for measurement and improvement are required (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>López-Picazo, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valverde-Iniesta, JJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle-Urra, JE</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Parra-Hidalgo, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tomás-Garcia, N</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la creación y funcionamiento de un sistema de acreditación de documentos de consentimiento informado (DCI) como intervención para mejorar su calidad formal y comprobar la mejora obtenida. Material y métodos: Tras una evaluación externa de la calidad de los DCI en un hospital de Murcia (España), se consensuaron los requisitos para los DCI y se diseñaron procedimientos de acreditación y uso. La efectividad se valoró comparando 2 evaluaciones externas del Programa EMCA (2011 y 2013), basadas en 19 criterios y muestras de 60 DCI para cada hospital público de la región. Resultados: Para ser acreditado un DCI debería cumplir 24 criterios: los 19 utilizados en evaluaciones externas, más 3 sobre legibilidad y 2 sobre validez científico-técnica. Se acordó un formulario para implementar los contenidos de cada DCI, que serían revisados y aprobados con vigencia de 5 años. Inicialmente se detectaron 8,2 defectos/DCI. La mejora obtenida fue del 89% (0,9 defectos/DCI), evidenciado mejoras significativas en 18 criterios y marcando benchmark para 16 de los 19 evaluados. Discusión: La acreditación supuso una mejora sustancial de los DCI del hospital (obteniendo el mejor resultado en las evaluaciones externas de su servicio de salud) y garantiza su contenido, legibilidad y comprensión. Ello obliga a valorar la conveniencia de su extensión a otros hospitales, aunque no esté clara la bondad de disponer de DCI comunes. Sin embargo, esta mejora es estructural y no garantiza que la globalidad del proceso de información/consentimiento que soporta se realice adecuadamente, precisando estrategias complementarias para su medición y mejora (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. calid. asist;30(2): 55-63, mar.-abr. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134288</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Introducción de un sistema de acreditación para los documentos de consentimiento informado hospitalario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7435^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d72^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37688^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
