<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-042051</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">6-year experience with extra peritoneal lumbar laparoscopic surgery. Indications, complications, and results in a reference Southamerican center</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: To report the experience in lumbar extraperitoneal laparoscopy surgery obtained while perfectioning the technique over a six-year period. METHODS: We perform a prospective study with 168 cases of extra peritoneal laparoscopic surgery for the treatment of various kidney-ureter and adrenal diseases between 1999 and 2004. Operations were classified by organ and complexity (ablative or reconstructive). We describe the number of cases, surgical time, mayor and minor complications, number of open conversions, hospital stay, time to return to daily-life activities, advantages and disadvantages, as well as comparative analysis with data from bibliography. RESULTS: Extraperitoneal access was employed in 168 laparoscopic operations: 44 renal biopsies, 8 renal cyst marsupializations, 49 nephrectomies (22 benign diseases/27 neoplasias).15 nephroureterectomies.22 adrenalectomies.15 pyelolithotomies/ureterolithotomies, 1 neprhropexy, 2 partial nephrectomies.11 pyeloplasties and 1 correction of retrocaval ureter. Operative time decreased significant only after the initial adaptation, with an average of 118 minutes in 138 ablative operations and 163 minutes in 30 reconstructive procedures. There was only one conversion in the second case of the series. The incidence of mayor and minor complications was 5.07% and 4.34% respectively for ablative surgery and 3.33% and 6.66% for reconstructive surgery. Average hospital stay varied from 1-4 days. Return to daily life activities took an average of 7 to 30 days in relation with procedure complexity. CONCLUSIONS: Lumbar extra peritoneal laparoscopic access is an excellent option of minimally invasive approach to ablative surgery, offering the advantages of avoidance of the peritoneal cavity and low complication index. Reconstructive surgery is feasible but technically more challenging, depending of the ability and adaptation of the surgeon to a smaller surgical workspace</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lasmar, Marco Tulio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rincón Ríos, Freddy</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaz Juliano, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wroclawski, Eric Roger</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tobias-Machado, Marcos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herminio Forseto, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Presentar la experiencia en cirugíalaparoscópica lumbar extraperitoneal obtenida conel perfeccionamiento de la técnica durante un períodode 6 años.MÉTODOS: Se realizó un estudio prospectivo con 168casos operados entre 1999 y 2004 a través de cirugíalaparoscópica con acceso extraperitoneal paradiversas patologías reno-ureterales y adrenales. Las cirugíasfueron subdivididas de acuerdo al órgano comprometidoy a la complejidad del procedimento (ablativoo reconstrutivo). Se describieron el número decasos operados, tiempo quirúrgico, índice de complicacionesmayores y menores, número de conversionespara acceso convencional, período de hospitalización,tiempo de retorno a las actividades habituales, las ventajasy desventajas, así como tambien análisis deacuerdo con los datos de la literatura.RESULTADOS: El acceso extraperitoneal fue empleadoen 168 cirugías laparoscópicas, siendo 44 biopsiasrenales, 8 marsupializaciones de quiste renal, 49nefrectomías (22 por enfermedades benignas y 27 porneoplasias), 15 nefroureterectomías, 22 adrenalectomías,15 pielolito/ureterolitotomías, 1 nefropexia, 2nefrectomías parciales, 11 pieloplastias y 1 correcciónde ureter retrocavo. El tiempo quirúrgico se redujo significativamentedespués del período de adaptación inicial,con un promedio de 110 min para 138 cirugíasablativas y de 163 min para 30 procedimientosreconstructivos. Hubo apenas una conversión en el 2.ocaso operado. La tasa de complicaciones mayores ymenores fue de 5,07% y 4,34% respectivamente parael total de cirugías ablativas y de 3,33% y 6,66% parael total de cirugías reconstrutivas. El tiempo promediode hospitalización global varió de 1 a 4 días. El retornoa las actividades habituales se dio en un promediode 7 a 30 días de post-operatorio, de acuerdo a lacomplejidad de la cirugía.CONCLUSIONES: El acceso laparoscópico lumbarextraperitoneal es una excelente opción de abordajemínimamente invasivo para cirugías ablativas, presentandolas ventajas al no violarse la cavidad peritoneal,con bajo índice de complicaciones. Las cirugías reconstrutivasson factíbles, pero técnicamente más difíciles,dependiendo de la habilidad y adaptación del cirujanoa un menor espacio de trabajo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;58(7): 657-664, sept. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-042051</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seis años de experiencia en cirugía laparoscópica lumbar extraperitoneal: indicaciones, complicaciones y resultados en un centro iberoamericano de referencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d318^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d318^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9585^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
