<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-67332</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-0095</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Levosimendan is the only calcium sensitiser currently used at clinical level. Its primary indication is decompensated heart failure, and although its effectiveness has been demonstrated in the medical patient, use in the surgical patient has been more restricted. Nevertheless, new publications have appeared in high risk situations, such as septic shock and cardiogenic shock. Other drug effects has been reported, which we believe deserve more attention, as the cardioprotective effect and the anti-myocardial stunning effect. Throughout this review, we intend to analyse the new contributions of this undoubtedly complex drug but, in our opinion, very useful in some situations (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caruezo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garea, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguirre, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Veiras, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Taboada, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masid, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marcos, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blanco, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El levosimendán es el único sensibilizante del calcio utilizado actualmente en la clínica. Su indicación fundamental es la descompensación de la insuficiencia cardiaca, y aunque su eficacia está demostrada en el paciente médico, su uso en el paciente quirúrgico ha sido mucho más restringido, a pesar de lo que ha ido apareciendo en publicaciones en situaciones de evidente riesgo para los enfermos, como son el shock séptico y el shock cardiogénico, y se han descrito algunos efectos, que en nuestra opinión merecen más atención como el efecto cardioprotector y antiaturdimiento miocárdico. A lo largo de esta revisión, pretendemos analizar las nuevas aportaciones aparecidas sobre este fármaco complejo sin duda, pero en nuestra opinión muy útil en algunas situaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actual. anestesiol. reanim;18(2): 55-63, abr.-jun. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-67332</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30170</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2357^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
