<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-72521</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-invasive ventilation after cardiac surgery. A prospective study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To report our experience with non-invasive ventilation (NIV) after cardiac surgery. Materials and methods: Prospective study of cardiac surgery patients admitted to our PICU between 2004 and 2007 who required NIV after extubation. Results: A total of 331 patients were admitted to the unit after cardiac surgery during this period. Of these, 159 were extubated in the operatin groom. NIV was introduced in 29 episodes on 26 patients. Fallot&#146;s tetralogy and AVD were the most common heart diseases, and 65% had type II respiratory failure. The respiratory problems usually involved were acute pulmonary oedema and atelectasis. Indication was elective in 70% of episodes. BiPAP Vision was the common est ventilator used and in the S/T mode(56%). Average length of use was 64h. Average length of stay in PICU was 22 days. Nine patients required reintubation, none of them at an early stage (first12h) which represents an efficiency of 66%. The effectiveness of NIV was related to the type of disease and inversely with the time NIV was needed. There were complications in 12 episodes. Four patients required tracheostomy, all of which were associated with previous lung disease. Survival was 100%. Conclusions: NIV is effective and safe after cardiac surgery. It has very good results in respiratory failure due to atelectasis or pulmonary oedema. NIV failure in these patients is strongly associated with preoperative pulmonary sequelae secondary to heart disease. NIV indication in these patients has to be carefully evaluated (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Piqueras Marimbaldo, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura Matute, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Balaguer Argallo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pons Ódena, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Palomeque Rico, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Describir según la experiencia de los autores el uso de la ventilación no invasiva (VNI) en pacientes postoperados cardíacos. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo de los pacientes postoperados cardíacos ingresados en la unidad de cuidados intensivos pediátricos (UCIP) entre los años 2004 y 2007 que precisaron VNI tras extubación. Resultados: Durante este período se intervinieron de cirugía cardíaca 331 pacientes, de los cuales 159 pacientes llegaron extubados a la unidad. Se aplicó VNI en 29 episodios sobre 26 pacientes. Las cardiopatías más frecuentes fueron Fallot y canal auriculoventricular. Diecinueve (65%) pacientes presentaron fallo respiratorio (FR) de tipo II y el resto presentó FR de tipo I. Los problemas respiratorios más frecuentes fueron el edema agudo de pulmón (EAP) y la atelectasia. En un 70% de los episodios la indicación fue electiva. El tipo de respirador más utilizado fue el BiPAP Vision y, en cuanto a la modalidad, la más utilizada fue el Spontaneous/Timed que supuso el 56%. La duración media de la VNI fue de 64h (rango de 41 a 88h). Los pacientes tuvieron una estancia media en la UCIP de 22 días. Nueve pacientes requirieron reintubación, ninguno de ellos de forma precoz (primeras 12h), lo que supone una eficacia del 66%. La eficacia de la VNI se correlacionó con el tipo de enfermedad y de forma inversa con las horas de uso de ésta. Se presentaron complicaciones en 12 episodios. Cuatro pacientes requirieron traqueostomía, todos ellos presentaban neumopatía asociada a hiperaflujo pulmonar previo. No falleció ningún paciente. Conclusiones: La VNI es eficaz y segura durante el postoperatorio cardíaco. Su eficacia es muy alta en caso de atelectasia o de EAP. El fracaso de la VNI se asocia de forma destacada a la afectación pulmonar previa a la cirugía, secundaria a la cardiopatía. Debe plantearse con cautela la indicación de la VNI en este subgrupo de pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);71(1): 13-19, jul. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-72521</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de ventilación no invasiva en pacientes postoperados cardíacos. Estudio retrospectivo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23699</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12552^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11621^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1270^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12091^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200907</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
