<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-61403</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-3334</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study is to examine the psychopathological consequences ofcohabiting with someone suffering from a personality disorder. The families of thesepatients, who play a key role, especially in treatment support, face a pathology whichhas repercussions, at least, for their own health and, eventually, for their quality of life.44 subjects were selected and divided into two groups according to whether they wereregular carers for someone with a personality disorder or not. The subjects completedSymptom Checklist-90-R (Derogatis, 1994) and were interviewed to capture details about themselves and their families and about any illness suffered by both the carer andthe patient suffering the personality disorder. The results indicate that the carer grouppresents more psychopathological symptoms than the control group, the most prominentbeing anxiety, depression, obsession, hostility and psychoticism(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, Nagore</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio tiene como objetivo conocer las consecuencias psicopatológicas quetiene el hecho de convivir con un enfermo con trastorno de personalidad. Las familiasde estos enfermos, que se constituyen en una pieza clave en el apoyo al tratamiento,deben hacer frente a una patología que, a menudo, repercute en su propia salud y, porende, en su calidad de vida. Para ello, fueron seleccionados 44 sujetos divididos endos grupos según fueran o no cuidadores habituales de un enfermo con trastorno depersonalidad, a los que les fue aplicado el Cuestionario de 90 Síntomas, SCL-90-R, deDerogatis (1994), además de una entrevista que recogía datos personales, familiares ysobre la enfermedad tanto del cuidador como del sujeto diagnosticado de trastorno depersonalidad. Los resultados indican que los sujetos cuidadores presentan una mayorcantidad de síntomas psicopatológicos, siendo los más destacados los de tipo ansioso,depresivo, obsesivo, hostilidad y psicoticismo(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apuntes psicol;27(1): 79-86, ene.-abr. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-61403</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síntomas psicopatológicos en familias cuidadoras de un enfermo con trastorno de personalidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10745^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6945</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
