<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-125632</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intervention through auditory feedback to improve balance in women who do physical activity</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Balance is an essential aspect of daily living and sport appearance. The deterioration of this capacity may cause disorder or injury from falls. The objective of this intervention is to determine the influence of proprioceptive exercise program with external auditory feedback on balance improvement. It involved eight women (M = 38 years, SD = 11.45) who performed constant exercise, divided into two groups. Group 1 program and auditory feedback, group 2 single program. A team of auditory feedback that was used for group 1 was created. Results in Group 1 had a significant improvement in measured equilibrium with the following tests: Functional Reach (p = .036), Get Up and Go (p = .021) and Dynamic Bar test (p = .044). According to the results, the two groups displayed an improvement in the balance by the proprioceptive program, but it was group 1, with auditory feedback, which shown the greatest improvement. The proprioceptive program along with auditory feedback can improve balance significant (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Estrada Contreras, Omar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Córdoba, Eugenio A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chillón Martínez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sobrino Sánchez, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El equilibrio es un aspecto fundamental para las actividades de la vida diaria y para el deporte. El deterioro en esta capacidad puede ocasionar trastornos o lesiones por caídas. El objetivo de esta intervención es determinar la influencia de un programa de ejercicios propioceptivos con feedback externo auditivo sobre la mejora del equilibrio. Participaron ocho mujeres (M = 38 años, DE = 11.45) que realizaban ejercicio constante, dividas en dos grupos. Grupo 1 programa y feedback auditivo, grupo 2 solo programa. Se creó un equipo de feedback auditivo que fue utilizado para el grupo 1. En los resultados el Grupo 1 tuvo la mejoría significativa en equilibrio medido con los siguientes test: Functional Reach (p = .036), Get Up and Go (p = .021) y Test Dinámico en Barra (p = .044). De acuerdo a los resultados obtenidos, los dos grupos presentan una mejoría en el equilibrio por el programa propioceptivo, pero es el grupo 1 con feedback auditivo, el que tuvo la mayor mejoría. El programa propioceptivo unido a feedback auditivo puede mejorar significativamente el equilibrio (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;23(2): 327-335, jul.-dic. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-125632</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención mediante feedback auditivo para la mejora del equilibrio en mujeres que realizan actividad física</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11866^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34332^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53749</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30524^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
