<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76510</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Patients in haemodialysis are more and more elderly, increasing the complications in their vascular access. Tunnelled permanent catheters (PC) are a good option, but present dysfunctions and/or infections, with a high rate of morbidity. Nursing plays a fundamental role in minimizing this risk, so we believe that it could be useful to monitor it and establish protocols from the multidisciplinary viewpoint. Our objectives were: to evaluate the usefulness of systematic monitoring of TPC; to compare the rate of infection and dysfunction between two types of TPC; to identify variables associated with infection; and to evaluate the existence of a relationship between infection and dysfunction. We studied 52 PC: 28 Opti-Flow® and 24 Schon-Cath®, fitted in 14 women and 30 men with an average age of72.3 among patients with Schon-Cath and 73.6 among those with Opti-Flow. The studied variables are: complications in fitting, problems in functioning and infection. Data were collected in a base placed in a network and implemented on line by nursing, nephrologists and radiologists. The results indicated: 1. An overall rate of 0.79 bacteraemia related to the catheter (BRC) / 1000 days of catheter, presenting a larger number of cases of infection with the Schon-Cath®.2. The Opti-Flow® show a high rate of radiological interventions and/or changes and a greater possibility of spontaneous loss.3. We note a relationship between handling and infection, closer in the Schon-Cath®, and attributable to greater problems of artery flow and venous pressure.4. The survival of the catheter increases with the administration of urokinase (UK) and radiological intervention (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Falcó, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ibeas López, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz Busqueta, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moya Mejía, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mañé Buixó, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Yuste Jiménez, Elios</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perandreu, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fortuño, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Ros, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García García, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los pacientes en hemodiálisis son cada vez más años, aumentando las complicaciones en su acceso vascular. Los catéteres permanentes (CP) tunelizados son una buena opción, pero presentan disfunciones y/o infecciones, provocando una alta morbilidad. Enfermería tiene un papel fundamental para minimizar este riesgo por lo que pensamos que su seguimiento y protocolización desde la multidisciplinaridad puede ser útil. Nuestros objetivos fueron: valorar la utilidad del seguimiento sistemático del CPT, comparar tasa de infección y disfunción entre dos tipos de CPT, identificar variables asociadas a la infección y valorar existencia de relación entre infección y disfunción. Estudiamos 52 CPT: 28 Opti-Flow® y 24 Schon-Cath®, colocados en 14 mujeres y 30 hombres con una media de edad de 72,3 años en los pacientes con Schon-Cathy 73,6 en los pacientes con Opti-Flow. Las variables estudiadas son: complicaciones en la colocación, problemas de funcionamiento e infección. Se recogieron datos en una base puesta en red e implementada online por enfermería, nefrólogos y radiólogos. Los resultados indicaron: 1. Una tasa global de 0,79 bacteriemias relacionadas con el catéter (BRC) / 1000 días de catéter, presentando un mayor número de casos de infección el Schon-Cath®.2. Los Opti-Flow® presentan una alta incidencia de intervenciones radiológicas y/o recambio y más posibilidad de salida espontánea. 3. Observamos una relación entre manipulación e infección, mayor en el Schon-Cath®, atribuible a mayores problemas de flujos arteriales y presiones venosas. 4. La supervivencia del catéter aumenta con la administración de urokinasa (UK) e intervención radiológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;9(3): 165-171, jul.-sept. 2006. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76510</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Monitorización sistemática del catéter permanente: una herramienta útil en el estudio de la tasa de infección y disfunción en dos tipos de catéteres tunelizados para hemodiálisis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29407^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29867</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
