<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-76007</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-4853</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of the experience and of out-of-hospital stroke code in thrombolytic treatment of acute stroke</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. We present the experience for thrombolytictreatment using recombinant tisular plasminogenactivator (rt-PA) at a university hospital. We analyze theinfluence of individual and collective acquired experienceand of the activation of an out-of-hospital stroke code(OSC) on the delays to onset of treatment, number ofpatients treated and outcome.Method. Prospective register of patients with ischemicstroke treated with rt-PA within the period 1/2004-12/2006. Comparison of results between patients treatedduring the three years of study and based on the individualexperience of the neurologist who applies the treatmentand on the patients treated with or without activationof OSC.Results. A total of 87 patients were treated (meanage: 66.6±13.7). Door-to-needle time was 79±21 min in2004, 64±22 in 2005 and 63±26 in 2006 (p=0.003).Experienced neurologists started thrombolysis sooner(door-to-needle time: 62±22 min vs 75±27, p=0.03).Activation of the ESC reduced door-to-needle time (53±17 min vs 65±21; p=0.032) and door-to-computed tomographyscan time (21±10 min vs 29±24; p=0.016). Therewere no differences in outcome in the different groups.Conclusions. Individual and collective acquired experienceand the activation of an OSC can lower in-hospitaldelays. This contributes to increasing the number of patientseligible for thrombolysis. Thrombolytic therapy issafe and effective even when it is applied by inexperiencedneurologists if strict guidelines are followed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso de Leciñana, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz Sánchez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Masjuán, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Culebras, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Barragán, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sendón, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zarza, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Se presenta la experiencia en el tratamientodel ictus isquémico con activador del plasminógeno tisularrecombinante (rt-PA) en un hospital universitario. Seevalúa la influencia de la curva de aprendizaje, individual ycolectiva, y de la activación del código ictus extrahospitalario(CIE) en las demoras hasta el inicio del tratamiento, en elnúmero de pacientes tratados y en su evolución.Método. Registro prospectivo de pacientes con ictus isquémicotratados con rt-PA entre enero de 2004 y diciembrede 2006. Análisis comparativo entre los pacientes tratadosen los 3 años del estudio y en función de la experienciadel neurólogo que aplica el tratamiento, así como en pacientestratados con o sin activación del CIE.Resultados. Se trataron 87 pacientes (66,6±13,7 años).El tiempo puerta-aguja fue de 79±21 min en 2004, 64±22 minen 2005 y 63±26 min en 2006 (p=0,003). Los neurólogoscon experiencia aplicaron el tratamiento más rápido (tiempopuerta-aguja: 62±22 frente a 75±27 min; p=0,03). La activacióndel CIE redujo el tiempo puerta-aguja (53±17 frentea 65±21 min; p=0,032) y el tiempo puerta-tomografíacomputarizada (21±10 frente a 29±24 min; p=0,016). Nohubo diferencias en la evolución de los pacientes en los distintosgrupos.Conclusión. La experiencia adquirida y la activación delCIE disminuyen las demoras intrahospitalarias, contribuyendoa aumentar el número de pacientes tratados con trombólisis.El tratamiento trombolítico es seguro y eficaz, inclusosi se aplica por neurólogos sin experiencia si se siguencriterios estrictos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neurologia;23(6): 349-355, jul.-ago.  2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-76007</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la curva de aprendizaje y del código ictus extrahospitalario en el tratamiento trombolítico del ictus agudo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d26532</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23425^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24892^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200808</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
