<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047168</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Epidemiology of anesthesia in Catalonia, Spain, in 2003</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: This article provides an epidemiological description of anesthesia practice in Catalonia, Spain, in 2003. Patients and method: Descriptive data on sex, age, and physical status of patients according to American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) classification were taken from responses to the questionnaire used in the ANESCAT 2003 survey. The results were extrapolated to the population of Catalonia in 2003 and the annual rates of anesthesia per 100 inhabitants calculated. Results: Based on the 23,136 completed questionnaires collected in the ANESCAT 2003 survey, it is estimated that 603,189 anesthetic procedures were performed in Catalonia (95% confidence interval [CI], 579,010-627,368). The annual rate of anesthesia was 9 per 100 inhabitants (95% CI, 8.6-9.4). Women represented 58% of the population in which anesthesia was performed. The median (10th-90th percentile) age was 52 (21-78) years and anesthetic procedures performed in patients over the age of 60 accounted for 39.3% of the total. The largest number of anesthetic procedures was performed in the 70 to 74 year age bracket (56,000 procedures). Below the age of 14, more males than females received anesthesia, while above that age the majority of patients were female. The highest rate of anesthesia was in men aged between 75 and 79 years (22.0%) and the lowest was in girls aged between 10 and 14 years (1.8%). The percentage of patients with an ASA class of 3 or more was 26.7%. Physical status was worse in male than in female patients. Forty-seven percent of all anesthetic procedures were performed in the city of Barcelona. Conclusions: The annual rate of anesthesia in Catalonia was 9 per 100 inhabitants, and was almost 3 times higher in the city of Barcelona than in the rest of the geographical area. Comparison with data from other European countries revealed higher severity and a larger proportion of women and older patients in Catalonia</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sabaté, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lucas, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Canet, Jaume</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayoral, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Descripción epidemiológica de la actividad anestésica y su incidencia sobre la población de Cataluña (España) en el año 2003. Pacientes y método: Se utilizaron los datos descriptivos del cuestionario empleado en la encuesta ANESCAT 2003 correspondientes a sexo, edad y estado físico de los pacientes según la escala de la American Society of Anesthesiologists (clase ASA). Los resultados se relacionaron con la población de Cataluña en 2003 y se calcularon las tasas anuales de anestesias por 100 habitantes. Resultados: De los 23.136 cuestionarios recogidos en ANESCAT 2003, se estimó que en el año 2003 se habían realizado en Cataluña 603.189 anestesias (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 579.010-627.368). La tasa anual de anestesias por 100 habitantes fue de 9 (intervalo de confianza del 95%, 8,6-9,4). El 58% de las anestesias se administró a mujeres. La edad mediana (percentiles 10-90) fue de 52 (21-78) años y la proporción de anestesias en pacientes mayores de 60 años fue del 39,3%. La franja de edad con más anestesias fue entre los 70 y 74 años, con 56.000. Por debajo de los 14 años se anestesió a más varones; por encima fueron mayoría las mujeres. La tasa más alta de anestesias fue en los varones de 75-79 años (22,0%) y la más baja en las mujeres entre 10 a 14 años (1,8%). El porcentaje de pacientes con clase ASA 3 o superior fue del 26,7%. El estado físico de los varones era peor que el de las mujeres. En Barcelona ciudad se realizó el 47% de todas las anestesias. Conclusiones: La tasa anual de anestesias en Cataluña fue de 9 por 100 habitantes, casi 3 veces más en Barcelona ciudad que en el resto del territorio. En la comparación con los datos de países del entorno destaca una mayor proporción de mujeres, de pacientes de edad avanzada y de mayor gravedad</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);126(supl.2): 13-18, mayo 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047168</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Epidemiología de la anestesia en Cataluña en 2003</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d771^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31670</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d18001</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200605</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
