<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-89179</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-6255</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The professional disease in Spain a Changing reality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The Royal Decree 1299/2006 of November10th, which established the new legal framework for occupationaldiseases, represents an answer to the need to updatethe concept of such diseases in Spain and to establish new reportingand recording criteria. The previously existing frameworkwas considered obsolete and cumbersome and lackinga preventive approach and clear diagnostic criteria, leading tounder-reporting. Furthermore, there are also legal reasons.Objective: Descriptive comparison between the old and thenew frameworks of occupational disease. Methods: Legislativestudy and analysis of the two Royal Decrees concerned(1995/78 and 1299/2006) with a review of the pertinent andupdated bibliography. Results and conclusions: Considerableadvances are observed regarding reporting, classificationand recording of occupational diseases in Spain. The trueimpact of this legislative change on the current reality of occupationaldisease remains to be seen (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno Manzano, Gregorio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Barreiro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabrera Fernández, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Ortiz de Salazar, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bizighescu, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El RD 1299/2006(1), por el que se establece el nuevo cuadrode EE PP, responde a la necesidad de actualizar el cuadro deEE PP existente en España(2) y de establecer nuevos criteriosde notificación y registro(3-5). Esta necesidad surge porque seconsidera un cuadro obsoleto, poco ágil en su manejo, sinun enfoque preventivo y sin criterios diagnósticos claros, loque provoca una infradeclaración, y por razones legales, yaque se trata de una disposición de aplicación y desarrollodel artículo 116 de la LGSS(6), a cuyo ámbito pertenece lanueva LPRL(7). Objetivo: Realizar una comparación descriptivaentre el antiguo cuadro de EE PP(2) y el nuevo cuadro establecido en el RD 1299/2006(1). Metodología: Estudio y análisis legislativo del RD 78/1995(2) y del RD 1299/2006(1)con revisión de la bibliografía más destacada y actualizada.Resultados y conclusiones: Tras el análisis de ambos cuadros,se observa un gran avance en cuanto a la declaración,clasificación y notificación de las EE PP en España. Queda pendiente analizar el verdadero impacto que supone este cambio legislativo en la realidad actual de las EE PP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Asoc. Esp. Espec. Med. Trab;17(2): 23-33, oct. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-89179</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad profesional en España: una realidad cambiante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9967^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16373</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200810</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
