<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053533</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-7199</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cancer trends in hospital morbidity and lethality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: Describe trends in morbidity and lethality of cancer in        University Hospital &#147;Joaquín Albarrán&#148; (La Habana, Cuba).        Method: Carry out a temporal series studies of patients admited        from january 1999 to december 2005. We obtain informationa about        admission, total and for cancer, deceased patients and letality rates        (deceased for cancer/admission for cancer x 100). From the 2005&#146;s        admission we obtain age, sex, cause of admission, and if the diagnostic        of cancer was doing during this admission or before.        Results: Trend of cancer&#146;s admision have continuous increase        during 1999-2005 period, with 3% of admission in 1999 to 7.99% in        2005. Lethality rates have an irregular behavior with smaller rate in        1999 (12.7%) and bigger in 2001 (27.86%). Internal Medicine service        gave care to 60.71% of cancer admission, with less frecuency in general        surgery service (26.81%). 44% of patients were diagnosis during this        admission, and 56% the diagnosis was doing in previous admission, of        wich 42.1% were admited to treatment (surgical and drugs) and 53.5%        for cancer complications.        Conclusions: We show a continuous increased trend in hospital cancer        morbidity. It is a commit to modify healthcare&#146;s strategies of cancer        patient adressed to guarante the quality of services in front of the incresed        demand</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Salomón Zaldívar, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Montero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Isla, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guanche Garcell, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Arzola, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la tendencia en la morbilidad y letalidad por cáncer        en el Hospital Universitario &#147;Joaquín Albarrán&#148; (La Habana, Cuba).        Método: Realizamos un estudio de series temporales de los ingresos        por cáncer (enero 1999-diciembre 2005). Se obtuvo la información de los        ingresos totales y por cáncer, las defunciones, y las tasas de letalidad        (fallecidos por cáncer/ingresos por cáncer x 100). De los ingresos ocurridos        durante el 2005 se registró la edad (media y desviación standard),        sexo, la causa de la admisión, y se precisó el momento del diagnóstico de        cáncer.        Resultados: Se demuestra un sostenido incremento de la proporción        de ingresos por cáncer, con la menor de 3% (año 1999) y la mayor de        7,99% (año 2005). Las tasas de letalidad tuvieron un comportamiento        irregular con la menor en el 1999 (12,7%) y la mayor en el 2001        (27,86%). El servicio de medicina interna atendió la mayoría de los        pacientes (60,71%), seguidos por cirugía general (26,81%). Al 44% de        los pacientes se les diagnosticó cáncer durante el ingreso, mientras que el        56% se diagnóstico previamente, de los cuales el 42,1% ingresaron para        tratamiento (quirúrgico o quimioterapia antineoplásica) y el 53,5% por        complicaciones propias del proceso maligno.        Conclusión: Se ha demostrado una tendencia ascendente en la morbilidad        hospitalaria por cáncer, lo que obliga a modificar las estrategias        de atención de estos pacientes que aseguren la calidad de los servicios        ante el incremento de la demanda</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Med Interna;24(1): 12-14, ene. 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053533</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tendencias de la morbilidad y letalidad hospitalaria por cáncer</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28631^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30047^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10537^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
