<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051666</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9168</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reduction in PPAR transactivation and transrepression activity in an experimental model of metabolic syndrome induced by dietary fructose</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In rodents, high-fructose diets induce hypertriglyceridemia and hepatic steatosis. In the present study, we investigated whether fructose administration modulates the transactivating and transrepressing activity of the hepatic peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor alpha (PPAR-alpha). Material and methods. Twenty-four Sprague-Dawley rats were randomized to 3 treatment groups: control, fructose and glucose groups (10% w/v carbohydrate in drinking water for 14 days). Plasma levels of triglycerides, non-esterified fatty acids, glucose, insulin, and leptin were measured. Triglyceride content, fatty acid Beta-oxidation activity, and expression (mRNA levels, AND protein and DNA-protein binding activity ) of the studied genes were determined in liver samples. Results. Fructose administration produced a 1.9 and 1.8-fold increase in plasma and hepatic triglyceride levels, respectively. Leptin levels were increased 2.4-fold in these animals, without hyperglycemia or insulin resistance. Both PPAR-alpha transactivating activity and hepatic fatty acid Beta-oxidation activity (48%) were reduced in fructose-administered rats. The transrepressing activity of PPAR-alpha was also reduced and, as a consequence, nuclear factor kB activity was increased (30%) in fructose-fed rats compared with that in control animals. These changes were not observed in glucose-administered rats, although both carbohydrates produced similar changes in hepatic expression of the transcription factors and enzymes involved in fatty acid synthesis. Conclusions. Hypertriglyceridemia and hepatic steatosis induced by fructose intake result from reduced hepatic catabolism of fatty acids associated with deficient hepatic PPAR-alpha activity</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vilà, Laia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Laguna, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roglans, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Dietas ricas en fructosa producen, en roedores, hipertrigliceridemia y esteatosis hepática. En el presente estudio, quisimos valorar cómo afectaba la administración de este hidrato de carbono a la actividad hepática de transactivación y transrepresión del receptor activado por proliferadores peroxisómicos alfa (PPAR-alfa). Material y métodos. Se aleatorizó a 24 ratas Sprague-Dawley en 3 grupos de tratamiento: control, fructosa y glucosa (10% peso/volumen [p/v] hidrato de carbono en agua de bebida, durante 14 días). En plasma se valoraron los valores de triglicéridos, ácidos grasos libres, glucosa, insulina y leptina. En tejido hepático se determinó: contenido de triglicéridos, actividad de betaoxidación de los ácidos grasos, valores de expresión (ARN mensajero, proteína y actividad de unión proteína-ADN) de los genes objeto de nuestro estudio. Resultados. La administración de fructosa produjo un incremento de 1,9 y 1,8 veces en los valores de triglicéridos plasmáticos y hepáticos, respectivamente. Las concentraciones de leptina se incrementaron 2,4 veces en estos animales, sin que apareciera hiperglucemia ni resistencia a la insulina. La actividad de transactivación de PPAR* se redujo, así como la actividad de betaoxidación hepática de los ácidos grasos (48%). La actividad de transrepresión de PPAR-alfa también se redujo en estos animales, y se produjo un incremento del 30% en la actividad del factor NF-kB en las ratas fructosa frente a animales control. Estos resultados no se observaron tras la administración de glucosa; no obstante, los 2 hidratos de carbono modificaron de forma similar la expresión hepática de factores de transcripción y enzimas clave implicados en la síntesis de ácidos grasos. Conclusiones. La hipertrigliceridemia y la esteatosis hepática inducida por la ingesta de fructosa son el resultado de una reducción en el catabolismo hepático de los ácidos grasos asociado a un déficit de actividad PPAR</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. arterioscler. (Ed. impr.);19(1): 1-12, ene.2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051666</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reducción en la actividad de transactivación y transrepresión de PPAR-alfa en un modelo experimental de síndrome metabólico por fructosa dietética</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23686^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5337^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5768^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200701</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
