<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143748</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effect of a long-term physical exercise program and/or diet on metabolic syndrome in obese boys</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: There have been just a few studies examining the influence of detraining on obese boys. They conclude that any gains regress to the untrained control values during the detraining period. Objective: The objective of the present study was thus to evaluate the effects of detraining (6 months) on metabolic syndrome after two types of intervention (both 31 months), one of an exercise program alone and the other of a diet-plus-exercise program, in obese boys. Methods: The participants were 18 sedentary boys (8- 11 years old) with a body mass index equal or greater than the 97th percentile for the age and sex (male) of the subject, without any dysfunction or metabolic problem. The participants were divided into two groups - the E group (physical exercise program) and the E+D group (physical exercise program plus a low calorie diet). Metabolic parameters were evaluated (TC, HDL, LDL, TG, glucose, insulin, Systolic Blood Pressure, and Diastolic Blood Pressure), allowing the metabolic syndrome index to be calculated. Results: Changes were observed in LDL-C (effect sizes = -3.19 and -2.28) and in the LDL-C/HDL-C ratio (effect sizes = -3.02 and -1.16) in the E and E+D groups, respectively. The prevalence of metabolic syndrome and obesity was completely removed only in the E group (100% no risk and non-obese subjects - &lt; 90th percentile). Conclusions: Detraining from a long-term exercise program (with or without diet) seems not to negatively affect the cardiovascular profile, suggesting that the program provides benefits and fosters healthy habits that can be maintained over time, preventing the development of metabolic syndrome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Pachón, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saavedra García, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escalante González, Yolanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Hermoso, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Existen pocos estudios que examinen la influencia del desentrenamiento en niños obesos. Estos estudios concluyen que tras el desentrenamiento se regresa a los valores iniciales antes de la intervención. Objetivo: El objetivo del presente estudio fue examinar los efectos del desentrenamiento (6 meses) sobre e l síndrome metabólico después de dos tipos de intervención (31 meses), una de las intervenciones consistió en un programa de ejercicio físico aislado y la otra además del ejercicio físico incluyó la dieta. Métodos: Participaron 18 niños sedentarios (8-11 años) con un índice de masa corporal igual o superior al percentil 97 en función de la edad y sexo (varones) sin ninguna disfunción o problema metabólico. Los participantes fueron divididos en dos grupos: Grupo E (realizó el programa de ejercicio físico) y grupo E+D (realizó el programa de ejercicio físico más una dieta hipocalórica). Se evaluaron los parámetros metabólicos (CT, HDL-C, LDL-C, TG, glucosa, insulina y presión sistólica y diastólica) que permitieron calcular el síndrome metabólico. Resultados: Se observaron cambios en el LDL-C (TE = -3.19 y -2.28) y el índice LDL-C/HDL-C (TE = -3.02 y - 1.16) en el grupo E y E+D respectivamente. La prevalencia del síndrome metabólico y obesidad fue eliminada por completo en el grupo E (100% sin riesgo en niños no obesos - &lt; percentil 90). Conclusiones: El desentrenamiento tras un programa de ejercicio a largo plazo (con y sin dieta) parece no tener efectos negativos en el perfil cardiovascular, sugiriendo que el programa aporta beneficio sobre la salud (síndrome metabólico) que se mantienen en el tiempo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;30(1): 94-103, jul. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143748</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de un programa de ejercicio físico y/o dieta a largo plazo sobre el síndrome metabólico en niños obesos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36032^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51716</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55220^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201407</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
