<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128168</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Temperature control for thermolabile medications</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Even though the importance of stability in thermolabile medications is a subject widely known by healthcare professionals, nowadays the problem has not lost its interest, and deficiencies have been notified over time, which have been occasionally very severe, both regarding the inadequate or careless way of storage and preservation, and the level of training for the staff responsible for the cold chain. In daily practice, there are many incidents that can breach the cold chain (electric failure, fridge breakdown, fridge door not well closed, fridge door being opened too many times, frozen medications because they have been placed up against the walls, accidental alteration of the thermostat, mistakes in storage), and their consequences on health have caused several demonstrated adverse effects, including local reactions, abscesses, syncopal episodes, etc., associated with an inadequate freezing. High economic costs have also been documented due to the need to replace medications because of a cold chain breach. Knowledge about the stability of thermolabile medications must become a matter of special interest for all healthcare professionals and, particularly, for Nursing professionals, because the control of medication maintenance is often assigned to them. The objective of this article is to offer a protocol regarding temperature control for thermolabile medication, which will contribute to guarantee the adequate preservation of thermosensitive medications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cano Íñiguez, Virginia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano Íñiguez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Aunque la importancia de la estabilidad de los medicamentos termolábiles es un tema ampliamente conocido por los profesionales sanitarios, el problema no pierde actualidad y a lo largo del tiempo se han venido notificando deficiencias, en ocasiones muy graves, tanto en lo referente a la inadecuada o poco cuidadosa forma de almacenamiento y conservación como en el nivel de formación del personal responsable de la cadena del frío. En la práctica diaria existen muchos incidentes que pueden rompen dicha cadena (fallo eléctrico, avería del frigorífico, puerta del frigorífico mal cerrada, múltiples aperturas de la puerta del mismo, medicamentos congelados por estar pegados a las paredes, alteración accidental del termostato, equivocaciones de almacenaje), de cuyas consecuencias sobre la salud hay demostrados numerosos efectos adversos, desde reacciones locales, abscesos, episodios sincopales, etc., relacionados con una inadecuada refrigeración. También están documentados elevados costes económicos por la reposición de medicación por la rotura de la cadena de frío. El conocimiento de la estabilidad de medicamentos termolábiles ha de constituir un tema de especial interés para todos los profesionales sanitarios y, de modo especial, para los profesionales de la Enfermería, dado que en muchas ocasiones tienen encomendado el control del mantenimiento de las medicaciones. El objetivo del presente trabajo es ofrecer un protocolo de control de temperatura de la medicación termolábil que contribuya a garantizar la correcta conservación de los medicamentos termosensibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(7): 12-16, sept. 2014. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128168</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El control de la temperatura de medicamentos termolábiles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12456^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54857</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12223</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4416^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16719</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201409</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
