<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124536</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perceptions of female immigrant domestic workers on the effects of the sector regulation in Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To examine the perceptions of female immigrant domestic workers of the effect of Royal Decree 1620/2011, which regulates the relationship of domestic workers in the family home and their employment conditions in Spain. Methods An exploratory study was performed using qualitative content analysis of three focus group discussions with immigrant women from Colombia, Ecuador and Morocco. Results Immigrant women positively assessed the theoretical benefits of the new regulation, but identified legal and economic barriers to obtaining a contract and being registered in the social security system by their employers, and to employers accepting the cost of these measures, especially for workers hired by the hour. These difficulties affected their possibilities of legalizing their status. The economic crisis posed a serious challenge to compliance with the new regulation. Conclusions Although the new regime encourages job creation with stronger working rights for these workers, immigrant women perceived that its implementation has been hampered by the current financial crisis and has not, therefore, improved their employment conditions (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Agudelo Suárez, Andrés A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vives Cases, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ronda Pérez, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Briones Vozmediano, Erica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Jacob, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ballester Laguna, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Explorar las percepciones de las mujeres inmigrantes trabajadoras del servicio doméstico sobre la puesta en vigor en España del Real Decreto 1620/2011, que regula la relación laboral del servicio del hogar familiar, y su efecto en sus condiciones de empleo. Métodos Estudio exploratorio mediante análisis de contenido cualitativo. Se realizaron tres grupos de discusión con mujeres inmigrantes (colombianas, ecuatorianas y marroquíes).Resultados A pesar de valorar positivamente los beneficios teóricos de la nueva normativa, las mujeres inmigrantes han identificado barreras legales y económicas para conseguir un contrato, ser dadas de alta en la seguridad social y que las personas empleadoras asuman su coste, en especial en el caso de las trabajadoras contratadas por horas. Estas dificultades influyen en la posibilidad de legalizar su situación. La confluencia con la crisis económica ha emergido como un problema que dificulta su cumplimiento. Conclusiones Aunque el nuevo régimen ha favorecido la creación de puestos de trabajo con mayores derechos laborales en el sector, las mujeres inmigrantes perciben que su puesta en marcha en el actual contexto de crisis económica no ha contribuido a mejorar sus condiciones de empleo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;28(2): 109-115, mar.-abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124536</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Percepción de las trabajadoras inmigrantes del servicio doméstico sobre los efectos de la regulación del sector en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15330^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6860^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
