<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165335</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lipid emulsion selection in parenteral nutrition. Biochemical and hematological paramaters</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Lipid emulsions (LE) are a component of parenteral nutrition (PN) and its fatty acid (FA) profile determines various physiological responses. Objectives: To assess the adequacy of a clinical not restricted protocol in the choice of LE by studying complementary biochemical and hematological parameters (BHP) at the beginning of the PN. Methods: A 4-year retrospective observational study of LE administered to patients with PN. Demographic, clinical, nutritional and analytical variables at the beginning of the PN were collected. Univariate and multivariate analyses were performed to study the correlation between the initial clinical and biochemical parameters and the LE profile used. Results: Four hundred and sixty patients (29.5%) out of 1,558 had BHP at the beginning of PN and used mainly the LE combinations soybean (SO) + medium-chain triglycerides (MCT) + olive (OO) + fi sh (FO) (37.4%) and SO + MCT + OO (35.6%). Statistically significant differences on the LE pattern were observed between patients with and those without initial BHP (44.8% vs 39.5% received FO, respectively). Conditions regularly associated with elevated C-reactive protein (CRP) were associated with increased use of FO LE: SO+OO+FO (OR: 4.52 [95% CI: 1.43-13.91]) and SO+MCT+OO+FO (OR: 3.34 [95% CI: 2.10-5.33]). In those complex conditions related with the critical patient MCT were used: hepatic failure (SO+MCT OR: 2.42 [95% CI: 1.03-5.68]) and renal failure (SO+MCT+FO OR: 3.34 [95% CI: 1.12-9.99]). Conclusions: The use of BHP at the beginning of PN treatment allows complementing the clinical and metabolic criteria in LE selection (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llop Talaveron, Josep</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Novak, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suñé Negre, Josep Maria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanmartí-Martinez, Núria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Badia Tahull, Maria B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jódar Masanes, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ticó Grau, Josep Ramon</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leiva Badosa, Elisabet</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el patrón de ácidos grasos (AG) de las emulsiones lipídicas (EL) utilizadas en nutrición parenteral (NP) condiciona diferentes respuestas fisiológicas. Objetivos: estudiar si los criterios clínicos de prescripción de EL en NP establecidos en nuestro protocolo abierto y basados en recomendaciones se correlacionan con marcadores bioquímicos y hematológicos iniciales. Métodos: estudio observacional retrospectivo de cuatro años. Se recogieron variables demográficas, clínicas, nutricionales y analíticas al inicio de la NP. Se realizó un análisis uni y multivariante para estudiar la asociación entre los valores iniciales de los parámetros bioquímicos y hematológicos (PBHE) y el tipo de emulsión lipídica empleada. Resultados: de los 1.558 pacientes, 460 pacientes (29,5%) tenían PBHE al inicio de la NP y utilizaron mayoritariamente las combinaciones soja (AS) + triglicéridos de cadena media (MCT) + oliva (AO) + pescado (AP) (37,4%) y AS+MCT+AO (35,6%). Se encontraron diferencias estadísticamente significativas en el patrón EL utilizado entre los pacientes con y sin PBHE: patrón de AG con AP 44,8% vs. 39,5%, respectivamente. Las situaciones clínicas con proteína C-reactiva (PCR) elevada se asociaron con mayor uso de EL con AP: AS+AO+AP (OR: 4,52 [IC 95%: 1,43-13,91] y AS+MCT+AO+AP (OR: 3,34 [IC 95%: 2,10-5,33]). En situaciones clínicas complejas asociadas con paciente crítico se utilizó EL con MCT: afectación hepática (AS+MCT OR: 2,42 [IC 95%: 1,03-5,68]) y afectación renal (AS+MCT+AP OR: 3,34 [IC 95%: 1,12-9,99]). Conclusiones: la inclusión protocolizada de PBHE al inicio de la NP permite complementar criterios clínicos y metabólicos en la elección de la EL (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(4): 767-775, jul.-ago. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165335</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Selección de emulsiones lipídicas en nutrición parenteral: parámetros bioquímicos y hematológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d51840^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5321^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24651^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7438^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5321^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30401^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54124^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24651^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
