<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106075</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Exclusion of black women: its representation shaping the professional nursing</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper intends to reflect on the exclusion of black women from the origins of the Brazilian professional nursing. Based on cultural history, this study took for granted a recommendation to avoid black presence within the first official schools for nurses, which excluded black women, before the organization of the nursing education. However the historical memory of care brings up that black carers were looking after sick people. Such memories damaged the images of nursing professional identity, described essentially as practiced by white woman, daughter of the elite. This reflection allows us to suppose that representations of blacks in Brazil reiterated certain stereotypes which by its turn restrained black inclusions within modern nursing while images visibility from this process had projected them as morally unqualified, characterizing them as inappropriate to work for the art and science of care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Oguisso,  Taka</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Souza Campos, Paulo Fernando de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio busca reflejar la exclusión de mujeres negras de los orígenes de la enfermería profesional brasileña. Basada en la historia cultural, el estudio presupone que la recomendación para que se evite la presencia negra en las primeras escuelas oficiales de formación superior, era necesaria la exclusión de las negras. Entre tanto, la memoria histórica del cuidado nos recuerda que las cuidadoras negras ejercían esa actividad junto a los enfermos antes de la organización de la enseñanza de la enfermería. Tales memorias crearon imágenes negativas sobre la identidad profesional de la enfermería brasileña, caracterizada esencialmente por la mujer blanca procedente de las élites. La reflexión nos permite suponer que las representaciones del negro en Brasil, reiteraron estereotipos que, a su vez, reprimían la inclusión de las negras en la enfermería moderna en la medida que la visibilidad de imágenes del proceso las proyectó como moralmente descalificadas, caracterizándolas como inapropiadas para el ejercicio del arte y de la ciencia del cuidado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;15(55): 26-30, oct.-dic. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106075</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Exclusión de mujeres negras. Su representación en la enfermería profesional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38410^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50262</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1963</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12960^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
