<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-121737</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-6141</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The primary health care from the users perspective</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify the characteristics of the development of the Primary Health Care strategy according to the users and factors that relate to the use of services. Materials and methods: Descriptive and mixed study. This study included 393 primary health care users. The sample selection was made according to established criteria. It used the focus group and the survey. The information was categorized and processed in SPSS 15.0. Results: The average age was 37.62 years. The main reasons for seeking care are recovering and disease prevent. The age was associated significantly with recover as one of the reasons for seeking attention p&lt;0.05. The highest level of studies showed statistically significant association with recovery as a reason for requesting attention p &lt;0.05 and the health status perception was associated with satisfaction with care last was offered or requested p&lt;0.05. Conclusions: The activities were directed to priority groups. The users benefited from the services through family visit, health day, mobile unit and community meetings. The factors related to services use were age, gender, geographic accessibility, satisfaction with the last care received, health status perception and recovery as one of the reasons for seeking health care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vélez Álvarez, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Giraldo Osorio, Alexandra</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Identificar lascaracterísticas del desarrollo de la estrategia de Atención Primaria de Saluddesde la perspectiva de los usuarios y los factores que serelacionan con la utilización de los servicios. Materiales y métodos: Estudio descriptivo, mixto. Muestra 393 usuarios beneficiarios de la estrategia. La selección de la muestra se realizó según criterios establecidos.Se utilizaron el grupo focal yla encuesta. La información fue categorizada y procesada en el SPSS 15.0.  Resultados: La edad promedio fue 37.62 años. Las principales razones para solicitaruna atención fueron recuperarse y prevenir la enfermedad. La edad se  asocio significativamente con recuperarse como una razón para solicitar una atenciónp&lt;0.05, el máximo nivel de estudios presentó asociación estadísticamente significativa con recuperarse como una razón para solicitaruna atención p&lt;0.05 y la percepción del estado de salud se asoció con la satisfacción con la ultima atención que se le ofreció o solicitó p&lt;0.05. Conclusiones: Las actividades estaban dirigidas a grupos prioritarios. Los medios porlos cuales los usuarios se beneficiaron del servicio fueron visita familiar, jornada de salud, unidad móvil y reuniones comunitarias. Los factores que se relacionaron conla utilización de los servicios fueron edad, género, accesibilidad geográfica, satisfacción con la última atención recibida, percepción del estado de salud yrecuperarse como una razón para solicitar una atención (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. glob;13(34): 232-251, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-121737</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La atención primaria de salud desde la perspectiva de los usuarios</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28449</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3709^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29902^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32094^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6447^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5932^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
