<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155017</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Axillary web syndrome following sentinel node biopsy for breast cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">A 49 year-old woman diagnosed with infiltrating lobular breast carcinoma, underwent a right mastectomy and sentinel node biopsy (SLNB). The resected sentinel lymph nodes were negative for malignancy, with an axillary lymphadenectomy not being performed. In the early post-operative period, the patient reported an axillary skin tension sensation, associated with a painful palpable cord. These are typical manifestations of axillary web syndrome (AWS), a poorly known axillary surgery complication, from both invasive and conservative interventions. By presenting this case we want to focus the attention on a pathological condition, for which its incidence may be underestimated by not including it in SLNB studies. It is important for nuclear medicine physicians to be aware of AWS as a more common complication than infection, seroma, or lymphoedema, and to discuss this possible event with the patient who is consenting to the procedure (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Macías Cortiñas, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Argibay Vázquez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruibal Morell, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieves Maldonado, SM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pubul Núñez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Paciente de 49 años diagnosticada de carcinoma lobulillar infiltrante de mama derecha, intervenida mediante mastectomía y biopsia selectiva de ganglio centinela (BSGC). Los ganglios linfáticos centinela resecados fueron negativos para malignidad, motivo por el cual no fue necesaria la realización de linfadenectomía axilar. En el periodo posquirúrgico temprano la paciente presentó una sensación de tensión cutánea en el hueco axilar asociada a un cordón palpable doloroso, manifestación típica del síndrome de web axilar (SWA), una complicación poco conocida de las intervenciones quirúrgicas axilares, tanto invasivas como conservadoras. Mediante la presentación de este caso queremos centrar la atención en una entidad patológica cuya incidencia podemos estar infravalorando al no incluirla en estudios prospectivos de BSGC. Es importante que los médicos nucleares seamos conscientes de la existencia del SWA como una posible consecuencia de la BSGC, más frecuente que la infección, el seroma o el linfedema y de que debemos informar a los pacientes que firman el consentimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);35(5): 325-328, sept.-oct. 2016. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155017</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de web axilar secundario a la biopsia selectiva del ganglio centinela en cáncer de mama</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23305^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8580^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35392^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31593^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1377^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23305^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9871^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1968^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23305^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
