<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99332</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">State of acute phase markers and oxidative stress in patients with kidney stones in the urinary tract</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: This present study has aimed to assess the state of acute phase markers and oxidative stress in patients with kidney stones. Material and methods: A prospective study was carried out on 100 patients with kidney stones and 25 healthy controls. Albumin, beta2 microglobulin, Gamma-glutamyl  transpepsidase, Lactatede hydrogenase, Tumor necrosis factor alpha, Interleukin 1 and Interleukin-6 were evaluated as acute phase markers and lipid peroxidation products, Superoxide dismutase and Glutathione peroxidase levels acted as oxidative stress markers. Results: An increase in renal cell damage markers as expressed by the beta2 microglobulin (p = 0.04), albumin (p = 0.004), Lactate dehydrogenase (p = 0.001) and Gamma glutamyl  transpepsidasa (p = 0.01) was observed in the patient group. There was a direct correlation between levels of beta2 microglobulin and stone size (r = 0.3, p = 0.03). The association between stone size and cytokine activation was observed to be stronger in patients with staghorn calculi. In these patients, Tumor necrosis factor alpha (p = 0.011), Interleukin 1 (p = 0.004) and Interleukin6 (p = 0.004) were significantly higher. Patients with stones in the urinary tract showed data of significantly higher oxidative stress, expressed as an increase in levels of lipid peroxidation products (p = 0.03) and a decrease in the antioxidant activity of Superoxide dismutase (p = 0.03)and Glutathione peroxidase (p = 0.002).Conclusions: Patients undergoing urolithiasis showed an elevation of acute phase markers, associated with oxidative stress as expressed by an increase in lipid peroxidation products and a decrease in the antioxidant enzyme activity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilar-Melero, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padillo-Ruiz, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Requena-Tapia, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Ojeda, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrasco-Valiente, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muntané-Relat, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Anglada-Curado, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: El objetivo del presente estudio es evaluar el estado de los marcadores de fase aguda y de estrés oxidativo en enfermos con litiasis renal. Material y métodos: Estudio prospectivo en enfermos con litiasis renal. Se incluyeron100 enfermos y 25 controles sanos. Se evaluaron como marcadores de fase aguda: albúmina, beta2 microglobulina, gamma-glutamil transpepsidasa, lactato deshidrogenasa, factor de necrosistumoral alfa, interleucina 1 e interleucina 6 y como marcadores de estrés oxidativo los niveles de lipoperóxidos, superóxido dismutasa y glutatión peroxidasa. Resultados: En los enfermos estudiados se apreció un incremento de los marcadores de daño celular renal expresado por la beta2 microglobulina (p = 0,04), albúmina (p = 0,004), lactato deshidrogenasa (p = 0,001), así como gamma-glutamil transpepsidasa (p = 0,01). Existió una correlación directa entre los niveles de beta2 microglobulina con el tamaño de la litiasis (r = 0,3; p = 0,03). La asociación entre la extensión del cálculo y la activación de las citoquinas se apreció de forma más intensa en los enfermos con cálculos coraliformes en los que las cifras de factor de necrosis tumoral alfa (p = 0,011), interleucina 1 (p = 0,004) e interleucina 6 (p = 0,004) fueron significativamente mayores. Los enfermos con litiasis de la vía urinaria presentaron cifras significativamente elevadas de radicales libres en plasma, expresados como lipoperóxidos (p = 0,03), que se acompañaron de un descenso en la actividad de las enzimas antioxidantes superóxido dismutasa (p = 0.03) y glutatión peroxidasa (p = 0,002). Conclusiones: Los pacientes con litiasis urinaria presentan una elevación de los marcadores de fase aguda, asociada a un incremento de especies reactivas del oxígeno y un descenso en la actividad de las enzimas antioxidantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;36(5): 296-301, mayo 2012. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estado de los marcadores de fase aguda y estrés oxidativo en los enfermos con litiasis de la vía urinaria</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52133^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32101^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24371^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22307^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d979^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7853^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
