<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-113415</identifier>
<setSpec>1887-8571</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Barodontalgies. Experimental study in dogs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The barodontalgies are clinical concerns in the military environment, whose physiopathology and treatment are nowadays still very controversial. Objectives: To describe the dentin-pulp complex response of the healthy tooth of the Beagle dog with or without amalgam fillings and composite resin in a hypobaric environment. Material and methods: The study is about 308 teeth all from Beagle dogs divided in 3 groups: without fillings, with amalgam fillings and composite resin fillings, subjected to an hypobaric change in a low pressure chamber ETC/APTFIOM, applying simulated military standard flight features (NATO STANAG 3114), and comparing the results to those of a non-flying control group performing an histological appraisal in two periods of time (3 hours and 21 days) following ISO/TR7405 guidelines. Results: On the microscopic study carried out immediately (3 hours) after the baro-trauma, the hypobaric changes produced on the flight provoked significant responses (p&lt;0,05) of the dentin-pulp complex; however there were no differences among pieces filled with different materials and those without any filling. Furthermore, the changes observed in this study disappeared when the hystologic study was carried out after a period of 21 days. Conclusions: there are some histological differences in the dentin-pulp complex response of dog&#146;s teeth that fly with regard to a nonflying control-group, but the response is similar whether they are, or not, filled with amalgam or composite resins. All the morphological changes observed are reversible over time (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vega del Barrio, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorenzo Beno, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Rebollar, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Las Barodontalgias son entidades clínico-nosológicas muy características del medio militar, cuya fisiopatología y tratamiento son todavía hoy día muy controvertidos. Objetivos: Describir la respuesta dentino-pulpar del diente sano de perro Beagle con y sin obturaciones de amalgama y resinas compuestas en medio ambiente hipobárico. Material y Método: Se estudian 308 dientes de perro Beagle divididos en tres grupos: sin obturaciones, con obturaciones de amalgama y con obturaciones de resinas compuestas, sometidos a un cambio hipobárico en cámara de baja presión ETC/APTF10M, siguiendo un perfil de vuelo militar simulado estándar (OTAN STANAG 3114) frente a un grupo control que no vuela, para valoración histológica en dos periodos de tiempo (3 horas y 21 días) siguiendo las normas ISO/TR7405. Resultados: En el estudio microscópico efectuado de forma inmediata (3 horas) tras el barotrauma, los cambios hipobáricos que genera el vuelo ocasionan respuesta histológicas pulpares significativas (p&lt;0,05); pero no existen diferencias entre muestras sin obturar u obturadas con distintos materiales. Además los cambios observados, desaparecen cuando el estudio histológico se efectúa tras un periodo de latencia de 21 días. Conclusiones: Existen diferencias histológicas en la respuesta dentino-pulpar de dientes de perro que vuelan respecto a un grupo control que no vuela, pero la respuesta es similar estén o no obturados con amalgama o resinas compuestas. Todos los cambios observados son reversibles con el tiempo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Sanid. mil;64(3): 167-176, jul.-sept. 2008. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-113415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Barodontalgias. Estudio experimental en perros</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4255</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14488^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22322</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3803^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
