<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124954</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation and management of rectus sheath hematomas. Analysis of our experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Rectus sheath hematoma is an uncommon clinical entity although it appears that its incidence is increasing. Factors most frequently associated are cough, abdominal trauma, and anticoagulation. The diagnosis is not easy and a test image is required in the majority of cases. The treatment is usually conservative. Surgery must be reserved in cases of hemodynamic instability or when hematoma is infected (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nofuentes, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Compañ, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mella, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Smilevska, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orts, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El hematoma de la vaina de los rectos es una entidad clínica infrecuente aunque parece que su incidencia está aumentando. Los factores más frecuentemente relacionados con su aparición son la tos, los traumatismos abdominales y la anticoagulación. El diagnóstico no es fácil y requiere una prueba de imagen en la mayoría de los casos. El tratamiento suele ser conservador. La cirugía se reserva en los casos de inestabilidad hemodinámica o cuando el hematoma está infectado (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;17(2): 69-71, abr.-jun. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124954</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación y manejo de los hematomas de la vaina de los rectos. Análisis de nuestra experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3386^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31090^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6556^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6623^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
