<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101913</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-9903</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Review of root fracture with atypical treatment for 23 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We are herewith presenting a case based on a maxillary right superior central incisor, which suffered a middle third fracture of the root. This fracture has been atypically treated and has been checked up throughout 23 years. The middle third fracture, which is comminuted in its central area, was caused by a contusion trauma. The patient came with urgency due to tooth mobility as well as an acute pain. After being diagnosed acute pulpitis and mid radicular fracture with subluxation, it was agreed to treat it throughout the whole process after its ferulization. Once treated, calcium hydroxide was left in the canal and two weeks after, with an asymptomatic tooth since the first day, it was sealed with calcium hydroxide with physiological saline solution and lateral condensation with gutta-percha. Three months after, ferulization was removed and the incisor was asymptomatic, functional and with mobility similar to the neighboring incisive. Radiograph examinations proved that the fracture presented different diagnosis throughout its 23 years. Nowadays, this incisor keeps being asymptomatic, firm and functional with a well done reshape (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fuentes Candelas, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Presentamos el caso de un incisivo central superior derecho, con fractura del tercio medio radicular, que fue tratado de forma atípica y se revisó durante 23 años de evolución. La fractura del tercio medio, conminuta en su área central, se produjo por un traumatismo contuso, acudiendo el paciente de urgencia por dolor agudo y movilidad del cliente. Con el diagnóstico de pulpitis aguda y fractura radicular media con subluxación, se decidió tratarlo en toda su longitud después de su ferulización. Practicado el tratamiento se dejó hidróxido de calcio en el conducto y a  las dos semanas, con un diente asintomático desde el primer día, se selló definitivamente con hidróxido de calcio en suero fisiológico y gutapercha en condensación lateral. Tres meses después se retiró la ferulización y el diente esta asintomático, funcional y con una movilidad semejante a la de los incisivos vecinos. Radiológicamente, el área de fractura presento distintos aspectos diagnósticos a lo largo de 23 años de seguimiento. Actualmente, el incisivo sigue asintomático,  firme, funcional y con un remodelado de su contorno bien definido (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endodoncia (Madr.);29(1): 27-32, ene.-mar. 2011. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101913</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Revisión de una fractura radicular con tratamiento atípico durante 23 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14485^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2162^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11326^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13549^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12107^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32000^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
