<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047034</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Reflections on the use and utility of nursing models and theories in clinical practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Theory is essential to explain and understand nursing practice. The theoretical framework helps to examine, organize, analyze and interpret patient data, supporting and facilitating decision-making. Likewise, the theoretical framework helps nurses to plan, predict and evaluate the results of nursing care. Therefore, the theoretical approach is a useful tool for reasoning and critical thinking and, moreover, helps nurses to use and manage all the information on a patient and to provide nursing care in a structured and effective manner. The use of Conceptual Models of Nursing in nursing care guarantees that all nurses share a common language and similar concepts with respect to the nursing paradigms, person, health, environment and care that characterize their professional role. The present article provides a reflection on an issue that continues to be of great importance - the dichotomy between nursing theory and practice</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mañé-Buxó, Nuria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Parra, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Ruiz, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abril-Sabater, Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Muñoz, Mercé</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rocabert-Luque, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varez-Peláez, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La teoría es esencial para explicar y comprender las prácticas enfermeras. El marco teórico ayuda a examinar, organizar, analizar e interpretar los datos del paciente, apoyando y facilitando la toma de decisiones. De la misma forma, favorece la planificación, la predicción y la evaluación de los resultados fruto de los cuidados. Por lo tanto, el enfoque teórico es una herramienta útil para el razonamiento, el pensamiento crítico y, además, favorece que las enfermeras puedan emplear y manejar toda la información acerca del paciente y gestionen la práctica del cuidado de forma ordenada y eficaz. El uso de modelos conceptuales de enfermería en la atención, garantiza que todas las enfermeras compartan un lenguaje común y concepciones similares respecto a los paradigmas enfermeros, persona, salud, entorno y cuidados que caracterizan el rol profesional. Aquí se plantea una reflexión acerca de lo que todavía, y aún siendo un tema de gran importancia, mantiene la dicotomía entre la práctica asistencial y la teoría enfermera</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);16(4): 218-221, jul. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047034</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Reflexiones acerca del uso y utilidad de los modelos y teorías de enfermería en la práctica asistencial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200607</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
