<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-73729</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: children with chronic medical conditions (CMC) are at high-risk of sufferingfrom serious complications due to influenza. Although routine annual influenza immunizationwith trivalent inactivated vaccine is recommended in these children, few of them fulfil the recommendation.The aim of our study is to assess the rate of influenza vaccine coverage amongchildren with CMC in a Primary Care Setting in a metropolitan area in Spain.Patients and methods: in the 2007-2008 influenza season, the computerized database ofall children aged 0-14 years in a Primary Care Setting was checked. Over 3,479 children, 232were indentified as high-risk. The administration of influenza vaccine in these children that yearwas assessed checking every computerized medical record.Results: the global influenza vaccine coverage among children with CMC was 43.1%. Fullimmunization was received in 98% of them. Depending on the underlying medical condition,the coverage was 44% in children with Asthma, 35% in Congenital Heart Diseases and 42.8%in Diabetes Mellitus. Children with CMC living in immigrant families had lower rate of influenzavaccination than those in Spanish families, 35.6% versus 45.7%.Conclusions: the rate of vaccine coverage among children with CMC in our setting is higherthan the one reported in medical reviews (range: 10-23%). Despite these good results, to increasethe rates of vaccination among children with CMC is needed. Health care professionalsshould design strategies to achieve a 75% rate of influenza vaccine coverage in high-risk childrenas a much better goal(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arriba Muñoz, A. de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Biosca Pàmies, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Escosa García, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Domínguez Cajal, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Sánchez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Íñiguez, J. P</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: los niños con enfermedades crónicas (EC) tienen más riesgo de presentarcomplicaciones importantes debidas a la gripe. Aunque la vacunación rutinaria anual convacuna trivalente inactivada está indicada en estos niños, son muy pocos los que cumplenesta recomendación. El objetivo de nuestro estudio es comprobar la cobertura de vacunaantigripal en niños con alto riesgo de complicaciones (ARC) en un centro de salud urbanoen España.Pacientes y métodos: durante el otoño e invierno 2007-2008 se revisó la base de datos delas historias clínicas de los niños de 0-14 años de edad, en un centro de salud. De un total de3.479 niños, 232 presentaban ARC. Se comprobó si habían recibido la vacuna antigripal en eseaño, examinando cada historia clínica informatizada.Resultados: la cobertura global de vacuna antigripal en niños con ARC fue 43,1%. El 98%de los niños vacunados recibió una vacunación completa. Según las patologías subyacentes encontradas,la cobertura vacunal fue del 44% en caso de asma, 35% en cardiopatía congénita y42,85% en diabetes mellitus. La cobertura de vacuna antigripal fue menor en niños de familiasinmigrantes con ARC que en españoles, 35,6% frente al 45,7%.Conclusiones: la cobertura de vacuna antigripal en nuestros niños con ARC es mayor que lacomunicada en la bibliografía médica (10-23%). A pesar de estos buenos resultados, se necesitaaumentar la vacunación antigripal en todos los niños con EC. Los profesionales de la saluddeberían diseñar estrategias para conseguir una cobertura de un 75% como un objetivo muchomejor(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;11(43): 399-411, jul.-sept.2009. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-73729</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cobertura de vacuna antigripal en niños de riesgo durante 2007-2008 en un centro de Atención Primaria en España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50229</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29592^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23109^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200909</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
