<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93854</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of the systems for measuring muscle strength applied to musical practice. Approach to a prototype suitable for instrumental practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: determine, in real time, its usefulness in the study of the force exerted by the hand of the musician on the instrument (piano and guitar) and the force exerted by the hand of the musician on the instrument, in real time. Material and methods: systems better adapted to the requirements of musical practice were chosen and analyzed on the instrument, using as experimental subjects a guitarist and a pianist. For every system examined the following was considered: the degree of interference with the musical technical act; easiness to swap the system from one instrument to another; resistance to deterioration with use (especially working on strings) and existence of a system and software to capture and analyze data that allow the user to set alarms or alert levels that will help him to do reeducation of the tension used to play (biofeedback) were analysed. Results: The guitar measures showed a maximum peak force of 9.14 N (0.93Kg) and the piano usually exceeded 9.8 N (1kg force). The other analized systems (thermal imaging, Chronopic, EMG and accelerometer) let us study the force, however important limiting factors behaved they were discarded. Conclusions: Miniature pressure sensors coated with an ultrathin latex sheath have proved effective for the study of the isometric and concentric force developed by the hand of the musician (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bonet-Bonet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fàbregas-Molas, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gomila-Serra, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Padullés-Rius, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rosset-Llobet, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar los sistemas de medida de la fuerza, en tiempo real, que ejerce la mano sobre el instrumento al tocar (piano y guitarra) y conocer la fuerza ejercida por la mano del músico, en tiempo real, sobre el instrumento. Material y Método: Se analizaron sobre el instrumento, en un guitarrista y un pianista experimentados. En cada sistema analizado se valoró: el grado de interferencia con el gesto técnico musical; la posibilidad de intercambiarlo de un instrumento a otro; la resistencia al deterioro con el uso (especialmente al trabajar sobre cuerdas); la existencia de un sistema y software de captura y análisis de los datos que permitiera al usuario definir alarmas o niveles de alerta útiles para poder hacer un trabajo de reeducación de la tensión utilizada para tocar (biofeedback). Se estableció un protocolo de pruebas y se experimentó sobre ambos instrumentos. Con el método que dio mejor resultado se procedió al estudio de la fuerza ejercida por la mano del músico sobre el instrumento. Resultados: Las medidas recogidas mostraron en el caso de la guitarra un pico de fuerza máximo de 9,14N (0,93Kg) y en el piano se superaban habitualmente los 9,8N (1kg de fuerza). Conclusiones: Los sensores de presión miniaturizados recubiertos con una funda de látex ultrafino han resultado ser eficaces para el estudio de la fuerza isométrica y concéntrica desarrollada por la mano del músico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);22(4): 226-234, oct.-dic. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93854</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de los sistemas de medición de la fuerza muscular en el ámbito de la práctica musical. Aproximación a un prototipo apto para la práctica instrumental</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13262^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9339</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14200^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23479^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1856^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23479^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54210^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23479^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7704^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9309^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52443^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52443^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54210^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32211^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36288^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
