<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100555</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The role of risk propensity in smokers and overweight people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The aim of this study is to investigate the nature of the link associating the risk propensity of smoking and overweight. For example, a person who is a smoker and obese does not have to be more prone to risk than another person who is obese and a non-smoker. Material and methods. The data was taken from the German Questionnaire on Personality and Daily (Cross section for the period 2005). This questionnaire was selected because it collects individual data on the sociodemographic characteristic, behaviours, risk attitudes, lottery games, and health status. Our main contribution is to analyse the role of risk propensity taking into account smoking and overweight. Results. Risk propensity encourages smoking, and to smoke and be overweight are positively associated. When the role of the unobserved characteristics are greater, the lower is the correlation between smoking and overweight. Although the risk propensity is an important determining factor of individual behaviour (smoking and overweight), its inclusion does not decrease the influence of personal circumstances and conditions. The need to define other measurements to be able to analyse the risk propensity of risk specific to risk behaviour is also highlighted. Discussion. To reduce the number of smokers would require interventions in life styles. Given that overweight is an important determining factor in the decision to smoke, to encourage healthy behaviours, such as physical exercise or balanced diets, could improve the health status of the population on reducing obesity rates, and consequently the number of smokers(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gil-Lacruz, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil-Lacruz, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El objetivo de este trabajo es estudiar la naturaleza del nexo de unión entre la propensión al riesgo, fumar y el sobrepeso. Por ejemplo, una persona que sea fumadora y obesa no tiene porque ser más propensa al riesgo que otra persona que sea obesa pero no fumadora. Material y métodos. Los datos proceden de la Encuesta Alemana sobre Personalidad y Vida Cotidiana (corte transversal para el periodo 2005). Hemos seleccionado esta encuesta porque recoge datos individuales sobre características socio-demográficas, comportamientos, actitudes de riesgo, juegos de loterías y estados de salud. Nuestra principal contribución es analizar el rol de la propensión al riesgo considerando el consumo de tabaco y sobrepeso. Resultados. La propensión al riesgo fomenta fumar, y fumar y el sobrepeso están correlacionados positivamente. Cuanto mayor es el papel de las características inobservadas, menor es la correlación entre fumar y el sobrepeso. Aunque la propensión al riesgo es un determinante relevante del comportamiento individual (fumar y sobrepeso), su inclusión no menoscaba la influencia de las circunstancias y condiciones personales. También destacamos la necesidad de definir medidas de propensión al riesgo específicas al comportamiento de riesgo a analizar. Discusión. Para reducir los ratios de fumadores sería necesario actuaciones sobre los estilos de vida. Dado que el sobrepeso es un determinante importante de la decisión de fumar, promover comportamientos saludables (ejercicio físico o dietas equilibradas, entre otras) podría mejorar el estado de salud de los ciudadanos al reducir los ratios de obesidad, y consecuentemente los ratios de fumadores(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);5(3): 139-149, jul.-sept. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100555</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El rol de la propensión al riesgo para fumadores y personas con sobrepeso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37609</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1860^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14418^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201209</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
