<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81833</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0558</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Endovascular treatment of a post-traumatic arterio-venous fistula: presentation of a clinical case and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Traumatic arteriovenous fistulas of the head and neck region are uncommon. The majority are due to penetration of blunt injury. We describe a successful endovascular treatment of a posttraumatic fistula between the left maxillary artery and the external jugular vein due to a penetration injury. This case and a review of the literature illustrate the causes, manifestations, image studies and treatment for a posttraumatic fistula between the maxillary artery and the external jugular vein. This case demonstrate the utility of endovascular treatment of head and neck injuries complications(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Burgueño, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marín, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pingarrón, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, J. del</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández-Prieto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Frutos, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las fístulas arteriovenosas en la cabeza y el cuello son entidades poco frecuentes. La mayoría es secundaria a heridas penetrantes por arma blanca. Se describe el tratamiento exitoso mediante cirugía endovascular de una fístula postraumática tras una herida penetrante entre la arteria maxilar interna izquierda y la vena yugular externa. A través de este caso clínico y la revisión de la literatura se ilustran las causas, manifestaciones, estudio radiológico y tratamiento de una fístula postraumática entre la arteria maxilar interna y la vena yugular externa. A través de este caso clínico se demuestra la utilidad de los procedimientos endovasculares en el tratamiento de estas complicaciones(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. oral maxilofac;32(2): 71-75, abr.-jun. 2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81833</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fístula arteriovenosa postraumática: tratamiento endovascular. Revisión de la literatura y presentación de un caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8606^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20180^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24339^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15348^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15348^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8606^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8606^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52881^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22935^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23232^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201006</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
