<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157603</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Neurosyphilis in the 21st century: a descriptive study in a tertiary hospital in Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Neurosyphilis can occur at any time following infection by Treponema pallidum and its incidence has increased over recent years. The epidemiological and clinical pattern has undergone a substantial change in the post-antibiotic era. AIMS. To describe and analyse the population of patients diagnosed with neurosyphilis at a tertiary hospital in Madrid from January to May 2015. Patients and methods. A retrospective analysis of the following data was performed: demographic, clinical, complementary tests &#150;serology, cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), neuroimaging&#150; and progression of 28 patients diagnosed between 2008 and 2015. Results. Most of the patients were males (89.3%), Spanish (60.7%), with a mean age of 53 ± 16.4 years. The most frequent forms were asymptomatic (39.3%), followed by ocular syphilis (21%), non-classical forms (14.3%), cognitive deterioration and neuropsychiatric alterations (11%). Fifty per cent presented a concomitant infection by human immunodeficiency virus, most of them asymptomatic, with a significant correlation between CD4+ T-cells and asymptomatic neurosyphilis. Only 50% presented VDRL+ in CSF, the diagnosis being based on the clinical features, serology and alterations in CSF (cytobiochemical or serological). Neuroimages were unspecific in most cases. The early and ocular forms were associated to a better clinical course. Conclusions. With respect to the pre-antibiotic era, an important decrease can be observed in the late-onset forms, as well as the appearance of non-classical forms that can mimic other conditions such as viral encephalitis. Diagnosis is complex and based on the clinical features, the serology and study of CSF, often with a complex interpretation, and thus clinical suspicion plays a fundamental role in the diagnosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villar Quiles, Rocío</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porta Etessam, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La neurosífilis puede ocurrir en cualquier momento tras la infección por Treponema pallidum y su incidencia está aumentando en los últimos años. El patrón epidemiológico y clínico ha experimentado un cambio sustancial en la era postantibiótica. Objetivo. Describir y analizar la población de pacientes con diagnóstico de neurosífilis de un hospital terciario de Madrid desde enero de 2008 a mayo 2015. Pacientes y métodos. Se analizaron retrospectivamente datos demográficos, clínicos, pruebas complementarias &#150;serología, líquido cefalorraquídeo (LCR), neuroimagen&#150; y evolución de 28 pacientes diagnosticados entre 2008 y 2015. Resultados. La mayoría fueron varones (89,3%), españoles (60,7%), con una edad media de 53 ± 16,4 años. Lo más frecuente fueron las formas asintomáticas (39,3%), seguidas de sífilis ocular (21%), formas no clásicas (14,3%), deterioro cognitivo y alteraciones neuropsiquiátricas (11%). El 50% presentaba infección concomitante por virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana, la mayoría asintomáticos, con una correlación significativa entre linfocitos T CD4+ y neurosífilis asintomática. Únicamente el 50% presentó VDRL+ en el LCR, basándose el diagnóstico en la clínica, la serología y las alteraciones en el LCR (citobioquímicas o serológicas). La neuroimagen fue inespecífica en la mayoría de los casos. Las formas tempranas y las formas oculares se asociaron a una mejor evolución clínica. Conclusiones. Respecto a la era preantibiótica, se observa un descenso muy importante en las formas tardías, así como la aparición de formas no clásicas que pueden simular otras entidades, como encefalitis víricas. El diagnóstico es complejo y se basa en la clínica, la serología y el estudio del LCR, a menudo con una interpretación compleja, por lo que la sospecha clínica es fundamental en el diagnóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;63(9): 393-402, 1 nov., 2016. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157603</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Neurosífilis en el siglo XXI: estudio descriptivo en un hospital terciario de Madrid</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13989^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14604^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24326^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9683^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54009^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29989^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13974^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
