<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-108297</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-239X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Motivational profiles of spanish adolescent athletes</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was to detect possible motivational profiles in a sample of adolescent athletes. Furthermore, the study analysed the differences in the perceived motivational climate&#146;s sub-factors and the satisfaction of the basic psychological needs of the different profiles that were found. A sample of 608 athletes was used, and subjects had a mean age of 14.43 years. The perceived motivational climate (PMCSQ-2), psychological mediators (BPNES), and motivation of the athletes in sport (SMS) were measured. Cluster analysis revealed two profiles. A highly motivated profile, with high scores in both forms of motivation: self-determined (intrinsic motivation and identified regulation) and non-self-determined motivation (introjected and external regulation), save for amotivation; and a moderately motivated profile, with moderate scores (around 3 and 4) in forms of self-determined and non-determined motivation. In the multivariate analysis of the perceived motivational climate&#146;s sub-factors and of the basic psychological needs according to the profile, significant differences were found in favour of the highly motivated profile both for the task-involving climate and egoinvolving climate sub-factors, as well as for the three psychological mediators. The results are discussed in regard to the importance of encouraging a climate that involves tasks and that tries to satisfy the need for autonomy, competence, and relationships with others during training sessions in order to obtain more self-determined motivational profiles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almagro, Barrtolomé J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno-Murcia, Juan Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sáenz-López, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo del estudio fue detectar posibles perfiles motivacionales en una muestra de deportistas adolescentes. Además, el estudio analizó las diferencias en los subfactores del clima motivacional percibido y en la satisfacción de las necesidades psicológicas básicas de los diferentes perfiles encontrados. Se utilizó una muestra de 608 deportistas, con una edad media de 14.43 años. Se midió el clima motivacional percibido (PMCSQ-2), los mediadores psicológicos (BPNES) y la motivación en el deporte (SMS). El análisis de cluster reveló dos perfiles: un perfil altamente motivado, con puntuaciones altas tanto en formas de motivación autodeterminada (motivación intrínseca y regulación identificada) como en motivación no autodeterminada (regulación introyectada y externa), salvando la desmotivación; y un perfil moderadamente motivado, con puntuaciones moderadas (en torno a 3 y 4) en formas de motivación autodeterminada y no autodeterminada. En el análisis multivariante de los subfactores del clima motivacional percibido y de las necesidades piscológicas básicas según el perfil, se encontraron diferencias significativas a favor del perfil altamente motivado tanto en los subfactores del clima motivacional tarea como ego, así como en los tres mediadores psicológicos. Se discuten los resultados en función de la importancia de fomentar un clima que implique a la tarea y que trate de satisfacer las necesidades de autonomía, competencia y relación con los demás durante los entrenamientos para obtener perfiles motivacionales más autodeterminados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. deport;21(2): 223-231, jul.-dic. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-108297</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Perfiles motivacionales de deportistas adolescentes españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5180^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35416^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28408</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28597^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9234^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201212</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
