<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-66242</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Sweat rate as best indicator of heat aclimation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: to determine which of three commonly used indexed to evaluate acclimation (tympanic temperature, sweat rate, or heart rat is the most sensitive and reliable). Material and methods: seven young University students (28+/-8 years and 4.2+/-0.6 L/min VO2max) pedalled at 60% del VO2max for 60 minutes during 7 days (maximum of 2 rest days in between) in a climatic chamber set at 34.4+/-0.3ºC and 27.7+/-0.1% of relative humidity with 0.2 m/s of wind speed. This acclimation protocol was repeated in 3 occasions () A1, A2 y A3) separated by 3 months to study  reliability. Results: After 3 days of acclimation sweat rate was higher than on day 1 in all (p&lt;0.05) although a steady-state was not achieved at day 7. Tympanic temperature at the end of exercise was unchanged with no effect of days of acclimation. Heart rate at the end of exercise was lower than the day 1 after 5-6 days in all acclimations (p&lt;0.05) without reaching a steady-state. There were a high reliability in sweat rate (R1=0.90) and heart rate (R1=0.84) but moderate for tympanic temperature (R1=0.71). Conclusions: Sweat rate is the most sensitive indication of acclimatation and we recommended its use over heart rate or tympanic temperature. Although the effects 1 week acclimation are lost within 3 months (day 1 of A1, A2, and A3 are similar) the responses are highly reliable. Finally, we confirm previous reports that indicates that indicate that over 7 days are needed to reach a steady-state response in sweat rate and heart rate</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mora, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lozano, Rubén</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peñaloza, Ricardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguado, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Coso, Juan del</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Determinar cual de los tres índices de aclimatación comúnmente utilizados (temperatura timpánica, ritmo de sudoración, o frecuencia cardiaca) es el más sensible y reproducible. Material y métodos: Siete jóvenes estudiantes universitarios (28+/- asños y 4,2+/-0,6 L/min VO2max) pedalearon a una intensidad del 60% del VO2max durante 60 minutos por 7 días (2 días de descanso máximo) en una cámara climática a 34,4+/-0,3ºC y 27,7+/-0,1% de humedad relativa, con 0,2 m/s de velocidad de viento. Este proceso de aclimatación se repitió 3 veces (A1, A2 y A3) espacidas por 3 meses para estudiar la reproducibilidad de las respuestas. Resultados: Tras 3 días de aclimatación el ritmo de sudoración (RS) subió por encima del ritmo del día 1 en todas las aclimataciones (p&lt;0.05) pero no alcanzó un estado estable tras 7 días. La reproducibilidad entre aclimataciones fue alta para el ritmo de sudoración (R1=0.90), y frecuencia cardiaca final (R1=0.71). Conclusiones: El ritmo de sudoración es el índice más sensible y reproducible de aclimatación y recomendamos su uso en vez de frecuencia cardíaca o temperatura timpánica. Aunque los efectos de una semana de aclimatación al calor se pierden en 3 mese (día 1 de A1, A2 y A3 son similares) las respuestas son altamente reproducibles. Por último, confirmamos datos anteriores que más de 7 días son necesarios para alcanzar la máxima adaptación en ritmo de sudoración y frecuencia cardíaca</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;23(116): 433-439, nov.-dic. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-66242</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ritmo de sudoración como mejor indicador de aclimatación al calor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30732^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13927^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1858^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d68^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14832^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2183^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2183^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6493^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2183^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13563^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
