<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-056279</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The old battle between the human species and Koch&#146;s bacillae. Can one dream of eradicating tuberculosis?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This article analyses the complexity of the age-old        battle that the human species has been waging for        millions of years against Mycobacterium tuberculosis.        We review all of the knowledge available about this        disease, and the most important future developments,        in order to reach the conclusion that it is indeed        possible to dream of eradicating this disease that has        caused such harm to humanity.        In spite of the human species possessing sufficient        knowledge to win the battle against Mycobacterium        tuberculosis, important conditioning factors, above all        social in character (poverty, immigration, HIV, MDR),        are favouring the bacteria in this war. And, in spite of        suitably applying all of the positive knowledge        acquired for the control of TB (detection and cure of        cases, chemoprofilaxis, BCG vaccination, etc.), it will        still take several centuries to achieve its eradication.        Only by discovering a vaccine that is 100% efficient, or        the discovery of new anti-microbial associations that        could cure the disease in no longer than 15 days, could        accelerate this advance towards its eradication. But,        unfortunately, there are no reasons allowing us to        dream that either of these two possibilities can be        fulfilled in the next 10 to 20 years.        Therefore, the dream of eradicating TB is a very        old dream, but one that unfortunately remains very        distant</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Caminero, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El presente trabajo trata de analizar la complejidad        de la vieja batalla que lleva librando, desde hace        millones de años, la especie humana contra Mycobacterium        tuberculosis, intentando realizar un repaso de        todos los conocimientos que se tienen sobre esta        enfermedad y de lo más importante de lo que puede        acontecer en el futuro, con el fin de llegar a la conclusión        de si es posible acabar soñando con erradicar esta        enfermedad que tanto daño ha causado a la humanidad.        A pesar de que la especie humana tiene suficientes        conocimientos para vencer la batalla a M. tuberculosis,        importantes condicionantes, sobre todo sociales        (pobreza, inmigración, VIH, MDR), están favoreciendo        la guerra del lado del bacilo. Y que, incluso aplicando        adecuadamente todos los buenos conocimientos        adquiridos para el control de la TB (detección y curación        de casos, quimioprofilaxis, vacunación BCG, etc.),        se tardaría aún varios siglos en poder conseguir la erradicación.        Sólo la posibilidad de descubrir una vacuna        100% eficaz, o el descubrimiento de nuevas asociaciones        antimicrobianas que pudiesen curar la enfermedad        en un plazo no superior a 15 días, podría acelerar este        ritmo hacia la erradicación. Pero, lamentablemente, no        existen fundamentos que permitan soñar con que cualquiera        de estas dos posibilidades pueda cumplirse en        los próximos 10-20 años.        Por lo tanto, el sueño de erradicar la TB es un        sueño muy antiguo, pero, lamentablemente, aún muy        lejano</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;30(supl.2): 163-180, 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-056279</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La vieja batalla entre la especie humana y el bacilo de Koch. ¿Es posible soñar con erradicar la tuberculosis?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23093^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23093^s22055</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3687</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13344</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33160^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7291^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33160^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14778^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
