<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-143485</identifier>
<setSpec>0048-7120</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of resistance traininig on blood glucose control and muscle function in sedentary adult women in Los Ángeles, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. A sedentary lifestyle is associated with numerous metabolic diseases, such as insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes mellitus. Recent studies have reported that resistance exercise is an effective method to counteract these metabolic diseases. Objective. To analyze the metabolic and physical effects of a 12-week resistance exercise program in 40 sedentary women aged between 30 and 60 years who worked at the University of Concepcion, Los Ángeles, Chile. The study was conducted between September and December, 2013. Materials and methods. Participants were randomly assigned to either an experimental group or to a control group. The experimental group trained four large muscle groups (arm flexors, trunk flexors, arm extensors and leg extensors) twice a week for 12 weeks. Glucose tolerance was measured with a fasting glucose test at baseline and 120 minutes after ingestion of anhydrous glucose dissolved in water. Besides, muscular resistance was measured through a 'life fitness multi station 3'. Results. Fasting glucose levels decreased in the experimental group (p = .023) but increased in the control group (p = .006). Muscle strength significantly improved in the four muscle groups evaluated in the experimental group compared with the control group (arm flexors; p = .001), (trunk flexors; p = .000), (arm extensors; p = .000) and (leg extensors; p = .000). Conclusions. Strength training can reduce fasting glucose levels and increase muscle strength in sedentary adult women (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Monsalves, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Saavedra, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zapata-Lamana, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cigarroa, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El sedentarismo se asocia a múltiples alteraciones metabólicas como la insulinorresistencia y la diabetes mellitus tipo II. Recientes estudios indican que el ejercicio de fuerza-resistencia es efectivo en contrarrestar estas alteraciones metabólicas. Objetivo. Analizar efectos metabólicos y físicos de un programa de entrenamiento de fuerza-resistencia en 40 mujeres de entre 30 y 60 años, sedentarias, trabajadoras de la Universidad de Concepción, Los Ángeles, Chile durante septiembre-diciembre del 2013. Materiales y métodos. Los participantes fueron asignados aleatoriamente a un grupo de trabajo que realizó un programa de entrenamiento de fuerza o a un grupo control que no realizó ejercicio físico. El grupo de trabajo entrenó 4 grandes grupos musculares (flexores de brazo y tronco, extensores de brazo y pierna) 2 veces por semana durante un periodo de 12 semanas. Se midió tolerancia a la glucosa a través de la glucemia basal en ayunas y 120 minutos después de haber ingerido glucosa anhidra disuelta en agua. Además, se midió fuerza-resistencia de los grupos musculares entrenados a través de una «multiestación life fitness 3». Resultados. El grupo de trabajo disminuyó los niveles de glucemia basal (p = 0,023) en comparación a la evaluación inicial, en cambio el grupo control los aumentó (p = 0,006). En relación a la fuerza-resistencia, el grupo de trabajo mostró mejoras significativas en los cuatro grupos musculares evaluados en comparación al grupo control (flexores de brazos; p = 0,001), (flexores de tronco; p = 0,000), (extensores de brazos; p = 0,000) y (extensores de piernas; p = 0,000). Conclusiones. El entrenamiento de fuerza es capaz de disminuir los niveles de glucemia basal B, además de incrementar la fuerza-resistencia muscular en mujeres adultas sedentarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rehabilitación (Madr., Ed. impr.);49(4): 202-209, oct.-dic. 2015. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-143485</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos del entrenamiento fuerza-resistencia en el control de glucosa y función muscular en mujeres adultas sedentarias de Los Ángeles, Chile</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2722^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53743</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53234^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53234^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33926^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53234^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
