<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166053</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Type II olecranon fractures in patients over 65. Tension band or pre-formed plate? Analysis and results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. The objective of this study was to compare the clinical outcomes of surgical treatment using tension band with needles and preformed plates in type ii olecranon fractures according to the Mayo classification in patients older than 65 years. Material and method. A descriptive, retrospective study of 49 patients with a mean age of 75.1 years who underwent surgery olecranon fracture using 2 different fixing systems. The Mayo classification was used to define them, excluding type i and iii, and the VAS to assess postoperative pain. Patients were assessed functionally by the questionnaire Quick DASH. All measurement was performed with goniometer and joint balance serial radiographs at one month, 3, 6 and 12 months. Minimum follow-up was one year. Results. In 26 patients the tension band was used and the preformed plates in 23. There were no statistically significant differences in functional outcomes, joint balance or postoperative VAS between the 2 groups. There were a greater proportion of patients who had to be operated because of problems related to osteosynthesis material in those in which preformed plates were used. Conclusions. Treatment of olecranon fractures with tension band with needles and cerclage remains the surgery of choice in patients older than 65 years (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cáceres-Sánchez, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liñán-Padilla, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. El objeto de este estudio fue comparar los resultados clínicos del tratamiento quirúrgico mediante banda a tensión con agujas y las placas preconformadas en las fracturas de olécranon tipo ii de Mayo en pacientes mayores de 65 años. Material y método. Estudio descriptivo, restrospectivo, de 49 pacientes con una edad media de 75,1 años, intervenidos quirúrgicamente de fractura de olécranon mediante 2 sistemas distintos de fijación. Se empleó la clasificación de Mayo para definirlas, excluyendo los tipos i y iii, y la EVA para valorar el dolor postoperatorio. Los pacientes fueron evaluados funcionalmente mediante el cuestionario Quick DASH. A todos se les realizó medición del balance articular con goniómetro y radiografías seriadas al mes, 3, 6 y 12 meses. El seguimiento mínimo fue de un año. Resultados. En 26 pacientes se empleó la banda a tensión y en 23, las placas preformadas. No hubo diferencias estadísticamente significativas en los resultados funcionales, el balance articular ni la EVA postoperatoria entre los 2 grupos. Sí destaca una mayor proporción de pacientes a los que hubo que intervenir por problemas relacionados con el material de osteosíntesis en aquellos en los que se emplearon placas preformadas. Conclusiones. El tratamiento quirúrgico de las fracturas de olécranon tipo ii en pacientes mayores de 65 años mediante el uso de placas preformadas no aportó mejores resultados que los obtenidos mediante la fijación con banda a tensión (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);61(5): 339-342, sept.-oct. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166053</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas de olécranon tipo ii en mayores de 65 años. ¿Banda a tensión o placa preformada? Análisis y resultados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5728^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53413^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53413^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53413^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55361</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
