<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-100332</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of diabetes mellitus in geriatric patients in nursing homes of Cádiz. Diagerca study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To determine prevalence and clinical characteristics of elderly diabetic patients in nursing homes. Material and method. Observational and multicentre study in 14 nursing homes in Cádiz (Spain). Study variables: age, sex, prevalence of diabetes, duration of diabetes, complications, macrovascular complications, retinopathy, nephropathy, and neuropathy. Metabolic control: frequency of baseline blood glucose and HbA1c determinations. Metabolic complications suffered. Treatment: oral and type of antidiabetics, insulinisation. Diabetes education. Functional and mental assessment using Barthel index and MMT. Data was analysed using SPSS v17.0. Results. A total of 1952 elderly institutionalised patients were studied, with a diabetes prevalence of 26.44%. The study included 312 patients with a mean age of 79.7 years, of whom 57.4% were women, and 66.9% knew of their diagnosis of diabetes for over 10 years. Vascular events were suffered by 55.1%, with the most common being ischaemic stroke (55.2%), followed by myocardial infarction (18%) and 14.5% with peripheral arterial disease. There were 29.6% with retinopathy, 21.3% diabetic nephropathy, and 25.6% suffering from distal symmetric polyneuropathy. HbA1c analysis was performed in 90.1% of patients, with 50% levels between 7 and 9%, with a six-monthly assessment rate of 63.4%. Metabolic complications: diabetic ketoacidosis 7.1%, hyperosmolar syndrome 2.9%, and 15.7% symptomatic hypoglycaemia. Oral hypoglycaemic agents were being taken by 66% of patients, with the most frequently used being metformin (55.3%) followed by gliclazide and repaglinide (10.2%, 3.4%, respectively). 50.2% were insulinised. 45.6% functional dependence. Barthel Index average of 48.4 points, with 46.1% diagnosed with dementia, moderate state, 36.7%. Conclusions. Diabetic prevalence in nursing homes is high, and institutionalised patients are elderly, long-standing diabetics, with both macro- and microvascular complications, and have a significant level of mental and functional disabilities(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Durán Alonso, Juan Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Conocer la prevalencia y las características clínicas de los ancianos diabéticos en residencias asistidas. Material y método. Estudio observacional, multicéntrico, realizado en 14 residencias geriátricas asistidas de la provincia de Cádiz. Variables del estudio: edad, sexo, prevalencia de la diabetes, tiempo de evolución de la diabetes, presencia de complicaciones (macrovasculares, retinopatía, nefropatía y neuropatía). Control metabólico: frecuencia de determinación de glucemias basales y de HbA1c. Complicaciones metabólicas sufridas; tratamiento utilizado: antidiabéticos orales y tipos, e insulinización; educación diabetológica; valoración funcional y mental. Los datos obtenidos se analizaron mediante programa estadístico SPSS v17.0. Resultados. Sobre 1.952 ancianos institucionalizados, la prevalencia de diabetes fue del 26,44%. Se incluyen en el estudio 312 pacientes, edad media: 79,7 años y el 57,4% eran mujeres. El 66,9% eran diabéticos desde hace más de 10 años. El 55,1% han sufrido algún evento vascular: ictus isquémico 55,2%; infarto de miocardio 18%, y arteriopatía periférica el 14,5%. El 29,6% padece retinopatía, el 21,3% padece nefropatía diabética y el 25,6% neuropatía diabética. El 90,1% de los pacientes dispone de determinación de HbA1c, presentando el 50% niveles entre 7 y 9%, con frecuencia de determinación semestral en el 63,4%. Como complicaciones metabólicas, el 7,1% presentó algún episodio de cetoacidosis diabética, el 2,9% síndrome hiperosmolar, y el 15,7% hipoglucemias sintomáticas. El 66% de los pacientes tomaban antidiabéticos orales, metformina el 55,3% seguido de glicazida el 10,2% y repaglinida el 3,4%. El 50,2% estaba insulinizado. El 45,6% sufría dependencia funcional con media en Barthel de 48,4 puntos. Y el 46,1% está diagnosticado de demencia, encontrándose en fase moderada el 36,7%. Conclusiones. La prevalencia de la diabetes en residencias es alta. Los ancianos diabéticos institucionalizados son de edad avanzada, con diabetes de larga evolución que han sufrido complicaciones tanto macro como microvasculares, más de la mitad ya insulinizados, y presentan un grado de discapacidad mental y funcional importante(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);47(3): 114-118, may.jun.2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-100332</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de diabetes mellitus en pacientes geriátricos institucionalizados en la provincia de Cádiz. Estudio Diagerca</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37656^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1812^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38644^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50238</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6450^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
