<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047983</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-3593</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Do we resist prevention? Focal groups to generate ideas that increase compliance</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVE. Identify interventions to be introduced, that increase compliance of four high impact preventive activities in health and low compliance (anti-smoking advise, screening of sexual practices of risk, contraception information, control of blood pressure values), and to detect the resistances and difficulties of the clinicians to these interventions and activities. DESIGN. Qualitative study with focal groups. SITE. Urban Health Area in Madrid. Years 1999-2000. PARTICIPANTS. Three groups: a) of all the managers and technicians of the health care administrations of the Area (10 participants), b) of the representatives of the clinicians, chosen by the clinics, one for each primary care team (PCT) (20 participants), c) of the clinical leaders chosen by the authors (15 participants). METHOD. Technique of focal groups, with one two-hour session, with moderator and external observer. Registry of the key opinions was done. RESULTS. The following ideas were identified: a) stickers/flash, b) modification of the sheet/plan of adult preventive activities, c) reminders written in the out-patient clinic, d) review of clinical records before beginning the visit, e) indicate uncontrolled blood pressure values, f) define nursing quality guidelines, g) educational workshops for the professionals, h) written reminders in the referrals to specialists, i) reminder sessions, j) internal audits. Resistances and difficulties in the interventions a, b, g, and h were identified. CONCLUSIONS. To increase four high impact preventive interventions in health and low compliance, interventions have been found, without finding resistances or difficulties, focused on the conduction of reminders and performance of evaluations</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Liñares Paz, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Maganto Sancho, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garzón González, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Cuñarro, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sacristán Rubio, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Orozco Sanmartín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO. Identificar intervenciones a introducir que aumenten el cumplimiento de cuatro actividades preventivas de alto impacto en la salud y de bajo cumplimiento (consejo antitabaco, despistaje prácticas sexuales de riesgo, información anticoncepción, control de cifras tensionales), así como detectar las resistencias y dificultades de los clínicos a estas intervenciones y actividades. DISEÑO. Estudio cualitativo con grupos focales. EMPLAZAMIENTO. Un Área de Salud urbana de Madrid. Años 1999-2000. PARTICIPANTES. Tres grupos: a) de todos los gestores y técnicos de las direcciones asistenciales del Área (10 participantes), b) de representantes de los clínicos, elegidos por éstos, uno por cada Equipo de Atención Primaria (EAP) (20 participantes) y c) de líderes clínicos seleccionados por los autores (15 participantes). MÉTODO. Técnica de grupos focales, con una sesión de unas dos horas, con moderador y observador externo. Se realizó registro de las opiniones clave. RESULTADOS. Se identificaron las siguientes ideas: a) pegatinas/flash, b) modificación de la hoja/plan de actividades preventivas del adulto, c) recordatorios escritos en la consulta, d) revisión de historias antes del comienzo de la consulta, e) marcar cifras tensionales descontroladas, f) definir normas de calidad en enfermería, g) talleres formativos a los profesionales, h) recordatorios escritos en las derivaciones a especialistas, i) sesiones recordatorio, j) auditorías internas. Se identificaron resistencias y dificultades en las intervenciones a, b, g y h. CONCLUSIONES. Para incrementar cuatro intervenciones preventivas de alto impacto en salud y de bajo cumplimiento se han encontrado intervenciones, sin hallar resistencias o dificultades, centradas en la realización de recordatorios y evaluaciones</dc:description>
<dc:source>SEMERGEN, Soc. Esp. Med. Rural Gen. (Ed. Impr.);32(7): 325-329, ago. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047983</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Nos resistimos a la prevención? Grupos focales para generar ideas que aumenten el cumplimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11758</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14904</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
