<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140014</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Evaluation of diet acceptance by patients with haematological cancer during chemotherapeutic treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: a compromised nutritional status is one of the factors that may increase the morbidity and mortality of chemotherapy patients. The goal of this study was to evaluate acceptance of the diet by patients with haematological cancer throughout their hospital stay for chemotherapeutic treatment. Method: this was a cross-sectional, descriptive, quantitative study, carried out from February to October 2014 in adult patients of both genders diagnosed with lymphoma and leukaemia. Food intake was evaluated on a daily basis through a recording instrument designed by the author. ANOVA test for repeated measurements was employed. Results: 32 patients were evaluated, with a mean age of 42 ± 11 years, the majority of whom were women (66%). We observed gastrointestinal disturbances in 72% of the patients, most commonly nausea (59%), followed by xerostomia (34%), vomiting (28%) and dysgeusia (25%). The percentage of leftover food was significant, varying from 23% to 35%. Lunch and dinner were the most frequently rejected meals. Light meals were more well-tolerated, having been accepted in 75% to 100% of the offers. Conclusion: The food records show that during chemotherapy cycles, patients present significant food rejection, specially with larger meals such as lunch and dinner, though light meals are better tolerated. Employing food options chosen by patients may be a strategy to improve dietary acceptance. More studies on this subject are necessary in order to improve nutritional care to this population, aiming to prevent and/or rehabilitate the nutritional status of these patients (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ferreira, Marilyn Gonçalves</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salles, Raquel Kuerten de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prockmann, Stéphanie</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Freitas, Ana Helena Ruschel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vieira, Francilene Gracieli Kunradi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: el estado nutricional amenazado es uno de los factores que puede elevar la morbimortalidad de los pacientes sometidos a quimioterapia. El objetivo de este estudio fue evaluar la aceptación de la dieta por parte de pacientes con cáncer hematológico durante la internación para quimioterapia. Métodos: investigación transversal, descriptiva y cuantitativa llevada a cabo entre febrero y octubre de 2014 con pacientes adultos de ambos sexos diagnosticados de linfoma y leucemia. Se realizó la evaluación diaria del consumo alimentario mediante la utilización de herramientas para colección de datos preparado por el autor. Se utilizó ANOVA para medidas repetidas. Resultados: fueron evaluados 32 pacientes con edad promedio de 42±11 años, siendo la mayoría mujeres (66%). Observamos trastornos gastrointestinales en el 72% de los pacientes, la mayoría de las molestias fueron náuseas (59%) además de xerostomía (34%), vómitos (28%), inapetencia (28%) y disgeusia (25%). El porcentaje de resto de ingesta alimentaria fue significativo, oscilando entre el 23% y el 35%. El mayor rechazo ocurrió en el almuerzo y la cena. Las meriendas fueron mejor aceptadas, con un porcentaje del 75% al 100%. Conclusión de la investigación: los registros de alimentos mostraron que durante los ciclos de quimioterapia se produjo un rechazo significativo de alimentos sobre todo en las comidas de mayor volumen, como el almuerzo y la cena, mientras que las comidas pequeñas, tales como aperitivos, son mejor toleradas. El uso de opciones de alimentos enumerados por los pacientes puede ser una estrategia para mejorar el cumplimiento de la dieta. Se necesitan más estudios sobre este tema para mejorar la atención a esta población, con el objetivo de prevenir y/o recuperar el estado nutricional de estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;32(2): 779-784, ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140014</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de la aceptación de la dieta por los pacientes con cáncer hematológico durante el tratamiento quimioterapéutico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28466^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32936^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15386^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15386^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23872^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32936^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23872^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8398^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4067^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
