<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158818</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-8264</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improvement of assistance quality. I. Definitions and evaluation cycle and improvement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This paper defines several aspects of quality of health care and the evaluation and the technique of improvement cycle. The elements are discussed in terms of the structure of the health care system, the processes of care, and outcomes resulting from care. Growing demand for health care, rising costs, constrained resources, and evidence of variations in clinical practice have increased interest in measuring and improving the quality of health care in many countries of the world. There has been a move away from assessing costs and activity to assessing quality with an emphasis on both efficient use of resources and on the effectiveness of health care. The evaluation and improvement cycle is an iterative six-step management method used in business technology for the control and continual improvement of processes and products which have demonstrated its applicability in quality health improvement (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Sáiz, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>San Norberto, EM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este artículo define diversos aspectos de la calidad de la asistencia sanitaria y la técnica del ciclo de mejora. Estos elementos son discutidos en términos de la estructura del sistema sanitario, los diversos procesos de salud y los resultados de los mismos. Existe una demanda creciente por el cuidado de la salud, que acarrea unos elevados costes, una escasez de recursos y la existencia de evidentes variaciones en la práctica clínica, lo que ha motivado un creciente interés en la medida y la mejora de la calidad de la asistencia sanitaria en muchos países del mundo. Ha existido un movimiento de valoración de los costes y una actividad de valoración de la calidad, con énfasis en el uso eficiente de los recursos y la efectividad en el cuidado de la salud. El ciclo de evaluación y mejora es un método iterativo de seis pasos empleado en técnicas empresariales para el control y la mejora continuada de procesos y productos, que ha demostrado su aplicabilidad en la mejora de la calidad sanitaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. investig. quir;19(4): 169-174, 2016. graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158818</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mejora de la calidad asistencial. I. Definiciones y ciclo de evaluación y mejora</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12224</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33551^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54376</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31493</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201600</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
