<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-118326</identifier>
<setSpec>2014-9832</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Assessment of knowledge in the management of mechanical ventilation in medical residents</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. In our environment patients who require mechanical ventilation are in areas where most of the time there is no specialist in intensive care, many patients are the responsibility of medical residents. The objective of this research was to validate an instrument to Spanish to determine the level of knowledge among residents in mechanical ventilation. Subjects and methods. A pilot test was performed which included medical residents from different years of training in the areas of Anesthesiology, Internal Medicine and Emergency Medicine, prior signed informed consent. We applied the questionnaire designed by Cox and translated from English into Spanish for validation. It was based on four clinical cases with 19 questions. Results. 81 questionnaires were applied, of whom 46% were Emergency medicine residents, 37% of Internal Medicine and17% of Anesthesiology. Half of the residents were a first year. The minimum score was 4 and the maximum of 17. Sixty-fiveper cent of the residents did not reach a passing score, and only 4% with an adequate level of knowledge. Not detected difficulties in implementation and understanding of the test. Conclusions. The complexity of the test was acceptable and was most useful in medical residents in their final years of training. The instrument is useful to assess knowledge on mechanical ventilation in the Spanish version. Level of knowledge was low in our sample studied (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Calixto-Bello, Rubén A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Bernardino, Carlos A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guerrero-Quintero, Laura G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prieto-Miranda, Sergio E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. En nuestro medio, los pacientes que requieren ventilación mecánica se encuentran en áreas donde la mayoría de las veces no se dispone de un especialista en cuidados intensivos, quedando a cargo de médicos residentes. El objetivo de este estudio fue validar un instrumento al castellano para conocer el nivel de conocimientos que tienen los residentes sobre ventilación mecánica. Sujetos y métodos. Se realizó una prueba piloto donde se incluyeron médicos residentes en diferentes años de formación de las áreas de anestesiología, medicina interna y urgencias médico-quirúrgicas, previo consentimiento informado. Se aplicó el cuestionario diseñado por Cox y traducido al castellano para su validación. Éste se basó en cuatro casos clínicos con 19 preguntas. Resultados. Se aplicaron 81 cuestionarios, de ellos el 46% correspondieron a médicos de urgencias, el 37% a médicos de medicina interna y el 17% a médicos de anestesiología. La mitad de los residentes fueron de primer año. La calificación mínima fue de cuatro aciertos, y la máxima, de 17. El 65% de los médicos residentes tuvieron calificación no aprobatoria y sólo el 4% alcanzó un nivel de conocimientos suficiente. No se detectaron dificultades en la aplicación y comprensión de la prueba. Conclusiones. La complejidad de la prueba fue aceptable y su mayor utilidad fue para médicos residentes en sus últimos años de formación. El instrumento resulta útil para evaluar conocimientos en ventilación mecánica en su versión al castellano. El nivel de conocimientos fue insuficiente en la muestra estudiada (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Fund. Educ. Méd. (Ed. impr.);16(4): 203-213, dic. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-118326</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Evaluación de conocimientos sobre el manejode ventilación mecánica en médicos residentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28141</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12541^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
