<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157470</identifier>
<setSpec>2253-654X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Contribution of early SPECT/CT to 99mTc-MIBI double phase scintigraphy in primary hyperparathyroidism: Diagnostic value and correlation between uptake and biological parameters</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. To evaluate the value of 99mTc-MIBI double-phase scintigraphy (DPS) and early SPECT/CT in the pre-surgical assessment of patients with primary hyperparathyroidism (PHPT). Also, to calculate the correlation between uptake and some biological parameters. Material and methods. Forty patients with PHPT were included: 37 solitary adenomas, 1 hyperplasia, and 2 double adenomas. Fifteen patients had ectopic glands. DPS and early SPECT/CT were acquired in all patients. Ultrasound was performed in 31/40. All patients underwent surgery, intra-operative iPTH measurements, and histopathological examinations. Qualitative DPS uptake was assessed and correlated to pre-surgical calcium, iPTH levels, gland weight, and maximum diameter. Results. In the planar study, there were 23 positive cases, 8 doubtful, and 9 negatives. With the SPECT/CT, 8/9 negatives cases were located. All doubtful cases were confirmed as positives. Gland location improved in 16 cases (12 ectopic). DPS+SPECT/CT failed to detect a solitary adenoma and at least one gland in three cases of multiglandular disease (MGD). The sensitivity by patient was: DPS 72.5%, DPS+SPECT/CT 90%, and ultrasound 42%. Ultrasound and scintigraphy (DPS+SPECT/CT) were concordant in 16/31 patients. For the rest of them, scintigraphy proved correct in 14/15, and both techniques failed in one case. There was a significant correlation between level of uptake and iPTH level, gland weight, and maximum diameter. Conclusion. Early SPECT/CT improves sensitivity and the locating of parathyroid pathological glands and increases diagnostic confidence. iPTH level, glandular size, and weight are related to the qualitative assessment of 99mTc-MIBI uptake in early DPS (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Soto, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, JG</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montes, AA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Selma, ML</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamazo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Talavera, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la gammagrafía de doble fase con 99mTc-MIBI (GDF) y el SPECT/TC precoz, en la valoración prequirúrgica del hiperparatiroidismo primario (HPTP), calculando la correlación entre grado de captación y algunos parámetros biológicos. Material y métodos. Se incluyeron 40 pacientes: 37 adenomas solitarios, dos adenomas dobles, una hiperplasia. Quince tenían glándulas ectópicas. En 40 pacientes se realizaron GDF y SPECT/TC; en 31/40, ecografía. Todos los pacientes fueron intervenidos, realizando determinación de PTHi intraoperatoria y examen histopatológico. Se evaluó cualitativamente la captación en la GDF, correlacionándose con calcio y PTHi prequirúrgicos, peso y diámetro máximo glandulares. Resultados. En el estudio planar se obtuvieron 23 casos positivos, 8 dudosos, y 9 negativos. Con SPECT/TC se localizaron 8/9 de los negativos. Todos los dudosos se confirmaron como positivos. La localización glandular mejoró en 16 casos (12 ectópicos). La GDF+SPECT/TC fallaron en la detección de un adenoma solitario y en la visualización de alguna de las glándulas en tres casos de enfermedad multiglandular (EMG). La sensibilidad por pacientes fue: GDF 72,5%, GDF+SPECT/TC 90%, ecografía 42%. Ecografía y gammagrafía (GDF+SPECT/TC) concordaron en 16/31 pacientes. De los no concordantes, la gammagrafía acertó en 14/15 y ambas técnicas fallaron en uno. Hubo correlación significativa entre captación y PTHi, peso y diámetro máximo glandulares. Conclusion. El SPECT/TC precoz mejora la sensibilidad y la localización de las paratiroides patológicas y aumenta la confianza diagnóstica. PTHi, tamaño y peso glandulares se correlacionan con la valoración cualitativa de la captación precoz de 99mTc-MIBI en la GDF (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. nucl. imagen mol. (Ed. impr.);35(6): 351-357, nov.-dic. 2016. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157470</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aportación del SPECT/TC precoz a la gammagrafía de doble fase con 99mTc-MIBI en pacientes con hiperparatiroidismo primario: valor diagnóstico y correlación de la captación con parámetros biológicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27858^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24338^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d244^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27858^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50516^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30483^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25783^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24895^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
