<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-167009</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Effects of an intensive thalassotherapy and aquatic therapy program in stroke patients. A pilot study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Stroke remains the leading cause of acquired disability. Health and social planning and management may vary and although prevention is crucial, having better treatments and strategies to reduce disability is needed. Aim. To determine the effect of an intensive program of thalassotherapy and aquatic therapy in stroke patients, valuing clinical parameters and functional validated scales. Patients and methods. A quasi-experimental prospective study consisting of a specific program assessed pre- and post- 3 weeks treatment to 26 stroke patients with a mild- moderate disability. The outcomes measured were: Berg Balance scale, Timed Up &amp; Go test, 10-meter walking test, 6-minute walking test and pain Visual Analogue Scale. Results. After intervention, participants had a significant improvement in all outcomes measured. Conclusions. Our results suggest that an intensive program of thalassotherapy and aquatic therapy could be useful during stroke rehabilitation to improve balance, gait and pain (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Maraver, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez-Badillo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morer, Carla</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Boestad, Cecilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zuluaga, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El ictus es la principal causa de discapacidad adquirida. Su planificación y gestión (sanitaria y social) varía y, aunque la prevención resulta crucial, no es menos importante disponer de mejores tratamientos y estrategias para reducir la discapacidad. Objetivo. Analizar la eficacia de un programa intensivo de talasoterapia y terapia acuática en pacientes con ictus, valorando parámetros clínicos y escalas funcionales validadas.  Pacientes y métodos. Se realizó un estudio prospectivo cuasi experimental con 26 pacientes con discapacidad leve-moderada postictus. Los pacientes fueron evaluados con las siguientes escalas: equilibrio de Berg, equilibrio dinámico/Timed Up &amp; Go, marcha de 10 metros, seis minutos de marcha y escala visual analógica del dolor, antes y después de realizar tres semanas de tratamiento. Resultados. Finalizado el tratamiento programado, se obtuvieron diferencias significativas para todas las variables estudiadas. Conclusión. Un programa intensivo de talasoterapia y terapia acuática contribuye a mejorar el equilibrio, la marcha y la percepción del dolor en estos pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;65(6): 249-256, 16 sept., 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-167009</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Efectos de un programa intensivo de talasoterapia y terapia acuática en pacientes con ictus. Estudio piloto</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7028^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30524^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34318^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14169^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54692^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
