<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79560</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of some Nursing Theories in the Clinical Practice</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The nursing practice understands experiences and phenomena that the nurse finds when care; these originate in: the patient, the relationship patient nurse, the nurse and the context. The theories arise of the practice and of the investigation and when validating them, they become in explanatory and directive of the same one; the practice based on theory is fed back and for methodological refinement, it becomes in autonomous and creative practice. The objective of this article is to allow to visualize that the applied theory, it changes the form of understanding and processing the information, because it demands depth of thoughts and search of new instruments of analysis to reflect on the actions. The theory validated in the practice offers a systematic form of development of empiric knowledge in a discipline and it indeed provides knowledge and understanding to reinforce it. Learning of how to think in a different way with relation to a problem allows to rehearse other behavior form to the understanding of the reality. It related some theoretical concepts with the nursing practice, by means of an nursing situation that was presented in classroom in 2006 for López, Mesa and Arroyave, students of the specialization in Nursing Care to the critically ill child, Nursing School - University of Antioquia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mejía Lopera, M. Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La práctica de enfermería comprende experiencias y fenómenos que la enfermera encuentra cuando brinda cuidado; éstos se originan en: el paciente, la relación enfermera-paciente, la enfermera y el contexto. Las teorías surgen de la práctica y de la investigación y al validarlas se convierten en explicativas y directivas de la misma; la práctica basada en teoría se realimenta y por refinamiento metodológico, se convierte en autónoma y creativa. El objetivo de este artículo es permitir visualizar que la teoría aplicada, cambia la forma de comprender y procesar información, porque exige profundidad de pensamiento y búsqueda de nuevos instrumentos de análisis para reflexionar las acciones. La teoría validada en la práctica desarrolla sistemáticamente el conocimiento empírico disciplinar y provee conocimiento y comprensión para reforzarla. Aprender a pensar de manera distinta con relación a un problema permite ensayar otros comportamientos para el entendimiento de la realidad. Se relacionan algunos conceptos teóricos con la práctica de enfermería, mediante una situación de enfermería presentada en clase en 2006 por López, Mesa y Arroyave, estudiantes de especialización en Cuidado de Enfermería al niño en estado crítico de salud, Facultad de Enfermería-Universidad de Antioquia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;17(3): 197-200, jul.-sept. 2008.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79560</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de algunas Teorías de Enfermería en la Práctica Clínica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d23591</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9907</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200809</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
