<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104211</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Requirements for and expectations of health technology assessment in Galicia (Spain). A qualitative study from the perspective of decision-makers and clinicians</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To explore perceptions of the use of health technology assessment (HTA) in the Galician public health system, identify opinions on the usefulness of the products and services developed by the Galician Health Technology Assessment Agency (avalia-t), and determine the barriers and facilitators to the transfer of results to clinical practice. Method We performed a qualitative study based on in-depth semi-structured interviews of 20 intentionally selected experts (10 health care professionals and 10 hospital decision makers). The interviews were tape recorded and transcribed for inductive thematic analysis. Results Interest in HTA activities was high, but most informants considered these activities to be underused as a tool to aid decision making in clinical practice. A series of key factors was identified to guarantee HTA use: greater dissemination of HTA activities and availability of the results, increased involvement and communication among health care professionals in the selection and prioritization of relevant research, contextualization and adaptation of results to the local context, increased organizational support and greater financial resources. Conclusions The present study allows end-users¿ opinions on the utility of the various products/services offered by HTA agencies to be contrasted in order to adapt HTA activity to their needs and requirements. The involvement of health care professionals in all HTA fields is perceived as one of the main lines of action for HTA agencies. Such involvement could be achieved by reinforcing personal contact and increasing feedback to collaborators(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Triana, Elena Gervas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez, María Vidal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Varela-Lema, Leonor</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mota, Teresa Cerdá</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Marisa López</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Merino, Gerardo Atienza</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Explorar la percepción de utilización de la evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias en el sistema sanitario público de Galicia, obtener valoraciones sobre la utilidad de los diferentes servicios y productos desarrollados por la Agencia de Evaluación de Tecnologías Sanitarias de Galicia (avalia-t), e identificar barreras y facilitadores a la transferencia de resultados a la práctica clínica. Método Estudio cualitativo basado en 20 entrevistas en profundidad semiestructuradas realizadas a expertos seleccionados mediante muestreo intencional (diez del ámbito clínico y diez de gestión). Las entrevistas fueron grabadas y se realizó un análisis temático inductivo de la información. Resultados Se evidenció un alto grado de interés por la evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias, aunque la gran mayoría de los entrevistados aludieron a su infrautilización como herramienta de decisión en la práctica asistencial. Se identificaron una serie de factores clave para garantizar el éxito de la evaluación: el aumento de las actividades de difusión y disponibilidad de los resultados, el fomento de la comunicación e implicación de los profesionales sanitarios en la selección y priorización de temas a evaluar, la contextualización y adaptación de los estudios al contexto, el aumento del respaldo organizativo y el mayor apoyo económico. Conclusiones El presente estudio permite contrastar con los usuarios finales la valoración/utilidad de los diferentes productos/servicios ofertados por las agencias para poder adecuar la actividad a sus necesidades y expectativas. La colaboración de los profesionales se plantea como uno de los principales ejes de acción para las agencias de evaluación, participación que hay que reforzar en la vertiente del contacto personal, al tiempo que debe fortalecerse la retroalimentación en los procesos de colaboración(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;25(6): 454-460, Dic. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104211</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Demandas y expectativas de la evaluación de tecnologías sanitarias en Galicia. Análisis cualitativo desde la perspectiva de decisores y clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28598</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37677</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50213</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
