<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120686</identifier>
<setSpec>1699-6585</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Relevance of use of short dental implants in patients with severe bone atrophy. Literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The purpose of this review is to determine the relevance of the use of short implants, defining them as "those whose length is &amp;#8804;8 mm" according to the existing bibliography about it. We have centred the search on the use of implants of this length in comparison to alternative treatments (bony grafts, bone augmentation, dental nerve transposition, etc.) in patients with severe maxillary atrophy. It provides answers to the following questions: Is the use of short dental implants a treatment of foreseeable results? Are the percentages of success in the medium and long term comparable to those of implants with an average standard length? In certain clinical situations, can they be used as a substitute for other advanced surgical techniques (bony grafts, bone augmentation, distalization of the dental nerve), diminishing with it the morbidity, the rehabilitation periods and the cost for the patient? Is it required a specific prosthetic and clinical protocol to guarantee the success in the rehabilitation? In which cases of maxillary atrophy is this technique/treatment contraindicated in favour of other ones like zygomatic implants or bone grafts? Through an almost-systematic search in meta-search engine, agencies of evidence (systematic reviews) and bibliographical databases, we expose the evolution of the evidence on the matter, the most recent data published and the conclusions obtained (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martínez Lara, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marzo Alzota, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ferrer Gallego, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Azañón Hernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El propósito de este artículo es determinar la pertinencia del uso de implantes cortos, definiéndolos como "aquellos cuya longitud es &amp;#8804;8 mm" a través de la bibliografía existente. Hemos centrado la búsqueda en la comparación del uso de implantes de esta longitud, frente a otros tratamientos alternativos (injertos óseos, elevación de seno, transposición del nervio dentario, etc.) en pacientes con atrofia maxilar severa. Se dan respuesta a las siguientes cuestiones: ¿El uso de implantes dentales cortos es un tratamiento de resultados previsibles? ¿Los porcentajes de éxito a medio y largo plazo son equiparables a los de implantes con una longitud media estándar? ¿Pueden sustituir en determinadas situaciones clínicas a técnicas quirúrgicas avanzadas (injertos óseos, elevación de seno, distalización del nervio dentario) disminuyendo con ello la morbilidad, los tiempos en la rehabilitación y los costes para el paciente? ¿Se requiere de un protocolo clínico y prostético específico para garantizar el éxito en la rehabilitación? ¿En qué casos de atrofia maxilar se contraindica esta técnica a favor de otras como son los implantes cigomáticos o los injertos óseos? A través de una búsqueda cuasi-sistemática en metabuscadores, agencias de evidencias (revisiones sistemáticas) y bases de datos bibliográficos, exponemos la evolución de la evidencia al respecto, los últimos datos publicados y las conclusiones obtenidas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Av. periodoncia implantol. oral;25(3): 153-164, dic. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120686</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Pertinencia del uso de implantes dentales cortos en pacientes con atrofia ósea severa. Revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3773^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24600^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29076</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28854^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201312</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
