<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96063</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Twin pregnancy complicated with acardiac fetus. Case report and review of the literature</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Twin-twin transfusion syndrome is one of the many distinguishing features of monochorionic twin pregnancy. This complication is specific to this type of pregnancy and has a variable spectrum of clinical manifestations, ranging from mild discordance of amniotic fluid to the coexistence of an acardiac fetus with another normal fetus, and the hemodynamic consequences for the latter resulting from this complication. We report a case of twin-twin transfusion syndrome with acardiac fetus diagnosed in the first trimester of pregnancy and discuss the therapeutic approach and perinatal results. The pathophysiologic characteristics, prognostic factors and treatment options reported in the current literature are also discussed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo, M. I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ouviña, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cumbraos, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Rodríguez, M. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La gestación gemelar monocoriónica o univitelina presenta entre sus múltiples peculiaridades la posibilidad de desarrollar el síndrome de transfusión fetofetal, una complicación específica de la misma con un espectro de manifestaciones clínicas variable, que abarca desde una discordancia leve de líquido amniótico hasta la coexistencia de un feto acardio con otro normoformado, y las consecuencias hemodinámicas para este último derivadas de esta complicación. Presentamos un caso clínico en que se desarrolla esta complicación, diagnosticada en primer trimestre, su evolución, actitud terapéutica elegida y resultados perinatales obtenidos; así como un recuerdo fisiopatológico del mismo, factores pronósticos y opciones terapéuticas recogidas en la literatura médica actual (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);39(1): 38-41, ene.-feb. 2012.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96063</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Gestación gemelar complicada con feto acardio. Presentación de un caso y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6483^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14830</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11698</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4261^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5440^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5426</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29142</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
