<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95507</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Comparative study of two enteral feeding formulas in hospitalized elders: casein versus soybean protein</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To compare the incidence of gastrointestinal side effects of two enteral feeding formulas with changes in the origin of protein (casein and isolated soy protein) in hospitalised elderly patients. Method: A cross sectional survey was done among a sample of elderly patients carrying nasogastric tube admitted to the Reina Sofia General Hospital (Murcia) during a period of 6 months. A formula based on casein or soybean protein was randomly assigned. The variables studied were: age, sex, cause for indication of EN, duration of the EN and maximum amount of EN administered per day. Nutritional status at admission and discharge, mortality and gastrointestinal side effects (diarrhoea, constipation, vomits or regurgitation) were also collected. Statistical analyses were performed with the Student's T and chi 2 tests, with a significance of 95%. Results: Sample conformed by 50 patients over 65 years (48% casein, 52% soybean) without statistically significant differences in age nor cause of indication of the EN. Either there were no differences in the nutritional status at the admission and discharge in both groups. Significant differences were observed in the incidence of diarrhoea (C: 45.83%, S: 7.69%, p = 0,009) and vomits (C: 41.66%, S: 15.38%, p = 0,05). Conclusions: A significant reduction in the incidence of gastrointestinal complications, a reduction in the incidence of ulcers by pressure and less mortality occurred on the group that took formula based on the soybean protein. The individualized nutritional evaluation must be performed routinely when the patient is admitted to the hospital for detection and treatment of early signs of malnutrition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zomeño Ros, AI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Valverde, FM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sánchez, MB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nicolás Hernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Álvarez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Ramos, MJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Talavera Espín, NV</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Comparar la incidencia de complicaciones gastrointestinales de dos fórmulas de nutrición enteral (NE) con distinta fuente proteica (caseína y proteína aislada de soja) en ancianos hospitalizados. Métodos: Estudio transversal sobre pacientes portadores de SNG a los que se asignó aleatoriamente una fórmula basada en caseína o en proteína de soja. Las variables recogidas fueron: edad, sexo, motivo de indicación y duración de la NE, cantidad máxima diaria de NE administrada, situación nutricional al ingreso y al alta, mortalidad y complicaciones gastrointestinales. Se compararon ambos grupos mediante la Chi Cuadrado de Pearson y la T de Student, fijando en ambas el grado de significación en el 95%. Resultados: Muestra de 50 pacientes mayores de 65 años (48% caseína, 52% soja) sin diferencias estadísticamente significativas en edad ni indicación de la NE . Tampoco hubo diferencias en el estado nutricional al inicio o al alta en ambos grupos. El grupo que recibió una fórmula basada en soja presentó menor incidencia de diarrea (C: 45,83%, S: 7,69%, p = 0,009) y vómitos (C: 41,66%, S: 15,38%, p = 0,05), mayor porcentaje de mejora del estado nutricional y menos mortalidad con diferencias estadísticamente significativas. Conclusiones: En el grupo que tomó proteína de soja se produjeron menos complicaciones gastrointestinales y de úlceras por presión al tiempo que la situación nutricional mejoraba. Se puede afirmar que esta NE es bien tolerada por el paciente y aporta importantes beneficios clínicos. Por otro lado, la valoración nutricional debe realizarse como rutina al ingreso de los ancianos en el hospital para detectar y tratar precozmente cualquier signo de malnutrición (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;25(4): 606-612, jul.-ago. 2010. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio comparativo de dos dietas enterales en ancianos hospitalizados: proteína de soja frente a proteína caseína</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2408^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33047^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30324^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6916^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28940^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201008</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
