<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-59684</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Uveitis and idiopathic juvenile arthritis in Spain. Epidemiologicla and therapeutic aspects</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Purpose: The purpose of this paper is to describethe frequency and characteristics of uveitis associatedwith juvenile idiopathic arthritis at a tertiaryreferral centre in SpainMethods: Review of clinical records. 205 childrendiagnosed with chronic juvenile arthritis over thelast 15 years, of whom 26 presented anterior uveitis.Patients were classified according to their patternof evolution, the time the uveitis was diagnosedwith respect to the onset of arthritis, and the severityof uveitis at diagnosis.Results: The prevalence of uveitis was 12.7%. Ofthe patients affected with uveitis 71% were girls.The average age at which the arthritis was diagnosedwas significantly earlier in the group of patientswho developed uveitis (4.06 years). No differenceswere observed in the incidence of uveitis in girlsand boys, nor in pauci/polyarticular affectation.ANA positivity was found in 84.6% of the uveitisaffectedpatients, this being significantly differentto the ANA- group. The average age at which uveitiswas diagnosed is 5.87 years. 48.1% of uveitispatients develop uveitis within 12 months of theonset of arthritis. This group presented more complicationsduring the evolution of the condition. A total of 84.7% of the uveitis-affected patients presentedwith a final visual acuity of &gt;0.5 during theobservation period.Conclusions: In our study, the development of uveitiswas significantly associated with an earlier age ofdiagnosis of the arthritis and with the presence ofANA positivity. No differences were observed betweenboys and girls, or between pauci and polyarticulargroups. A greater prevalence of complications wasobserved in cases presenting with a shorter time intervalbetween the diagnosis of arthritis and uveitis andin those that presented with complications on diagnosis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Peralta, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Romero, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Consuegra, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abelairas, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sendagorta, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir la frecuencia y característicasde la uveítis asociada a la artritis idiopática juvenilen un centro de referencia terciario en España.Métodos: Se estudiaron 205 niños diagnosticadosde artritis idiopática juvenil en los últimos 15 años,de los cuales 26 desarrollaron uveítis anterior. Seclasificó a los pacientes según su patrón de evolución,el momento de diagnóstico de uveítis y la gravedadde la misma al diagnóstico.Resultados: La prevalencia de uveítis entre losniños con artritis idiopática juvenil fue de 12,7%,de las cuales el 71% eran niñas. La edad media deldiagnóstico de artritis fue significativamente menoren el grupo de pacientes que desarrollaron uveítis (4años).No se observaron diferencias en la incidencia deuveítis en niños/as ni en la afectación pauci/poliarticular.Se encontraron ANA+ en el 84,6% de lospacientes con uveítis, presentando diferencias significativascon el grupo ANA-.La edad media de diagnóstico de uveítis fue de 5,87años. El 48,1% de los pacientes desarrollaron lauveítis en los primeros doce meses del diagnósticode artritis. Este subgrupo de pacientes presentó máscomplicaciones en su evolución. El 84,7% del total de pacientes con uveítis seguidos en consulta presentaronuna agudeza visual media final &gt;0,5.Conclusiones: En nuestro estudio el desarrollo deuveítis se asocia de manera significativa con lamenor edad al diagnóstico de artritis y con la presenciade ANA+. Se observa una mayor prevalenciade complicaciones en los casos que presentan unmenor intervalo de tiempo entre el diagnóstico deartritis y uveítis, y en aquellos que presentaroncomplicaciones al diagnóstico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;84(3): 133-138, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-59684</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uveítis y artritis idiopática juvenil. Epidemiología, pronóstico y tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1177^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19035^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1177^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15007^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1177^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
