<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-104852</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dietary fibre and cardiovascular health</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the leading cause of mortality and morbidity in developed countries. CVD is an inflammatory disease associated with risk factors that include hypercholesterolemia and hypertension. Furthermore, the evolution of this disease depends on the amount of modified lipoproteins (e.g. oxidized) present in the arterial subendothelium. Diet is considered the cornerstone for CVD treatment, as it can lower not only atherogenic lipoprotein levels and degree of oxidation, but also blood pressure, thrombogenesis and concentrations of some relevant factors (e.g. homocystein).Among different diets, the Mediterranean diet stands out due to their benefits on several health benefits, in particular with regard to CVD. Rich in vegetable foods, this diet contributes both quantitatively and qualitatively to essential fibre compounds (cellulose, hemicellulose, gums, mucilages, pectins, oligosaccharides, lignins, etc.). The present paper analyzes the effects of fibre consumption on a) cholesterol and lipoprotein levels; b) systolic and diastolic blood pressures; and c) antioxidant availability and profile. Some studies and meta-analysis are revised, as the possible mechanisms by which fibre may decrease plasma total cholesterol and LDL-cholesterol and blood pressure and to act as antioxidant, as well. In addition, author&#146;s own publications regarding the effect of fibre matrix (e.g. seaweeds) on aryl esterase and the gene expression of some key antioxidant enzymes are reviewed. The paper also includes data concerning the possible interaction between fibre and some hypolipemic drugs, which may make it possible to attain similar hypolipemic effects with lower dosages, with the consequent decrease in possible side effects. The review concludes with a summary of nutritional objectives related to the consumption of carbohydrates and fibre supplements (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Muniz, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enfermedad cardiovascular (EC) sigue siendo la causa más frecuente de morbi-mortalidad en los países desarrollados. Es considerada una enfermedad inflamatoria asociada a la presencia de algunos factores de riesgo como hipercolesterolemia e hipertensión. El desarrollo de la EC depende de la cantidad de lipoproteínas modificadas (p.e. oxidadas) presente a nivel del espacio subendotelial arterial. La dieta se considera piedra angular en el tratamiento de la EC, ya que no sólo puede reducir el nivel y la oxidación de las lipoproteínas aterogénicas, la presión arterial sino el impacto de algunos factores relevantes (p.e. trombogénesis, homocisteína). Resalta entre muchas dietas la tipo mediterráneo debido a sus beneficios contrastados en múltiples aspectos de salud. La dieta mediterránea contiene una amplia variedad de vegetales que aportan la mayoría de los componentes (celulosa, hemicelulosa, gomas, mucílagos, pectinas, oligosacáridos, ligninas, etc) que integran el concepto de fibra tanto cuantitativa como cualitativamente. De algunos de ellos hay clara evidencia científica de sus beneficios bajo el punto de vista de la EC. La revisión se ha estructurado en los siguientes puntos que analizan los efectos de la fibra dietética sobre a) el contenido plasmático de colesterol y lipoproteínas; b) la presión arterial sistólica y diastólica y c) la capacidad y perfil antioxidante. Se revisan algunos estudios y meta-análisis, se proponen posibles mecanismos por los que la fibra dietética disminuye los niveles de colesterol total, LDL-colesterol y presión arterial y actúa como antioxidante. Además se revisan algunas publicaciones propias sobre los efectos de una matriz fibrosa (algas) sobre la actividad de la arilesterasa y la expresión génica de enzimas antioxidantes clave. El artículo también revisa la posible interacción de la fibra con fármacos hipolipemiantes. Esta interacción permitiría reducir la dosis del fármaco y los posibles efectos secundarios. La revisión termina con algunos objetivos nutricionales relacionados con el consumo de alimentos ricos en hidratos de carbono y fibra dietética (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;27(1): 31-45, ene.-feb. 2012. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-104852</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fibra dietética y salud cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23102^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d931^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32247</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23100^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8248^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201202</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
