<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-051873</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Petrous bone fracture. Our experience: 1999-2004</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To review the petrous bone fractures    during the last five years (1999-2004) in our hospital, its    manage, control, and analysis onf the associated factors.    To analyse the managing protocoles and current bibliography.    Material and methods: We review 266 temporal bone    fractures, 74 with petrous bone association. We analyse    these fractures by sex distribution, injurie severity, otorhinolaryngological    clinical findings, production mechanism    and radiological findings. The cases are discussed and    compared with current bibliography. Conclussions: Petrous    bone fractures must be always suspected in patients with    head trauma, specially if it associates severity and otorrhagia.    It is necessary a deep colaboration between neurosurgeons, radiologists and otorhinolaryngologists to obtain    a good management, control and follow up of the patients</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Callejo, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cortés Andrés, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quilis Quesada, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramírez Sabio, JB</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Paula Vernetta, C de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchís García, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marco Algarra, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dualde Beltrán, D</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Realizar una revisión de las fracturas de    peñasco ocurridas en los últimos 5 años (1999-2004) en    nuestro hospital, su manejo, control y análisis de los factores    implicados. Analizar los protocolos de actuación y la bibliografía    actual. Material y métodos: Se revisan 266 fracturas    de hueso temporal, 74 con implicación del peñasco. Se analizan    estas fracturas en función de la distribución por sexo,    gravedad del traumatismo, clínica otorrinolaringológica debut,    mecanismo traumático de producción, y hallazgos radiológicos.    Se discuten minuciosamente los resultados y se    comparan con la bibliografía actual. Concluciones: Las fracturas    de peñasco se han de sospechar siempre en los pacientes    con antecedente de traumatismo craneoencefálico    (TCE) especialmente en los de gravedad moderada a grave    y sobre todo si hay otorragia. Es necesaria una estrecha colaboración    entre los servicios de neurocirugía, radiología y    ORL para un adecuado manejo, valoración y seguimiento    de los pacientes</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;57(10): 450-454, dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-051873</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Fracturas de peñasco. Nuestra experiencia: 1999-2004</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50518^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10769^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28583</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
