<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166843</identifier>
<setSpec>2254-2884</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Analysis of puncture of coated intravascular prostheses after salvage of arteriovenous fistula, after 12 months of experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: To evaluate the medium-term efficacy of a new intravascular prosthesis (VIABAHN(R)), and its safety, by analyzing the incidence of adverse events associated with its puncture. Patients and method: Twenty patients, with VIABAHN(R) implanted, were studied for pseudoaneurysms with thrombosis, ulcers in the puncture sites, failure of angioplasty or restenosis in less than 6 months. Parameters of AVF, primary and secondary patency (6 and 12 months), presence of complications and control of prosthesis deterioration by phlebography at 3 and 6 months were studied. For the puncture, a period of 4 weeks was expected. Results: A period of 15 ± 9.4 months was analyzed. The mean of the functional parameters of the AVF during hemodialysis was: blood flow rate: 362.5 ± 43.3 ml / min, Arterial Pressure: -209.5 ± 35.6 mmHg, Venous Pressure: 215.8 ± 34.5 mmHg, Kt 55 ± 5.4 l and recirculation 12.7 ± 3.7%. At 6 months, 66% (95% CI: 54-77) of the patients had primary permeability and 77% (95% CI 67-87) had secondary permeability. At 12 months 38% (IC 95% 24-52) primary permeability and 76% (IC 95% 66-87) secondary permeability. No adverse events related to the puncture, nor radiologically objectified deterioration in prostheses were observed. There was an episode of infection requiring removal of the prosthesis. Conclusión: The VIABAHN(R) coated vascular prosthesis is effective and safe in the rescue of stented and / or thrombosed native AVFs, as it provides excellent dialysis parameters and high primary and secondary permeability, without repeated puncture associated with complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gómez López, Victoria Eugenia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casas Cuesta, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calle Mafla, Óscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Crespo Montero, Rodolfo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Macías, Carolina</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Evaluar la eficacia a medio plazo de una nueva prótesis intravascular (VIABAHN(R)), y su seguridad, analizando la incidencia de eventos adversos asociados a su punción. Pacientes y Método: Se estudiaron 20 pacientes, a los que se les implantó VIABAHN(R), por pseudoaneurismas con trombosis, úlceras en las zonas de punción, fracaso de angioplastia o reestenosis en menos de 6 meses. Se estudió: Parámetros de la FAV, permeabilidad primaria y secundaria (6 y 12 meses), presencia de complicaciones y control del deterioro de la prótesis mediante flebografía a los 3 y 6 meses. Para la punción se esperó un periodo de 4 semanas. Resultados: Se analizó un periodo de 15±9.4 meses. La media de los parámetros funcionales de la FAV durante la hemodiálisis fue: Fs: 362.5±43.3 ml/min, PA: -209.5±35.6 mmHg, PV: 215.8±34.5 mmHg, Kt 55±5.4 l y Recirculación 12.7±3.7%. A los 6 meses el 66% (IC 95% 54-77) de los pacientes tenía permeabilidad primaria y el 77% (IC 95% 67-87) tenía permeabilidad secundaria. A los 12 meses el 38% (IC 95% 24-52) permeabilidad primaria y el 76% (IC 95% 66-87) permeabilidad secundaria. No se observaron eventos adversos relacionados con la punción, ni se objetivó radiológicamente deterioro en las prótesis. Hubo un episodio de infección que requirió la retirada de la prótesis. Conclusiones: La prótesis vascular recubierta VIABAHN(R) es eficaz y segura en el rescate de las FAVs nativas estenosadas y/o trombosadas, ya que proporciona excelentes parámetros de diálisis y alta permeabilidad primaria y secundaria, sin que su punción repetida se asocie a complicaciones (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. nefrol;20(3): 247-251, jul.-sept. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166843</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Análisis de la punción de prótesis intravasculares recubiertas tras el rescate de la fístula arteriovenosa después de 12 meses de experiencia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24885^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55420^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1732^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29321^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24519^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6234^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201709</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
