<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-129254</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Predictive value of optical coherence tomography on the outcome of lung adenocarcinoma with choroidal metastases</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical case: A 59 year-old male, with the diagnosis of lung adenocarcinoma stage IV , following palliative systemic chemotherapy treatment. He was referred to our department due to bilateral blurred vision. In the eye-fundus we observed: bilateral choroidal metastases with macular involvement, and in optical coherence tomography (OCT): neurosensory detachment in both eyes. This neurosensory detachment showed improvement with chemotherapy before the clinical and radiologic improvement. Discussion: OCT could be a great tool in order to predict the response to systemic treatment in cases of lung adenocarcinoma associated with choroidal metastases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Fernández, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Burgueño-Montañés, C</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Varón, 59 años, con adenocarcinoma pulmonar estadio IV , en tratamiento paliativo con quimioterapia sistémica. Acude a nuestro servicio por visión borrosa bilateral. En el fondo de ojo se observan metástasis coroideas bilaterales con compromiso macular, y en tomografía de coherencia óptica (OCT) desprendimiento neurosensorial en ambos ojos. Este se reduce drásticamente con el tratamiento quimioterápico, anticipándose a la mejoría clínica y radiológica del paciente. Discusión: La OCT puede ser una buena herramienta para vaticinar la respuesta al tratamiento sistémico en casos de adenocarcinoma pulmonar asociado a metástasis coroideas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;89(1): 38-41, ene. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-129254</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor predictivo de la tomografía de coherencia óptica en la evolución del adenocarcinoma pulmonar con metástasis coroideas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d8352^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28269^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d238^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9555^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201401</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
