<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86353</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Usefulness of platelet-rich plasma as a scaffold for stromal cells in regenerative therapies of the Nervous System</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To analyze survival and neural differentiation of human stromal stem cells supported in biological matrices of fibrin and blood plasma. Methods: In vitro studies have been conducted using fibrin, platelet-poor plasma and platelet-rich plasma, as scaffolds of human stromal stem cells obtained from bone marrow. Results: at seven days of culture, human stromal cells showed poor survival on fibrin scaffolds, while the survival is virtually 100% using plasma scaffolds. As for the phenotypic differentiation into neurons or astrocytic cells, differentiation is absent on fibrin scaffolds. However, on scaffolds of platelet-poor plasma, 35.4% of cells express markers of neuronal differentiation and 20.8% expressed astrocytic differentiation markers. The percentage of stromal cells expressing neuronal and astrocytic markers increases, with statistically significant difference (p &lt;0.05), to 41.6% and 26.7% respectively, when the scaffold is platelet-rich plasma. Conclusion: The platelet-rich plasma is an excellent biological scaffold for bone marrow stromal cells in cell therapy strategies on the Nervous System (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Zurita, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguayo, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vaquero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la supervivencia y diferenciación neural de células madre estromales (CME) humanas, soportadas en matrices biológicas de fibrina y de plasma sanguíneo. Métodos: Se realizaron estudios in vitro utilizando matrices de fibrina, de plasma pobre en plaquetas (PPP) y de plasma rico en plaquetas (PRP), como soporte de células estromales humanas obtenidas de médula ósea. Resultados: A los siete días de cultivo, las células estromales humanas mostraron escasa supervivencia sobre matrices de fibrina, mientras que la supervivencia y capacidad proliferativa fue del 100% sobre matrices de plasma. En cuanto a la diferenciación fenotípica hacia células nerviosas, la diferenciación fue nula sobre matrices de fibrina. Sin embargo, sobre matrices de PPP, el 35,4% de las células expresaron marcadores de diferenciación neuronal y el 20,8% expresaron marcadores de diferenciación astrocítica. El porcentaje de CME que expresaron marcadores neuronales y astrocíticos se incrementaron (p&lt;0,05), al 41,6% y 26,7% respectivamente, cuando la matriz de soporte es PRP. Conclusión: El PRP se comporta como una matriz adecuada de soporte biológico para células estromales de médula ósea, con posible utilidad en estrategias de terapia celular aplicadas al Sistema Nervioso (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);22(1): 38-46, ene.-mar. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86353</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilidad del plasma rico en plaquetas como soporte de células estromales en terapias regenerativas del Sistema Nervioso</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30496^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52020^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22921^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7435</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9613^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5567^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30827^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19524^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23315^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23315^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32747^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32747^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22316^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201103</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
