<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-68116</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6640</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Neonatal hypotonia constitutes a diagnostic challenge due to the wide variety of etiologies and the broad array of supplementary tests necessary to arrive at the correct diagnosis. Clinically, we can differentiate between paralyzing and non paralyzinghypotonia. Congenital myopathies, including nemaline myopathy, belong to the latter group. Nemaline myopathy is a non progressive congenital disorder of skeletal muscle, characterized by the presence of rod-like structures, or nemaline bodies, in muscle fibers. We report the case of a premature infant who was assessed on the suspicion of neuromuscular disease. The results of the initial diagnostic studies were normal, but muscle biopsy eventually revealed the rod-like structures characteristic of nemaline myopathy. The clinical course was unsatisfactory and, after undergoing tracheotomy at the age of three months, at the time of writing, he was ten months old and required home continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) ventilation. The diagnosis of nemaline myopathy requires a high index of suspicion and the performance of a muscle biopsy. At the present time, genetic counseling cannot be provided in sporadic cases (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Gilino, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez Andrés, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Caballero Balanzá, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguar Carrascosa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipotonía neonatal constituye un reto diagnóstico, debido a la gran variedad de etiologías y de exploraciones complementarias necesarias para llegar a su diagnóstico. Clínicamente, se pueden agrupar en hipotonías paralíticas y no paralíticas; entre estas últimas encontramos el grupo de las miopatías congénitas, al que pertenece la miopatía nemalínica (MN).La MN es una enfermedad congénita no progresiva de la musculatura esquelética caracterizada por la presencia de bastoncillos o cuerpos nemalínicos en las fibras musculares. Presentamos el caso clínico de un recién nacido prematuro con sospecha de enfermedad neuromuscular, en el que se iniciaron estudios para un diagnóstico etiológico, que fueron normales. La biopsia muscular mostró los cuerpos nemalínicos característicos de la MN. La evolución clínica no fue satisfactoria; se realizó una traqueotomía a los 3 meses de vida y en la actualidad, a los 11 meses de vida, precisa ventilación domiciliaria con presión positiva continua en la vía respiratoria. El diagnóstico de MN requiere un alto índice de sospecha y la biopsia muscular como confirmación. En la actualidad no puede ofrecerse consejo genético en los casos esporádicos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Pediatr Esp;66(6): 292-296, jun. 2008. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-68116</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d1183^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31278^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9414^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31278^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9313^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9328^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200806</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
