<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-160573</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-8799</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Circulating microRNA as regulators of the molecular response in exercise in healthy people</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Circulating microRNAs (c-miRNAs) are cell-to-cell communicators implicated in the regulation of molecular responses with strong potential in exercise and practical implications in health. Despite this fact, the number of papers published on this topic is scarce and with inconsistent results. Thus, the aim of this review was to summarize the information available, to analyze the heterogeneity of the results and to identify which are the future perspectives in this field of research. The results of the studies included in this revision clearly show that acute exercise and training induce a response in c-miRNA profile. This response depends on the model, intensity and dose of exercise. However, there are some questions which must be answered: what are the secretory organs or tissues, the mechanisms of transport, and the tissue and gene targets. A number of differences between studies in the methodologies used (detection technique, number of c-miRNAs analyzed, normalization strategy), in the experimental design (sampling points) and in the characteristics of the participants (aging, exercise background, dietary intake) makes it difficult to establish direct comparisons and to draw firm conclusions. Finally, this role of exercise as c-miRNA profile modulator, could be considered a valuable alternative to upcoming pharmacological and nutritional interventions based on miRNAs. Moreover, the validation of c-miRNAs as biomarkers of exercise will allow the development of more specific recommendations, using training as a therapeutic and preventive tool, and exploring the maximal limits for a safe and healthy exercise (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzalo Calvo, David de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Iglesias Gutiérrez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Sanjurjo, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dávalos, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díez Robles, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los microRNAs circulantes (c-miRNAs) son reguladores de la expresión génica y mediadores de la comunicación intercelular, con un gran potencial como coordinadores de la respuesta molecular al ejercicio y, por tanto, con eventuales implicaciones prácticas para la salud y el rendimiento. Sin embargo, su respuesta al ejercicio agudo y al entrenamiento en personas sanas es poco conocida, principalmente porque hasta el momento se ha publicado un número reducido de artículos, con resultados dispares. El objetivo de esta revisión es agrupar y sintetizar el conocimiento disponible, analizar las causas de esta heterogeneidad en los resultados e identificar las principales perspectivas de futuro en esta área. Los resultados de los trabajos incluidos en esta revisión muestran que el ejercicio agudo y el entrenamiento inducen una respuesta en el perfil de c-miRNAs influida por el modelo, duración, intensidad y dosis de ejercicio. Queda pendiente, no obstante, conocer su origen, forma de transporte, destino, así como validar sus dianas génicas. Sin embargo, estos estudios muestran entre sí numerosas diferencias metodológicas (técnica de detección, número y tipo de c-miRNAs analizados, estrategia de normalización), en el diseño experimental (puntos de muestreo) y en las características de los sujetos (edad, historial de entrenamiento), que hace difícil, tanto establecer comparaciones directas entre ellos, como extraer conclusiones generales sólidas. Finalmente, este papel del ejercicio, como modulador del perfil de c-miRNAs, podría constituir una alternativa viable y coadyuvante a las terapias farmacológicas y dietéticas basadas en miRNAs que actualmente se encuentran en desarrollo. Además, su validación como biomarcadores de ejercicio podría contribuir al desarrollo de recomendaciones de ejercicio más precisas, a optimizar su aplicación como herramienta preventiva o terapéutica y a explorar los límites máximos del ejercicio saludable (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch. med. deporte;33(176): 394-403, nov.-dic. 2016. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-160573</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">MicroRNA circulantes como reguladores de la respuesta molecular al ejercicio en personas sanas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37535^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1848</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
