<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115674</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-5962</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The push and pull factors related to early retirees&#146; mental health status: a comparative study between Italy and Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In recent years, early retirement has attracted increasing attention in the literature. Using a larger Italian- Spanish sample, this study examines the push and pull factors related to early retirees&#146; mental health status, as well as the moderating effects of perceived self-efficacy on the relationships between reasons for early retirement and mental health. Analyses revealed that poor retirees&#146; mental health is positively correlated to the push factor Pressure from Employer and negatively related to the pull factor Pursue Own Interests. Thus, mental health status is better for Italian retirees than for their Spanish counterparts. The Italian sample shows that Pursue Own Interests was negatively related to poorer mental health particularly under the low self-efficacy condition. Findings suggest that mental health depends on both the motivating reasons that lead people to retire early and the personal resources available to them to manage this psychosocial transition (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alcover, Carlos María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Simbula, Silvia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Negrini, Alessia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Panari, Chiara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El interés por el estudio de la jubilación anticipada se ha incrementado en los últimos años. Utilizando una muestra ítalo-española este estudio examina los factores que empujan y atraen a la jubilación anticipada y sus relaciones con la salud mental, así como los efectos moderadores de la auto-eficacia en dichas relaciones. Los resultados muestran una relación positiva entre los peores niveles de salud mental y el factor de empuje Presión del Empleador y una relación negativa con el factor de atracción Perseguir Intereses Propios. Así, el estado de salud mental es mejor para los jubilados italianos que para sus homólogos españoles. En la muestra italiana Perseguir Intereses Propios se relaciona negativamente con los peores niveles de salud mental en la condición de baja auto-eficacia. Los resultados sugieren que la salud mental depende de las razones que motivan hacia la jubilación anticipada y los recursos personales para afrontar esta transición psicosocial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psicol. trab. organ. (1999);29(2): 51-58, mayo-ago. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115674</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los factores que empujan y atraen a la jubilación anticipada y sus relaciones con la salud mental: un estudio comparativo entre Italia y España</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12594^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10608^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10608^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12594^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28451^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8775^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
