<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-15719</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacious psychological treatments for agoraphobia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In vivo exposure and cognitive-behavioral therapy have demonstrated their efficacy for agoraphobic anxiety and avoidance; however, the effects of cognitive-behavioral therapy might be smaller if time given to in vivo exposure is reduced. Cognitive-behavioral therapy is also a probably efficacious treatment for other aspects of agoraphobia (frequency of panic, worry about panic, interference) and associated problems (general anxiety, depressed mood). Furthermore, cognitive-behavioral therapy is effective and efficient, and, in comparison with in vivo exposure, is associated with fewer dropouts of treatment and fewer relapses in panic attacks. Nonetheless, their short-term and mid-term effects in frequency of panic attacks, worry about panic, interference, general anxiety and depressed mood have not been established in a consistent way in comparison with placebo or other treatments; moreover, measures as fear of fear or anxiety sensitivity have not been considered in that respect. Finally, results about predictors of treatment outcome have been generally inconsistent (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bados López, Arturo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La exposición en vivo (EV) y la terapia cognitivo-conductual (TCC) son tratamientos bien establecidos para la ansiedad y evitación agoragofóbicas, aunque los efectos de la segunda pueden ser menores si se reduce el tiempo dedicado a la EV. La TCC es un tratamiento probablemente eficaz para otros aspectos de la agorafobia (frecuencia de pánico, preocupación por el pánico, interferencia) y para problemas asociados (ansiedad general, humor deprimido). Además, la TCC es una terapia efectiva y eficiente que tiende a producir menos abandonos del tratamiento y menos recaídas en ataques de pánico que la EV. Sin embargo, sus efectos sobre frecuencia de ataques, preocupación por el pánico, interferencia, ansiedad general y humor deprimido no han sido consistentemente establecidos a corto y medio plazo en comparación al placebo u otros tratamientos. Medidas como el miedo al miedo o susceptibilidad a la ansiedad no han sido ni tan siquiera consideradas en estas comparaciones. Finalmente, los resultados sobre las variables predictoras de los efectos del tratamiento han tendido a ser generalmente inconsistentes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);13(3): 453-464, ago. 2001. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-15719</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamientos psicológicos eficace para la agorafobia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d383^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d383^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29912^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
