<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-132520</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Metabolic emergencies in the oncology patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Amongst the principal metabolic situations that can require emergency attention in the oncology patient we find: hypercalcaemia, hyponatraemia, tumoural lysis syndrome, lactic acidosis, hyperuricaemia, renal failure, hyperammonaemia, hypermpotasaemia, etc. Hypercalcaemia is the most frequent metabolic complication in oncology, appearing in 10-30% of these patients. It has two main mechanisms, tumoural lysis and humoural hypercalcaemia mediated by PTHrP (a protein related to parathormone). The principal factor for its diagnosis is suspicion, since some symptoms are non-specific and can be attributed to other causes such as somnolence, constipation, etc. Treatment will be based on intensity and is started with calciuretic measures with an intense hydration with physiological serum and on some occasions with furosemide. Anti-reabsorptive measures include calcitonin, bisphosphonates, mithramycin, gallium nitrate and on occasions corticoids. Bisphosphonates such as pamidronate and zoledronate seem to be highly useful in these cases. Hyponatraemia is classified depending on plasmatic osmorality; when this is low we find ourselves facing an authentic hyponatraemia that can develop with an extra-cellular volume that is high (cardiac insufficiency, cirrhosis, nephrotic syndrome and renal insufficiency), low (renal and extra-renal sodium losses) and normal (principally SIADH, related to a high elimination of sodium in the urine with high urinary osmolarity in spite of this being low in blood). Several types of tumour and different chemotherapy drugs can produce this SIADH. Treatment will vary according to the type and intensity, but in general this is based on hydric restriction and the replacement of the sodium deficit, either through physiological serum or through hypertonic saline serums depending on the case, and on occasions furosemide for the elimination of excess water (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Elejalde, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Entre las principales situaciones metabólicas que pueden precisar atención urgente en el paciente oncológico se encuentran: hipercalcemia, hiponatremia, síndrome de lisis tumoral, acidosis láctica, hiperuricemia, insuficiencia renal, hiperamonemia, hiperpotasemia, etc.  La hipercalcemia es la complicación metabólica más frecuente en oncología apareciendo en el 10-30% de estos pacientes. Sus principales mecanismos son dos, la lisis tumoral y la hipercalcemia humoral mediada por la PTHrP (proteína relacionada con la parathormona). Para su diagnóstico lo principal es su sospecha ya que algunos síntomas son inespecíficos y atribuibles a otras causas como somnolencia, estreñimiento, etc. El tratamiento estará basado en la intensidad y se inicia con medidas calciuréticas con una intensa hidratación con suero fisiológico y en algunas ocasiones furosemida. Las medidas antirreabsortivas incluyen la calcitonina, bifosfonatos, mitramicina, nitrato de galio y en ocasiones corticoides. Bifosfonatos como el pamidronato y el zolendronato parecen ser muy útiles en estos casos. La hiponatremia se clasifica en función de la osmolaridad plasmática; cuando ésta es baja nos encontramos ante la verdadera hiponatremia que puede cursar con volumen extracelular elevado (insuficiencia cardíaca, cirrosis, síndrome nefrótico e insuficiencia renal), disminuido (pérdidas renales y extrarrenales de sodio) y normal (SIADH principalmente, relacionado con una eliminación alta de sodio en orina con alta osmolaridad urinaria a pesar de ser ésta baja en sangre). Varios tipos de tumor y diversos fármacos quimioterápicos pueden producir este SIADH. El tratamiento variará según el tipo y la intensidad pero, en general, éste se basa en una restricción hídrica y la reposición del sodio deficitario bien a través de suero fisiológico o de sueros salinos hipertónicos según el caso y en ocasiones furosemida para la eliminación del exceso de agua (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;27(supl.3): 53-62, 2004. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-132520</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Urgencias metabólicas en el paciente oncológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10171</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7189^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7189^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7114^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7114^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4705</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
