<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147645</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-6202</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Hyperglycemia associated to ziprasidone. Clinical case</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Schizophrenia is a chronic disease that constitute one of de most incapacitate psichiatrics disorders. Using second-generation antipsychotic drugs, we can hope minimal extrapyramidal effects and a effective action for negative symptoms. We related the pharmacotherapeutic follow-up (PF) of a clinical case of hiperglycemia as an adverse effect of ziprasidone that cause diabetes. Objectives: Identify the negative clinical outcomes of the psichiatric-patient treatment with the PF method and contribute with the medicine doctor to resolve them characterizing the patient and valuing the efficacy and security of the treatment. Methods: We use Dáder method for PF. Results: The PF related hyperglycemia as an adverse event of ziprasidone administration. It made possible the dosage adjust to an ineffective dosage of metformin and the diabetes control. The informative pharmaceutical intervention provokes the neuroleptical drug removed, changing the diagnostic and the treatment as consecuence. Conclusions: PF of the patients treated with atypical antipsychotic drugs can help to evidence an associate the adverse events of this drugs. It is necessarily the pharmaceutical-control of glucose-levels and weight of the these patients to try to decrease the morbi-mortality associated to these drugs usage. Moreover, it would be necessarily the elaboration of management-guides for these patient-pattern at community pharmacy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Chamorro, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gosálvez Mariño, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Chamorro, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La esquizofrenia es una enfermedad crónica que constituye uno de los trastornos mentales más incapacitantes. Los antipsicóticos de segunda generación provocan unos efectos extrapiramidales mínimos y una acción sobre los síntomas negativos. Se refiere el seguimiento farmacoterapéutico (SFT) de un caso clínico de una hiperglucemia como efecto adverso de ziprasidona que desencadena una diabetes. Objetivos: Identificar los resultados clínicos negativos de la farmacoterapia de un paciente psiquiátrico mediante el SFT y colaborar con el médico en su resolución, mediante la caracterización del paciente y la valoración de la efectividad y la seguridad de la terapia. Metodología: Se ha utilizado el método Dáder de SFT. Resultados: El SFT se asocia con una reacción adversa de hiperglucemia a ziprasidona. La intervención farmacéutica promueve el ajuste de una dosis inefectiva de metformina para lograr el control de la diabetes. Otra intervención farmacéutica informativa ocasiona una retirada del neuroléptico, se produce un cambio de diagnóstico y una modificación del tratamiento. Conclusiones: El SFT de los pacientes tratados con antipsicóticos atípicos puede ayudar a poner de manifiesto los efectos adversos de estos fármacos. Es necesario, por parte del farmacéutico, establecer un control de los niveles de glucemia y del peso de los pacientes tratados con antipsicóticos atípicos, para intentar disminuir la morbimortalidad asociada al uso de estos medicamentos. Además, se necesitan guías de manejo de este tipo de pacientes en farmacia asistencial (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pharm. care Esp;9(2): 57-64, jun. 2007. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147645</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Hiperglucemia asociada a ziprasidona. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52955^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7124^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12940^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54217^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
