<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164123</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Association between meal intake behavior and blood pressure in Spanish adults</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives: Eating frequency has been suggested to modify blood pressure. Yet, the results are inconclusive, possibly because eating frequency, particularly meal intake behavior (MIB), does not differentiate between meals and snacks. Hence, the aim of this study was to examine the association between more specific MIBs, like the consumption of the three main meals, the intake of forenoon and afternoon meals and snacking between the regular meals, and systolic/diastolic blood pressure (SBP/DBP). Methods: This cross-sectional study includes 1,314 Spanish adults aged 20-79 years. Data collection occurred during cardiovascular health day events organized in four Spanish cities (Madrid, Las Palmas, Seville and Valencia) in 2008. Linear regression analysis was performed to assess the independent association between the mentioned MIBs and SBP/DBP, controlling for several confounders in multiples models. Results: After adjusting for sex, age and individual risk factors, having an afternoon meal was associated with lower SBP (ß -3.91, 95% CI [-6.33, -1.49]) and DBP (ß -2.35, 95% CI [-3.76, -0.94]). This association was attenuated when introducing dietary intake and waist circumference in the predictive models (SBP: ß -2.83, 95% CI [-5.25, -0.40]; DBP: ß -1.67, 95% CI [-3.04, -0.31]), although it still remained significant. None of the other investigated MIBs showed any associations with SBP/DBP. Conclusions: This study suggests that SBP/DBP might be reduced by the intake of an afternoon meal. However, population-based prospective studies are needed in order to confirm the consequences of the investigated associations on health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carmenate-Moreno, María Margarita</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-López, Santiago</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Keller, Kristin</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: evidencias sugieren que el número de ingestas alimentarias modifican la presión arterial. Sin embargo, los resultados encontrados no son concluyentes, probablemente debido a que esta conducta relacionada con la ingesta de alimentos (CRIA) no diferencia entre comidas y snacks. Este estudio examina la asociación entre CRIA más específicas como la realización de las tres comidas principales, de la media mañana, de la merienda y picar entre las comidas regulares, y la tensión arterial sistólica y diastólica (TAS y TAD). Métodos: es un estudio transversal, en el cual fueron incluidos 1.314 españoles (20-79 años). Los datos fueron recogidos en las Jornadas de Salud Cardiovascular en Madrid, Las Palmas, Sevilla y Valencia, durante el año 2008. Se aplicaron análisis de regresión lineal, controlando el efecto de diversos factores de confusión en múltiples modelos. Resultados: después de ajustar por sexo, edad y factores de riesgo individual, tomar la merienda se asoció directamente a menor TAS (ß -3,91, 95% CI [-6,33, -1,49]) y TAD (ß -2,35, 95% CI [-3,76, -0,94]). La introducción del consumo alimentario y la circunferencia de cintura en los modelos predictivos atenuó esta asociación (TAS: ß -2,83, 95% CI [-5,25, -0,40]; TAD: ß -1,67, 95% CI [-3,04, -0,31]). Ninguna de las otras CRIA investigadas mostró asociaciones con TAS y TAD. Conclusiones: el estudio sugiere que tanto la TAS como la TAD podrían verse reducidas mediante la ingesta de la merienda, aunque se requieren estudios adicionales para confirmar y profundizar en las consecuencias sobre la salud de las asociaciones investigadas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;34(3): 654-660, mayo-jun. 2017. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164123</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asociación entre conductas relacionadas con la ingesta de alimentos y tensión arterial en adultos españoles</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1821^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5350^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4499^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24769</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50314</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
