<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-047783</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-6266</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">COPD: influence of a home exercise programme on dyspnoea</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Respiratory rehabilitation (RR) is a beneficialtherapy for those patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease(COPD). However, the application of the majority of the programmesdesigned demands a high consumption of resources andfew have demonstrated their efficacy in the long term.Objective: To compare the long-term effectiveness of a programof minimally supervised home RR in relation to the changesin dyspnoea and functional capacity in patients with ChronicObstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD).Method: Prospective randomized clinical trial of 1 year duration,with 2 groups: rehabilitation and control. The results of thepatients who have completed an inclusion period of 6 months areshown. Two pre-training and post-training variables were measured:dyspnoea by means of Mahler&#146;s basal dyspnoea index(MBDI) and transitional dyspnoea index (TDI), and the exercisecapacity by means of the 6 minutes walk test (6MWT).Patients: Individuals with moderate and serious COPD whocame to a pneumology consultation and who fulfilled the establishedcriteria of inclusion in a programme of RR.Intervention: The RR group was instructed in a home exerciseprogram with training of the upper and lower limbs.Results: Nineteen patients were evaluated (age 65 ± 6 yearsand average FEV1 of 39%), which were randomly assigned to eachstudy group: RR group (n = 11) and control group (n = 8). TheMBDI was 4.6 in the RR group and 4.75 in the control group. At 6months the TDI was 3.5 in the RR group and 0.63 in the controlgroup, with differences in all the subscales. The distance covered inthe 6MWT increased in both groups, although with a difference of46 metres in favour of the of RR group.Conclusions: A program of minimally supervised home RRobtains a significant improvement in the dyspnoea and capacityfor effort in the patients with COPD</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rubio Sánchez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jurado Gámez, B</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Cabrera, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mayordomo Riera, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">INTRODUCCIÓN: La rehabilitación respiratoria (RR) es unaterapia beneficiosa para los enfermos con enfermedad pulmonarobstructiva crónica (EPOC). Sin embargo, la aplicación de lamayoría de los programas diseñados exige un elevado consumo derecursos y pocos han demostrado su eficacia a largo plazo.OBJETIVO: Comparar en pacientes con Enfermedad PulmonarObstructiva Crónica (EPOC) la efectividad a largo plazo de unprograma de RR domiciliaria mínimamente supervisado en relacióna los cambios en la disnea y capacidad funcional.DISEÑO: Ensayo clínico prospectivo, aleatorizado, de 1 añode duración, con 2 grupos: rehabilitación y control. Se presentanlos resultados de los pacientes que han completado un periodo deinclusión de 6 meses. Se midieron pre-entrenamiento y post-entrenamientodos variables: la disnea mediante el índice de disneabasal de Mahler (IDBM) e índice transicional de disnea (ITD), y lacapacidad de ejercicio mediante la prueba de 6 minutos marcha(P6MM).PACIENTES: Individuos con EPOC moderada y grave queacuden a una consulta de Neumología y que cumplen unos criteriosestablecidos de inclusión en un programa de RR.INTERVENCIÓN: Al grupo de RR se le instruyó en un programade ejercicio domiciliario con entrenamiento de extremidadessuperiores e inferiores.RESULTADOS: Se evaluaron 19 sujetos (edad 65 ± 6 años yporcentaje de FEV1 medio de 39%), que se asignaron aleatoriamentea cada grupo de estudio: Grupo RR (n = 11) y grupo control(n = 8). El IDBM fue de 4,6 en el grupo RR y 4,75 en el grupo control.A los 6 meses el ITD fue 3,5 en el grupo RR y 0,63 en el control,con diferencias en todas las subescalas. La distancia recorridaen el 6MWT se incrementó en ambos grupos, aunque con una diferenciade 46 metros a favor del grupo de RR.CONCLUSIONES: Un programa de RR domiciliario y mínimamentesupervisado consigue una mejoría significativa en la disneay en la capacidad de esfuerzo en los pacientes con EPOC</dc:description>
<dc:source>Neumosur (Sevilla);18(2): 69-77, jun. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-047783</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">EPOC: influencia sobre la disnea de un programa de ejercicio domiciliario</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12558^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12535^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5179^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4479^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
