<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79210</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-7632</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Lifestyle, dietetic habits and overweight and obesity prevalence in a pediatric population</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to determine the prevalence of overweight and obesity in children, characteristicsof their dietary habits, lifestyle and other associated determinants. Material and method: design: cross-sectional study. Location: Primary Health Center, urbanarea. Participants: children &gt; 6 and &lt; 10 years of ABS El Carmel (Barcelona) (n = 716).Selection criteria: random sample (n = 340; prevalence: 15%; CI: 95%; accuracy: 3%)from the database SIAP (System for Information in Primary Care), no exclusion criteria were established. No answer: n = 63 (95%: address error; 5%: lack of interest). Measurements: weight, height (for BMI), Quick Test and Short Test from Krece Plus (fordiet and lifestyle). Descriptive and bivariate analysis: Chi-square, t-test, ANOVA test, correlationtest and logistic regression. Results: two hundred and seventy-six surveys (81.4%). Overweight prevalence: 11.59%(95% CI: 7.81%-15.32%); obesity prevalence: 10.14% (95% CI: 6.58%-13.7%). Food habits:52.3% optimal feeding habits and 4.4% inadequate. Lifestyle: 58.7% bad lifestyle and 3.6% goodlifestyle. The BMI mean was higher (p &lt; 0.05) in inactive children, in low education level of mothers, or in born outside Spain. Overweight and obesity in children is 3.6 times higher (95% CI:1.37-8.05) if the father is obese and 3.1 times higher (95% CI: 1.19-7.31) if the mother is obese. Conclusions: the study provides a baseline for establishing the guidelines and activities ofthe community intervention program for preventing childhood obesity (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bosch Moraga, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casademont Ferrer, M. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Bueno, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Edo Martínez, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fábrega Bautista, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ollero Torres, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montaner Gomis, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gamero García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: conocer la prevalencia del sobrepeso y la obesidad en la población infantil,las características de sus hábitos dietéticos, su estilo de vida y otros determinantes asociados. Material y métodos: diseño: estudio descriptivo transversal. Emplazamiento: Centro de Atención Primaria, ámbito urbano. Participantes: niños &gt; 6 y &lt; 10 años del ABS El Carmel (Barcelona) (n = 716). Criterios de selección: muestra aleatoria &#150;n = 340; prevalencia: 15%; intervalo deconfianza (IC): 95%; precisión: 3%&#150; de la base de datos SIAP (Sistema de Informaciónen Atención Primaria). No se establecieron criterios de exclusión. Sin respuesta: n = 63(95%: errores de filiación; 5%: falta de interés). Mediciones principales: peso y talla &#150;para el índice de masa corporal (IMC)&#150;, test rápido Krece Plus y test corto de actividad física Krece Plus (para hábitos dietéticos y estilode vida). Análisis descriptivo y bivariado: chi al cuadrado, test de la t de Student, test deAnova, test de correlación y regresión logística. Resultados: 276 encuestas (81,4%). Prevalencia del sobrepeso: 11,59% (IC 95%:7,81%-15,32%); prevalencia de la obesidad: 10,14% (IC 95%: 6,58%-13,7%). Hábitos alimentarios: 52,3% tiene una alimentación óptima y 4,4% presenta hábitos inadecuados. Estilo de vida: malo: 58,7%; bueno: 3,6%. La media del IMC es superior (p &lt; 0,05) en los niños más inactivos, cuando el nivel de estudios de la madre es bajo o si nacieron fuera de España. El sobrepeso y la obesidad infantiles son 3,6 veces superiores (IC 95%: 1,37-8,05) si el padre es obeso y 3,1 veces superiores (IC 95%: 1,19-7,31) si lo es la madre. Conclusiones: el estudio proporciona una línea de base para establecer las directricesy actividades del programa de intervención comunitaria para la prevención de la obesidad infantil (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Pediatr. aten. prim;12(45): 53-65, ene.-mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79210</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estilos de vida, hábitos dietéticos y prevalencia del sobrepeso y la obesidad en una población infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4592</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22182</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16508</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8195</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
