<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-158320</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">High intensity focused ultrasound with Focal-One® device: prostate-specific antigen impact and morbidity evaluation during the initial experience</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. We report our initial experience in the treatment of prostate cancer (PCa) with high-intensity focused ultrasound (HIFU) using the Focal-One® device. Material and methods. Retrospective review of the prospectively populated database. Between June 2014 to October 2015, 85 patients underwent HIFU (focal/whole-gland) treatment for localized PCa. Preoperative cancer localization was done with multiparametric magnetic resonance imaging (mpMRI) and transperineal mapping biopsies. Treatment was carried out using the Focal-One® device under general anesthesia. Oncological follow-up: PSA measurement and control biopsy with mpMRI according to protocol. Questionnaire-based functional outcome assessment was done. Complications were reported using Clavien classification. Results. The median PSA was 7.79ng/ml (IQR 6.32-9.16), with a median prostate volume of 38cc (IQR: 33-49.75). Focal and whole-gland therapy was performed in 64 and 21 patients respectively. Ten patients received salvage HIFU. Complications were encountered in 15% of cases, all Clavien 2 graded. Mean hospital stay was 1.8 days (0-7) and bladder catheter was removed on day 2 (1-6). Mean percentage reduction of PSA was 54%. Median follow-up was 3 months (IQR: 2-8). Functional outcomes: All patients were continents at 3 months and potency was maintained in 83% of the preoperatively potent. Conclusions. Focal-One® HIFU treatment appears to be a safe procedure with few complications. Functional outcomes proved no urinary incontinence and sexual function were maintained in 83% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rozet, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez-Salas, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barret, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fregeville, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cathelineau, X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cathala, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galiano, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Linares Espinos, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Renard-Penna, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Prapotnich, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia-Nieto, AE de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sivaraman, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mombet, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez-Reggeti, JI</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Reportamos nuestra experiencia inicial en el tratamiento del cáncer de próstata (PCa) con ultrasonido focalizado de alta intensidad (HIFU) utilizando el dispositivo Focal-One®. Material y métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de datos recogidos prospectivamente. Entre junio de 2014 y octubre de 2015, 85 pacientes recibieron tratamiento HIFU (focal/total), para PCa localizado. La localización preoperatoria del tumor fue realizada con resonancia magnética multiparamétrica (mpMRI) y biopsias prostáticas mediante mapeo transperineal. El tratamiento fue realizado utilizando el dispositivo Focal-One® bajo anestesia general. Seguimiento oncológico: medición del PSA y biopsia control con mpMRI según protocolo. Los resultados funcionales fueron evaluados mediante cuestionarios validados y las complicaciones reportadas utilizando la clasificación Clavien. Resultados. La mediana de PSA fue 7,79ng/ml (6,32-9,16) con una mediana de volumen prostático de 38cc (33-49,75). El tratamiento fue focal y total en 64 y 21 pacientes respectivamente. Diez pacientes recibieron tratamiento de rescate. La tasa de complicaciones fue del 15%, todas Clavien 2. La estancia hospitalaria media fue 1,8 días (0-7) y la sonda vesical fue retirada el día 2 (1-6). La media de reducción porcentual del PSA fue 54%. La mediana de seguimiento fue 3 meses (2-8). Resultados funcionales: todos los pacientes estuvieron continentes a los 3 meses y la potencia se mantuvo en el 83% de los previamente potentes. Conclusiones. El tratamiento HIFU Focal-One® es un procedimiento seguro con pocas complicaciones. Los resultados funcionales no reportan casos de incontinencia y la función sexual se mantuvo en el 83% (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;40(10): 608-614, dic. 2016. tab, ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-158320</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ultrasonido focalizado de alta intensidad con el dispositivo Focal-One®: impacto sobre el antígeno prostático específico y evaluación de la morbilidad durante la experiencia inicial</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d779^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31536^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53691^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30596^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11914^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53691^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
