<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-119223</identifier>
<setSpec>1889-1780</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Construct of Emotional Labour and its Relationships with Burnout</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">This study examines the dimensions of Emotional Labour (EL) through the reliability and validity of Emotional Labour Questionnaire (TREMO), and determines the relationship between EL and Burnout in a multi-occupational sample. Emotional Labour refers to the expression of desirable emotions in the organization to influence relationship with customers or users. Previous studies underline the correlations between Emotional Labour and Burnout as response to chronic interpersonal and emotional stress at work, and which includes three components: emotional exhaustion, depersonalisation and personal accomplishment. The sample of this study consists of 594 participants (cashiers, sales agents and waiters). The factor analysis has been used as the main technique to explore the dimensions of the Emotional Labour and the correlations and regression analysis have been performed to analyse the relationship between the Emotional Labour and Burnout. The results of this study show adequate psychometric data on reliability, construct, and criteria validity for the evaluation of EL with the TREMO Questionnaire. This study also identifies five dimensions of Emotional Labour in which the Expression of Positive Emotion (EE) explaining the highest percentage of the variance. Furthermore, this study determines the existence of significant relations between the dimensions of Emotional Labour and Burnout (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mababu Mukiur, Richard</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Este estudio analiza las dimensiones del constructo Trabajo Emocional (TE) mediante la fiabilidad y validez del Cuestionario de Trabajo Emocional (TREMO), y determina la relación entre el TE y el desgaste profesional (burnout) en una muestra multiocupacional. El TE hace referencia a la expresión de las emociones deseables para influir en las relaciones con los clientes o usuarios y tiende a generar el burnout como respuesta al estrés crónico interpersonal y emocional en el trabajo. La muestra de este estudio está constituida por 594 participantes (cajeros, comerciales y camareros). Se ha utilizado principalmente el análisis factorial como técnica para explorar las dimensiones del TE y las correlaciones y el análisis de regresión para determinar la relación entre el TE y el burnout. Los resultados de este estudio demuestran que los análisis de fiabilidad y validez factorial realizados muestran que el Cuestionario TREMO presenta resultados psicométricos adecuados para la evaluación de TE. En la misma línea, los análisis de este estudio determinan cinco dimensiones del TE con la Expresión de las Emociones positivas (EE) explicando el mayor porcentaje de la varianza. Además, este estudio presenta unas relaciones significativas entre el TE y el desgaste profesional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Int. j. psychol. psychol. ther. (Ed. impr.);12(2): 219-244, jun. 2012. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-119223</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">El constructo de Trabajo Emocional y su relación con el Síndrome del Desgaste Profesional</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2087^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33140</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31198</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
