<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-AOT-2147</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Social and health resources in Catalonia. Current situation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The network of social and health care has advanced since its inception. Furthermore, news services have been created and some resources have been adapted within the framework of respective health plans. This article presents the current situation of the different social and health resources in Catalonia, as well as the main changes that have occurred in recent years, more specifically in the period of the Health Plan 2011-2015. This period is characterised by an adaptation of the social and health network within the context of chronic care, for which the development of intermediate care resources has become the most relevant aspect. There is also a need to create a single long-term care sector in which the health care quality is guaranteed. Moreover, in this period, integral and cross-care level is promoted in the health system through a greater coordination between all different levels of care. The social and health network, due to its trajectory and expertise, plays a key role in the quality of care for people with social and medical needs (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Bullich-Marín, Ingrid</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvà-Casanovas, Antoni</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez-Ferrína, Pau</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabanes-Durana, Concepció</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La red sociosanitaria ha evolucionado desde su creación adaptando los recursos o creando nuevos servicios bajo el impulso de los respectivos planes de salud. En este artículo se presenta el estado de los diferentes recursos sociosanitarios de Cataluña, así como los principales cambios que se han producido en los últimos años, más concretamente en el periodo del Plan de Salud 2011-2015. Esta etapa se caracteriza por una adecuación de la red sociosanitaria en el marco de la atención de la cronicidad, en la que ha tomado mayor relevancia el desarrollo de recursos de atención intermedia. Paralelamente, se plantea la necesidad de crear un único sector de larga duración en el que esté garantizada una atención sanitaria de calidad. También se impulsa la atención integral y transversal en el sistema sanitario, mediante una mayor coordinación entre los diferentes niveles asistenciales, en el que el ámbito sociosanitario, por su trayectoria y expertez, juega un papel determinante en la calidad de la atención a las personas con necesidades sociales y sanitarias (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);52(6): 342-347, nov.-dic. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-AOT-2147</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recursos sociosanitarios en Cataluña. Situación actual</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201712</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
