<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123628</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-5020</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Medication adherence and use of health services in patients with psychosis in the region of osona (Catalonia, Spain)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe and analyze sociodemographic and clinical characteristics, medication adherence and use of health resources by country of birth of psychosis diagnosed patients treated with long-term antipsychotic injectable drugs in the region of Osona (Catalonia, Spain). Method: Descriptive observational study in psychosis diagnosed patients over 18 years old, receiving long-term antipsychotic injectable treatment and treated at a Mental Health Center for adults in Vic (Catalonia, Spain). Results: 185 patients were included, of them: 163 (88.1%) were born in Spain and 22 (11.9%) abroad. The sample was gender homogeneous with differences in age, employment status, family situation and diagnosis (p&lt;0.05). Findings about medication adherence to long-term antipsychotic injectable ambulatory treatment reflected good compliance in both populations. 57.7% of Spain-born patients and 9.1% of abroad-born patients received the injectable treatment at Primary Care Center (p&lt;0,001). The rest of them received the treatment at Mental Health Center for adults. 22 patients (11.9%) were admitted at psychiatry hospitalization ward, 16 (9.8%) of them were born in Spain and 6 (27.3%) abroad (p=0.012). Conclusions: All patients diagnosed with psychosis, either born or not in Spain, describe good adherence to long-term antipsychotic injectable treatment, with similar use of health resources from a quantitative point of view and some differences in the type of visits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Palmarola-Ginesta, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Puigoriol-Juvanteny, Emma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bleda-García, Francesc</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vila-Ribas, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chirveches-Pérez, Emilia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arrufat-Nebot, Francesc Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir y analizar las características demográficas y clínicas, adherencia al tratamiento y utilización de los servicios de salud, según el país de nacimiento de las personas afectadas de psicosis tratadas con antipsicóticos inyectables de acción prolongada, en la comarca de Osona (Cataluña, España). Método: Estudio observacional y descriptivo sobre pacientes diagnosticados de psicosis, en tratamiento farmacológico con antipsicóticos inyectables de acción prolongada, mayores de 18 años y atendidos en un Centro de Salud Mental de adultos de Vic (Cataluña, Barcelona). Resultados: Se incluyeron 185 pacientes, nacidos en España 163 (88,1%) y fuera 22 (11,9%). La muestra fue homogénea respecto al sexo y con diferencias respecto a la edad, situación laboral, familiar y diagnóstico (p&lt;0,05). Los hallazgos en torno a la adhesión al tratamiento ambulatorio inyectable de acción prolongada reflejan un buen cumplimiento en ambas poblaciones. Se administró dicho tratamiento en los Centros de Atención Primaria al 57,7% de los pacientes nacidos en España y al 9,1% de los no nacidos en el país (p&lt;0,001). El resto fue atendido en el Centro de Salud Mental de Adultos. Veintidós pacientes (el 11,9% del total) fueron ingresados como agudos; de ellos 16 (9,8%) nacidos en España y 6 (27,3%) no nacidos (p=0,012). Conclusiones: Todos los pacientes diagnosticados de psicosis, nacidos y no nacidos en España, presentan una buena adherencia al tratamiento antipsicótico inyectable de acción prolongada, con un uso similar de recursos sanitarios desde un punto de vista cuantitativo y algunas diferencias respecto a la tipología de las visitas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Enferm;37(4): 282-289, abr. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adherencia al tratamiento y utilización de servicios de salud. Pacientes con psicosis</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3706^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14542^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52950^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12054^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
