<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138606</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Unified Protocol for psychiatric and psychological assessment of candidates for transplantation of organs and tissues, PSI-CAT</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Transplantation is the treatment option that offers improved survival and quality of life as compared to organ failure. Psychiatric and psychological aspects of transplant candidates are important, especially in the pre-assessment stage, as the influence of these factors can hinder post-surgical outcome in both the implanted organ survival and the quality of life of the transplanted person. Of particular importance, are the factors related to pathology due to substance use, psychopathology, and psychosocial support. There are currently few guidelines on the correct evaluation of patients eligible for these complex procedures. Method. Nineteen psychiatrists and clinical psychologists from six public hospitals in Catalonia conducted a systematic consensus to determine the design of a Unified Protocol psychological and psychiatric evaluation. An annual work plan was implemented, during which; the objectives were defined, a literature review was conducted, the inclusion and exclusion criteria were discussed, questionnaires were selected, and a structured interview was developed. Results. With the implementation of the work plan, the Assessment Protocol presented in this article was designed. Conclusions. systematic work and improving cooperation between psychiatrists and clinical psychologists, has led to homogeneity and consensus on a unified evaluation protocol (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Castan Campanera, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopez Lazcano, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcántara Tadeo, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez del Pozo, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Costa Requena, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rangil Muñoz, Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lligoña Garreta, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diez Quevedo, Crisanto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peri Nogués, Josep María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fidel Kinori, Sara Guila</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El trasplante es la opción terapéutica que ofrece mayor supervivencia y calidad de vida frente al fallo de un órgano. Los aspectos psiquiátricos y psicológicos de los candidatos a trasplante son relevantes, especialmente en la etapa de evaluación previa, pues la influencia de estos factores puede dificultar la evolución posquirúrgica, tanto en la supervivencia del órgano implantado como en la calidad de vida de la persona trasplantada. Son de especial importancia los factores vinculados a la patología por uso de sustancias, los trastornos psicopatológicos y el soporte psicosocial. Actualmente, existen pocas Guías que orienten sobre la correcta evaluación de los pacientes candidatos a estos procedimientos complejos. Método. Diecinueve psiquiatras y psicólogos clínicos de 6 hospitales públicos de Cataluña realizaron un trabajo sistemático de consenso para llegar al diseño de un protocolo unificado de evaluación psicológica y psiquiátrica. Se implementó un plan de trabajo anual, se definieron objetivos y se realizó una revisión bibliográfica, se discutieron los criterios de inclusión y exclusión, se seleccionaron los cuestionarios y se elaboró la entrevista estructurada. Resultados. Con el cumplimiento del plan de trabajo, se diseñó el Protocolo de Evaluación que se presenta en este artículo. Conclusiones. El trabajo sistematizado y la colaboración intercentros de psiquiatras y psicólogos clínicos ha facilitado homogeneizar y consensuar un protocolo unificado de evaluación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);8(3): 130-136, jul.-sept. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138606</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Protocolo unificado para la evaluación psiquiátrica y psicológica de candidatosa trasplante de órganos y tejidos, PSI-CAT</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13383^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29074^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201509</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
