<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150498</identifier>
<setSpec>1132-1296</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Religiosity in the healing process of the individual with systemic arterial hypertension</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We aimed at interpreting the influence of religion on the interface of Systemic Arterial Hypertension in the healing. Ethnographic study based on the healing. Ethnographic study based on Interpretive Anthropology carried on with 22 individuals in a town in Minas Gerais. The 'nervousness problem' is a nosocomial category related to the disease, resulting from the urban lifestyle, and the command for reharmonization is ascribed to the divine plan. Religion as resignificance for life is put into action for relief of the evils, of the suffering and for the healing of the infirmity. It supplies revitalization of energies; better well-being; healthier behavior and health care. We reiterate the need of preparing health professionals, mainly the nurse, to recognize, respect and encourage religiousness of chronic condition individuals under her care, provided the individual feels improvements in her living process, which allows to offer 'care' within the perspective of holistic assistance to health (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Veiga, Eugenia Velludo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fava, Silvana Maria Coelho Leite</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Dázio, Eliza María Rezende</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rezende, Eliane García</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivamos interpretar la influencia de la religión en la interfaz del tratamiento de la Hipertensión Arterial Sistémica en el proceso de cuidado. Estudio etnográfico fundamentado en la Antropología Interpretativa realizado con 22 personas de un municipio de Minas Gerais. El problema de "los nervios" o "lo nervioso" constituye la categoría nosológica que se relaciona con la enfermedad como consecuencia del estilo de vida urbano; y el orden para la rearmonización se coloca en el plano de lo divino. La religión como resignificación de la vida es accionada para el alivio de los males, de los sufrimientos, y para la curación de la enfermedad. Esta proporciona una revitalización de las energías, un mejor bienestar, comportamientos sanos y cuidados a la salud. Reiteramos la necesidad de la preparación de los profesionales de la salud, principalmente del enfermero, para reconocer, respetar e incentivar la religión de la persona crónica que está bajo sus cuidados, siempre que esta sienta mejorías en su proceso de vivir, lo que permite al enfermero ofrecer cuidados dentro de una perspectiva de asistencia integral a la salud (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Index enferm;24(4): 207-211, oct.-dic. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150498</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La religiosidad en la curación de la persona con hipertensión arterial sistémica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d897^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28437</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3222^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36285^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12490</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201512</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
