<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-123809</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-9895</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">No disponible</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Community-acquired pneumonia (CAP) is the sixth leading cause of death in our country and the main indication for antibiotic prescription. Assessing its severity can be done using gravity index (PSI, CURB- 65) or sepsis biomarkers such as C-reactive protein (CRP) and procalcitonin. Objective: To analyze the predictive value (mortality, admission to intensive care unit, readmissions) of the gravity index, biomarkers and the combination of both groups in the severity assessment of CAP. Patients and methods: A prospective observational study was carried out with patients admitted with CAP in Internal Medicine and Pneumology of a tertiary hospital. We analyzed clinical and analytical parameters, risk classes of the gravity index and treatment received. Poor outcome events were recorded (ICU admission and mortality) during 90 days. Results: 155 patients were included with mean age of 71 years, 94% male. A 73.6% belonged to high risk classes of the gravity index, which had worse outcome. Overall mortality was 12.9%: at 30 days it was associated with high score of PSI, and at 90 days with high levels of procalcitonin. In patients at low risk of death based on gravity index, procalcitonin levels were low. The other biological parameters were not associated with the prognosis. Conclusion: The combination of procalcitonin with clinical scales helps defining low-risk patients, deciding admission and assessing severity in patients with CAP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Miguel Díez, J de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Millán-Núñez Cortés, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cabezón Estévanez, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bellón Cano, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La neumonía adquirida en la comunidad (NAC) supone la sexta causa de muerte en nuestro medio y la principal indicación de antibióticos. Para su valoración pronóstica se emplean índices de gravedad (PSI, CURB-65) y marcadores biológicos de sepsis como la proteína C reactiva (PCR) y la procalcitonina. Objetivo: Analizar el valor pronóstico (mortalidad, ingreso en unidad de cuidados intensivos &#150;UCI&#150;, reingresos) de la combinación de estos índices de gravedad con biomarcadores en pacientes con NAC. acientes y métodos: Estudio prospectivo observacional de pacientes ingresados por NAC en Medicina Interna y Neumología de un hospital terciario. Se analizaron parámetros clínicos, analíticos, riesgo según índices de gravedad y tratamiento. Se registraron durante 90 días eventos de mala evolución (ingreso en UCI y mortalidad). Resultados: Se incluyeron 155 pacientes con edad media de 71 años, el 94% varones. Los pacientes con alta puntuación de los índices de gravedad (73,6%) presentaron evolución desfavorable. La mortalidad global fue de 12,9%; a los 30 días se asoció a alta puntuación del índice PSI, y a los 90 días a niveles elevados de procalcitonina. En pacientes de bajo riesgo según los índices de gravedad los niveles de procalcitonina fueron bajos. El resto de parámetros biológicos no se asociaron con la evolución. Conclusión: La procalcitonina complementa a los índices de gravedad a la hora de definir pacientes de bajo riesgo, decidir el ingreso hospitalario y valorar la gravedad en pacientes con NAC (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. patol. respir;17(2): 44-49, abr.-jun. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-123809</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Combinación de índices de gravedad con biomarcadores en la valoración pronóstica de la neumonía adquirida en la comunidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11443^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22124^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31549^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31136^s32387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22372^s22063</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
