<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-162103</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-0882</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors associated with early discharge after inguinal hernia repair</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: In Mexico outpatient inguinal hernia repair is not widely accepted by surgeons prefer hospital surveillance against early discharge to home, the rate of complications and other factors. There is a legislated rules for patients (NOM-205-SSA1-2002) that can be selected for outpatient surgery. Patients and methods: An observational analytical cohort prospective study in patients with tension-free inguinal hernia repair between December 2010 and February 2011 in the Bajio UMAE IMSS, n = 50, studying the variables: evolution time of hernia, surgical time, intraoperative complications, postoperative pain, nausea and vomiting after surgery and discharge management. Two categories: inpatient and outpatient, valuing the exit criteria for scale of White and Song. Results: 50 patients, 42 men and 8 women, age 54.32 years. 36 (72 %) outpatients and 14 (28 %) in patients. Ambulatory criteria 31 (86 %) and hospitalization 6 (42 %). Of the variables only pain was significant (p = 0.05). The other variables were not significant. Conclusions: This study shows that patients operated on by tension-free inguinal hernia repair can be managed on an outpatient basis using the criteria of White and Song. Pain was the only relevant factor (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Robles Plascencia, SJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Magdaleno García, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Meléndez Delgado, MD</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: En México la hernioplastia inguinal ambulatoria es poco aceptada por cirujanos, ya que prefieren la vigilancia hospitalaria frente al alta precoz al domicilio por el índice de complicaciones y otros factores. Hay una normativa legislada para los pacientes (NOM-205- SSA1-2002) que pueden ser selec-cionados para la cirugía ambulatoria. Pacientes y métodos: Estudio observacional de cohorte prospectivo en pacientes con hernioplastia inguinal sin tensión (n = 50), operados entre diciembre del 2010 y febrero del 2011, en los que son evaluadas las variables tiempo de evolución de la hernia, tiempo operatorio, complicaciones intraoperatorias, dolor postquirúrgico y presencia de náuseas y vómitos posoperatorio, según el tipo adoptado de alta clínica: con hospitalización o con alta ambulatoria (alta precoz), siguiendo los criterios de alta de White y Song. Resultados: 50 pacientes (42 hombres y 8 mujeres), con edad media de 54,3 años. De ellos, en 36 (72 %) con alta precoz (ambulatoria), 31 (86 %) tenían criterios para la ambulatorización, mientras que 5 (14 %) no cumplían con tales criterios. Los 14 restantes (28 %) quedaron hospitalizados, de los que sólo 6 (42 %) tenían criterios de hospitalización y 8 (57 %) no. De las variables estudiadas, sólo el dolor fue más patente en los ambulatorizados, con significación estadística (p = 0,05); no tuvieron significación estadística otras variables. Conclusión: Los pacientes operados mediante hernioplastia libre de tensión pueden ser manejados de forma ambulatoria siguiendo los criterios de White y Song. El dolor fue el único factor relevante a considerar en aquellos que se pretendan ambulatorizar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir. mayor ambul;22(1): 3-9, ene.-mar. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-162103</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores relacionados con el alta precoz tras la reparacion de hernia inguinal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10336^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32095</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d557^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54711^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6711^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10545^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12415^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
