<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122720</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Muscle Glucose Metabolism in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease Patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Muscle dysfunction is one of the most extensively studied manifestations of COPD. Metabolic changes in muscle are difficult to study in vivo, due to the lack of non-invasive techniques. Our aim was to evaluate metabolic activity simultaneously in various muscle groups in COPD patients. Methods: Thirty-nine COPD patients and 21 controls with normal lung function, due to undergo computed axial and positron emission tomography for staging of localized lung lesions were included. After administration of 18-fluordeoxyglucose, images of 2 respiratory muscles (costal and crural diaphragm, and rectus abdominus) and 2 peripheral muscles (brachial biceps and quadriceps) were obtained, using the standard uptake value as the glucose metabolism index. Results: Standard uptake value was higher in both portions of the diaphragm than in the other muscles of all subjects. Moreover, the crural diaphragm and rectus abdominus showed greater activity in COPD patients than in the controls (1.8±0.7 vs 1.4±0.8; and 0.78±0.2 vs 0.58±0.1; respectively, P&lt;0.05). A similar trend was observed with the quadriceps. In COPD patients, uptake in the two respiratory muscles and the quadriceps correlated directly with air trapping (r=0.388, 0.427 and 0.361, respectively, P&lt;0.05). Conclusions: There is greater glucose uptake and metabolism in the human diaphragm compared to other muscles when the subject is at rest. Increased glucose metabolism in the respiratory muscles (with a similar trend in their quadriceps) of COPD patients is confirmed quantitatively, and is directly related to the mechanical loads confronted (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Sergi</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho-Muñoz, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chalela, Roberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Llorens, Juana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Joaquim Gea, Joaquim</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauricio Orozco-Levi, Mauricio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Trampal, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La disfunción muscular es una de las manifestaciones sistémicas más estudiadas en la EPOC. Las alteraciones metabólicas musculares son difíciles de estudiar in vivo, debido a la falta de técnicas no invasivas. El objetivo fue evaluar sincrónicamente la actividad metabólica de diferentes grupos musculares en pacientes con EPOC. Métodos: Se incluyeron 39 pacientes y 21 controles (función pulmonar normal), candidatos a realización de tomografía axial computarizada y por emisión de positrones para estadificación de lesión pulmonar localizada. Tras infusión de 18-fluor-deoxi-glucosa, se captaron imágenes de 2 músculos respiratorios (porciones costal y crural del diafragma, y recto abdominal) y 2 músculos periféricos (cuádriceps y bíceps braquial), utilizando como índice de metabolismo glucídico el standard uptake value. Resultados: Este índice fue superior en ambas porciones del diafragma comparado con el resto de los músculos en todos los sujetos. Además, el diafragma crural y el recto del abdomen mostraban mayor actividad en los pacientes con EPOC que en los controles (1,8 ± 0,7 vs. 1,4 ± 0,8; y 0,78 ± 0,2 vs. 0,58 ± 0,1; respectivamente; p &lt; 0,05). El cuádriceps mostraba una tendencia similar. En los pacientes con EPOC los niveles de captación de ambos músculos respiratorios y del cuádriceps se correlacionaron directamente con el atrapamiento aéreo (r = 0,388; 0,427 y 0,361, respectivamente; p &lt; 0,05). Conclusiones: Existe mayor nivel de captación-utilización de glucosa en el diafragma humano respecto de otros músculos en respiración tranquila. Se confirma cuantitativamente que los pacientes con EPOC tienen incrementado el metabolismo glucídico de sus músculos respiratorios (con tendencia similar para el cuádriceps), en relación directa con las cargas mecánicas que afrontan (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;50(6): 221-227, jun. 2014. tab, graf, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122720</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de glucosa en los músculos de pacientes con enfermedad pulmonar obstructiva crónica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d50351^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36008^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53086^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38793^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19334^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201406</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
