<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114420</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact of anti-diabetic therapy based on glucagon-like peptide-1 receptor agonists on the cardiovascular risk of patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Anti-diabetic drugs have, in addition to their well-known glucose lowering-effect, different effects in the rest of cardiovascular factors that are associated with diabetes mellitus. Glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1) receptor agonists have recently been incorporated to the therapeutic arsenal of type 2 diabetes mellitus. The objective of this review is to summarize the available evidence on the effect of the GLP-1 receptor agonists on different cardiovascular risk factors, mediated by the effect of GLP-1 receptor agonists on the control of hyperglycaemia and the GLP-1 receptor agonists effect on other cardiovascular risk factors (weight control, blood pressure control, lipid profile and all other cardiovascular risk biomarkers). In addition, we present the emerging evidence with regards to the impact that GLP-1 receptor agonists therapy could have in the reduction of cardiovascular events and the currently ongoing studies addressing this issue (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Camafort Babkowski, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los fármacos antidiabéticos tienen, además de su conocido efecto hipoglucemiante, diferentes efectos sobre el resto de los factores de riesgo cardiovascular asociados a diabetes mellitus. Recientemente se han incorporado al arsenal terapéutico de la diabetes mellitus de tipo 2 los agonistas del receptor del glucagon-like peptide-1 (AR-GLP-1, «péptido tipo 1 similar al glucagón»). El objetivo de este trabajo es resumir la evidencia disponible sobre el efecto de los AR-GLP-1 en diferentes factores de riesgo cardiovascular, mediado tanto por el efecto hipoglucemiante de los AR-GLP-1 como por su efecto sobre los demás factores de riesgo cardiovascular (control del peso, presión arterial, perfil lipídico y otros marcadores de riesgo cardiovascular). Además, se presenta la incipiente evidencia con respecto al impacto que el tratamiento con AR-GLP-1 pudiera tener en la reducción de los episodios cardiovasculares y los estudios que hay actualmente en marcha para abordar este aspecto (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);141(4): 167-174, ago. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114420</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto del tratamiento antidiabético con fármacos agonistas del receptor de péptido de tipo 1 similar al glucagón en el riesgo cardiovascular de pacientes con diabetes mellitus tipo 2</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50567^s32387</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7182^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
