<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-106453</identifier>
<setSpec>2172-3761</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Indications and brand names of the generic drugs</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">After the appearance on the generic drug market of active ingredients with significant impact on the National Health Care System invoicing, a debate has been opened on their indications and interchangeability for this reason. Simultaneously, the doubt also arises about the influence of the different excipients or the different non-therapeutic fraction existing between reference medications and their corresponding generic ones. The differences in the indications are motivated by the second indication patent, together with the possibility of omitting the protected indications on the data sheet, as is contemplated in the regulation that regulatesthe authorization of the medication. On the other hand, the evaluation procedure assures that the differences in the non-therapeutic fraction of a drug (excipients, salt, esters, etc.) have been evaluated in regards to their toxicity, effect in pharmacokinetics and equivalent availability (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paredero Domínguez, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Tras la aparición en el mercado de medicamentos genéricos de principios activos con gran impacto en la facturación del Sistema Nacional de Salud, se ha abierto un debate sobre las indicaciones de los mismos y la intercambiabilidad por este motivo. A la vez, resurge la duda sobre la influencia de los diferentes excipientes o de la diferente fracción no terapéutica que existe entre medicamentos de referencia y sus correspondientes genéricos. Las diferencias en las indicaciones están motivadas por la patente de segunda indicación, junto con la posibilidad de omitir en la ficha técnica las indicaciones protegidas, tal como se contempla en la normativa que regula la autorización de medicamentos. Por otro lado, el procedimiento de evaluación garantiza que las diferencias en la fracción no terapéutica de un medicamento (excipientes, sales, ésteres, etc.) ha sido valorada en cuanto a su toxicidad, efecto en la farmacocinética y biodisponibilidad equivalente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Farm. aten. prim;8(1/3): 7-14, dic. 2010. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-106453</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las indicaciones y marcas de los medicamentos genéricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d22965</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11742</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36467</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4410^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51460</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30149^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
