<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038969</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Cholesterol absorption inhibitors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hypercholesterolemia is a cardiovascular risk factor. Effective and long-term reduction of total and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol concentrations lowers mortality from coronary heart disease. Until now the most effective cholesterol-lowering drugs have been hydroxymethyl glutaryl coenzyme A reductase inhibitors (statins). However many patients do not achieve standard treatment goals as defined by clinical guidelines with statins in monotherapy and require combination therapy with other lipid lowering drugs. The present review discusses the pharmacologic agents that act through inhibition of cholesterol absorption and their role in the clinical management of hypercholesterolemia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Boix, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Picó, A. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La hipercolesterolemia es un factor de riesgo cardiovascular. La reducción eficaz y a largo plazo de las concentraciones de colesterol total y ligado a lipoproteínas de baja densidad previene la mortalidad por enfermedad coronaria. Hasta la fecha los fármacos más eficaces para reducir las concentraciones plasmáticas de colesterol eran los inhibidores de la hidroximetilglutaril coenzima A reductasa (estatinas). Sin embargo, en muchos pacientes la monoterapia con estos fármacos no consigue la reducción del colesterol hasta las cifras establecidas por las guías de actuación clínica, por lo que se hace necesario el tratamiento combinado con otros hipolipemiantes. En el presente artículo se revisan los fármacos que actúan fundamentalmente a través de una inhibición de la absorción del colesterol y su utilidad en la práctica clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;52(6): 297-308, jun. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038969</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inhibidores de la absorción del colesterol</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2834^s22062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8251^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3343^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d931^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33014^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
