<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-93249</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Improving lectures in Medicine: ten examples of mini-cases to be used in the teaching of pharmacology</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Lectures are the preferred method of teaching in many schools of Medicine. However, this method has several limitations, such as the passive role assumed by students and the loss of their attention. In order to improve the use of lectures, some authors have suggested the use of minicases. These are short texts that include several questions, which are related with the contents of the lecture and students are asked to answer them at its end. The present paper describes an experience of using minicases in the teaching of pharmacology. It offers ten examples to illustrate how they are built. Most of them are related with the real world, they permit to put knowledge of basic sciences in context of clinical problems and stimulate the understanding of key concepts of the discipline (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Baños, J. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Farré, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las clases magistrales constituyen un método pedagógico muy utilizado en las facultades de medicina. Sin embargo, tiene diversas limitaciones entre las que se encuentran la pasividad y la pérdida de la atención de los alumnos. A fin de estimular la atención y revigorizar su empleo, se han empleado textos cortos que plantean preguntas que pueden resolverse con la información proporcionada en la clase magistral (minicasos). El presente artículo describe una experiencia de su uso en la docencia de la farmacología y ofrece diez ejemplos para ilustrar sobre su empleo. La mayoría de ellos están ambientados en el mundo real, permiten contextualizar los conocimientos básicos de farmacología y estimulan la  comprensión de los conceptos claves (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);14(2): 105-111, jun. 2011.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-93249</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Dinamización de la clase magistral en medicina: diez ejemplos de minicasos utilizados en la docencia de la farmacología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10790^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14042^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32065^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4591</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
