<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-164639</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recommendations for the use of everolimus in de novo kidney transplantation: False beliefs, myths and realities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The immunosuppressive combination most commonly used in de novo kidney transplantation comprises a calcineurin inhibitor (CI), tacrolimus, a mycophenolic acid derivative and steroids. The evidence which underlies this practice is based in the Symphony trial with controlled follow-up of one year, in which no comparator group included the combination CI-mTOR inhibitor. Different high-quality clinical trials support the use of everolimus as a standard immunosuppressive drug associated with reduced exposure of a CI in kidney transplantation. This combination could improve health related outcomes in kidney transplantation recipients. The present recommendations constitute an attempt to summarise the scientific evidence supporting this practice, discuss false beliefs, myths and facts, and offer specific guidelines for safe use, avoiding complications (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pascual, Julio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Marqués, Gonzalo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Calabuig, Asunción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oppenheimer, Federico</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutiérrez Dalmaue, Alex</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rivera, Constantino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Diekmann, Fritz</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Sáez, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La combinación inmunosupresora más utilizada en trasplante renal de novo incluye un inhibidor de calcineurina (IC), tacrolimus, un derivado del ácido micofenólico y esteroides. La evidencia que sustenta esta práctica se basa en el ensayo clínico Symphony, de evolución controlada durante un año, en el que no existía ningún grupo comparador con IC asociado a un inhibidor de mTOR. Diversos ensayos clínicos de alta calidad sustentan la indicación del uso de everolimus como inmunosupresor básico asociado a una exposición reducida de un IC en pacientes que reciben un trasplante renal. Esta combinación podría mejorar las expectativas de resultados en salud. Estas recomendaciones tratan de aportar la evidencia científica que apoya esta práctica, discuten las falsas creencias, mitos y realidades de la combinación y concretan pautas que permiten utilizarla con seguridad y evitar complicaciones  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;37(3): 253-266, mayo-jun. 2017. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-164639</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones para el uso de everolimus en trasplante renal de novo: falsas creencias, mitos y realidades</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6235^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55896^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7344^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19291^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4400</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29475</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31818^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55657^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201706</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
