<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79886</identifier>
<setSpec>1576-1959</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to treatment and success after a year in the abandonment of tobacco addiction</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know cessation rate of a program forbecoming unaccustomed to tobacco with group therapyand pharmacological treatment and to identify predictingitems of success of the treatment.Patients and method: prospective study of a descriptive-analytical cohort. The studied variables were: age,sex, profession, age of fi rst consumption, number ofcigarettes/ day, Fagerström&#146;s test, situations of specialconsumption, current motivation (punctuation from0 to 10), Russell&#146;s test, previous attempts, coexistencewith smokers, consumption of other substances,tobacco dependent diseases, physical exercise, cooximetría,Index of Corporal Mass, use of medicamentsmodality and adherence to the treatment.Group therapies began formed by groups between15-20 people with a total of 8 sessions a year. Thetreatment was considered fi nalized the last session ofthe year and contacted telephonically in case of notbeing present at the workshop.Results: success after a year. Auto-declared abstinenceconfi rmed by cooximetria was considered to be asuccess (carbon monoxide &lt;10 ppm). A regression logisticanalysis univariante and multivariant was applied,determining the odds ratios with the confi dence intervalsof 95%. The studied population was formed by193 individuals, 55% males and 42% females, with anaverage age of 45. The medium age of fi rst consumptionwas 15 and Fagerström&#146;s test was of 6. The 84,7%of the individuals fulfi lled well the treatment. The ratesof success were of 91% after 15 days and of 49 % ofsuccess after a year. The variables: complete treatmentdose (OR: 9,83); IMC (OR: 1,24); consciousness ofdependency (1,28) and percentage of smokers at work(OR: 0,98) they have been associated independentlywith success after a year (multi-varied model)...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gombau, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mateu, M. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Adell, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castillo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quintó, Ll</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer la tasa de cesación de un programade deshabituación tabáquica con terapia grupal ytratamiento farmacológico e identifi car predictores deéxito del tratamiento.Pacientes y método: estudio prospectivo descriptivo-analítico de una cohorte. Las variables estudiadasfueron: edad, sexo, profesión, edad del primer consumo,número de cigarrillos/día, test de Fagerström,situaciones de especial consumo, motivación actual(puntuación del 0 al 10), test de Russell, intentos previos,convivencia con fumadores, consumo de otrassustancias, enfermedades tabacodependientes, ejerciciofísico, cooximetría, Índice de Masa Corporal, usode fármacos modalidad y adherencia al tratamiento. Seiniciaron terapias de grupo de entre 15-20 personascon un total de 8 sesiones al año. La última sesión alaño se da fi nalizado el tratamiento y se contacta telefónicamenteen caso de no asistir al taller.Se consideró éxito al año la abstinencia autodeclaraday confi rmada mediante cooximetría (monóxido decarbono &lt; 10 ppm). Se aplicó un análisis de regresiónlogística univariante y multivariante, determinando lasodds ratios con los intervalos de confi anza del 95%.Resultados: La población de estudio estaba compuestapor 193 individuos, el 55 % varones y el 45%mujeres, con un media de edad de 45 años. La edadmediana del primer consumo era de 15 años, el test deFagerström era de 6 y el 85% de los individuos cumplióbien el tratamiento. Las tasas de éxito fueron del91% a los 15 días y de un 49% de éxito al año. Lasvariables: dosis completa tratamiento (OR: 9,83); IMC(OR: 1,24); conciencia de dependencia (1,28) y porcentajede fumadores en el trabajo (OR: 0,98) se hanasociado de forma independiente con el éxito al año(modelo multivariado)...(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prev. tab;12(1): 12-30, ene.-mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79886</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La adherencia al tratamiento grupal más vareniclina y el éxito al año en el abandono tabáquico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28603</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12051^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d51528</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14417^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33882^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
