<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-81851</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-3429</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Impact factor and quality of scientific publications on Microbiology: the example of the Spanish Journal of Chemotherapy</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. The impact factor of a journal is the quantitative analysis of the number of citations obtained during a specific period of time. This currently is the standard tool to measure the quality of the publication and a way to evaluate the research trajectory of a scientist. Methods. Search for bibliometric indicators: Journal Citation Reports, SCImago Journal Rank and Potencial Impact Factor for the Spanish Medical Journals of the Instituto de Historia de la Ciencia y Documentación López Piñero (IHCD). To identify criteria of editorial quality, of visibility and of spreading by reviewing databases such as the Online Regional Information System for Scholarly Journals from Latin America, the Caribbean, Spain and Portugal (LATINDEX), SciELO (Scientific Electronic Library Online), DIALNET and the Collective Periodical Publications Catalogue of Spanish Healthcare Science Libraries, known as C17. Results. For the first time, the Spanish Journal of Chemotherapy appears in the 2009 edition of JCR, previously by joined the two spanish journals Clinical Microbiology and Infectious Diseases and International Microbiology, both ranked at a lower position. While calculating factors of national and international impact of the five publications included in the category of Pharmacology and Pharmacy as part of the project initiated by the IHCD, the Spanish Journal of Chemotherapy showed the best results. Conclusions. The Spanish Journal of Chemotherapy obtained good results in analysed bibliometric indicators, positioning it at the top of the ranking of Spanish medical journals. A good spreading helped to maintain visibility on the publication in the editorial field(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Carabantes Alarcón, David</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. El factor de impacto de una revista es el análisis cuantitativo del número de citas recibidas durante un período específico de tiempo. Actualmente es la herramienta estándar para medir la calidad de las publicaciones y una forma para evaluar la trayectoria investigadora de un científico. Métodos. Búsqueda de indicadores bibliométricos: Journal Citation Reports (JCR), Factor de impacto potencial de las revistas médicas españolas del Instituto de Historia de la Ciencia y Documentación López Piñero (IHCD) y SCImago Journal Rank. Identificar criterios de calidad editorial, difusión y visibilidad revisando bases de datos como el Sistema Regional de Información en Línea para Revistas Científicas de América Latina, el Caribe, España y Portugal (LATINDEX), SciELO (Scientific Electronic Library Online), DIALNET y el catálogo de publicaciones periódicas en Bibliotecas de Ciencias de la Salud Españolas, conocido como C17. Resultados. La Revista Española de Quimioterapia aparece por primera vez en la edición 2009 del JCR, previamente se incorporaron dos revistas españolas Enfermedades Infecciosas y Microbiología Clínica e International Microbiology, y ambas ocupaban bajos puestos en el ranking. Al calcular los factores de impacto nacional e internacional de las cinco publicaciones que se incluyen en la categoría de Farmacología y Farmacia dentro del proyecto realizado por el IHCD, la Revista Española de Quimioterapia es la publicación que alcanzó los mejores valores. Conclusiones. La Revista Española de Quimioterapia obtuvo unos buenos resultados en los indicadores bibliométricos analizados y se sitúa a la cabeza de las publicaciones médicas españolas. Una buena difusión hace que sea más sencillo mantener la visibilidad de la publicación en el ámbito editorial(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Quimioter;23(3): 135-143, sep.2010.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-81851</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factor de impacto y calidad de las publicaciones científicas en Microbiología: el ejemplo de la Revista Española de Quimioterapia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30918^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50084</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28626</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50090</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11756^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4418^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24536</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50105</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
