<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-165478</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Refractory aqueous misdirection syndrome: A possible complication of penetrating keratoplasty</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Clinical case: An 85 year-old woman presented with a flat anterior chamber of the left eye, severe ocular hypertension, and a normal ultrasound examination in the day following a penetrating keratoplasty (PK). The clinical status did not respond to maximum medical therapy, laser posterior capsulotomy, anterior hyaloidotomy, and complete 23 G vitrectomy. The patient refused further intervention, and light perception was lost after 6 months of follow-up. Discussion: This is the first report of refractory aqueous misdirection syndrome following primary PK. Despite maximum medical and surgical management efforts, aqueous misdirection syndrome subsequent to primary PK may have a catastrophic outcome (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Filipe, HP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Faria, MY</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gama, I</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Almeida, LD</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodrigues, WM</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Caso clínico: Una mujer de 85 años presentó atalamia del ojo izquierdo e hipertensión ocular grave con ecografía normal al día siguiente de la queratoplastia penetrante (QP). Este estado clínico no ha respondido a la terapia médica máxima, con láser y a la vitrectomía 23 G completa. La paciente rechazó otras intervenciones quirúrgicas y la percepción de la luz se perdió después de 6 meses de seguimiento. Discusión: Esta es la primera descripción de síndrome de dirección inadecuada del humor acuoso refractario tras la QP no precedida de trasplante corneal previo. A pesar de los esfuerzos médicos y quirúrgicos máximos, el síndrome de dirección inadecuada del humor acuoso tras QP puede tener una evolución catastrófica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;92(8): 390-393, ago. 2017. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-165478</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Síndrome de dirección inadecuada del humor acuoso refractario: una posible complicación de la queratoplastia penetrante</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d52861</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28053^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29474^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38335^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15223^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23041^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1089</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201708</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
