<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-124669</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical sessions on patient care in order to probe into what nurses think</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Since 2009, the Hospital Universitario Virgen de las Nieves (HUVN) has been conducting clinical sessions on patient care, with the objective of achieving a deep understanding about the use of nursing methodology, and creating the habit of continuous reflection about the quality of careapplied. This paper intends to make public the experience developed during the years 2011-2012 in terms of clinical sessions on patient care. During the period studied, 35 clinical sessions on patient care have been conducted, distributed among the healthcare centres of the hospital complex; 19 of these have been clinical cases, 12 have been patient care updates, three reviews of clinical practice guidelines, and one review of integrated healthcare system. The average attendance to these sessions was of 16 professionals per session. The topics covered included specific health situations of interest for patient care units, investigation into differential diagnoses, and the incorporation of scientific evidence. As an improvement, it has been suggested to incorporate criteria forthe assessment of the nursing process, and of the structure of clinical sessions on patient care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Toral López, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rivas Campos, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Quiñoz Gallardo, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vellido González, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Carrión, Pilar</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Desde 2009 el Hospital Universitario Virgen de las Nieves (HUVN), en Granada, viene realizando sesiones clínicas de cuidados con el objetivo de profundizar en el uso de la metodología enfermera, y crear el hábito de la reflexión continua sobre la calidad de los cuidados que se aplican. Con este trabajo se pretende dar a conocer la experiencia desarrollada durante los años 2011-2012 en la realización de sesiones clínicas de cuidados. Durante el periodo estudiado se han desarrollado un total de 35 sesiones clínicas de este tipo, distribuidas en los centros asistenciales del complejo hospitalario, de las cuales 19 han sido casos clínicos, 12 actualizaciones en cuidados, tres revisiones de guías de práctica clínica y una revisión de proceso asistencial integrado. La media de asistencia a las sesiones ha sido de 16 profesionales por sesión. Los temas tratados incluyen situaciones de salud específicas de interés en las unidades asistenciales, la indagación en diagnósticos diferénciales y la incorporación de la evidencia científica. Como mejora se propone la incorporación de criterios para la evaluación del proceso enfermero y de la estructura de las sesiones clínicas de cuidados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;17(4): 55-60, mayo 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-124669</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sesiones clínicas de cuidados para profundizar en el pensamiento enfermero</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53794^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29050</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4577^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10881</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201405</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
