<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95561</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The management of pressure ulcers in nursing home care. Obstacles and facilitators</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and aims: the PU is a problem that adversely affects the quality of life among the elderly, contributing to morbidity and mortality in the institutionalized population.The heterogeneous reality of care and epidemiological variability of these injuries make it difficult to approach insocio-sanitary institutions. Knowing the management of pressure ulcers in nursing homes and obstacles to its proper management, raising strategies to optimize care. Method: literature review on the basis of national and internationaldata. Results: the adoption and implementation of best practice guidelines for prevention and treatment of PU offers a high variability. Obstacles are detected at the managerialand institutions, economic and material costs, training,staff attitudes and motivations, implementation andcare. Conclusions: the use of programs tailored to the centers, the continued commitment of the institution, comprehensive plans and multidimensional, interdisciplinary training and continuous assessment would be some recommendations for improving care for prevention and treatment of elderly patients with PU (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Palma, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vallejo Sánchez, Jesús Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos: las úlceras por presión (UPP)son un problema que repercute negativamente en la calidad de vida del anciano, contribuyendo a la morbilidad y mortalidad de la población institucionalizada. La heterogénea realidad de la asistencia y la variabilidad epidemiológica de estas lesiones dificultan su abordaje en las instituciones socio-sanitarias. Intentaremos conocer la gestión de las UPP en las residencias de mayores y los obstáculos que impiden su adecuado manejo, planteando estrategias para optimizar los cuidados. Método: revisión bibliográfica en bases de datos nacionales e internacionales. Resultados: la adopción e implementación de las mejores directrices de prevención y tratamiento de UPP ofrece una elevada variabilidad. Se detectan obstáculosa nivel de dirección e instituciones, costes económicos y materiales, formación, actitudes y motivaciones del personal, implantación y cuidados. Conclusiones: el uso de programas adaptados a los centros, el compromiso mantenido de la institución, planes globales y multidimensionales, formación interdisciplinar y evaluación continua serían algunas de las recomendaciones para la mejora de los cuidados de prevención y tratamiento de ancianos con UPP (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);21(3): 108-113, Sep. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95561</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La gestión de úlceras por presión en residencias de mayores. Obstáculos y facilitadores</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6863^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50219</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30212^s22019</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32818</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
