<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155628</identifier>
<setSpec>0365-6691</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Combined phacoemulsification and XEN45 surgery from a temporal approach and 2 incisions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the safety and effectiveness of phacoemulsification combined with XEN45 implant surgery in patients with cataract and open-angle glaucoma, with 12-month follow-up. Methods: A prospective study conducted on 30 eyes requiring phacoemulsification with, at least, 2 medications to control intraocular pressure (IOP). Phacoemulsification combined with XEN45 implant surgery was performed within 15minutes of administering subconjunctival mitomycin C. Surgery was performed through 2 temporal incisions, separated by 90°, using the inferior to enter the XEN45 and to implant it in the superior nasal region. A record was made of the best corrected visual acuity, IOP before and 1 day, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, and 12 months after surgery, the number of antiglaucomatous medications, and complications. Results: The best corrected visual acuity was 0.37±0.2 and 0.72±0.15 before and 12 months after surgery, respectively. The pre-operative IOP was 21.2±3.4mmHg, with 3.07 drugs, decreasing by 61.65% on the first day, 37.26% at 1 month, 35.05% at 3 months, 31% at 6 months, 30.6% at 9 months, and 29.34% at 12 months. The number of medications decreased by 94.57%. Complications occurred in 3 eyes, 2 of them were excluded because we could not complete the implantation (280° subconjunctival haemorrhage and XEN extrusion when trying to reposition). In a third case, the bleb was encapsulated at 5 months after surgery. Conclusions: The phacoemulsification combined with XEN45 implant surgery can effectively reduce IOP and the number of drugs in mild-moderate open-angle glaucoma, as they rehabilitate the VA. The use of only 2 micro-invasive incisions makes it simple, quick and safe, with few complications at 12 months follow-up from surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gargallo Benedicto, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Olate Pérez, Á</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Duch Samper, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreiro Rego, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cerdà Ibáñez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Torregrosa, VT</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Osorio Alayo, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar la eficacia y seguridad de la técnica combinada de facoemulsificación e implante XEN45 empleando acceso temporal y 2 únicas incisiones, en casos de catarata y glaucoma crónico de ángulo abierto, con seguimiento de 12 meses. Métodos: Estudio prospectivo de 30 ojos que requerían facoemulsificación y que precisaban, al menos, dos medicamentos para controlar presión intraocular (PIO). Se efectuó cirugía combinada de facoemulsificación e implante XEN45 a los 15 min de administrar mitomicina C subconjuntival. El procedimiento se realizó a través de 2 incisiones temporales, separadas por 90°, utilizando la inferior para introducir el XEN45 e implantarlo en región nasal superior. Se registró agudeza visual mejor corregida, PIO previa y en días 1-30-90-180-270 y 365 poscirugía, número de medicamentos hipotensores y complicaciones. Resultados: La agudeza visual mejor corregida preoperatoria fue 0,37±0,2 y 0,72±0,15 a los 12 meses. La PIO previa fue 21,2±3,4mmHg con 3,07 fármacos, descendiendo un 61,65% el primer día, 37,26% al mes, 35,05% al tercer mes, 31% al sexto mes, 30,6% al noveno mes y 29,34% a los 12 meses. El número de fármacos disminuyó un 94,57%. Solo hubo complicaciones destacables en 3 ojos, de ellos, 2 se excluyeron al no poder completar implantación (uno por hemorragia subconjuntival en 280° y otro, por extrusión del XEN al intentar recolocarlo). En un tercero, la ampolla se encapsuló a los 5 meses poscirugía. Conclusiones: La cirugía combinada de facoemulsificación e implante XEN45 reduce eficazmente la PIO y el número de medicamentos en el glaucoma crónico de ángulo abierto leve-moderado, al tiempo que rehabilita la AV. El empleo de solo 2 incisiones posibilita una cirugía microinvasiva sencilla, rápida y segura con escasas complicaciones tras 12 meses de seguimiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Soc Esp Oftalmol;91(9): 415-421, sept. 2016. ilus, tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155628</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cirugía combinada mediante facoemulsificación e implante XEN45 con acceso temporal y 2 únicas incisiones</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2431^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28204^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32250^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33880^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32652^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15187</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201609</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
