<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-159993</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ovarian vein thrombosis: Casuistry over 5 years and literature review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The ovarian vein thrombosis (OVT) is a rare but serious complication in the postpartum. It affects between 0.02% and 0.2% of all pregnancies, from 0.02% to 0.18% of vaginal deliveries and between 1% and 2% of caesarean sections. In up to 90% of cases it affects the right ovarian vein and it may extend as far as the inferior vena cava, causing serious complications. Early diagnosis and treatment are crucial. We present the cases of ovarian vein thrombosis having occurred in the postpartum period during the last 5 years in the Complejo Hospitalario de Pontevedra and a review of existing literature (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pardo Pumar, MI</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ouviña Millán, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cumbraos Alvarez, JM</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moral Santamarina, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rial, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La trombosis de la vena ovárica (TVO) es una complicación infrecuente pero grave en el posparto. Afecta entre el 0,02-0,2% del total de gestaciones, 0,02-0,18% de los partos vaginales, y entre el 1-2% de las cesáreas. Hasta en el 90% de los casos afecta a la vena ovárica derecha, y puede extenderse hasta la vena cava inferior originando complicaciones muy graves. El diagnóstico y tratamiento tempranos son fundamentales. Presentamos los casos de trombosis de la vena ovárica ocurridos en el puerperio durante los últimos 5 años en el Complejo Hospitalario de Pontevedra, y una revisión de la bibliografía existente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);44(1): 28-30, ene.-mar. 2017.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-159993</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trombosis de la vena ovárica: casuística en 5 años y revisión de la literatura</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d6625^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12080^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33768^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38861</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10230^s22040</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
