<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-148198</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-9728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Ego, Alter and Object: Explaining Personal Involvement with a Social Object Based on Perceived Collective Involvement and Group Identification</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The present paper aims at testing a model to predict personal involvement with a social object which was inspired by the social psychological triangle proposed by Moscovici. The triangle bridges three essential aspects of social psychology: the individual, the other and a social object. It was operationalized as an empirical model to explain personal involvement with a social topic from two predictors: perceived collective involvement of group members with the same topic and group identification. The sample was formed by 805 Brazilian undergraduates. The participants completed scales that measured their identification with university students, their perception of students&amp;#8223; involvement with two social objects, university course or job, and their own personal involvement with those topics. Regression analyses supported the hypothesis that group identification, perceived collective involvement and their interaction maintained positive relations with personal involvement. Discussion focuses on the relativity of results to specific objects, the complexity of determinant factors of personal involvement and the pertinence of the triangular look to characterize social psychological research (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Wachelke, Joao</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Natividade, Jean</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Wolter, Rafael</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Andrade, Alexsandro De</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El trabajo tiene como objetivo poner a prueba un modelo para predecir la implicación personal con un objeto social, inspirado en el triángulo de la psicología social propuesto por Moscovici. El triángulo une tres aspectos esenciales: el individuo, el Otro y un objeto social. Fue puesto en práctica como un modelo empírico para explicar la implicación personal de un tema social desde dos factores de predicción: la implicación colectiva percibida de los miembros del grupo con el mismo tema y la identificación con el grupo. La muestra fue formada por 805 estudiantes universitarios brasileños. Los participantes completaron escalas que medían su identificación con los estudiantes universitarios, su percepción de la implicación de los estudiantes con dos objetos sociales, curso universitario o trabajo, y su implicación personal con esos temas. Los análisis de regresión apoyan la hipótesis de que las dos variables y su interacción mantienen relaciones positivas con la implicación personal. La discusión se centra en la relatividad de los resultados a objetos específicos, la complejidad de los factores determinantes de la implicación personal y la pertinencia de la mirada triangular para caracterizar la investigación psicosociológica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An. psicol;32(1): 174-182, ene. 2016. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-148198</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ego, Alter y objeto: explicando la implicación personal con un objeto social basada en la participación colectiva percibida y la identificación con el grupo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6276</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54367^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23896</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37614</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4602</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6184</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201601</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
