<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134845</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-139X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adherence to pharmaceutical guidance in patients over 85 years of age with chronic heart failure-stage C. Effects on 12-month mortality</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe factors related to prescription on discharge of treatment for Chronic Heart Failure(CHF)-Stage C and to analyse whether this is related to 12month-mortality. Material and methods: Observational follow-up study of patients over 85 hospitalized during 2006/7 with Stage C-Chronic Heart Failure in an outskirt support hospital. Drug-prescription adherence was assessed according to the American Heart Society 2005-Guidelines and recommendations of the American Geriatrics Society-2007. A multivariate analysis of logistic regression was performed to obtain odds for 12-month mortality for each recommended therapy, adjusting by mortality risk factors. Results: 104 patients aged 90±3yr were followed on discharge, 85% of which were women. NYHA-classes were distributed NYHA I-28,2%, II-37,9%, III-30,1%, IV-3,9%. Most frequently prescribed drugs were loop diuretics (83,3%) and IACEs/ARB (62%), and the less frequent beta-blockers (19,1%). IACEs/ARB were prescribed to those with lower functional impairment (p=0.04), and beta-blockers to those with worse NYHA class (p=0.02). All recommended prescriptions had a tendency to 12 month mortality risk reduction, even adjusted by age, functional status, co-morbidity, NYHA class and co-morbid atrial fibrillation, except for spironolactone (OR-1,8; IC95% 0,48&#150;17,19). Conclusions: Treatment with CHF disease-modifying therapies except for spironolactone can reduce 12 month risk mortality, also in the oldest old. There exists room for improvement in frequency of drug prescription in this group of age (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Domínguez de Pablos, Gema</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Minaya Saiz, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esteve Arríen, Ainhoa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir factores relacionados con la prescripción farmacológica al alta hospitalaria de tratamiento para Insuficiencia Cardiaca (IC)-estadio C y analizar la relación entre dicho tratamiento y la incidencia de muerte al año. Material y Métodos: Estudio observacional prospectivo de pacientes mayores de 85 años ingresados en 2006 y 2007 con IC descompensada en un hospital de apoyo periurbano. La adecuación de la prescripción farmacológica se evaluó según las recomendaciones de la Sociedad Americana de Geriatría-2007 y American Heart Association-2005. Se realizó un análisis multivariante de regresión logística para objetivar el riesgo de mortalidad con los fármacos recomendados para tratar la IC estadío C ajustado por factores basales predictores de mortalidad. Resultados: Se siguieron 104 pacientes de 90±3 años, 85% mujeres con clase funcional basal NYHA I-28,2%, II-37,9%, III-30,1%, IV-3,9%. La fármacos más frecuentemente prescritos fueron diuréticos de asa (83,3%) e IECAs/ARA II (62%) y el menos frecuente beta-bloqueantes (19,1%). Se prescribieron más IECAs/ARAII a menor deterioro funcional (p=0.04), más Betabloqueantes a peor clase NYHA (p=0.02). Todos los fármacos estudiados presentaron una tendencia a reducir el riesgo de mortalidad al año ajustado por edad, situación funcional, comorbilidad, clase NYHA y presencia de fibrilación auricular, salvo la espironolactona (OR-1,8; IC95% 0,48&#150;17,19). Conclusiones: El tratamiento con fármacos moduladores de IC salvo la espironolactona puede reducir el riesgo de mortalidad al año en pacientes también mayores de 85 años, existiendo un margen de mejoría en la frecuencia de prescripción en este grupo de edad (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. geriatr. gerontol. (Ed. impr.);44(2): 90-93, mar. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134845</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Seguimiento de guías farmacoterapéuticas en mayores de 85 años con insuficiencia cardiaca estadio C. Efecto sobre la mortalidad al año</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28625</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33550^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32285</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14384</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200903</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
