<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109092</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Dysplasia in the development of the hip</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Developmental dysplasia of the hip (DDH) causes anatomical changes that cause early coxarthrosis. Although risf factors have been determined, the aetiology and physiopathology remains exactly unknown. Neonatal screening with physical examination and ultrasound have been stablished in order to diagnose this disease early in life. A diagnosis in the first months of life is essential as it enables a normal hip to form and prevent the appearance of early coxarthrosis. Treatment principles are to be able to reduce the hip without provoking avascular necrosis of the femoral head, and to normalize the acetabular development. Knowledge of the orthopaedic and surgical options is essential in order to achieve success in the treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gonzalez-Moran, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moraleda, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albiñana, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salcedo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La displasia del desarrollo de la cadera provoca cambios anatómicos que dan lugar a una coxartrosis precoz. La etiología y la patofisiología de la displasia de cadera no se conocen con exactitud, aunque se han determinado factores de riesgo. Se han establecido programas de despitaje neonatal clínicos y ecográficos que lleven a un diagnóstico precoz de esta afección. Un diagnóstico en los primeros meses de vida es fundamental porque permite obtener una cadera normal y evitar la aparición de una coxartrosis precoz. El tratamiento debe conseguir reducir la cadera, evitando la aparición de una necrosis avascular de la cabeza femoral, y normalizar el desarrollo del acetábulo. Existen opciones ortopédicas y quirúrgicas que deben ser conocidas para lograr un éxito en el tratamiento (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);57(1): 67-77, ene.-feb. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109092</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Displasia del desarrollo de la cadera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6775^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6775^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6775^s22061</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22878^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6775^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10162^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38340</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23791^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6775^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5369^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201302</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
