<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-044948</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Intervention programs in hospital nutrition: actions, design, components and implementation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Metabolic, Nutrient and Feeding Intervention Programs must become the methodological tool for dealing with the health problem posed by disease-associated-malnutrition on one side, and the "Bad Practices" affecting the nutritional status of the patient, on the other one. Programs like these ones should prescribe clear policies and actions in the three domains of contemporary medical practice: assistance, research and education. The fullfillment of these Program's objectives, and the relization of the implicit benefits, will only be possible if a methodological platform that armonically integrates elements of Continuous Education, Cost Analysis, Recording and Documentation, and Quality Control and Assurance, is created. The experience acumulated after the inception and conduction of the Intervention Program at the Clinical-Surgical "Hermanos Ameijeiras" Hospital (Havana City, Cuba) has served to demostrate that it is feasible not only to create a theoretical and practical body to satisfy the aforementioned goals, but, also, to export it to another institutions of the country, in view of the fact that minimal investments for adquiring the resources needed to deploy such Program, as well as for training and capacitation of medic and para-medic personel in the corresponding Recording &amp; Documentation and Feeding &amp; Nutrition Good Practices might result in short-term economical and medical care benefits (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Santana Porbén, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barreto Penié, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los Programas de Intervención Alimentaria, Nutrimental y Metabólica deben constituirse en la herramienta metodológica para el enfrentamiento del problema de salud que representa la desnutrición asociada a las enfermedades por un lado, y las "malas prácticas" atentatorias contra el estado nutricional del paciente, por el otro. Estos Programas deben prescribir políticas y acciones claras en los 3 dominios de la práctica médica contemporánea: asistencial, investigativa y educativa. El logro de los objetivos de tales Programas, y la realización de los beneficios implícitos, sólo será posible si se crea una plataforma metodológica que integre armónicamente elementos de Educación Continuada, Análisis de Costos, Documentación y Registros, y Control y Aseguramiento de la Calidad. La experiencia acumulada después de la implementación y conducción del Programa de Intervención en el Hospital Clínico-Quirúrgico "Hermanos Ameijeiras" (Ciudad Habana, Cuba) ha permitido demostrar que no sólo es posible crear el cuerpo teórico-práctico necesario para satisfacer los objetivos enunciados, sino que, además, puede ser extendido hacia otras instituciones de salud del país, por cuanto inversiones mínimas en la adquisición de la logística necesaria para echar a andar el Programa, así como para la capacitación y entrenamiento del personal médico y paramédico en las correspondientes Buenas Prácticas de Documentación &amp; Registros y de Alimentación &amp; Nutrición, pueden redundar rápidamente en beneficios asistenciales y económicos tangibles (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;20(5): 351-357, sept.-oct. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-044948</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Programas de intervención en nutrición hospitalaria: acciones, diseño, componentes, implementación</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5661^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6917^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3482</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6454</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28466</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32109</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12222</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9932</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3380</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200510</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
