<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-043507</identifier>
<setSpec>0304-5013</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Oral contraceptives and motor capabilities</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To identify variations in certain motor capabilities during the distinct phases of the menstrual cycle in relation to the use or nonuse of oral contraceptives. Subjects and method: The study included 22 sportswomen participating in the Cuban national preselections for handball and rhythmic gymnastics with an asymptomatic, regular menstrual cycle of 28 ± 2 days' duration. Results: Track speed was faster and explosive strength was greater in sportswomen using oral contraceptives than in nonusers. Aerobic power in the postmenstrual phase was also greater in sportswomen using oral contraceptives than that in nonusers but in other phases aerobic power was lower. Conclusions: There is an association between the use of oral contraceptives and sporting performance, which should be taken into account in training and competition. This association should be studied in relation to particular sporting activities, menstrual cycle phases, and individual characteristics</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Almenares-Pujadas, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Leal, E. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo-Miranda, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Se definen las variaciones de algunas capacidades motrices durante las fases del ciclo menstrual, estableciendo la relación con el uso o no de anticonceptivos orales. Sujetos y método: Se incluyen en el estudio las 22 deportistas de las preselecciones nacionales cubanas de balonmano y gimnasia rítmica que tenían un ciclo menstrual regular y asintomático, de 28 ± 2 días de duración. Resultados: Las deportistas que utilizan anticonceptivos tienen una velocidad de desplazamiento y fuerza explosiva superior a las otras deportistas, y su potencia aerobia en la fase posmenstrual es superior, pero en las otras fases es menor que en las que no los utilizan. Conclusiones: Existe relación entre el uso de anticonceptivos orales y el rendimiento deportivo, lo que se debe tener en cuenta para el entrenamiento y la competición. Se recomienda estudiar esta influencia según la especialidad deportiva, la fase del ciclo menstrual y las características individuales</dc:description>
<dc:source>Prog. obstet. ginecol. (Ed. impr.);49(1): 20-24, feb. 2006. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-043507</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anticonceptivos orales y capacidades motrices</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3295</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13562</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8766^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9241^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25369</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9236^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200602</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
