<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-155738</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4415</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Use of grafts in rotator cuff re-rupture</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. Rotator cuff re-ruptures appear in 38-65% of cases. In order to reduce this rate, many studies have been performed using different types of biomaterial for purely mechanical aims (re-inforce the suture) and/or biological agents (growth factor transporterts). The aim of this study is to review 22 cases treated with xenografts and analyse various current alternatives. Materials and methods. A descriptive and retrospective study was conducted using the variables of age, sex, laterality, time of surgery, involvement in MRI, number of anchors, and final mobility results on the Constant and the University of California Los Angeles (UCLA) validated scales. Results. The study included 22 patients, with a mean age of 51.7±4.6 years. A mean of 2 anchors were used and 13 patients were treated with a porcine intestinal submucosa implant, 6 with equine pericardium, and 3 with porcine dermis. Final results were: 37.6±13 points for the Constant test, and 16.9±3.9 points on the UCLA scale. The follow up was 36±10.2 months. Conclusions. In our experience, xenografts could provide good functional results and they would be a surgical alternative to tendon transfers in cases of massive tears. Further studies should be conducted with other biomaterials (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Navarro-Martínez, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Hidalgo, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos-Yubero, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Najarro-Cid, FJ</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zurera-Carmona, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Martín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. La rerrotura del manguito rotador aparece en un 38-65% de los casos. Con el fin de disminuir esta tasa se han realizado múltiples estudios que emplean diferentes tipos de biomateriales con fines puramente mecánicos (reforzar la sutura) o biológicos (transportadores de factores de crecimiento). Nuestro objetivo es revisar 22 casos tratados mediante xenoinjertos, así como analizar las diversas alternativas actuales. Material y método. Estudio observacional, descriptivo y retrospectivo donde consideramos edad, sexo, lateralidad, tiempos de intervención, afectación en RNM, número de anclajes empleados y resultados de movilidad final en las escalas de Constant y de la Universidad de California Los Ángeles (UCLA). Resultados. Se observó a 22 pacientes, con una edad media de 51,7±4,6 años, en los que utilizamos una media de 2 anclajes. De ellos, 13 pacientes fueron tratados con parches de submucosa intestinal porcina, 6 con pericardio equino y 3 con dermis porcina. Los resultados finales fueron de 37,6±13 puntos para el test de Constant frente a los 16,9±3,9 puntos para el test UCLA. Seguimiento de 36±10,2 meses. Conclusiones. En nuestra experiencia, los xenoinjertos proporcionan unos resultados funcionales aceptables para manguitos cuya sutura haya resultado ineficaz y son una alternativa a las transferencias tendinosas en casos de roturas masivas. Se precisan más estudios con otros tipos de biomateriales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. cir. ortop. traumatol. (Ed. impr.);60(5): 286-295, sept.-oct. 2016. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-155738</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Utilización de injertos en la reparación de rerroturas del manguito rotador</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1709^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33675^s22070</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1696^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23405^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13907^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
