<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134545</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Biases and adjustments in nutritional assessments from dietary questionnaires</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">In nutritional epidemiology, it is essential to use Food Consumption Assessment Methods that have been validated and accepted by the international community for estimating food consumption of individuals and populations. This assessment must be made with the highest quality possible so as to avoid, as far as possible, sources of error and confusion in the processes. The qualities that are required in a measurement method are validity and accuracy; validity being the main factor. Lack of validity produces biases, or systematic errors. These can reside in the process of subject selection, or processes of information gathering where the lack of accuracy produces random errors. For many nutrients, the intra-individual variances are due to many factors such as day-of-the-week or season, and could create problems in the data analyses. Adjustments are needed to minimize these effects. Confounding factors may over- or under-state the real magnitude of the observed association, or even alter the direction of the real association. Total energy intake can be a confounding variable when studying a relationship between nutrient intake and disease risk. To control for this effect several approximations are proposed such as nutrient densities, standard multivariate models and the nutrient residual model (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Arija, Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ramón, Josep Mª</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abellana, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ribot, Blanca</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">En la epidemiología nutricional es esencial la utilización de los Métodos Valoración del Consumo Alimentario validados y aceptados por la comunidad internacional para estimar el consumo alimentario de los individuos y grupos de población. Esta estimación debe hacerse con la mayor calidad posible, evitando, en la medida de lo posible, las fuentes de error y confusión en la medida del consumo alimentario. Las cualidades que otorgan calidad a un método de medida son la validez y la precisión, siendo la validez la principal característica. La falta de validez produce sesgos o errores sistemáticos, los cuales pueden ser en el proceso de selección de los sujetos o en el proceso de obtención de la información; y la falta de precisión produce errores aleatorios. Para muchos nutrientes, las variaciones intra-individuales debidas a muchos factores como el día de la semana o la estación del año, podrían crear problemas en los análisis de datos. Para minimizar este efecto se deben realizarse algunos ajustes en los análisis. Los factores de confusión pueden exagerar o subestimar la verdadera magnitud de la asociación o incluso alterar la dirección de la asociación. El consumo total de energía puede ser una variable de confusión en el estudio de la relación entre la ingesta de nutrientes y el riesgo de enfermedad. Para controlar este efecto se proponen varias aproximaciones: la densidad de nutrientes, modelo multivariado estándar y el modelo residual de nutrientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;31(supl.3): 113-118, mar. 2015. ilus, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134545</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Sesgos y ajustes en la valoración nutricional de las encuestas alimentarias</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28601</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24535</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9936^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
