<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-058955</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enamel defects, caries in primary dentition and fluoride sources: relationship with caries in permanent teeth</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To examine the relationship between the presence of enamel defects, dental caries in primary teeth, and exposure to various fluoride technologies and the presence of dental caries in permanent teeth in children with mixed dentition.                 Materials and methods: A cross-sectional study was conducted in 713 children aged 6-9 years old in 4 elementary schools in Campeche, Mexico through the use of a questionnaire for the mothers and an oral examination in the children. The dependent variable was the prevalence of caries in permanent dentition.                 Results: The mean number of decay, missing or filling teeth in primary dentition (dmft) and in permanent dentition (DMFT) was 2.48 (2.82) (deft &gt; 0 = 58.9%) and 0.40 (0.98) (DMFT &gt; 0 = 18.2%), respectively. The significant caries index (SiC), which is calculated in deciduous dentition, was 5.85 for 6 year-olds. Multivariate logistic regression adjusted for variables related to fluoride exposure revealed that older age (OR = 2.99), a deft of &gt; 0 (OR = 5.46), and lower maternal educational level (OR = 1.57) were significantly associated with a higher number of dental caries in permanent teeth. An interaction between sex and enamel defects was also found.                 Conclusions: The number of dental caries in both primary and permanent dentitions was relatively smaller than that found in prior studies performed in Mexican populations. The results confirm that the presence of caries in primary dentition is strongly associated with caries in permanent dentition. No significant relationship was found between fluoride exposure and dental caries in permanent dentition</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Medina-Solís, Carlo Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gerardo Maupomé, Gerardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ana Alicia Vallejos-Sánchez, Ana Alicia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Minaya-Sánchez, Mirna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova-Rosado, Juan Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casanova-Rosado, Alejandro José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Explorar la relación entre la presencia de defectos del esmalte (DE), la experiencia de caries en la dentición temporal, y la exposición a diversas fuentes de fluoruros, con la presencia de caries en la dentición permanente de niños con dentición mixta.                 Material y métodos: Se realizó un estudio transversal en 713 sujetos de 6-9 años de edad de 4 escuelas de Campeche, México, mediante un cuestionario dirigido a las madres, y un examen clínico bucal a los niños. La variable dependiente fue la prevalencia de caries en la dentición permanente.                 Resultados: El promedio de dientes temporales cariados, extraídos y obturados (ceod) y dientes permanentes cariados, perdidos y obturados (CPOD) fue de 2,48 (2,82) (ceod &gt; 0 = 58,9%) y 0,40 (0,98) (CPOD &gt; 0 = 18,2%), respectivamente. El índice SiC (índice de caries significativa, calculado en la dentición temporal) fue de 5,85 para los niños de 6 años de edad. En el análisis de regresión logística multivariado permanecieron significativas, después de ajustar por variables de exposición a fluoruros, la mayor edad (odds ratio [OR] = 2,99), el ceod &gt; 0 (OR = 5,46), la menor escolaridad de la madre (OR = 1,57) y una interacción entre sexo y defectos del esmalte.                 Conclusiones: Las caries en la dentición temporal y permanente fueron relativamente menores que las observaciones publicadas por otros estudios en México. Los resultados confirmaron que la caries en la dentición temporal se asoció fuertemente con la caries en la dentición permanente. No hubo una relación significativa entre las fuentes de fluoruro y la caries dental en la dentición permanente</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;21(3): 227-234, mayo 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-058955</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Defectos del esmalte, caries en dentición primaria, fuentes de fluoruro y su relación con caries en dientes permanentes</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28447^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14466^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27736</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14461^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3758^s22042</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3745^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3747^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200705</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
