<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-161543</identifier>
<setSpec>1695-4033</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Invasive meningococcal disease in Navarra in the era of a meningococcal C vaccine</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Systematic childhood vaccination against meningococcus C has had a considerable impact on meningococcal invasive disease (MID). The aim of this study is to perform an analysis on the epidemiology, the clinical features, and the factors associated with a worse prognosis of MID, in the era of a meningococcal C vaccine. Material and methods: The study included confirmed cases of MID in children less than 15 years of age in Navarra, Spain, between 2008 and 2014. The risk of death or permanent sequelae was evaluated according to the presence of clinical features and analytical parameters at diagnosis. Results: The average annual incidence was 7.9 cases per 100,000 children, with the highest attack rate in children &lt; 1 year. Of 53 cases analysed, 87% were due to meningococcus B. Fever (100%), rash (91%), and elevation of procalcitonin (94%) were the most frequent findings at diagnosis. Some sign of shock was observed in 70% upon arrival at the hospital. The casefatality rate was 3.8% and 10 % survived with permanent sequelae. Glasgow coma scale &lt; 15 (odds ratio [OR] = 9.2), seizure (OR = 8.3), sepsis without meningitis (OR = 9.1), thrombocytopenia (OR = 30.5), and disseminated intravascular coagulation (OR = 10.9) showed a greater association with a worse prognosis. Conclusion: The MID continues to be a significant cause of morbidity and mortality in children. Therefore, new advances are needed in the prevention, early diagnosis, and detection of the factors associated with poor prognosis (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herranz, Mercedes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bernaola, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Desirée</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castilla, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez-Baz, Iván</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La vacunación sistemática infantil frente al meningococo C ha tenido un impacto considerable en la enfermedad meningocócica invasiva (EMI). El objetivo de este estudio es analizar la epidemiología, las manifestaciones clínicas y los factores asociados a un peor pronóstico de la EMI en la era de la vacuna antimeningocócica C. Material y métodos: Se analizaron los casos de EMI confirmados en menores de 15 años diagnosticados en Navarra entre 2008 y 2014, y se evaluó el riesgo de muerte o secuelas permanentes, según la presencia de determinados hallazgos clínicos o analíticos al diagnóstico. Resultados: La incidencia media anual fue 7,9 casos por 100.000 niños, con mayor tasa de ataque en niños &lt; 1 año. De 53 casos analizados, el 87% fueron por meningococo B. Fiebre (100%), exantema (91%) y elevación de la procalcitonina (94%) fueron los hallazgos más frecuentes al diagnóstico. El 70% de los casos presentaba algún signo de shock a su llegada al hospital. La letalidad fue del 3,8% y un 10% sobrevivió con secuelas permanentes. Una puntuación en la escala de coma de Glasgow &lt; 15 (odds ratio [OR] = 9,2), convulsión (OR = 8,3), sepsis sin meningitis (OR = 9,1), trombocitopenia (OR = 30,5) y coagulación intravascular diseminada (OR = 10,9) se asociaron con un peor pronóstico. Conclusión: La EMI continúa causando una morbimortalidad importante en la población infantil, por lo que sigue siendo necesario avanzar en su prevención, en su diagnóstico temprano y en reconocer los factores asociados a mal pronóstico (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Pediatr (Barc);86(4): 213-219, abr. 2017. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-161543</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enfermedad meningocócica invasiva en Navarra en la era de la vacuna conjugada antimeningocócica C</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28418</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8759^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8755^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8759^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56009^s22038</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8759^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d56009^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24811</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8755^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
