<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-038840</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The SHORT method. Initial extrahospitalary triage when faced with multiple victims</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: We have developed the SHORT Method as an initial pre-hospitalary triage procedure for multiple-victim incidents (MVI) to be applied by non-sanitary personnel (firemen, police, etc.). The initial aim of this method has been to simplify and protocolise the initial rescue operations. Aims: Validation of the SHORT method and comparative study to the most frequently used severity scales in the discriminaton of the severest victims. Methods: The effectiveness of this method has been assessed through the implementation of MVI simulations and practical triage workshops, with a total of 214 clinical cases. Participants in the rescue operations were Fire Department and Rescue personnel and non-sanitary personnel of the Urgent Ambulance Service of the Basque Autonomous Community. The adequacy of the most frequently used severity scales as initial triage in MVI has been assessed. The parameters of such scales have been examined in the context of the most severe cases in MVI and compared to those of the SHORT method in terms of their ability to stratify severity. Results: The SHORT method has evidenced 91,8% sensitivity and 97% specificity in the discrimination of severe and less severe victims. The mean triage time per victim was 18 seconds (range 19; SD 0,25). In the comparative study, the SHORT method was as effective as the remainder of the scales examined. Conclusions: The SHORT method has been shown to be effective and quick in the discrimination of the more severe victims. The parameters expressed in this method allow characterisation of the victim&#146;s severity, as demonstrated by the sensitivity and specificity indices. Due to its simplicity, it is more adequate than the other scales examined for application by non-sanitary personnel (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Buzón Gutiérrez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso Giménez-Bretón, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Larrea Redín, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peláez Corres, M. N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gil Martín, F. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castelo Tarrio, I</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Hemos desarrollado el Método SHORT como triaje inicial prehospitalario ante incidentes con múltiples víctimas (IMV) para ser aplicado por personal no sanitario (bomberos, policía, etc.). El objetivo inicial de este método ha sido simplificar y protocolizar la labor inicial de rescate. Objetivo: Validación del Método SHORT y estudio comparativo con las escalas de gravedad más utilizadas en cuanto a discriminación de las víctimas más graves. Métodos: Se ha estudiado la eficacia de este método mediante la puesta en práctica de simulacros de IMV y talleres prácticos sobre triaje, con un total de 214 casos clínicos. En el rescate ha participado personal de extinción de incendios y salvamento y personal no sanitario de la Red de Transporte Sanitario Urgente de la Comunidad Autónoma Vasca (CAV). Se ha analizado la adecuación como primer triaje en IMV de las escalas de gravedad más utilizadas. Se han estudiado los parámetros de éstas en el contexto de los cuadros clínicos de mayor gravedad en IMV, y se han comparado, en cuanto a su capacidad para estratificar la gravedad, con los parámetros del método SHORT. Resultados: El método SHORT ha presentado una sensibilidad del 91,8% y una especificidad del 97%, en cuanto a la discriminación de víctimas graves frente al resto de víctimas. El tiempo medio de triaje por víctima ha sido de 18 segundos (rango: 19; desviación estándar: 0,25). En el estudio comparativo, el método SHORT resulta tan eficaz como el resto de escalas analizadas. Conclusiones: El método SHORT resulta eficaz y rápido para discriminar a las víctimas más graves. Es posible reflejar la gravedad de la víctima con los parámetros expresados en este método, hecho que se constata con los índices de eficacia como sensibilidad y especificidad. Debido a su sencillez de realización, resulta más adecuado que el resto de escalas estudiadas para practicarlo por personal de rescate no sanitario (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);17(4): 169-175, ago. 2005. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-038840</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Método SHORT. Primer triaje extrahospitalario ante múltiples víctimas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28838^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4250^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11812</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35148</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4707^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35146</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
