<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-128863</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Does medication abuse in patients with chronic migraine influence the effectiveness of preventive treatment with topiramate?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Patients with chronic migraine (CM) and medication abuse are difficult to treat, and have a greater tendency towards chronification and a poorer quality of life than those with other types of headache. Aim: To evaluate whether the presence of medication abuse lowers the effectiveness of topiramate. Patients and methods: A series of patients with CM were grouped according to whether they met abuse criteria or not. They were advised to stop taking the drug that they were abusing. Treatment was adjusted to match their crises and preventive treatment with topiramate was established from the beginning. The number of days with headache and intense migraine in the previous month and at four months of treatment was evaluated. Results. In all, 262 patients with CM criteria were selected and 167 (63.7%) of them fulfilled abuse criteria. In both groups there was a significant reduction in the number of days with headache/month and number of migraine attacks/month at the fourth month of treatment with topiramate. The percentage of reduction in the number of days with headache/ month in CM without abuse was 59.3} 36.1%, and with abuse, 48.7} 41.7% (p = 0.0574). The percentage of reduction in the number of days with intense migraine/month in CM without abuse was 61.2%, and with abuse, 50% (p = 0.0224). Response rate according to the number of days with headache/month in CM without abuse was 69%, and with abuse, 57%. Response rate according to the number of intense migraines/month in CM without abuse was 76.8%, and in CM with abuse, 61% (p = 0.0097). Conclusions. Topiramate was effective in patients with CM with and without medication abuse, although effectiveness is lower in the latter case (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Latorre Jimenez, Ana M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gracia Naya, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernando Quintana, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanchez Valiente, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Santos Lasaosa, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rios, Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Garcia Gomara, M Jose</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Artal Roy, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mauri Llerda, Jose Angel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Los pacientes con migraña crónica (MC) y abuso de medicación son difíciles de tratar y tienen peor calidad de vida que otros pacientes con migrañas. Objetivo. Valorar si la presencia de abuso de fármacos disminuye la efectividad del topiramato. Pacientes y métodos. Una serie de pacientes con MC fueron agrupados según presentasen criterios de abuso o no abuso de fármacos. Se les aconsejo la supresión del fármaco del cual abusaban. Se ajustó el tratamiento de sus crisis y se inició tratamiento preventivo desde el principio con topiramato. Se valoró el número días con cefalea y migrañas intensas en el mes previo y al cuarto mes de tratamiento. Resultados. Fueron seleccionados 262 pacientes con criterios de MC, y de ellos 167 (63,7%) cumplieron criterios de abuso. En ambos grupos hubo una reducción significativa del número de días con cefalea/mes y numero de crisis de migraña/mes al cuarto mes de tratamiento con topiramato. Porcentaje de reducción de días con cefalea/mes en MC sin abuso, 59,3} 36,1%; y con abuso, 48,7} 41,7% (p = 0,0574). Porcentaje de reducción de migrañas intensas/mes en MC sin abuso, 61,2%; y con abuso, 50% (p = 0,0224). Tasa de respondedores según numero de días con cefalea/mes en MC sin abuso, 69%; y con abuso, 57%. Tasa de respondedores según numero de migrañas intensas/mes en MC sin abuso, 76,8%; y en MC con abuso, 61% (p = 0,0097). Conclusiones. El topiramato fue efectivo en pacientes con MC sin y con abuso de fármacos, aunque con menor efectividad en estos últimos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;59(9): 385-391, nov. 2014. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-128863</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿El abuso de fármacos en pacientes con migraña crónica influye en la efectividad del tratamiento preventivo con topiramato?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34281^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d934^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50485^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9068^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11729^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201411</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
