<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-MFM2-10778</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Palliative care at the paediatric intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to understand the perceptions and needs of relatives and professionals regarding palliative care (PC) at the Paediatric Intensive Care Unit (PICU), and to identify any challenges and strategies for its implementation.  Method: a narrative review. A bibliographic search was conducted through the following databases: PudMed, Cuiden, Cochrane Library Plus, Cinahl, Scopus, Enfispo, Medes, Pesquisa and Proquest. The descriptors used were: palliative care (cuidados paliativos), nursing (Enfermería) and paediatric intensive care units (cuidados intensivos pediátricos). The inclusion criteria for article selection were: original articles and/or reviews, published between 2005 and 2015, written in English or Spanish.  Results: two hundred and thirty (230) articles were located; of these, 189 were eliminated by applying exclusion criteria and duplication. Only 25 of the 41 remaining articles provided information about the thematic categories of interest for the analysis: (1) perceptions and needs of relatives, (2) perceptions and needs of professionals, (3) challenges for integrating palliative care at the PICU, and (4) strategies for the application of palliative care at the PICU. Of the 25 articles included in the review, 79% were original and 21% were reviews.  Conclusions: the main challenges for the integration of PC at the PICU are the lack of training on PC and communication strategies among professionals. For a successful implementation of palliative care at the PICU, it is necessary to shift the philosophy of care towards a more humanized setting including emotional support for the healthcare staff. Strategies such as the family-focused model of care and the coordination with PC specialists will minimize the difficulties that might arise in the implementation of this type of care (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Galindo Maycas, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Abad Ruiz, M Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lorente Arnaiz, Sara</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: conocer las percepciones y necesidades tanto de la familia como de los profesionales sobre los cuidados paliativos (CP) en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Pediátricos (UCIP) e identificar dificultades y estrategias para su aplicación.  Método: revisión narrativa. Se llevó a cabo una búsqueda bibliográfica a través de las bases de datos: PudMed, Cuiden, Cochrane Library Plus, Cinahl, Scopus, Enfispo, Medes, Pesquisa y Proquest. Se usaron los siguientes descriptores: cuidados paliativos (palliative care), Enfermería (nursing) y cuidados intensivos pediátricos (pediatric intensive care units). Los criterios de inclusión para la selección de los artículos fueron: artículos originales y/o revisiones, publicados entre 2005-2015, escritos en inglés o español. Resultados: se localizaron 230 artículos, se eliminaron 189 aplicando criterios de exclusión y duplicidades. De los 41 artículos restantes, solo 25 aportaban información sobre las categorías temáticas de interés para el análisis: (1) percepciones y necesidades de las familias, (2) percepciones y necesidades de los profesionales, (3) dificultades para la integración de los cuidados paliativos en la UCIP, y (4) estrategias para la aplicación de los cuidados paliativos en UCIP. De los 25 documentos incluidos en la revisión, el 79% fue original, mientras que el 21% fue revisión.  Conclusiones: la falta de formación en CP y de estrategias comunicativas entre los profesionales son las principales dificultades de la integración de los CP en la UCIP. Para el éxito de la implantación de los cuidados paliativos en la UCIP es necesario un cambio de filosofía en la atención hacia un entorno más humanizado que incluya soporte emocional para el personal sanitario. Estrategias como el modelo de atención centrado en la familia y la coordinación con especialistas en CP minimizan las dificultades que puedan surgir en la implantación de estos cuidados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;20(9): 63-72, nov. 2017. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-MFM2-10778</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cuidados paliativos en la Unidad de Cuidados Intensivos Pediátricos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3439^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23699^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10353^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23699^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201711</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
