<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-122145</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-8046</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Using the taping in the clinical management of patients with sub-acromial impingement: a systematic review</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The sub-acromial impingement (SAI) is the most common musculoskeletal disorder of shoulder pathologies. In recent times, the taping has become a relatively new and quite common indication in recent years. There will be a synthesis of evidence through a systematic review (SR) of randomized trials that had compared the use of taping for the management of these patients. The aim of this review is to determine the effect of taping on pain in subjects with sub-acromial pinch. The research strategy included randomized clinical trials (RCTs) databases were used: Medline, Cinahl, PEDro, Central, LILACS. In addition, we searched electronic journals, conference proceedings, randomized trials registry and contacted experts in the field. The results were two articles that met our eligibility criteria. We conclude that there is low quality evidence suggesting that the application of taping, would be effective to improve functionality and reduce pain at rest and during movements up to 1 week after application, in subjects with sub-acromial pinch compared  to physical therapy program (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vargas Vargas, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pavez von Martens, G. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Carreño, L. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera Eguía, R. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cofré Bolados, C. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zafra Santos, E. O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Araya Quintanilla, F. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soto Aliaga, J. X</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Di Santo, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Espinoza Salinas, A. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aguilera Eguía, T</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El pinzamiento sub-acromial (SPS) es el trastorno músculo- esquelético más frecuente de las patologías de hombro. El taping se ha transformado en una indicación relativamente nueva y bastante común en los últimos años. Se realizará una síntesis de la evidencia a través de una revisión sistemática (RS) de ensayos clínicos aleatorizados que hayan comparado el uso del taping para el manejo de estos pacientes. El objetivo de esta revisión es determinar el efecto del taping sobre el dolor en sujetos con pellizcamiento sub-acromial. La estrategia de búsqueda incluyó ensayos clínicos aleatorizados (ECA); las bases de  datos usadas fueron: Medline, Cinahl, PEDro, Central, LILACS. Además, se realizó una búsqueda en revistas electrónicas, actas de congresos, Registro de Estudios Clínicos Aleatorizados y se contactó con expertos en el tema. Los resultados obtenidos fueron de dos artículos que cumplían con nuestros criterios de elegibilidad. Se concluye que existe evidencia de baja calidad que sugiere que la aplicación de taping sería efectiva para mejorar la funcionalidad, reducir el dolor en reposo y durante los movimientos hasta en una semana posterior a su aplicación, en  sujetos que presentan pellizcamiento sub-acromial en comparación a un programa de terapia física (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Dolor;21(1): 39-49, ene.-feb. 2014. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-122145</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Uso del taping en el manejo clínico de sujetos con pinzamiento sub-acromial: revisión sistemática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29834</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1480^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29507</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32937^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54277^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201402</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
