<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-116389</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Remission and functioning in major depressive disorder</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Evidence from numerous clinical studies has shown that the optimal goal for the treatment of depression is remission. Remission implies that the signs and symptoms of the disease are absent or virtually absent, which is typically associated with a return to the patient&#146;s previous daily functioning. Functioning in depression is a broad concept that covers different domains. There are many validated instruments for its assessment, these being reviewed in this article. Furthermore, recovering the pre-morbid level of functioning level is increasingly being identified as a significant target in addition to symptomatic remission. In this sense, functional recovery has been associated with better prognosis of depression and is also a clinical goal expressed by the patient. Several factors, like complete remission of symptoms, with no residual symptoms, maintenance of remission, quality of remission, early remission, have been identified as contributors to functional recovery. In order to facilitate the clinical outcomes, evaluation of and search for symptomatic remission as well as functional recovery need to be integrated into the clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Romera, Irene</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gilaberte, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perez, Víctor</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La evidencia procedente de numerosos estudios clínicos ha demostrado que el objetivo óptimo en el tratamiento de la depresión es la remisión. La remisión implicaría que los signos y síntomas de la enfermedad estén ausentes o prácticamente ausentes, lo cual se asocia típicamente con una vuelta a la funcionalidad diaria previa del paciente. La funcionalidad en depresión es un concepto amplio, que cubre diferentes dominios, existiendo numerosos instrumentos validados para su valoración que se revisan en este artículo. Asimismo, cada vez más se identifica que la recuperación de la funcionalidad al nivel pre-mórbido es un objetivo significativo adicional a la remisión sintomática. En este sentido, la recuperación de la funcionalidad se ha relacionado con un mejor pronóstico de la depresión, siendo también un objetivo clínico expresado por el paciente. Entre los factores contribuyentes a la recuperación funcional se encuentra la remisión completa de los síntomas, sin síntomas residuales, el mantenimiento de la remisión, calidad de la misma, así como que esta se produzca de una manera temprana. Con el fin de favorecer los resultados clínicos se hace necesaria la integración en la práctica clínica de la evaluación y búsqueda de no sólo la remisión sintomática sino también de la recuperación funcional (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;41(5): 263-268, sept.-oct. 2013. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-116389</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Remisión y funcionalidad en el trastorno depresivo mayor</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3885^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33888</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201310</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
