<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-95873</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-8621</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Abdominal aortic aneurysm treated by endovascular surgery. A case report</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">An aneurysm is an abnormal dilation or irreversible convex of a portion of an artery. The most common site of aneurysms is the abdominal aorta and their appearance is often due to degeneration of the arterial wall, associated with atherosclerosis and favored by risk factors such as smoking and hypertension, among others. Left untreated, aneurysm of the abdominal aorta usually leads to rupture. Treatment is surgical, consisting of the introduction of a prosthesis, composed basically of astent and an introducer, into the aorta. We report the case of a person diagnosed with abdominal aortic aneurysm in a routine examination who was admitted for ambulatory surgical treatment. We designed a nursing care plan, following Virginia Henderson&#146;s conceptual model. The careplan was divided into 2 parts, a first preoperative phase and a second post implantation or monitoring phase. The care plan contained the principal nursing diagnoses, based on the taxonomies of the North American Nursing Diagnosis Association (NANDA), nursing interventions classification (NIC) and nursing outcomes classifications (NOC), and collaboration problems/potential complications. The patient was discharged to home after contact was made with his reference nurse inthe primary health center, since during the hospital phase, some NOC indicators remained unresolved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Campo, M. E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Zarrabeitia, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cobo-Sánchez, J. L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calvo-Diez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alconero-Camarero, A. R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Casaus-Pérez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mirones-Valdeolivas, L. E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Un aneurisma es una dilatación anormal o abombamiento irreversible de una porción de una arteria. La aorta abdominal es el lugar donde con mayor frecuencia se desarrollan los aneurismas y su aparición suele ser debida a la degeneración de la pared arterial, relacionada con la arteriosclerosis y favorecida por factores de riesgo como el tabaquismo y la hipertensión arterial, entre otros. La evolución natural de un aneurisma de aorta abdominal no tratado es hacia la rotura. El tratamiento esquirúrgico, consistente en la introducción en la aorta de una prótesis cuyos componentes básicos son un stent y un introductor. El caso clínico que se presenta es el de un paciente diagnosticado de aneurisma de aorta abdominal en un examen de salud rutinario, que ingresa ambulatoriamente para la realización de este procedimiento quirúrgico. Para ello se elaboró un plan de cuidados, siguiendo el modelo conceptual de Virginia Henderson. El plan se dividió en 2 partes: una fase de ejecución o preoperatoria y otra de vigilancia o período postimplante. En él hemos usado la taxonomía NANDA, NOC y NIC, problemas interdependientes y complicaciones potenciales. El paciente fue dado de alta a su domicilio tras contactar con la enfermera de referencia en el centro de salud, ya que durante la fase hospitalaria quedaron pendientes de resolución algunos indicadores NOC propuestos (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm. clín. (Ed. impr.);18(2): 96-103, mar. 2008. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-95873</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paciente intervenido de aneurisma de aorta abdominal por técnica quirúrgica endovascular. Caso clínico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d15058</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30829^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4805</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200803</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
