<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-86587</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-9915</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Workplace bullying and health complaints: The moderating role of physiological activation</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Previous research has shown that workplace bullying is related to several negative outcomes. In this line of research, few studies have focused on possible moderators of the experience of bullying. The aim of the present study was to examine the moderating role of physiological activation, measured as systolic blood pressure, in the relationship between bullying and health problems. The sample was made up of 213 employees, who filled in a questionnaire about health and well being, and participated in a voluntary medical check-up that was carried out by an independent Occupational Health Service. Results revealed that physiological activation strengthened the relationship between bullying and health problems, so that those with high levels of blood pressure reported more health complaints in bullying situations. These results are in line with the allostatic load theory (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alfredo Rodríguez Muñoz, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno, Ynomig</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sanz Vergel, Ana Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Moreno Jiménez, Bernardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación sobre acoso psicológico en el trabajo ha mostrado que este fenómeno se encuentra relacionado con distintas consecuencias negativas. En este campo de investigación, son escasos los estudios que incluyan variables moderadoras en sus diseños. El objetivo del presente estudio consiste en analizar el posible papel moderador de la activación fisiológica, medida como presión sistólica, en la relación entre el acoso psicológico en el trabajo y los problemas de salud. La muestra estuvo compuesta por 213 trabajadores, que cumplimentaron un cuestionario sobre factores psicosociales y salud, y participaron en un reconocimiento médico voluntario llevado a cabo por una mutua externa. Los resultados de los análisis de regresión múltiple jerárquica mostraron que la activación fi siológica fortalece la relación entre acoso y los problemas de salud, puesto que aquellas personas con altos niveles de presión arterial presentaban mayores problemas de salud en situaciones de acoso psicológico. Estos datos concuerdan con los planteamientos del modelo de carga alostática (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Psicothema (Oviedo);23(2): 227-232, abr.-jun. 2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-86587</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Acoso psicológico en el trabajo y problemas de salud: el papel moderador de la activación fisiológica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30511^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12027^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34724</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15335^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d231^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52463^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16054^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13299</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201106</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
