<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74996</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-1406</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Candida albicans outbreak in a neonatal intensive care unit</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The appearance of Candida albicans in three patients made physiciansinvestigate an outbreak. Outbreak description and microbiologic screening:Case 1 developed C. albicans in the placenta culture and in the blood culturecarried out on the 8th day of birth. Four days after this candidemia, C. albicanswas recovered in a catheter tip of a second neonate (case 2) and finally fivedays later other newborn (case 3) developed C. albicans in the hemoculture.After that, the hands of all caregivers as well as case 3&#146;s incubator, case 1&#146;smother, and from all nine neonates in the unit were studied with swabs. A wetmount was done to all swabs and then they were cultured in ChromagarCandida and SDA. All C. albicans were studied by RAPD. RAPD study showedthat C. albicans recovered from placenta and blood cultures of case 1, thecatheter tip of case 2 and the blood culture of case 3, resulted to be identicaland these yeasts were related to the C. albicans from the mouth of case 1mother and the mouth of another colonized newborn. C. albicans was notfound in the others swabs. The isolations of identical C. albicans allowed tosuppose the horizontal transmission from the case 1, that had acquired itcongenitally. Not only isolation of unusual Candida species would be an alert.Despite patients&#146; personal factors to justify a fungal infection, the recovery ofC. albicans in a short period of time should warn physicians about thepossibility of a horizontal transmission(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Tiraboschi, Iris Nora</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Foccoli, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carnovale, Susana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Kurlat, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, Norma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Benetucci, Ariana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lasala, María Beatriz</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El aislamiento de Candida albicans en tres pacientes (dos en hemocultivos)sugirió la existencia de un brote epidémico. En el caso 1 se aisló C. albicans dela placenta de la madre, así como de una muestra de sangre del recién nacidotomada a los ocho días de vida. Cuatro días después del diagnóstico de estacandidemia, se aisla C. albicans en la punta del catéter de otro neonato (caso 2),y cinco días después en los hemocultivos de un tercer neonato (caso 3). Antela sospecha de un brote epidémico, se investigó la existencia de colonización.Se tomaron mediante hisopo muestras de las manos del personal, la cuna delcaso 3, la madre del caso 1 y los nueve neonatos internados. Cada hisopo sesembró en Chromagar Candida® y agar glucosado de Sabouraud.Los aislamientos de C. albicans recuperados fueron estudiados por RAPD.El estudio por RAPD mostró que los aislamientos de C. albicans de la placenta,los de los hemocultivos de los casos 1 y 3, y el de la punta de catéter del caso2 eran genotípicamente idénticos. Se aisló C. albicans de otros dos neonatos(boca e ingle en uno e ingle en el otro) y de la boca de la madre del caso 1.Esta última cepa y la de la boca del neonato colonizado estarían genéticamenterelacionadas con la de los casos mencionados. No se aisló C. albicans delresto de los hisopos. Los aislamientos de C. albicans idénticos permitieronsuponer la trasmisión horizontal a partir del caso 1, quien la había adquiridocongénitamente. Aunque los pacientes tengan factores de riesgo quejustifiquen una infección por Candida, el aislamiento de C. albicans en variasmuestras en un tiempo corto, debe hacer sospechar la posibilidad de latrasmisión horizontal de la infección(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Iberoam Micol;24(4): 263-267, 2007. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74996</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de candidemia por Candida albicans en neonatología</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2208^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2209^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11353^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
