<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96598</identifier>
<setSpec>0033-8338</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Multislice CT in a diagnostic imaging department: radiation doses delivered in 1 year</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective To determine the usage of CT in our diagnostic imaging department and the dose of radiation CT delivered to patients. Material and methodsWe carried out two studies, a retrospective study on the administrative data from one year and a prospective study over one month, to determine the amount of activity of the two multislice CT scanners in our department. We recorded the total number of examinations, the different types of examination performed, and the age distributions of the patients examined. We used these data and the results of dosimetric measurements to estimate the typical radiation dose for each type of examination, its contribution to the collective radiation dose, and the total collective radiation dose from CT examinations at our hospital. ResultsThe retrospective study found that 15038 examinations were performed in 12678 patients in one year. The most common CT examinations were cranial (38.2%), abdomen-pelvis (17.5%), chest-abdomen (11.7%), chest (9.3%), and lumbar-sacral spine (6.8%). Some protocols used doses of radiation that were higher than those recommended by European experts. The total collective dose of radiation delivered to patients at our hospital by CT was estimated at 70 person.Sv. Abdomen-pelvis examinations contributed 31% of the total dose. ConclusionsThis study has provided detailed knowledge about the use of CT in our diagnostic imaging department, about the dose of radiation delivered, and about possibilities for improving the use of our CT scanners (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fraile, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Calzado, Alfonso</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cordeiro, César</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salmerón, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-López, Laura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alonso, Verónica</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo Conocer detalladamente los exámenes de tomografía computarizada (TC) realizados en un servicio de radiodiagnóstico y su contribución a las dosis de radiación recibidas por los pacientes. Material y métodos Se han llevado a cabo 2 estudios, uno retrospectivo de 1 año sobre los datos administrativos y otro prospectivo de 1 mes para conocer la actividad de los 2 equipos de TC multicorte del servicio, y obtener el número total de exámenes, las distribuciones de edad de los pacientes y las frecuencias de los distintos tipos de exploración. Con esos datos y los resultados de medidas dosimétricas se han estimado los valores de dosis típicos para cada tipo de examen, su contribución a la dosis colectiva y la dosis colectiva total debida a los exámenes de TC del hospital. Resultados Se efectuaron un total de 15.038 exploraciones a 12.678 pacientes en el año del estudio retrospectivo. Los tipos de exploración más frecuentes son las de cráneo (38,2%), abdomen-pelvis (17,5%), tórax-abdomen (11,7%), tórax (9,3%) y columna lumbosacra (6,8%). Hay protocolos que presentan valores de los índices de dosis superiores a los de referencia propuestos por expertos europeos. La dosis colectiva total de los exámenes de TC del hospital se ha estimado en 70 persona.Sv. Los exámenes de abdomen-pelvis contribuyen con el 31% del total. Conclusiones Este trabajo ha servido para conocer con detalle la práctica con TC en un servicio de radiodiagnóstico, las posibilidades de mejora en el uso de los equipos y para estimar las dosis de radiación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Radiología (Madr., Ed. impr.);51(2): 163-170, mar.-abr. 2009. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96598</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tomografía computarizada multicorte en un servicio de radiodiagnóstico: estudio de las dosis impartidas durante 1 año</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4367</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12314^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
