<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101251</identifier>
<setSpec>1886-6581</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of maturity and specific playing positions on physical fitness in young soccer players</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To describe the physical fitness of a young athlete population grouped in two categories: maturity and specific positions. Sample: We studied 95 players (13-16 years) belonging to soccer schools. Methods: The variables used in this study were age, the specific position (center, defense, forward, goalkeeper), weight, height, maturity, the aerobic capacity, the maximum isometric strength of the upper arms, the maximum force, the explosive force and elastic-explosive of the lower body, speed in 30m (time), the rate of change of direction and agility and trunk flexibility. Results: Significant differences were found between normal and delayed maturity groups in: linear velocity, static force, maximum isometric force (right) and production of maximum rate of force. The same results and also significant differences in the variable flexibility were observed between delayed and advanced maturity groups. Significant differences were found between specific position (midfielders and forwards) in the static force variable. Conclusions: (i) Advanced players (in maturity) scored better in physical fitness, (ii) the physical fitness evaluation at these ages does not appear to be appropriate to select soccer players, (iii) it seems important to include specific training for each position, (iv) it seems important to give more attention to goalkeeper training(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Soarez, Helena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barrigas, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fragoso, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Massuça, Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Describir las características condicionales de una población de deportistas jóvenes, tanto por nivel madurativo como por puestos específicos. Muestra: Se han estudiado 95 jugadores de fútbol (13-16 años) pertenecientes a escuelas deportivas de futbol. Métodos: Las variables utilizadas en este estudio han sido: edad, puesto específico (medio, defesa, delantero, portero), peso, altura, maduración, capacidad aeróbica, fuerza isométrica máxima del tren superior, fuerza máxima, fuerza explosiva y elástico-explosiva del tren inferior, velocidad linear 30m (tiempo), velocidad de cambio de dirección, y agilidad y flexibilidad del tronco. Resultados: Se han encontrado diferencias significativas entre los grupos de maduración retrasado y normal en las variables velocidad linear, fuerza estática, fuerza isométrica máxima derecha y tasa máxima de producción de fuerza. Entre los grupos de maduración retrasado y avanzado se han encontrado los mismos resultados y diferencias significativas en la variable flexibilidad. En la valoración por puestos específicos se han encontrado diferencias significativas en la fuerza estática de los medios y de los delanteros. Conclusiones: a) Los jugadores con maduración avanzada presentan mejores valores condicionales; b) las pruebas condicionales, en estos rangos de edad, no parecen ser determinantes para poder realizar la selección de jugadores; c) se hace necesario incluir entrenamientos específicos para cada puesto, y d) el portero necesita una mayor atención en su entrenamiento(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Apunts, Med. esport (Internet);47(174): 73-81, abr.-jun. 2012. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101251</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Impacto de la maduración y de los puestos específicos en la condición física en jóvenes futbolistas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13298^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27892^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52421^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55404^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
