<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114891</identifier>
<setSpec>0377-4732</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Explosive homicidal behavior in a case with alterations in the electroencephalogram</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Epilepsy is characterized by the onset of various types of crisis which are accompanied by specific alterations in EEG as paroxysmal outbreaks. Registration may be normal during intercritical periods. Sometimes, alterations in response to specific activation mechanisms can be evidenced. Diagnosis of the non-convulsive crises can be difficult to establish. In some types of epilepsy, especially in that of the temporal lobe, aggressive behaviors during the crises have been described. We present the case of a 20 year-old male, a murderer with no previous deviant behavior, who displayed an explosive violent behavior. His particular experience of the events led to the suspicion of the existence of organicism. EEG showed an alteration compatible with epilepsy that might explain the onset of the aggressive conduct (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín-Martín, JUlio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vicente-González, Secundino</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cano-Rosás, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Noriega de Castro, Julián</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Salvat-Puig, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La epilepsia se caracteriza por la aparición de diversos tipos de crisis que se acompañan de alteraciones específicas en el EEG en forma de brotes paroxísticos. Durante los periodos intercríticos el registro puede ser normal. En ocasiones, pueden evidenciarse alteraciones en respuesta a mecanismos de activación específicos. El diagnóstico de las crisis no convulsivas puede ser difícil de establecer. En algunos tipos de epilepsia, especialmente en la del lóbulo temporal, se han descrito conductas agresivas durante las crisis. Exponemos el caso de un homicida, varón de 20 años, sin antecedentes de conductas conflictivas, que presentó una conducta violenta explosiva que junto con su especial vivencia de los hechos llevó a la sospecha de la existencia de organicidad. El EEG evidenció una alteración compatible con epilepsia que podría explicar la aparición de la conducta agresiva (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. med. legal;39(2): 74-77, abr.-jun.2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114891</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Conducta explosiva homicida en un caso con alteraciones en el electroencefalograma</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33525^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54306^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4641^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54306^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d378^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6864^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d54306^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6864^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1545^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15158^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
