<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96214</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6627</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Nursing registers on sleep and patient perception in a psychiatric unit. A comparative study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. Insomnia is a frequent problem in people who suffer from mental illnesses. The nursing staff control and register whether or not patients sleep. The aim of this article is to analyze the concordance between the perceptions of the patients of a psychiatric unit on the quality of sleep, and the notes in this respect contained in the nursing records. Methods. A comparative study between the answers given by the patients of our unit to 126 questions on insomnia on specific nights, and what was reflected in their nursing records. A reduced version of the Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS-5) was used. Results. The average value obtained according to the patients&#146; answers was higher (worse sleep) than that given by the nurses, both globally and by item. The nursing records showed much lower values than those given by the patient; Pearson&#146;s correlation analysis gave a coefficient of 0.26. Analysis of the degree of agreement provided an index of 0.13 that does not differ significantly from nil agreement. Conclusions. There is a difference between the nursing observations and the subjective sensations of the patients about how they sleep. They indicate that they sleep worse than the nursing records reflect. External observation and self-perception are not antagonistic aspects, but two complementary aspects of patients &#145;sleep (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gárriz, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Antomás, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Huarte, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento. El insomnio es un problema frecuente en las personas que sufren enfermedades mentales. El personal de enfermería controla y registra si los pacientes duermen o no. El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar la concordancia entre las percepciones de los pacientes de una unidad psiquiátrica de agudos sobre la calidad de su sueño y las notas recogidas en el evolutivo de enfermería al respecto. Material y métodos. Estudio comparativo entre las respuestas dadas por pacientes de nuestra unidad a 126 cuestionarios sobre insomnio en noches concretas y lo reflejado en sus historias de enfermería. Se utilizó una versión reducida de la Escala Atenas de Insomnio (EAI-5) Resultados. El valor medio obtenido según las respuestas de los pacientes es superior (peor sueño) al dado por las enfermeras, tanto de manera global como por ítem. La historia de enfermería refleja valores mucho más bajos que los otorgados por el paciente, el análisis de correlación de Pearson proporcionó un coeficiente de 0,26. El análisis de grado de acuerdo proporcionó un ICC de 0,13 y no difiere de manera significativa al acuerdo nulo. Conclusiones. Hay discordancia entre las observaciones de enfermería y las sensaciones subjetivas de los pacientes sobre cómo duermen. Refieren dormir peor de lo que refleja la historia de enfermería. La observación externa y la autopercepción no son aspectos antagónicos, sino dos aspectos complementarios del sueño de los pacientes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>An Sist Sanit Navar;34(3): 373-381, sept.-dic. 2011. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96214</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Registros de enfermería sobre el sueño y percepción de los pacientes en una unidad psiquiátrica. Estudio comparativo</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28202^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24807</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13275^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28627</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201112</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
