<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-87436</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Iatrogenic pressure ulcers of nasal location</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: One of the risks of using endonasal tubes (ET) is the developmentof pressure ulcers (PU). Aim: to find out the incidence of patients with nasal PU,study the risks factors for its development and find the predictable variables.Methods: a twelve-month observational and prospective study was carried out incritically ill patients carrying a ET admitted to our intensive care unit. Conclusion:time of stay and time spent carrying the ET, along with the anaemia, is statisticallyassociated with the development of nasal PU. The multivariate studyshowed that the time spent carrying the ET is the most influential variable in thedevelopmente of nasal PU  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Costa, Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guzmán Ucha, M. del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez Fernández,  Consuelo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cores Fresco, Rita M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Esperón Güimil, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Camiña, M. del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vilas Pastoriza, M. Dolores</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piñeiro Dios, M. José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: Uno de los riesgos del uso de sondas endonasales (SE) es la apariciónde úlceras por presión (UPP). Objetivo: Averiguar la incidencia de pacientescon UPP nasales, estudiar factores de riesgo de aparición y encontrarvariables predictivas. Metodología: Estudio de doce meses, observacional prospectivo,realizado en pacientes ingresados en la unidad de cuidados intensivosportadores de SE. Conclusiones: Los tiempos de estancia y de permanenciacon la SE, además de la anemia, se asocian estadísticamente con la apariciónde UPP. Tras el estudio multivariante, el tiempo que el paciente permanececon SE es la variable que influye en que aparezcan las UPP nasales (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);21(2): 29-36, mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-87436</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Úlceras por presión iatrogénicas de localización nasal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3681^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28201^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
