<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052100</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-0010</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tumour induction by ethylnitrosourea in the central nervous system</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction. Experimental central nervous system (CNS) tumours have been proposed as a useful model for thestudy of oncogenesis, epiphenomena related to cancer and for the design of new therapeutic strategies. Development. Theadministration of chemical substances is one of the most commonly-used methods to induce CNS neoplasms. N-ethyl-Nnitrosourea(ENU) belongs to the nitrosourea family, a wide group of alkylating agents that are able to induce brain tumoursin litters after transplacentary administration at the 15th day of pregnancy. This nitrogenous urea compound has a highmutation inducibility affecting the expression of oncogenes such as p53, neu/erbB-2 and Ras. Prenatal exposition of SpragueDawley rats to ENU induces intra-axial tumours of glial lineage and extra-axial malignant schwannomas. Although theprecise mechanism of tumour induction is unclear, it is known to affect cell differentiation of primitive neuroepithelium fromthe subventricular plate generating oligodendrogliomas, astrocytomas, mixed gliomas or ependimomas. Conclusion. The transplacentaryadministration of ENU induces the development of gliomas and schwannomas that are similar to those found inhumans. Animal models are necessary and useful for further studies to get an early diagnosis and to establish correcttherapeutic indications</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ullibarri-Ortiz de Zárate, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lafuente-Sánchez, J. V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bulnes-Sesma, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. La utilización de modelos experimentalesin vivo de tumores en el sistema nerviosos central (SNC) ha traídoimportantes avances a la neurooncología. Estos modelos animaleshan permitido el estudio de procesos de oncogénesis, de sus epifenómenosy del diseño de nuevas estrategias terapéuticas. Desarrollo.Existen varios métodos de inducción de neoplasias en el SNC,de los cuales la administración de sustancias químicas es una delas modalidades más utilizadas. La N-etil-N-nitrosourea (ENU) esun agente alquilante capaz de inducir tumores cerebrales en la descendenciade ratas gestantes tras su administración transplacentaria.Se tata de un compuesto nitrogenado de la urea con alto podermutagénico que afecta a la expresión de ciertos oncogenes comop53, neu/erbB-2 y Ras. Mediante la exposición prenatal a ratasSprague Dawley del carcinógeno ENU se inducen tumores intraaxialesde estirpe glial y tumores extraaxiales como los schwannomasmalignos. Aunque se desconoce el mecanismo preciso de inducciónde los tumores gliales, se sabe que afecta a la diferenciaciónde las células neuroepiteliales primitivas de la placa subventricular,lo que genera oligodendrogliomas, astrocitomas, gliomasmixtos o ependimomas. Conclusión. La administración transplacentariade ENU permite obtener gliomas y schwannomas malignossimilares a los encontrados en los humanos. Esto puede ayudaral estudio en profundidad de dichos tumores para llegar a realizarun diagnóstico precoz y asentar unas indicaciones terapéuticasprecisas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Neurol;43(12): 733-738, dic. 2006. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052100</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Inducción de tumores en el sistema nervioso central mediante etilnitrosourea</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11733</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9567^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30579</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2316^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4886^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9567^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2316^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19154</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d479^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d479^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29056^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30202^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30202^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6053^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10022^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9556^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1262^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9635^s22036</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10040^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35411</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5130^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5130^s22000</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
