<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134465</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-005X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of ceftaroline in skin and soft tissue infections</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Skin and soft tissue infections (SSTI) are relatively common. Although most of these infections are mild, a few are severe, requiring hospital admission for intravenous antimicrobial therapy and, fairly frequently, surgery. These infections can be produced by any microorganism, but the most frequent is Staphylococcus aureus. Traditionally, the bacteria causing community-acquired SSTI have been sensitive to antimicrobial agents but this situation has changed with the dissemination of community-acquired microbial resistance, as has occurred in many countries with the increase in methicillin-resistant S. aureus (MRSA). These changes complicate empirical therapy and increase the risk of monotherapy being insufficient to cover all the diagnostic possibilities of SSTI. Within this epidemiological framework, ceftaroline, because of its activity against MRSA, can be used as empirical monotherapy for SSTI (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cisneros, José Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barberán, José</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las infecciones de piel y partes blandas (IPPB) son relativamente comunes. La mayoría suelen ser leves, pero ocasionalmente pueden ser graves, por lo que requieren ingreso en el hospital para tratamiento antimicrobiano intravenoso y, con relativa frecuencia, quirúrgico. Cualquier microorganismo puede producir estas infecciones, pero Staphylococcus aureus es el más frecuente. Tradicionalmente, las bacterias causantes de las IPPB adquiridas en la comunidad han sido sensibles a los antimicrobianos, pero esta situación ha cambiado con la diseminación de las resistencias microbianas a la comunidad, como ha ocurrido en muchos países con el incremento de S. aureusresistente a meticilina (SARM). Estos cambios hacen más difícil el tratamiento empírico y aumentan el riesgo de que la monoterapia sea insuficiente para cubrir todas las posibilidades diagnósticas de las IPPB. En ese marco epidemiológico, ceftarolina, por su actividad frente a SARM, permite realizar el tratamiento empírico de las IPPB con monoterapia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Enferm Infecc Microbiol Clin;32(supl.2): 27-31, mar. 2014. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134465</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de ceftarolina en infecciones de piel y partes blandas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32025^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53002^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d911^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2547^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19542^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201403</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
