<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-83186</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic radical cystectomy. Where do we stand?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Laparoscopic Radical Cystectomy (LRC) has been proposed since 1999 as a less invasive alter-native to Open Radical Cystectomy (ORC). Pioneers of the technique claim that LRC led to faster recovery, shorter hospital stay and more rapid return to daily activities respect to ORC while offering the same functional and oncological results.About 900 cases are published in peer reviewed papers. The greatest series is formed by a cohort of 85 patients. The preferred urinary diversion is the ileal conduit (46%) although in recent series the ileal neobladder is increa-singly adopted. Urinary diversion is usually performed extracorporeally through an abdomen incision of about 5&#150;10 used also for the extraction of the specimen.The mean or median follow up of LRC series does not exceed 31 months and the longest follow up reported up to now is 58 months in the series examined. Overall survival rate varies from 72% to 95%.While feasibility of LRC has been demonstrated, cancer control has far from been assured, mainly in consequen-ce of limited follow-up of the series and an unexpected low disease free survival rate. Moreover the advocated advantages related to LRC seem to be related to pa-tients&#146; selection rather than to less invasiveness. Actually when characteristics of the patient and of the disease are similar, outcomes of LRC and ORC, in terms of hos-pitalization and recovery, are comparable.LRC is currently an experimental procedure which can not be considered at the present time a concrete alter-native to ORC(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Puppo, Paolo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Naselli, Angelo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La Cistectomía Radical Laparoscópica (CRL) ha sido propuesta desde 1999 como una alternativa menos invasiva de la Cistectomía Radical Abierta (CRA). Los pioneros en esta técnica reclaman que la CRL tiene una recuperación más rápida, estancias hospitalarias más cortas y un retorno a las actividades diarias más rápido en comparación con la CRA a la vez que ofrece a los mismos resultados funcionales y oncológicos.Se han publicado unos 900 casos en revistas con sistemas de revisión por pares. La serie más larga está formada por una cohorte de 85 pacientes. La derivación urinaria preferida es el conducto ileal (46%) aunque en series recientes la adopción de la neovejiga ileal está aumentando. La derivación urinaria se realiza normalmente extracorpórea a través de la incisión abdominal de unos 5-10 cm utilizada también para extracción de la pieza.La media o mediana de seguimiento de las series de CRL no supera los 31 meses y hasta ahora el seguimiento más largo comunicado en las series examinadas es de 58 meses. La tasa de supervivencia global varía entre 72% y 95%.Aunque la viabilidad de la CRL ha sido demostrada, está lejos de haber demostrado el control oncológico, principalmente como consecuencia del seguimiento limitado en las series y de una inesperada baja tasa de supervivencia libre de enfermedad. Además, las ventajas defendidas de la CRL parecen estar más relacionadas con la selección del paciente que con una menor invasión. Realmente cuando las características del paciente y de la enfermedad son similares, los resultados de la CRL y la CRA en términos de hospitalización y de recuperación son comparables.La CRL es realmente un procedimiento experimental que no puede ser considerada como una alternativa(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(7): 508-519, sept. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-83186</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Cistectomía radical laparoscópica. ¿Dónde estamos?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24595^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14947^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1770^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201009</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
