<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-99331</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Erectile Dysfunction and Its Severity Are Related to the Number of Cardiovascular Risk Factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim: Erectile dysfunction (ED) is a very common condition in the general population. ED isclosely related to Hypertension (HT), Diabetes Mellitus (DM), Dyslipidemia (DLP) and Metabolic Syndrome (MS). This study has aimed to clarify whether the presence and severity of ED are related to the presence and number of cardiovascular risk factors (CVRF). Material and methods: We retrospectively analyzed the characteristics of 242 males referred to our center for a prostate biopsy from September 2007 to December 2009. The following variables were collected prospectively: age, height, weight, body mass index (BMI), AHT, DM, DLP and obesity (BMI &lt; 30 kg/m2). The Erection Hardness Score Questionnaire was used to assess erectile function. We analyzed the relation between the presence and severity of ED and the presence of HT, DM, DLP and obesity. We analyzed the clinical variables based on the presence or absence of ED and in relationship to its severity. Results: The presence of ED was related to HT (OR: 1.805 [1.128-2.887]; p = 0.013), DM (OR3.585 [1.613-7.966]; p = 0.001) and Dyslipidemia (OR: 1.928 [1.062-3.500]; p = 0.029). Erectile function was not related to Obesity (OR: 0.929 [0.522-1.632]; p = 0.795). Patients with ED were more likely to have more CVRF (p = 0.009) and the severity of ED was related to the presence of HT (p &lt; 0.001), DM (p &lt; 0.001), DLP (p = 0.001) and the number of CVRF (p &lt; 0.001).Conclusions: The presence and severity of ED correlate with the presence of HT, DM, Dyslipidemia and the number of DVR (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gosálbez, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Luque, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Piqueras, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alvarez-Vijande, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Cruz, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Alcaraz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peri, Ll</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Izquierdo, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez-Márquez, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corral, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: La disfunción eréctil (DE) es un estado muy común entre la población. Está en clara relación con la hipertensión arterial (HTA), la diabetes mellitus (DM), la dislipemia (DLP) y el síndrome metabólico (SM). El objetivo del presente estudio es esclarecer si la presencia y severidad de la DE están en relación con el número de factores de riesgo cardiovascular (FRCV). Material y métodos: Analizamos retrospectivamente las características de 242 varones derivados a nuestro centro para la realización de biopsia prostática entre septiembre de 2007 y diciembre de 2009. Se recogieron prospectivamente las siguientes variables: edad, altura, peso, índice de masa corporal (IMC), HTA, DM, DLP y obesidad (IMC &lt; 30 kg/m2). Para describirla función eréctil utilizamos el cuestionario Erection Hardness Score. Analizamos la relación entre la presencia y severidad de DE y la presencia de HTA, DM, DLP y obesidad. Analizamos las variables clínicas en función de la presencia o ausencia de DE y en relación con su severidad. Resultados: La presencia de DE se relaciona con HTA (OR: 1,805 [1,128-2,887]; p = 0,013), DM (OR: 3,585 [1,613-7,966]; p = 0,001) y DLP (OR: 1,928 [1,062-3,500]; p = 0,029). La función eréctil no se relacionó con obesidad (OR: 0,929 [0,522-1,632]; p = 0,795). Los pacientes con DE eran más susceptibles de tener más FRCV (p = 0,009) y la severidad de la DE se encontró en relación con HTA (p &lt; 0,001), DM (p &lt; 0,001), DLP (p = 0,001) y el número FRCV (p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones: La presencia y severidad de la DE se encuentra en relación con la HTA, la DM, la DLP y el número de FRCV (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;36(5): 291-295, mayo 2012. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-99331</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La disfunción eréctil y su severidad están en relación con el número de factores de riesgo cardiovascular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50514^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7152^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7350^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3942</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201205</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
