<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-152312</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Treatment of the postoperative bowel obstructions in children: laparoscopic vs. open adhesiolysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To compare the results of laparoscopic versus open adhesiolysis in children affected by postoperative bowel obstruction. Methods. Retrospective study reviewing charts of all patients who were operated on due to postoperative adhesions in our Department. Demographic data, clinical characteristics and postoperative data were collected. Results. During the last 8 years, 37 patients were operated on for postoperative intestinal obstructions. 40.5% were operated by laparoscopy and 59.5% by laparotomy. Mean ages were 6.31 and 4.32 years in laparoscopic and open groups, respectively. There were no differences in days of evolution of the occlusion, neither in their medical history. Patients in laparoscopic group had better outcomes in the need of central lines (15% vs 61.90% p= 0.012), use of parenteral nutrition (38.46% vs 83.33% p= 0.005), beginning of the enteral nutrition (4.04 vs 8.17 days p= 0.004) and hospital stay (7.77 vs 13.05 days p= 0.027). Conclusions. Open and laparoscopic adhesiolysis are effective to treat adhesive cases. Laparoscopic adhesiolysis has some advantages over open surgery: less need of central lines and parenteral nutrition, earlier start of enteral nutrition, less rate of complications and shorter hospital stay (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gallego Mellado, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Deltell Colomer, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González López, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Albertos Mira-Marcelí, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Encinas Goenechea, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro de la Calzada, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mira Navarro, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sánchez París, O</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Liceras Liceras, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gonzálvez Piñera, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Hortigüela, ME</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Comparar los resultados de la adhesiolisis laparoscópica frente a la técnica abierta en niños con oclusiones postoperatorias. Método. Estudio retrospectivo de los pacientes intervenidos por oclusiones postoperatorias en nuestro centro. Se recogieron variables demográficas, las características clínicas del paciente y del cuadro oclusivo y los resultados postoperatorios. Resultados. En los últimos 8 años, se han realizado 37 intervenciones por oclusiones intestinales postoperatorias: un 40,5% mediante laparoscopia y un 59,5% mediante laparotomía. La media de edad fue 6,31 y 4,32 años para la técnica laparoscópica y abierta, respectivamente. No encontramos diferencias en el tiempo de evolución del cuadro oclusivo, ni en los antecedentes quirúrgicos. Sin embargo, el grupo de adhesiolisis laparoscópica presentó mejores resultados que el de cirugía abierta en: necesidad de vía central (15% frente a 61,90% p= 0,012), uso parenteral (38,46% frente a 83,33% p= 0,005), reinicio de la nutrición enteral (4,04 días frente a 8,17 p= 0,004) y estancia postoperatoria (7,77 frente a 13,05 días p= 0,027). Conclusiones. Ambos abordajes son eficaces para la resolución de la oclusión. La adhesiolisis laparoscópica aporta ventajas frente a la cirugía abierta: menor necesidad de vía central y de nutrición parenteral, reinicio precoz de la nutrición enteral y menor estancia hospitalaria (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;28(3): 123-127, jul. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-152312</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento de las oclusiones postoperatorias en niños: ¿adhesiolisis abierta o laparoscópica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d274^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7578^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d55043^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201507</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
