<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156212</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-1728</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The Municipal Welfare Midwives and attention to the poor women of Malaga (1900-1956)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aim of this study was focused on knowing professional development characteristics and Clinical Practice of Midwives in the Municipal Charity of Malaga in 1900-1956. Method and Materials: This was descriptive and historic study. The collection of information has been made through primary and secondary sources. Results: The process to install the relief houses in the City of Malaga, started in 1862 by Order of the Civil Governor. Conclusions: The incorporation of the healthcare scenario allowed Midwives coverage during the reproductive process of poor women of Malaga through the Municipal Welfare (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cubillas Rodriguez, Inmaculada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rengel Díaz, Cristobal</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres Díaz, Ángela</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales Gil, Isabel María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El objetivo de este estudio consiste en conocer las características del desarrollo profesional y la práctica clínica de las Matronas de la Beneficencia Municipal Malagueña en el período de 1900-1956. Material y Método: Se ha realizado un estudio histórico descriptivo. La recogida de información se ha realizado a través de fuentes primarias y secundarias. Resultados: El proceso para instalar las casas de socorro en la ciudad de Málaga, se inició en 1862 por orden del Gobernador Civil que urgió al Ayuntamiento para que las estableciese. Conclusiones: La incorporación de la Matrona al escenario sanitario permitió una cobertura durante el proceso reproductivo a las mujeres pobres de Málaga a través de la Beneficencia Municipal (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cult. cuid;20(45): 64-73, mayo-ago. 2016. ilus, graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156212</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Las Matronas de la Beneficencia Municipal y su atención a las mujeres pobres de Málaga (1900-1956)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29613</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6835</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38889</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8600^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d17570^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2652^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38885</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11641^s22034</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201608</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
