<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048392</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Therapeutic recommendations in the oncohematological patient</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">More than 10 million new cancer cases are detected each year worldwide, 95% of which are caused by predisposing factors, and of those, more than one third are linked to dietary factors as the main cause. The ability of maintaining an adequate nutritional status in oncohematologic patients is a common problem since the disease itself and the therapy may lead to a protein-caloric hyponutrition state that influence their quality of life and survival.For that reason, in this section we will focus on the prevalence and etiology of hyponutrition in oncologic patients, assessing the possible causes related with the tumor itself, with the patient and with administered therapies.We will also discuss performing a correct nutritional assessment in this type of patients and thus determining the main effects derived from hyponutrition status; finally, we will discuss the objectives of nutritional support and the best nutritional plan that will have to be adjusted to each patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Paz, R de</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martín Salces, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Navarro, F</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Globalmente, en el mundo, se producen cada año más de 10 millones de casos nuevos de cáncer, el 95% de los cuales están causados por factores ambientales y, de ellos, más de la tercera parte están ligados a factores dietéticos como causa principal. La capacidad para mantener un estado nutricional adecuado en el paciente oncohematológico es un problema común; ya que tanto el desarrollo de la propia enfermedad como su tratamiento, pueden dar lugar a un estado de desnutrición calórico proteico, que afecta a su calidad de vida y su supervivencia. Por ello en este apartado, abordaremos la prevalencia y la etiología de la desnutrición en el paciente oncológico, valorando las posibles causas relacionadas con el propio tumor, con el paciente o con los tratamientos administrados. Pero también se mencionarán las pautas para realizar una correcta evaluación nutricional en este tipo de pacientes y determinar así los principales efectos derivados del estado de desnutrición, y por último se abordarán los objetivos del soporte nutricional así como un plan nutricional óptimo que deberá ser ajustado a cada paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;21(3): 379-385, mayo-jun. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048392</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Recomendaciones nutricionales en el paciente oncohematológico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d32108</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22017</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38061^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32936^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200606</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
