<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-057000</identifier>
<setSpec>1696-5981</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Periprosthetic hip fracture indications and treatment</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: A review is presented of 54 femoral periprosthetic    fractures following hip arthroplasty, with the purpose    of defining treatment recommendations according to the    location, stability of the implant, and bone reserve.    Material and methods: A study was made of the periprosthetic    fractures recorded in our Service between    2000-2005, with systematization according to the Vancouver    classification. The most frequent cause of fracture    was low-energy traumatism, while the most constant risk    factor was the presence of osteopenia. We recorded 7    type AG, 3 type AL, 22 type B1, 12 type B2, 6 type B3    and 4 type C fractures. Orthopedic treatment was provided    in all AG and in some B1 fractures, with arthroplasty revision    surgery in all AL, B2 and B3 fractures, and open    reduction and synthesis in all C and in some B1 fractures.    Results: A high postoperative complications rate was    observed. Emphasis is therefore placed on the need for    prevention by applying a careful surgical technique to    avoid the catastrophic consequences of these fractures</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Blanco Pozo, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Pesquera, J. M. </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Moya Gómez, J</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">periprotésicas femorales tras artroplastia de cadera con el    objetivo de poder hacer recomendaciones terapéuticas    según la localización, estabilidad del implante y reserva    ósea.    Material y métodos: ocurridas en nuestro Servicio entre    los años 2.000 y 2.005 sistematizándolas según la clasificación    de Vancouver. La causa más frecuente fueron los    traumatismos de baja energía y el factor de riesgo más    constante la presencia de osteopenia. Se encontraron 7    tipo AG, 3 tipo AL, 22 tipo B1, 12 tipo B2, 6 tipo B3 y 4    tipo C. Se realizó tratamiento ortopédico en todas las AG y    algunas B1, revisión de la artroplastia en todas las AL, B2    y B3 y reducción abierta y síntesis en todas las C y algunas    B1.    Resultados: Se evidenció una alta tasa de complicaciones    postquirúrgicas por lo que se insiste en su prevención    mediante una cuidadosa técnica quirúrgica que evite las    consecuencias catastróficas de estas fracturas</dc:description>
<dc:source>Patol. apar. locomot. Fund. Mapfre Med;5(supl.1): 26-32, 2007. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-057000</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Indicaciones y tratamiento de las fracturas periprotésicas de cadera</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33577^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6778^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6780^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19574</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200700</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
