<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-163585</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-3074</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tools for planning and measuring consumption in nutritional interventions: food fortification</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Nutritional interventions at the population level are justified when there are nutrient deficiencies in the population. The most trusted and preferred methods are those that provide individual results that can be added to reveal the overall situation of the population. The methods of dietary assessment most commonly used in nutrition programs include the Food Balance Sheets (FBS), the twenty-four Hours Recall (24 HR), Food Frequency Questionnaires (FFQ), Fortification Rapid Assessment Tool (FRAT) and Household Consumption and Expenditure Surveys (HCES). Each method of dietary assessment has strengths and weaknesses that vary according to context and purpose. The choice of method should be based on the data needs of the program, the availability of methods, cost and a clear understanding of the advantages and disadvantages involved (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García-Casal, María Nieves</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Las intervenciones nutricionales a nivel poblacional están justificadas cuando en una población existen deficiencias de nutrientes. Los métodos más confiables y preferidos son aquellos que proporcionan resultados individuales que al ser sumados pueden revelar la situación general de la población. Los métodos de evaluación de la dieta más comúnmente utilizados en programas de nutrición incluyen las Hojas de Balance de Alimentos (FBS), el Recordatorio de veinticuatro Horas (24 HR), los Cuestionarios de Frecuencia de Consumo alimentario (FFQ), la Herramienta de Evaluación Rápida de Fortificación (FRAT) y las Encuestas de Consumo y Gasto en los Hogares (HCES). Cada método de evaluación de la dieta tiene fortalezas y debilidades que varían según el contexto y la finalidad. La selección del método debe basarse en las necesidades de datos del programa, la disponibilidad de los métodos, el costo y una clara comprensión de las ventajas y desventajas involucradas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. esp. nutr. comunitaria;21(2): 30-33, abr.-jun. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-163585</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Herramientas para planificar y medir el consumo en intervenciones nutricionales: fortificación de alimentos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16570^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d25401^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24457</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28222^s22018</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
