<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-120587</identifier>
<setSpec>0212-1611</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Application of an obesity treatment protocol for 2 years</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To evaluate the effectiveness of a clinic protocol used in the Complexo Hospitalario Universitario de Vigo (CHUVI) for obese outpatients. Patients and methods: The study included 47 obese outpatients. All of them were evaluated in clinical department and applied the obesity protocol for a period of 2 years. Variables as weight, BMI and levels of obesity in the initial and final time were evaluated. Results and discussion: In obese patients between 26 and 65 years was observed a tendency to reduce their degree of obesity, with significant differences in 2012 compared to 2010. There are differences in behavior between men and women in terms of change in obesity graduation. Conclusions: In our study we found differences in behavior between men and women in terms of grade change in obesity, in women there is a greater tendency to reduce (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Álvarez González, Myrian</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molares Vila, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias Álvarez, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carnero Gregorio, Oscar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carnero Gregorio, Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Méndez, Luisa Fernanda</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villaverde Taboada, Carlos</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Blach Italiani, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Freire, Paula</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la eficacia de un protocolo clínico para pacientes obesos utilizado en la consulta de obesidad del Complexo Hospitalario Universitario de Vigo (CHUVI). Pacientes y métodos: En el estudio participaron 47 pacientes procedentes de la consulta de obesidad del CHUVI. Todos ellos fueron evaluados en consulta y siguieron el protocolo de obesidad durante un periodo de 2 años. Se evaluaron variables como el peso, el IMC y los grados de obesidad en el momento inicial y final. Resultados y discusión: En pacientes obesos entre 26 y 65 años se observa una tendencia a disminuir su grado de obesidad, con diferencias significativas en el 2012 respecto al 2010. Hay diferencias de comportamiento entre hombres y mujeres en cuanto al cambio de graduación en la obesidad. Conclusiones: En nuestro estudio hemos comprobado diferencias de comportamiento entre hombres y mujeres en cuanto al cambio de graduación en la obesidad; en las mujeres hay una mayor tendencia a reducirlo (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nutr Hosp;29(2): 300-304, 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-120587</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Aplicación de un protocolo de tratamiento de obesidad durante 2 años</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d9951^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50271</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27977</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4071^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23862</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1862^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201400</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
