<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-79172</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-1375</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Influence of the initial glucose load on patients undergoing peritoneal dialysis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The aims of the study were to determine whether different glucose loads at the start of peritoneal dialysis could be negative for survival of the technique or of the patients, and to find out what factors affect them and how nursing staff can act in this regard. A retrospective study was carried out from 2004 to2008. The sample comprised 63 patients, classified in 3 groups according to the glucose concentration. Epidemiological, analytical, peritoneal transport and rinsing, comorbility and dialysis dose data were compiled. The results show that the three groups were differentiated by the total glucose weight (p=0.001),average concentration (p&lt;0.001), serum albumin(p&lt;0.05), and the dialysate/creatinine plasma quotient(p=0.036).There were 15 deaths, with no significant differences found for the survival of the patients between the groups (p=0.163), although first-year survival was 95.2%, 94.1% and 78.4%. The factors that influenced survival were age, cardiovascular disease, total Kt/V, diuresis and albumin. Failure of the technique occurred in 8 patients and there were no differences between the groups (p=0.769), nor any independent factors affecting the survival of the technique. In conclusion, we have been unable to prove that a higher initial glucose load affects the survival of the patients or of the technique (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Martín Espejo, Jesús Lucas</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cirera Segura, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los objetivos del estudio fueron determinar si diferentes cargas de glucosa en el inicio de la diálisis peritoneal pueden ser negativas para la supervivencia de la técnica o de los pacientes y conocer qué factores les afectan y cómo puede actuar Enfermería al respecto. Se realizó un estudio retrospectivo desde 2004 a2008. La muestra la constituyeron 63 pacientes, clasificados en 3 grupos según la concentración de glucosa. Se recogieron datos epidemiológicos, analíticos, transporte y aclaramiento peritoneal, comorbilidad y pauta de diálisis. Los resultados demuestran que los tres grupos se diferenciaban en el peso total de glucosa(p=0,001), en su concentración media (p&lt;0,001),en la albúmina sérica (p&lt;0,05), y el cociente dializado-plasma de creatinina (p=0,036).Tuvieron lugar 15 fallecimientos, no encontrando diferencias significativas para la supervivencia delos pacientes entre los grupos (p=0,163), aunque la supervivencia del primer año fue del 95,2%,94,1% y 78,4%. Los factores que influyeron en la supervivencia fueron la edad, la enfermedad cardiovascular, el Kt/V total, la diuresis y la albúmina. El fallo de la técnica tuvo lugar en 8 pacientes y no hubo diferencias entre los grupos (p=0,769), ni factores independientes que influyeran en la supervivencia de la técnica. Como conclusión, no hemos podido demostrar que una mayor carga de glucosa inicial, afecte a la supervivencia de los pacientes o a la técnica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. Soc. Esp. Enferm. Nefrol;13(1): 37-43, ene.-mar. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-79172</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Influencia de la carga inicial de glucosa sobre los pacientes en diálisis peritoneal</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28620</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24542</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7849^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10174^s22021</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50524^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29504^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6091^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201003</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
