<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-150244</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Perceived social support in pathological gamblers and treatment effectiveness</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Pathological gambling affects 0.4-1.5 percent of the global population. Therapy has proved effective, even though low therapeutic compliance and frequent withdrawals weakens good treatment results. The aim of this paper is to evaluate the relationship between social support, therapeutic adherence, and gambling cessation. Four aspects of social support were measured: cohabitation, patient's companion, commitment, and intervention with patient's companion, in a sample of 68 pathological gamblers. Results show a non-significant trend for social support and treatment compliance to be associated to treatment success. Seventy-six percent of high social support patients kept the treatment up to the end vis-à-vis42.1% of low social support patients. Therapeutic success shows a significant relationship to a stable couple relationship. Individuals who had stable couple relationship were twice likely to finish treatment successfully. Results suggest that social support should be considered as a critical variable in pathological gambling treatment (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lloret, Daniel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Montesinos, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Aracil, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Segura, José Vicente</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El juego patológico afecta entre el 0.4% y el 1.5% de la población mundial. Aunque existen procedimientos terapéuticos eficaces, la escasa adherencia terapéutica y las recaídas amenazan los resultados. El objetivo es determinar la relación entre el apoyo social, la adherencia terapéutica y el cese del juego. Se evaluó convivencia, acompañamiento, implicación e intervención del acompañante en una muestra de68 jugadores patológicos. Los resultados muestran una asociación no significativa entre apoyo social y adherencia al tratamiento y éxito terapéutico. Se mantuvieron en tratamiento el 76.0% de los que tenían apoyo social alto frente al 42.1% que tenían apoyo social bajo. El éxito terapéutico presenta una asociación significativa con el estado civil. Las personas que mantienen una relación de pareja estable tienen el doble de probabilidad de finalizar el tratamiento con éxito. Los resultados sugieren considerar el apoyo social como una variable decisiva en el tratamiento de la ludopatía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;27(1): 15-22, mar. 2016. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-150244</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La percepción del apoyo social en jugadores patológicos y su relación con el éxito del tratamiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5855^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10548</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3883</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13328</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12049^s22041</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53386</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37675</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7352</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24570^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201603</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
