<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-115468</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-4008</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">What is the diagnostic yield of the peripheral blood smear?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objetive. Although examination of peripheral blood smear is a very helpful tool in the diagnosis of several pathologies, it is essential that the person who performs it knows the patient clinical data and what to look for in order to obtain the highest benefit. The aim of this study is to determine the proportion of useful blood smears in clinical practice and to identify possible predictive factors. Patients and methods. We prospectively analysed 618 consecutive peripheral blood smears performed in our laboratory, requested by 6 hospitals in Madrid. Clinical features provided by the physician and abnormalities in complete blood count (none / white cells / red cells / platelets / all of them) were evaluated in each case. According to the information obtained from them, blood smears were classified into: a) non-diagnostic; b) a previously-known diagnosis is confirmed, and c) new relevant information provided. Results. No useful information was obtained by 402 (65.04%) blood smears. A higher proportion of previous clinical suspicions was observed in helpful blood smears compared to non-diagnostic ones (20% vs 5.1%, P&lt;.001), and also less for completely normal blood counts (3.8% vs 42.7%, P &lt;.001). Conclusions. In our experience, two thirds of requested peripheral blood smears provide no useful information at all. Clinical suspicion and the presence of at least one abnormality in complete blood count showed a significant impact in blood smear yield(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alonso-Domínguez, Juan Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jiménez-Rolando, Marta</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ataúlfo González-Fernández, Fernando</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Villarrubia Espinosa, Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Velasco-Rodríguez, Diego</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillén, Raquel</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo. A pesar de que el frotis de sangre periférica es una herramienta muy útil en el diagnóstico de diversas enfermedades, para que aporte beneficio es crucial que el encargado de examinarlo conozca datos clínicos del paciente y sepa qué tiene que buscar o descartar. El objetivo de nuestro trabajo fue evaluar el beneficio real que aporta el frotis y los factores que predicen su impacto en la práctica clínica. Pacientes y métodos. Se analizaron de forma prospectiva todos los frotis consecutivos (n = 618) solicitados en un mes por 6 hospitales de la comunidad de Madrid y revisados en nuestro laboratorio. En cada frotis se evaluó la información previa aportada por el médico peticionario y la serie hematológica alterada. Clasificamos cada frotis, según lo que aportó al clínico, en: a) sin información relevante; b) confirma diagnóstico ya conocido, y c) aporta información relevante para el diagnóstico o pronóstico. Resultados. No se obtuvo ninguna información relevante en 402 frotis (65,04%). En los frotis útiles se observó mayor proporción de sospechas diagnósticas previas (20%) en comparación con los no diagnósticos (5,1%) (p &lt; 0,001) y menos peticiones con hemograma normal (3,8 vs 42,7%, p &lt; 0,001). Conclusiones. En nuestra experiencia, 2 de cada 3 frotis solicitados no aportan ninguna información relevante. Conocer la sospecha diagnóstica y tener al menos una de las 3 series alteradas tiene impacto significativo en la rentabilidad del frotis(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. lab. clín;6(3): 122-127, jul.-sept. 2013.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-115468</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Cuál es la rentabilidad diagnóstica del frotis de sangre periférica?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1800^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1800^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33556^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1800^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1800^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1800^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201309</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
