<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-96071</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-1813</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Residents in an Intensive Care Unit, what perception they have on their training?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Aim. Our work tries to answer the following question: what is the perception of residents on their training in the Intensive Care Units (ICU)?Subjects and methods. We have conducted a qualitative study based on grounded theory. Participants are residents from different specialties working in the ICU of four hospitals of our National Health Service. The study consist of three parts: resident&#146;s subjective perception of those aspects most appreciate in their clinical practice; resident&#146;s prioritizations of routine ICU&#146;s activities, and semi-structured interviews with key informants. Results. According to the resident&#146;s opinions, the clinical practice at the beside of patients, and carried out with autonomy and with a good tutoring support are central to their training; nevertheless some central competencies such as research, difficult communication, team work or resource management are undervalued, while others such as patient safety or bioethics are absent from their comments. Conclusions. Our work highlight that resident&#146;s perception about their training during they compulsory period in ICU has some shortcoming, because some key aspects of current medicine are not perceived as priorities in their training (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Rucabado-Aguilar, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarrete-Navarro, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García-Alcántara, Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rodríguez-Elvira, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guillamet-Lloveras, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Murillo-Cabezas, Francisco</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Roca-Guiseris, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vázquez-Mata, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Este trabajo intenta responder a la pregunta de cuál es la visión que tienen los residentes de su formación en las unidades de cuidados intensivos (UCI).Sujetos y métodos. Hemos realizado un estudio cualitativo tipo grounded theory. Los participantes son residentes de cualquier especialidad que estuviesen trabajando en las UCI durante el estudio. El diseño tiene tres partes: percepción subjetiva de los residentes de aquellos aspectos que ellos consideran más útiles para su formación, priorización de las actividades regulares más características de las UCI y entrevistas semiestructuradas con informadores claves. Resultados. Nuestro trabajo identifica que los residentes consideran como eje de su formación la práctica clínica a &#145;pie de cama&#146; desarrollada con autonomía y apoyada en una buena tutorización. Paralelamente, otras competencias nucleares como la investigación, la comunicación en situaciones complejas, el trabajo en equipo o la gestión de recursos están infravaloradas, mientras que otras como la seguridad del paciente o la bioética no se han detectado en las respuestas de los residentes. Conclusión. La percepción de los residentes sobre formación durante su estancia en las UCI adolece de algunas carencias, dado que ciertos aspectos claves de la medicina actual no se perciben como prioridades en dicha formación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Educ. med. (Ed. impr.);14(3): 189-194, sept. 2011. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-96071</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Los residentes en las unidades de cuidados intensivos, ¿cuál es su percepción de la formación que reciben?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12224^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7530^s22060</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7560^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4569^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11795</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53814^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201109</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
