<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-138655</identifier>
<setSpec>1137-6821</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Emergency department training on the appropriate prescription of anticoagulants in atrial fibrillation and on patient follow-up after discharge</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives. The main objective was to evaluate the effect of an emergency department training intervention on the use of a protocol for prescribing anticoagulant therapy in atrial fibrillation and on following patients after discharge. Methods. Quasi-experimental pre-post study of a training intervention; the control patients were not matched but were selected consecutively before and after the intervention. All patients were over the age of 18 years, had atrialfibrillation identified by electrocardiogram, and indications for anticoagulant therapy, specifically a score of 2 or more on the CHADS2-DS2-VASc scale (cardiac failure, hypertension, age &gt;75 years, diabetes, stroke [doubled], vascular disease, age 65-74 years, sex). The primary outcome was percentage of patients on anticoagulant therapy on discharge from the department. The secondary outcome was the percentage of patients on therapy 1 month after discharge. Results. A total of 184 patients (86 before the intervention and 98 afterwards) were included. Training significantly increased the prescription of anticoagulants in the department (before the intervention, 32 patients [37%] vs 95[97%] afterwards; P&lt;.001). In the preintervention period, 26 patients (30% were on anticoagulants 1 month later; in the postintervention period, 26 (30%) were still on therapy (P&lt;.001). Conclusions. This study shows that emergency staff training is effective for implementing protocols based on anticoagulant therapy guidelines (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pedraza, Jorge</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Urbano, María del Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz, María del Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valle Alonso, Joaquín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lopera Lopera, Elisa</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos. Evaluar el resultado de una intervención formativa realizada en el servicio de urgencias (SU), en cuanto a la correcta prescripción y uso de un protocolo de anticoagulación en pacientes con fibrilación auricular (FA) y su posterior seguimiento. Método. Estudio cuasi-experimental con un grupo de control no equivalente, pre/post intervención formativa. Se seleccionaron dos grupos de pacientes (pre y postintervención) mediante muestreo consecutivo, mayores de 18 años, que se presentaron en el SU con FA identificada en el ECG y con criterios de anticoagulación según la estratificación de riesgo de la escala CHA2DS2-VASc &amp;#1048576; 2. El resultado primario fue la proporción de pacientes anticoagulados al alta del SU. El resultado secundario fue la proporción de pacientes anticoagulados al mes del alta del SU. Resultados. Se incluyeron 184 pacientes (86 preintervención, 98 postintervención). La intervención aumentó de manera significativa el comienzo de la anticoagulación [preintervención 32 (37%) vs postintervención 95 (97%);p &lt; 0,001] y el seguimiento al mes de comenzar el tratamiento [preintervención 26 (30%) vs postintervención 91(93%); p &lt; 0,001]. Conclusiones. Una intervención formativa en el SU es efectiva para implementar los protocolos adaptados a las guías de práctica clínica de la anticoagulación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Emergencias (Sant Vicenç dels Horts);27(2): 82-86, abr. 2015. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-138655</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención en el servicio de urgencias para lograr un inicio y seguimiento adecuados de la anticoagulació en pacientes con fibrilación auricular</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4713^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35251</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28380</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4711^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1287^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53262^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28483^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
