<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-60610</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">HIV-mother-to-child transmission in a tertiary hospital in the era of generalization of preventive interventions</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective: Since 1994, when the PACTG 076 results were published, the rate of vertical transmission has decreased from 25% to 2%. Nowadays the prevalence of HIV infection in Catalan pregnant women is 0.17% yet it is 0.5% in our hospital. Our objectives were: to analyze the number of new cases of HIV infection by vertical transmission; to determine the importance of risk factors; to prove how important is to identify HIV-infected pregnant women; to determine the role of the rapid HIV-1 testing in labour room; and to detect mistakes in the prophylactic strategies. Patients and method: One hundted and twenty four newborns from HIV-infected pregnant women born in Hospital del Mar were prospectively followed from 1996&#150;2005. All them were separated in different groups in order to compare them. Results: Eight children were infected, corresponding to 6.45%. In the group of newborns whose mothers were identified as infected during pregnancy, even with prophylactic measures well done, the transmission rate was 3.6% and it was 3.8% in the group born after 1999. When the prophylactic strategies were correct, 30% of pregnant women reached delivery with HIV RNA &lt;1,000/ml copies. In the multivariate analysis, two variables were significant: amniorrhexis &gt;4h and lack of identification of pregnant women as being HIV positive. Conclusions: The identification of HIV-pregnant women has been crucial to avoid HIV mother-to-child transmission. Rapid HIV-1 testing in labour room is key to set up preventive strategies in order to avoid the infection in the newborn. Adequate prophylaxis percentages are still low and improvement is needed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Mur Sierra,  Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mur Milà, Estanislao</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guxens Junyent,  Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López-Vílchez, M. Ángeles</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento y objetivo: Desde que en 1994 se publicaron los resultados del estudio PACTG 076, la tasa de transmisión vertical del virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) ha ido disminuyendo. La prevalencia de la infección entre las gestantes catalanas es del 0,17%, y en nuestro hospital del 0,5%, en 2005. Los objetivos del trabajo han sido: analizar el número de nuevos casos de infección por el VIH por transmisión vertical; detectar la importancia de los diferentes factores de riesgo; demostrar la importancia de identificar a las gestantes infectadas; objetivar el papel de la prueba rápida en sala de partos, y detectar los fallos en la prevención de la transmisión vertical. Pacientes y método: Se han incluido, de manera prospectiva, los 124 recién nacidos hijos de madre infectada por el VIH positiva nacidos en el Hospital del Mar, Barcelona entre 1996 y 2005, divididos en diferentes grupos para compararlos entre ellos. Resultados: Han resultado infectados 8, lo que supone un 6,45%. En el grupo de madres identificadas con profilaxis correcta, la tasa de transmisión fue del 3,6% y en el grupo posterior a 1999 del 3,8%. Cuando la profilaxis es correcta, hay un 30% más de gestantes con carga viral &lt;1.000copias/ml. El modelo multivariado de regresión logística mostró como significativas dos variables: amniorrexis &gt;4h y la no identificación de la gestante como infectada por el VIH. Conclusiones: La identificación de la gestante es un factor primordial para evitar la transmisión vertical. La prueba diagnóstica rápida del VIH en la sala de partos es fundamental para establecer medidas preventivas y evitar la transmisión vertical. Los porcentajes de profilaxis correcta son bajos y susceptibles de una gran mejoría (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);132(13): 487-494, abr. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-60610</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Transmisión vertical global del virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana en la época de la generalización de las medidas preventivas</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29416^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32282^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38332^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32857^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24718^s22069</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200904</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
