<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-30365</identifier>
<setSpec>1136-4890</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Clinical anatomy of the superficial peroneal nerve in the distal leg</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Applied anatomy of the superficial peroneal nerve in real clinical situations requires a good knowledge of the anatomical relationships and their common variations. Here we present an anatomoclinical description not only of the normal superficial peroneal nerve but also of its different variations with surgical implications based on twelve lower limbs. In order to gain some landmarks, the followings measurements were taken: a) distance from the upper end of the fibular head to the lower eminence of the lateral malleolus; b) number of branches from the nerve when it emerges through the superficial sural fascia; c) distance from the nerve emergence point to the lateral malleolus; d) distance from the nerve division to the lateral malleolus. We also recorded the site were the nerve pierces the sural fascia from the anterior or lateral muscular compartment. The data obtained seem to be sufficiently reliable for usual clinical practice, but it must be taken into account that frequent and important variations may occur (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>Sociedad Anatómica Española</dc:publisher>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La anatomía aplicada del nervio peroneo superficial en situaciones clínicas reales requiere un buen conocimiento de las relaciones anatómicas y sus variaciones comunes. Presentamos aquí una descripción anatomoclínica no sólo del nervio peroneo superficial sino también de sus diferentes variaciones con implicaciones quirúrgicas, basadas en el estudio de 12 miembros inferiores. Con el fin de obtener algunos parámetros de referencia, se determinaron las siguientes mediciones: a) distancia desde el extremo superior de la cabeza del peroné hasta la eminencia inferior del maleolo lateral; b) número de ramas del nervio cuando emerge a través de la fascia sural superficial; c) distancia desde el punto de emergencia del nervio hasta el maleolo lateral; d) distancia desde la división del nervio hasta el maleolo lateral. También registramos los lugares donde el nervio atraviesa la fascia sural desde el compartimiento muscular anterior o lateral. Los datos obtenidos parecen ser suficientemente fiables para la práctica clínica habitual, pero debe tenerse en cuenta que pueden existir variaciones frecuentes e importantes (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Eur. j. anat;7(supl.1): 15-20, jul. 2003. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Anatomía clínica del nervio peroneo superficial en la parte distal de la pierna</dc:title>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:creator>Morro, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Llusa, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pacha, D</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Carrera, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Permanyer, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Molona, O</dc:creator>
<dc:language>en</dc:language>
<dc:identifier>ibc-30365</dc:identifier>
<dc:subject>^d8044^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4271^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10733^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34379</dc:subject>
<dc:date>200307</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
