<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109143</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-9891</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Why people with fibromyalgia persist in activity despite the increasing pain? A Delphi Study of the content of the Clinic Scale of Persistence in Activity in Fibromyalgia</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background and objective. There is evidence of the relevance of fear, anxiety and avoidance of activity in the maintenance of pain in fibromyalgia. Recently, an opposite pattern based on the persistence in activity has been described. To date, the cognitions that impede modifying this pattern are unknown. Therefore, the aim of this study is to reach consensus on the content of an instrument that assesses those cognitions. Material and methods. A Delphi method was applied to reach consensus on the content of the Clinic Scale of Persistence in Activity in Fibromyalgia (CCAP-FM). Results. After three rounds of consultation, an acceptable consensus was reached. Those items that received an average rating of relevance lower than 5/10 and that at least the 75% of experts recommended removing were excluded. The preliminary questionnaire of persistence in activity was composed of 30 items. Conclusions. The consensus on the content of the CCAP-FM will allow advancing towards the assessment of the relation between the modification of the cognitions responsible for the maintenance of the persistence in activity and the clinical improvement in people with fibromyalgia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Conesa, Arantxa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torres, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arias, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Herrero, Maria Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Collado, Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Valdés, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martí, Mireia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez, Emili</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción. Existen sólidas pruebas de la relevancia del miedo, la ansiedad y la evitación de la actividad en el mantenimiento del dolor en la fibromialgia. Recientemente se ha descrito un modelo opuesto basado en la persistencia en la actividad. Actualmente desconocemos las cogniciones que dificultan la modificación de este patrón de comportamiento. Por consiguiente, el objetivo del estudio es la definición consensuada del contenido de un instrumento que las evalúa. Material y métodos. Mediante consulta prospectiva a expertos se consensuó el contenido del Cuestionario Clínic de Persistencia en la Actividad en la Fibromialgia (CCAP-FM). Resultados. Tras 3 rondas de consulta se alcanzó un acuerdo aceptable. Se excluyeron los ítems que obtuvieron una valoración media consensuada de relevancia inferior a 5/10 y que al menos el 75% de los expertos recomendó eliminar. El cuestionario preliminar de persistencia en la actividad quedó compuesto por 30 ítems. Conclusiones. La definición del contenido del CCAP-FM permitirá iniciar el proceso de evaluación de la relación entre la modificación de las cogniciones responsables del mantenimiento de la persistencia en la actividad y la mejoría clínica de las personas con fibromialgia(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev. psiquiatr. salud ment. (Barc., Ed. impr.);6(1): 33-44, ene.-mar. 2013. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109143</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Por qué las personas con fibromialgia persisten en la actividad a pesar del dolor creciente?: estudio Delphi sobre el contenido del Cuestionario Clínic de Persistencia en la Actividad en Fibromialgia</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d5342^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24385^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12436</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1012^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d37627^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10333^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1014^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10167^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12023^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
