<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-054296</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tobacco smoking and sputum smear conversion in pulmonary tuberculosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: To analyze if cigarette smoking delays the sputum smear conversionin pulmonary tuberculosis.PATIENTS AND METHOD: Ninety eight patients were diagnosed with pulmonary tuberculosis. Patientswere all not immunosuppressed, infected by human immunodeficiecy virus (HIV) or drugresistant. Sixty four of them were smokers with a pack-year index (standard deviation) of 33.69(23.12). Delayed sputum smear conversion (DC) was considered when 2 positive sputum cultureresults were obtained in the second month of anti-tuberculous treatment and was associatedwith the following variables in 2 groups: a) total group (in which all the patients were included):age, sex, smoking habits, risk factors (alcohol consumption, diabetes mellitus, immunosuppression,drug addicion, malnutrition), time with symptoms, radiologic presentation andbacterial load, and b) smokers: age, sex, risk factors, time with symptoms, radiologic presentation,bacterial load and pack-year index. For the statistical analysis, &amp;#967;2 test, Student t test andlogistic regression model were used, considering the dependant variable DC.RESULTS: In the total group, 17 patients (17.3%) had DC, 16 of them had a history of smokingand in the univariate analysis it was associated with: alcohol consumption, time with symptoms,radiologic presentation as bilateral cavitary infiltrates and smoking habits. The logistic regressionanalysis showed an association with smoking habits (odds ratio = 9.8; p = 0.03) andbilateral cavitary infiltrates (odds ratio = 3.61; p = 0.02). In the group of smokers, DC was associatedin the univariate analysis with the female sex.CONCLUSIONS: Smoking habits delay sputum conversion in patients with pulmonary tuberculosisnot associated with HIV and non-resistant bacilli. According to these results it is necessary toassist smoking cessation in patients who are receiving antituberculous treatment</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fernández Álvarez, Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Toste, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Martín, Isidro Jesús</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecuona Fernández, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Medina Gonzálvez, Agustín</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Galindo Morales, Rosa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rubinos Cuadrado, Gemma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gullón Blanco, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO Y OBJETIVO: Analizar si el consumo de tabaco retrasa la negativización microbiológicaen la tuberculosis pulmonar.PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: Se incluyó a 98 pacientes diagnosticados de tuberculosis pulmonar, sin inmunodepresióncausada por el virus de la inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH) ni resistencia farmacológica.Eran fumadores 64, con un índice medio (desviación estándar) de 33,69 (23,12)paquetes/año. Se consideró conversión bacteriológica retardada (CR) a la persistencia de 2 cultivospositivos al segundo mes del inicio del tratamiento antituberculoso, y se relacionó con lassiguientes variables en 2 grupos: a) general (que englobaba a todos los pacientes): edad, sexo,tabaquismo, factores de riesgo (consumo de alcohol, diabetes mellitus, inmunodepresión, adiccióna drogas, desnutrición), tiempo de evolución de los síntomas, presentación radiológica ycarga bacilar, y b) fumadores: edad, sexo, índice paquetes/año, factores de riesgo, tiempo deevolución de los síntomas, presentación radiológica y carga bacilar. En cuanto al estudio estadístico,se realizaron los siguientes análisis: distribución de la &amp;#967;2, prueba de la t de Student yregresión logística paso a paso hacia adelante, considerando como variable dependiente la CR.RESULTADOS: En el grupo general presentaron CR 17 pacientes (17,3%), de los que 16 referíanantecedentes de tabaquismo, y en el estudio univariado la CR se relacionó con el consumo dealcohol, el tiempo de evolución de los síntomas, la presentación radiológica cavitaria bilateral yel tabaquismo. En el análisis de regresión logística mantenían la relación el tabaquismo (oddsratio = 9,80; p = 0,03) y la cavitación bilateral (odds ratio = 3,61; p = 0,02). En el grupo defumadores, la CR se asoció en el análisis univariado únicamente con sexo femenino.CONCLUSIONES: El tabaquismo retrasa la CR en pacientes diagnosticados de tuberculosis pulmonarno ligada al VIH y con aislamientos sensibles. Dada la trascendencia de este hallazgo, espreciso reforzar su abandono durante el tratamiento antituberculoso</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);128(15): 565-568, abr. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-054296</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tabaquismo y negativización bacteriológica del esputo en la tuberculosis pulmonar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23925^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14798^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9362^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d999^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13568^s22046</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
