<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049835</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Are reversible the neurotoxic effects of synthetic drugs?</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">It is clear from animal studies that substituted amphetamine derivatives have two sort of effects: immediate and reversible, and prolonged and reversible. The immediate effect of substituted amphetamine intake is an increment to extracellular levels of serotonin and dopamine that return to normality in about 6 h. And may produce an augmentation of corporal temperature. However, this reversible effect is followed by other long lasting that usually occurs in the period between 24 h and one week. Inthis case, damage in serotonergic neurons appears, involving reuptake proteins and fine axon terminals, that are persistently lost. The mechanisms that might cause these neurotoxic effects are unknown, but it seems that an increment in cellular oxidative systms may have a role. Animal studies have also shown that an enduring cessation of amphetamine derivatives intake results in a progressive serotonergic re-inervation, but with a pattern that is different from the previously established during the normal development. Although we don´t know if such re-inervation process may develop in human beings, is tempting to speculate that it will occur given that it happens in non-human primates. The behavioural consequences of serotoninergic system damage and the hypothetical re-inervation process in humans are also unknown. However, they might be related to several behavioural malfunctions such as anxiety, depression or memory impairments that former amphetamine derivatives users exhibits in the span of their lives</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ambrosio, Emilio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La investigación preclínica sobre las drogas de síntesis realizada en animales de laboratorio nos indica que las acciones neurotóxicas pueden ser de dos tipos: a corto y reversibles y a largo plazo e irreversibles. En efecto su consumo se traduce enseguida en un aumento de las concentraciones extracelulares de serotonina y dopamina que parece conllevar una subida de la temperatura corporal, pero este efecto es reversible en un tiempo medio de 6 horas. Sin embargo, una segunda acción aparece entre un día y una semana más tarde, con consecuencias neurotóxicas que afectan sobre todo al sistema serotoninérgico y a las terminaciones finas de las fibras nerviosas de serotonina que proceden de los núcleos del rafe dorsal, puede que sea por un incremento en la oxidación de ciertos procesos celulares en esas neuronas. La suspensión de la administración de esas neuronas. La suspensión de la administración de esas drogas hace que, a lo largo plazo, haya un nuevo crecimiento de las dañadas terminaciones finas, pero un patrón de reinervación distinto al que originalmente había. Es probable que en humanos ocurra un proceso parecido, puesto que esto ocurren en primates no humanos. Tampoco conocemos las consecuencias psicológicas a largo plazo del daño neurotóxico que causan las drogas de síntesis en humanos, incluida, en su caso, una posible reinervación de las terminaciones serotoninérgicas, si se abandona durante un tiempo considerable el consumo. Pero es sabido que la serotonina es un neurotransmisor implicado en numerosos procesos cognitivos y emocionales y puede que sean la causa de las disfunciones psicológicas mantenidas que muestran los que han consumido drogas de síntesis</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);18(2): 101-104, abr. 2006.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049835</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">¿Son reversibles los efectos neurotóxicos de las drogas de síntesis?</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29633</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3564^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34349^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d843^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24311^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34349^s22075</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8939^s22078</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d843^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24311^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33535^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8939^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34349^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d676^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34349^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12345</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d841</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8939^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8939^s22079</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23987^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8869^s22068</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
