<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136721</identifier>
<setSpec>0003-3170</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Role of endoglin in the physiological events involved in post-ischemic revascularization</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Long-term ischemia is frequent during and after vascular surgery, and the recovery of affected organ function depends on the re-establishment of blood supply. Ischemia triggers processes such as inflammation, angiogenesis, or vasculogenesis that will lead to tissue remodeling and blood supply restoration. All these events are closely related and highly regulated to achieve complete recovery. Endoglin is a co-receptor for TGF-&amp;#946; cytokines superfamily that plays a central role in vascular physiology, angiogenesis, inflammation and post-ischemic blood supply recovery. Our laboratory has been involved for a long time in the study of endoglin function and its mechanisms of action and involvement in the regulation of vascular function, angiogenesis, inflammation, and fibrosis, as well as in diseases such as hypertension and preeclampsia. The aim here is to review how post-ischemic revascularization takes place, and to assess the role of endoglin in these events, and its importance as a possible therapeutic target (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lopez-Novoa, J. M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Núñez-Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La isquemia de larga duración es un proceso bastante común durante y tras la cirugía vascular, y la correcta recuperación de la función del órgano afectado depende de que se recupere el flujo sanguíneo del órgano afectado. La isquemia desencadena procesos como la inflamación, angiogénesis o vasculogénesis, que permitirán la reperfusión del órgano. Endoglina es un correceptor para los miembros de la superfamilia de citocinas de TGF-&amp;#946;. En nuestro laboratorio llevamos muchos años estudiando la función y los mecanismos de acción de endoglina, así como su implicación en regulación del tono vascular, angiogénesis, inflamación, fibrosis y en enfermedades como la preeclampsia y la hipertensión. Nuestro objetivo en este trabajo es revisar cómo se suceden los eventos que tienen lugar en la revascularización postisquémica, y mostrar las evidencias que colocan a endoglina como una molécula clave en estos eventos y como una posible diana terapéutica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Angiologia;67(3): 206-215, mayo-jun. 2015. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136721</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Papel de endoglina en los eventos fisiológicos involucrados en la revascularización postisquémica</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29490^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32666^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7678^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23568^s22002</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7426^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28903^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23812^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201506</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
