<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-157143</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-2896</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Adaptation and Validation of the Spanish Version of OSA-18, a Quality of Life Questionnaire for Evaluation of Children with Sleep Apnea-Hypopnea Syndrome</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: To analyze the reliability and validity of the Spanish version of the OSA-18 quality of life questionnaire in children with apnea-hypopnea syndrome (SAHS). Method: Children with suspected SAHS were studied with polysomnography (PSG) before and after adenotonsillectomy (AA). Age, gender, clinical data, PSG, anthropometric data, and Mallampati and Brodsky scales were analyzed. OSA-18 was administered at baseline and 3-6months post AA. After translation and backtranslation by bilingual professionals, the internal consistency, reliability, construct validity, concurrent validity, predictive validity and sensitivity to change of the questionnaire was assessed. Results: In total, 45 boys and 15 girls were evaluated, showing BMI 18±4, neck 28±5, Brodsky (0: 7%; &lt;25%: 12%; 25-50%: 27%; &gt;50 to &lt;75%: 45%; &gt;75%: 6%), AHI 12±7 pre AA. Global Cronbach alpha was 0.91. Correlations between domains were significant except for emotional aspects, although the total scores correlated with all domains (0.50 to 0.90). The factorial analysis was virtually identical to the original structure. The total scores showed good correlation for concurrent validity (0.2-0.45). With regard to predictive validity, the questionnaire adequately differentiated levels of severity according to Mallampati (ANOVA P=.002) and apnea-hypopnea index (ANOVA P=.006). Test-retest reliability was excellent, as was sensitivity to change, both in the total scores (P&lt;.001) and in each domain (P&lt;.001). Conclusions: The Spanish adaptation of the OSA-18 and its psychometric characteristics suggest that the Spanish version is equivalent to the original and can be used in Spanish-speaking countries (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Pastor, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Arlandis, Mar</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Landete, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Selma, María José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sancho Chust, José Norberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Navarro, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Martínez García, Miguel Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ferrer, Patricia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Senent, Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chiner, Eusebi</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: Adaptar al español y analizar la fiabilidad y la validez de la versión española del cuestionario OSA-18 de calidad de vida (CVRS) en el síndrome de apnea-hipopnea del sueño (SAHS) infantil. Método: Se incluyeron niños con sospecha de SAHS a los que se practicó polisomnografía (PSG) pre y post adenoamigdalectomía (AA). Se analizó: edad, género, clínica, PSG, datos antropométricos, grados de Brodsky y Mallampati. Se administró OSA-18 basal y entre 3-6meses post AA. Tras la traducción-retrotraducción por personas bilingües se evaluaron la consistencia interna, la fiabilidad, la validez de constructo, la validez concurrente, la validez predictiva y la sensibilidad a los cambios. Resultados: Se evaluaron 45 niños y 15 niñas: IMC18±4, cuello 28±5, Brodsky (0: 7%; &lt;25%: 12%; 25-50%: 27%; &gt;50 a &lt;75%: 45%; &gt;75%: 6%), IAH: 12±7 pre AA. El alfa de Cronbach del global fue 0,91. Las correlaciones entre dominios fueron significativas salvo para aspectos emocionales, aunque el global se correlacionó con todos los dominios (0,50-0,90). El análisis factorial mostró una estructura prácticamente idéntica al original. En la validez concurrente, el global mostró buena correlación (0,2-0,45). En su validez predictiva, diferenció adecuadamente los niveles de gravedad según Mallampati (ANOVA p=0,002) e índice apnea-hipopnea (ANOVA p=0,006). La sensibilidad al cambio fue excelente, tanto en el global (p&lt;0,001) como en cada dominio (p&lt;0,001), así como la fiabilidad test-retest. Conclusiones: La adaptación española del OSA-18 es comprensible y sus características psicométricas sugieren que la versión española es equivalente a la original y puede ser empleada en países de habla hispana (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Bronconeumol;52(11): 553-559, nov. 2016. graf, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-157143</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Adaptación y validación al español del cuestionario de calidad de vida OSA-18 para la evaluación del síndrome de apnea-hipopnea de sueño infantil</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28610</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13273^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30611^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32026</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35256</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28575</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12018^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201611</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
