<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-053674</identifier>
<setSpec>0300-8932</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Factors Predictive of Cardiovascular Disease in Patients With Type-2 Diabetes and Hypercholesterolemia. ESODIAH Study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction and objectives. We investigated the pattern of cardiovascular disease and the factors that predict such disease in outpatients with type-2 diabetes and hypercholesterolemia. Methods. This prospective open observational study included outpatients of both sexes (mean age 62 [8] years) with type-2 diabetes and hypercholesterolemia. Clinical manifestations of cardiovascular disease (e.g., angina, myocardial infarction, stroke and peripheral arterial disease), glucose and HbA1c levels, and cardiovascular risk factors were recorded every 4 months throughout the 2-year follow-up period. Overall, 838 patients completed follow-up. Results. During follow-up, 81 patients (9.6%) presented with a cardiovascular event, nine of which were fatal. Cardiovascular events were more frequent in patients with a history of an ischemic condition than in those without: 58 of 258 (22.5%) and 23 of 579 (4%), respectively (P&lt;.01). Previous angina or myocardial infarction was the strongest predictor of cardiovascular risk (relative risk [RR]=4.08, 95% confidence interval [CI] 2.39-6.95), followed by previous stroke (RR=2.96, 95% CI 1.26-6.93), high low-density lipoprotein (LDL)-cholesterol level &amp;#8805;135 mg/dL (RR=2.79, 95% CI 1.56-5.01), peripheral arterial disease (RR=2.44, 95% CI 1.27-4.68), a high HbA1c level (RR=2.08, 95% CI 1.22-3.57), and obesity (RR=1.69, 95% CI 1.0-2.86). Conclusions. The incidence of cardiovascular disease in this southern European population of patients with type-2 diabetes and hypercholesterolemia was high. A history of an ischemic condition and a high LDL-cholesterol level during follow-up were the strongest predictors of cardiovascular disease</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Masana, Luis</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Biarnés, Josefina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Falkon, Liliana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pintó, Xavier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Clotilde</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Corbella, Emili</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueras, Rosaura</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ricart, Wifredo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción y objetivos. Evaluar el patrón y los factores predictivos de enfermedad cardiovascular (ECV) en los pacientes ambulatorios con diabetes tipo 2 e hipercolesterolemia. Métodos. Estudio prospectivo, abierto y observacional en el que se incluyó a pacientes de ambos sexos (62 ± 8 años) con diabetes tipo 2 e hipercolesterolemia. Se registraron las manifestaciones clínicas de ECV, incluidos la angina, el infarto de miocardio, el ictus y la enfermedad arterial periférica; la glucosa, la hemoglobina glucosilada (HbA1c) y los factores de riesgo cardiovascular se evaluaron cada 4 meses durante un período de seguimiento de 2 años, que fue completado por 838 pacientes. Resultados. En total, 81 pacientes (9,6%) presentaron un episodio de ECV y 9 fallecieron durante el seguimiento. La ECV fue más frecuente en los pacientes con historia previa de enfermedad isquémica que en los pacientes sin ella (58 de 258 [22,5%] frente a 23 de 579 [4%], respectivamente; p &lt; 0,01). La angina o el infarto de miocardio previos fueron los predictores más potentes del riesgo cardiovascular (riesgo relativo [RR] = 4,08; intervalo de confianza [IC] del 95%, 2,39-6,95), seguidos del ictus previo (RR = 2,96; IC del 95%, 1,26-6,93), el exceso de colesterol unido a lipoproteínas de baja densidad (cLDL) (&amp;#8805; 135 mg/dl) (RR = 2,79; IC del 95%, 1,56-5,01), la arteriopatía periférica (RR = 2,44; IC del 95%, 1,27-4,68), el exceso de HbA1c (RR = 2,08; IC del 95%, 1,22-3,57) y la obesidad (RR = 1,69; IC del 95%, 1,0-2,86). Conclusiones. La incidencia de ECV en esta población de pacientes del sur de Europa con diabetes tipo 2 e hipercolesterolemia es elevada. El hecho de haber presentado un episodio isquémico previo y el exceso de cLDL durante el seguimiento son los predictores más potentes del riesgo de presentar futuros episodios de ECV</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Cardiol;60(3): 251-258, mar. 2007. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-053674</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Factores predictivos del riesgo de enfermedad cardiovascular en los pacientes con diabetes tipo 2 e hipercolesterolemia. Estudio ESODIAH</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3946^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d34247^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2359^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28606</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7117^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8251</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200703</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
