<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-134304</identifier>
<setSpec>1134-928X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Proactive intervention from a geriatric unit in complex chronic patient's care admitted to an acute hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">We establish the Complex Chronic Patient (CCP) Care Program within the framework of the Catalonia's 2011-2015 Health Plan, in order to respond to a profile of patients in situation of clinical complexity. The interdisciplinary social-sanitary geriatric functional unit (UFIS) of the Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge (HUB) has implemented a proactive intervention program for CCPs whose age is equal to or greater than 80 years. Objectives: To describe the methodology for identifying and addressing the CCP and the strategies adopted to ensure the comprehensiveness, integration, and continuity of care. To analyze and describe the parameters used for the Global Geriatric Assessment (CGA) of the CCPs served by our unit. Methodology: Computerized medical records help identify CCPs entering the HUB. GGA is implemented within 24 hours after admission in order to avoid complications during admission, to establish the most appropriate device at the time of discharge, and to ensure continuity of care. Results and conclusions: We assessed 97 patients between October 2012 and February 2013. They entered mainly through emergencies from home, and were autonomous or with mild dependence for basic daily living activities before admission, with good cognitive status. At discharge most returned home with a Preparation for Discharge Protocol (PREALT) to ensure continuity of care. This intervention aims to reduce re-admissions, facilitate the return home and avoid or delay the institutionalization of the patient (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Cabot García, Carmen</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ortega Matas, M. Cristina</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Porras Tovar, Francisca</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pastor Maylin, Lourdes</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cantos Santamaría, M. Teresa</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fàbregas Lorenzo, Anna</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Dentro del marco del Pla de Salut de Catalunya 2011-2015 se establece el Programa de Atención del Paciente Crónico Complejo (PCC) para dar respuesta a un perfil de pacientes en situación de complejidad clínica. La unidad funcional interdisciplinar sociosanitaria de geriatría (UFIS) del Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge (HUB) ha implantado un programa de intervención proactiva de los PCC cuya edad es igual o mayor de 80 años. Objetivos: exponer la metodología en la identificación y atención de los PCC y las estrategias adoptadas para garantizar la atención integral, integrada y la continuidad asistencial. Analizar y describir los diferentes parámetros de la valoración geriátrica integral (VGI) a los PCC atendidos por nuestra unidad. Metodología: la historia clínica informatizada permite identificar a los PCC que ingresan en el HUB. Dentro de las primeras 24 h del ingreso, se realiza VGI con la finalidad de evitar complicaciones durante el ingreso, valorar el dispositivo más idóneo en el momento de alta y garantizar la continuidad asistencial. Resultados y conclusiones: se ha valorado a 97 pacientes entre los meses de octubre de 2012 y febrero de 2013, ambos inclusive. Ingresan fundamentalmente por vía de urgencias procedentes de su domicilio, autónomos o con dependencia leve para las actividades básicas de la vida diaria (ABVD) antes de su ingreso, con un buen estado cognitivo. Al alta hospitalaria la mayoría regresa a su domicilio con el protocolo de preparación al alta (PREALT) para garantizar la continuidad asistencial. Con esta intervención se pretende disminuir los reingresos hospitalarios, facilitar el retorno al domicilio y evitar o retrasar la institucionalización del paciente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gerokomos (Madr., Ed. impr.);25(4): 152-158, dic. 2014. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-134304</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Intervención proactiva desde una unidad de geriatría en la atención del paciente crónico complejo ingresado en un hospital de agudos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d3285^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28563^s22024</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9922^s22049</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9918^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24693^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
