<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-101616</identifier>
<setSpec>1139-9287</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychiatric disorders secondary to nonconvulsive status epilepticus of frontal origin. Two clinical case reports</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Non convulsive status epilepticus (NCSE) is common but often under-diagnosed. Due to the absence of specific symptoms, it is frequently misdiagnosed as a psychiatric disorder, which delays treatment. The cases of two patients who exhibited psychiatric symptoms and subtle cognitive disturbances (without confusion) as the sole manifestation of frontal lobe NCSE are reported. Both patients were initially treated as psychiatric disorders (depression and anorexia nervosa). The correct diagnosis was established by the electroencephalographic study, in one case after the patient experienced a generalized tonic-clonic seizure and in the other, after failure to improve with supposedly adequate treatment. There are reports of patients with NCSE whose symptoms suggest a psychiatric disorder (inappropriate behavior, emotional disinhibition, perseveration, reduced speech and motivation). This can occur without altered consciousness and symptoms may fluctuate, making the correct diagnosis extremely difficult. This entity can occur at any age and without a previous history of seizures. A high level of suspicion is necessary for prompt electroencephalographic study to confirm the diagnosis. Early treatment will correct the symptoms and significantly improve quality of life for patients and their families (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gabler-Santelices, Guillermo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Chicharro-Ciuffardi, Ada</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González-Silva, Mónica</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Marinis-Palombo, Alejandro de</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El estado epiléptico no convulsivo (EENC) es una entidad frecuente, aunque muchas veces subdiagnosticada. Debido a la ausencia de síntomas específicos es frecuentemente confundida inicialmente con trastornos psiquiátricos, lo que retarda el tratamiento. Presentamos dos pacientes que manifestaron síntomas psiquiátricos y trastornos cognitivos sutíles (sin confusión) como única manifestación de un estado epiléptico no convulsivo de orígen frontal. Ambos fueron tratados inicialmente como un trastorno psiquiátrico (depresión mayor y anorexia nerviosa). El diagnóstico correcto fue establecido con el estudio electroencefalográfico, realizado luego de que uno de los pacientes experimentara una crisis convulsiva y el otro no evidenciara mejoría con el tratamiento psiquiátrico. Existen reportes de pacientes con EENC cuyos síntomas sugieren un trastorno psiquiátrico (conducta inapropiada, desinhibición afectiva, perseverancia, reducción del lenguaje y desmotivación). Esto puede ocurrir sin compromiso de conciencia, y los síntomas pueden ser fluctuantes, lo que hace en ocasiones el diagnóstico muy difícil. Esta entidad puede ocurrir a cualquier edad y sin historia previa de crisis. Es necesario un alto nivel de sospecha para indicar la realización de un estudio electroencefalográfico para confirmar el diagnóstico. Un tratamiento precoz corregir á los síntomas y mejorará significativamente la calidad de vida del paciente y su familia (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Esp Psiquiatr;40(3): 155-160, mayo-jun. 2012. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-101616</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Trastornos psiquiátricos secundarios a estados epilépticos no convulsivos de origen frontal. A propósito de dos casos clínicos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22033</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s29166</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13612^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761^s22010</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5761^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201206</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
