<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-114553</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-573X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Recurrent pemphigoid gestationis in the puerperium</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Like other organs and systems, the skin undergoes changes during pregnancy, including physiological alterations such as chloasma or the development of stretch marks. However, the skin is also affected by other pathological changes present in the context of pregnancy-related diseases, such as intrahepatic cholestasis, or dermatoses, whether pregnancy-specific or not. Herpes gestationis is a pregnancy-specific dermatosis, whose onset usually occurs in the second half of gestation. Onset in the the postpartum period is much less frequent. The recurrence rate in subsequent pregnancies is very high. We describe the case of a patient who was diagnosed with herpes gestationis during the inmediate puerperium. The patient had previously developed this clinical entity in the postpartum period after her first pregnancy (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Vidal Hernández, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Leal Gómez, E</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Rial, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Robles Gaitero, M</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La piel sufre durante la gestación, al igual que otros órganos y sistemas corporales, cambios fisiológicos como el cloasma o la aparición de estrías. Sin embargo, es también subsidiaria de presentar otras alteraciones patológicas, en el contexto de una enfermedad del embarazo, como la colestasis intrahepática, o bien de una dermatosis, específica o no de la gestación. El herpes gestacional es una dermatosis específica del embarazo cuyo debut tiene lugar, generalmente, en la segunda mitad de la gestación y en un menor número de casos durante el puerperio y cuya tasa de recurrencia en sucesivos embarazos es muy elevada. Describimos el caso de una paciente diagnosticada durante el puerperio inmediato de herpes gestacional, cuadro clínico que había presentado también tras finalizar su primera gestación (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. investig. ginecol. obstet. (Ed. impr.);40(4): 179-182, jul.-ago. 2013. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-114553</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Penfigoide gestacional recidivante en el puerperio</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d11691^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29423^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29502^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13255^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201308</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
