<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-88740</identifier>
<setSpec>0004-0614</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Flexible ureterorenoscopy (URS): technique and results</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">OBJECTIVES: This paper has two main objectives: First, to expose the URS technique used in our Department because there are important differences with respect to others centres published, explaining same aspect that can benefit to the better development of the technique. Second, we present the results of a series of 100 cases. Flexible ureterorenoscopy (Flex URS) has been little used to date, mainly because of the technical difficulties created by the deficient quality of the instruments used, such as ureteroscopes offering scant visibility, poor illumination, a small working channel, deficient quality of the forceps and baskets, etc.                           METHODS: We present our recent series of flexible URS for the treatment of renal lithiasis.We performes a retrospective analysis of this treatment corresponding to the period between January 2007 and March 2010. In this period we have treated 100 patients.The medium size of the stone treated is 1.5cm (0.5-6cm) and we used ureteroscopic protector sheath in all cases. The lithotripter system used in all cases was Ho:YAG Laser with 200 and 365 micras fibersRESULTS: The stone-free rate (SFR) in the immediate postoperative period was 77% (77/100 patients). Residual stones, defined as stone fragments visualized in the operating room via fluoroscopy and directly with the flexible ureteroscope.Three months after surgery, the SFR was 92.7% (89/96 patients) confirmed by intravenous urography. Regarding complications, we had 5 patients with ureteral lesions during protector sheath pass and 9 patients that presented at the emergency room with pain secondary to the double J catheter.CONCLUSIONS: Flexible URS for of renal lithiasis can be defended in stones measuring up to 2 cm in diameter, based on our treatment algorithm(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Aguilera Bazán, Alfredo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Peña Barthel, Javier de la Peña</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rando Tous, Alberto</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cansino Alcaide, José Ramón</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Sánchez, David</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hidalgo Togores, Luís</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Reinoso Elbers, Javier</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez González, Sonia</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">OBJETIVO: Los objetivos fundamentales de éste trabajo son dos. Por una parte exponer la técnica empleada en nuestro Servicio ya que difiere en algunos aspectos importantes de las publicadas en otros centros, explicando en algunos casos pequeños detalles que pueden ayudar al mejor desarrollo de la técnica. Por otra parte, exponemos los resultados de una serie de 100 casos.MÉTODOS: Presentamos nuestra serie reciente de URS Flex para el tratamiento de la litiasis renal. Para ello hemos revisado de forma retrospectiva éste tratamiento desde Enero de 2007 hasta Marzo de 2010. El tamaño medio de la litiasis tratada es de 1.5cm (0.5-6cms) y en todos los casos utilizamos vainas protectoras del ureteroscopio. La litotricia empleada en todos los casos fue láser de holmio con fibras de 200 y 365 micrasRESULTADOS: El porcentaje de pacientes que quedaron libres de litiasis (stone free rate-SFR) tras la cirugía en el postoperatorio inmediato fue de 77/100 pacientes (77%) contabilizando como resto litiásico fragmentos visualizados mediante la fluoroscopia del quirófano y la visión directa del URS Flex. A los 3 meses de la cirugía 89/96 pacientes (92.7%) estaban libres de litiasis comprobado mediante urografía intravenosa.Respecto a las complicaciones destacar 5 pacientes con lesión ureteral durante la colocación de la vaina protectora y 9 pacientes que acudieron a urgencias en el postoperatorio por molestias secundarias al catéter doble J.CONCLUSIÓN: Como conclusión podemos defender el tratamiento de las litiasis renales mediante URS Flex hasta un tamaño máximo de 2 cm siguiendo nuestro algoritmo terapéutico(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Arch Esp Urol;63(10): 862-870, dic. 2010. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-88740</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">URS Flexible. Técnica y resultados</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22004</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23501^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14912^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d52124^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31988^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33778^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31988^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31988^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201012</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
