<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-052530</identifier>
<setSpec>1575-0922</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Patient with behavioral alterations</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Sixty percent of pancreatic tumors are insulinomas (90% benign and isolated; 10% multiple, usually associated with multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1, and 5-10% malignant). Because of the possibility of recurrence, accurate diagnosis and long-term follow-up are essential. We present the case of a 74-year-old man who presented with behavioral alterations related to recurrent hypoglycemic episodes. Fasting test, several imaging techniques, and fine-needle aspiration biopsy of a hepatic lesion were performed and a malignant insulinoma was diagnosed. We discuss the distinct diagnostic and treatment options in this kind of neoplasm (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Díaz, José Ángel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Ferre, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lecumberri, Edurne</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El insulinoma constituye el 60% de los tumores que asientan en el páncreas, de los cuales el 90% son benignos y únicos; el 10% son múltiples, la mayoría asociados a MEN 1 y el 5-10% son malignos. La posibilidad de recidiva obliga a un diagnóstico y seguimiento a largo plazo. Presentamos el caso de un varón de 74 años en el que se inicia un cuadro de alteración de la conducta relacionado con episodios de hipoglucemia repetidos. Tras los resultados del test de ayuno, las pruebas de imagen y la punción-aspiración con aguja fina de la lesión hepática, se diagnostica de insulinoma maligno. Se discute acerca de las distintas opciones diagnósticas y terapéuticas del insulinoma maligno (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Endocrinol Nutr;54(4): 232-235, abr. 2007. ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-052530</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Paciente con alteración de la conducta</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24375</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7510^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7510^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7510^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10378^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38338</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200704</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
