<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-049220</identifier>
<setSpec>0001-6519</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Distant metastases in head and neck cancer</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: The presence of distant metastasis        (DM) after the initial treatment of head and neck squamous        cell carcinoma (HNSCC) is not considered a common event        and it is associated to a poor outcome. Purpose: To investigate        the prevalence and risk factors associated with the        diagnosis of distant metastasis in SCC. Methods and Materials:        A retrospective study of 633 patients with HNSCC to        describe the clinical characteristics of the DM. Results: During        the follow-up period after the initial treatment, 6.2% of        the patients were diagnosed of having distant metastasis.        The site of primary tumor was hypopharynx in 14.4%, unknown        origin in 11.8% and oropharynx in 8.5%. The most        common sites of DM were the lungs (58%) and the bone        (22%). Three year overall survival in patients with DM was        2.5% (versus 49,5% in the control group). Conclusions: This        study confirms that DM have an adverse impact in survival.        There is a need of guidelines for screening of distant        metastases in patients with HNSCC in order to get an early        diagnosis and a more effective treatment. Because of the poor        prognosis of DM, protocols including adjuvant chemotherapy        should be investigated</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Llorente Pendás, JL</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Suárez Nieto, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hermsen, M </dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Álvarez Marcos, CA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Franco Gutiérrez, V</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cuesta Albalad, MP</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Espina, H</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La presencia de metástasis a distancia        (MD) no es un evento muy frecuente en los carcinomas        de cabeza y cuello (CECC) y se asocia con muy mal pronóstico.        Objetivo: Investigar la las principales características clínicas        y factores de riesgo asociados con el diagnóstico de        MD en CECC. Material y método: Estudio retrospectivo de        633 pacientes con CECC para describir las características clínicas        de las MD. Resultados: Se observan en el 6,2% de los        CECC. Las localizaciones que más las originan son la hipofaringe        (14,4%), los primarios de origen desconocido (11,8%)        y la orofaringe (8,5%), apareciendo con mayor frecuencia en        pulmón (58%) y hueso (22%). Determinan un gran impacto        en la supervivencia, reduciéndola al 2,5% a los 3 años        (49,5% en el grupo control a los 5 años). Conclusiones: Es        preciso realizar un seguimiento adecuado para su detección        precoz y tratamiento eficaz, investigando nuevos protocolos        terapéuticos que incluyan la quimioterapia</dc:description>
<dc:source>Acta Otorrinolaringol Esp;57(8): 369-372, oct. 2006. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-049220</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Metástasis a distancia en el cáncer de cabeza y cuello</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22064</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28604</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6409^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2337^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200610</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
