<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-78879</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychometric properties of the GHQ-28 in opiate-dependent patients</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To know the psychometric properties of the GHQ-28 when it is applied to a sample of opiate-dependent patients. Method: Participants were 138 opiate-dependent patients. Reliability was estimated by means of the Cronbach&#146;s alpha and Spearman-Brown coefficients. Confirmatory Factor Analysis was applied to check the four-factor structure proposed by Goldberg and Hillier. The sensitivity and specificity of the instrument for the detection of possible psychiatric cases were measured using ROC (Receiver Operating Characteristic) analysis, using as criterion the DSMIV diagnosis from the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview. Results: Reliability estimation was adequate. Validity results could not confirm the four-factor structure of GHQ-28 proposed by Goldberg and Hillier. The sensitivity and specificity parameters show optimum values of 60.7 % and 73.7 %, respectively, 65.9 % of the participants being correctly classified. Conclusions: GHQ-28 shows adequate reliability and appropriate sensitivity and specificity parameters when it is applied to opiate-dependent patients. However, the original factorial structure could not be confirmed. Given these results and those from other validity studies in which the relationships with Severity of Dependence, Physical Health and Health-Related Quality of Life were shown, the GHQ-28 can be considered a useful instrument for screening in clinical practice (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Lozano Rojas, Oscar M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rojas Tejada, Antonio J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Moreno, Pedro</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Conocer las propiedades psicométricas del GHQ-28 cuando se administra a una muestra de pacientes con dependencia a opiáceos. Método: 138 pacientes con diagnóstico de dependencia a opiáceos han participado en el estudio. La fiabilidad se ha estimado por el procedimiento alpha de Cronbach y dos mitades con Spearman-Brown. Se ha aplicado un análisis factorial confirmatorio para conocer la estructura factorial del instrumento. La sensibilidad y especificidad del instrumento para la detección de posibles casos psiquiátricos se ha realizado mediante el estudio de la curva COR (Característica Operativa del Receptor), usando como criterio el diagnóstico DSM-IV aportado por la Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview. Resultados: Los resultados de la estimación de la fiabilidad del instrumento son adecuados. En cuanto a los resultados de validez no se ha podido confirmar la estructura de cuatro factores delGHQ-28 propuesta originariamente por Goldberg y Hillier. Los parámetros de sensibilidad y especificidad muestran unos valores óptimos de 60,7%y 73,7% respectivamente, estando correctamente clasificados el 65,9%de los participantes. Conclusiones: El GHQ-28 muestra una adecuada fiabilidad si bien no se ha podido confirmar la estructura factorial original. Los parámetros de sensibilidad y especificidad son apropiados. Dados estos resultados y los proporcionados por otros estudios de validez donde se muestra la relación con la severidad de la dependencia, la salud física y la calidad de vida relacionada con la salud, se puede considerar que el GHQ-28 puede ser un instrumento útil para el screening en la práctica clínica (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);22(1): 65-72, ene.-mar. 2010. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-78879</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Propiedades psicométricas del GHQ-28 en pacientes con dependencia a opiáceos</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d37719</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28624</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29310</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28608^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9488^s22016</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24572</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12031^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201001</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
