<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-75324</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Publications on Women, Health and Gender in Spain (1990-2005)</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: The studies on women, gender and health areincreasingly more frequent in Spain. This research is aimed atascertaining the topics dealt with in these publications, the disciplinesstudying said topics, the sex of the leading author and whetherthese topics have been approached from a gender-related standpoint.Methods: A search was conducted for published studies inBiomedicine, Sociology, Nursing, Anthropology and Psychologydatabases. The main key words used were [women or gender] and[health] and [Spain]. Original articles, reviews and monographicstudies, both national and international, published within the1990-2005 period were included. The variables taken into considerationwere the topic of study, field of expertise, gender focusand sex of those publishing the work. A total of 298 works wereincluded.Results: The topics dealt with the most were sexual and reproductivehealth (39.2%) and mental health (12.4%). A total of 58.7%of the works were authored by a woman as the leading author and47.3% had no gender focus. A total of 85.3% of the publications onsexual and reproductive health do not incorporate the gender standpoint,whilst 94.1% of the works on productive and reproductivework did however include this standpoint. A total of 80.4% of theworks in Biomedicine have no gender focus.Conclusions: Even though they are scarce, the works having agender focus are signed mostly by women as the leading authors. Inthe material studied, women's health continues to be confined toreproduction, it being necessary for other factors having a direct bearingon women's health to be included(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Ruiz-Pérez, Isabel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castaño-López, Esther</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bolívar-Muñoz, Julia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Plazaola-Castaño, Juncal</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Los estudios sobre mujeres, género y salud soncada vez más frecuentes en España. El objetivo de esta investigaciónha sido conocer los temas tratados en estas publicaciones, las disciplinasque los estudian, el sexo de la persona que firma en primerlugar y si han sido abordadas con enfoque de género.Métodos: Se llevó a cabo una búsqueda bibliográfica en bases dedatos de Biomedicina, Sociología, Enfermería, Antropología y Psicología.Las principales palabras clave empleadas fueron [mujeres ogénero] y [salud] y [España]. Se incluyeron artículos originales, revisionesy monografías, nacionales e internacionales, publicadas entre1990 y 2005. Las variables contempladas fueron el tema de estudio,área de conocimiento, enfoque de género y sexo de la primera autoría.Se incluyeron 298 trabajos.Resultados: Los temas más abordados son salud sexual y reproductiva(39,2%) y salud mental (12,4%). El 58,7% de los trabajos tienencomo primera autora a una mujer y el 47,3% no tienen enfoquede género. El 85,3% de las publicaciones sobre salud sexual y reproductivano incorporan la perspectiva de género, mientras el 94,1% delos trabajos sobre trabajo productivo y reproductivo sí. El 80,4% delos trabajos en medicina no tienen enfoque de género.Conclusiones: Los trabajos con enfoque de género están firmadosmayoritariamente por mujeres como primeras autoras, si bienson escasos. En el material estudiado, la salud de las mujeres siguecircunscribiéndose a la reproducción, siendo necesario incorporarotros determinantes de salud(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;80(6): 705-716, nov.-dic.2006. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-75324</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Publicaciones sobre mujeres, salud y género en España (1990-2005)</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50261</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1325</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29154</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d10697^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200612</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
