<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111569</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mental Health at School</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Mental disorders have a major impact on children&#146;s emotional and intellectual development, with a noticeable influence on all learning processes. The school is a particularly good place where to prevent, diagnose and approach mental health and behavioral problems. Even though there are not many epidemiological data, those available inform about the relevance of these disorders in the child and adolescent population, and its consequences upon the adult individual. According to a report by the WHO, it is estimated that approximately 5-15% of the child population shows psychological disorders which have a severe effect upon the child&#146;s social life. The present article, focused on the intervention of the school nurse in mental health problems within the educational setting, is the seventh in a series of nine, which intends to make public this emerging nurse profile (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>García Marina, M. Concepción</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>González Prieto, Noemí Irma</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Langa, Natividad</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Los trastornos mentales tienen enormes repercusiones en el desarrollo emocional e intelectual de los niños, con una marcada influencia en todos los procesos de aprendizaje. La escuela es un lugar privilegiado para prevenir, diagnosticar y abordar los problemas de salud mental y conducta. Aunque los datos epidemiológicos son escasos, los que existen dan cuenta de la relevancia de estos trastornos en la población infanto-juvenil y sus repercusiones en el individuo adulto. Según un informe de la OMS se estima que aproximadamente el 5-15% de la población infantil presenta trastornos psicológicos que afectan gravemente a la vida social del niño. El presente artículo, centrado en la intervención de la enfermera escolar en los problemas de salud mental en el ámbito educativo, es el séptimo de una serie de nueve, que persigue dar a conocer este perfil enfermero emergente (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;16(3): 70-74, abr. 2013. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111569</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">La salud mentalen la escuela</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4589^s22066</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12954^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28480^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8771^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201304</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
