<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-036415</identifier>
<setSpec>0025-7753</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Mortality after hip fracture: a three year follow-up study</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">BACKGROUND AND OBJECTIVE: We designed this study to know the mortality rate of hip fractures after 3 years of follow-up. PATIENTS AND METHOD: We admitted 194 patients with hip fractures (cases) from our reference hospitals and 184 without hip fractures (control) who were selected from an ambulatory health centre. After 3 years, morbidity and mortality causes were analyzed using medical records. RESULTS: Mortality rate in cases was 40% compared with only 16.5% in patients without hip fracture (control group) (p = 0,000; non adjusted RR = 2.4; adjusted RR = 3.9). In the multivariant analysis, age (RR = 1.1), heart failure (RR = 2.5),neoplasia (RR = 3.5), dementia (RR = 5) and hipfracture were independently associated with mortality after 3 years of follow-up. CONCLUSIONS: Patients with hip fracture showed a higher mortality (24%) than thosewithout hip fracture after 3 years of follow-up</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Alabart Teixidó, Andreu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Tobias Ferrer, Joan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Zorrilla Ribeiro, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Brossa Torruella, August</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Belmonte Garridof, Montserrat</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>López Borras, Ester</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">FUNDAMENTO Y OBJETIVO: Se ha diseñado un estudio de cohortes históricas para conocer la mortalidad y las variables asociadas con la fractura de fémur. PACIENTES Y MÉTODO: Se incluyeron 194 casos con fractura del extremo proximal del fémur (FEPF) procedentes de los hospitales, y 184 pacientes sin FEPF procedentes del ámbito de atención primaria. Se registraron la mortalidad y las causas de morbimortalidad. RESULTADOS: A los 3 años, la mortalidad fuedel 40% en los casos, y del 16,5% en los controles (riesgo relativo [RR] no ajustado =2,4; p &lt; 0,01; RR ajustado = 3,9). En el análisis multivariante, las variables edad (RR =1,1), insuficiencia cardíaca (RR = 2,5), neoplasias(RR = 3,5) y demencia (RR = 5,0) se asociaron con la mortalidad. CONCLUSIONES: La mortalidad de los casos fue un 24% superior a los controles de la misma edad y sexo</dc:description>
<dc:source>Med. clín (Ed. impr.);124(2): 53-54, ene. 2005. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-036415</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Mortalidad a los tres años de los pacientes con fractura de fémur</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5368^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9562^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3718^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6486^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29362</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24551</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200501</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
