<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-147171</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Efficacy of the retroperitoneal-assisted laparoscopic pyeloplasty versus the mini posterior lumbotomy approach</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective. To evaluate the results of the retroperitoneal-assisted laparoscopic pyeloplasty (RALP) versus the mini posterior lumbotomy pyeloplasty (MPLP). Material and Methods. A retrospective study of 77 patients diagnosed with ureteropelvic junction obstruction between 2007 and 2013 was made, analyzing the surgical technique, complications and results. The anteroposterior pelvic diameter of the kidney, the thickness of the renal parenchyma, the renal function and the morphology of the renogram curve were also evaluated and compared. Results. We performed 50 RALP and 21 MPLP. Median age of intervention: 10.85 moths (ICR 86.8) in RALP and 23.30 moths (ICR 54.7) in MPLP. No significant differences were found in surgical time (p&gt;0.05). Double J was left in 90% of the RALP and 52.4% of the MPLP. Median length of incision was 1.5 cm of the RALP and 3.0cm in MPLP(p0,05). The follow-up was performed using ultrasound in an average of 68,04 months of age (range 7.5-186.5) and diuretic renogram in an average of 50,25 months of age (range 6,6-173,8). The above parameters showed improvements in both groups of patients without significant differences. Conclusions. In our experience, the RALP is a technique with a greater rate of complications than the expected. Moreover, the MPLP, is a technique we consider safe and with adequate aesthetic and functional results (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gracia Romero, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Atuan, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Rihuete Heras, MA</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bragagnini Rodríguez, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Delgado Alvira, R</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Estors Sastre, B</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo. Evaluar la pieloplastia asistida por retroperitoneoscopia, exteriorizando la unión pieloureteral (PAR) versus la pieloplastia por minilumbotomía posterior en ángulo costovertebral (PMLP). Material y Métodos. Estudio retrospectivo de 77 pacientes diagnosticados de estenosis pieloureteral (2007-2013), se analizaron técnica, complicaciones y resultados, mediante la valoración del diámetro anteroposterior de la pelvis renal, grosor del parénquima renal, función renal y morfología de la curva del renograma. Resultados. Realizamos 50 PAR y 21 PMLP. Edad mediana de intervención: 10,85 meses [rango intercuartílico (IC) 86,8] en PAR y 23,3 meses (rango IC 54,7) en PMLP. No hubo diferencias significativas en tiempo quirúrgico. Se dejó doble J en 90% de las PAR y en 52,4% de las PMLP. La incisión fue 1,5 cm en la PAR y 3,0 cm de mediana (rango IC 1,0) en la PMLP (p0,05). El seguimiento mediante ecografía en una media de 68,04 meses de edad (rango 7,5-186,5) y renograma diurético en una media de 50,25 meses de edad (rango 6,6-173,8), evidenciaron mejora en los parámetros arriba señalados en ambos grupos de pacientes, sin diferencias significativas. Conclusiones. En nuestra serie, la PAR es un abordaje con un índice de complicaciones mayor al esperado. Por otra parte, la PMLP es un abordaje seguro y con resultados estéticos y funcionales adecuados (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;28(2): 49-54, abr. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-147171</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Eficacia de la pieloplastia asistida por retroperitoneoscopia versus a la realizada por minilumbotomía posterior</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7022^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d36296^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7857^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23500^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2715</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30912^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d14924^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201504</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
