<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-166894</identifier>
<setSpec>0211-6995</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Calciphylaxis: Beyond CKD-MBD</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Calcific uraemic arteriolopathy (CUA), also called calciphylaxis, is a rare but potentially fatal vascular disorder that almost exclusively affects patients with chronic renal failure. The objective of this study was to analyse various risk factors for developing CUA and its subsequent clinical course according to the treatment received. Materials and methods: A retrospective study that included patients diagnosed with CUA from December 1999 to December 2015. Various risk factors, clinical course and treatment options were analysed. Results: A total of 28 patients (53.6% females) with a mean age of 67.2±11.8 (38-88) years were included. At the time of diagnosis, 53.6% were on haemodialysis, 25% were kidney transplant patients and 21.4% had normal renal function. The use of steroids (100%, P=.001) was the main risk factor in renal transplant patients. Skin lesions resolved in 60.7% (especially in those receiving multitargeted therapy). Patient survival at 12 months was 29% in transplant patients, 57% in haemodialysis patients and 100% in normal renal function patients (log-rank 6.88, P=.032). Chronic renal failure (P=.03) and hypoalbuminaemia (P=.02) were the main risk factor for CUA mortality. Conclusions: Although the incidence of CUA remains low, CUA mortality is very high, Special attention to its occurrence in kidney transplant patients and «non-renal» CUA forms is required. Oral anticoagulants and steroids appear to be the main risk factors, CUA is a challenge; a registry of patients and determining standard therapy are required  (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Praga, Manuel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Polanco, Natalia</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Mérida, Eva</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Morales, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández, María</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gutierrez, Eduardo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La arteriolopatía urémica calcificante (CUA), también llamada calcifilaxis, es un trastorno vascular poco frecuente pero potencialmente mortal que afecta casi exclusivamente a pacientes con insuficiencia renal crónica. El objetivo de este estudio fue analizar los diferentes factores de riesgo para el desarrollo de CUA y su posterior evolución según la terapia recibida. Material y métodos: Estudio retrospectivo que recoge aquellos pacientes con diagnóstico de CUA desde diciembre de 1999 hasta diciembre de 2015. Se analizaron diferentes factores de riesgo, evolución y diferentes opciones terapéuticas. Resultados: Se incluyeron 28 pacientes (53,6% mujeres) con una edad media de 67,2±11,8 años (38-88). En el momento del diagnóstico, el 53,6% estaba en hemodiálisis, un 25% eran pacientes con un trasplante renal y el 21,4% presentaba función renal normal. En los pacientes trasplantados, el consumo de esteroides (100%; p=0,001) fue el principal factor de riesgo. La resolución de lesiones cutáneas se produjo en el 60,7% (especialmente en los que recibieron tratamiento multitarget). La supervivencia de los pacientes a los 12meses fue de 29, 57 y 100% en los pacientes trasplantados, hemodiálisis y con función renal normal respectivamente (log-rank 6,88; p=0,032). La presencia de insuficiencia renal crónica (p=0,03) e hipoalbuminemia (p=0,02) fueron los principales factores de riesgo de mortalidad CUA. Conclusión: Aunque la incidencia de la CUA sigue siendo baja, su mortalidad es muy elevada, por lo que debe prestarse especial atención a la presentación de la CUA en los trasplantados renales y en las formas «no renales». Los anticoagulantes orales y los esteroides aparecen como principales factores de riesgo. La CUA es un reto: necesitamos un registro de nuestros pacientes y establecer una terapia estándar (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Nefrologia;37(5): 501-507, sept.-oct. 2017. graf, atb, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-166894</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Calcifilaxis: más allá de CKD-MBD</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d13642^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d932^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50497^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31085^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2149^s22032</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201710</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
