<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-111452</identifier>
<setSpec>1888-6116</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Study of the benefit of an exercise programme and branched amino acid supplements in patients with liver cirrhosis</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objetive: To evaluate the efficacy and safety of an exercise programme to increase muscle mass, effort tolerance and quality of life in cirrhotic patients. Patients and methods: Seventeen compensated cirrhotic patients were randomized into either an exercise group (n=8) or a control group (n=9). The programme of moderate exercise was given for 12 weeks. All patients received oral leucine (10 g/day) during the study. Anthropometric measurements, effort tolerance and quality of life were determined at study start and end. We also analysed the safety during the study. Results: In the exercise group thigh circumference increased (p=0.02) and effort tolerance improved (p=0.01) and 2-min step test (p=0.02). Moreover, quality of life improved significantly in this group. In the control group there were no statistically significant changes in any of the studied parameters. We did not observe complications of cirrhosis in either group. Conclusion: Our results suggest that moderate physical exercise in patients with compensated cirrhosis is safe and improves quality of life, effort tolerance and muscle mass (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Villanueva, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Torrades, M. T</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Soriano, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Vidal, S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cárdenas, G</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Córdoba, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nieto, J. C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Juárez, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Guarner, C</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Nadal, M. J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Bascuñana, H</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Román, E</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Analizar un programa de ejercicio físico moderado y sus efectos sobre la masa muscular y la tolerancia al esfuerzo en pacientes con cirrosis. Pacientes y métodos: Se estudiaron 17 pacientes con cirrosis hepática compensada divididos aleatoriamente en dos grupos: grupo ejercicio (n=8), que realizó un programa de ejercicio físico moderado durante 12 semanas, y grupo control (n=9). Todos los pacientes recibieron 10 g/día de leucina. Se analizaron cambios antropométricos, tolerancia al ejercicio y calidad de vida; además, se evaluó la seguridad durante el programa. Resultados: En el grupo ejercicio se observó un aumento en el perímetro del m. cuádriceps (p=0,02) y una mejora de la tolerancia al esfuerzo en el test de la marcha (p=0,01) y el test de los escalones (p=0,02). Además, en este grupo mejoró la calidad de vida de forma significativa. No observamos complicaciones de la cirrosis, deterioro hemodinámico o de la función renal en ninguno de los dos grupos durante el estudio. Conclusión: El ejercicio físico moderado en pacientes con cirrosis compensada es seguro, aumenta la masa muscular y mejora la tolerancia al esfuerzo y la calidad de vida (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Trauma (Majadahonda);24(1): 6-11, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-111452</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Estudio del beneficio de un programa de ejercicio físico y suplementos de aminoácidos ramificados en la dieta dirigido a pacientes con cirrosis hepática</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22039</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d27937^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22067</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d601^s22044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23631^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8276^s22009</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8108^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d601^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
