<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-140234</identifier>
<setSpec>1138-7262</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">The attitude of nursing students towards persons with disability</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: to analyze the attitude towards persons with disability of students of Degree in Nursing from the Escuela de Enfermería (School of Nursing) de la Fe (University of Valencia). Method: a transversal descriptive study with 284 students of Degree in Nursing from the Escuela de Enfermería La Fe who completed the Scale of Attitudes towards the Persons with Disability (EAPD-G), which includes five sub-scales. Other variables: gender, age, having been in contact with disabled persons. Analysis: hypothesis contrast through Pearson&#146;s Chi Square Test, odd ratios (ORs) estimation and 95% Confidence Intervals (CI 95 %). Results: the survey was answered by 217 students. In subscale 2 (acknowledgement / denial of rights), &gt; 40-year old students showed a better attitude than &lt; 20-year-old students (OR: 4.18; CI95%: 0.98-17.77). In sub-scale 4 (generic description), &gt; 40-year-old students had a 14 times higher likelihood vs. &lt; 20-year-old to describe disabled persons adequately (OR: 14.06; CI95%: 1.69-116). The likelihood to assess the abilities of disabled persons was higher in those who had had contact with disabled persons vs. those who had not (OR: 1.77; CI 95 %: 1.03-3.13). Conclusions: as the age of students increases, there is a better attitude shown in the acknowledgement of rights and the generic description of disabled persons. Previous contact with disabled persons will improve the score in the sub-scale Assessment of Abilities. No differences by gender were observed (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Munsuri Rosado, José</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pinazo Hernandis, Sacramento</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: analizar las actitudes hacia las personas con discapacidad de estudiantes de Grado de Enfermería de la Escuela de Enfermería de la Fe (Universidad de Valencia). Método: estudio descriptivo transversal en 284 estudiantes de Grado de Enfermería de la Escuela de Enfermería La Fe que cumplimentaron la escala de evaluación de actitudes hacia las personas con discapacidad (EAPD-G) que contiene cinco subescalas. Otras variables son: sexo, edad, haber mantenido contacto con personas discapacitadas. Análisis: contraste de hipótesis mediante Chi Cuadrado de Pearson, cálculo odds ratios (OR) e intervalos de confianza al 95% de seguridad (IC95%) Resultados: contestaron 217 estudiantes. En la subescala 2 (reconocimiento/negación de derechos), los alumnos mayores de cuarenta años tenían mejor actitud que los menores de 20 (OR: 4,18; IC95%: 0,98-17,77). En la subescala 4 (calificación genérica), los mayores de 40 años tenían 14 veces más probabilidad respecto a los menores de 20 de calificar adecuadamente a las  personas con discapacidad (OR: 14,06; IC 95%: 1,69-116). La probabilidad de valorar las capacidades de las personas con discapacidad era mayor en quienes habían tenido dicho contacto con estas personas respecto a quienes no (OR: 1,77; IC 95%: 1,03-3,13). Conclusiones: a medida que aumenta la edad de los alumnos/ as hay una mejor actitud reflejada en el reconocimiento de derechos y en la calificación genérica de las personas con discapacidad. El contacto previo con personas con discapacidad mejora la puntuación en la subescala valoración de las capacidades. No se observaron diferencias de género (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Metas enferm;18(6): 22-26, jul.-ago. 2015. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-140234</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Actitudes de los estudiantes de Enfermería hacia las personas con discapacidad</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d4245</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13725^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23897</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28571</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d30935</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201508</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
