<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-127341</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-1221</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Enterocolitis associated with Hirschsprung&#146;s Disease.  Experience in a pediatric teaching hospital</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Hirschsprung&#146;s associated enterocolitis (HAEC) is the most serious and potentially fatal complication of the disease, with a significant morbidity and mortality. The effect of HAEC varies remarkably among the publications since the lack of consensus and the absence of established diagnostic criteria. Patients diagnosed with Hirschsprung&#146;s disease (HD) were selected and treated between January 2009 and December 2012 in Fundación HOMI, finding 41 cases of HD, 6 of them with total aganglionosis. 76% of the patients had HAEC, 18 of them during the neonatal period and 6 of them after the final pull-through; 23% presented recurrent enterocolitis episodes. HAEC was the first clinical manifestation in 25 (61%) of the patients with HD. From HD patients limited to the rectum and sigmoid 67% had enterocolitis unlike TCA (total colonic agangliniosis) cases in which all presented HAEC episodes. In our setting, HAEC remains to be an unknown complication; this revision demonstrates its high incidence and mortality (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Niño Salcedo, J. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Perilla López, M. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaramillo Barberi, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fierro Ávila, F</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Jaimes de la Hoz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Méndez Manchola, M</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García Giraldo, A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Castañeda Espinosa, S</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">La enterocolitis asociada a la enfermedad de Hirschsprung (EAEH) es la complicación más grave y potencialmente fatal de la enfermedad, con una morbilidad y mortalidad significativas. La incidencia de EAEH varía notablemente entre las publicaciones dada la falta de consenso y la ausencia de criterios diagnósticos establecidos. Se seleccionaron los pacientes con diagnóstico de enfermedad de Hirschsprung (EH) tratados entre Enero de 2009 a Diciembre de 2012 en la Fundación Hospital de La Misericordia (HOMI) encontrando 41 casos de EH, 6 de ellos con aganglionosis total. En el 76% de los pacientes se realizó el diagnóstico de EAEH, 18 de ellos en el periodo neonatal y 6, tras el descenso defnitivo; 23% presentaron episodios de enterocolitis recurrente. La EAEH fue la primera manifestación clínica en 25 (61%) de los pacientes con EH. De los pacientes con EH limitada al recto y sigmoides, un 67% tuvieron enterocolitis a diferencia de los casos de aganglionosis total del colon (ATC), donde todos presentaron episodios de EAEH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Cir Pediatr;27(2): 78-83, abr. 2014. ilus, tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-127341</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Enterocolitis asociada a enfermedad de Hirschsprung.  Experiencia en un Hospital Universitario Pediátrico</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7399</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12508^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22226</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d4840^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11622^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d6786^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201404</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
