<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-74755</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Norovirus outbreaks in hospitals and nursing homes in Catalonia, Spain</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background. The low infectious dose and multipletransmission routes favour the appearance of norovirusoutbreaks. The objective of this study was to compare theincidence of norovirus outbreaks in hospitals and nursinghomes in Catalonia.Methods. A descriptive study of norovirus outbreaksbetween 15/10/2004 and 30/10/2005 was carried out. Anepidemiological survey was completed for each outbreak.Norovirus in clinical samples was determined by PCRtechniques. The incidence in each centre and the annualincidence of outbreaks by centre were calculated. Differenceswere calculated using the chi-square test and the Student&#146;s ttest, taking a p value of &gt; 0.05 as significant.Results. Seventeen outbreaks (6 in hospitals and 11 innursing homes) were detected. The global attack rate was33.4% (652/1951) and was slightly higher in nursing homes(35.2%) than in hospitals (31.4%).A total of 94.1% (16/17) of outbreaks were caused byperson-to-person transmission and only 5.9% (1/17) by foods.The mean number of days between the first and last case was11.4 (SD = 6.9).The mean duration of symptoms was 2.39 days (SD=1.6),and was higher hospitals, 2.63 (SD=1.7), than in nursinghomes, 1.97 (SD=1.7) (p &lt; 0.0001).Conclusions. Norovirus is responsible for a large numberof outbreaks due to person-to-person transmission. Controlshould be standardized to reduce the number and duration ofoutbreaks(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Grupo de estudio de gastroenteritis víricas en Cataluña</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamentos. La baja dosis infectiva y las múltiples víasde transmisión facilitan la presentación de brotes de norovirus.El objetivo fue comparar la incidencia de brotes por norovirusen hospitales y residencias en Cataluña.Métodos. Se realizó un estudio descriptivo de la serie debrotes de norovirus en el período del 15/10/2004 al 30/10/2005.Se rellenó una encuesta epidemiológica para cada brote. Lasvariables fueron: número de expuestos, enfermos, mecanismo detransmisión, ámbito (centros sanitarios o residencias), regiónsanitaria, mes del año, y duración. Mediante técnicas de PCR seinvestigó la presencia de norovirus en muestras clínicas. Se calculóla incidencia en cada centro y la incidencia anual de brotespor centros. Las diferencias se determinaron con la prueba de c2y la t de Student con un grado de significación (p) inferior a 0,05.Resultados. Se detectaron 17 brotes, 6 en centros sanitariosy 11 en residencias. La tasa de ataque global fue del33,4% (652/1951) y fue ligeramente superior en las residencias(35,2%) que en los centros sanitarios (31,4%).El 94,1% (16/17) de los brotes se produjeron por transmisiónpersona a persona y sólo el 5,9% (1/17) por alimentos. Lamedia de días entre el primer y último caso del brote fue de11,4 (DE = 6,9).La duración media de los síntomas fue de 2,39 días(SD=1,6) y también fue superior en los pacientes hospitalizados2,63 (SD=1,7) en comparación a los pacientes de residencias1,97 (SD=1,7) (p &lt; 0,0001).Conclusiones. Norovirus es responsable de un númeroimportante de brotes por transmisión persona a persona. Se debeprotocolizar su control para reducir su número y su duración(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;83(5): 745-750, sep.-oct.2009. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-74755</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brotes por norovirus en residencias y centros sanitarios de Cataluña</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35604^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5900^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28589^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31757^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28320^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28477^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d31799^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200910</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
