<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-90653</identifier>
<setSpec>1135-5727</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Tonsillopharyngitis outbreak caused by foodborne group A beta-hemolytic streptococcus</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Background: Although infrequent, some authors have reported outbreaks of foodborne tonsillopharyngitis. On May 11, 2010 a series of cases of tonsillopharyngitis among those attending a fellowship meeting on 8 March was notified to the Epidemiological Surveillance Network in Andalusia (SVEA). The aim of this study is to epidemiologically characterise the outbreak . Methods: Descriptive analysis of reported cases and case -control exposure to the implicated food. The variables taken into account were age, sex, symptoms and start date. Sources of information used were the records of the SVEA and individual digital report (DIRAYA). Frequencies and attack rates were calculated, and a Bayesian analysis for the comparison of difference in proportions of disease was carried out for a 95% probability or credibility range (IP). Results: Among the 130 attendees at a communion 41 cases of tonsillopharyngitis (attack rate 31.5%) were detected, and in smears Group A Beta-Hemolytic Streptococcus was isolated. The most affected age group was the 25-44 year-olds, 16 (39,0%); 68.6% (24) female. The egg salad showed a probability greater than 80% P(Delta&gt;0.10 and Delta&gt;0.15) for a 95% IP of risk of disease after intake and a probability of having a lower risk of no disease. Conclusions: It was a Group A Beta-Hemolytic Streptococcal outbreak, the epidemiological evidence indicates exposure to common single source, hence the hypothesis of dietary origin, the implicated food was egg salad. Contributing factors could be cross-contamination after preparation favoured by the bad practice and the conditions of the place(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Nieto Vera, Juan</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Pérez Alonso, Aránzazu</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Cruz Calderón, María Victoria</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Figueroa Murillo, Estrella</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Fundamento: Aunque no son frecuentes, algunos autores han comunicado brotes de faringoamigdalitis de origen alimentario. El 11 de mayo de 2010 se notificó a la Red de Vigilancia Epidemiológica de Andalucía (SVEA) que había personas con cuadro de faringoamigdalitis que tenían en común haber asistido a una comunión celebrada el día 8. El objetivo de este trabajo es la caracterización epidemiológica del brote Método: Estudio observacional descriptivo de casos notificados y análisis de casos control por exposición a los alimentos implicados. Se analizaron las variables edad, sexo, sintomatología y fecha de inicio de síntomas. Fuentes de información fueron los registros del SVEA e historia digital individual (DIRAYA). Se calcularon frecuencias, tasas de ataque, y análisis bayesiano de comparación de diferencia de proporciones de enfermar para un intervalo de probabilidad o credibilidad (IP) del 95%. Resultados: De 130 asistentes a una celebración se detectaron 41 casos de faringoamigdalitis (tasa ataque 31,5%) y se aisló en frotis Estreptococo betahemolítico A. El grupo de edad más afectado fue el de 25-44 años: 16 (39,0%);hubo más afectación de las mujeres 24 (68,6%) mujeres. La ensaladilla de huevo presentó una probabilidad mayor del 80% P(Delta&gt;0,10 y Delta&gt;0,15) para un IP del 95% de enfermar tras su consumo y la probabilidad de tener menos riesgo de no enfermar. Conclusiones: Se trató de un brote por estreptococo betahemolítico A. El análisis epidemiológico evidenció exposición a fuente única y común, siendo plausible la hipótesis del origen alimentario, posiblemente por la ensaladilla de huevo contaminada por algún manipulador de alimentos. Como factores contribuyentes se identificaron inadecuadas medidas higiénico-sanitarias en la manipulación y conservación de los alimentos(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Salud Publica;85(4): 383-390, jul.-ago.2011. tab, ilus</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-90653</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Brote de faringoamigdalitis de origen alimentario por estreptococo betahemolítico A</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d24356^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28599</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28605</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d5650^s22048</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13678^s22052</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13678^s22001</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22074</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28441^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d24356^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d11437^s22054</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201108</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
