<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-048594</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-0108</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Prevalence of Helicobacter pylori infection in the general adult population of the province of Ourense</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objectives: to determine the prevalence of Helicobacter pyloriinfection in the general adult population of the province ofOurense.Material and methods: a cross-sectional study was carriedout with a randomly selected populational sample. The diagnosisof Helicobacter pylori infection was reached using the 13C-ureabreath test.Results: three hundred and eighty-three subjects were studied,with a prevalence rate of 69.1% (95% CI: 61.7-75.1%);69.8% (95% CI: 63.2-76.6%) in males and 68.4% (95% CI:61.5-75.4%) in females (difference not statistically significant).Prevalence increases with age up to a maximum of 88.4% in the45-54 years age group, and decreases thereafter to a rate of57.1% in individuals over the age of 84 years.Conclusion: this study reveals that the prevalence rate of Helicobacterpylori infection is high in the general adult populationof the province of Ourense. It increases with age until it peaks inthe group of middle-aged individuals and is similar in both sexes</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Gayoso Diz, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sueiro Benavides, R. A</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Fernández Seara, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Macenlle García, R</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivos: conocer la prevalencia de la infección por Helicobacterpylori en la población general adulta de la provincia deOurense.Material y métodos: se ha realizado un estudio transversalcon una muestra poblacional seleccionada al azar. El diagnósticode la infección por Helicobacter pylori se ha realizado mediantela prueba de aliento con 13C-urea.Resultados: se han estudiado 383 sujetos, obteniéndoseuna prevalencia del 69,1% (IC 95%: 61,7-75,1%), del 69,8%(IC 95%: 63,2-76,6%) en hombres y del 68,4% (IC 95%:61,5-75,4%) en mujeres, diferencia no significativa. La prevalenciaaumenta en relación con la edad, hasta un máximo del88,4% en el grupo de 45-54 años, y decrece en los grupos siguienteshasta alcanzar el 57,1% en los individuos de más de84 años.Conclusión: este estudio muestra que la prevalencia de la infecciónpor Helicobacter pylori es elevada en la población generaladulta de la provincia de Ourense. Aumenta con la edad hastaalcanzar un máximo en el grupo de edad media, y es similar enambos sexos</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Enferm Dig;98(4): 241-248, abr. 2006. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-048594</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Prevalencia de la infección por Helicobacter pylori en la población general adulta de la provincia de Ourense</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29156</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28584</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13411^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d20174</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28596</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29157^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d19059</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200604</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
