<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-136678</identifier>
<setSpec>1130-5274</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Psychological advice in a case of grief following Madrid 3/11 terrorist attacks</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">The loss of a beloved one unchains a wide range of psychological reactions. Many people can face the event without the need of professional help. However, other people find it difficult to show and work out their feelings about the loss, particularly if it happened suddenly and unexpectedly This paper deals with the psychological advice provided to a 45 years old male following the loss of his niece in Madrid 3/11 terrorist attacks. Advice was provided along 12 sessions. Intervention goals were 1) accepting the loss, 2) working on emotions and loss sorrow, 3) readapting to an environment where the beloved person is not living anymore, and 4) emotional relocation of the deceased beloved one and keeping on living. As soon as the patient was able to think of and talk about his niece sadly but with no grief, advice was stopped. Post-intervention results with pre-test and post-test measures bore out symptom remission (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Magaz, Ana</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Camacho, Sergio</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Para una persona, la pérdida de alguien significativo en su entorno produce una amplia gama de reacciones y sentimientos. Muchas personas son capaces de afrontarlas sin la ayuda de un profesional, sin embargo, otras tienen dificultades a la hora expresar y elaborar sus sentimientos respecto a la pérdida, más aún cuando esta es repentina e imprevista. En este trabajo se presenta el asesoramiento psicológico a un varón de 45 años tras el fallecimiento de una sobrina en los atentados terroristas ocurridos en Madrid el día 11 de marzo de 2004. El asesoramiento se realizó en 12 sesiones y los objetivos de la intervención fueron: (1) Aceptar la realidad de la perdida. (2) Trabajar las emociones y el dolor de la pérdida. (3) Adaptarse a un medio en el que el fallecido esta ausente, y (4) Resituar emocionalmente a la persona fallecida y continuar viviendo. El asesoramiento finalizó cuando el paciente fue capaz de pensar y hablar de su sobrina con tristeza pero sin dolor. Los resultados evaluados tras la intervención con medidas pretests y postest, confirmaron la remisión de los síntomas (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Clín. salud;15(3): 253-271, sept.-dic. 2004. graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-136678</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Asesoramiento psicológico en un caso de duelo tras los atentados del 11 M</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d231</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23898</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12050^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d3437^s22045</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29210</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23274</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200412</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
