<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-110737</identifier>
<setSpec>0213-9111</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Maternal occupation, pregnancy length and low birth weight</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Objective: To assess the association between maternal occupation during pregnancy with the presence of low birth weight and preterm delivery. Method: The sample consisted of 1,341,686 preterm infants and 1,217,897 low birth weight infants in Spain (1996-2000) with valid information on maternal occupation from the National Registry of Births. Maternal occupation was the main exposure variable coded according to groups of occupation (CNO-79) and outcomes were low birth weight (&lt;2500g) and preterm birth (&lt;37 weeks). Crude and adjusted odds ratios (OR) and 95% confidence interval (CI) were calculated through the maximum verisimilitude method. Results: The highest prevalence of preterm infants was found in mothers working in agriculture (10.8%) and the lowest in professional women (6.6%). The highest prevalence of low birth weight was observed in the women working in the services sector (3.5%) and manual workers in industry and construction (3.4%) while the lowest prevalence was found in professional women (2.5%). Women working in agriculture had a higher risk of preterm birth than professional women (aOR=1.68; 95%CI: 1.57-1.80). The risk of low birth weight was higher in women working in the service sector (aOR=1.36; 95%CI: 1.30-1.42), housewives (aOR=1.30; 95%CI: 1.28-1.38), agricultural laborers (aOR=1.29; 95%CI: 1.14-1.44) and manual workers in industry and construction (aOR=1.29; 95%CI: 1.21-1.36). Conclusions: The results of this study suggest that belonging to certain occupational groups during pregnancy could affect the risk of low birth weight and preterm birth (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Regidor, Enrique</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Hernández-Mora, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Ronda, Elena</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>García, Ana María</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Objetivo: Evaluar la relación de la ocupación materna durante el embarazo con el bajo peso en los recién nacidos y con los partos pretérmino. Método: La muestra consistió en 1.341.686 nacimientos pretérmino y 1.217.897 con bajo peso, en España (1996-2000), con información válida sobre ocupación materna procedente del Registro Nacional de Nacimientos. La ocupación materna fue la variable principal codificada por grupos de ocupación (CNO-79), y las de resultados fueron el bajo peso (&lt; 2.500 gramos) y los partos pretérmino (&lt; 37 semanas). Se calcularon las odds ratios (OR) y sus intervalos de confianza al 95% (IC95%), crudas y ajustadas mediante el método no condicional de máxima verosimilitud. Resultados: La mayor prevalencia de recién nacidos pretérmino se encuentra en las madres que se dedican a la agricultura (10,8%) y la menor en las profesionales (6,6%). Respecto al bajo peso, la prevalencia más alta se observa en las trabajadoras del sector servicios (3,5%) y del manual de industria y construcción (3,4%); las profesionales son las que muestran menor prevalencia (2,5%). En comparación con las mujeres profesionales, las agricultoras presentan un mayor riesgo de nacimientos pretérmino (ORa=1,68; IC95%: 1,57-1,80). En relación con el bajo peso, se observan riesgos mayores en las trabajadoras del sector servicios (ORa=1,36; IC95%: 1,30-1,42), las dedicadas a las labores del hogar (ORa=1,30; IC95%: 1,28-1,38), las que trabajaron en la agricultura (ORa=1,29; IC95%: 1,14-1,44) y las trabajadoras manuales en industria y construcción (ORa=1,29; IC95%: 1,21-1,36). Conclusiones: Los resultados de este estudio sugieren que pertenecer a determinados grandes grupos ocupacionales durante el embarazo puede tener un efecto en el riesgo de bajo peso al nacer y de parto pretérmino (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Gac Sanit;23(3): 179-185, mayo-jun. 2009. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-110737</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Ocupación materna, duración de la gestación y bajo peso al nacimiento</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d16360</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9975^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d7925^s22027</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d32153^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d15330</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>200906</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
