<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-133763</identifier>
<setSpec>0210-4806</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">American cranberry (proanthocyanidin 120mg): Its value for the prevention of urinary tracts infections after ureteral catheter placement</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Introduction: Urinary tract infection (UTI) is among the most frequent complications after urinary tract surgical procedures, mainly when catheter placement is necessary. Although the use of American cranberry has been related with a reduced risk of UTI, there is no study reporting the value of its prevention effect against catheter-associated urinary tract infections. Material and methods: A prospective trial comparing UTI rate (positive urine culture) among 31 patients with double J catheter (JJ) and adding American cranberry (120 mg) in routine prophylactic therapy, and 31 patients with JJ catheter only receiving routine prophylactic therapy. Results: Regarding general characteristics of the populations no significant difference among groups have been found. Only significant differences have been observed when the variables &#147;cranberry treatment&#148; and &#147;dwell time of JJ catheter&#148; were related. &#147;Dwell time of JJ catheter&#148; was higher in patients with UTI (35.9 compared 28.5 days [P = .03]). UTI percentage was lower in cranberry supplemented patient group (12.9 compared to 38.7% [P = .04]). Conclusions: We can conclude that American cranberry (120 mg) has an adjuvant effect in the prevention of UTI in patients with JJ catheter after surgery (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Sanchez-Martínez, N</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Díaz-Molina, P</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Flores-Sirvent, L</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Sequeira-García del Moral, J</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Barnoiu, O. S</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Baena-González, V</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">Introducción: La infección del tracto urinario (ITU) representa una de las complicaciones más frecuentes tras los procedimientos sobre la vía urinaria, sobre todo si se requiere la colocación de un catéter. El tratamiento con arándano rojo se ha relacionado con una disminución del riesgo de ITU, pero hasta ahora no se ha realizado ningún estudio que valore si este efecto preventivo se produce en pacientes portadores de un catéter ureteral a nivel de la vía urinaria, que es el objetivo de este estudio. Material y métodos: Se trata de un ensayo prospectivo en el que se se comparó la tasa de ITU (urocultivo positivo) en 31 pacientes portadores de catéter doble J (JJ) y profilaxis con arándano rojo (120 mg) como adyuvante al tratamiento profiláctico habitual, con la tasa de ITU de 31 pacientes portadores de JJ que solo recibieron profilaxis habitual. Resultados: La caracterización de los pacientes no encontró diferencias significativas entre los 2 grupos. En el análisis de los factores de riesgo y la aparición de ITU, únicamente las variables tratamiento con arándano y tiempo de permanencia del JJ mostraron diferencias significativas. El tiempo de permanencia del catéter fue mayor en aquellos pacientes con ITU, 35,9 respecto a 28,5 días (p = 0,03), y el grupo tratado con arándano mostró un porcentaje de ITU menor que aquellos que no recibieron arándano, 12,9 y 38,7%, respectivamente (p = 0,04). Conclusiones. Podemos concluir que el arándano (120 mg) tiene un efecto adyuvante en la prevención de la ITU en pacientes portadores de JJ tras la cirugía (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Actas Urol Esp;39(2): 112-117, mar. 2015. tab, graf</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-133763</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Valor preventivo adyuvante del arándano rojo americano (proantocianidinas 120 mg) en las infecciones del tracto urinario tras la colocación de catéter ureteral</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d14952^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23500^s22020</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29770</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d53052^s22057</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d22780</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d38094^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d331</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28607</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d9062</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d23138^s22073</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d35799</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8682</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
