<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-109965</identifier>
<setSpec>0214-4840</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Alcohol consumption in men punished for intimate partner violence: individual and contextual factors</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">Alcohol consumption is often associated with violence against women. The aim of this paper is to analyze the relationship between alcohol and other relevant variables in the intervention with men convicted of intimate partner violence, both at the individual and contextual spheres. Clinical symptomatology, Drug abuse, Impulsivity, Self-esteem, Assumption of responsibility, Intimate support perception, Social rejection perception, Accumulation of stressful life events, Income perception and Social support in community are assessed in a sample of 291 participants in an intervention program for men condemned for intimate partner violence. Data were analyzed using bivariate correlations and ANOVAs. Statistically significant differences were obtained among Risk consumers and Not risk consumers in Clinical symptomatology, Drug abuse, Impulsivity, Selfesteem and Attribution of blame to personal context as individual variables and Intimate support perception, Social rejection and Accumulation of stressful life events as contextual variables. Results of previous work are confirmed and the importance of considering social factors in the participants&#146; environment when considering decreasing alcohol consumption and intimate partner violence is demonstrated. New tools for enhancing interventions in rehabilitation programs with men convicted for violence against women is provided(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Catalá-Miñan, Alba</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Lila, Marisol</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Oliver, Amparo</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El consumo de alcohol ha sido relacionado de manera recurrente con la violencia contra la mujer. El objetivo de este trabajo es analizar las relaciones entre consumo de alcohol y otras variables relevantes en la intervención con hombres condenados por delito de violencia de género, en los ámbitos individual y contextual. Se evalúa Sintomatología clínica, Abuso de drogas, Impulsividad, Autoestima, Asunción de responsabilidad, Percepción de apoyo íntimo, Percepción de rechazo social, Acumulación de eventos vitales estresantes, Percepción de ingresos económicos y Apoyo social comunitario en una muestra de 291 participantes de un programa de intervención para hombres penados por violencia contra la pareja. Se analizan los datos mediante correlaciones bivariadas y ANOVAs. Se obtienen diferencias estadísticamente significativas entre Consumidores de riesgo y No consumidores de riesgo en Sintomatología clínica, Abuso de drogas, Impulsividad, Autoestima y Atribución de la culpa al contexto personal como variables individuales y en Percepción de apoyo íntimo, Rechazo social y Acumulación de eventos vitales estresantes como variables contextuales. Se confirman los resultados de trabajos anteriores y se evidencia la relevancia de considerar factores del entorno social de los participantes a la hora de disminuir el consumo de alcohol y la violencia contra la pareja, aportando nuevas herramientas para la mejora de los programas de intervención con hombres penados por violencia contra la mujer(AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Adicciones (Palma de Mallorca);25(1): 19-28, ene.-mar. 2013. tab</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-109965</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Consumo de alcohol en hombres penados por violencia contra la pareja: factores individuales y contextuales</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d29611</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d440^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28612</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13323^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d13564^s22083</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d33536^s22080</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d50302</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201303</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
