<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<ibecs-document>
<record>
<header>
<identifier>ibc-156648</identifier>
<setSpec>0034-947X</setSpec>
</header>
<metadata xmlns="http://example.org/myapp/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://example.org/myapp/schema.xsd">
<dc:title xml:lang="en">Non-drug treatment of attention déficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and its approach in the school setting</dc:title>
<dc:description xml:lang="en">ADHD is the most frequency neurodevelopmental disorder during the childhood and adolescent. Studies have shown that the most effective treatment is a multimodal approach with the involvement of the family, teachers and counselors. Cognitive behavioral therapy (indicated as initial treatment of this disorder) and parthent training have shown positive affects in controlling the symptoms of ADHD and conduct problems. ADHD leads to serius difficulties in the control of time, planing and organization, persistence to the implementrion and completion of a task, in following the rules, motivation, working memory and other functions, if it is not addressed properly will lead the student with ADHD enviroment becomes a priority in these approach and techniques in the scholl invironment applicable to the overall treatment of ADHD (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:creator>Fenollar Iváñez, Francisco Miguel</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Gómez Sánchez, José Antonio</dc:creator>
<dc:creator>Muñoz Ruiz, A</dc:creator>
<dc:language>es</dc:language>
<dc:description xml:lang="es">El TDAH es el trastorno del neurodesarrollo más frecuente en la infancia. Los estudios han demostrado que el tratamiento más efectivo es aquel que tiene un enfoque multimodal con la implicación de la familia profesores y orientadores escolares. La terapia cognitivo-conductual (indicada como tratamiento inicial de este trastorno) y el entrenamiento para padres han demostrado tener efectos positivos en el control de la sintomatología de TDAH y los problemas de conducta. El TDAH conduce a graves dificultades en el control del tiempo, en la planificación y organización, en la persistencia ante la realización y finalización de un tarea, en el seguimiento de las normas, en la automotivación, en la memoria de trabajo y en otra funciones que si no se abordan de forma adecuada conducirán al alumno con TDAH al fracaso escolar. Por ello, el abordaje en el entorno escolar se convierte en algo prioritario en este tipo de pacientes. Este trabajo resume las principales técnicas conductuales y de abordaje en el entorno escolar aplicables al tratamiento global del TDAH (AU)</dc:description>
<dc:source>Rev Esp Pediatr;71(2): 90-97, mar.-abr. 2015.</dc:source>
<dc:identifier>ibc-156648</dc:identifier>
<dc:title xml:lang="es">Tratamiento no farmacológico del trastorno por déficit de atención e hiperactividad (TDAH) y su abordaje en el entorno escolar</dc:title>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22012</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22047</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d29315</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d2694</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21034</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d28461</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21030</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d21044</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d1295^s22053</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225^s22056</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22031</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d12225</dc:subject>
<dc:subject>^d8036^s22011</dc:subject>
<dc:type>article</dc:type>
<dc:date>201503</dc:date>
</metadata>
</record>
</ibecs-document>
